<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.wat.037 SYSTEM "egp.wat.037.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.wat.037">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Water Towers</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Dori M. Penny</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.wat.037</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Penny, Dori M.">Dori M. Penny</author>. <title level="a">"Water Towers."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">865-866</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-29</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">WATER TOWERS</head>

<figure n="egp.wat.037" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Nebraska Public Power District structure, April 1991</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>A water tower, or elevated tank, is designed to
hold enough water to provide a supply area
with sufficient amounts for periods of peak use
and, in the case of a system failure, one day's
use. A water tower, however, is so much more
than a reservoir for water. Along highways,
they mark the location and declare the name of
countless small and large communities. They
also provide an opportunity for ardent fans of
high school sports, young lovers, and graduating
seniors to declare themselves in height-defying
graffiti. The need for water and the
need to express pride in hometowns and relationships
have made the water tower an enduring
feature of the Great Plains landscape.</p>

<p>Water towers are generally constructed
from steel. Many were produced by companies
known to residents of Plains states
from bridge nameplates. A wide variety of
shapes are used including those referred to as
doorknobs, lattice towers, and fully enclosed
domes. Many smaller communities used a
shape that one author, Anne Dingus, has likened
to the head of the Tinman in the classic
movie, <title level="m">The Wizard of Oz</title>. After the tank is
erected, the steel is given a protective coat of
paint. The name of the town and sometimes a
logo is then painted on the tank. Repainting is
performed to maintain the condition of the
tank as well as to cover graffiti. Water towers
can seem deceptively small in appearance because of their height. However, they can hold
anywhere from 15,000 gallons to as much as 3
million gallons of water.</p>

<p>The operation of a water tower is fairly simple.
Because it needs to be elevated above the
rest of a water system, it is constructed on a
scaffold or, in the case of a tank, positioned on
a hill. The height&#8211;usually between 100 and
300 feet&#8211;of a water tower is necessary in
order to provide pressure. Water is pumped
from a treatment plant or a well into a city's
water system and also into the tower. Because
the water tower is providing storage, the system's
pump can be sized to supply average
rather than peak demand. During any period,
if the city's system needs more water, water is
allowed to flow from the tank and increase the
supply through the pipes. If demand decreases,
the water flows into the tank and is
then stored until it is needed.</p>

<p>Because of the simplicity of their design,
water towers have survived since the first half
of the twentieth century. Towers are familiar
and well-remembered landmarks to former
and current residents of communities. They
stand as sentinels over stable and growing
communities as well as over towns that have
been bypassed by highways and economic development.
The real importance of a water
supply and the symbolic importance of the
water tower ensure that the it will continue to
be an elemental part of the Plains landscape.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Dori M. Penny<lb/>
LTA, Inc., Laramie, Wyoming</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Dingus, Anne. "The Water Tower." <title level="j">Texas Monthly</title>. 1998.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>