<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.med.019">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main"><hi rend="italic">Fort Worth Star-Telegram</hi></title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Gerald L. Grotta</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.med.019</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Grotta, Gerald L.">Gerald L. Grotta</author>. <title level="a">"<hi rend="italic">Fort Worth Star-Telegram</hi>."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">512</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-26</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main"><hi rend="italic">FORT WORTH STAR-TELEGRAM</hi></head>

<p>In 1936 the <title level="j">Amarillo Globe</title> said of the legendary
publisher of the <title level="j">Fort Worth Star-Telegram</title>:
"West Texas is bound on the north by Colorado
and Oklahoma, on the west by New
Mexico, on the south by Mexico, and on the
east by Amon Carter." Thirty years earlier
there had been only two newspapers in Fort
Worth&#8211;the morning <title level="j">Telegram</title> and the morning
<title level="j">Record</title>. Then in 1906 young Amon Carter
agreed to become advertising manager of a
new evening newspaper, the <title level="j">Star</title>.</p>

<p>Initially, the <title level="j">Star</title> floundered, and it never
managed to break even. Then in 1909, in an audacious
move, the near-bankrupt <title level="j">Star</title> bought
the larger and much more successful <title level="j">Telegram</title>,
and the <title level="j">Fort Worth Star-Telegram</title> was born,
with Amon Carter as primary owner and publisher.
Together, the new publisher and his
newspaper were to become a major force in
shaping not only Fort Worth but all of West
Texas and eastern New Mexico&#8211;a sizable
chunk of the Great Plains.</p>

<p>Until then, West Texas had been largely ignored
by everybody. However, Amon Carter
had a much different vision of the future of
this vast expanse of hot, dry, windy plains.
That future was to include a great oil boom
and irrigated croplands to supplement the historic
cattle industry. As Amon Carter would
tell audiences, West Texas is larger than New
York, Massachusetts, Pennsylvania, and Maryland
combined. The <title level="j">Fort Worth Star-Telegram</title>
embraced the residents of West Texas, and the
citizens of West Texas embraced the <title level="j">Fort Worth Star-Telegram</title>. The newspaper would
eventually serve an area of 350,000 square
miles and deliver copies every day to homes up
to 700 miles west of Fort Worth, well into New
Mexico. It dominated the market in such West
Texas population centers as Amarillo, Abilene,
Lubbock, Midland-Odessa, and El Paso. By
1913 it had become the fourth-largest newspaper
in Texas, with a circulation of 40,000. By
1918 its 66,000 subscribers made it the largest
newspaper in all of Texas. Then in 1923 circulation
reached 115,000, and it was the largest
newspaper in the southern United States&#8211;
larger than the <title level="j">Dallas Morning News</title> or the
<title level="j">Houston Chronicle</title> or the <title level="j">Atlanta Journal</title>.
Much of this growth came from subscribers in
West Texas and eastern New Mexico. It wasn't
until midcentury that newspapers in much
larger cities finally passed the <title level="j">Fort Worth Star-Telegram</title> in circulation.</p>

<p>The decline of home-delivery circulation
throughout West Texas and eastern New Mexico
began in the second half of the century.
Passenger trains that had delivered the newspaper
to those far-flung towns stopped running,
and there was no other economical way
to spread the newspaper throughout this vast
region. People in isolated West Texas communities
had used the <title level="j">Fort Worth Star-Telegram</title>'s
ads from large Fort Worth department stores
to order merchandise for mail delivery. When
department stores&#8211;both independent and
chain&#8211;began to open in West Texas they
reduced the need for mail-order shopping,
which in turn reduced the value of West Texas
subscribers for the Fort Worth stores. Finally,
as cities grew, the newspapers in West Texas
began to improve and expand. In a way, the
successful development of West Texas that had
been fostered by the <title level="j">Fort Worth Star-Telegram</title>
helped reduce the need for that newspaper in
much of the region.</p>

<p>On June 23, 1955, Amon Carter died, and his
son, Amon Carter Jr., became publisher. Then
in 1974 the <title level="j">Fort Worth Star-Telegram</title> was purchased
by Capital Cities of New York, and in
1996 Capital Cities/<hi rend="smallcaps">ABC</hi> merged with the Walt
Disney Company. Within a year, Disney/<hi rend="smallcaps">ABC</hi>'s
publications, including the <title level="j">Fort Worth Star-Telegram</title> and the <title level="j">Kansas City Star</title>, were purchased
by Knight-Ridder, the second largest
newspaper group in the country.</p>

<p>By the end of the twentieth century, the <title level="j">Fort Worth Star-Telegram</title> had changed its focus
from West Texas to the Fort Worth metropolitan
area and eastward into the rapidly
growing Arlington and Mid-Cities area between
Fort Worth and Dallas. But no story of
the West Texas region of the Great Plains
would be complete without the newspaper
that "discovered" West Texas, nurtured it,
promoted it, and served it so well for most of
the first half of the century.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">CITIES AND TOWNS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ct.023">Fort Worth, Texas</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Gerald L. Grotta<lb/>
Texas Christian University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Flemmons, Jerry. <title level="m">Amon: The Texan Who Played Cowboy for America</title>. Lubbock: Texas Tech University Press, 1998.</bibl>
<bibl>Meek, Phillip J. <title level="m">Fort Worth Star-Telegram: "Where the West Begins."</title> New York: Newcomen Society in North America,
1981.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>