<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.pe.029">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Glaciation</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>William J. Wayne</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.pe.029</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Wayne, William J.">William J. Wayne</author>. <title level="a">"Geology."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">630-631</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-22</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">GLACIATION</head>

<p>During the Pleistocene epoch (from two million
to 10,000 years ago), continental glaciers
invaded the Great Plains only in the northern
portions; nevertheless, their effects on the entire
region were profound. Glacial ice repeatedly
blocked the rivers that drained eastward,
forming ice-marginal lakes and diverting the
rivers southward. Wind deflated sand and silt
from the floodplains of the rivers that carried
sediment-laden meltwater from both the enlarged
glaciers in the Rocky Mountains and the
continental ice sheet, creating fields of dunes
and depositing a loess mantle on the uplands.
Permafrost (perennially frozen ground) developed
around the ice margin where strong
winds swept the blanket of snow from the surface.
Lowered temperatures along the glacier
margin and southward caused major changes
in distribution of the biota of the entire region.</p>

<p>The Laurentide ice sheets that developed
in eastern and central Canada expanded to
reach the Great Plains at least seven times between
about 2.2 million years ago and less than
10,000 years ago, when the margin of the last
glacier melted from the area. After each period
of glaciation, ice disappeared long enough
for soil profiles to form on the sediments left
behind.</p>

<p>The early glaciations were the most extensive.
They have been dated approximately by
the relationships of the tills they deposited in
reference to four ashfall deposits, three from
the Yellowstone Caldera, and one from Bishop,
California. One till lies beneath the oldest of
these ash lenses, dating back more than 2
million years, and at least four till units lie
between ash lenses deposited from 1.27 million
to 610,000 years ago. All of these are now referred
to as pre-Illinoian tills. The outer margin
of one or more of these early continental
glaciers extended into northeastern Kansas
and eastern Nebraska, then angled northwestward
across the Dakotas and northern Montana,
where it approached the piedmont glaciers
of the Rocky Mountains.</p>

<p>All the major rivers that drain eastward
from the Rocky Mountains built alluvial fans
where they left the mountain front and deposited
gravel and sand along their routes toward
the northeast and east. Uplift in the late Cenozoic
period (around two million years ago)
resulted in downcutting by those rivers, so that
terraces, identified by soil profile, preservation,
relative height, and presence of ash lenses,
exist along the valleys. Stream diversions and
piracy have since changed the courses of many
streams in the Central and Northern High
Plains. The Missouri River, which formerly
drained northeastward into the Hudson Bay
Lowland, was ponded several times by ice
dams and ultimately diverted into its present
course. The ancestral Platte River, its upper
course rejuvenated by uplift in the Rocky
Mountains and its discharge augmented by increased
precipitation and, perhaps, meltwater
from late Pliocene mountain glaciers, carried a
vast amount of coarse gravel eastward across
eastern Wyoming and into west-central and
northern Nebraska, where it accumulated as
the Broadwater and Long Pine Formations.
Across the Central Plains, the ancestral Platte
shifted its course repeatedly throughout the
Pleistocene in response to local uplift (the Chadron
Arch), aggradation, and glacial blocking,
finally following its present course after having
spread sheets of gravel across wide areas of
east-central Nebraska. In the Southern Plains,
sand and silt, probably blown from the floodplains
of the Pecos and Canadian Rivers, accumulated
in a sequence that becomes finer northeastward
across western Texas and Oklahoma
(Blackwater Draw Formation) and reaches as
far as south-central Nebraska. Deposition began
more than 1.4 million years ago and continued
intermittently until less than 118,000
years ago, with paleosols (ancient soils) recording
periods of stability.</p>

<p>Glaciations took place between 610,000
years ago and the first of the Illinoian glaciations,
300,000 years ago, but left no recognizable
record in the Great Plains. Nor have tills
of Illinoian age been identified with certainty
in the Great Plains, although the ice undoubtedly
reached the region, and tills of that age
should exist buried beneath the deposits of the
last, or Wisconsinan, glaciation.</p>

<p>The most complete record of the effects of
glaciation in the Great Plains, as elsewhere, is
that of the late Wisconsinan ice sheet, which
reached its maximum extent about 20,000
years ago and covered the region north of a
diagonal line from southeastern South Dakota
to southern Alberta. Lobes of Wisconsinan ice
expanded into lowlands from the James River
basin to the upper Milk River basin in Montana.
Meltwater flooded down the Missouri
River Valley, as well as down rivers that were
fed by alpine glaciers in the Rocky Mountains.
Strong northwesterly winds deflated sand and
silt from these ribbons of outwash to accumulate
as dunes along the rivers and loess over
much of the upland.</p>

<p>Strong winds associated with both glaciers
and dry interglacial conditions generated dunes
from alluvial sediments deposited in central Nebraska
along an abandoned mid-Pleistocene
route of the Platte River. Late Wisconsinan
winds built massive dunes from these sand
fields, which were reactivated repeatedly during
dry phases over the last 10,000 years. The
strong northwesterly winds eroded troughs
and ridges in the zone adjacent to the ice margin
and swept the zone free of snow so that
permafrost developed. Lakes formed where
drainage was blocked by the ice. The largest of
these, Lake Agassiz, covered more than half of
Manitoba and extended into Saskatchewan,
Ontario, Minnesota, North Dakota, and the
northeast corner of South Dakota. This huge
lake drained through the Minnesota River Valley
until the retreating ice margin had uncovered
outlet routes to the east. By about 11,000
years ago, the ice margin lay along the north
side of Lake Winnipeg, although the Laurentide
ice sheet did not entirely disappear until
about 6,000 years ago.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">WATER</hi>: <ref n="egp.wat.012">Kettle Lakes</ref>; <ref n="egp.wat.013">Lake Agassiz</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>William J. Wayne<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Morrison, Roger B., ed. <title level="m">Quaternary Nonglacial Geology:
Conterminous U.S.</title>, The Geology of North America, vol.
<hi rend="smallcaps">K</hi>-2. Boulder <hi rend="smallcaps">CO</hi>: Geological Society of America, 1991.</bibl> <bibl>Sibrava, Vladimir, D. Q. Bowen, and G. M. Richmond, eds.
<title level="m">Quaternary Glaciations in the Northern Hemisphere</title>. Oxford:
Pergamon Press, 1986.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>