<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fil.059">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Saunders, Russell (1919-2001)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>David J. Wishart</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fil.059</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</author>. <title level="a">"Saunders, Russell (1919-2001)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">278</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-12</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">SAUNDERS, RUSSELL (1919-2001)</head>
<figure n="egp.fil.059" rend="granted" type="noclick">
<figDesc>Headshot of Russell Saunders</figDesc>
</figure>    

<p>Born on a farm near Winnipeg, Manitoba, on
May 21, 1919, Russell M. Saunders repeatedly
risked his life as perhaps the greatest movie
stuntman of Hollywood's halcyon days. As a
child he was fascinated by the acrobats in traveling
circuses, and he worked on his acrobatic
skills until he had achieved Canadian championships
in diving and gymnastics. After
being rejected by the Canadian Air Force because
he was color-blind, he moved to California.
There he quickly found his way to Muscle
Beach in Santa Monica, where acrobats and
body builders performed and paraded. Even
in his later years he spent much of his time on
the beach, giving free gymnastics lessons to
children.</p>

<p>But it was in the movie business that Saunders
made his name. He appeared in more
than a hundred movies, doubling for stars
such as Alan Ladd, Robert Cummings, and
Gene Kelly. He was particularly revered by his
peers for his ability to capture the exact mannerisms
of the stars as he performed the dangerous
feats they were unable to do. In <title>The Three Musketeers</title> (1948), for example, he
jumped from a rooftop, caught hold of a flag,
and, as it ripped, swung on the shreds through
an open window. In another film as Richard
Widmark's double he leaped off a fifty-foot
cliff, breaking his arm on a rock in the water.
Saunders was also in the climactic fight scene
in <title>Shane</title> (1953), unknown to audiences, who
saw only Alan Ladd and his antagonists in the
blur of action. Russell Saunders died in a West
Los Angeles nursing home on May 29, 2001.</p>

<closer>
<signed>David J. Wishart<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>