<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ct.047">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Saskatoon, Saskatchewan</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Randy William Widdis</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ct.047</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Widdis, Randy William">Randy William Widdis</author>. <title level="a">"Saskatoon, Saskatchewan."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">183</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-28</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">SASKATOON, SASKATCHEWAN</head>

<p>Saskatoon, the largest city in the province of
Saskatchewan, with a population of 220,000,
has experienced both stunning growth and
marked stagnation during its relatively short
history. The community was founded in 1882
by John Lake, who came to the Canadian
Northwest to examine the land granted by
the Dominion government to the Torontobased
Temperance Colonization Society and
to choose a site for the administrative center
of the colony. Lake and his compatriots selected
a spot along the South Saskatchewan
River, where the banks on both sides were low
enough to provide a crossing. Legend has it
that the original location on the east side was
named Saskatoon after the berries growing on
the bushes beside the river.</p>

<p>After the influx of the first Temperance
Colony settlers in 1883, the community grew
very slowly. The leaders of the colony realized
that their isolation hindered development,
and they lobbied hard for a rail connection.
Their efforts paid off in 1887 when the government
granted the Qu'Appelle, Long Lake and
Saskatchewan Railway and Steamboat Company
a land subsidy of 6,400 acres per mile to
build a rail line from the main Canadian Pacific
Railway line to Prince Albert, across the
river at Saskatoon. The railway decided to locate
its station on the lower western bank
where there was easier access to water for the
steam locomotives. In response, the society
surveyed a new town site with the station at
its center, and the original settlement was allowed
to languish.</p>

<p>The coming of the first railway line did not
spur significant development, but it did make
Saskatoon a shipping center, increasing the
importance of the Battleford Trail, and it made
possible the export of three commodities: buffalo
bones, cattle, and grain. Yet with a population
of only 113 in 1901, Saskatoon was stagnating.
At this point a number of factors ensuring
an incredible burst of growth came into play.</p>

<p>Among the most important was the 1902
purchase of over one million acres of land between
Regina and Saskatoon from the railway
and the Dominion government by the Saskatchewan
Valley Land Company, a colonization
company organized by midwestern
capitalists. It was the settlement of land by
American immigrants, among other groups,
that would provide the hinterland so necessary
to the community's growth. The local
economy also received a boost with the arrival
by rail of the Barr colonists, drawn from industrial
cities of England, in 1903. Over 1,500
colonists disembarked from the train and
were outfitted by local merchants before making
their way west to the Lloydminster area.</p>

<p>The major impetus for growth came from
1908 to 1914, when the Grand Trunk Pacific and
the Canadian Pacific Railways constructed
new lines to Saskatoon, making the city the
self-proclaimed "Hub of the Prairies." With
the coming of the railways, the wholesale-retail
function expanded, and Saskatoon became the
major distribution center for central Saskatchewan.
Much of the capital financing new businesses
came from Britain, France, and Holland
as well as from eastern Canada. In 1906 Saskatoon
became a city when it joined with Nutana,
the original settlement on the eastern
bank, and Riverdale, the village created by Barr
colonists who had remained in the area. The
crowning glory for the city was being awarded
the provincial university in 1909, an achievement
that would generate employment and
provide a cultural focus for its inhabitants. Its
population grew to more than 12,000 by 1911 and
more than doubled during the next ten years.</p>

<p>All of this development took place within a
context of the integration of the Canadian
West into the national and world economic
systems. Saskatoon was well located on a good
site and far enough away from Winnipeg and
Edmonton to capture its own significant hinterland.
But like other Prairie communities, its
fortunes would rise and fall with that of the
wheat economy. During the periodic global
recessions of the 1920s and the Depression the
following decade, growth declined. Efforts to
diversify the economy by industrializing were
relatively unsuccessful because of a lack of water
power produced from a river whose flow
was too slow in the winter, Saskatoon's isolation
from large markets, and the lack of investment
occurring during times of economic recession.
Saskatoon did manage to attract some
industry, however, including Quaker Oats,
Robin Hood Flour, and the Massey Harris and
Rumely farming implement companies.</p>

<p>It was only after World War II that Saskatoon
would enlarge its industrial base, an expansion
founded initially on the mining industry.
By the end of the 1940s five potash
mines were operating in Saskatoon's vicinity,
making the city the "Potash Capital of the
World." The local economy diversified as a result
of increasing exploitation of oil and minerals
in the western and northern parts of the
province, respectively. By the 1960s manufacturing
had become increasingly important as
chemical, textile, fiber optics, steel fabrication,
and a host of other food-processing, engineering,
and machinery industries established
themselves. Since the 1990s there has been a
significant development of high technology,
with biotechnology, computer software, microelectronics,
aerospace, pharmaceutical,
and animal health firms locating in the university's
research park. Major businesses, including
Northern Telecom, Develcon Electronics,
and Advanced Data Systems, have located in
the city. All this has resulted in Saskatoon increasing
its population more than 300 percent
between 1951 and the present. Yet even as the
city diversifies and expands its economic base,
it and other communities in the province still
rely overwhelmingly on a resource sector that
has proven to be increasingly fragile in a fastchanging
world.</p>
</div1>


<div1> <p/>
<closer>
<signed>Randy William Widdis</signed>
University of Regina</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Delaney, William, John Duerkrop, and William Sarjeant.
<title level="m">Saskatoon: A Century in Pictures</title>. Saskatoon: Western Producer
Prairie Books, 1982.</bibl> <bibl>Kerr, Don, and Stan Hansen.
<title level="m">Saskatoon: The First Half Century</title>. Edmonton: NeWest
Press, 1982.</bibl> <bibl>Peel, Bruce, and Eric Knowles. <title level="m">The Saskatoon Story, 1882–1952</title>. Saskatoon: General Printing and Bookbinding
Company, 1952.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>