<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.na.102">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Sacred Geography</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Kari Forbes-Boyte</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.na.102</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Forbes-Boyte, Kari">Kari Forbes-Boyte</author>. <title level="a">"Sacred Geography."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">599</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-20</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">SACRED GEOGRAPHY</head>

<p>While Great Plains Indian religions differ considerably
from one another, they all exhibit a
sacred geography. All of nature is regarded as
being sacred, yet certain geographical features
and areas figure more prominently than others
on the sacred map.</p>

<p>Sacred places have multiple levels of meaning
to Indigenous cultures. First, sacred places
are acts of creation, usually designed by a
World Maker. The places are revealed through
the society's mythology (sacred truth), thereby
becoming the physical manifestations of the
mythological system. Second, Great Plains
Indians hinge both their religious perceptions
and their religious ceremonies on sacred
places. The locale where a ritual takes place is
as significant as the ritual itself. Third, symbolism
is an important component of sacred
places. Last, the religious perceptions that
Plains Indians have of their physical environment
lead to a psychological stability evident
in a condition referred to as "existential insideness."
Existential insideness is knowing that a
particular place is where one belongs, completing
the self-identity of an individual. Existential
insideness is supported through the
spiritual system of the culture when there is an
acknowledgment of sacred places.</p>

<p>The mythological traditions of many Plains
Indians are located in real places. Thus, place is
both mythic and geographical. For example,
<hi rend="italic">Pahuk</hi>, meaning "Mound on the Water," located
in eastern Nebraska on a high bluff above
the Platte River, is one of five known Pawnee
sacred sites. The Pawnees believe Pahuk is
one of the locales where the Sacred Animals
(<hi rend="italic">Nahu-rac</hi>) held council during mythic times
and where a young Pawnee boy learned healing
practices from the animal council. The boy
took the knowledge to his people, curing his
fellow villagers and eventually teaching his
skills to other young men of the village. Traditionally,
Pawnee doctors would visit Pahuk
yearly to renew their healing powers and to
give thanks to those mythic beings who bestowed
the knowledge on their predecessor.</p>

<p>A place made sacred through mythology is
continually consecrated by rituals. The Lakota
religion recognizes seven sacred ceremonies.
Each of these ceremonies is identified with
specific sites where the rituals are performed.
The <hi rend="italic">hanbleceya</hi> (vision quest) ceremony is executed
at Bear Butte in western South Dakota
near the Black Hills, a place the Lakotas describe
as "their most sacred altar." The hanbleceya
is a prayer for spiritual guidance. The
Lakotas recognize Bear Butte as a particularly
worthy site for visions because the seeker is
generally successful, and visions experienced
there can reveal future events that are necessary
for the continuation of humanity.</p>

<p>Symbolism plays a primary role in the recognition
of sacredness for Great Plains Indian
peoples. Natural landforms or human-manufactured
structures often symbolize the
cosmos: their shapes possess the power of
what they symbolize. The "medicine wheel,"
to many Plains cultures, represents an organization
of the cosmos based on a recognition of
the four sacred directions. These circular rock
formations are found throughout the Plains
region and are regularly visited by Indian people
on pilgrimages. The best-known example,
the Big Horn Medicine Wheel, is sacred to
the Cheyennes, Lakotas, Arapahos, and Shoshones.</p>

<p>Existential insideness, the feeling that one
belongs to a particular place, characterizes
Plains Indians' relationships with their homeland.
According to the Lakotas, their religion
cannot be practiced without access to the sacred
places. When this bond is severed, severe
psychological alienation and cultural disintegration
can ensue. Many Native American
peoples' sense of identity comes from walking
on land also walked on by their ancestors, or
by being able to identify places that are not
only significant to them as individuals but also
significant to their ancestors. To lose this identity,
through loss of sacred lands, would have
devastating consequences for the generations
to come.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Kari Forbes-Boyte</signed>
Sacramento City College</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Eliade, Mircea. <title level="m">The Sacred and the Profane: The Nature of
Religion</title>. New York: Harcourt, Brace, and World, Inc.,
1957.</bibl> <bibl>Vecsey, Christopher. <title level="m">Handbook of American Indian
Religious Freedom</title>. New York: Crossroad Publishing Company,
1991.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>