<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.gen.007">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Captivity Narratives</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Birgit Hans</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.gen.007</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Hans, Birgit">Birgit Hans</author>. <title level="a">"Captivity Narratives."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">326</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-18</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">CAPTIVITY NARRATIVES</head>

<p>Captivity narratives are the accounts written
by men and women reporting on their experiences
as abductees of Native Americans. From
the seventeenth century to the end of the
nineteenth century such accounts accompanied
the westward-moving frontier, and
their storylines, established in the first known
captivity narrative by Mary Rowlandson in
1682, remained essentially the same: conflict
between the settlers and Indians, capture by
the Indians, ordeal at the hands of the captors,
and a return to European American society.</p>

<p>In general, male captives adjusted easier to
their new lives with Native American peoples
than did female captives, who, with very few
exceptions, feared for their virtue and prayed
for a return to civilization. Through the centuries
in these captivity narratives, stock
phrases are perpetuated&#8211;for example, bashing
brains out and burning people at the stake.
Their descriptions of elements of the captors'
cultures tend to be generic and confusing, but
the message is clear: Native American cultures
are considered inferior to European American
civilization, and Native Americans are perceived
as emotionless, cruel, and traitorous.
The captives' detailed descriptions of torture
scenes and the suffering of women and children
provided justification for armed conflict
on the western frontier and the displacement
of Native Americans, whose voices were very
rarely heard in the captivity documents.</p>

<p>Women and children brought civilization
to the frontier, and in the minds of their contemporaries,
their removal from their fledgling
communities represented a basic threat to
civilization. It was acceptable to convert Native
Americans to Christianity and make
farmers of them, and thereby to make them
part of the mainstream. Women captives,
however, found it impossible to exert a civilizing
influence on their captors, and their captivity
narratives revealed their belief that Native
Americans had to disappear in order for
civilization to come. Documents and testimonials
attached to the narratives were meant
to encourage the reader to believe in the historical
truth of the narratives and to treat the
information contained therein as fact.</p>

<p>Captivities during the settlement of the
Plains were much more widely distributed
than those during colonial times, and Plains
captivity narratives exerted significant influence
on their readers. Stories like Fanny Kelly's
painted a vivid picture of Native Americans
who rejoiced in the killing of women and
children. Kelly despairs as she recognizes her
small daughter's scalp and then witnesses the
hopelessness of a fellow captive forced to
"marry" her captor and the degeneration of a
captive who, from infancy, had grown up
among the Native Americans. Kelly also described
"barbaric" customs and physical assaults.
These highly emotional descriptions
and reports of repeated treachery by the Sioux
helped to convince settlers on the Northern
Plains that military expeditions were necessary,
and that any sympathy with the Native
Americans was misguided. Glenda Riley, in
her analysis of women's voices on the frontier
and especially in the Southern Plains, reveals
accounts that reflect Kelly's attitude, as well as
accounts of women who came to an understanding
of Native American people and their
increasingly desperate situation.</p>

<p>The closing of the frontier and the end of
Indian wars in the Plains in the late nineteenth
century did not diminish the popularity of
captivity narratives. They continued to follow
the standard form of the genre, but some elements&#8211;
for example, the heroism of the captives
and their deeds&#8211;became more exaggerated.
At the same time, portrayals of Native
Americans became more sympathetic. Instead
of condemning Native American cultures
wholesale, they allow some noble characters
to emerge. An interesting change in the basic
plot of captivity narratives has occurred in the
last thirty years with the emergence of romance.
The captive remains with her Native
American captor and exerts a "civilizing" influence
over him and his tribe&#8211;she achieves
what the earlier woman captive could not.
There is also hope for some Native American
cultures in these romances. These new conventions
are evident in such recent films as
<title>Dances with Wolves</title> (1990), which, while ethnographically
more accurate, as newer audiences
demand, romanticizes traditional
Lakota culture and also plays on images of the
"noble" and the "savage" Native American
(the latter in this case are Pawnees). Captivity
narratives remain a formula rather than portrayals
of complex and contemporary peoples;
they deal with the conflict between Native and
European Americans in terms entirely satisfying
to the latter audience, while denying complexity
and contemporaneity to Native American
peoples.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">FILM</hi>: 
<title><ref n="egp.fil.016"><hi rend="italic">Dances with Wolves</hi></ref></title>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Birgit Hans<lb/>
University of North Dakota</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Kelly, Fanny. <title level="m">Narrative of My Captivity among the Sioux Indians</title>.
Chicago: Lakeside Press, 1990 [1871].</bibl> <bibl>Riley, Glenda.
<title level="m">Women and Indians on the Frontier, 1825–1915</title>. Albuquerque:
University of New Mexico Press, 1984.</bibl> <bibl>Stedman, Raymond
William. <title level="m">Shadows of the Indian: Stereotypes in American Culture</title>. Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1982.</bibl>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>