<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.pg.065">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Progressive Conservative Party</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Geoffrey Lambert</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.pg.065</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Lambert, Geoffrey">Geoffrey Lambert</author>. <title level="a">"Progressive Conservative Party."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">683-684</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-05</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">PROGRESSIVE CONSERVATIVE PARTY</head>

<p>The name of this party will strike many as
an oxymoron. Yet it unintentionally catches
something of the party's essence. It has been a
coalition of ardent supporters of the free market
system and minimal government, and of
those (the so-called Red Tories) who have an
organic view of society and believe that the
state has an obligation to preserve social harmony and to take care of those who cannot
easily fend for themselves.</p>

<p>The party came into being in 1854 and
was known subsequently as the Conservative
Party, until it added the "Progressive" in 1943.
Their new federal leader, John Bracken, who
for twenty years was premier of Manitoba, insisted
on the change. He had been a Progressive,
but never a Conservative, until he assumed
the party's leadership. Also commonly
known as the Tories or the <hi rend="smallcaps">PC</hi>s, the party is
closest in ideology to the Republican Party in
the United States and the British Conservatives
(the terms <hi rend="smallcaps">PC</hi>, Conservative, and Tory are
used interchangeably here). The party was the
dominant player in national politics from 1867
to 1896 and spent thirty years in power in the
twentieth century. The Progressive Conservatives
have been, until recently, the chief rival to
the Liberals.</p>

<p>In the Prairie Provinces the party has generally
been laissez-faire in economics, socially
conservative, skeptical of the ability of government
to bring about positive change, and
strongly supportive of free trade. (It was a
Progressive Conservative national government
that negotiated the North American
Free Trade Agreement with the United States
which came into effect in 1989.) However, the
Red Tory element has not been absent, and the
party has often been infused with a streak of
populism. One example of the former would
be Duff Roblin, premier of Manitoba from
1958 to 1967, and of the latter, John Diefenbaker
from Saskatchewan, prime minister of
Canada from 1957 to 1963.</p>

<p>The Conservative Party in Manitoba was in
existence from 1883, being favored by many
settlers from Ontario. The party was in power
from 1900 to 1915 under the leadership of Sir
Rodmond Roblin, a relatively progressive
Conservative for his day. However, his government
fell in 1915, the result of a financial scandal
involving the construction of the legislative
building in Winnipeg. Although the party
survived, and served in a coalition government
during World War II and its aftermath,
not until 1958 did it again form a government
on its own. Ironically, it was Sir Rodmond
Roblin's grandson, Duff Roblin, who came to
power in that year. He is widely regarded as
perhaps the greatest of all Manitoba premiers.
He is credited with breaking the province's
Depression mentality and in expanding access
to education and other services. Perhaps his
most enduring monument is the Floodway, a
huge dike around Winnipeg, which has several
times saved the city from flooding. The
pcs have held office on a number of occasions
since Roblin left office. Their premiers have
been Walter Weir (1967-69), Sterling Lyon
(1977-81), and Gary Filmon (1988-99). Filmon
was regarded as a more moderate figure
than his two predecessors.</p>

<p>The party has been much less successful in
Saskatchewan at the provincial level, though
the unique personality and appeal of John
Diefenbaker at the federal level made the province
for a while the most loyal source of Tory
support. In fact, only three times since the
province entered Canadian Confederation in
1905 has the party formed the provincial government.
J. T. Anderson had the misfortune to
win power in 1929. Saskatchewan was hit as
badly as any jurisdiction in North America by
the Depression, a situation compounded by
several years of drought. So, after Anderson's
defeat in 1934, the Conservative Party was virtually
moribund for years while the Liberals
and the Cooperative Commonwealth Federation
(later, the New Democratic Party) took
turns in office.</p>

<p>In 1982, however, the general Prairie dislike
of the federal Liberals undermined support
for that party at both levels of government
and, after eleven years of New Democratic
Party rule, Saskatchewan voters concluded
that it was time for a change. So, Grant Devine
became the first Tory premier in forty-eight
years. Devine's was a generally centrist government.
It combined laissez-faire policies
(such as the privatization of some public enterprises)
with activism (an expansion of the
rural hospital system). Devine was defeated by
the New Democratic Party in 1991. Since then,
the party's reputation has suffered from revelations
that several of its cabinet and caucus
members, while in office, enriched themselves
by illegal means. Thus, there is a rather grim
joke in the province that the headquarters of
the Saskatchewan <hi rend="smallcaps">PC</hi> Party are to be found in
the local penitentiary.</p>

<p>Alberta is a profoundly conservative province,
where dedication to free enterprise and
limited government is stronger than elsewhere.
Indeed, Alberta is regarded as the most
"American" of provinces. Though the Conservatives
did not form a government there until
1971, sixty-six years after the province's entry
into Confederation, ideologically conservative
parties have been triumphant. The United
Farmers of Alberta formed the government
from 1921 to 1935, and Social Credit from 1935
to 1971. In the latter year, the old-fashioned
image of the government and the widespread
desire for change resulted in the election of
the Progressive Conservatives under the leadership
of Peter Lougheed (1971–85), one of the
most charismatic figures in Prairie politics in
the last half-century.</p>

<p>Under Lougheed, Alberta's vast economic
resources were fully tapped, an equitable pricing
agreement for oil and natural gas reached
with the federal government, the province's
standing in the country enhanced, a Heritage
Fund (money set aside for future contingencies)
established, and Alberta transformed
into a modern economy and society. Frequently
at odds with the federal government,
Lougheed won repeated reelection with huge
majorities. The pcs were still in office in 2001.
Lougheed's successors were Don Getty (to
1992) and Ralph Klein since Getty's departure.</p>

<p>Alberta and Manitoba provide a good comparison
of the varieties of Canadian and Prairie
conservatism. In Alberta, the politics of
the Progressive Conservative Party have often
been reminiscent of the more radical elements
of the Republican Party in the United States.
Manitoba's Progressive Conservatives have
tended to be more moderate and centrist.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">INDUSTRY</hi>: <ref n="egp.ind.041"><hi rend="smallcaps">NAFTA</hi></ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Geoffrey Lambert<lb/>
University of Manitoba</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Campbell, Colin, and William Christian. <title level="m">Parties, Leaders
and Ideologies in Canada</title>. Toronto: McGraw-Hill Ryerson
Ltd., 1995: 25–65.</bibl> <bibl>Friesen, Gerald. <title level="m">The Canadian Prairies:
A History</title>. Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 1987.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>