<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.rel.047">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Sweat Lodge</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Raymond A. Bucko</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.rel.047</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Bucko, Raymond A.">Raymond A. Bucko</author>. <title level="a">"Sweat Lodge."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">758</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-19</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">SWEAT LODGE</head>

<p>The sweat lodge is a contemporary religious
ritual of ancient origin used by Native Americans
throughout the Great Plains. Eastern Indian
groups removed to the Plains by the U.S.
government also engage in ceremonial sweating.
Groups like the Cherokees and Chickasaws
originally utilized permanent, domeshaped
log houses with subterranean floors
that were also used for sleeping in winter. This
entry will focus on the original Plains groups,
among whom the ceremony takes place in a
small, circular domed structure constructed of
pliable saplings (often willow) with a single
entrance facing a specific cardinal direction.
The frame of this impermanent structure is
tightly covered, formerly with skins but today
with blankets, tarps, and sometimes sheet plastic.
A pit is dug in the lodge to receive stones
that are heated in a fire outside the lodge. This
fireplace and frequently a mounded altar constructed
of earth excavated from the interior
pit are aligned with the entrance of the lodge.</p>

<p>The ceremony consists in entering the lodge,
filling the pit with hot stones that are reverenced
as ancient and spiritual in nature, pouring water
on the hot rocks, praying, singing, speaking
from one's heart, closing and opening the door a
set number of times, and emerging from the
lodge. Important elements in the ceremony that
vary in emphasis from group to group are communication
with the spiritual realm, moral
and/or physical purification, the humbling of
oneself, healing of self and/or others through
the physical and/or spiritual agency of the
sweat, and voluntary suffering to achieve a specific
need or to fulfill a pledge for requests already
granted.</p>

<p>Variations in the ceremony and structure of
the lodge are accounted for by three factors:
historic era, cultural group, and specific ritual
leader. Nevertheless, there is remarkable consistency
in the core ritual and structure across
time and among different Plains groups. Variations
include the incorporation of a prayer
pipe and a variety of symbolic objects such as
a buffalo skull placed on the altar outside of
the sweat lodge; the erection of a pole on
which to tie offerings; the use of switches
made of sage, willow, cherry, buffalo tail, or
horse hair; song accompaniment with a drum
and/or rattle; the sacred use of plants such as
sage, cedar, or pine needles; the pouring of
herbal infusions on the rocks; drinking water
between rounds and sometimes pouring it on
oneself; spiritual supplication through crying;
spiritual talks, particularly by the leader and
sometimes other participants; joking when
the door is open; and bathing in a cold stream
at the conclusion of the ceremony.</p>

<p>The sweat lodge can be a ceremony in itself
but is also used in preparation for other ceremonies
such as the Sun Dance, sacred bundle
ceremonies, vision quests, and sometimes Native
American Church meetings. Among some
tribes, men and women sweat together, while
in others they are segregated. There are ritual
restrictions for women in menses.</p>

<p>The ritual is widely used for marking significant
life events, consoling and encouraging,
protecting the group from misfortune
such as disease, succeeding in battle and hunting,
predicting future events, and averting future
disaster. Many traditional stories of the
revival of the dead through the agency of the
sweat lodge attest to the great power of this
ceremony.</p>

<p>The ceremony has markedly increased in
practice since the beginning of the twentieth
century, not only by Indian people on the reservations
but more recently in urban areas,
correctional facilities, veterans groups, and
substance abuse treatment facilities. The spiritual
strengthening and social conviviality inherent
in the sweat serve to unite family members,
Indians from different tribes, and non-Indians,
although the proper place and role of
outsiders in the sweat lodge and in Indian ritual
in general are controversial.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">ARCHITECTURE</hi>: <ref n="egp.arc.035">Native American Traditional Architecture</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Raymond A. Bucko<lb/>
Le Moyne College</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Bruchac, Joseph. <title level="m">The Native American Sweat Lodge: History
and Legends</title>. Freedom <hi rend="smallcaps">CA</hi>: Crossing Press, 1993.</bibl>
<bibl>Bucko, Raymond A., S.J. <title level="m">The Lakota Ritual of the Sweat
Lodge: History and Contemporary Practice</title>. Lincoln: University
of Nebraska Press, 1998.</bibl> <bibl>Vecsey, Christopher. "The
Genesis of Phillip Deere's Sweat Lodge." In <title level="m">Imagine Ourselves
Richly: Mythic Narratives of North American Indians</title>,
edited by Christopher Vecsey. New York: Crossroad, 1988:
206–32.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>