<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.mus.042">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Schools of Music</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Lawrence R. Mallett</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.mus.042</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Mallett, Lawrence R.">Lawrence R. Mallett</author>. <title level="a">"Schools of Music."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">547</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-03</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">SCHOOLS OF MUSIC</head>

<p>The Great Plains has witnessed the development
of many music programs in higher education
that are, to a large extent, responsible
for the rich musical heritage and culture of its
people. These schools and departments of music
in the region's colleges and universities have
contributed greatly to the quality of life in the
Great Plains in addition to training future
teachers and professional and amateur musicians.
Six music programs in higher education
have a tradition of musical excellence and represent
the impact that all of the schools and
departments of music have had on the people
of the Great Plains.</p>

<p>Two of these music programs, the University
of Kansas and the University of Nebraska.
Lincoln, are among the oldest in the Great
Plains. They are geographically close to each
other, and their music programs developed at
approximately the same time. Both music
programs were granted membership in the
National Association of Schools of Music
(<hi rend="smallcaps">NASM</hi>) in 1928, the first year nasm began
awarding national accreditation. The first evidence
of a music department at the University
of Kansas appears in the university catalog of
1877-78, which lists music by special instructors.
In 1884 a committee introduced music
study to the curriculum to furnish instruction
in all branches of music to both amateur and
professional students, to combine music with
regular collegiate work, and to train teachers.
The idea that all three could be offered in a
single department was unheard-of before 1884
and was not generally accepted until well after
World War I.</p>

<p>The University of Nebraska catalog of 1877
describes the availability of vocal and instrumental
study. The names of several different
music instructors appear in the records between
1877 and 1887. In 1892 a plan was presented
to enhance the music program by establishing
a conservatory that would operate as a
separate entity by generating its own funds.
The conservatory would serve the university
by offering instruction for which credit would
be granted. The current School of Music at the
University of Nebraska-Lincoln evolved from
this plan and was officially founded in 1894.
The following description of the School of Music
appeared in a 1910 issue of the <title level="j">Musical Courier</title>: "It stands here in a city of 40,000 inhabitants,
situated in the center of a great prairie,
isolated from all the great art centers of the
United States." The board of regents purchased
the School of Music in 1930, and it became an
official academic unit of the University of
Nebraska-Lincoln.</p>

<p>Two additional institutions developed comprehensive
music programs in the Great
Plains. The School of Music at the University of
Oklahoma became one of the first music programs
in the country to be granted membership
in <hi rend="smallcaps">NASM</hi> in 1931, and the music program at
the University of Colorado grew to become a
College of Music and was awarded accreditation
in <hi rend="smallcaps">NASM</hi> in 1941.</p>

<p>Alberta College in Edmonton is one of Canada's
oldest arts institutions. The music department,
now the Conservatory of Music, was
established in 1903 and has become one of the
largest music programs in Canada. The School
of Music at the University of Manitoba can be
traced to 1944, when students in arts and sciences
could minor in music with courses in
music theory and music history. A degree program
in music was instituted in 1963.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Lawrence R. Mallett<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>