<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.asam.015">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Kano, Father Hiram Hisanori (1889-1986)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Mark R. Ellis</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.asam.015</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Ellis, Mark R.">Mark R. Ellis</author>. <title level="a">"Kano, Father Hiram Hisanori (1889-1986)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">144-145</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-22</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">KANO, FATHER HIRAM HISANORI (1889-1986)</head>

<p>Hiram Hisanori Kano was born into a Japanese
noble family on January 30, 1889. His
warlord father was the governor of the province
of Kagoshima and a member of the Japanese
parliament. As the second son in the
family, young Kano was not required to follow
his father's career. Instead, he chose to study
agriculture at the Imperial University in Tokyo,
where he graduated with a bachelor of
science degree in 1916. Kano eventually found
his way to the Great Plains after William Jennings
Bryan, a family friend, convinced his
father that he could receive a better agricultural
education in the United States. With a
handwritten note from Bryan in his pocket,
Kano journeyed to Lincoln, Nebraska, where
in 1918 he earned a master's degree in agricultural
economics at the University of Nebraska.</p>

<p>In 1919 Kano married Ai "Ivy" Nagai in
Seattle; the couple had two children. He put
his agricultural education to good use when
he bought a 300-acre farm near Litchfield, Nebraska.
Kano became active in the Japanese
Americanization Society, teaching English
and working as an intermediary or translator
for immigrants. In 1921 Kano and Rev. George
Allen Beecher, the Episcopal bishop for western
Nebraska, successfully defeated a bill introduced
in the Nebraska legislature that
would have barred Japanese residents from
owning property and serving as legal guardians
of their children. During the 1920s Kano
became active in the Episcopal Church, working
with Japanese living in the Platte River
valley. He was ordained a deacon in 1928 and
became a priest in 1936.</p>

<p>Kano's life took a dramatic turn on December
7, 1941, when the Japanese attacked Pearl
Harbor. After conducting services in North
Platte, Nebraska, that Sunday morning, he was
arrested by local police and interrogated by
federal agents. Because of his family ties to the
Japanese government and his position as a
leader of Japanese immigrants in the Great
Plains, federal authorities deemed Kano a
threat to national security and sent him to
an internment camp. While being held away
from his family, Kano taught English classes
to fellow internees. In 1944 he was released and
allowed to move his family to Nashota, Wisconsin,
where he entered a seminary, earning
another master's degree in 1946. Returning to
Nebraska, Kano worked as an Episcopal missionary
among Nebraska's Japanese residents
until his retirement in 1957. After leaving the
priesthood, Kano moved to Fort Collins, Colorado,
where he and his wife bought a small
farm. Kano died on October 24, 1988.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Mark R. Ellis<lb/>
University of Nebraska at Kearney</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Kano, Hiram Hisanori. <title level="m">A History of the Japanese in Nebraska</title>.
Lincoln: Nebraska Committee for the Humanities,
1984.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>