<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ind.055">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Sugar Beet Processing</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Richard Reisig</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ind.055</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Reisig, Richard">Richard Reisig</author>. <title level="a">"Sugar Beet Processing."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">434</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-04</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">SUGAR BEET PROCESSING</head>

<p>Sugar beets of the Beta vulgaris species have a
white inner flesh and look more like a large
parsnip than a red beet. The sugar beet crop
is planted in early spring and harvested in
the fall, when it is at maximum sugar content.
To grow beets, a farmer signs a contract with a
company to plant a certain amount of acreage;
usually payment is made by the company on
the basis of the sugar content of the beets
and also the price of refined sugar sold by the
company. Many U.S. sugar companies today
are owned by cooperatives made up of beet
growers.</p>

<p>Harvesting machines uproot the beets, cut
off the tops, and then convey the beets into a
truck. The beets are delivered to the factories
and receiving stations, where they are dumped
either directly into the process or stored in
large piles for later use. The sugar factory operates
round the clock and must be fed a continuous
supply of beets once the "campaign," or
processing season, gets under way. Campaign
length is usually from 120 to 150 days and even
longer in the northern regions.</p>

<p>Upon entering the factory, the beets are
washed and sliced into long thin strips called
"cossettes." The cossettes then enter the diffuser,
where water carries away the sugar in
the form of raw juice. The exhausted beet material,
called "pulp," goes to the dryer or silo to
be sold as livestock feed. After leaving the diffuser,
the raw juice is purified with lime and
then put through two stages of carbonation in
which carbon dioxide gas is added to precipitate
the lime and nonsugars. The juice then
passes through several filtration steps to remove
impurities. This purified juice, called
"thin juice," then goes to the evaporators to be
concentrated into "thick juice." It is then filtered
again to assure purity.</p>

<p>The pure thick juice then enters crystallization,
where there are typically three stages:
white pan, high raw pan, and low raw pan.
The syrups arrive at the vacuum pans, where
the liquid is boiled into a thick supersaturated
liquid. At just the exact moment in the boiling
stage, the sugar boiler initiates the crystal formation
by "seeding" the pan with an extremely
fine sugar slurry. The sugar crystals
are grown to the proper size, then the mass of
sugar crystals is dropped to centrifugal machines
to be spun at high speed. The liquid
portion, or "mother liquor," is separated from
the sugar crystals and saved for further crystallization
and sugar removal. The liquid from
the final boiling is exhausted of sugar and is
called molasses. The molasses is saved for further
desugarization and sold as an animal feed
by-product.</p>

<p>The final white sugar is centrifuged from
the white pan mass and washed. The damp
sugar crystals are then sent to the sugar granulator
for drying. From the granulator, the
sugar goes to packaging, truck, or rail loading
or is stored in huge storage silos. It requires
approximately forty pounds of sugar beets to
produce a five-pound bag of granulated sugar.</p>

<p>In the crop year 2000 more than 32 million
tons of beets were harvested in the United
States in twelve states. The major sugar beet
growing area is the Red River Valley, which
straddles the boundary of Minnesota and
North Dakota. Nearly half of all the sugar beets
grown in the United States come from this
area. Among other Plains states, Montana,
Colorado, Wyoming, and Nebraska all produce
more than one million tons of sugar
beets. During the 2000 production year there
was a total of ten sugar beet companies in the
United States, with a total of twenty-eight operating
factories. Of these factories, thirteen
are in the Great Plains region. They are located
in the states of Colorado, Nebraska, Wyoming,
Montana, and North Dakota. The beet sugar
companies of the Great Plains include Western
Sugar Company, Holly Sugar Corporation,
American Crystal Sugar Company, Minn-Dak
Farmers Co-op, and Rogers Sugar. There are
two sugar beet growing areas in Canada, located
in Ontario and Alberta. Canada has one
sugar beet factory, located in Taber, Alberta,
that annually contributes approximately 10
percent of Canada's total refined sugar production.
Despite the above-noted production, the
United States and Canada are net importers of
sugar.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">AGRICULTURE</hi>: <ref n="egp.ag.064">Sugar Beets</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Richard Reisig<lb/>
Western Sugar Company</signed>
</closer>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>