<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.na.106">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Sign Language</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Allan R. Taylor</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.na.106</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Raylor, Allan R.">Allan R. Taylor</author>. <title level="a">"Sign Language."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">600-601</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-20</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">SIGN LANGUAGE</head>

<p>The Plains Sign Language (<hi rend="smallcaps">PSL</hi>) is the most
sophisticated Aboriginal sign language known.
<hi rend="smallcaps">PSL</hi> is a direct signaling system; its symbols are
understood without any reference to a spoken
language. At its zenith in the mid–nineteenth
century, <hi rend="smallcaps">PSL</hi> was the principal lingua franca of
the trans-Mississippi West. There were three
dominant regional dialects: Southern Plains,
Northern Plains, and Plateau (the mountainous
region north of the Great Basin). The
variation between these was mostly in vocabulary,
although sign mechanics also varied.</p>

<p>It is not known where or when <hi rend="smallcaps">PSL</hi> originated,
but it was likely the Texas Gulf Coast,
where a large number of mutually unintelligible
languages were spoken. Given its complexity
and wide use, the <hi rend="smallcaps">PSL</hi> must be many centuries
old. The earliest probable observations
of the <hi rend="smallcaps">PSL</hi> by Europeans were by Spaniards in
the Southern Plains in the first half of the sixteenth
century. During the nineteenth century,
the <hi rend="smallcaps">PSL</hi> was used throughout the Plains,
from the Texas Panhandle to the Missouri
River and beyond, eventually reaching the Canadian
Prairies. But sign use was also prominent
outside this area, wherever tribes were
influenced by Plains culture.</p>

<p>During the period when the <hi rend="smallcaps">PSL</hi> was an
ongoing lingua franca, the Kiowas, Comanches,
Cheyennes, and Arapahos were known
as especially skilled signers. It may be significant
that these tribes, who spoke mutually unintelligible
languages, were often allies. Adult
men are thought to have been the primary
users of <hi rend="smallcaps">PSL</hi>, although some women knew and
used <hi rend="smallcaps">PSL</hi> as well. Apart from conversational
uses, <hi rend="smallcaps">PSL</hi> was also usual in public storytelling.
This use survives into the present. Signing was
also used for oratory, largely before multilingual
audiences.</p>

<p>psl makes heavy use of portrayal of meanings
by descriptive gesture, thus <hi rend="smallcaps">PSL</hi> is heavily
pantomimic, but many signs are also merely
conventional. <hi rend="smallcaps">PSL</hi> is, then, a mixed system
varying from gestures whose reading is obvious,
to gestures whose meaning cannot be
inferred and which must be learned. All <hi rend="smallcaps">PSL</hi>
signs are built from around eighty mutually
contrasting basic gestures. Each sign usually
includes three or four of these, formed with
either one or both hands, which may be used
in a stationary position or moved about. Signs
are normally produced in a continuous flow
of motion, but sentences and longer segments
of discourse may be set off by brief pauses.
When signing is done at a distance, movements
are exaggerated in various ways to
make the sign more "readable."</p>

<p>Signing was often accompanied by verbal
language. Usually the verbal speech had the
same meaning as the signed message. But this
does not mean that signed messages were a
translation of a spoken analog, following the
rules of the spoken language. <hi rend="smallcaps">PSL</hi> is an independent
language with its own rules. The order
of words in a signed sentence is fairly free, and
the same thing can usually be said with a number
of alternate word orders, though a particular
word order is usually preferred. In general,
subjects precede verbs, and modifiers follow
the element modified.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, <hi rend="smallcaps">PSL</hi> is now almost completely
obsolete, although some signers can
still be found here and there on Plains reservations.
But time is short. Soon, only memories
will remain as testimony to the former existence
of the fascinating and colorful system of
communication which we know as the Plains
Sign Language.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Allan R. Taylor</signed>
University of Colorado at Boulder</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Clark, William Philo. <title level="m">The Indian Sign Language</title>. Lincoln:
University of Nebraska Press, 1982.</bibl> <bibl>Taylor, Allan R. "Nonverbal
Communication in Aboriginal North America: The
Plains Sign Language." In <title level="m">Aboriginal Sign Languages of the
Americas and Australia</title>, edited by Thomas A. Sebeok and
Donna Jean Umiker-Sebeok, 2:223–44. New York: Plenum
Press, 1978.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>