<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.law.019">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Haskell, Ella Knowles (1860-1911)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>John R. Wunder</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.law.019</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Wunder, John R.">John R. Wunder</author>. <title level="a">"Haskell, Ella Knowles (1860-1911)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">452</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-04</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">HASKELL, ELLA KNOWLES (1860-1911)</head>

<p>On a December evening in 1889, after Cornelius
Hedges and two other Montana lawyers
had conducted an unusual bar exam, Hedges
wrote in his diary, "Examined Miss Knowles
for admission to the Bar and was surprised to
find her so well read. She beat all that I have
ever examined." Ella Knowles Haskell might
have enjoyed that assessment had she ever
read it, because the words summarized her
life.</p>

<p>Born July 31, 1860, in Northwood Ridge,
New Hampshire, Ella Knowles became a
woman of many firsts. She would be the first
woman to become a lawyer in Montana, the
first woman to run for a major political party
for state attorney general, and probably the
first woman to serve as an assistant state attorney
general and represent a state before a
state supreme court.</p>

<p>Ella's early years were spent in New Hampshire
and Maine, where she embraced education
and sought to expand women's rights. At
age twenty she entered Bates College as one of
its first women students. She graduated in
1884 magna cum laude and started to read law
in a New Hampshire law office.</p>

<p>Ella Knowles then developed an illness for
which she was advised to move West. In 1888
she arrived in Helena, Montana, and thereafter
claimed Montana as her permanent home.
After teaching for a year in Helena, she resolved
to begin preparing for a legal career by
reading law with local attorney Joseph W.
Kinsley. In order to practice law, however, Ella
had to persuade the Montana territorial legislature
to change Montana's law that restricted
legal practice to men, and then she needed to
pass a bar exam. In February 1889 the legislature
revised its laws to allow women to practice
law, and that December Ella Knowles easily
passed her bar exam.</p>

<p>Knowles opened her own law office in 1891.
She prevailed in her first case, suing a black
restaurant owner in justice of the peace court
on behalf of a Chinese client who had been
employed in the restaurant and cheated out of
$5 of back wages.</p>

<p>Ella Knowles quickly made a reputation as a
progressive and energetic lawyer, and it resulted
in her nomination in 1892 by the Populist
Party to run for attorney general. Although
she came in a close third, losing to
Republican incumbent Henri Haskell, she
garnered more statewide votes than any other
Populist candidate. Prior to the campaign,
Haskell had gained authorization to hire an
assistant attorney general, and after the campaign
he offered the position to Ella Knowles.
She accepted and proceeded to represent the
state in public lands issues, and she defended
the state's anti-Chinese legislation before the
Montana Supreme Court. In May 1895 Ella
Knowles married Haskell, and as Ella Knowles
Haskell she continued to represent the state
of Montana until her husband's term expired
in 1896.</p>

<p>During these years Ella was active politically.
In 1896 she was chosen president of the
Montana Women Suffrage Association. That
same year she was selected to attend the Populist
Party's national convention in Omaha. She
went on the stump for William Jennings
Bryan in both the 1896 and 1900 presidential
campaigns.</p>

<p>In 1897 Ella divorced Henri Haskell and relocated
eventually in Butte, where she hung up
her shingle once again. Over the next fourteen
years she became an expert on mining law,
corporate law, and property law. She also accumulated
significant wealth from investments
in mines and from her corporate work
and continued to lecture on woman's rights in
Montana, the Great Plains, and the West.</p>

<p>On January 27, 1911, Ella Knowles Haskell
died from an infection at her home in Butte at
the young age of fifty.</p>

<closer>
<signed>John R. Wunder<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Larson, T. A. "Montana Women and the Battle for the
Ballot." <title level="j">Montana: The Magazine of Western History</title> 28
(1973): 24–41.</bibl> <bibl>Roeder, Richard B. "Crossing the Gender
Line: Ella L. Knowles, Montana's First Woman Lawyer."
<title level="j">Montana: The Magazine of Western History</title> 32 (1982): 64–
75.</bibl> <bibl>Wunder, John R. "Law and Chinese in Frontier Montana."
<title level="j">Montana: The Magazine of Western History</title> 30
(1980): 18–31.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>