<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fol.010">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Farm Inheritance Practices</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Ron G. Stover</author>
<author>Mary Kay Helling</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2009</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fol.010</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2009</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2009 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Stover, Ron G.">Ron G. Stover</author> and <author n="Helling, Mary Kay">Mary Kay Helling</author>. <title level="a">"Farm Inheritance Practices."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">294-295</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-16</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">FARM INHERITANCE PRACTICES</head>

<p>The transfer of family resources from one
Great Plains generation to the next is often
difficult and stressful. The farm is perhaps the
most difficult of all family resources to pass
down because it represents both an economic
enterprise and a way of life. The inheritance
practices, therefore, go beyond law and cross
over into folkways, where the decisions are
made in the family, albeit within the wider
context of formal legalities.</p>

<p>Typically, two generations are involved in
the transfer. The "senior generation"&#8211;the
family members transferring the farm—may
still be principal owners and managers, or
they may have already begun to transfer control
to someone else. The "junior generation"
are the children of the senior generation and
the spouses of the children.</p>

<p>When planning the transfer of the family
farm, family members often identify specific
goals they want to accomplish. For some family
members&#8211;often those whose farm has
been in the family for many generations&#8211;
ensuring that the family farm remains intact
and in the family is an important goal. The
maintenance of the family farm as a viable
financial entity is often a second goal: the family
wants the transfer accomplished in a way
that ensures that the junior generation is not
burdened by financial costs which prevent the
successful operation of the family farm. A
third goal is to use the revenues from the family
farm to provide an income adequate to support
the retirement of the senior generation.</p>

<p>To attain these goals, family members use
various principles. First, families sometimes
insist on the principle of equality of treatment
of the junior generation. Here, families want
to ensure that each member of the junior generation
receives an equal share of the family
farm resources. Goals incompatible with this
principle may be sacrificed to ensure equality
and fair treatment for each child. If necessary,
the farm will be sold and the resulting financial
assets evenly divided so that all offspring
are treated equitably. Second, some farm families
embrace the principle that the "right" to
inherit a share of the family farm must be
earned. This principle implies that only those
who have shown a commitment to the family
farm through hard work on the farm have any
claim. Providing choice for the junior generation
is a third principle that sometimes guides
the transfer. Families adopting this principle
want to ensure that members of the junior
generation have the opportunity to choose
their own futures, whether running the family
farm or embarking on a nonagricultural career.
Fourth, an exchange relationship might
be established between the senior and junior
generation. One child&#8211;typically the eldest
son&#8211;receives the farming operation but must
agree to take care of the parents as long as they
live. Siblings of that child might receive a symbolic,
but very small, portion of the farm. Finally,
families vary in who is permitted to participate
in the inheritance decision-making
process. Some families insist that only members
of the senior generation should be involved.
Other families want all immediate
family members&#8211;the senior generation and
the junior generation&#8211;to be actively involved.
Spouses of the children are explicitly excluded.
Some families embrace an inclusive
principle. They want all family members&#8211;the
senior generation, the children of the senior
generation, and the spouses of those children
&#8211;to be involved in the process.</p>

<p>Combining goals can often be unattainable.
For example, the use of the farm as a retirement
package can preclude the transfer of a
financially viable farm to the junior generation.
To obtain the financial resources to fund
the senior generation's retirement, the junior
generation may be required to rent or even
buy the farm, thus incurring costs that reduce
its financial viability. However, some combinations
are compatible. The preservation of
the family farm and the maintenance of the
family farm as a financially viable economic
enterprise are not mutually exclusive. In fact,
they are mutually reinforcing.</p>

<p>Prioritizing some goals prevents the adoption
of certain principles. For example, passing
on a financially viable farm while maintaining the principle of equitable treatment
among the members of the junior generation
is not always possible. Securing a financially
viable operation sometimes requires some
members of the junior generation to receive
less than other members of the family. However,
the selection of certain transfer principles
can facilitate the accomplishment of specific
goals. The principle specifying that one
child will inherit the farm and be required to
support the parents is consistent with all three
goals: the farm is preserved when the entire
farming operation is transferred intact; the
farming operation is not financially burdened
by the necessity of having to rent, or even buy,
the operation from the senior generation; and
the farming operation can be considered a retirement
package since some farm income
must be used to support the parents in their
retirement.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Ron G. Stover<lb/>
Mary Kay Helling<lb/>
South Dakota State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Stover, Ron G., and Mary Kay Helling. "Goals and Principles
of the Intergenerational Transfer of the Family Farm."
<title level="j">Free Inquiry in Creative Sociology</title> 25 (1998): 201–12.</bibl> <bibl>Stover,
Ron G., and Mary Kay Helling. "Transferring the Family
Farm." <title level="j">Extension Extra</title> 14040 (1996): 1–3.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>