<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.edu.002">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Abbot, Edith (1876-1957)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>John Sorensen</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.edu.002</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Sorensen, John">John Sorensen</author>. <title level="a">"Abbot, Edith (1876-1957)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">198</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-28</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">ABBOTT, EDITH (1876-1957)</head>

<p>Edith Abbott was among the most important
Americans who were involved in the establishment
of social work as a profession&#8211;a profession
akin to those of law, medicine, and
theology, requiring not merely the "good intentions"
of its practitioners but a scrupulous
intellectual education and a rigorous practical
training. As the first woman to become the
dean of a major American university graduate
school (University of Chicago, School of Social
Service Administration), Abbott prepared
several generations of social servants to assume
what she called "the grave responsibility
of interfering with the lives of human beings."</p>

<p>Abbott was born in Grand Island, Nebraska,
on September 26, 1876. She grew up
in a family of social activists that included
her younger sister (and lifelong professional
colleague), Grace Abbott, the great American
champion of children's rights. Edith and
Grace Abbott were the daughters of Elizabeth
Griffen, an early leader of the Nebraska suffrage
movement, and of O. A. Abbott, a pioneer
lawyer who was the first lieutenant governor
of Nebraska. Describing the sisters'
unusual upbringing amid family guests such
as Susan B. Anthony and Lucy Stone, Edith
Abbott later said, "We were brought up to
stand by our guns, popular or not&#8211;and if unpopular,
so much the better!"</p>

<p>In 1906 Edith Abbott, having earned a doctorate
in economics at the University of Chicago,
was awarded a trip to England, where
she lived in a settlement house and came into
contact with the famed socialists Beatrice and
Sidney Webb of the Fabian Society. Abbott's
successful studies in London led to a teaching
post at Wellesley College in Massachusetts
and, soon thereafter, the opportunity to return
to Chicago to become a resident of Jane
Addams's Hull House.</p>

<p>Edith Abbott's first book, the influential
<hi rend="italic">Women in Industry</hi>, was published in 1910. It
was at about this same time that she joined the
faculty of the Chicago School of Civics and
Philanthropy. She was a key figure in the 1920
effort to move this institution of social work
training to the University of Chicago, where
it was renamed the School of Social Service
Administration (<hi rend="smallcaps">SSA</hi>). Abbott thereafter
led the ssa to become one of the first programs
of social work&#8211;perhaps the very first&#8211;
at a great American university. She became
dean of the school in 1924.</p>

<p>For many years, through the Great Depression,
Edith Abbott worked closely with
her sister, Grace (then the highest-ranking
woman in the federal government), to combat
a wide array of social ills. It was through their
joint efforts that many early forms of social
welfare, some of which have been credited
with leading to the New Deal programs that
helped end the Great Depression, were begun.
The Abbott sisters formed a complementary
team, with each providing an invaluable and
unique service. As Edith Abbott put it, "I
could assemble the facts and write a report,
but Grace had the gift of applying the proper
legislative remedy."</p>

<p>Edith Abbott continued to publish important
books on immigration, the tenements of
Chicago, American pioneers in social welfare,
and the philosophy of social welfare education.
She was the cofounder in 1927 of the
publication <hi rend="italic">Social Service Review</hi> and was also
its longtime editor; she was named president
of the American Association of Schools of Social
Work from 1925 to 1927; she was appointed
to the Wickersham Commission (the
National Committee on Law Enforcement
and Observance) in the late 1920s; and she was
the president of the National Conference of
Social Work in 1937.</p>

<p>In 1942 Abbott retired from her position as
dean of the ssa. She served as dean emeritus
and continued teaching until 1952, when she
returned to her hometown, where she died on
July 29, 1957.</p>

<p>At the time of Edith Abbott's death, Wayne
McMillen of <hi rend="italic">Social Service Review</hi> wrote,
"History will include her name among the
handful of leaders who have made enduring
contributions to the field of education. Social
work has now taken its place as an established
profession. She more than any other one person
gave direction to the education required
for that profession. Posterity will not forget
achievements such as these."</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</hi>: <ref n="egp.pg.002">Abbott, Grace</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>John Sorensen<lb/>
New York, New York</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Papers of Grace and Edith Abbott, Regenstein Library,
University of Chicago. Costin, Lela. <hi rend="italic">Two Sisters for Social
Justice: A Biography of Grace and Edith Abbott</hi>. Urbana:
University of Illinois Press, 1983.</bibl> <bibl>Sorensen, John. "My Sister
and Comrade: A Radio Portrait of Grace Abbott." Nebraska
Public Radio, Lincoln, 1997.</bibl>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>