<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.mus.034">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Native American Music</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>J. Bryan Burton</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.mus.034</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Burton, J. Bryan">J. Bryan Burton</author>. <title level="a">"Native American Music."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">543-544</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-02</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">NATIVE AMERICAN MUSIC</head>

<p>Music lies at the heart of Indian culture. From
birth to death, all occasions, sacred and secular,
personal and tribal, in the life of the Plains
Indian are inextricably intertwined with musical
performances.</p>

<p>Music serves numerous functions in traditional
Indian culture, including religious ceremonies,
healing ceremonies, work songs,
game songs, courtship, storytelling, songs to
bring success in hunting, agriculture, and war,
and social songs and dances. As traditional
culture has been influenced through contact
with non-Indian cultures, the purposes and
functions of music have been adapted so that
music retains its meaningful role in cultural
identity.</p>

<p>The music of the Plains is the most familiar
Native American music to non-Indian peoples,
due in large part to its use in television
and motion pictures (including the Academy
Award–winning <title>Dances with Wolves</title>, which
featured performances by the Porcupine Singers,
a well-known Lakota musical group). The
high, tense vocal style, the descending melodic
pattern, the vocables (meaningful syllables
without a direct English translation), and the
rhythmic drumming of the Plains are immediately
identifiable as "Indian music" throughout
the world. Because of its familiarity, it is
often erroneously used in entertainment venues
to represent the musical practices of all
Indians, regardless of tribal or cultural identity.
A recent renaissance of interest in Native
cultures has, in large part, corrected this misconception.</p>

<p>The defining characteristics of Plains style
music include a tense, tight, and rather strained
vocal style; among Northern Plains tribes a
high vocal range, among the tribes of the
Southern Plains a medium range; "collapsible"
melodic contour-melodies that begin high,
drop drastically lower over the course of a
song, and frequently end with repetitions of
the tonic pitch; ululations produced by rapidly
fluttering the tongue against the roof of the
mouth; singing mostly in unison; and, normally,
one large drum played by several musicians
to accompany songs. Lyrics may be sung
entirely in a tribal language, entirely in vocables,
in English, or in any combination.</p>

<p>Drums, the best-known type of Indian instrument,
are made in many sizes and shapes
and from diverse materials. Both small hand
drums&#8211;twelve to eighteen inches in circumference
and covered on one or both sides with
a rawhide head and played by one person&#8211;
and larger "powwow" drums&#8211;sometimes the
size of a marching band bass drum and played
simultaneously by several musicians&#8211;are
commonly used among Plains tribes. In contemporary
practice, the word "drum" refers
not only as a noun to the instrument itself but
also as a verb to the performers who play it
and sing. Many tribes consider the drum to
represent the heartbeat of Mother Earth and
to offer a means of communication with the
supernatural. Because of this significance,
tribes often establish strict protocols for playing
the drum.</p>

<p>Rattles are the most ubiquitous type of instrument
and display great inventiveness with
natural materials. Modern Plains Indians have
incorporated virtually every type of material
imaginable into the construction of rattles:
gourds, turtle shells, carved wood, deer
hooves, animal horns, animal hide, and tree
bark. Other percussive instruments include
large dance bells attached to the arms or legs of
dancers to provide an ambient accompaniment
to dancing, rasps, and wooden sticks.</p>

<p>Flutes and whistles are the primary melodic
instruments among Plains Indians. Members
of Coronado's sixteenth-century expedition
into the Southern Plains provided the first
documentation of flute music by non-Indian
sources, while Lewis and Clark noted the use
of flutes among Northern Plains peoples in
the early nineteenth century. In pre-twentieth-century
traditional practices, the flute was
used primarily to perform courting songs,
though some tribes used flutes and whistles
in healing ceremonies. Flute performance
among Plains tribes, however, had virtually
disappeared by the early twentieth century.
Kiowa musician Doc Tate Nevaquaya is credited
with reviving the tradition of flute making
and playing in the late 1940s and 1950s.
Contemporary musicians, including Kevin
Locke (Lakota), Joseph Fire Crow (Cheyenne),
Tom Mauchahty Ware (Comanche-Kiowa),
and Robert Tree Cody (Dakota-Maricopa),
have expanded the role of the Indian flute far
beyond its traditional role in courtship and
healing to embrace social songs, dances, and
popular songs. The sound of the Indian flute is
now heard in motion picture scores and jazz
and rock bands in addition to more traditional
venues.</p>

<p>Native American music continues to thrive
and evolve. Contemporary musicians are exploring
combinations of traditional and non-
Indian musics to create new styles and genres
that retain a distinctively Native American
identity. Non-Indian popular music genres
such as rock, country, and jazz have been successfully
adapted into the modern Indian repertoire
by artists such as Tom Bee (Lakota)
performing with <hi rend="smallcaps">XIT</hi>, the first commercially
successful all-Indian rock band, and Keith
Secola (Anishinaabe) and the Wild Band
of Indians. Indian musicians such as Buffy
Sainte-Marie (Cree) and R. Carlos Nakai (Ute-
Navajo) contribute to motion picture and television
scores, and the orchestral and choral
compositions of Oklahoma-born composerconductor
Louis Ballard (Quapaw-Cherokee)
mark the beginnings of Indian symphonic and
chamber music. Pianist Paul La Roche (Lakota)
combines traditional and New Age elements
in his unique works for keyboard.</p>

<p>Powwows and tribal fairs held throughout
the Great Plains provide opportunities to experience
all musical styles and genres of today's
Plains Indians, including generationsold
traditional songs and dances as well as
contemporary popular music. Modern powwows
and tribal fairs are celebrations of Native
American culture and include displays of
tribal arts and crafts, meals of traditional Native
foods, and discussions of social and political
issues in addition to the music and dance.
They are as much community social events as
dance performances. Music and dance include
ceremonial performances restricted to initiated
members of the tribe; competitive dancing
featuring world-class performers of grass
dances, fancy dances, jingle dress, and specialty
dances; and the after-hours social dances
referred to as "forty-nine" dances, the popular
music and dance of younger tribal members.
Among the larger Plains powwows and tribal
fairs held annually are Red Earth Powwow,
Oklahoma City, Oklahoma; Gathering of Nations,
Albuquerque, New Mexico; Crow Fair,
Crow Agency, Montana; and United Tribes
Powwow, Bismarck, North Dakota. However,
smaller local gatherings offer insights into Indian
song and dance in a more intimate setting
that allows more interaction among performers
and audience members.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">NATIVE AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.na.091">Powwows</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">SPORTS AND RECREATION</hi>: <ref n="egp.sr.012">Crow Fair</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>J. Bryan Burton<lb/>
West Chester University of Pennsylvania</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Burton, J. Bryan. <title level="m">Moving within the Circle: Contemporary Native American Music and Dance</title>. Danbury <hi rend="smallcaps">CT</hi>: World
Music Press, 1993.</bibl> <bibl>Heth, Charlotte, ed. <title level="m">Native American Dance: Ceremonies and Social Traditions</title>. Washington <hi rend="smallcaps">DC</hi>:
Smithsonian Institution Press, 1992.</bibl> <bibl>Laubin, Reginald,
and Gladys Laubin. <title level="m">Indian Dances of North America&#8211;
Their Importance to Indian Life</title>. Norman: University of
Oklahoma Press, 1989.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>