<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.law.033">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main"><hi rend="italic">Montana v. United States</hi></title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Mark R. Scherer</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.law.033</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Scherer, Mark R.">Mark R. Scherer</author>. <title level="a">"<hi rend="italic">Montana v. United States</hi>."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">457-458</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-05</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main"><hi rend="italic">MONTANA V. UNITED STATES</hi></head>

<p>In <hi rend="italic">Montana v. United States</hi> (1981), the U.S.
Supreme Court ruled that the Crow Tribe of
Montana did not possess the inherent sovereign
power to regulate hunting and fishing
by nonmembers of the tribe on lands owned
by non-Indians within its reservation boundaries. The decision arose out of a dispute between
the Crows and the state of Montana
over the question of which entity had jurisdiction
to control hunting and fishing within
the reservation boundaries and primarily
focused on the right to regulate fishing and
duck hunting on and around the Big Horn
River, which flows through the Crow reservation.
The Crows based their claim on their
inherent powers of tribal sovereignty and the
language of the various treaties that created
their reservation and, they argued, gave them
ownership of the bed of the Big Horn River.
Montana, on the other hand, argued that it
took title to the riverbed at the time it became
a state and that it had always maintained the
authority to regulate hunting and fishing by
non-Indians within the reservation.</p>

<p>In an attempt to resolve the conflict, the
United States, acting as trustee for the tribe,
initiated a lawsuit in 1975 seeking a judicial
resolution of both the threshold question of
title to the riverbed and the accompanying
jurisdictional dispute over hunting and fishing
rights. The federal district court ruled in
favor of Montana, holding that the state rather
than the Crows owned the banks and bed of
the Big Horn River. The Ninth Circuit Court
of Appeals reversed the district court's decision,
holding, with some qualifications, that
the treaties establishing the Crow Reservation
had vested title to the riverbed in the United
States as trustee for the tribe and that the
Crows could regulate hunting and fishing
within the reservation by nonmembers. In its
1981 decision, the Supreme Court reversed the
court of appeals, essentially restoring the district
court's judgment in favor of the state of
Montana.</p>

<p>Two components of the ruling are key. On
the question of title to the riverbed, the Court
held that, notwithstanding certain ostensibly
contradictory language in the 1851 and 1868
treaties by which the Crow Reservation was
formed, title to the riverbed passed to the state
of Montana upon its admission into the Union
in 1889. With respect to the broader issues
of inherent tribal sovereignty, the Court acknowledged
that Indian tribes still maintain
certain powers of self-government but went
on to hold that those powers extend only to
the control of "internal relations." Extension
of tribal power beyond the realm of internal
tribal matters, the Court ruled, would be "inconsistent
with the dependent status of the
tribes." Finding that control of hunting and
fishing by nonmembers on lands no longer
owned by the tribe (but still within its reservation)
bears "no clear relationship to tribal selfgovernment
or internal relations," the Court
held that the Crows did not possess the "retained
inherent sovereignty" to regulate those
activities.</p>

<p>The <hi rend="italic">Montana</hi> decision and others like it are
universally perceived by Native Americans
and their supporters as troubling judicial assaults
on the remnants of tribal sovereignty,
confirming the extremely fragile nature of
that sovereignty and reiterating the ultimate
power of the federal government to define the
precise scope and extent of Indian powers of
self-determination.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">NATIVE AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.na.024">Crows</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Mark R. Scherer<lb/>
University of Nebraska at Omaha</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Bloxham, Steven John. "Tribal Sovereignty: An Analysis of
Montana v. United States." <title level="j">American Indian Law Review</title> 8
(1980): 175–81.</bibl> <bibl>Canby, William C., Jr. <title level="m">American Indian Law in a Nutshell</title>. 3rd ed. St. Paul <hi rend="smallcaps">MN</hi>: West Group, 1998.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>