<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.afam.032">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Omaha Race Riot</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Orville D. Menard</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.afam.032</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Menard, Orville">Orville Menard</author>. <title level="a">"Omaha Race Riot."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">19</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-12-03</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">OMAHA RACE RIOT</head>
<figure n="egp.afam.032" rend="granted" type="noclick">
<figDesc>"Rioters on the south side of Douglas County Courthouse,Omaha, Nebraska,September 28, 1919." (NSHS RG2281-72). (nebraskastudies.org)</figDesc>
</figure>     

<p>During the frenzy of a riot in Omaha, Nebraska,
on September 28, 1919, Will Brown,
an African American, was lynched near the
Douglas County courthouse. He was accused
of raping Agnes Loebeck, a white woman.
Identified by Loebeck and Milton Hoffman,
the young man with her on the night of the
alleged attack, Brown had been taken to the
police station and then transferred to the
courthouse jail. On Sunday morning, the
twenty-eighth, a crowd of mostly young men
gathered at a school on the south side and was
led downtown by Hoffman, adding followers
as it progressed.</p>

<p>Earlier in the afternoon the situation
seemed nonthreatening, but it turned ugly as
time passed and more people appeared on the
scene. From 300 at the school, the crowd increased
late in the day to an estimated 4,000
at the courthouse. Demanding that Brown
be handed over to them, the demonstrators
turned on the police and set the courthouse on
fire. When firefighters appeared, their hoses
were cut into pieces by rioters who had broken
into nearby hardware stores and stolen axes as
well as firearms. Mayor Edward P. Smith was at
the scene and came out of the courthouse at
about 10:30 p.m. to try to restore order. He
became a target of the mob and was nearly
lynched himself before being rescued.</p>

<p>The mob then turned its attention back to
Brown, who along with other prisoners had
been taken to the roof of the courthouse as the
fire spread. Finally the rioters achieved their
goal and Brown was taken and reportedly
handed over the heads of the rioters down
the stairs. By the time the ground floor was
reached, he had likely been beaten to death.
Hoisted into the air on a lynch rope, his swaying
body was then riddled with bullets. Not
yet satisfied, the crowd pulled his corpse to a
nearby intersection where he was burned, and
what remained of Will Brown was then towed
about downtown Omaha. The victim's death
certificate gave his age as "about 40," marital
status unknown, birthplace left blank, and the
principal cause of death bullet wounds and
strangulation.</p>

<p>During the night federal troops restored
order, and in the morning, armed with machine
guns, they guarded downtown streets.
Several arrests were made in the following
days for complicity in the riot, but a grand
jury's deliberations resulted in only a few indictments
of little consequence.</p>

<p>Omaha was not the only city where rioting
blighted the summer and fall of 1919. Chicago
and Washington dc, among others, had outbreaks
of racial violence and deaths. But in
Omaha racial tensions may have been orchestrated
for political purposes. A reform movement's
candidates had been elected in 1918,
defeating the political machine headed by
Thomas "Old Man" Dennison that had dominated
city hall for two decades. Direct accusations
by church leaders and an assessment
by Gen. Leonard Wood assigned responsibility
for the lynching to political ambition.
They asserted that to discredit the reformers,
Dennison and his newspaper ally, the Omaha
Bee, exaggerated crime and racial tensions to
create the atmosphere that exploded on September
28, 1919. Two years later voters restored
the Dennison slate to office. Will Brown appears
to have been the victim of political
machinations as well as racial prejudice.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">CITIES AND TOWN</hi>: <ref n="egp.ct.037">Omaha, Nebraska</ref>.</p>


<closer>
<signed>Orville D. Menard<lb/>
University of Nebraska at Omaha</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Menard, Orville D. <title level="m">Political Bossism in Mid-America: Tom
Dennison's Omaha</title>. Lanham <hi rend="smallcaps">MD</hi>: University Press of
America, 1989.</bibl> <bibl>Menard, Orville D. "<title level="a">Tom Dennison, the
Omaha Bee, and the 1919 Omaha Race Riot</title>." <hi rend="italic">Nebraska
History</hi> 68 (1987): 152–65.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>