<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.mus.051">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">West Texas Family Music Making</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Pamela H. Brink</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.mus.051</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Brink, Pamela H.">Pamela H. Brink</author>. <title level="a">"West Texas Family Music Making."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">550-551</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-03</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">WEST TEXAS FAMILY MUSIC MAKING</head>

<p>Defined by the dramatic landscape of the
Llano Estacado, a vast mesa 3,000 feet high
and 300 miles across with accompanying canyonlands,
the high plains of Texas are bordered
by Oklahoma on the north, the Edwards
Plateau on the south, New Mexico on
the west, and I-35 on the east. This land, commonly
known as West Texas, possesses a distinctive
regional culture shaped by the cattle,
cotton, and oil industries, a perennial wind,
and a seemingly endless sky. One of the most
meaningful manifestations of this regional
culture is a tradition of music making that has
influenced the shape and style of popular music
since Amarillo's Eck Robertson made the
nation's first country music recording in 1922.</p>

<p>For the farm families who settled here in
the early 1900s, music making was not only a
prominent form of family entertainment but
also one of the few opportunities available to
escape a hardscrabble existence. Those with a
talent on the fiddle could earn more money
playing for a Saturday night dance than they
could chopping cotton for a week.</p>

<p>Bob Wills came from a musical family who
moved to Memphis near Amarillo in 1913. His
father, John T. Wills, was a famous contest
fiddler, often competing against Eck Robertson
for championship status. To the Wills
family, string band music was a serious study,
and by the time Bob Wills was ten years old,
he was playing mandolin to his father's fiddle
at local dances. As bandleader for Bob Wills
and His Texas Playboys, Wills gained international
fame by developing and popularizing
western swing music through tours, recordings,
and Hollywood movies.</p>

<p>The pattern of Wills's career is emblematic
of a family music-making tradition that permeates
West Texas, a tradition rooted in rigorous
fiddle or guitar training learned primarily
at home, polished with family members and
friends for public performance, and inspired
in rhythm and technique by a regional predilection
for ballroom dancing based on a
strong backbeat. Since Bob Wills, West Texas
music has achieved that backbeat with drums.</p>

<p>Hoyle Nix also came from a cotton-farming,
musical family and learned the fiddle from his
father, Jonah. In 1946 he formed the West Texas
Cowboys, based out of Big Spring. Brother Ben
played guitar in the band, and Hoyle's son Jody
joined the group at age eight as the drummer.
The West Texas Cowboys is a classic western
swing band featuring lead fiddle, so when Jody
took over the band in 1985, he gave up his
drums for the fiddle he had been playing in the
background since age eleven.</p>

<p>Tommy Hancock, as fiddler and bandleader,
and Charlene Condray, as lead singer,
met and married in Lubbock while performing
with the Roadside Cowboys in the 1950s.
They reopened the Cotton Club in Lubbock in
the 1960s and welcomed a new generation of
musicians to their performance arena. Influenced
by the counterculture movement, in the
1970s the Hancocks moved to New Mexico,
where their children grew up singing and
playing music for entertainment. The family
ultimately formed a musical touring group,
the Supernatural Family Band, and today
Charlene and daughters Traci and Conni still
perform together as the Texana Dames.</p>

<p>In instrumental virtuosity, performance
style, range of selection, and family ties, the
Maines Brothers Band stands as the quintessential
West Texas music group. Four of the
seven-member band are brothers whose father,
Wayne Maines, and uncles, James and
Sonny, were the feature artists for the original
Lubbock-based Maines Brothers Band popular
in the 1950s and 1960s. Brothers Lloyd and
Steve took up guitar as teenagers, and Kenny
started playing electric bass at age eleven.
Soon they were performing with their father's
band and playing gigs with their own group.
When he was old enough, brother Donnie
joined them on drums. Today, besides performing
with his brothers, Lloyd Maines coproduces
and plays pedal steel and guitars for
the Dixie Chicks, which features his daughter
Natalie Maines as lead singer.</p>

<p>When the Maines Brothers Band takes the
stage, audiences are treated to a primarily
guitar-led rhythm celebration of the complete
spectrum of West Texas music. A concert
might easily include songs made famous by
television personalities Mac Davis from Lubbock
and Jimmy Dean from Plainview, a rendition
of the Rhythm Orchids' "Party Doll,"
a medley of greats from Wink's Roy Orbison
or Lubbock's Buddy Holly, plus favorites by
Odessa's Gatlin Brothers and Lubbock's Jimmie
Dale Gilmore and Joe Ely. With an instrumental
combination that includes a myriad of
guitars, harmonica, drums and other percussion,
pedal steel, Hawaiian slide, fiddle, mandolin,
keyboard, and occasional jazz accordion
and horns, the band has the musicianship to
entertain with everything from Bob Wills's
"San Antonio Rose" to favorites by Terry Allen
and Butch Hancock. While Kenny Maines is
the primary lead vocalist, band members Steve
Maines and Jerry Brownlow also take their
turns, and everybody else joins in on harmony,
including sister LaTronda Maines.</p>

<p>Versatile instrumentation is the foundation
of West Texas music, with vocals serving as
just a basic part of the mix. Except for Roy
Orbison and Don Williams of Floydada, West
Texas music tends to feature craggy-edged
lead vocalists who sell a song with spirit rather
than tone and tenor. Nowhere is this more
apparent than in the list of female stars who
hail from West Texas. From Natalie Maines to
Seminole's Tanya Tucker, Fort Worth's Lee
Ann Barton, Lubbock's Angela Strehli, Anton's
Jeannie C. Reilly, and Kermit's Charline
Arthur, West Texas female singers tend to
project a raw, unschooled bluesy edge and a
worldly wise demeanor to match.</p>

<p>Lubbock's Kimmie Rhodes is another example
of the raspy-voiced West Texas lead vocalist,
but her career points more significantly to
the prolific songwriting tradition that emanates
from the region. From Amarillo's Susan
Gibson and "Wide Open Spaces" to Kimmie
Rhodes and Natalie Maines, to Jimmie Dale
Gilmore's long list of lyrics and Butch Hancock's
even longer list, to Joe Ely, Terry Allen,
Angela Strehli, and her brother Al Strehli, current
performing artists from West Texas continue
to generate volumes of poignant and
witty lyrics, many with a decidedly selfconscious
regional perspective.</p>

<p>Their talents are equally matched by their
predecessors. Buddy Holly is credited with
popularizing original songwriting in rock and
roll recordings, and his songs have withstood
the test of time, including his first hit, "That'll
Be the Day," and his "Not Fade Away," which
became the unofficial theme song for the
Grateful Dead. Waylon Jennings, electric bass
player on the final, fatal Buddy Holly tour who
gave up his seat to the Big Bopper, penned a
number of memorable songs alone and in collaboration
with fellow "outlaw" Willie Nelson.
Holly's lifelong friend and member of the
Crickets, Sonny Curtis, also has many songs to
his credit, including <title>The Mary Tyler Moore Show</title> theme song and "Walk Right Back."</p>

<p>Woody Guthrie represents yet another generation
of West Texas songwriters. Although
born in Oklahoma, Guthrie didn't play music
until he moved to Texas as a teenager in 1929.
He learned guitar from his uncle Jeff and put
together the Corncob Trio, which represented
Pampa at the 1936 Texas centennial celebration.
Guthrie soon left West Texas, as did his
contemporaries Hugh and Karl Farr, who
joined Roy Rogers in Hollywood to become
members of the Sons of the Pioneers. Guthrie
remained a lone and significant voice of the
people, writing volumes of folk songs, including
what has been termed our uno.cial national
anthem, "This Land Is Your Land."</p>

<p>While the core of West Texas music is the
family, a musical kinship runs even deeper,
crossing stylistic lines to make manifest an innovative
instrumental virtuosity celebrated by
every age and social grouping. Tommy Allsup
serves as a significant case in point. Allsup
began his career playing electric guitar for Bob
Wills and the Texas Playboys, organized his
own band in Odessa with Moon Mullican as
his boogie-woogie pianist, served as a sessions
player at the Norman Petty Studio in Clovis,
New Mexico, and played lead guitar on the
final Buddy Holly tour, giving up his seat
on the plane to Richie Valens. Through his
Odessa recording studio in 1965, he produced
the Zager and Evans hit "In the Year 2525" and
in Nashville the two-album set <title>Bob Wills, For the Last Time</title>, featuring many of the original
Playboys and Hoyle and Jody Nix. His career
runs the gamut of popular musical styles, usually
defined in ethnic and generational lines,
to confirm Waylon Jennings's observation: "I
have always felt that blues, rock and roll, and
country are just about a beat apart."</p>

<closer>
<signed>Pamela H. Brink<lb/>
Associated Authors and Editors, Inc.</signed>
</closer>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>