<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.na.040">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Hunting</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Pekka H&#228;m&#228;l&#228;inen</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.na.040</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="H&#228;m&#228;l&#228;inen, Pekka">Pekka H&#228;m&#228;l&#228;inen</author>. <title level="a">"Hunting."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">576-577</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-15</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">HUNTING</head>

<p>The celebrated horse-mounted bison hunters
of the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries in
the Great Plains have captured the popular
imagination, but their reign represents only a
relatively short phase in the long and complex
history of Plains Indian hunting. Twelve thousand
years ago, the Plains was home to eightton
mastodons, twelve-feet-tall mammoths,
giant bison, and wild horses. A growing number
of Clovis people hunted these massive animals
by driving them into swamps or box canyons
and piercing their thick hides with sharp,
fluted darts and spears using atlatls, or leverlike
spear throwers. Such ventures were dangerous,
but the rewards were worth the risk: a single
kill could keep a hunting group of thirty to fifty
people furnished with meat and fat for weeks.
By around 9000 <hi rend="smallcaps">B.C.</hi>, however, warming climate,
changing vegetation cover, and, apparently,
overhunting pushed the Pleistocene
megafauna into extinction, marking the end of
the first great hunting culture of the Plains.</p>

<p>The Plains people adjusted to the disappearance
of large mammals by concentrating
their efforts on smaller animals such as deer,
elk, pronghorn antelopes, grizzlies, and modern
species of bison. They perfected a wide
range of killing techniques: they camouflaged
themselves in animal skins and patiently
stalked their prey; ambushed individual animals
at water holes; drove entire herds into
manmade corrals; or stampeded bison over
high bluffs and then slaughtered the crippled
animals with spears, darts, and stones. About
2,000 years ago Plains Indians also learned the
use of the bow and arrow, which allowed them
to kill effectively from a safe distance.</p>

<p>By about 1000 <hi rend="smallcaps">A.D.</hi>, however, encouraged
by a wetter climate, the Plains people began to
focus increasingly on farming, and hunting
gradually became a secondary economic activity.
By the thirteenth century there were still
large numbers of nomadic hunters on the
western shortgrass Plains (where Spanish explorers
would encounter their descendants in
the sixteenth century), but most Plains Indians
lived along the eastern river valleys,
where they based their economies on farming
and sporadic hunting excursions.</p>

<p>This trend was suddenly reversed in the
seventeenth and eighteenth centuries when
horses became available to the Plains Indians.
The horse was the missing tool that made it
possible for Indians to begin a systematic exploitation
of the enormous resource of protein,
fat, and hides that was stored in the bodies
of an estimated 30 million bison in the
Plains. On horseback, hunters could follow
the migrating herds more closely and over a
wider range, kill the animals more e.ciently,
and carry back more meat and hides. Attracted
by previously unimagined hunting
possibilities, Indians poured into the Plains
from all directions, creating one of most renowned
hunting cultures in history.</p>

<p>By the early nineteenth century the Plains
Indians had mastered an array of equestrian
bison-hunting techniques that were carefully
adapted to the seasonal and geographical variations
of the region. In the winter, hunters
drove bison into snow-filled gulches or snowdrifts,
and in the summer, into swamps, rivers,
or corrals. In the Northern Plains, where
horses were in short supply, many groups continued
to rely on pedestrian hunting techniques,
such as the foot surround. Many Plains
groups also burned sections of grasslands to
make bison migrations and aggregations more
predictable. The most popular method was the
mounted chase, in which hunters galloped after
bison on carefully trained running horses,
thrusting lances or shooting volleys of arrows
at the sides of the animals. A short bow remained
the bison hunters' preferred weapon,
because muskets were difficult to load and
handle on horseback, and because powder and
ball were scarce and expensive, and thus better
reserved for warfare.</p>

<p>In the winter and spring Plains Indians usually
hunted in small groups of few individuals,
but in the summer and fall, when bison congregated
into massive herds, hunting became a
collective effort of hundreds of people. A typical
mass hunt involved several stages, each
consecrated by rituals. The preparation began
with a bison-calling ceremony, usually a dance,
song, or prayer performed by a medicine man.
When the herd was located, a camp police of
distinguished warriors took over, making sure
nobody would try to start the hunt prematurely
and stampede the herd. On the chief's
order, the entire camp moved out as an orderly
column&#8211;first the scouts, then medicine men,
priests, and leaders, and finally old men,
women, and children. Young men rode on
both sides of the column, providing protection
and ready to charge when the prey came in
sight. The actual hunt might take only about
thirty minutes, for bison had more endurance
than horses and could pull away in few minutes,
but that was enough time for most hunters
to bring down several animals. After the
chase was over, the families moved in to
butcher their animals (each hunter used arrows
and lances of his own design for recognition),
turning the carcasses swiftly into piles of
sliced meat, tallow, and hides. A successful
hunt ended with ritual smoking, dancing, and
feasting, which helped Indians maintain a
proper relationship with animal spirits.</p>

<p>Although all Plains groups continued to
hunt deer, elk, bears, porcupines, and other
animals for clothing, food, tools, and jewelry,
by the late eighteenth century most Plains Indians
had developed a singular dependency
on the buffalo. The western Plains became the
domain of highly specialized hunter-nomads
who fed, clothed, sheltered, and decorated
themselves from the skin, flesh, fat, and bones
of the bison. What they could not get by hunting,
they acquired by trading surplus hides,
dried meat, pemmican, and other products of
the hunt. The eastern horticulturists, too, intensified
their hunting practices and began to
make extended semiannual hunting expeditions
to the western Plains.</p>

<p>This emphasis on bison hunting persisted
even after the advent of the commercial fur
trade in the late eighteenth century. Some
northern groups began producing deerskins
and beaver pelts for trading posts, but most
Plains Indians refused to take up trapping and
instead provisioned European American trappers
with bison meat and pemmican. From
the 1830s on, following the collapse of beaver
trade, bison robes became the primary focus
of the fur trade, and during the following four
decades Plains Indians produced more than
200,000 hides and skins and 40 to 100 tons of
pemmican a year for European American
markets.</p>

<p>Such reliance on a narrow ecological base
ultimately proved unsustainable, pushing the
bison populations into a steep decline by the
mid–nineteenth century. The traditional
Plains Indian hunting culture came to an end
in the 1870s and 1880s with the near extermination
of the bison by commercial white
hunters and the often violent removal of Indians
into reservations, where Indian agents
endeavored to transform them from hunters
into farmers. Some Indians refused to give up
their chosen lifestyle and continued to leave
reservations in a desperate search for the few
surviving bison. By the 1890s, however, all
Plains Indians had been forced to abandon
their dream of living as hunters. Today, a few
Plains Indians make a living by hunting, or by
mixing hunting with other economic activities,
but even these efforts are threatened by
the ongoing legal struggles among tribal, state,
and federal governments over hunting rights.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Pekka H&#228;m&#228;l&#228;inen<lb/>
Texas A&amp;M University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Frison, George C. <title level="m">Prehistoric Hunters of the High Plains</title>.
San Diego: Academic Press, 1991.</bibl> <bibl>Isenberg, Andrew C. <title level="m">The
Destruction of the Bison: An Environmental History, 1750–
1920</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2000.</bibl>
<bibl>Lowie, Robert H. <title level="m">Indians of the Plains</title>. New York: McGraw-
Hill Book Company, Inc., 1954.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>