<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.rel.046">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Sun Dance</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Dale Stover</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.rel.046</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Stover, Dale">Dale Stover</author>. <title level="a">"Sun Dance."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">757</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-19</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">SUN DANCE</head>
<figure n="egp.rel.046" rend="granted">
<figDesc>"INDIAN SUN DANCE: Native American Sioux Sun Dance, a man with his chest skin attached, with sinew, to a pole, drummers, spectators" by George Catlin</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>The Sun Dance is a distinctive ceremony that
is central to the religious identity of the Indigenous
peoples of the Great Plains. It developed
among the horse-mounted, bisonhunting
nations who populated the Great
Plains in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries.
Those nations at the core of its practice
in the bison-hunting era that have continued
its practice into the contemporary period include
the Arapahos, the Cheyennes (Southern
and Northern), the Blackfoot (who include
the Siksikas or Blackfoot proper, the Bloods or
Kainahs, and the Northern and Southern Piegans
or Pikunis), and the Sioux (including in
particular the westernmost Sioux, who are the
seven tribes of the Lakota nation, but also including
the Yanktons and Santees, who comprise
the six tribes of the Dakota nation).
From these four nations, the Sun Dance ceremony
spread to the Kiowas and Comanches,
who ranged the Southern Plains, and to Northern
Plains nations such as the Plains Crees of
Saskatchewan and the Sarcees of Alberta, as well
as to virtually every other Plains nation in the
land between these two extremes, including the
Arikaras, Assiniboines, Crows, Gros Ventres,
Hidatsas, Mandans, Pawnees, Plains Ojibwas,
Poncas, Shoshones, and Utes.</p>

<p>The Canadian and U.S. governments perceived
this ceremony as superstitious rather
than religious and suppressed it, and full liberty
to practice the Sun Dance was regained only
after the mid–twentieth century. Some Sun
Dances, including the Kiowa, Comanche, and
Crow ceremonies, ended in the nineteenth century.
Others persisted clandestinely through the
time of suppression. The Crows in 1941 formally
renewed practice of the ceremony by receiving
the Shoshone form as their own.</p>

<p>The name Sun Dance derives from the Sioux
identification of it as <hi rend="italic">Wi wanyang wacipi</hi>,
translated as "sun gazing dance." Other Plains
peoples have names for the ceremony that do
not refer to the sun. The Arapaho, Cheyenne,
and Blackfoot names for the ceremony all refer
to the medicine lodge within which the ritual
dancing occurs. The medicine lodge is constructed
of pole rafters radiating from a sacred
central pole. However, the best-known and
most widely practiced contemporary form of
the ceremony is that of the Sioux, who do not
construct a medicine lodge. Instead, the Sioux
make a hocoka, or ritual circle, with a sacred
cottonwood tree erected in the center and a
circular arbor built around the entire perimeter,
except for an open entrance to the east, so
that the dancing takes place within a central
arena that is completely open to the sky and
to "sun gazing." However, both traditions,
whether that of the medicine lodge or of the
hocoka, involve ritual ways of making local
space sacred as a setting for renewal of the
people's relationship with the land itself and
with all the beings of their life-world, both
human and other-than-human.</p>

<p>The ceremony is highly variable because its
performance is intimately connected to the
authoritative guidance of visions or dreams
that establish an individual relationship between
one or more of the central participants
and one or more spirit persons. In all cases,
however, the primary meaning is understood
to be the performance of acts of sacrifice in
ritual reciprocity with spiritual powers so
that the welfare of friends, family, and the
whole people is enhanced. The Arapaho,
Cheyenne, Blackfoot, and Sioux nations all
practice sacrificial acts of piercing the flesh,
often described pejoratively as "torture" by
outsiders. Others, such as the Ute, Shoshone,
and Crow nations, perform sacrificial acts of
embodying their spiritual intentions through
fasting and intense dancing, but not through
piercing.</p>

<p>Some Indigenous interpreters have suggested
an analogy between the piercing of sun
dancers and the piercing of Jesus on the cross,
seeing both as acts of voluntary sacrifice on
behalf of other beings and the cosmic welfare.
While this interpretation may facilitate understanding
for some, interpreters must be wary
of imposing any religious category that clashes
with the central concern of the Sun Dance: to
establish and maintain kinship with all the
people's relatives, including other humans, the
animal and plant relatives of this earth, and
the cosmic relatives of the spirit realm.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">ARCHITECTURE</hi>: <ref n="egp.arc.035">Native American Traditional Architecture</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Dale Stover<lb/>
University of Nebraska at Omaha</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Densmore, Frances. <title level="m">Teton Sioux Music and Culture</title>. Lincoln:
University of Nebraska Press, 1992.</bibl> <bibl>Dorsey, George
Amos. <title level="m">The Arapaho Sun Dance: The Ceremony of the Offerings
Lodge</title>. Field Columbian Museum Publication, no.
75. Chicago: Field Museum of Natural History, 1903.</bibl> <bibl>Farr,
William E. <title level="m">The Reservation Blackfeet, 1882–1945: A Photographic
History of Cultural Survival</title>. Seattle: University
of Washington Press, 1986.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>