<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ind.012">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Chouteau, Pierre, Jr. (1789-1865)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>David J. Wishart</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ind.012</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</author>. <title level="a">"Chouteau, Pierre, Jr. (1789-1865)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">413-414</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-02</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">CHOUTEAU, PIERRE, JR. (1789-1865)</head>

<p>Pierre Chouteau Jr., familiarly known as "Cadet"
(meaning second-born son), was the
leading entrepreneur in the Great Plains for
much of the first half of the nineteenth century.
Son of the St. Louis trader and banker
Jean Pierre Chouteau (1758–1849), Pierre was
destined to succeed: after all, his family was
instrumental in the founding of St. Louis, and,
with great enterprise as well as timely switches
of political allegiance and strategic marriages,
they had amassed a fortune from mining,
banking, and the fur trade, a fortune that
Pierre would multiply.</p>

<p>He was born in St. Louis on January 19,
1789, and by the time he was fifteen he was
engaged in the fur trade with the Osages. In
1810 he left to develop his family's interests
in the Dubuque (Iowa) lead mines, but while
mining remained an interest for him until the
1850s, his sights were set on the West.</p>

<p>Back in St. Louis in 1812, Chouteau opened
a store with the merchant Bartholomew Berthold
and began an association with the western
fur trade that would last for half a century.
The partnership backed Manuel Lisa's trading
expedition to the upper Missouri in 1819 and
lost heavily. In the maelstrom of competition
for the Indian trade that followed, Berthold
and Chouteau built trading posts on the Missouri
as far north as present-day South Dakota.
Gradually, Chouteau eased into an economic
relationship with John Jacob Astor's
American Fur Company, a relationship that
was formalized in 1826 with a merger of interests
that left Pierre as head of the company's
Western Department.</p>

<p>From that point on, Pierre Chouteau Jr.'s
wealth and influence soared. After Astor's retirement
from the fur trade in 1834, Chouteau's
company (by then Pratte, Chouteau and Company)
became the dominant force in the fur
trade on the Central and Northern Great
Plains, with a network of trading posts stretching
from Fort Union (present-day North Dakota)
to Fort Laramie (present-day Wyoming).
A disastrous overextension of operations into
the volatile Rocky Mountain trapping system
in 1834 (a rare miscalculation on Chouteau's
part) was terminated in 1839. By that time his
enterprise was simply P. Chouteau Jr. and
Company, and under that name it moved hundreds
of thousands of bison robes through
St. Louis to the main markets in the eastern
United States over the following twenty-five
years.</p>

<p>Pierre Chouteau Jr. was a driven man and a
ruthless competitor&#8211;the epitome of a frontier
capitalist. He was also an innovator who, for
example, was instrumental in introducing
steamboat navigation on the Missouri River in
1832, which revolutionized the scale of the fur
trade. He was deeply involved in the negotiation
of Indian treaties, in part because of the
clauses that mandated the payment of debts to
traders. The lucrative and often nefarious business
of supplying annuities to Indian reservations
was another of his endeavors. Through
these and other ventures, he built an estate
worth millions of dollars.</p>

<p>In the late 1850s his health began to fail. In
1859 he lost his sight; three years later he lost
Emile, his wife of fifty years. Pierre Chouteau
Jr. died on September 16, 1865, in St. Louis, a
city he had done so much to build.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">HISPANIC AMERICANS</hi>: Lisa, Manuel.</p>

<closer>
<signed>David J. Wishart<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Lecompte, Janet. "Pierre Chouteau Junior." In <title level="m">The Mountain Men and the Fur Trade of the Far West</title>, edited by
LeRoy R. Hafen, 9: 91–123.</bibl> <bibl>Glendale <hi rend="smallcaps">CA</hi>: Arthur H. Clark
Company, 1972.</bibl> <bibl>Sunder, John E. <title level="m">The Fur Trade on the Upper Missouri, 1840–1865</title>. Norman: University of Oklahoma
Press, 1965.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>