<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.war.012">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Cold War</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Scott D. Hughes</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.war.012</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Hughes, Scott D.">Scott D. Hughes</author>. <title level="a">"Cold War."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">825</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-26</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">COLD WAR</head>

<p>The cold war was primarily a struggle between
the United States and the Soviet Union to decide
which of their respective economic and
ideological systems&#8211;free-market capitalism
or centrally controlled socialism&#8211;would
dominate world affairs. Beginning during the
closing years of the 1940s, the conflict deepened
during the 1950s as the two powers sought
to influence events around the globe. As the
ideological battles played out, technological
advances in weaponry increased the threat of
thermonuclear holocaust. This threat nearly
became reality in 1962, when the world went to
the brink of war during the Cuban missile crisis.
The cold war ended in 1991 when the Soviet
Union collapsed and reformed into the Federation
of Independent States.</p>

<p>Profoundly altering American culture and
life, the protracted conflict affected every region
of the United States, including the Great
Plains. The influence of the cold war in the
Great Plains began shortly after World War II.
In 1948 the Strategic Air Command (<hi rend="smallcaps">SAC</hi>) established
its headquarters at Offutt Air Force
Base outside Omaha, Nebraska. <hi rend="smallcaps">SAC</hi> served as
the air arm of the nation's offensive strategy
for waging nuclear war, and it existed as an
icon of American military power for the duration
of the cold war. Throughout the 1950s this
power was projected by the presence of longrange
bombers, such the <hi rend="smallcaps">B</hi>-36 and <hi rend="smallcaps">B</hi>-52, planes
that were capable of deployment into Soviet
airspace. With the introduction of intercontinental
ballistic missiles (<hi rend="smallcaps">ICBMS</hi>), the primary
importance of bombers waned, and various
generations of missiles, including the Atlas,
the Titan, the Minuteman, and the Cruise,
gained strategic prominence. Deployed across
the Great Plains, the weapons systems were
housed at air force bases located at Schilling,
Kansas; Altus, Oklahoma; Lincoln, Nebraska;
Ellsworth, South Dakota; and other sites. Supporting
the missiles and bombers were early-warning
radar installations existing in three
lines across the Northern Plains and the Prairie
Provinces. The various installations served
as economic engines, providing well-paid and
secure civilian support employment to local
inhabitants in host communities.</p>

<p>While the cold war brought economic benefits
to many of the inhabitants of the Great
Plains, it extracted a price as well. Most significantly,
the presence of bombers and missiles
across the region meant that inhabitants
faced a high probability of being targeted during
a nuclear attack. In recognition of this, the
federal government initiated a widespread
civil defense effort. In 1948 federal officials appointed
Russell J. Hopley, president of Northwestern
Bell Telephone of Omaha, Nebraska,
as the first director of the Office of Civil Defense
Planning. By October of that year, Hopley
had published <title level="m">Civil Defense for National
Security</title>, a manual that detailed protection
techniques that Americans could use in the
advent of war. The manual advocated a philosophy
of crisis relocation&#8211;the swift evacuation
of urban populations. The manual also
stressed the importance of combating panic
through a public information campaign. This
philosophy eventually gave way to another approach
that promoted personal responsibility
for civil defense: the home-based fallout
shelter.</p>

<p>During the early 1950s, in one installment
of the <hi rend="smallcaps">CBS</hi> television network show <title>Retrospect</title>,
national news host Douglas Edwards interviewed
the Brown family of Topeka, Kansas,
about their "experiment in survival." The exercise
involved both parents and their eight
children spending a week in a fallout shelter. It
so happened that the father was a commercial
builder who had built the featured structure.
In retrospect, the show was more a marketing
ploy for a business than a depiction of how a
middle-class American family might survive a
nuclear attack.</p>

<p>In reality, the civil defense effort proved little
more than a psychological salve for the American
populace. By the mid-1950s the Eisenhower
administration recognized that nuclear
war meant national suicide. Nevertheless, the
administration continued to promote the
myth of personal responsibility for civil defense
in order to avoid demoralizing the American
public. Ironically, the civil defense shelters
provided little, if any, protection against the
fallout threat people faced from the nearest
actual threat, government-conducted atmospheric
testing of nuclear weapons at the Nevada
Test Site.</p>

<p>The cold war never flared into open hostility
between the United States and the Soviet
Union. The weapons of mass destruction that
dotted the Great Plains served to threaten and
deter aggression from a society the U.S. government
viewed as a danger to the American
way of life and American global economic
aims. Such protection proved expensive, however.
By 1995 the costs associated with the cold
war had exceeded $5 trillion. The Great Plains
emerged from its cold war experience with
deep ties to the federal defense budget, and
with fallout shelters now used for storing
canned goods and for refuge from tornadoes.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">ARCHITECTURE</hi>: <ref n="egp.arc.009">Cold War Architecture</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">IMAGES AND ICONS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ii.042">Missile Silos</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Scott D. Hughes<lb/>
Albuquerque, New Mexico</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>May, Elaine Tyler. <title level="m">Homeward Bound: American Families in
the Cold War</title>. New York: Basic Books, 1988.</bibl> <bibl>Oakes, Guy.
<title level="m">The Imaginary War: Civil Defense and American Cold War
Culture</title>. New York: Oxford University Press, 1994.</bibl> <bibl>Pessen,
Edward. <title level="m">Losing Our Souls: The American Experience in the
Cold War</title>. Chicago: Ivan R. Dee, 1993.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>