<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.war.039">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Sand Creek Massacre</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Henrietta Mann</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.war.039</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Mann, Henrietta">Henrietta Mann</author>. <title level="a">"Sand Creek Massacre."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">835</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-28</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">SAND CREEK MASSACRE</head>
<figure n="egp.war.039" rend="granted">
<figDesc>"Depiction of the Sand Creek Massacre by Cheyenne eyewitness and artist Howling Wolf (c. 1875)"</figDesc>
</figure> 

<p>Southern Cheyennes and Arapahos will forever
remember the Sand Creek Massacre,
which occurred on November 29, 1864, when
Col. John M. Chivington and his men of the
Colorado Third Volunteer Regiment attacked
their camp. Cheyennes called this ordained
Methodist minister a "holy-speaking white
man," yet his statement "Damn any man who
is in sympathy with an Indian" expressed his
antipathy toward them.</p>

<p>Two opposing forces caused the massacre.
On one hand were the men of the volunteer
Third Colorado Cavalry, known as the "Bloodless
Third" because their 100-day enlistment
had nearly expired without action against Native
Americans and led by Colonel Chivington.
On the other were the Cheyenne Dog Soldiers,
who were opposed to the peaceful goals of
Black Kettle and who had been making raids
on white settlements&#8211;raids that were traced to
some warriors of Black Kettle's band. These
raids, and blatant land greed thwarted by the
failure to acquire mineral-rich Cheyenne and
Arapaho lands in treaty conferences in 1851 and
1861, led Gov. John Evans to order Chivington's
command to attack.</p>

<p>Black Kettle's mostly peaceful band reported
to Fort Lyon as "friendlies" and were told by
the sympathetic commanding officer, Maj. Edward
Wynkoop, that they should camp near
Fort Lyon under military protection. Vister,
a Cheyenne woman, described their sense of
safety as they settled in along Sand Creek on
the night before the attack. At dawn they were
surprised by the attack, in which Chivington
ordered his men to take no prisoners. Vister
recalled that a male relative brought her a
pony, striking it on its flanks to flee. Instead,
she turned to find her younger brother, whom
she pulled up behind her as bullets whizzed
around them. One bullet struck her in the leg
as they raced away from the besieged camp that
flew a U.S. flag and a white flag on a lodgepole.</p>

<p>Vister's wound healed, but the trauma ran
deep in her spirit. Cheyennes and Arapahos
carry the memory of this massacre. In his testimony
before a congressional committee, interpreter
John Smith described the atrocities: "All
manner of depredations were inflicted on their
persons; they were scalped, their brains knocked
out; the men used their knives, ripped open
women, clubbed little children, knocked them
in the head with their guns, beat their brains
out, mutilated their bodies in every sense of the
word."</p>

<p>Upon their return to Denver, Chivington
and his men displayed scalps and other body
parts from their victims to a cheering crowd in
the Denver opera house. Reaction in the East
could not have been more opposite&#8211;shock
and outrage greeted the news, especially when
details of the large number of women and children
killed, as well as the way in which they
died, became public knowledge. The military
held an investigation and Congress held two,
which transcended their original purpose and
became investigations of all U.S. Indian policy.
Congress condemned Chivington and his
men, but as their enlistments had run out, they
were no longer under military jurisdiction.</p>

<p>In response to the massacre, some Cheyennes
and their allies the Arapahos and Lakota
Sioux initiated raids all over the Northern
Plains, particularly along the Platte River. It
was the start of roughly ten years of war in the
Northern Plains.</p>

<p>On October 14, 1865, U.S. government commissioners
negotiated the Treaty of the Little
Arkansas River, which read in part, "The
United States being desirous to express its
condemnation of, and, as far as may be, repudiate
the gross and wanton outrages perpetrated
against certain bands of Cheyenne and
Arrapahoe Indians, on the twenty-ninth day
of November, <hi rend="smallcaps">A.D.</hi> 1864, at Sand Creek, in Colorado
Territory, while the said Indians were at
peace with the United States, and under its
flag, whose protection they had by lawful authority
been promised and induced to seek,
and the Government being desirous to make
some suitable reparation for the injuries then
done, will grant 320 acres of land by patent,"
as well as individual payments for property
lost to survivors. This promise has not yet
been kept.</p>

<p>In 1996 the General Conference of the
United Methodist Church adopted a resolution
apologizing "for the atrocities committed
at Sand Creek, Colorado, by one of their own
clergy members." They also offered to "extend
to all Cheyennes and Arapahos a hand of reconciliation,
and ask forgiveness for the death
of over 200 mostly women and children."</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">NATIVE AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.na.015">Black Kettle</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Henrietta Mann<lb/>
Montana State University-Bozeman</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Hoig, Stan. <title level="m">The Sand Creek Massacre</title>. Norman: University
of Oklahoma Press, 1961.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>