<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ha.029">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Missouri Company</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>W. Raymond Wood</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ha.029</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Wood, W. Raymond">W. Raymond Wood</author>. <title level="a">"Missouri Company."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">362-363</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-02</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">MISSOURI COMPANY</head>

<p>The Spanish had a tenuous grasp on the upper
Louisiana Territory in the waning years of the
eighteenth century. The Missouri Company
was founded in an effort to exploit its riches.
France had ceded Louisiana to Spain in the
secret Treaty of Fountainbleau in 1762, although
residents of Louisiana did not learn of
the transaction until late in 1764, and French
control of upper Louisiana was not formally
surrendered to Spain until 1770. France regained
control in 1800 and sold Louisiana to
the United States three years later. During the
latter years of the eighteenth century, Spanish
officials in St. Louis tried to halt British trade
incursions in the area. The Missouri River was
the key to Spanish domains west of the Mississippi
River, though they were slow to exploit
the trade there. Spaniards had not ventured
much farther west than the French had
before them. But they were competing with
British traders from the Mississippi River who
were reaching the Omahas and other tribes
along the lower Missouri.</p>

<p>On October 15, 1793, François Luis Hector
Carondelet, Louisiana's governor-general, and
Jacques Clamorgan oversaw the founding of
the Company of Discoveries of the Upper
Missouri. Although it was later commonly
called simply the Missouri Company, it was
known under ten variant names. This company
of St. Louis merchants was intent on exploiting
the fur resources of the upper Missouri
River and removing the British threat to
Spanish domains. Clamorgan, director of the
company, planned to build a series of forts on
the Missouri and hoped eventually to extend
the company's interests west to the Pacific
Ocean.</p>

<p>The new company made its first explorations
of the river in the fall of 1794, when Jean
Baptiste Truteau ascended as far as presentday
central South Dakota. He did not reach
the Mandans, but he did build a post on the
Missouri, Ponca House, not far from the
mouth of the Niobrara. Results were disappointing.
In April 1795 the company sent a
second and larger expedition upriver under
the leadership of a man named Lecuyer. This
expedition was a fiasco due to Lecuyer's poor
leadership and the hostility of the Poncas.</p>

<p>In July 1795 company o.cials in St. Louis
heard news that threatened to further usurp
trade in their domain, news of a direct threat
to Spanish control of the upper Missouri
River. Two traders from the Mandans had deserted
and made their way downriver, where
they told the Spanish commandant of upper
Louisiana, Zenon Trudeau, about direct trade
between Canadian traders and the Mandans,
and that the British had built a fort at the
villages of the Mandans.</p>

<p>The company concluded preparations for a
third expedition, a far larger one, nearly the
size of the later Lewis and Clark expedition.
The party was under the direction of the
Scotsman James Mackay, a former trader in
Canada, and John Thomas Evans, a Welshman
who had come to the United States seeking
the legendary Welsh Indians. Their four
vessels and thirty men left St. Louis in August
or September 1795. They built a post for the
Otoe Indian trade near the mouth of the
Platte River, then established Fort Charles not
far from present-day Sioux City. In 1796 Evans
made his way to the Mandans and expelled the
Canadian traders from their trading post, but
he decided not to continue on to the West
Coast as Mackay had ordered him, and he returned
to St. Louis. Mackay had already done
so, and the third expedition ended&#8211;again, a
failure. Any significant Spanish presence on
the Missouri River promptly evaporated, and
the Canadians resumed their trade with the
Mandans. The expedition's greatest contribution
to history was the information it provided
for Lewis and Clark seven years later.</p>

<p>The Missouri Company did not long survive
these setbacks. Clamorgan was blamed
for its losses, but he enlisted the aid of a powerful
Canadian trader, Andrew Todd, and expanded
operations to the upper Mississippi
River. With Todd, he formed a new company
&#8211;Clamorgan, Loisel and Company&#8211;that
competed with the Missouri Company, with
which he was still associated. When Todd died
in 1796 the financially tottering firm was temporarily
rejuvenated by St. Louis leaders such
as Auguste Chouteau, but under Clamorgan's
erratic hand the firm slowly expired and was
no longer in operation by the time of the
Louisiana Purchase.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">INDUSTRY</hi>: <ref n="egp.ind.022">Fur Trade</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>W. Raymond Wood<lb/>
University of Missouri-Columbia</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Nasatir, Abraham P. <title level="m">Before Lewis and Clark: Documents Illustrating the History of the Missouri, 1785–1804</title>. St.
Louis: St. Louis Historical Documents Foundation, 1952.</bibl>
<bibl>Nasatir, Abraham P. "Jacques Clamorgan." In <title level="m">The Mountain Men and the Fur Trade of the Far West</title>, edited by Le
Roy R. Hafen, 2: 81–94. Glendale <hi rend="smallcaps">CA</hi>: Arthur H. Clark,
1965.</bibl> <bibl>Wood, W. Raymond. "Fort Charles, or 'Mr. Mackey's
Trading House.'" <title level="j">Nebraska History</title> 76 (1995): 2–7.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>