<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.arc.039">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Ranch Architecture</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Timothy H. Evans</author>
<author>Eileen F. Starr</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.arc.039</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Evans, Timothy H.">Timothy H. Evans</author> and <author n="Starr, Eileen F.">Eileen F. Starr</author>. <title level="a">"Ranch Architecture."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">91-92</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-13</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">RANCH ARCHITECTURE</head>

<p>Great Plains ranches can best be viewed as a
built environment consisting of hay fields,
pastures, ditches, corrals, fences, dugouts,
wells, roads, and a variety of buildings. The
ranch landscape is, in turn, an integral part of
a broader ranch culture that includes occupational
skills such as branding and fencing,
traditional crafts such as saddle making and
cooking, folk art forms such as barn dances
and yard art, esoteric folk speech, and many
other elements.</p>

<p>Plains ranch culture has its origins in Mexican
haciendas, which were well established in
southern Texas by the 1700s. Haciendas were
large land grants with complexes of buildings
that were essentially villages, including a large
house and many outbuildings, cisterns, wells,
ditches, fences, and corrals. Often the haciendas
also included a church.</p>

<p>American ranchers in Texas continued to
organize their ranches this way, since the hacienda
was well adapted to the Great Plains
environment and to ranching. As ranches
spread north onto the Central and Northern
Plains in the late nineteenth century, migrants
from the East, South, Midwest, and Europe
brought traditional forms and technologies
that influenced the architecture.</p>

<p>Typically, the earliest ranchers relied on
readily available construction materials such
as wood, stone, mud, and sod. Ranchers also
built with scrap material: unused buildings
were torn down for their materials or moved
to a neighboring ranch, a tradition that persists
today. With the arrival of railroads in the
1860s, the choice of construction materials
and of plans for ranch buildings expanded
dramatically. Mass-produced products such
as windows, doors, molding, and construction
materials changed the character of ranch
architecture. Land-grant universities produced
numerous publications through their
experiment stations and extension offices, as
did agricultural journals. By the twentieth
century, information on scientific farming
and ranching practices from both academic
and popular sources ordered designs for barns,
poultry houses, corrals, and other buildings.
The Midwest Plan Service, a consortium of
universities that shared agricultural information,
including building plans, began in the
1920s. It continues to order plans of pole barns
and many other structures today.</p>

<p>The architecture and arrangement of
ranches are, above all, utilitarian. Buildings
tend to be clustered parallel and perpendicular
to each other, in a linear or rectilinear plan.
Most open toward the entrance of the cluster;
some open toward its center. Barns and stables,
with their attached systems of corrals and
outbuildings, are most often located in front
of the living area, so that a visitor passes them
on the way to the house. The living area, including
house and bunkhouse, is set farther
back and often surrounded by trees and gardens.
Ranch buildings tend to be near streams
or rivers or at least a well, and irrigated hay
fields are adjacent to the buildings. Unirrigated
pasturelands are farther out, with line
cabins (distant shelters for ranch hands) if the
ranch is big enough to need them.</p>

<p>Within ranch complexes, the number and
type of buildings vary according to the function
of the ranch (sheep, horse, cattle, cowcalf,
or yearling), the size of the ranch, the
date of construction, the ethnic origin of the
builder, and the location. Generally, the number
of buildings has decreased from the nineteenth
century on, as rural electrification and
the availability of consumer goods have reduced
the necessity for specialized structures
such as icehouses, root cellars, and blacksmith
shops.</p>

<p>Like other ranch buildings, houses were
functional. Often, a homesteader's cabin was a
single room or dugout made from available
materials such as sod, dimension lumber, or
railroad ties. Before widespread industrialization,
traditional forms passed down through
generations dictated the overall plan of ranch
houses. They were not always simple, however;
in southeastern Wyoming, for example,
wealthy British remittance men built elaborate,
stylish mansions. At successful ranches,
fashionable houses were constructed from designs
found in pattern books, with manufactured
decorations. Only occasionally were architects
retained to design individual houses
or barns.</p>

<p>Barns, stables, loafing sheds (which afford
protection for animals), and the networks of
fences and corrals to which they are connected
are the working heart of most ranches. The
appearance and design of a barn depend upon
the barn's function and construction materials,
the ethnicity of the builder, and the latest
trends in the scientific agricultural community.
Most ranch barns are used to keep horses
and store hay, tack, and other equipment, including
tractors. Common barn types include
three-bay barns and transverse-crib barns,
which range in length from three cribs to as
many as twenty. As with houses, earlier barns
tended to follow folk modes, while later barns
were often built with manufactured components and influenced by academic and government
publications. Technological changes
over time such as the addition of silos or
mechanized hay carriers and forks affected
the design. Large barns may also serve as social
centers, where ranch families gather for
dances.</p>

<p>Ranches may have many other outbuildings,
including sheds of various kinds, openfaced
stables, dugouts used for storage, chicken
coops, springhouses, storehouses, and garages.
Ranches also have a variety of fences and corrals,
loading docks, gates, ditches for irrigation
of hay fields, hay stackers, windmills, water
tanks, and cisterns. Some structures such as
dance halls, corrals for spring brandings and
auctions, rodeo grounds, and dipping vats reflect
the communal activities that take place at
ranches.</p>

<p>Like any business, ranching has changed
with the times. Many modern ranches have
prefabricated trailers, modular houses, or
Quonset huts. Older buildings may be abandoned,
moved, put to other uses, or torn
down to save on property taxes. Although
most ranches still have horses, motorized vehicles
have reduced their numbers and made
large horse barns unnecessary. Many traditions
persist, however, including overall organization.
Computers and other new technology,
changes in public land policies, the
increased importance of agribusiness, and
other factors will continue to change the face
of Plains ranching.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">AGRICULTURE</hi>: <ref n="egp.ag.019">Cattle Ranching</ref>; 
<ref n="egp.ag.054">Ranches</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Timothy H. Evans<lb/>
Western Kentucky University<lb/>
Eileen F. Starr<lb/>
National Park Service</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Graham, Joe S. <title level="m">Hecho en Tejas: Texas-Mexican Folk Art and Crafts</title>. Denton: University of North Texas Press, 1991.</bibl>
<bibl>Noble, Allen G. <title level="m">Wood, Brick and Stone: The North American Settlement Landscape</title>. Amherst: University of Massachusetts
Press, 1984.</bibl> <bibl>Starrs, Paul F. <title level="m">Let the Cowboy Ride: Cattle Ranching in the American West</title>. Baltimore <hi rend="smallcaps">MD</hi>:
Johns Hopkins University Press, 1998.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>