<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.fol.037 SYSTEM "egp.fol.037.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fol.037">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Quilting</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Patricia C. Crews</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2009</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fol.037</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2009</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2009 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Crews, Patricia C.">Patricia C. Crews</author>. <title level="a">"Quilts."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">311-312</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-17</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">QUILTING</head>

<figure n="egp.fol.037" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Star of Bethlehem quilt, made by Maria L. Gear Mook (1833-1914), Johnson County, Nebraska</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Patchwork quilts came to the Great Plains
with the first European settlers who carried
them in wagons and on pack mules. During
the westward migration, quilts served not only
as utilitarian bedding&#8211;both as pallets and
covers&#8211;but as shelter when draped as overnight,
tentlike structures and sometimes as
doors and room dividers in the rude homes
that were erected hastily in the early months
of settlement.</p>

<p>Women traveling across the Great Plains
during the mid–nineteenth century on the
Oregon Trail left many records of quilts in
their diaries, letters, and memoirs. Later in the
century, when Kansas, Nebraska, and Oklahoma
became destinations rather than mile
markers on the journey to Oregon or California,
women again recorded details of the
quilts they brought with them to their new
homes. Among surviving writings, however,
there is no mention of actual quilt making
during the westward migration. There are
some references to mending, sewing, and
knitting on the road, but not to quilt making.
Most healthy emigrants preferred to walk
rather than ride in wagons. Moreover, the
bumpy ride inside covered wagons made it
virtually impossible to sew the precise seams
required for making quilt blocks. On the other
hand, women resumed quilt-making activities
quickly after reaching their destinations, some
almost as soon as they had a roof over their
head. For example, according to family tradition,
Clarissa Palmer, a homesteader in northwestern
Nebraska, fashioned a silk crazy quilt
from scraps her family sent to her during the
first year she "sat" her claim.</p>

<p>Quilts and quilt makers in the Great Plains
are notable for their conservative character
and for their tendency to reliably reflect national
trends in quilt making. This is not surprising
because, by the time women in the
Great Plains began making quilts in large
numbers during the last quarter of the nineteenth
century, an increasing number of national
magazines had begun to standardize
quilt-making styles and patterns. Women's
magazines such as <title level="j">Godey's Ladies Book</title>, <title level="j">Delineator</title>,
<title level="j">Ladies' Home Journal</title>, <title level="j">Woman's Home Companion</title>, and <title level="j">McCall's</title> featured quilt patterns,
articles about quilt making, and nostalgic
images of old quilts. By the 1920s, newspapers&#8211;
most notably the <title level="j">Kansas City Star</title> but
also the <title level="j">Omaha World-Herald</title> and Dallas's
<title level="j">Semi-Weekly Farm News</title>&#8211;presented traditional
and original quilt patterns on a regular
basis and offered patterns that could be ordered
from the paper's home office. The availability
of patterns from newspapers had an
enormous standardizing influence on quilt
patterns during the first half of the twentieth
century.</p>

<p>The agricultural fair, an established American
tradition by the time Kansas, Nebraska,
Oklahoma, and the Dakotas were settled,
also helped nationalize and standardize aesthetics.
Fairs and expositions were eagerly
awaited annual events in all settled areas and
provided friendly competition, recognition,
and an opportunity to display one's needlework
skills. Prizewinning quilts, no doubt, inspired
imitation.</p>

<p>Quilt making remained a popular pastime
in the United States throughout the nineteenth
century. In the early 1900s, while much
of the country turned to mass-produced
woven blankets, the largely rural population
of the Great Plains continued to use handmade
quilts for bedding. Consequently, quilt
making remained a vital part of everyday life
in the Plains until the 1940s. Many presentday
quilters from the Dakotas to Texas recall
learning to sew by piecing blocks for a patchwork
quilt. For generations, girls were taught
to sew and to quilt by their mothers and
grandmothers and were expected to do their
share in making quilts and clothing for the
family. Young women made quilts in anticipation
of the day when they would have homes
of their own. Many quilters born during the
early 1900s readily recall growing up with a
quilt in progress in a quilting frame in their
homes. Often the frames were suspended by
ropes from the ceiling and were raised and
lowered as necessary.</p>

<p>Because quilting had never gone out of style
and quilts had never gone out of use in the
largely agricultural Great Plains, the surge of
print media attention given to quilts in the
first quarter of the twentieth century only reinforced
the unflagging interest in quilt making
held by rural quilters of the region.</p>

<p>Most surviving nineteenth-century quilts
from the Great Plains are star patterns. Star
patterns (single and multiple) remained the
most popular design among American quilters
of European descent until the 1930s. The
names of star patterns sometimes varied from
state to state: for example, the Bethlehem Star
became the Lone Star in Texas, and a fourpointed
star pattern became known as Rocky
Road to Kansas.</p>

<p>Northern Plains Indian women favored
dazzling, large, single-star patterns for their
quilts. Quilting, introduced by the wives of
missionaries in the late 1800s, sparked a new
cultural practice among Plains Indian women
of the Dakotas and Montana. Quilts eventually
replaced buffalo robes in the wrapping
of the dead. Star quilts were, and are, given in
celebration at births and to honor loved ones
at graduations. And quilts&#8211;mainly star designs&#8211;
always serve as a focal point in the Native
Americans' customary "giveaway."</p>

<p>Other quilt patterns and styles enjoyed periods
of popularity in the Plains. For example,
log cabin quilts and crazy quilts were fad styles
that swept the region and the nation between
1870 and 1900. Plains women more often made
their crazy quilts of practical wool or cotton
fabrics, instead of the silks favored by eastern
women. During the 1920s and 1930s a
hexagon-based mosaic pattern called Grandmother's
Flower Garden, as well as the Double
Wedding Ring, Dresden Plate, and Nine Patch
patterns rose in popularity. They remained
among the most prevalent patterns for quilters
of European descent until the 1960s. A resurgence
of interest in quilting began in the
1970s and continues in the twenty-first century
with quilters from Texas, Kansas, and Nebraska
at the forefront of the revival.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">GENDER</hi>: <ref n="egp.gen.029">Quilting Circles</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Patricia C. Crews<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Brackman, Barbara, Jennie A. Chinn, Gayle R. Davis, Terry
Thompson, Sara Reimer Farley, and Nancy Hornback.
<title level="m">Kansas Quilts and Quilters</title>. Lawrence: University Press of
Kansas, 1993.</bibl> <bibl>Crews, Patricia Cox, and Ronald Naugle,
eds. <title level="m">Nebraska Quilts and Quilt Makers</title>. Lincoln: University
of Nebraska Press, 1991.</bibl> <bibl>Yabsley, Suzanne. <title level="m">Texas Quilts, Texas Women</title>. College Station: Texas <hi rend="smallcaps">A&amp;M</hi> University
Press, 1984.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>