<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.mus.049 SYSTEM "egp.mus.049.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->


<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.mus.049">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Welk, Lawrence (1903-1992)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Robert W. Groves</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.mus.049</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Groves, Robert W.">Robert W. Groves</author>. <title level="a">"Welk, Lawrence (1903-1992)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">549-550</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-03</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">WELK, LAWRENCE (1903-1992)</head>

<figure n="egp.mus.049">
<figDesc>Lawrence Welk</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>The sixth of eight children, Lawrence Welk
was born on a farm near Strasburg in southcentral
North Dakota on March 11, 1903, to
Ludwig and Christina Schwann Welk, German
Russian immigrants from the Odessa region
of the Ukraine. Throughout his career,
Welk claimed that his lifelong frugality, work
ethic, and strong Catholic Church ties were
products of his impoverished and strictly disciplined
upbringing. A largely self-taught musician,
Welk quit school during the fourth
grade, purchased his first piano accordion at
age seventeen, and left the farm on his twentyfirst
birthday to begin a career as a regional
musician and dance band leader.</p>

<p>In 1926 he began his first significant fulltime
job in South Dakota as an accordionist
and actor with the Peerless Entertainers, a
small traveling show led by George T. Kelly,
the individual Welk credited with teaching
him the basics of advertising, showmanship,
and audience sensitivity. From 1927 to 1937
Welk traveled the Plains states with his own
six- to ten-piece territory band under various
names (Welk's Novelty Orchestra, the Hotsy-Totsy Boys, and the Honolulu Fruit Gum Orchestra),
and from 1927 to 1934 they played
live radio shows over <hi rend="smallcaps">WNAX</hi> in Yankton, South
Dakota. During this period his most notable
and regular bookings were in the seven Tom
Archer Ballrooms located in Iowa, Nebraska,
South Dakota, and Missouri. In 1931 he married
Fern Renner in Yankton. They had three
children: Shirley (b. 1932), Donna (b. 1937),
and Lawrence Jr. (b. 1940).</p>

<p>In late 1937 Welk got his first national exposure
under management of the Fredericks
Brothers with broadcast performances at the
William Penn Hotel in Pittsburgh. It was during
this booking in early 1938 that he began
distinguishing his musical style as "champagne
music," and soon thereafter he had his
own waltz-ballad, "You're My Home Sweet
Home," rearranged as "Bubbles in the Wine,"
his signature theme for the remainder of his
career. While at the William Penn he also
hired the first of seven "champagne ladies"
(Lois Best, 1938–40; Jayne Walton, 1940–45;
Joan Mowery, 1945–47; Helen Ramsey, 1947–
49; Roberta Linn, 1949–53; Alice Lon, 1953–59;
and Norma Zimmer, 1960–82). From 1940 to
1950 Welk's band was based in Chicago, where
he most often played the Trianon Ballroom.</p>

<p>Welk moved his band in 1951 to the Aragon
Ballroom in Santa Monica, California, and
was featured from 1952 to 1955 on weekly
broadcasts from the ballroom over <hi rend="smallcaps">KTLA</hi> television.
In 1955 Welk began weekly national
broadcasts over <hi rend="smallcaps">ABC</hi>. After <hi rend="smallcaps">ABC</hi> dropped the
show in 1971, it continued in syndication until
Welk's retirement in 1982. During the early
years of this period Welk hired his most famous band member, accordionist Myron Floren
(1950); his personal manager, Sam Lutz
(1952); and his musical director, George Cates
(1956). All three remained with him until his
retirement. In 1956 he hired the four Lennon
Sisters as featured singers, the first of a long
line of young singers and dancers who would
become part of his "musical family" over the
next twenty-one years. In order to keep his
now famous musical family intact (he paid
only union scale salaries, a policy that never
changed throughout his career), he initiated a
unique profit-sharing plan in 1956 based in
part on how long a member of the show remained
with the organization.</p>

<p>After building his audience through years
of live appearances, he maintained their loyalty
as television viewers with the stylistic consistency
of his programming, the personalized
presentation of his musical family, his famous
accent and misstatements, and his simple,
North Dakota farm boy demeanor. Welk retired
at the end of the 1982 season, and the
decision was made not to continue the show
without him. Even though his show never received
a broadcast award, it remains the most
watched and longest running program of its
kind in television history. Reruns continue
over public television stations. In 1994 Lawrence
Jr. opened the Welk Theater and Resort
in Branson, Missouri, where the shows are
headlined by members of the original television
cast. The Lawrence Welk Archive,
which contains his scrapbooks, band arrangements,
and memorabilia, is located at North
Dakota State University in Fargo. Welk died
on May 12, 1992, in Santa Monica, California.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Robert W. Groves<lb/>
North Dakota State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Schwienher, William. <title level="m">Lawrence Welk: An American Institution</title>.
Chicago: Nelson-Hall, 1980.</bibl> <bibl>Welk, Lawrence.
<title level="m">Wunnerful, Wunnerful: The Autobiography of Lawrence Welk</title>, edited by Bernice McGeehan. Englewood Cliffs <hi rend="smallcaps">NJ</hi>:
Prentice-Hall, 1971.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>