<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.ind.033 SYSTEM "egp.ind.033.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ind.033">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Justin, H. J., and Sons</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Jane Pattie</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ind.033</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Pattie, Jane">Jane Pattie</author>. <title level="a">"Justin, H. J., and Sons."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">424</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-02</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">JUSTIN, H. J., AND SONS</head>

<figure n="egp.ind.033" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Joe and Annie Justin devised the first self-measuring kits for mail-order cowboy boots, 1907.</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>More than a century ago, "Big Daddy" Joe
Justin never dreamed his boots would become
the "Standard of the West." He just knew he
did not want to be a cigar maker like his father.
Spanish Fort, Texas, south of Red River
Crossing on the Chisholm Trail, was a bustling
town in 1879 when twenty-year-old H. J. "Joe"
Justin arrived from Lafayette, Indiana, with
five dollars in his pocket. He began repairing
boots. With a thirty-five-dollar grubstake, he
soon opened a small shop and made boots for
the trail hands. Justin married Annie Allen of
Hood County, Texas, in 1886, and the couple's
first son, John, was born in Spanish Fort.</p>

<p>When an east–west railroad was built eighteen
miles south, Spanish Fort's businessmen
moved to the tracks in 1889 and established
Nocona. In 1894 Joe and Annie devised a self-measuring
kit for ordering boots by mail, and
cowboys across the West soon wore Justin
boots. The Justin family grew to three boys
and four girls. Annie and the children all
worked in the boot shop alongside Joe.</p>

<p>The two oldest boys, John and Earl, became
partners in 1908 with their father in H. J. Justin
and Sons. John and Earl supervised ten
to twelve men in the shop, and Joe traveled
around the country with boot samples. In 1911
the company did $180,000 in boot business in
twenty-six states, Canada, Mexico, and Cuba.</p>

<p>Joe Justin's health began to fail in 1916,
and he turned the company over to his sons,
John, Earl, and Avis. When Joe Justin died in
1918, his boots were already a legend of the
American West. In 1925 Justin's sons moved
their growing company to larger quarters in
Fort Worth, where better shipping facilities
and a ready workforce were available. Their
sister, Enid Justin, chose to remain in the old
shop and continue production as Nocona
Boot Company.</p>

<p>Justin boots continued to grow in popularity,
with new styles, stitching, leathers,
and lightweight boots&#8211;the "Western Gypsy"
line&#8211;designed especially for women. In 1950
John Justin Jr., Joe's grandson, was named vice
president and general manager. He soon took
full control of the company. By 1952 company
sales topped $1 million for the first time. His
innovative ideas on designs, production, and
marketing led to H. J. Justin and Sons' continued
growth. By 1954 the company was shipping
100,000 pairs of boots a week.</p>

<p>John Justin Sr. worked at the plant until
his death in 1959. John Jr. bought the remaining
family-owned shares in the company in
1967 and became sole owner. Two years later,
Justin became chief executive officer of Justin
Industries, Inc., a diversified holding company,
with the boot company as one of its four
subsidiaries.</p>

<p>Justin Boot Company celebrated its 100th
anniversary in 1981, the same year that Justin
Industries bought Nocona Boot Company
from eighty-year-old Enid Justin. In 1990 Justin
Industries added another major competitor
to its fold&#8211;Tony Lama Boot Company of
El Paso, Texas.</p>

<p>John S. Justin Jr. retired as <hi rend="smallcaps">CEO</hi> of Justin
Industries in 1999. For the first time in 120
years, the reins of management of the boot
company passed to the hands of someone
other than a member of Joe Justin's family.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Jane Pattie<lb/>
Aledo, Texas</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>H. J. Justin and Sons, Archives, Justin Industries, Inc., Fort
Worth <hi rend="smallcaps">TX</hi>.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>