<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ct.041">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Regina, Saskatchewan</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Randy William Widdis</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ct.041</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Widdis, Randy William">Randy William Widdis</author>. <title level="a">"Regina, Saskatchewan."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">179</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-28</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">REGINA, SASKATCHEWAN</head>

<p>Regina, the capital of Saskatchewan, is a prime
example of a community overcoming the disadvantages
of geography through both good
fortune and great effort. The site possessed
few natural advantages, situated as it was on a
poorly drained treeless plain, with a shallow
creek littered with the bones of buffalo slaughtered
by Metis and Indians its only source of
water. Yet the decision of the Canadian Pacific
Railway to abandon its originally surveyed
route along the North Saskatchewan River in
favor of one straight west from Winnipeg
would set into motion a chain of events leading
to the selection of this most unlikely location
as the capital of Canada's Northwest Territories.
Battleford, the original capital of the
territories, was deemed by the Dominion government
and the railway to be too far from the
main line. They wanted the capital to be at a
central position in order to have adequate
communications with the East. Edgar Dewdney,
the lieutenant governor of the territories,
lobbied for the location of this new capital on
a tract of land owned by him and a number of
associates, but eventually the railway chose a
location for a station and town site two miles
to the east. Dewdney was mollified to some
extent when the government decided to build
the North-West Mounted Police barracks and
the lieutenant governor's residence on his
property. The railway surveyed the site, laying
out some 13,000 lots during the fall and winter
of 1882.83, and the new capital was named
after Queen Victoria.</p>

<p>Regina's fortunes were closely tied to agricultural
development, but settlement lagged
for almost twenty years because of poor crops,
a limited local market, lack of local capital,
and continuing settlement of the American
West. After 1900 better harvests and increasing
prices for wheat, cheaper transportation rates,
and a massive immigration to the Canadian
West solidified its status as a key urban center
in the region. In 1902 the Canadian Pacific
Railway granted Regina local distributing
freight rates and special rates on farm machinery,
which reduced the cost of shipping to
the city, making it more competitive with
Winnipeg, the regional metropolis. The city
was also designated a customs port of entry
that year, which prompted a number of agricultural
machinery businesses, including
Massey Harris and International Harvester, to
establish distributing operations. Regina's security
as a government center was ensured
when it was made the capital of the new Province
of Saskatchewan in 1905. New lines built
by the Canadian Northern and the Grand
Trunk Railways to different regional centers
expanded the city's hinterland. As a result of
these developments, the population of Regina
had increased from 2,249 in 1901 to more than
30,000 a decade later.</p>

<p>Yet like its neighbors, Regina would struggle
in its attempts to attract industry because
of its distance from major markets, the prohibitive
costs of power, and the stiff competition
offered by other cities in the limited
provincial market. As a result, Regina's development
was locked into the boom-andbust
nature of the wheat monoculture. The
city did benefit from its position as political
capital, a factor that played a major role in
the location decisions of the Saskatchewan
Wheat Pool and various banks and credit
unions. Yet the decline of wheat prices, triggered
by global depression, combined with
drought and grasshopper and rust infestations
devastated the city during the 1930s. The Depression
witnessed the emergence of a loose
alliance of farm and labor movements in the
province, and in 1933 the Cooperative Commonwealth
Federation was formed and held
its first national convention in Regina, drafting
the socialist political charter that became
known as the Regina Manifesto.</p>

<p>The fortunes of the city have continued to
be tied to agriculture, although less so than
before because of the development of industries
linked to potash and oil discoveries
throughout the province and a growing internal
market. While potash and mineral development
have combined with the high-tech
sector to propel Saskatoon to a position of
primacy, Regina has benefited more directly
from the province's oil boom. Petroleum from
Alberta's oil fields transported to eastern Canada
via the Interprovincial Pipeline was first
refined in Regina in 1950. Oil from western
Saskatchewan was first refined in Regina in
1954, but because of its high sulphur content
much of the light and medium crude found in
the province is shipped elsewhere. The more
viscous and heavy oil found in western Canada
is now refined in the upgrading facility
built in Regina in the 1980s. The oil boom's
most important legacy was the Interprovincial
Steel and Pipe Construction Company, built
in Regina in the late 1950s, the largest single
manufacturing enterprise in Saskatchewan
and the only steel mill in western Canada.</p>

<p>With a present population of just over
195,000, the city has continued to benefit from
its status as provincial capital, securing the
crown corporations and administrative expansion
associated with the growth of the welfare
state. The most visible manifestation of its
association with government is the development
of the 2,300-acre park centered around
Wascana Lake, an artificial creation made possible
by the damming of Wascana Creek,
whose grounds provide a setting for the Legislative
Building and government offices, the
University of Regina, the Saskatchewan Centre
of the Arts, museums, galleries, and a science
center. Administered jointly by the city, the
province, and the university since 1962, the
park provides a wide range of recreational activities
and has won prizes for its design all
over the world.</p>

<p>In addition to its political function, Regina
has continued in its role as a regional service
and distribution location and in this context
has become the western Canadian call center
for large companies such as Sears Canada and
Royal Bank. It has recently become the headquarters
for Crown Life Insurance Company
and AgrEvo Incorporated, one of the world's
largest chemical crop protection companies.
In addition, the university's new research park
has begun to attract some high-tech companies
linked to the computer and petroleum
industries. Yet like other Prairie cities, Regina
still relies heavily on resource-based industries
and thus is affected greatly by changing world
markets.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">INDUSTRY</hi>: <ref n="egp.ind.046">Petroleum, Canada</ref> /
<hi rend="smallcaps">MEDIA</hi>: <ref n="egp.med.028"><title level="j"><hi rend="italic">Leader-Post</hi></title> (Regina)</ref> (Regina) / <hi rend="smallcaps">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</hi>: <ref n="egp.pg.014">Cooperative Commonwealth Federation</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Randy William Widdis<lb/>
University of Regina</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Brennan, J. William. <title level="m">Regina: An Illustrated History</title>. Toronto:
James Lorimer and Company, 1989.</bibl> <bibl>Drake, Earl.
<title level="m">Regina: The Queen City</title>. Toronto: McClelland and Stewart
Ltd., 1955.</bibl> <bibl>Riddell, W. A. <title level="m">Regina: From Pile o' Bones to Queen City of the Plains</title>. Burlington: Windsor Publications
Ltd., 1981.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>