<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fol.014">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Folk Dance</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Enid Cocke</author>
<author>Susan Sanders</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2009</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fol.014</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2009</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2009 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Cocke, Enid">Enid Cocke</author> and <author n="Sanders, Susan">Susan Sanders</author>. <title level="a">"Folk Dance."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">297</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-16</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">FOLK DANCE</head>

<p>Folk dance in the Great Plains has its roots in
many traditions and reflects the history and
culture of its peoples. Native American dances,
with their origins in ritual, ceremonies, and
initiation, were passed on from one generation
to another. European folk dances evolved in
the same way, although they came to serve a
social rather than ritual function. In some
Plains communities, a specific ethnic identity
has continued unbroken to the present. In
Lindsborg, Kansas, for example, descendants
of Swedish settlers still maintain their tradition
of Swedish music, dance, and festivals. Modern
technology and communication bring an everwidening
mix of dance from other lands,
which reflects the universality of folk dance
and the diversity of the American and Canadian
nations. However, some uniquely North
American forms of folk dance developed in the
Great Plains.</p>

<p>The settlers who entered the Great Plains in
the nineteenth century brought the dance
forms that they knew: the quadrille and the
popular couple dances of the time. Farther
east, the quadrille, a dance performed by four
couples in a square formation, had become
increasingly complex. A specific quadrille, the
Standard Lancers, for instance, consisted of
five different sections; thus, people felt the
need of formal instruction under a dancing
master to learn and memorize the sequence of
figures. A second source of what evolved into
square dancing in the Plains was the big circle
dances of the Appalachian region. In these
dances, alternate couples moved out to the
couple on their right, performed a few figures
with them, and then moved on to the next
couple. A third feature of the square dance was
the caller. Since dancing masters and dancing
schools were not available to the pioneers,
dancers relied on one person to call out the
figures. These figures were performed in a
four-couple square rather than a big circle, but
they still had the visiting-couple format, in
which one couple went out and danced various
figures with each of the other couples in succession.
Interspersed with the square dances
were couple dances consisting of simple patterns
danced to the rhythms that had become
popular in nineteenth-century Europe: the
waltz, polka, schottische, and a version of the
mazurka called the Varsouvienne.</p>

<p>In the Southern Great Plains these same
square dances and couple dances were featured,
but there was also a strand of folk dance
coming up from Mexico. Both Spanish colonial
dances and dances of Mexican influence
were popular, many of them done to waltz or
polka music. The "fandango," or Spanish ball,
was a popular assembly where dancing and
socializing took place. However, the opposition
of the churches to dancing was particularly
strong in Texas, Oklahoma, and Kansas,
resulting in the flourishing of "play parties"
instead of dances. Another factor in this region
was the great distances that separated
people, as well as the scarcity of both musicians
and women. On the great cattle ranches
of West Texas, people would come from fifty
miles around if a fiddler were found and a
dance scheduled. The furniture would be
taken out of the largest room in the house, and
the dancing would continue until dawn. Given
the gender ratio, men would either wait their
turn to dance or put on an apron or tie a scarf
around their arm and dance the woman's part.
With regional variations, these same square
dances and couple dances took hold throughout
the Great Plains, including the Canadian
Prairie Provinces. In addition to private
homes, granges and military posts provided
settings for dances and social gatherings.</p>

<p>In the twentieth century these dance forms
continued in pockets throughout the Great
Plains, but a new approach to folk dancing
developed. Researchers, teachers, and recreation
leaders revived the dances of the previous
century and made them popular once
again, but this time as a recreational activity.
Researchers also collected ethnic dances in
Europe and brought them again to the United
States. Over time, square dancing evolved into
a highly organized activity with a long sequence
of lessons required before dancers
could join clubs.</p>

<p>A folk dance that is currently popular in the
Plains states is the contra dance, a "longways"
dance in which couples face each other in long
lines. Contra dancing, which originated in
England and was popular in colonial America,
employs figures used in square dancing but
keeps them to a limited number. It endured in
New England and has now become popular
across the country. A major feature of contra
dancing is the use of live, rather than recorded,
music. In the Canadian provinces,
club square dancing and international folk are
the predominant folk dance activities. All the
current folk dance forms&#8211;contra, square, and
international folk&#8211;are sustained by local associations
as well as regional and national organizations,
some of which produce annual
festivals to further promote their activity.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Enid Cocke<lb/>
Manhattan, Kansas<lb/>
Susan Sanders<lb/>
Lawrence, Kansas</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Casey, Betty. <title level="m">Dance across Texas</title>. Austin: University of
Texas Press, 1985.</bibl> <bibl>Harris, Jane A., Anne M. Pittman, Marlys
S. Waller, and Cathy L. Dark. <title level="m">Dance a While</title>. Boston: Allyn
and Bacon, 2000.</bibl> <bibl>Shaw, Lloyd. <title level="m">Cowboy Dances</title>. Caldwell
id: Caxton Printers, 1939.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>