<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.fil.001.01 SYSTEM "egp.fil.001.01.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fil.001">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Film</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>David J. Wishart</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fil.001</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</author>. <title level="a">"Film."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">255-258</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-09</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">FILM</head>

<figure n="egp.fil.001.01" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Piqua, Kansas, birthplace of Buster Keaton</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>The Great Plains has inspired a long and rich
tradition of cinema and have produced a remarkably
deep pool of actors and filmmakers.
Westerns derive much of their force from the
vastness of the Plains landscape, a suitably
grand setting for the conflict between good
and evil. The pioneer film is based on the immigrants'
struggle with this harsh yet fertile
environment, and the Plains has also been a
classic setting for the small-town movie, claustrophobic
even in those wide-open spaces. Significant
documentaries and realistic dramas
have conveyed the exploitation of the region's
inhabitants by external forces as well as their
efforts to resist those forces. And a galaxy of
stars has risen from Plains cities, towns, and
farms, from Lon Chaney (born in Colorado
Springs in 1883), Roscoe "Fatty" Arbuckle
(Smith Center, Kansas, 1887), and Buster Keaton
(Piqua, Kansas, 1895) to Dennis Hopper
(Dodge City, Kansas, 1936), Demi Moore (Roswell,
New Mexico, 1963), and Brad Pitt (Shawnee,
Oklahoma, 1963).</p>

<p>While it is the American rather than the
Canadian Plains that has produced the stars
(Rod Cameron of Calgary notwithstanding),
it is mainly the Prairies that have developed a
genuine Plains aesthetic in film. Indeed, the
very first Great Plains films depicting life on
the Prairies were made in 1897 by Manitoba
farmer James Freer. Films set in the American
Plains have been overwhelmed by Hollywood
pretensions. Even a revisionist Western like
<title>Dances with Wolves</title> (1990) is a distortion, albeit
a spectacular one, of the history of the
region and of the Native Americans, to whom
the director, Kevin Costner, tries to pay homage.
Filmmaking in the Prairie Provinces has
also been influenced by Hollywood distribution
monopolies, but because of the support
of the National Film Board of Canada (established
in 1939) and of the provincial governments,
the opportunity has been there for
the production of Prairie feature films and
documentaries that are made in the region.
Consequently, it is that part of the Great
Plains that is most likely to see its history and
culture on the big screen without translation
by Hollywood.</p>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Actors and Filmmakers</head>

<p>Perhaps if any region is thoroughly investigated
the result will be the same, but it does
seem that an inordinate number of actors and
directors have come from the Great Plains.
Stars were born the length and breadth of the
region, from Edmonton, Alberta (Michael J.
Fox, 1961) to San Saba, Texas (Tommy Lee
Jones, 1946), and from Denver, Colorado
(Douglas Fairbanks Sr., 1883) to Kansas City,
Missouri (Jean Harlow, 1911). Investigate any
subregion of the Plains, and the depth of film
talent becomes evident. Omaha, Nebraska, for
example, was home to two-time Oscar winner
Marlon Brando (1924), to the debonair and
light-footed Fred Astaire (1899), to the sensitive
and tragic Montgomery Clift (1920), and
to that durable tough guy, Nick Nolte (1941).
In rural Nebraska were born Henry Fonda
(Grand Island, 1905), who played perhaps his
finest role as Tom Joad, the displaced Plains
farmer in <title>The Grapes of Wrath</title> (John Ford,
1940); <title>The Fugitive</title>, David Janssen (Naponee,
1930); <title>Our Man Flint</title>, James Coburn (Laurel,
1928); leading man Robert Taylor (Filley, 1911);
Tony- and Academy Award–winning actress
Sandy Dennis (Hastings, 1937); B-movie stars
Hoot Gibson (Takamah, 1892) and Coleen
Gray (Staplehurst, 1922); torch-song diva
Ruth Etting (David City, 1896); master comedian
and stuntman Harold Lloyd (Burchard,
1888); and movie mogul Darryl Zanuck
(Wahoo, 1902).</p>

<p>Many of these Plains people did not stay
long in the region, but surely the Plains stayed
in them. Buster Keaton, for example, spent his
early years in the tiny railroad town of Piqua
in southeastern Kansas serenaded by piercing
whistles, screeching brakes, and clanging bells.
Even though the Keatons&#8211;small-time performers
in ten-cent shows&#8211;moved to New
York in 1899, when Buster was four, these
memories stayed with him all his life, and
many of his films, including perhaps his greatest,
<title>The General</title> (1926), feature trains. In his
autobiography, <title>My Wonderful World of Slapstick</title>
(1967), Keaton recounts how Pickway
(Piqua) was virtually blown away by a tornado
soon after he was born. Like the trains, Plains
winds stayed with him: how else to account
for the daredevil scene in <title>Steamboat Bill</title>
(1927), when Keaton is tumbled through River
Junction by a howling wind, until finally he is
enveloped by the falling facade of a two-story
building, a small window passing around him
and, literally (for this was not a camera trick),
saving his life.</p>

<p>Other filmmakers from the Great Plains
have dealt more explicitly with their Plains
upbringing. Gordon Parks, the youngest in a
family of sixteen children, was born in 1912
and grew up in the segregated small town of
Fort Scott, Kansas. It was a racist town, and
the family's clapboard house was crowded,
but in his autobiographical novel, <title>The Learning Tree</title> (1963), and in the lyrically beautiful
film of the same name that he produced and
directed in 1969 as Hollywood's first African
American director, the memories of his Plains
upbringing are also affectionate. The place
was a learning tree, his mother had told him,
and trees bear both good and bad fruit.</p>

<p>Parks gratefully left Fort Scott for Minnesota
in 1927, probably passing through
Kansas City, where Robert Altman was then
two years old. Altman grew up in comfortable,
middle-class circumstances and learned
his trade directing industrial films and television
series and commercials in Kansas City in
the early 1950s. Perhaps it was because of the
central location of that city, at the crossroads
between North and South, East and West, that
Altman would go on to become the preeminent
director of films that explore and dissect
American dreams, mythologies, and hypocrisies.
His first film and one of his later feature
films were set in Kansas City. His teenage
hoodlum film, <title>The Delinquents</title> (1956), was
shot in his hometown, and he left for Hollywood
as soon as it was finished. In 1996 Altman
made Kansas City, evoking the city of his
youth with its gangsters, crooked politicians,
and, most of all, its vibrant jazz scene. Using
local musicians, Altman reprised the jazz sessions
he had caught as a teenager in the Kansas
City clubs, making us all wish we had been
there. Another two of his more than thirty
feature films&#8211;<title>Buffalo Bill and the Indians</title>
(1976) and <title>Come Back to the Five and Dime, Jimmy Dean, Jimmy Dean</title> (1982)&#8211;also have
Plains settings.</p>

<p>A filmmaker doesn't have to be from the
Plains, of course, to make a Plains movie. Two
of the most significant Plains films of recent
years, the documentary Incident at Oglala and
the feature film Thunderheart, both released
in 1992 and both set on Pine Ridge Reservation
in South Dakota, were made by Michael
Apted, an Englishman.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Great Plains Films</head>

<p>Innumerable mainstream Hollywood films
have been set in the Great Plains. The grand
finales of <title>North by Northwest</title> (Alfred Hitchcock,
1959) and <title>Close Encounters of the Third Kind</title> (Steven Spielberg, 1977) are played out in
spectacular Plains settings (Mount Rushmore,
South Dakota, and Devil's Tower, Wyoming,
respectively), although these are not otherwise
Plains films. On the other hand, many Plains
films such as <title>Oklahoma!</title> (Fred Zinneman,
1955) and <title>Oklahoma Crude</title> (Stanley Kramer,
1973) were actually filmed elsewhere (the former
in Arizona and the latter in Stockton, California).</p>

<p>The Western is the genre most clearly associated
with the Plains. Many Westerns are actually
"placeless," taking place in what Richard
Slotkin calls "mythic space." Precise locations
are often ambiguous, because the West in such
films is too big for any one place. The "placelessness"
is accentuated by the fact that many
Westerns were filmed on stage sets. Yet many
Westerns, while retaining their mythic qualities,
are clearly set in the Great Plains and
depict events in Plains history, albeit refracted
through a lens. These include cattle-drive films
such as Howard Hawks's <title>Red River</title> (1948),
which is based on the opening of the Chisholm
Trail in the 1860s. In the film, a tough older
man, Thomas Dunson (John Wayne), and a
sensitive young man, Matthew Garth (Montgomery
Clift, in his first movie role), are pitted
against each other over whether to drive the
herd to the old destination at Sedalia, Missouri,
or to the new railheads in Kansas. The
competition heads toward a showdown, but
the gunfight never materializes, because the
honorable Dunson cannot kill his "spiritual"
son. Many other cattle-drive films similarly
combine personal drama and historical epic,
but none as effectively as <title>Red River</title>. <title>The Virginian</title>
(Victor Fleming, 1929; Stuart Gilmore,
1946) is also a Western with a Plains setting
(Medicine Bow, Wyoming) and again the classic
Western theme: the rugged, innocent, and
honorable cowboy confronted with a moral
dilemma.</p>

<p>Homesteader films, another aspect of the
Western genre, are often set in the Plains. One
of the earliest, <title>The Homesteader</title> (1917), was by
an African American, Oscar Micheaux, who
had actually homesteaded in South Dakota in
the first years of the twentieth century. Based
on his own novel of the same name (1917),
Micheaux tells the story of an African American
settler who makes good and is involved in
an interracial love affair. Written, produced,
and directed by Micheaux and filmed in Gregory
County, South Dakota, this was the first
feature film made entirely by African Americans.</p>

<p>The homesteader tradition has continued
into recent decades&#8211;battling the Plains environment
is an enduring theme in literature
(e.g., O. E. R&#246;lvaag's <title>Giants in the Earth</title>, 1927)
and film. The classic film of Prairie Provinces
settlement, <title>Drylanders</title> (Donald Haldone,
1963), is a saga of homesteading in southern
Saskatchewan from the late nineteenth century
to the 1930s. The first film produced
by the National Film Board of Canada, <title>Drylanders</title>
stayed close to historical reality, from
the initial sod house to the dust storms of the
1930s. The poignant film <title>Heartland</title> (Richard
Pearce, 1979) slowly and gracefully traces the
tribulations of a housekeeper and her daughter
who move to frontier Wyoming to work
for a dour rancher (played by Rip Torn) and
end up finding affection. Terrence Malick's
haunting <title>Days of Heaven</title> (1978), the story of a
steelworker and his lover who flee Chicago
after a fight (murder?) to work as itinerant
laborers in the wheat fields of the Texas Panhandle
in the years just before World War I, is
also a homesteader film. After all, this area
was, along with eastern Montana, a twentiethcentury
Plains frontier. The film, shot in Alberta,
captures the unpredictability of the
Plains environment in a sequence of close-ups
that show a wheat seed germinating deep in
the fertile soil and then, months later, a wheat
kernel being devoured by a grasshopper, one
of millions that have descended to strip the
fields to the ground.</p>

<p>There are, of course, numerous films about
the conflicts between European Americans
and Native Americans in the Great Plains.
These movies, like the writing of history itself,
tell as much about the times in which they
were made as they do about the times they
portray. During the course of fifty years in
movies, Plains Native Americans have gone
from "savage" to "noble survivor," while at the
same time Gen. George Armstrong Custer has
gone from conquering hero to arrogant fool.
Significant Plains films in this transition include
<title>Soldier Blue</title> (Ralph Nelson, 1970), which
graphically depicts the atrocities of the 1864
Sand Creek Massacre, and Arthur Penn's audacious
<title>Little Big Man</title> (also 1970), which takes
the 120-year-old Jack Crabb through virtually
every event of the Plains Indian wars. However,
these films are as much about Vietnam
and My Lai as they are about Native Americans.
<title>Dances with Wolves</title>, for all its romanticizing
and revising of Plains Indian life
(Pawnees were hardly the aggressors in their
conflicts with Lakotas), goes farther than most
other Westerns by giving Native American actors
prominent roles and by employing Lakota
in the dialogue, with English subtitles. In
many respects, Costner's film can be seen as a
successor to Elliot Silverstein's <title>A Man Called Horse</title> (1970), which also uses Native American
actors and language as the setting for a European
American's heroics and distorts history
in the process.</p>

<p>The end of the West, leaving its people dislocated,
is another classic theme in Plains Westerns,
and Texas is a favorite setting. The best
example, perhaps, is <title>Hud</title> (Martin Ritt, 1963),
which was adapted from Larry McMurtry's
novel <title>Horseman, Pass By</title> (1961). <title>Hud</title> features
the conflict between an honorable old man
(played by Melvyn Douglas), who has an abiding
pride in the Texas ranch he has built over
the years, and his cynical son (Paul Newman),
who values nothing. The passing of the West
here is associated with the loss of principles
and the severing of the attachment to the land.
<title>Giant</title>, which won an Academy Award for director
George Stevens in 1956, covers some of
this same territory, both actually and figuratively.<title>Set and filmed in West Texas, </title><hi rend="italic">Giant</hi> follows
Bick (Rock Hudson) and Leslie Benedict
(Elizabeth Taylor) through the transition from
big ranching money to big oil money that took
place from the 1920s to the 1940s. A central
figure, Jeff Rink (played rather movingly by
James Dean in his last acting role), represents
the loss of humanity that comes with wealth.
Another theme is the caste system, in which
Mexicans are relegated to a servile role and to
segregated, poverty-stricken living conditions.
Yet on this issue the film ends on an optimistic
note, as Bick finally rejects the racism he has
grown old with. The prejudices, conflicts, and
accommodations between European Americans
and Latinos (and in this case African
Americans too) are also featured in John
Sayles's <title>Lone Star</title> (1996), a penetrating analysis
and gripping account of contemporary life in
fictional Rio County, located at the southern
extremity of the Great Plains, where the Edwards
Plateau meets the Rio Grande.</p>

<p>The end of the West is a central theme in <title>The Last Picture Show</title> (Peter Bogdanovich, 1971),
also the best of another Plains genre, the smalltown
movie. Adapted from another McMurtry
novel, this film, suitably shot in black and
white, is a painful and moving look at a small
Texas town in decline. It tells the coming-ofage
stories of two young men whose energy
and hopes are in stark contrast to the lives of
boredom and deceit led by the town's adults.
The only saving grace is Sam the Lion (played
by Ben Johnson, who had himself grown up in
the small Plains town of Foraker, Oklahoma),
who runs the movie house and provides a link
to the town's more vibrant past. But the movie
house closes (the last film shown is <title>Red River</title>),
and Sam dies, leaving only a dusty cocoon of a
place.</p>

<p>Even as historic Westerns have declined in
popularity in recent decades, the end-of-the-
West movie remains an effective theme, a poignant
evocation of the loss of a purportedly
simpler and more noble way of life before the
forces of modernism. The best recent example
is Stephen Frears's <title>The Hi-Lo Country</title> (1999),
a story of friendship between two cowboys,
Big Boy (Woody Harrelson) and Pete (Billy
Crudup), set on the Plains of eastern New
Mexico in the years immediately following
World War II, when the cattleman and the
cattle drive were giving way to the corporation
and the truck.</p>

<p>The Plains is also a favorite setting for road
movies, providing the spaces that must be
crossed to escape circumstances or to find redemption.
<title>Badlands</title> (Terrence Malik, 1973),
loosely based on the Charles Starkweather
murder spree, <title>Thelma and Louise</title> (Ridley
Scott, 1991), which feminizes this generally
male genre, and the humorous and uplifting
<title>Pow-Wow Highway</title> (Jonathan Wacks, 1988),
the story of the spiritual quest of a young
Northern Cheyenne man from his impoverished
Montana reservation to New Mexico via
the sacred Bear Butte, all involve flights by
automobile across the Plains.</p>

<p>Some of the most important Plains films
deal with the exploitation of the region by
outside forces and the political responses of
the people. The opening scene of <title>The Grapes of Wrath</title>, where Tom Joad walks across the flat
Plains landscape, evokes a sense of exposure
and vulnerability and prepares the viewer for
the exodus of the Joads from Oklahoma to
California. Four years before Ford's classic,
Pare Lorentz's documentary, <title>The Plow that Broke the Plains</title>, had blamed the machine for
the Dust Bowl and the ruin of families like the
Joads. This powerful piece of propaganda
(made for the Resettlement Administration)
depicted an army of huge tractors moving
across the land, tearing through the virgin sod
and exposing the soil to the winds. Lorentz
backed off, however, from blaming the economic
forces behind those machines.</p>

<p>There is no backing off in John Hanson and
Rob Nilsson's <title>Northern Lights</title> (1979). The directors
use footage of North Dakota farm
families shot by Nilsson's grandfather between
1915 and 1921 as background for the story of
the rise of the populist Nonpartisan League.
The film conveys better than any other the feel
of the Northern Plains landscape and the lives
of farm families at the mercy of eastern industrialists.
A similar subject, the life of a prairie
farmer, is covered in <title>Paper Wheat</title> (Albert
Kish, 1979), which is set in Saskatchewan and
was another production of the National Film
Board of Canada.</p>

<p>There are also Plains films that stand alone,
outside of any genre. <title>The Wizard of Oz</title> (Victor
Fleming, 1939) is such a film, unless, of course,
it too is a road movie, from black-and-white
Kansas to Technicolor Oz and then back to
"no place like home." The film is based on the
book <title>The Wonderful Wizard of Oz</title> (1900) by L.
Frank Baum, who spent three years in South
Dakota during the drought and economic depression
of the late 1880s and early 1890s. Just
as the book is often seen as a critique of the
politics of the 1890s, the movie can also be
perceived as an allegorical commentary on the
1930s political scene. Opening in the sepiatoned
Dust Bowl of Kansas, it takes the viewer
to a blooming land transformed by Franklin
Roosevelt's New Deal.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Images of the Great Plains in Film</head>

<p>Popular images of places are probably shaped
more by movies than by any other medium,
and often those images have little to do with
historical or geographical reality. "Hollywood's
Canada," for example, is made up of
wild and impenetrable forests populated by
scarlet-clad Mounties. The Prairies, apparently
too tame and unexciting for Hollywood,
were rarely used as a film setting. Two useful
studies of Hollywood's Oklahoma (one by
Jack Spears, the other by Thomas Bohn and
Joseph Millichap) provide an opportunity to
focus on one Plains state and its celluloid image.</p>

<p>Most of the (at least) fifty-five feature films
that deal with Oklahoma concentrate on historical
themes of settlement. The land rush of
1889 and the oil boom of the early twentieth
century are favorite motifs. The other major
event in Oklahoma's history, the relocation of
Native Americans to then Indian Territory, is
not such a popular theme. This is not surprising,
because the traditional objective has been
to glorify the "winning of the West," using
Oklahoma as the setting, not to expose the
brutality and dire consequences of Native
American relocation. Most of the movies are
less about the actual place than about the
American ideology of taming the frontier. The
best movie in this tradition is <title>Cimarron</title> (Wesley
Ruggles, 1931), which won three Academy
Awards in 1931, including best picture. This
sprawling epic takes a pioneer Oklahoma family
from the land rush through the emergence
of the state to the oil fields and burgeoning
cities of the 1920s, along the way editorializing
on prejudice against Jews and Native Americans
and corruption in state government. Despite
such qualifications, the message is one of
successive frontiers offering opportunity to
enterprising Americans.</p>

<p>There is, however, an ambivalence in the
movie image of Oklahoma. Oklahoma is the
verdant land&#8211;"a colorful picture postcard,"
to use Spears's words—of the musical <title>Oklahoma!</title>,
but it is also the derelict oil fields of
<title>Tulsa</title> (Stuart Heisler, 1949), the ruined soil
and lives of <title>The Grapes of Wrath</title>, and the
small-town confinement of <title>The Dark at the Top of the Stairs</title> (1960), which was based on
the play by Kansan William Inge and directed
by fellow Kansan Delbert Mann. This ambivalent
image&#8211;garden and desert&#8211;can be extended
to cover the entire Plains region. Its
roots go back as far as Zebulon Pike, who in
1806 compared the Southern Plains to the Sahara,
and Lewis and Clark, who saw extraordinary
fecundity during their passage along
the eastern edge of the Central Plains in 1804.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Filmmaking in the Great Plains</head>

<p>Just like the Plains automobile companies that
turned out small numbers of distinctive cars
until the 1920s, when Detroit took over and
they went under, so small filmmaking companies
produced movies in various parts of
the Plains until they succumbed to the Hollywood
studio system.</p>

<p>One of the earliest Plains film companies
was founded by "Buffalo Bill" Cody in Denver
in 1913, with financial backing from the Denver
Post. The Colonel William F. Cody (Buffalo
Bill) Historical Pictures Company's sole
achievement, if that is the correct word, was
<title>The Indian Wars</title> (1914), which purported to
give an accurate representation of four key battles:
Summit Springs (1869), Warbonnet Creek
(1876), the Mission (1890), and Wounded Knee
(1890). The film was shot at the sites of the
battles and featured, in addition to Cody, Lt.
Gen. Nelson Appleton Miles, troops from the
Twelfth U.S. Cavalry, and more than a thousand
Lakotas. <title>The Indian Wars</title> was screened in
Washington dc, Denver, and Omaha, Alliance,
and Chadron, Nebraska, in 1914 before being
mired in controversy and withdrawn from circulation.
The government may have thought
that the military was presented as too much the
aggressor at Wounded Knee, Native Americans
resented their portrayal as "savages," and the
public simply did not think much of the entire
production.</p>

<p>A year later, the Black Hills Feature Film
Company had its brief moment of glory in the
northwestern Nebraska town of Chadron in
1915 with the production of the silent Western
<title>In the Days of '75 and '76</title>. The company was
organized by the townspeople, in particular,
the chief of police, James O. Hartzell, whose
wife wrote the script and whose daughter
played the lead role of Calamity Jane. A more
experienced company, Harman Brothers Film
Manufacturers of Omaha, was brought in for
technical advice. Shot in the nearby Nebraska
Pine Ridge country and the Black Hills of
South Dakota and using only local talent, the
seven-reel film was completed in a month. It
premiered to an enthusiastic audience, anxious
to catch glimpses of themselves and their
acquaintances, at Chadron's Rex Theater on
September 24, 1915, and subsequently played
at nearby frontier towns in Nebraska, Wyoming,
and South Dakota. It was a typical
Western genre film of the times, with saintly
heroes, vile villains, gambling, shootouts, and
friendly and hostile Indians. Within a year the
film had dropped out of sight, and so had the
Black Hills Feature Film Company.</p>

<p>Similar companies flourished briefly
throughout the Plains in the first two decades
of the twentieth century. Oklahoma seems to
have had more than its share, perhaps because
the frontier was living history in this newest
state, and former outlaws could parlay their established
fame into acting. William M. Tilghman,
for example, a famous frontier marshal,
moved effortlessly into directing silent Westerns
for the Oklahoma Natural Mutoscene
Company in 1908. The first, <title>The Wolf Hunt</title>,
shot in the Wichita Mountains, was screened
by President Theodore Roosevelt in the East
Room of the White House in 1909. The film
featured former outlaw Al Jennings, by then a
lawyer in Lawton. Jennings, a poor actor, went
on to a Hollywood career. Tilghman's second
film, <title>The Bank Robbery</title> (1908), starred Jennings
as his outlaw self as well as Comanche
chief Quanah Parker and many citizens of
Cache, where it was shot. Clearly, occupational
mobility was a feature of frontier life, and
the distinction between movies and real life
was blurred.</p>

<p>The Lincoln Motion Picture Company was
the most important of the early film companies
to be associated with the Plains. A
young Omaha, Nebraska, mailman, George P.
Johnson, and his film actor brother, Noble
(both Plains born, in Colorado Springs),
formed the company in 1915 in an effort to free
African American filmmakers from dependence
on European American financiers and
to combat the racist stereotypes propagated by
D. W. Griffith's <title>The Birth of a Nation</title> (1915).
Noble ran the studio in Los Angeles while
George promoted and distributed their films
from Omaha. In its movies and by its example,
the Lincoln Motion Picture Company
proclaimed that African Americans had every
right to participate fully in American life. But
the Johnsons constantly had to struggle to obtain
financing, and by 1920 they were competing
not only against the European American
movie establishment but also against other
African American companies, including that
of Oscar Micheaux. There was simply not
enough ticket-buying money in the African
American community to support such enterprises,
and in 1922 the Lincoln Motion Picture
Company folded.</p>

<p>In the Prairie Provinces, Calgary emerged
as a center of film production between 1919
and 1923 due to the entrepreneurship of Earnest
G. Shipman ("Ten Percent Ernie"), who
located there after obtaining the film rights
to James Oliver Curwood's stories. Shipman
produced five profitable films and a sixth that
was a financial disaster. He left the business,
and Prairie filmmaking declined.</p>

<p>In subsequent years, despite the suffocating
dominance of Hollywood, films have continued
to be made locally in the Great Plains.
Often they are associated with film schools
and public television stations. An annual
Great Plains Film Festival is now held at the
University of Nebraska-Lincoln to showcase
Plains filmmakers and films. Texas has a thriving
film industry, but its hub is Austin, outside
the Plains proper. North of the forty-ninth
parallel, film cooperatives and corporations in
Winnipeg, Regina, Saskatoon, and Calgary are
taking advantage of federal and provincial
funding to create television dramas and documentaries
(and occasionally low-budget feature
films) on Prairie Province topics and in
Prairie Province settings.</p>

<p>Meanwhile, the Plains continue to produce
movie stars and filmmakers, and directors
continue to be attracted to the region for its
epic landscapes, dramatic (and unfurling) history,
and mythic resonances.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">AFRICAN AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.afam.031">Micheaux, Oscar</ref>; <ref n="egp.afam.034">Parks, Gordon</ref> /
<hi rend="smallcaps">CITIES AND TOWNS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ct.049">Small Towns</ref> / 
<hi rend="smallcaps">LITERARY TRADITIONS</hi>: <ref n="egp.lt.003">Baum, Frank L.</ref>; 
<ref n="egp.lt.030">Inge, William</ref>; <ref n="egp.lt.044">McMurtry, Larry</ref>; <ref n="egp.lt.080">The Western</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT</hi>:
Dust Bowl / <hi rend="smallcaps">PROTEST AND DISSENT</hi>: <ref n="egp.pd.039">Nonpartisan League</ref>.</p>
</div2>

<closer>
<signed>David J. Wishart<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Berton, Pierre. <title level="m">Hollywood's Canada: The Americanization of Our National Image</title>. Toronto: McClelland and Stewart
Limited, 1975.</bibl> <bibl>Bohn, Thomas W., and Joseph Millichap.
"Film Images of Oklahoma." <title level="j">Film and History</title> 10 (1980):
83-89.</bibl> <bibl>Cripps, Thomas. <title level="m">Slow Fade to Black: The Negro in American Film, 1900-1942</title>. London: Oxford University
Press, 1977.</bibl> <bibl>Eisloeffel, Paul J., and Andrea I. Paul. "Hollywood
on the Plains: Nebraska's Contribution to Early
American Cinema." <title level="j">Journal of the West</title> 33 (1994): 13-19.</bibl>
<bibl>Etulain, Richard W. "Recent Interpretations of the Western
Film: A Bibliographical Essay." <title level="j">Journal of the West</title> 22
(1983): 72-82.</bibl> <bibl>Hilger, Michael. <title level="m">From Savage to Nobleman: Images of Native Americans in Film</title>. Lanham <hi rend="smallcaps">MD</hi>: Scarecrow
Press, 1995.</bibl> <bibl>Horne, C. S. "Interpreting Prairie Cinema."
<title level="j">Prairie Forum</title> 22 (1997): 135-51.</bibl> <bibl>Katz, Ephraim. <title level="m">The Film Encyclopedia</title>. 2nd ed. New York: Harper Collins,
1994.</bibl> <bibl>Keaton, Buster, with Charles Samuels. <title level="m">My Wonderful World of Slapstick</title>. London: George Allen and Unwin,
1967.</bibl> <bibl>McGilligan, Patrick. <title level="m">Robert Altman: Jumping off the Cliff</title>. New York: St. Martin's Press, 1989.</bibl> <bibl>Parks, Gordon.
<title level="m">Voices in the Mirror: An Autobiography</title>. New York: Doubleday,
1990.</bibl> <bibl>Paul, Andrea. "Buffalo Bill and Wounded
Knee: The Movie." <title level="j">Nebraska History</title> 71 (1990): 183-90.</bibl>
<bibl>Slotkin, Richard. "John Ford's Stagecoach and the Mythic
Space of the Western Movie." In <title level="m">The Big Empty: Essays on Western Landscapes and Narrative</title>, edited by Leonard Engel.
Albuquerque: University of New Mexico Press, 1994:
261-83.</bibl> <bibl>Spears, Jack. "Hollywood's Oklahoma." <title level="j">Chronicles of Oklahoma</title> 67 (1989-90): 340-81.</bibl>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>