<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.sr.027">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Heisman Trophy Winners</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Thomas P. Jundt</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.sr.027</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Jundt, Thomas P.">Thomas P. Jundt</author>. <title level="a">"Heisman Trophy Winners."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">776</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-21</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">HEISMAN TROPHY WINNERS</head>

<p>The first Great Plains Heisman Trophy winner
was Texas Christian University's Davey
O'Brien, who claimed the honor in 1938, the
third year it was awarded to the nation's outstanding
college football player. It would be
fourteen years before another Plains star, Billy
Vessels of Oklahoma, won the award in 1952,
unless Nile Kinnick, who had attended high
school in Omaha but won the trophy while at
Iowa in 1939, is counted. A second Heisman
drought hit the Plains after Vessels's victory,
this time lasting until 1969, when Oklahoma's
Steve Owens ended the dry spell and began a
steady stream of Plains Heisman champions.
In 1972 Nebraska's Johnny Rodgers was honored,
followed in 1977 by Earl Campbell of
Texas, Oklahoma's Billy Sims in 1978, Nebraska's
Mike Rozier in 1983, Barry Sanders of
Oklahoma State in 1988, Colorado's Rashaan
Salaam in 1994, Ricky Williams of Texas in
1998, and Eric Crouch of Nebraska in 2001.</p>

<p>Of these eleven Heisman heroes, however,
only four&#8211;Billy Vessels, Johnny Rodgers,
Barry Sanders, and Eric Crouch&#8211;were homegrown
products of the Plains.</p>

<p>Billy Vessels, of tiny Cleveland, Oklahoma,
has been called the first Heisman winner of
the modern era because it was his outstanding
play in a nationally televised game, against
Notre Dame in 1952, that moved him to the
front of that year's Heisman class. When informed
that he had won the Heisman, Vessels
replied, "What's the Heisman?" The growing
presence and influence of television and its
fondness for spectacles like the awarding of
the Heisman make it likely that Vessels was
the last winner who had no knowledge of the
award.</p>

<p>In contrast to Vessels and his small-town
background, 1972 winner Johnny Rodgers
grew up on the streets of Omaha's north side.
At Nebraska he was known for his incredible
runs as a wide receiver and punt returner,
most notably, a 72-yard return against Oklahoma
in the 1971 "Game of the Century." But
he was also known for his run-ins with the
law. Heisman voters struggled with the issue
of awarding the trophy to a convicted felon,
but in the end Rodgers's failings seemed to
pale when compared to his successes in overcoming
great adversity in his life. He was only
the third wide receiver to win the award.</p>

<p>Barry Sanders attended high school at Wichita
North. He dreamed of attending the University
of Oklahoma but was turned down by
coach Barry Switzer because he was only five
feet seven inches tall and weighed only 175
pounds. Instead, he was welcomed at Oklahoma
State, where he shattered National Collegiate
Athletic Association (<hi rend="smallcaps">NCAA</hi>) rushing
records. "We just blew it," Switzer later said
about passing over Sanders. "I admire talent,
and Barry Sanders is a phenomenal talent."
After winning the Heisman during his junior
year in 1988, Sanders moved to the National
Football League, where he became the acclaimed
running back of the Detroit Lions.</p>

<p>Eric Crouch graduated from Millard North
High School in Omaha and from the University
of Nebraska–Lincoln. With his forty-yard
dash time of 4:47, Crouch holds the <hi rend="smallcaps">NCAA</hi> Division
I-A quarterback record with fifty-nine
career rushing touchdowns, but he also completed
51.5 percent of his passes during his college
career, and, when called upon, as in the
2001 victory over Oklahoma, he dazzled as a
receiver.</p>


<p><ref target="http://www.heisman.com/index.php">Heisman</ref> website.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Thomas P. Jundt<lb/>
Brown University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Bell, Jack, et al., eds. <title level="m">The Heisman: Sixty Years of Tradition
and Excellence</title>. Bronxville <hi rend="smallcaps">NY</hi>: Adventure Quest, 1995.</bibl>
<bibl>Brady, John T. <title level="m">The Heisman: A Symbol of Excellence</title>. New
York: Athenaeum, 1984.</bibl> <bibl>Rader, Benjamin G. <title level="m">American
Sports: From the Age of Folk Games to the Age of Televised
Sports</title>. Englewood Cliffs <hi rend="smallcaps">NJ</hi>: Prentice-Hall, 1999.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>