<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.afam.038">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Scott Family</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Cheryl Brown Henderson</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.afam.038</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Henderson, Cheryl Brown">Cheryl Brown Henderson</author>. <title level="a">"Scott Family."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">21</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-12-08</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">SCOTT FAMILY</head>

<p>The Scott family of Topeka, Kansas, has earned
a special place in the legal culture of the Great
Plains. Three generations of attorneys have
come from their ranks, and among their
achievements is their successful effort to secure
the educational equality of all American
children.</p>

<p>Elisha Scott Sr. (1890&#8211;1963) was born in
Memphis, Tennessee, the youngest of thirteen
children. Eventually, the Scott family made
their way to Topeka, settling on Lane Street in
West Topeka. His mother was employed as a
domestic worker and his father sold coal by
the bushel and herded cattle. Elisha Scott's life
was shaped not only by his hard-working parents
but also through the efforts of a local,
well-respected minister, the Rev. Charles Sheldon.
Reverend Sheldon replaced Scott's worn
clothing and made sure he had a few dollars in
his pocket, but his crucial act of generosity
came when he paid Scott's tuition at the Kansas
Technical Institute, an all&#8211;African American
vocational school. In 1916 Scott graduated
from Washburn College with a degree in law.
He was the only African American in his graduating
class and only the third African American
to graduate from Washburn Law School.</p>

<p>Scott went on to become one of Topeka's
most prominent attorneys. His courtroom
flair gained him national exposure. It was not
uncommon for his mail to be addressed simply
as "Colored Lawyer, Topeka." Scott was
known for taking cases that seemed impossible
to win. He used every legal maneuver
available to secure an acquittal. His financial
breakthrough came in the mid-1920s when he
successfully represented a group of African
American and Native American clients from
Oklahoma and Texas who had been driven off
their land. As it turned out, the land was rich
in oil.</p>

<p>Scott and his wife, Esther, had three sons,
John, Charles Sr., and Elisha Jr., who would
grow up to join their father in the family law
firm. John J. Scott (1919–1984) received his
formal education at Topeka High School and
the University of Kansas. After graduation,
John followed in his father's footsteps and in
1942 entered the law school at Washburn University.
He completed only two years before he
was called for active duty in World War II. In
1946 Scott returned to Washburn University
to complete his law degree. He graduated on
June 8, 1947, and joined the family law firm.
Charles Scott Sr. (1921–1989) also attended
Topeka Public Schools and graduated from
Topeka High School. In 1940 he began pursuing
a career in law by enrolling at Washburn,
only to be interrupted by World War II. During
the war he was assigned to the all-black
Second Calvary Division and served in southern
France. Charles Scott and his father enjoyed
an especially close relationship, especially
during wartime. In 1946, after the war,
Charles Scott reenrolled in Washburn University
and acquired his law degree in 1948. From
there he joined the family firm.</p>

<p>During his initial years in private practice,
Charles Scott Sr. and his father were successful
in securing the racial integration of elementary
schools in South Park, Johnson County,
Kansas. Later, Charles and John represented
plaintiffs in several cases that sought to allow
blacks access to swimming pools, theaters,
and restaurants in Topeka. In 1951 Charles and
John Scott were among the attorneys who represented
the naacp in filing their landmark
case, <title>Brown v. The Board of Education of Topeka</title>.
Although the case was unsuccessful in
district court, it was won on appeal in a unanimous
decision by the U.S. Supreme Court on
May 17, 1954, and the principle of racially diverse
learning environments was established.</p>

<p>Only in their early thirties, Charles and
John had gained national attention as a result
of the <title>Brown</title> case. They probably could have
practiced law anywhere. Charles chose to stay
in Topeka to pursue civil and human rights
issues, while John relocated to Washington
dc, where he took a position in the Department
of the Interior as assistant solicitor.</p>

<p>Charles Scott Jr. (b. 1948) also followed in
the footsteps of his father. In 1979 Charles,
an attorney in private practice in Kansas City,
Kansas, together with two local Topeka attorneys
and representatives of the American Civil
Liberties Union (<hi rend="smallcaps">ACLU</hi>), petitioned the federal
court to reopen the original <title>Brown</title> case. Their
purpose was to determine if Topeka Public
Schools had ever in fact complied with the
Supreme Court's ruling of 1954. The petition
to reopen was in direct response to a schooldistrict
policy allowing enrollment based on
parental choice rather than neighborhood
boundaries. As a result, Topeka schools were
once again placed under legal scrutiny. In 1992
they were ordered by the federal court to develop
a plan to remedy all vestiges of school
segregation. The solution included constructing
three magnet schools, one of which is
named for the Scott attorneys.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">LAW</hi>: 
    <ref n="egp.law.011"><hi rend="italic">Brown v. The Board of Education of Topeka</hi></ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Cheryl Brown Henderson<lb/>
Brown Foundation for Educational Equity, Excellence and Research</signed>
</closer>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>