<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.pg.052">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">National Progressive Party</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>J. E. Rea</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.pg.052</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Rea, J. E.">J. E. Rea</author>. <title level="a">"National Progressive Party."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">677-678</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-30</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">NATIONAL PROGRESSIVE PARTY</head>

<p>The National Progressive Party of Canada was
born of frustration and expired in futility. At
bottom it was an attempt to achieve regional
economic goals at the national level through
third-party political action in a traditionally
two-party context. The grain growers of the
Canadian Plains and their rural allies in Ontario
participated in provincial politics as well
and with much greater success.</p>

<p>The first small shipment of wheat for export
left the Prairies in 1876. But it was not
until the completion of the Canadian Pacific
Railway in the mid-1880s that the agricultural
potential of the area began to be realized. It
was capable of producing, in extraordinary
quantities, the best hard wheat in the world.
For the individual producer, however, it was a
costly progress from farm gate to final sale.
Along the way lurked predators of many kinds
taking their profits from the value of the farmer's
wheat. First were the bankers who provided
his credit. Then came the local elevator
or storage companies, the grain dealers on the
Winnipeg Exchange, the railways, the terminal
elevators, the shipping lines, the insurance
brokers, the importers, and the millers. The
international price of the farmer's bushel of
wheat had to satisfy them all. To the individual
grain grower, the most vulnerable link in this
chain, the game seemed loaded against him.</p>

<p>It was the impotence of the individual
farmer that drove them together. In 1902 they
formed the Territorial Grain Growers Association,
and, after Alberta and Saskatchewan
became provinces in 1905, they as well as Manitoba
created provincial organizations. For
most farmers the critical question was control
of production costs. They had to sell their
wheat in an uncontrollable world market and
buy all their necessities from protected industries
in Central Canada. Effective cost control
would depend, ultimately, on political action
on the tariff.</p>

<p>With the protectionist Conservatives in
power in Ottawa after 1911, the western farmers
could expect little relief from that direction.
When the Nonpartisan League won
North Dakota in 1916, Canadian farmers began
to dream of a third-party assault on Ottawa.
That same year, the Canadian Council of
Agriculture, a lobby group, issued the Farmers'
Platform demanding lower tariffs, tax reform,
and public ownership of transportation
and communication facilities.</p>

<p>The move toward independent political action
was stalled by the exigencies of the World
War I and the disruption of the world wheat
market. With Argentina and Australia out of
the game because of shipping shortages and
submarine threats, Canada and the United
States had little choice but to negotiate with
Britain a fixed price for wheat and compel all
their producers to participate in a regulated
market. As it turned out, the price was well
above prewar prices. A coalition government
was formed by the ruling Conservatives and
most Liberals in Canada to prosecute the war
vigorously on a nonpartisan basis. The western
grain growers gave their support, and
their most prominent leader, T. A. Crerar,
president of United Grain Growers, a successful
farmer-owned cooperative, entered the
cabinet as minister of agriculture.</p>

<p>Crerar had not abandoned his low-tariff
principles. He made it clear to the prime minister,
Sir Robert Borden, that if the government
maintained high-tariff policies after the war, he
could no longer remain in the cabinet. When
the Union government introduced its budget in
the late spring of 1919, it contained no provisions
for lower tariffs. Crerar promptly resigned
and was immediately joined by ten others.
They began calling themselves Progressives
and were in the unusual position of having a
parliamentary delegation before any such party
was organized in the country.</p>

<p>The following year the National Progressive
Party was formally organized, Crerar was confirmed
as leader, and a refurbished Farmers'
Platform was their banner. Across the Prairies
and in rural Ontario they seemed to carry all
before them. When the Union government
called a federal election in late 1921, the Progressives
permanently disrupted Canadian
politics. For the first time since Confederation
in 1867 there was a credible third party on the
national scene. The Liberals, with a plurality of
seats in the House of Commons, formed the
country's first minority government. The Progressives
had won sixty-five seats and thus became
the second-largest group in the House.
They declined the role of Official Opposition,
to which they were entitled, because they were
hamstrung by their own rather confused ideology.
Crerar could never enforce party discipline
on this "restless and unreliable band."</p>

<p>Largely because they were unwilling and
unable to exploit their balance of power position,
the Progressives were not successful in
national affairs. Prime Minister Mackenzie
King quickly realized that the Progressives
would never support the high-tariff Conservatives
and thus he had little to fear from
them. His position, though tenuous, was nevertheless
secure. There were inconclusive negotiations
about an arrangement between
Liberals and Progressives, but King would not
commit himself to lower tariffs and risk his
Montreal support for undependable assurances
from Crerar. The latter, for his part,
could not organize his followers into a disciplined
political force. So on their major issue
of tariff reform, the Progressives gained little.
They were able to secure the restoration of
favorable freight rates on grain shipments,
known as the Crow's Nest Pass rates. It was
their only significant achievement.</p>

<p>A year after the election, Crerar resigned
the leadership of the Progressive Party. There
were personal reasons for his decision, but it
was also evident that he had grown discouraged
by the internal divisions of the party. As
the Progressives disintegrated, the grain growers
of the Prairies were turning once again to
economic action to serve their needs. The new
pooling movement swept them in a new direction.
In the election of 1925 they were reduced
to twenty-four seats. Most of them drifted
into the Liberal Party until only a small group
of less than a dozen, known as the "Ginger
Group," remained in the House.</p>

<p>What had these angry farmers accomplished?
They formed a minority government
briefly in Ontario and they came to dominate
the politics of the Prairie Provinces, ensuring
attention to their demands. On the national
level, they ended the two-party system in Canada
and forced the restoration of favorable
freight rates. Western dissent became an enduring
factor in Canadian politics.</p>

<closer>
<signed>J. E. Rea<lb/>
University of Manitoba</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Laycock, David. <title level="m">Populism and Democratic Thought in the
Canadian Prairies, 1910 to 1945</title>. Toronto: University of
Toronto Press, 1990.</bibl> <bibl>Morton, William Lewis. <title level="m">The Progressive
Party in Canada</title>. Toronto: University of Toronto
Press, 1950.</bibl> <bibl>Rea, J. E. T. A. <title level="m">Crerar, A Political Life</title>. Montreal:
McGill-Queen's University Press, 1997.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>