<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ag.007">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Agricultural Price Supports</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Bruce Johnson</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ag.007</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Johnson, Bruce">Bruce Johnson</author>. <title level="a">"Agricultural Price Supports."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">34</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-12-10</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">AGRICULTURAL PRICE SUPPORTS</head>

<p>Since the 1930s the United States and Canada
have operated agricultural price-support programs.
The intent has been multifaceted, but
primarily the purpose has been to manage agricultural
output levels in order to increase the
price per unit and thereby raise the net income
of farmers.</p>

<p>In the United States, the Agricultural Adjustment
Administration was formed in 1933,
after commodity prices fell by more than 50
percent from 1929 to 1932. Farmers were experiencing
negative net farm income year after
year, trying desperately, and often unsuccessfully,
to avoid bank foreclosure. Farmers continued
producing even though there were no
markets for what was already in hand.</p>

<p>This desperate situation of chronic overproduction
by U.S. producers led to the Agricultural
Adjustment Act of 1933, which established
government supply management
for, initially, seven major farm commodities:
wheat, corn, cotton, rice, tobacco, milk, and
hogs. The arguments for establishing these
programs and continuing them since have
largely centered upon the farmer's poor bargaining
power in the marketplace, the belief
that agriculture has a constant propensity to
overproduce, and the need for price stability.</p>

<p>Commodity programs in the United States
have not been without critics, who have argued
that artificially high prices have weakened
the competitiveness of the United States
in the world market. They have also argued
that the programs have contributed to the
trend toward fewer and larger farms since
payment flows have tended to be directly proportional
to production volume. Thus, critics
believe the programs have led to impractical
and unsustainable solutions.</p>

<p>While the intent was similar, Canadian
efforts to support prices have taken a much
different strategy. Canada historically has not
restricted the production of individual grains
and has not idled cropland. Instead it has relied
on the Canadian Wheat Board (<hi rend="smallcaps">CWB</hi>) to
set the marketing and export policy for its major
agricultural grains. Using this single-seller
agency and heavily regulated producer quotas,
it has accomplished a price support system
for Canadian producers in its three Prairie
Provinces.</p>

<p>A second means by which Canada has influenced
the income of agriculture producers
has been through heavily subsidized rail
transportation services for grain movement.
In essence, the rates are in relation to the distance
from the Prairie Provinces to the key
ports, thus equalizing the terms for producers
across the entire grain-producing region. In
so doing, Canadian crop production took on a
geographic configuration far different from
what it would have been without graduated
transportation subsidies.</p>

<p>Farm commodity programs have had a major
impact in the Great Plains, wherever
wheat, corn, and other feed grains are dominant
crops. Program participation by Plains
farmers has been relatively high, which has led
to a major income transfer into the economies
of rural counties. In fact, in many years U.S.
farm price-support programs have constituted
from one-third to one-half of net farm
income in many Plains states. These payments
reached record highs in 2000, when direct
government payments represented $28 billion&#8211;
61 percent&#8211;of the U.S. total net farm
income of $46 billion. And in several of the
Plains states, the government payment component
was 75 percent or more of the total
state net farm income. Canadian programs
have had similar impacts on producer income
levels in the Prairie Provinces. Moreover, the
layers of regulatory and compliance detail attached
to program participation in the United
States and Canada have significantly shaped
cropping patterns and land-use practices. Conservation
management practices have been instituted
over time using the economic incentive
of farm program participation.</p>

<p>Over the course of the last two U.S. farm programs
of 1996 and 2002, substantial changes in
strategy have taken place. In contrast to earlier
efforts to manage supply levels and therefore
increase commodity prices, the intent has now
shifted to allow more farmer freedom of production
levels and to rely on a market clearing
system driven heavily by global forces of international
trade. The result has been more volatile
and generally lower commodity price levels
for those crops covered by the programs. In
turn, direct and price deficiency payments are
now being made to farmer producers relative
to their production volume to maintain income
levels. The level of these payments has
been substantial in recent years, and dependency
upon them among producers is very
high. In fact, crop producers across the U.S.
Great Plains could be said to be on "economic
life support" via these programs as market
prices of major commodities have fallen below
unit cost of production.</p>

<p>Because the current 2002 U.S. farm program
is scheduled to continue for at least the
next five years, the economic safety net legislation
is in place for the near-term future. However,
given the larger economic and political
uncertainties facing this nation, there is no
guarantee that future funding will be at the
initial levels proposed. If budget constraints
force cutbacks, this safety net could begin to
unravel.</p>

<p>For the Plains economy, which remains
heavily tied to production agriculture, the implications
of this change could be profound. If
U.S. federal farm transfer payments drop significantly
in the face of low commodity prices,
farm income variability from year to year and
from one producer to the next will magnify.
Canadian producers may well face similar
challenges from these economic forces. Those
producers with expertise in risk management
and astute marketing will be able to survive
economically and perhaps even thrive, while
others without these skills and resources will
likely exit production agriculture at accelerating
rates. There will also be some others
who will focus more on agricultural products
(i.e., organic products marketed direct from
the farm) than agricultural commodities and
find economically viable niches, but their
numbers are likely to be modest in the context
of the entire agricultural sector. In sum, entire
farming communities and regions within the
Plains may be economic winners or losers depending
upon the adjustments they are willing
and able to make as the history of agricultural
farm programs transitions and the
structure of the agricultural sector evolves.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Bruce Johnson</signed>
<signed>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Cramer, Gail L., and Eric J. Wailes. <title level="m">Grain Marketing</title>. Boulder
co: Westview Press, 1993.</bibl> <bibl>Paarlberg, Don. <title level="m">Farm and
Food Policy: Issues of the 1980s</title>. Lincoln: University of Nebraska
Press, 1980.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>