<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->


<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.arc.025">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Goff, Bruce (1904-1982)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Arn Henderson</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.arc.025</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Henderson, Arn">Arn Henderson</author>. <title level="a">"Goff, Bruce (1904-1982)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">82</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-12</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">GOFF, BRUCE (1904-1982)</head>

<p>Bruce Goff is regarded as a major visionary
architect. His imaginative designs are an extension
of precepts of organic architecture developed
by Louis Sullivan and Frank Lloyd
Wright. Born in Alton, Kansas, on June 8,
1904, Gott was raised mainly in Tulsa, Oklahoma.
He began his career in architecture at
age twelve with a part-time drafting job. He
established himself as an imaginative designer
and was responsible for several notable buildings
in Tulsa during the 1920s. His Boston Avenue
Methodist Church (1926-28) is regarded
as one of the most significant twentiethcentury
churches.</p>

<p>Goff practiced and taught in Chicago during
the 1930s and served in a construction battalion
in Alaska with the U.S. Navy during
World War II. He practiced briefly in San
Francisco before returning to Oklahoma in
1946 as a professor of architecture at the University
of Oklahoma. Later that year he was
appointed chairman of the school, a position
he held until 1955. Beginning in the 1940s
Goff's architectural expression became increasingly
diverse. Central to his philosophy
was the uniqueness of both clients and building
sites as primary determinants of design.
Yet despite the visual diversity of his buildings,
there are common characteristics that establish
a sense of continuity and inform us of his
ideals.</p>

<p>The most prominent characteristic of his
residential work is a reliance on several alternative
modes of geometry to organize floor
plans. Goff would frequently develop a plan
derived from a primary geometric form, such
as a circle, triangle, or hexagon, with the interior
volume defining a vertical axis. Other
characteristics include an open plan with visual
extensions into adjacent spaces and a
concern for spatial modulation. The concept
of interior furnishings as an integral and
built-in part of the architecture is another
characteristic. Natural light in Goff's buildings
is often introduced by skylights or clerestories,
and views from the interior to the exterior,
especially on the front facade, are often restricted.
Many of his houses have exaggerated
eaves with a thin edge that evokes a feeling
of lightness. Facades are highly articulated,
and materials are rich in pattern, texture, and
color. Water, in the form of interior or exterior
pools, is another element of many designs,
for Goff had a particular fascination
with reflectivity.</p>

<p>The Bavinger House, completed in 1955 on a
rural site in Norman, Oklahoma, is regarded
as one of Goff's premier designs. The plan of
the house is a logarithmic spiral built of rubble
sandstone inset with blue-green cullets. The
spiral wall appears to emerge from the earth
and wrap around a central mast more than
fifty feet in the air. The roof of the house is
a warped plane suspended from the central
mast. Interior "rooms" are defined as a series
of platforms suspended within the spiraling
space. Each of these platforms is accessible by
stairs that wrap around an interior wall of the
spiral as it converges on the central mast. The
lowest platform, located at the wide part of the
spiral, is a conversation area raised slightly
above the floor. Above are platforms that function
as sleeping areas and an uppermost platform
that is a glass-enclosed studio. Each
of these platforms also contains a coppercovered
storage cylinder. Collectively, this ensemble
of elements&#8211;platform and cylinder&#8211;
establish a dominant rhythm that, like the
enclosing spiraling space, ascends upward.
Contrasting with these repetitive geometric elements,
the floor below is a collage of fieldstone,
irregular planter beds, and pools of water
with goldfish.</p>

<p>Goff left the university in 1955 and relocated
his practice in Bartlesville, Oklahoma. He
later established his office in Kansas City for
several years before moving to Tyler, Texas,
where he continued to work until his death
on August 4, 1982. During the last quartercentury
of his career he continued to develop
much impressive work, including the Japanese
Pavilion of the Los Angeles County Art
Museum.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Arn Henderson<lb/>
University of Oklahoma<lb/>
</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>DeLong, David G. <title level="m">Bruce Goff: Toward Absolute Architecture</title>.
New York: Architectural History Foundation and
mit Press, 1988.</bibl> <bibl>Saliga, Pauline, and Mary Woolever, eds.
<title level="m">The Architecture of Bruce Goff, 1904-1982: Design for the Continuous Present</title>. Chicago: Art Institute of Chicago and
Prestel-Verlag, 1995.</bibl> <bibl>Welch, Philip B. <title level="m">Goff on Goff: Lectures and Conversations</title>. Norman: University of Oklahoma
Press, 1996.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>