<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.asam.018">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Nikka Yuko Garden</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Lennox Tierney</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.asam.018</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Tierney, Lennox">Lennox Tierney</author>. <title level="a">"Nikka Yuko Garden."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">145-146</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-22</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">NIKKO YUKO GARDEN</head>

<p>Japanese Gardens exist in all parts of the world,
and the Great Plains states and provinces host
some of the finest examples. Though there are
important gardens in Sioux Falls, South Dakota,
and in Devon near Edmonton, as well as
other Plains cities, the preeminent example is
the Nikka Yuko Garden (<hi rend="italic">Ni</hi> for <hi rend="italic">Nihon</hi> [Japan],
<hi rend="italic">Ka</hi> for Canada, Yuko for widespread friendship)
in Lethbridge, Alberta.</p>

<p>Japanese gardens occur in several different
formations. Meditation gardens are for quiet
contemplation, rather than for walking, and
consist of flat, dry-raked gravel with beautiful
"island" stones irregularly placed in the
sand or gravel area. Certain elements pertain
to the basic cosmic forces seen in all gardens.
namely the air, earth, fire, and water as universal
components. Some of these elements
occur as garden furniture or in the form
of other features such as lanterns (fire), ponds
(water), stones (earth), and of course the omnipresent
air. Nothing in nature is absolute;
hence dry gardens contain some water&#8211;
usually in a <hi rend="italic">tsukubai</hi> (basin) in one part of the
garden. In the case of the Nikko Yuko, water
additionally is suggested by the <hi rend="italic">shakkei</hi> (borrowed
landscape) view of a nearby lake.</p>

<p>Strolling gardens can also feature roji,
which include hills, streams, ponds, waterfalls,
and pathways. The latter give access to all
these beautiful aspects of nature as expressed
within the traditions of the Japanese garden.</p>

<p>Another form of the garden is the <hi rend="italic">cha-niwa</hi>
(tea master's garden). It is always small, never
pretentious, reserved in its nature, and minimal
in its number of plants. Some cha-niwa
are single-plant gardens reduced to the barest
essentials. Plants in this type of garden are
indicative of the immediate area and never
rare or exotic. The tea ceremony forms the
ultimate aesthetic occasion in Japanese art
and it takes place in a <hi rend="italic">cha shitso</hi> (tea house) in
a tea master's garden, usually within a larger
Japanese garden. Its simplicity causes this
form of garden to be the one most easily understood
of all the various forms of the Japanese
garden.</p>

<p>The Nikka Yuko Garden in Lethbridge contains
most of the above-mentioned characteristics
in an area slightly larger than three-andone-
half acres. The garden was established in
November 1964 and was two years in construction.
Dr. Tadashi Kubo of Osaka, Japan,
who earlier had built a Japanese garden in
San Diego, California, was instrumental in
the Lethbridge project. He was assisted by
Masami Sugimoto and Dr. Bob Hironaka of
Lethbridge during the two-year construction
phase. Mountains of earth were moved, distant
stones were donated and brought to the
site, and a water-circulation system was developed.
A garden was born.</p>

<p>Plants were donated. A pebble-picking picnic
produced bushels of stones from the Oldman
River for the ariso beaches of the garden's
pond. The necessary wooden structures were
built in Japan and shipped to Canada. Prince
and Princess Takamatsu of Japan officially
opened the garden on July 14, 1967, Canada's
centennial year. The dream of a fine Japanese
garden in the Plains had come true&#8211;a place of
peace and quiet, of <hi rend="smallcaps">WABI</hi> (beauty in simplicity)&#8211;
in the vastness of the Alberta prairie.</p>

<p><ref target="http://www.nikkayuko.com/">Nikko Yuko Garden</ref> website.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Lennox Tierney<lb/>
University of Utah</signed>
</closer>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>