<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.art.055">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Russell, Charles M. (1864-1926)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Susan E. Williams</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.art.055</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Dippie, Brian W.">Brian W. Dippie</author>. <title level="a">"Russell, Charles M. (1864-1926)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">128-129</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-22</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">RUSSELL, CHARLES M. (1864-1926)</head>

<p>Charles Marion Russell, born in St. Louis,
Missouri, on March 19, 1864, is today known
worldwide as Montana's "cowboy artist." The
third of six children, he grew up in comfortable
circumstances, but he was a misfit&#8211;a
dreamer who struggled with school and at an
early age set his heart on going west. In 1880
his parents yielded to his desire and, just before
his sixteenth birthday, granted him permission
to accompany a sheepman they knew
to Montana Territory. After a stint with a professional
meat hunter, Kid Russell (as he came
to be known) in 1882 hired on as night herder
on a trail drive from Billings to the Judith
Basin. Cattle driving and cowboying fit Russell's
romantic temperament, and for the next
eleven years (apart from the summer of 1888,
which he loafed away sketching Indians in Alberta),
he "sung to the horses and cattle,"
earning a reputation as an amusing raconteur
with an exceptional gift for portraying the life
around him.</p>

<p>Russell's small watercolor Waiting for a
Chinook, which shows a starving cow surrounded
by hungry wolves, summed up the
devastating winter of 1886–87 on the Northern
Plains and brought him his first real recognition
as an artist. In 1893, persuaded that
the open range cattle industry was finished,
Russell took up his art full time and in 1896
married Nancy "Mame" Cooper, an unsophisticated
eighteen-year-old with a head for
business and drive and ambition enough for
both of them. She assumed management of
his career, encouraging him in 1904 to make
the first in a series of trips to New York City,
where he met professional illustrators, editors,
and publishers who shared his enthusiasm for
western subjects. After a one-man exhibition
at the Folsom Galleries in New York in 1911,
Russell branched out, exhibiting at the inaugural
Calgary Stampede in 1912&#8211;his first international
exposure&#8211;and, significantly, at
London's Dor&#233; Galleries in 1914.</p>

<p>By then Russell was an established artist.
Though he did little illustration, his paintings
became familiar to the world through postcards,
calendars, and color reproductions. Especially
adept at modeling, Russell had his
first bronze cast in 1904, contributing to the
opinion after Frederic Remington's death in
1909 that he was America's most accomplished
western artist. Russell's repertoire was set
early. He added other subjects to it (mountain
men, hunting dramas in the high country,
wildlife studies, North-West Mounted Police
in action, some shooting scrapes), but the
body of his work consisted of cowboy scenes,
equally divided between roping and riding
pictures, and Indian scenes, including buffalo
hunts but mostly showing parties of warriors
moving across open space or perched on
bluffs, surveying the land below that once was
theirs. Indeed, the commemorative, nostalgic
tone of these pieces defined the entire body of
Russell's work and his commanding theme:
"the West that has passed."</p>

<p>Escalating prices followed Russell's rise to
prominence. By 1920, when the Russells began
spending their springs in California, a major
oil painting commanded $10,000. Other celebrities
were drawn into his orbit (Hollywood
movie stars, popular writers, and every
western artist of his day), and the rich and
influential became his patrons. But Charlie
Russell was a homebody at heart. He was always
most comfortable visiting with friends
in Great Falls, where he and Mame had lived
since 1897, shooting the breeze outside a saloon
or cigar store with cronies from his
rangeland days, and passing his summers at
Bull Head Lodge, his cabin built in 1905 at
the foot of Lake McDonald in what became
Glacier National Park. He liked his simple,
homespun routine, telling the yarns that were
published in two "joke books," <title level="m">Rawhide Rawlins Stories</title> (1921) and <title level="m">More Rawhides</title> (1925),
and collected in <title level="m">Trails Plowed Under</title>, a Western
classic that appeared in 1927, the year after
Russell died (on October 24) and was buried
in Great Falls.</p>

<p>Charles M. Russell remains one of the most
beloved of westerners, admired as much for
his sense of humor, his basic decency, and his
fierce loyalty to a time and a place as for the
artwork enshrined in museums across America.
His modest home and log cabin studio in
Great Falls bespeak a humble man who made
great things out of the ordinary clay of human
experience, closely observed and lovingly
recorded.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Brian W. Dippie<lb/>
University of Virginia</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Dippie, Brian W., ed. <title level="m">Charles M. Russell, Word Painter: Letters 1881–1926</title>. Fort Worth: Amon Carter Museum in
Association with Harry N. Abrams, 1993.</bibl> <bibl>Dippie, Brian
W., ed. <title level="m">Charlie Russell Roundup: Essays on America's Favorite Cowboy Artist</title>. Helena: Montana Historical Society
Press, 1999.</bibl> <bibl>Taliaferro, John. <title level="m">Charles M. Russell: The Life and Legend of America's Cowboy Artist</title>. Boston: Little,
Brown and Company, 1996.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>