<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fil.056">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Prairie Films</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Gerald S. Horne</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fil.056</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Horne, Gerald S.">Gerald S. Horne</author>. <title level="a">"Prairie Films."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">277</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-12</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">PRAIRIE FILMS</head>
<figure n="egp.fil.056" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Film poster for Who Has Seen The Wind (1977) </figDesc>
</figure>    

<p>The basis of a regional culture is a common
history and geography. The history of the Prairies,
a history of colonial expansion and exploitation,
has provided the basis for many a
yarn and many an artistic work. In terms of
geography, the look of the land and its unyielding
climate have inspired many to write
and paint and to make films. It may not be
possible to identify a specific type of film
called a "Prairie film," but over the years there
have been attempts to capture and transmit
Prairie culture in cinematic form. A completely
satisfying cinematic reflection of the
Prairie experience has yet to be created.</p>

<p>With cinema, as with publishing and some
forms of visual art, the demands of the marketplace
must also be taken into consideration.
Certainly, the Prairie region has been its
own marketplace. Some films have recuperated
their costs within the region. However,
production gatekeepers expect financial success,
which often means raising money by distribution
beyond the Prairies.</p>

<p>When Hollywood became a world center
for film production, producers realized that
Prairie history and geography could be exploited
in one of the most successful film
genres: the Western. By the time Edwin S. Porter
made <title>The Great Train Robbery</title> in 1903,
readers of pulp novels had already developed a
taste for stories of cowboy heroes and villains,
so it made sense to bring these characters to
the movie screen. Westerns could also employ
the appealing choreography of horse and
stagecoach chases, gunfights, and powwows.</p>

<p>Westerns have been successful in the marketplace,
but the genre is extremely restrictive
in terms of plot conventions. We must look to
independent filmmakers to provide us with
films that explore the finer aspects of the
Prairie experience. Independent filmmakers
also have to make money. Production costs for
even a short documentary film can be thousands
of dollars per minute. Government and
private foundations provide some funds for
independent production, but they tend to
place some creative demands on the filmmaking
process. When funding institutions reside
outside the Prairies, filmmakers face a battle
to tell regional stories that are true to their
cultural roots.</p>

<p>Some of the best cinema reflections of the
Prairie experience can be found embedded in
films whose purpose is not necessarily art but
some form of communication or commerce.
Educational films, industrial or promotional
films, television "movies of the week," and
in some cases commercial feature films have
contained scenes or elements that could be
said to reflect the Prairie experience.</p>

<p>One of the first Prairie films was also one of
the first films made in Canada. James Freer, a
Manitoba farmer, made a film of farm life in
1898. The film was sponsored by the Canadian
Pacific Railway to promote, in England, the
sale of land on the Prairies. No prints remain
of this first Prairie film, though it has been
much talked about, but one can speculate:
being a promotional piece, it is unlikely that it
contained images of blizzards or other elements
illustrating the harder aspects of life on
the Prairies during this period.</p>

<p>A long drought in regional production occurred
between 1925 and 1950. A few educational
films and documentaries appeared, but
cinematic storytelling was, for the most part,
left to Hollywood. The results have been disappointing
in their slavish use of Hollywood
conventions and stereotypes.</p>

<p>When television came to the Prairies in the
mid-1950s, tv stations produced some documentaries
as part of their mandate to reflect
the region for their viewers, usually in the form
of hard news reportage or promotion of local
events and institutions. The National Film
Board of Canada offered other opportunities
for the representation of Prairie themes and
stories. Notable <hi rend="smallcaps">NFB</hi> films of the 1950s include
<title>Corral</title> (1954), about an Alberta cowboy rounding
up and breaking wild horses, and <title>Paul Tomkowicz: Street Railway Switchman</title> (1954),
based on the elderly Tomkowicz's account of
working on the Winnipeg street railway line on
a cold winter day.</p>

<p><title>Drylanders</title> (1964), one of the first feature
film productions of the <hi rend="smallcaps">NFB</hi>, tells the story of a
family of settlers who arrive from eastern
Canada in the late 1800s to claim a piece of
land. The film includes images of the family
making their way west with an oxen cart,
building a sod hut in which to live during
their first winter, welcoming their first
bumper crop of wheat, then watching as the
land blows away during the "dirty thirties."</p>

<p>The 1970s was a period of expansion of the
Canadian motion picture industry. Money was
available in the form of loans and tax incentives
through the Canadian Film Development
Corporation (<hi rend="smallcaps">CFDC</hi>), later Telefilm Canada.
Some government- and foundation-funded
feature films have been successful at telling a
Prairie story while managing to make money
for their producers. These include <title>Who Has Seen the Wind</title> (1977), based on W. O. Mitchell's
coming-of-age novel; <title>The Hounds of Notre Dame</title> (1981), based on the early years of P&#232;re
Athol Murray at Notre Dame College in Wilcox,
Saskatchewan; and <title>Why Shoot the Teacher</title>
(1978), based on the Max Braithwaite novel of
the same name.</p>

<p>In the 1980s and 1990s film development
corporations were formed in Manitoba, Alberta,
and Saskatchewan to supplement federal
government funding from Telefilm Canada
with provincial government funds. The
budgets of SaskFilm and other Canadian film
agencies help to finance the one-to-four-million-
dollar movies of the week destined for
the pay television market. These films employ
some regional actors and craftspeople and use
regional locations. Unfortunately, the locations
are seldom identified within these films
and instead appear as generic U.S. cities. The
stories for these movies are chosen for their
wide commercial appeal rather than their regional
flair.</p>

<p>Regional filmmakers are unable to gain significant
funding for their projects because regional
films are not deemed financially viable.
Telefilm Canada and provincial film development
agencies seldom fund a project unless a
large percentage of its budget has been secured
from a major broadcaster or distributor.
A regional story by a regional writer is less
likely to gain the cooperation of a mainstream
coproducer or broadcaster.</p>

<p>Clearly, it is up to Prairie filmmakers themselves
to depict the Prairie experience in a
form that avoids stereotypes but manages to
entertain a wide audience well enough to attract
adequate funding and distribution both
within and outside the region.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Gerald S. Horne<lb/>
Burnaby, British Columbia</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Clandfield, David. <title level="m">Canadian Film</title>. Toronto: Oxford University
Press, 1987.</bibl> <bibl>Horne, G. S. "Interpreting Prairie Cinema."
<title level="j">Prairie Forum</title> 22 (1997): 135–51.</bibl> <bibl>Magder, Ted. <title level="m">Canada's Hollywood: The Canadian State and Feature Films</title>.
Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 1993.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>