<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fol.031">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Pecos Bill</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>F. E. Abernethy</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2009</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fol.031</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2009</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2009 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Abernethy, F. E.">F. E. Abernethy</author>. <title level="a">"Pecos Bill."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">307</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-16</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">PECOS BILL</head>

<p>Pecos Bill is a semilegendary cowboy-culture
hero of the Southwest. According to tales, Bill
was the strongest, meanest cowboy west of the
Pecos River, the greatest roper and bronc
buster and gunfighter. He rode a panther that
weighed as much as three steers and a yearling
and used a rattlesnake for a quirt. He invented
calf roping and branding and built the first six-shooter.
He could ride a cyclone while rolling
a cigarette with one hand. He dug the Rio
Grande one droughty year so he could get water
from the Gulf of Mexico up to the Pecos.
He staked out New Mexico for his ranch
spread and used Arizona as a calf pasture. He
became the mythical cowboy supertype.</p>

<p>Bill was born in the early 1830s of pioneer
Texas stock. When another family settled fifty
miles downriver, his family moved west because
of the crowded conditions. Bill fell out
of the wagon when it was crossing the Pecos,
and because there were so many kids in the
family, his folks did not miss him until it was
too late to go back. Bill was raised by coyotes,
and for food he ran down deer and jackrabbits.
Bill was ten years old when a cowboy rode
up on him while he was squeezing two bears
to death to get meat for supper. The cowboy
finally convinced Bill that he was human by
pointing out that he had no tail. So Bill threw
in with humans and began the adventures that
have earned him literary and folkloric fame.</p>

<p>Pecos Bill first came to literary life in an article
by journalist Edward O'Reilly in <title level="j">The Century Magazine</title> in October 1923. O'Reilly claims
to have heard stories about Pecos Bill in his
childhood and from cowboys sitting around
the chuck wagon. In 1934 Mody Boatright took
O'Reilly's stories and expanded them into
three chapters of his <title level="m">Tall Tales from Texas Cow Camps</title>. Because the only known means of dissemination
of Pecos Bill tales has been in published
literature, some scholars question the
validity of Pecos Bill as a true folk character.
The final authority on Texas legends, J. Frank
Dobie of the Texas Folklore Society, asserted
that Pecos Bill was unknown before O'Reilly's
article. Dobie based his judgment on his own
encyclopedic knowledge of southwestern folklore
and on the fact that O'Reilly once admitted,
in a lawsuit against a writer who plagiarized
his article, that he had invented Pecos
Bill. Pecos Bill seems to have been more the
product of journalism than folklore.</p>

<closer>
<signed>F. E. Abernethy<lb/>
Stephen F. Austin State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Boatright, Mody. <title level="m">Tall Tales from Texas Cow Camps</title>. Dallas:
Southwest Press, 1934.</bibl> <bibl>Botkin, B. A. "The Saga of Pecos
Bill." In <title level="m">A Treasury of American Folklore</title>. New York:
Crown Publishers, Inc., 1944: 180–85.</bibl> <bibl>O'Reilly, Edward.
"The Saga of Pecos Bill." <title level="j">The Century Magazine</title> 106 (1923):
827–33.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>