<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fil.021">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Fairbanks, Douglas, Sr. (1883-1939)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>John C. Tibbetts</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fil.021</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Tibbetts, John C.">John C. Tibbetts</author>. <title level="a">"Fairbanks, Douglas, Sr. (1883-1939)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">266</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-12</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">FAIRBANKS, DOUGLAS, SR. (1883-1939)</head>
<figure n="egp.fil.021" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Douglas Fairbanks in The Thief of Bagdad (1924)</figDesc>
</figure>    

<p>A major force in the motion picture industry
in the 1910s and 1920s, Douglas Fairbanks is
best remembered for his swashbuckling costume
pictures. He was born Douglas Elton Ulman
on May 23, 1883, in Denver, Colorado, the
last of three children to Ella and H. Charles
Ulman. After his father deserted the family, he
was raised by his mother, who reassumed the
surname of her first husband, Fairbanks. The
family relocated to New York City in 1900, and
young Doug began appearing in a succession
of light comedies on Broadway. By 1914 he had
established himself as a leading performer in
satiric comedies like <title>The Show Shop</title> and <title>The New Henrietta</title>.</p>

<p>Lured to Hollywood in 1915, his buoyant
optimism and physical agility transferred easily
to the motion picture screen. In just his first
year at Triangle.Fine Arts, the spectacular success
of open-air adventures like <title>The Lamb</title> (1915) and <title>The Good Bad Man</title> (1916) and farcical comedies like <title>His Picture in the Papers</title> and <title>American Aristocracy</title> (1916) encouraged him to
form his own production company, the Douglas
Fairbanks Film Corporation. Two years
later he joined Mary Pickford (soon to become
his second wife), Charles Chaplin, and D. W.
Griffith at United Artists, through which he
released his legendary swashbuckling costume
pictures, including <title>The Mask of Zorro</title> (1920),
<title>The Three Musketeers</title> (1921), <title>Robin Hood</title>
(1922), <title>The Thief of Bagdad</title> (1924), and <title>The Black Pirate</title> (1926). After the box office failure
of his first talkie, <title>The Taming of the Shrew</title>
(1929), costarring Mary Pickford, his career
trajectory faltered, and he retired from the
screen after making <title>The Private Life of Don Juan</title> (1934) in England. Restless to the end, he
divorced Pickford in 1936, married again a year
later, and, after years of traveling and a series of
half-hearted business ventures, died in his
sleep of a heart attack in the early morning
hours of December 12, 1939.</p>

<p>Fairbanks remains the very embodiment of
energy and optimism. In action and philosophy
his was the poetry of pose, the strut of
sentiment. He was an equal opportunity enthusiast
who played no favorites in the democracy
of delights. He pulled high-fives with
the world and claimed its privileges. An influential
businessman as well as a film celebrity,
he helped found the Academy of Motion Picture
Arts and Sciences (serving as its first president),
promoted the importation and distribution
in America of international art
house films like Eisenstein's <title>Potemkin</title> (1925),
and encouraged technical innovations in the
film industry like the Technicolor process
(which he employed in <title>The Black Pirate</title>).</p>

<p>His upbringing in Colorado and stage training
in New York City lent his work a peculiar
blend of western vigor and eastern attitude.
Particularly in the cycle of Westerns he made
from 1915 to 1919, East meets West and civilization
collides with nature in imaginative and
entertaining ways. In pictures like <title>The Lamb and The Mollycoddle</title> (1920), he's an effete aristocrat
tested by the rigors of cowboy life. In
<title>The Good Bad Man</title> and <title>The Half Breed</title> (1916)
he's a bandit and an Indian, respectively, seeking
the legitimacy of society. And in <title>Wild and Woolly</title> (1917) and <title>Knickerbocker Buckaroo</title>
(1919) he erases altogether the boundaries that
separate the cowboy from the clubman. Shot
on locations in prairie Kansas, the desert
Southwest, and the Grand Canyon, these films
provide spectacular scenic arenas for his
boundless energies and flamboyant acrobatics.
In a typical moment from The Mollycoddle, he
stands poised on the rim of the Grand Canyon,
suddenly raises his hands, and shouts, "Hurrah
for God!" It's a defining moment.</p>

<closer>
<signed>John C. Tibbetts<lb/>
University of Kansas</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Schickel, Richard. <title level="m">His Picture in the Papers</title>. New York:
Charterhouse, 1973.</bibl> <bibl>Tibbetts, John C. "The Choreography
of Hope: The Films of Douglas Fairbanks, Sr." <title level="j">Film Comment</title>
32 (1996): 50–55.</bibl> <bibl>Tibbetts, John C., and James M.
Welsh. <title level="j">His Majesty the American: The Films of Douglas Fairbanks, Sr.</title> Cranbury <hi rend="smallcaps">NJ</hi>: A. S. Barnes, 1977.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>