<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ag.011">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Barbed Wire</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Anne Dingus</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ag.011</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Dingus, Anne">Anne Dingus</author>. <title level="a">"Barbed Wire."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">35</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-12-10</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">BARBED WIRE</head>

<p>Barbed wire signaled the end of the Old West
and the beginning of modern ranching. Its
advent during the 1870s and 1880s sounded the
death knell for the trail drive and the open
range and allowed the expansion of farming.
Cattlemen at first resented barbed wire, but
after a decade of wrangling over access to water
and grasslands and waging fence-cutting
wars, they acknowledged its benefits and
adopted the newfangled fencing.</p>

<p>No single person invented barbed wire, but
in 1874 Joseph F. Glidden of DeKalb, Illinois,
was the first to receive a patent for his innovation,
a double strand of twisted wire interspersed
with shorter lengths wrapped around
it to form barbs. A few run-ins with the barbs
convinced even stubborn critters to avoid the
fence. Glidden dubbed his design "the Winner,"
a name that proved prophetic. He joined
forces with a local merchant, Isaac L. Ellwood,
to manufacture the Winner; soon they
counted among their customers 150 railroad
companies, who used the fence to protect
their tracks from herds running free. Eventually
more than a thousand barbed-wire designs
flooded the market, many with colorful
names such as Split Diamond, Necktie, Buckthorn,
Arrow Plate, and Spur-Rowel.</p>

<p>In one persuasive incident in downtown San
Antonio in 1878, barbed-wire salesman John
W. "Bet-a-Million" Gates successfully corralled
a herd of rambunctious longhorns inside
a fence of Glidden's wire, which, he
bragged, was "light as air, stronger than
whisky, and cheap as dirt." Ranchers all across
the Great Plains had to acknowledge that
Gates's claims were true. They also appreciated
barbed wire's availability in a region short
on wood for fences, its resilience in extreme
weather, and its ease of installation. Most importantly,
it permitted the selective breeding
of stock. The legendary plainsman Charles
Goodnight, for example, was able to maintain
a pure strain of imported English Herefords
and to develop the "cattalo," a buffalo-shorthorn
cross.</p>

<p>Not all of the consequences of barbed wire
were good. Large outfits could better afford
both the fencing and the labor to erect it;
smaller-scale ranchers were enraged to find
themselves cut off, overnight, from once-public
water holes, pastures, and trails. In
Texas angry cowboys struck back at cattle
barons with nighttime wire-snipping raids. By
1883 the attacks had escalated into violence,
forcing the Texas Rangers to patrol dozens of
hot spots and prompting the state legislature
to declare fence cutting a felony (a law that
still stands today). And during severe blizzards
throughout the Plains, drift fences&#8211;
intended to prevent herds from drifting off
the ranch&#8211;instead proved fatal to livestock,
which headed south by instinct, only to pile
up at the wire and freeze by the thousands.</p>

<p>Today barbed wire is a fixture of the Great
Plains. Cowboys have long counted among
their regular duties the erection, inspection,
and repair of fence line. The open range has
long been closed, but barbed wire's story is
preserved in two archives, the Kansas Barbed
Wire Museum in LaCrosse and the Devil's
Rope Museum in McLean, Texas.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Anne Dingus<lb/>
Austin, Texas</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>McCallum, Henry D., and Frances T. McCallum. <title level="m">The Wire
That Fenced the West</title>. Norman: University of Oklahoma
Press, 1965.</bibl> <bibl>Slatta, Richard W. <title level="m">The Cowboy Encyclopedia</title>.
New York: W. W. Norton &amp; Company, 1994.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>