<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.ct.013 SYSTEM "egp.ct.013.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ct.013">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">College Towns</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Blake Gumprecht</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ct.013</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Gumprecht, Blake">Blake Gumprecht</author>. <title level="a">"College Towns."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">163-164</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-27</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">COLLEGE TOWNS</head>

<figure n="egp.ct.013" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Aggieville (Manhattan) is a blur of activity after a 1984 Kansas State victory in football over the
University of Kansas.</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>More than a dozen Great Plains cities and
towns owe their development and contemporary
character to the presence of colleges
or universities. College towns like Lawrence,
Kansas, Brookings, South Dakota, and Chadron,
Nebraska, while distinct from one another
because of the different nature of the
schools located in them, are nonetheless similar
in many ways to hundreds of other cities
nationwide that are dominated by institutions
of higher education. With their youthful and
comparatively diverse populations, highly educated
workforces, relative absence of heavy
industry, and presence of cultural opportunities
unusual for cities of their size, these
towns stand apart from the rest of the region.</p>

<p>As elsewhere in the United States, many
colleges on the Plains were founded outside
the largest cities, so they came to have a controlling
influence over the places where they
were located. Colleges were placed in smaller
towns not because, as is often assumed, college
founders had an antiurban attitude but
because small towns actively pursued colleges
as a way to assure their economic survival.
Rarely did the municipality that won designation
as seat of a college have any special locational
advantages. More often than not, it
was successful because it offered the largest
amount of money and the biggest plot of land
or was politically adept. Backroom deals and
unethical behavior were common. Town leaders
in Lawrence, for example, bribed legislators
deciding where to locate the University of
Kansas for $4 a vote.</p>

<p>Most college towns remained relatively
small places, with the college often serving as
but one part of a diversified economy, until
after World War II, when a college degree increasingly
came to be viewed as a prerequisite
for success. Enrollments boomed through the
mid-1970s, and college towns grew rapidly as a
result. As higher education institutions fueled
local economic development, town leaders
began to resist less desirable types of industry,
and college towns became more onedimensional
in the process. To some degree,
they resemble company towns, with the college
as the number one employer, biggest
property owner and landlord, and most powerful
political force. In many, the majority of
the population has some connection to the
college. In Vermillion, South Dakota, a town
of fewer than 10,000 residents that is home to
the University of South Dakota, students and
staff number more than 8,000.</p>

<p>The most fundamental difference between
college towns and the rest of the Great Plains
is demographic. In a region that is growing
older, college towns are ever young. Nearly
half the residents of Manhattan, Kansas, home
of Kansas State University, are eighteen to
twenty-four years old. While many towns on
the Plains are losing people, college towns are
growing. The population of Brookings, home
of South Dakota State University, grew 14 percent
between 1990 and 2000. In a region that
has long battled brain drain, college towns
again are an exception. In Laramie, Wyoming,
home of the University of Wyoming, 40 percent
of adults have a college degree. College
towns are also comparatively cosmopolitan.
Students at Oklahoma State University come
from fifty states and 116 countries. Residents
of Stillwater, where Oklahoma State University
is located, are three times more likely than
Oklahomans in general to have been born
outside the United States.</p>

<p>The nature of higher education institutions
and the people associated with them give college
towns distinctive personalities. Most are
regional cultural centers, with the college
campus serving as the focus of such activity.
With their concert halls, theaters, museums,
sports stadiums, parklike landscapes, and
busy calendars of events, campuses serve not
only as environments for learning but also as
public spaces. At the University of Oklahoma
in Norman, for example, the Catlett Music
Center hosts concerts several nights a week.
Two campus art museums feature regular exhibits.
The university recently opened a thirty-eight-
million-dollar museum of natural history.
Millions of people visit Norman every
year to attend football games, an annual medieval
fair, and other campus events.</p>

<p>The university influence is also significant
off campus. Nearby shopping areas strongly
reflect the ever-changing tastes of young people
and the nonmainstream orientation of
many academics. In some college towns, such
as Manhattan and Norman, commercial districts
have developed next to campus that are
separate from the city's downtown. Certain
types of businesses tend to be unusually plentiful
in college town business areas: bookstores,
coffeehouses, T-shirt stores, bike shops, ethnic
restaurants, health food stores, and, most
conspicuously, bars. There are eighteen bars
in a six-block area of Manhattan's Aggieville
district.</p>

<p>The social differences that exist in college
towns have also led to the emergence of
distinctive residential landscapes. The large
number of students is marked by the high-rise
dorms of campus, the faux classicism of "fraternity
row" (for example, University Avenue
in Grand Forks, North Dakota), and the disheveled
rental houses of the "student ghetto"
(for example, Lawrence's Oread neighborhood).
Most college towns also have at least
one campus-adjacent neighborhood that is
home to concentrations of faculty and administrators.
Characterized by tree-lined streets
and stately homes, these neighborhoods were
often marketed directly to professors; in Norman,
one such subdivision was platted as Faculty
Heights.</p>

<p>College towns are also relatively unconventional
places. The sexual revolution first played
out in college towns as diverse as Lawrence,
which had an active gay rights organization
as early as 1970, and Chadron, home of tiny
Chadron State College, where a local theater
drew national attention in 1969 when it began
showing X-rated movies to a largely student
audience. Lawrence was a center of the 1960s
counterculture and, since that time, has maintained
its reputation for liberalism, once electing
a state representative known as "Marijuana
Mike," successfully fighting development of a
suburban shopping mall, and voting disproportionately
for left-leaning presidential candidates
like Ralph Nader. It has nurtured poets,
artists, musicians, and eccentrics. Suggestive of
the different character college towns possess in
a largely conservative region, a 1980s Lawrence
rock band penned a song paying tribute to the
distinctive nature of the Kansas college town. It
was entitled Berlin on the Plains.</p>


<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">EDUCATION</hi>: 
<ref n="egp.edu.021">Land-Grant Universities</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Blake Gumprecht<lb/>
University of South Carolina</signed>
</closer>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>