<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ii.026">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Frontier Violence</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Mark R. Ellis</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ii.026</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Ellis, Mark R.">Mark R. Ellis</author>. <title level="a">"Frontier Violence."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">387</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-09-29</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">FRONTIER VIOLENCE</head>

<p>When people think of nineteenth-century <geogName rend="region" reg="Great Plains">Great Plains</geogName> towns such as <placeName rend="settlement" key="ks.dc" reg="Dodge City, Kansas">Dodge City, Kansas</placeName>, <placeName rend="settlement" key="ne.oga" reg="Ogallala, Nebraska">Ogallala, Nebraska</placeName>, and <placeName rend="state" key="sd.dea" reg="Deadwood, South Dakota">Deadwood, South Dakota</placeName>, they often conjure up images of frontier violence. One image that comes to mind is of <persName reg="Dillon, Matt">Marshal Matt Dillon</persName>, with six-shooters drawn, facing an unruly cowboy on a dusty street in <placeName rend="settlement" key="ks.dc" reg="Dodge City, Kansas">Dodge City</placeName>. Someone else might imagine a pair of luckless horse thieves being dispatched by vigilantes in Ogallala. Still another image might be of the cowardly assassination of <persName reg="Hickok, James Butler (Wild Bill)">Wild Bill Hickok</persName> by <persName reg="McCall, Jack">Jack McCall</persName> in <placeName rend="settlement" key="sd.dea" reg="Deadwood, South Dakota">Deadwood</placeName>'s <placeName rend="saloon" key="sal.s10" reg="Saloon #10">Saloon #10</placeName>. Whatever the image, the overall picture is of a <geogName rend="region" reg="Great Plains">Great Plains</geogName> frontier where violence and disorder ruled the day. No other region of the <placeName rend="country" key="usa" reg="United States of America">United States</placeName> is given this distinction more than the <geogName rend="region" reg="Great Plains">Great Plains</geogName>.</p>

<p>Why do people perceive the American <geogName rend="region" reg="Great Plains">Great Plains</geogName> as violent? Nobody pictures the <geogName rend="region" reg="Canadian Plains">Canadian Plains</geogName> in the same manner. Instead of gunfighters, highwaymen, and vigilantes, images of the <orgName rend="law" key="law.nwmp" reg="North-West Mounted Police">North-West Mounted Police</orgName>, with their connotations of law and order, define the <geogName rend="region" reg="Canadian Plains">Canadian Plains</geogName>. The American <geogName rend="region" reg="Great Plains">Great Plains</geogName>, however, were never as violent as popular culture assumes. Since the publication of <persName reg="Dykstra, Robert">Robert Dykstra</persName>'s <hi rend="italic">The Cattle Towns</hi> (1968), scholars have begun, although not without protest, to chip away at the myth of a violent <geogName rend="region" reg="Great Plains">Great Plains</geogName>. <placeName rend="settlement" key="ks.dc" reg="Dodge City, Kansas">Dodge City</placeName>, as <persName reg="Dykstra, Robert">Dykstra</persName> points out, witnessed an average of only 1.5 homicides per year during its ten years as a cattle-trading center; it was hardly a town plagued by lethal violence. <placeName rend="settlement" key="ne.oga" reg="Ogallala, Nebraska">Ogallala, Nebraska</placeName>, the "cowboy capital" of the <placeName rend="state" key="ne" reg="Nebraska">Cornhusker State</placeName> and often described as the "Gomorrah of the trail," recorded only six killings during its ten years (1875–84) as an end-of-the-trail cattle town.</p>

<p>The driving force behind the creation of a violent <geogName rend="region" reg="Great Plains">Great Plains</geogName> has been the media: nineteenth- century newspapers, dime novels, and popular histories and twentieth-century television Westerns and Hollywood. Without the nineteenth-century media and dime novelists, the names of <persName reg="McCarty, Henry (Billy the Kid)">Billy the Kid</persName>, <persName reg="Earp, Wyatt">Wyatt Earp</persName>, <persName reg="Hickock, James Butler (Wild Bill)">Wild Bill Hickok</persName>, and <persName reg="Masterson, Bat">Bat Masterson</persName> would not be the cultural icons they are today. In 1867 <hi rend="italic"><orgName rend="publication" key="pub.hnmm" reg="Harper's New Monthly Magazine">Harper's New Monthly Magazine</orgName></hi> published an article on <persName reg="Hickock, James Butler (Wild Bill)">James Butler Hickok</persName>, better known as <persName reg="Hickock, James Butler (Wild Bill)">Wild Bill</persName>, and his <geogName rend="region" reg="Great Plains">Great Plains</geogName> exploits. This widely read article exaggerated <persName reg="Hickock, James Butler (Wild Bill)">Wild Bill</persName>'s prowess with a gun and the number of men he had killed. He quickly became a frontier hero and a popular subject of dime novelists who pushed the number of <persName reg="Hickock, James Butler (Wild Bill)">Hickok</persName> killings higher with each new publication; by the time of his death in 1876 he was credited with more than 100 killings. Thereafter, <persName reg="Hickock, James Butler (Wild Bill)">Hickok</persName> became a frontier icon, and the Kansas towns where he lived and worked&#8211;<placeName rend="settlement" key="ks.hay" reg="Hays, Kansas">Hays</placeName>, <placeName rend="state" key="ks.abi" reg="Abilene, Kansas">Abilene</placeName>, and <placeName rend="state" key="sd.dea" reg="Deadwood, South Dakota">Deadwood</placeName>&#8211;became ingrained in popular culture as places where lethal violence ruled.</p>

<p>Perhaps the most lethal of the <geogName rend="region" reg="Great Plains">Great Plains</geogName> towns, at least in popular culture, was <placeName rend="settlement" key="ks.dc" reg="Dodge City, Kansas">Dodge City</placeName>. Founded in 1872 and for more than ten years an end-of-the-trail cattle town, <placeName rend="settlement" key="ks.dc" reg="Dodge City, Kansas">Dodge City</placeName> became a favorite of eastern journalists. In 1878 the <hi rend="italic"><orgName rend="publication" key="pub.npg" reg="National Police Gazette">National Police Gazette</orgName></hi> published a story about a <placeName rend="settlement" key="ks.dc" reg="Dodge City, Kansas">Dodge City</placeName> shooting that introduced <persName reg="Earp, Wyatt">Wyatt Earp</persName> to the American public. In 1883 news reports about the "Dodge City War" (a nonlethal conflict) were picked up by the <orgName rend="newspaper" key="news.ap" reg="Associated Press">Associated Press</orgName>, sparking nationwide commentary on western lawlessness and confirming in the public mind that <placeName rend="settlement" key="ks.dc" reg="Dodge City, Kansas">Dodge City</placeName> was in fact the "Sodom of the West." During the twentieth century books such as <persName reg="Lake, Stuart N.">Stuart N. Lake</persName>'s <hi rend="italic"><persName reg="Earp, Wyatt">Wyatt Earp</persName>: Frontier Marshal</hi> (1931) and popular television Westerns such as <hi rend="italic">Gunsmoke</hi> kept <placeName rend="settlement" key="ks.dc" reg="Dodge City, Kansas">Dodge City</placeName> at the forefront of frontier iconography.</p>

<p>To be fair, the <geogName rend="region" reg="Great Plains">Great Plains</geogName> did experience its share of violence during the first few decades after the Civil War. The federal government fought wars against the <orgName rend="tribe" key="tri.com" reg="Comanche">Comanches</orgName> and <orgName rend="tribe" key="tri.kio" reg="Kiowa">Kiowas</orgName> on the Southern Plains and the <orgName rend="tribe" key="tri.ls" reg="Lakota Sioux">Lakota Sioux</orgName> and <orgName rend="tribe" key="tri.che" reg="Cheyenne">Cheyenne</orgName> on the <geogName rend="region" reg="Northern Plains">Northern Plains</geogName>. <persName reg="James Butler (Wild Bill), Hickok">Wild Bill Hickok</persName>, <persName reg="Masterson, Bat">Bat Masterson</persName>, and <persName reg="Earp, Wyatt">Wyatt Earp</persName> patrolled the <placeName rend="state" key="ks" reg="Kansas">Kansas</placeName> cow towns as armed lawmen. Gunmen, lawmen, and innocent bystanders were gunned down on the streets and in the saloons of <placeName rend="settlement" key="ks.dc" reg="Dodge City, Kansas">Dodge City</placeName>, <placeName rend="settlement" key="ne.oga" reg="Ogallala, Nebraska">Ogallala</placeName>, and <placeName rend="settlement" key="sd.dea" reg="Deadwood, South Dakota">Deadwood</placeName>. And vigilantes hanged and shot victims in every <geogName rend="region" reg="Great Plains">Great Plains</geogName> state and territory. The problem is that such violent incidents were episodic rather than epidemic and should not be used to define an entire region. The nineteenth-century <geogName rend="region" reg="Great Plains">Plains</geogName> were probably far less violent than the contemporary <geogName rend="region" reg="South">South</geogName> or eastern urban centers such as <placeName rend="settlement" key="ny.nyc" reg="New York City, New York">New York City</placeName>.</p>

<p>Despite the relatively undramatic historical reality of violence in the <geogName rend="region" reg="Great Plains">Great Plains</geogName> the public will always believe the myth. Hollywood will continue to make movies about the wild and violent <geogName rend="region" reg="The West">West</geogName>, popular writers will still produce fictional accounts of gunfighters and lawmen, and untrained historians will continue to define the region through the eyes of <persName reg="McCarty, Henry (Billy the Kid)">Billy the Kid</persName>, <persName reg="Hickok, James Butler (Wild Bill)">Wild Bill Hickok</persName>, and <persName reg="Earp, Wyatt">Wyatt Earp</persName>.</p>

<p><geogName rend="region" reg="Great Plains">Great Plains</geogName> communities also keep the idea of a violent <geogName rend="region" reg="Great Plains">Great Plains</geogName> alive and kicking through tourism. While driving across the <geogName rend="region" reg="Great Plains">Great Plains</geogName> travelers can visit dozens of Boot Hill cemeteries, including those in <placeName rend="settlement" key="ne.oga" reg="Ogallala, Nebraska">Ogallala</placeName> and <placeName rend="settlement" key="ks.dc" reg="Dodge City, Kansas">Dodge City</placeName>. <placeName rend="settlement" key="ks.abi" reg="Abilene, Kansas">Abilene, Kansas</placeName>, offers the Wild Bill Rodeo. In <placeName rend="settlement" key="sd.dea" reg="Deadwood, South Dakota">Deadwood, South Dakota</placeName>, tourists can compete in quick-draw contests at the annual Wild Bill Days or take a tour of <placeName rend="cemetery" key="cem.mmc" reg="Mount Moriah Cemetery">Mount Moriah Cemetery</placeName>, where <persName reg="Hickock, James Butler (Wild Bill)">Hickok</persName> is buried next to <persName reg="Calamity jane">Calamity Jane</persName>. At <placeName rend="settlement" key="ks.dc" reg="Dodge City, Kansas">Dodge City</placeName> visitors can stay overnight at the Boot Hill Bed and Breakfast while enjoying the annual Dodge City Days. It's hard to blame writers, producers, and <geogName rend="region" reg="Great Plains">Great Plains</geogName> towns for perpetuating the image of frontier violence. After all, <persName reg="Eastwood, Clint">Clint Eastwood</persName> will always sell more tickets at the box office as a mysterious gunslinger than as a <geogName rend="region" reg="Great Plains">Plains</geogName> sodbuster. It's good entertainment, and the public wants their myths and heroes to be left alone.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">CITIES AND TOWNS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ct.011">Cattle Towns</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">LAW</hi>: <ref n="egp.law.038">North-West Mounted Police</ref>.</p>


<closer>
<signed rend="right"><hi rend="italic">Mark R. Ellis<lb/>
University of Nebraska at Kearney</hi></signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1 type="ref">
<bibl>Dykstra, Robert R. <title level="m">The Cattle Towns</title>. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1968.</bibl> <bibl>Stansbery, Karyn. "<title level="a">The Law at the End of the Trail: Ogallala, 1873–1887</title>." <title level="j">Nebraska History</title> 79 (1998): 2–13.</bibl> <bibl>Udall, Stewart, Robert R. Dykstra, Michael A. Bellesiles, Paula Mitchell Marks, and Gregory Nobles. "<title level="a">How the West Got Wild: American Media and Frontier Violence</title>." <title level="j">Western Historical Quarterly</title> 31 (2000): 277–95.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>