<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.wat.026">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">River Compacts</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Norman W. Thorson</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.wat.026</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Thorson, Norman W.">Norman W. Thorson</author>. <title level="a">"River Compacts."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">860-861</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-29</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">RIVER COMPACTS</head>

<p>Interstate river compacts are used extensively
in the Great Plains to voluntarily apportion
interstate rivers among two or more states. In
addition, although the Canadian Constitution
does not provide for interprovincial compacts,
a series of four agreements collectively known
as the Prairie Provinces Water Apportionment
Agreement apportions water among Alberta,
Saskatchewan, and Manitoba. Regional rivers
subject to compacts, in whole or in part, include
the Arkansas, Belle Fourche, Big Blue,
Canadian, Niobrara, Pecos, Red, Republican,
and Platte in the United States, and the
Saskatchewan, Churchill, Assiniboine, and
Qu'Appelle in Canada.</p>

<p>With few exceptions, rights to use surface
waters, including the waters of interstate
streams, are created and administered under
state law. If interstate flows are not apportioned
among riparian states, interstate conflicts
over use are inevitable. The U.S. Supreme
Court has held that each riparian state
is entitled to an equitable share of a river's
flow. Thus an upstream state cannot, by virtue
of its geographical position alone, claim all of
the water that originates in, or flows through,
the state. A state that suffers actual injury as a
consequence of another state's water development
activities can bring a suit against the offending
state under the original jurisdiction
of the Supreme Court. Such suits, known as
equitable apportionment suits, ask the Court
to equitably divide the river among the competing
states. However, equitable apportionment
suits are costly, time-consuming, and
notoriously unpredictable. Moreover, they
can be pursued only after serious water conflicts
have arisen. In theory, interstate compacts
offer riparian states an opportunity to
negotiate an equitable distribution of a river's
benefits before serious conflicts develop.</p>

<p>An interstate river compact is in the nature
of a treaty among riparian states. The compact
limits the sovereign powers that each of the
compacting parties might otherwise exercise
over river flows within their borders. Although
some river compacts address issues such as
pollution, flood control, and water management,
the primary purpose of most river compacts
is to allocate flows among competing
states. Apportionment can limit consumption
in an upper state or mandate delivery to a
lower state. Given variations in annual flow,
the choice of method can be significant. Moreover,
the delivery obligation or the consumption
limitation can be stated on a volume basis
or as a mandated rate of flow. Compliance can
be measured annually or with reference to
multiyear averages. An unresolved issue in
most river compacts is whether groundwater
that is hydrologically linked to surface waters is
also subject to allocation or regulation under
the compact.</p>

<p>The process of negotiating a river compact is
deceptively simple and analogous to negotiating
a contract. Typically, the process begins
with Congress authorizing riparian states
to negotiate a compact, although nothing
prevents states from negotiating without a
congressional invitation. Participating states
appoint representatives to negotiate a draft
agreement. If state representatives reach agreement
on a draft text, the text is introduced as
legislation in each of the participating states.
States indicate their willingness to be bound by
compact terms by enacting the legislation. The
compact does not become a legally binding
document, however, until Congress ratifies it.
Congressional ratification is required by the
Compacts Clause of the U.S. Constitution. Apparently,
framers of the Constitution were
concerned that without such an approval
mechanism, groups of states might amass political
power at the expense of the federal government.
This concern is readily apparent with
respect to river compacts, given the significant
federal interest in interstate river systems.</p>

<p>The process of congressional ratification
transforms an interstate compact agreement
into federal law. As federal law, terms of the
compact preempt and supercede any inconsistent
provisions of state or local laws. With respect
to river compacts, any state water law
provisions that are inconsistent with terms of
the compact are preempted. Thus, state constitutional
provisions purporting to create unlimited
rights to divert and appropriate water
are, after compacting, limited to the share of a
river's flows that have been allocated to the
state in question. Apportionment of water by
compact also binds individual water users,
whether or not they were parties to the compact
negotiations, although many river compacts
provide that they have no effect on preexisting
water rights. On the other hand,
congressional ratification permits states to
reach agreements that would otherwise comprise
an unconstitutional interference with the
export of water to other states.</p>

<p>Compact commissions administer most
river compacts. Typically, each state will have
one or more voting representatives on the
commission. The federal government often
has a nonvoting representative. The precise
structure of the compact commission and the
powers that it can exercise are set forth in the
compact agreement. Commission powers can
be extensive or limited. One theoretical advantage
of compacts over litigation in apportioning
river benefits is that compacts can
provide for continuing administration to respond
to changed conditions or new facts developed
over time. In practice, however, most
river compacts give commissions little power
to respond to changed conditions. Typically,
commission powers and duties are limited to
data collection, compliance monitoring, and
report drafting.</p>

<p>In the absence of strong compact commissions,
enforcement of river compacts is typically
a matter for negotiated settlement or interstate
litigation. Suits between states for
breach of a compact obligation are within the
original and exclusive jurisdiction of the U.S.
Supreme Court. The Court may issue authoritative
interpretations of compact language,
order states to comply with terms of the agreement,
or award damages for past failures to
comply with terms of the agreement. Historically,
the Court has often expressed its preference
that states negotiate and compromise
their differences rather that resorting to litigation.
Many compacts specifically provide that
they can be amended, usually through a process
that requires formal state ratification and
congressional consent. Most also provide that
they can be terminated by unanimous consent
of the party states.</p>

<p>Recent litigation among Plains states has focused
on the extent to which interstate compacts
were intended to apply to groundwater
pumping. Developments in hydrology have
demonstrated that some groundwater sources
are linked hydrologically with surface water
flows. While a few compacts, such as the Kansas-
Nebraska Big Blue River Compact, specifically
address the impact of groundwater pumping
on surface water flows, most compacts are
silent about groundwater. The Arkansas River
Compact, for instance, makes no mention of
groundwater, but it does provide that future
water development may not materially deplete
river flows to the detriment of water users in
Colorado and Kansas. In <title>Kansas v. Colorado</title>
(1997), the U.S. Supreme Court upheld the contention
of Kansas that postcompact groundwater
pumping in Colorado had caused material
depletions of the usable state line flows
of the Arkansas River in violation of the compact.
Similarly, in ongoing litigation between
Kansas and Nebraska over use of water in the
Republican River basin, Kansas has alleged that
the Republican River Compact should be interpreted
as apportioning groundwater that is hydrologically related to the river flow, despite
the absence of specific language in the compact
that would mandate that result. Both
cases illustrate the difficulty of trying to reconcile
principles of modern hydrology with
agreements negotiated before groundwater.
surface water relationships were clearly
perceived.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Norman W. Thorson<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Grant, Douglas L. "Water Apportionment Compacts Between
States." In <title level="m">Waters and Water Rights</title>, edited by Robert
E. Beck. Charlottesville <hi rend="smallcaps">VA</hi>: Michie Law Publishers,
1996: 639–65.</bibl> <bibl>Muys, Jerome C. <title level="m">Interstate Water Compacts:
The Interstate Compact and Federal-Interstate Compact</title>.
Arlington <hi rend="smallcaps">VA</hi>: National Water Commission, 1971.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>