<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.lt.080">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">The Western</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Franz G. Blaha</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.lt.080</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Blaha, Franz G.">Franz G. Blaha</author>. <title level="a">"The Western."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">496-497</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-25</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">THE WESTERN</head>

<p>The Western, contrary to the mainstream
novel of the American West by authors like A.
B. Guthrie Jr., Ole R&#246;lvaag, Willa Cather, and
Edna Ferber, is a mass-produced subgenre of
popular literature rigidly defined by a formulaic
plot, conventional characters, and its setting
in the Old West, a semimythical place and
time in American history. Rather than describing
the settlers' psychological and spiritual relationship
to the land or giving a realistic picture
of a particular region of western America,
the Western is a nostalgic adventure novel,
drawing on the dialectic struggle between savagery
and civilization, law and lawlessness, and
East and West at an imaginary, epic moment
when the two opposing poles were believed to
be in a precarious balance. Thus the Western is
set predominantly in the Great Plains and in
the mountains and deserts of the Southwest
during the second half of the nineteenth century.
According to John Cawelti, the Great
Plains is a particularly appropriate setting for
the Western because of the region's openness,
its inhospitableness to human settlement, its
extremes of light and climate, as well as its
grandeur and beauty.</p>

<p>The Western traces its roots to the romantic
novels of James Fenimore Cooper, notably, his
Leatherstocking series, which deplores the relentless
eradication of the "savage but noble"
Native Americans through the onslaught of
European American civilization. This romantic
sympathy for the Native Americans soon
gave way to the crude juxtaposition of settler
and savage in the dime novels of the 1860s and
1870s such as Edward Ellis's <title level="m">Seth Jones; or, The Captives of the Frontier</title> (1860). In Edward L.
Wheeler's <title level="m">Deadwood Dick on Deck</title> (1878), set
in the Black Hills, Indians no longer exist even
as an opposing force.</p>

<p>The basic formula for the contemporary
Western derives from two sources: semifactual
accounts of the life of cowboys such as Andy
Adams's <title level="m">The Log of a Cowboy</title> (1903), a fictional
diary of a cattle drive from Texas through the
Great Plains to Montana, and Owen Wister's
<title level="m">The Virginian: A Horseman of the Plains</title> (1902).
Set in Wyoming in the 1870s, <title level="m">The Virginian</title>
introduced to the genre the cowboy hero, the
tenderfoot narrator, the Code of the West, the
climactic shootout, and the young schoolteacher
from the East who tries to civilize the
hero but ends up being converted to his Western
values in the end. <title level="m">The Virginian</title> was written
at a time when the frontier was declared
closed, when it became clear that American
society in the twentieth century would be inescapably
secular, urban, and industrial, when
gender roles were becoming increasingly
blurred, and when waves of immigration from
Europe began to change the ethnic composition
of the country. Wister's nostalgic glance
back at a time and place when these trends
might still have been reversed as well as his
admonition that the basic values of the Old
West must be preserved to guide the country in
the right direction struck a responsive chord in
a large segment of the population.</p>

<p>The result was countless formulaic imitations
of the basic ingredients of <title level="m">The Virginian</title>,
notably by Zane Grey, Max Brand (pen name
of Frederick Faust), Ernest Haycox, and Louis
L'Amour. Directing their novels initially at the
readers of pulp magazines, these writers reduced
the plot of <title level="m">The Virginian</title> to a heroic
adventure formula with a limited number of
variations: the conflict between ranchers and
settlers or between cattlemen and sheep men,
the story of the cowboy turned gunfighter, the
conflict between cavalry and Indians, adventures
accompanying the construction of the
transcontinental railroad, and the former
outlaw-turned-marshal haunted by his past,
all revolving around a love story. These "romantic"
Westerns reaffirm the dominance of
male-dominated western values such as monogamous
love, instinctive rather than institutional
Christianity, a patriarchal family
structure, and the justified use of violence in
defense of these values. Females are civilizers
and therefore initially hostile to this code of
behavior, but they are always converted to accepting
the male view in the end. Thus Wister's
attempt to represent the allegorical forces
vying for dominance in a future American society
was reduced to a formulaic erotic struggle
between a western male and an eastern
female.</p>

<p>This nostalgic fantasy of the victory of male
western values became more and more unsustainable
as the vision of the Old West was
blurred by the counterimage of contemporary
urban, industrial society. In the 1950s the tone
of the Western became darker and more cynical,
the young cowboy heroes giving way to
jaded older men, mainly sheriffs and marshals,
confronted with an apathetic population,
increasingly organized villains, and more
ambiguously virtuous women. The optimistic
"myth of foundation" of the romantic Western
gave way to the "myth of transition," the
need to save what could be saved of traditional
western values in a modern world that has lost
its way. This view is mainly expressed in the
classic Western films of the period, notably
<title level="m">High Noon</title> (1952), <title level="m">Shane</title> (1953, based on the
novel by Jack Schaefer), John Ford's <title level="m">The Man Who Shot Liberty Valance</title> (1962), and <title level="m">Cheyenne Autumn</title> (1964, based on the novel by
Mari Sandoz).</p>

<p>In the second half of the twentieth century
the classic formula of the Western came under
pressure from the counterculture of the 1960s
and the revisionist New Western historians.
Minority groups and women began to claim
their rightful place in western popular fiction,
and former heroes of the West were now cast in
the role of villains, as can be seen in Thomas
Berger's <title level="m">Little Big Man</title> (1964) and the 1990 film
<title level="m">Dances with Wolves</title>.</p>

<p>Although the traditional popular Western
has been in decline in print, in film, and on
television after its heyday in the 1950s, it is too
early to pronounce it moribund, as some commentators
have done recently. If anything, the
Western is moving away from its formulaic,
ultraconservative past to become a part of the
more sensitive, diverse mainstream of literature
about the American West, as evidenced by
the novels of Larry McMurtry (<title level="m">Leaving Cheyenne</title>,
1962; <title level="m">Lonesome Dove</title>, 1985) and Elmer
Kelton (<title level="m">The Day the Cowboys Quit</title>, 1971; <title level="m">The Man Who Rode Midnight</title>, 1987). But for aficionados
of the more formulaic Westerns,
there are the excellent, historically well-researched
Plains Western series of Terry C.
Johnston (some thirty novels in his Plainsman
series), Richard S. Wheeler (his Barnaby Sky
series, which focuses on Plains Indian cultures),
Tabor Evans (the prolific author of the
Longarm series), and Harry Combs to ensure
the continued viability of the most American
of literary genres.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">FILM</hi>: <ref n="egp.fil.016"><hi rend="italic"><title>Dances with Wolves</title></hi></ref>; <ref n="egp.fil.064">Westerns</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Franz G. Blaha<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Cawelti, John G. <title level="m">The Six-Gun Mystique</title>. Bowling Green
<hi rend="smallcaps">OH</hi>: Popular Press, 1971.</bibl> <bibl>Durham, Philip, and Everett L.
Jones. <title level="m">The Western Story: Fact, Fiction, and Myth</title>. New
York: Harcourt Brace, 1975.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>