<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.ind.027 SYSTEM "egp.ind.027.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ind.027">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Headbolt Heater</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Andrew L. Freeman Jr.</author>
<author>David J. Wishart</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ind.027</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Freeman, Jr., Andrew L.">Andrew L. Freeman Jr.</author> and <author n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</author>. <title level="a">"Headbolt Heater."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">421</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-02</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">HEADBOLT HEATER</head>

<figure n="egp.ind.027" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Advertisement for the Headbolt Heater</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Without a doubt, necessity was the mother of
invention in the case of the headbolt heater&#8211;
necessity and an enterprising man. The necessity
was getting a car to start in the frigid
North Dakota winter; the man was Andrew
Freeman, an electrical engineer who, as general
manager of Minnkota Power Cooperative,
brought electricity to the rural areas of
North Dakota.</p>

<p>The year was 1947, and Freeman, like everyone
else in Grand Forks, found that even if he
succeeded in getting his car running, it took so
much out of the battery that soon the engine
was dead. He started experimenting with devices
that would heat the engine of his <hi rend="smallcaps">V</hi>-8
Ford. At first, using scrap copper tubing as
inserts and a ribbon wire heating element
from an old flatiron, he devised a method of
heating the two hoses that went from the bottom
of the radiator to the engine block. On a
thirty-degree morning he attached the heating
elements to an electrical cord, plugged it in,
waited for two hours, and immediately started
the engine. Unfortunately, when Freeman
tried to install his invention on a neighbor's
Plymouth, he found that it did not work; nor
was it successful on another neighbor's Chevrolet.
So he thought again.</p>

<p>Freeman concluded that he needed a way to
get heat directly to the water in the engine
block. He discovered that in most cars the
headbolts extended directly into the water. After
much experimentation over a period of
three years, Freeman developed a system that
transmitted electricity via a brass tube through
a replaced headbolt into the water. The electric
lead extended from the heater through the radiator
grill to the outlet.</p>

<p>In 1947, with two colleagues, Freeman
formed the Five Star Manufacturing Company
of East Grand Forks to manufacture
headbolt heaters. The company did not do
well at first, not least because there was a manufacturing
error in the first 25,000 heaters. But
soon the product was refined and the manufacturing
process mechanized until the company
was turning out 200,000 heaters a year
for sale in the United States and Canada. Altogether
Freeman estimates that he sold as
many as two million headbolt heaters.</p>

<p>Eventually, other types of tank and plug
heaters took over, and improvements in engine
design diminished their general necessity.
Still, engine heaters continued to go by
the name "headbolt heaters," which is testimony
to the lasting legacy of Andrew Freeman's
invention.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Andrew L. Freeman Jr.<lb/>
Bemidji, Minnesota<lb/>
David J. Wishart<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>McCutchon, Beverly. <title level="m">Reflections: Andrew Freeman, 1909– 1996</title>. Grand Forks <hi rend="smallcaps">ND</hi>: Minnkota Power Cooperative, Inc.,
1996.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>