<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ea.017">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Icelanders</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Bill Holm</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ea.017</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Holm, Bill">Bill Holm</author>. <title level="a">"Icelanders."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">235-236</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-04</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">ICELANDERS</head>

<p>About one-quarter of Iceland's small population,
already shrunken by famine, disease, and
volcanic disaster, immigrated to the middle
of the North American continent in the last
three decades of the nineteenth century. Since
they left a treeless place where the only real
crop was native grass, the landscape of the
Great Plains seemed less strange and forbidding
to them than to the many immigrants
who had left more temperate wooded places
on the European continent. Icelanders expected
harsh and lengthy winters in the New
World, and of course the Great Plains fulfilled
those expectations. The torrid summers surprised
but did not delight them. In Iceland the
temperature seldom rose above 60&#186;F.</p>

<p>In the Old Country, these immigrants had
been mountain sheep farmers and, on the
coast, fishermen, egg gatherers, and seabird
catchers. In good years they ate salt fish,
smoked mutton, and hard tack. Though they
did harvest the native grasses, they had never
planted a crop, tasted pork, or seen a gathering
of more than three or four cows at a time
(and those usually old milkers).</p>

<p>The earliest immigrants located in Spanish
Fork, Utah, and Washington Island in Lake
Michigan, but the great bulk of the 16,000 immigrants
moved to the Great Plains. In the
United States they settled on farms in Lyon
and Lincoln Counties in western Minnesota,
the terminus of the railroad in 1875. A few
years later they colonized the northeastern
counties of North Dakota (then Dakota Territory),
settling mostly around Mountain and
Cavalier on the old shore of Lake Agassiz at
the western edge of the Red River Valley.</p>

<p>The bulk of the Canadian immigration, beginning
in 1873, went north of Winnipeg to
the interlake country, where the Canadian
government had established New Iceland. The
harsh climate and infertility of the district
soon promoted a migration to better land in
the North Dakota settlements, to Glenboro
and Brandon in Manitoba, to Wynyard in central
Saskatchewan, and finally, in 1888, to
Markerville, Alberta, eighty miles north of
Calgary. Some Icelanders continued west to
the Pacific, establishing settlements between
Seattle, Washington, and Vancouver, British
Columbia, but most seemed more comfortable
with long views, grass, and wind. Winnipeg,
to this day, boasts the largest concentration
of Icelanders in any city outside
Reykjavik.</p>

<p>By the beginning of the twentieth century,
the immigration was substantially complete. A
half dozen towns and districts in the Great
Plains had assumed an Icelandic identity, and
the countryside there was populated by families
with names like Gislason, Gottskalkson,
and Thorbjornsson. The Icelanders were unusual
among immigrants in their literacy and
their devotion to books and learning. Hardly
an immigrant chest, no matter how poor the
owner, was without the Icelandic sagas and
a handful of favorite Icelandic poets. As the
generations passed, the Icelanders sent their
children off to university&#8211;an unattainable
dream in the Old Country&#8211;where they became
mostly lawyers, judges, teachers, and
journalists, sometimes of great distinction.
The Icelanders preferred such vocations to
business or farming. Vilhjalmur Stefansson,
born in 1878 in New Iceland, left North Dakota
to become one of the most famous Arctic explorers
of the twentieth century, but even he is
best remembered for the quality of his prose.</p>

<p>This small immigrant community's great
legacy to the Plains is to have produced three
of the best Icelandic poets of the twentieth
century. They all lacked formal schooling but
were well-read men of the laboring class, one a
hired man, the other two farmers. K. N. Julius
(1860–1936) of Mountain, North Dakota, was
the first light-verse satirist in modern Icelandic:
many of his humorous poems describe
immigrants' struggles with English. Guttormur
Guttormsson (1878–1966) of Riverton,
Manitoba, was a panegyrist in Old Icelandic
poetic forms of Canadian nature. And Stephan
G. Stephansson (1859–1927) of Markerville,
Alberta, considered by Icelanders to be
one of the giants of their literature, was a great
innovator in language and a profound philosophical
thinker. All three wrote in their beloved
Icelandic but greeted their neighbors in
accented English. In the subsequent generations,
Icelandic, like all immigrant languages,
steadily evaporated in the New World. The
descendants of these great poets must now
read them in translation. Still, their works
stand on as monuments to the Icelandic heritage
in the Great Plains.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Bill Holm<lb/>
Minneota, Minnesota</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Arnason, David, and Vincent Arnason, eds. <title level="m">The New Icelanders</title>.
Winnipeg: Turnstone Press, 1994.</bibl> <bibl>Palmer, Howard.
"Escape from the Great Plains: The Icelanders in
North Dakota and Alberta." <title level="j">Great Plains Quarterly</title> 3
(1983): 219–33.</bibl> <bibl>Walters, Thorstina. <title level="m">Modern Sagas: The Story of the Icelanders in North America</title>. Fargo: North
Dakota Institute for Regional Studies, 1953.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>