<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.na.090">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Poundmaker (ca. 1842-1886)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>F. Laurie Barron</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.na.090</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Barron, F. Laurie">F. Laurie Barron</author>. <title level="a">"Poundmaker (ca. 1842-1886)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">594</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-15</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">POUNDMAKER (ca. 1842-1886)</head>
<figure n="egp.na.090" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Poundmaker, a leader of the Plains Cree First Nation (Image courtesy of the National Archives of Canada, C-001875)</figDesc>
</figure>
    
<p>Poundmaker, whose Indian name was <hi rend="italic">P&#299;tikwahanapiw
&#299;yin</hi>, was born around 1842. The
son of an Assiniboine Indian and a mixed-blood
mother of French descent, he was a
member of a prominent Plains Cree family
from the House Band in what today is central
Saskatchewan.</p>

<p>Poundmaker was destined to become an influential
leader. In 1873 he was adopted by
Crowfoot, head chief of the powerful Blackfoot
nation of southern Alberta. This happened
during a brief truce in the wars between
the Crees and the Blackfoot, when Poundmaker
visited Crowfoot's camp for the first
time. One of Crowfoot's wives, who was grieving
the loss of a son in battle, was struck with
Poundmaker's resemblance to her dead son
and prevailed upon the chief to adopt the Cree
as a replacement. For his part, Crowfoot was
greatly impressed with Poundmaker's statesmanlike
bearing and commitment to peacemaking,
and so he readily agreed. The adoption
invested Poundmaker with the attributes
of a Blackfoot family member; it bestowed new
wealth on him in the form of horses gifted by
his adoptive family; and it conferred upon him a
new Blackfoot name, <hi rend="italic">Makoyi-koh-kin</hi> (Wolf
Thin Legs). When Poundmaker returned home,
he was accorded special standing because of
his personal connection to a nation that traditionally
had been an enemy of the Crees.
Within a few years he was elevated to the rank
of a councilor, or minor chief, in the River
People Band led by Chief Red Pheasant.</p>

<p>Poundmaker proved to be a strong critic of
government policy. In 1876, during the negotiation
of Treaty Number 6 at Fort Carlton, he
took exception to the very notion of confining
Indians to reserves. "This is our land!" he protested
to the government commissioners. "It
isn't a piece of pemmican to be cut off and
given in little pieces back to us." He also insisted
that the terms offered did not provide
adequately for agricultural assistance or for
famine relief during hard times. He eventually
signed the treaty but remained resistant to
taking up reserve life. In 1878, when Red Pheasant
agreed to move onto a reserve, Poundmaker
formed his own band and made a lastditch
effort to hunt down the few remaining
buffalo. A year later he and his starving band
accepted a reserve some forty miles west of
Battleford, Saskatchewan. Although he made
efforts to master farming, he nevertheless remained
a determined critic of the government,
which routinely ignored both Indian
treaty rights and the starvation that stalked the
reserves.</p>

<p>Owing to circumstances beyond his control,
Poundmaker was implicated in the North-
West Rebellion of 1885. Like most Indian leaders,
he did not want to join the disaffected
Metis who had clashed with government forces
at Batoche and elsewhere. While he was known
to criticize government policy and the deplorable
conditions on reserves, his main aim was
to achieve reform through peaceful means,
particularly the renegotiation of Treaty 6.
However, soon after the outbreak of hostilities,
Poundmaker progressively lost control over
his camp, which came to include dissident
Metis and a number of Assiniboines who had
murdered a farm instructor. At Battleford he
was unable to prevent his warriors from looting
homes and offices that had been abandoned
when the occupants fled for protection
to the police barracks nearby. Later, Poundmaker's
authority was preempted by his band's
warrior society, which, at Cut Knife Hill, Saskatchewan,
resisted an assault by government
forces led by Lt. Col. William Dillon Otter.
Throughout these events Poundmaker cautioned
restraint and took steps to protect prisoners.
He is also credited with preventing the
warriors from inflicting heavy losses on Otter's
troops as they retreated in disarray.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, Poundmaker was blamed by a
government determined to cripple Indian society
by removing its leadership. He was subjected
to a humiliating surrender at the hands
of Gen. Frederick Dobson Middleton, placed
on trial in 1885 for treason, and sentenced to
three years in Stony Mountain Penitentiary,
Manitoba. He was granted early release in 1886
but died of tuberculosis four months later, on
July 4, while visiting Crowfoot. Initially buried
at Blackfoot Crossing, Alberta, his remains
were reinterred at Cut Knife Hill in 1967.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">WAR</hi>: <ref n="egp.war.032">North-West Rebellion</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>F. Laurie Barron</signed>
University of Sasketchewan</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Jefferson, Robert. <title level="m">Fifty Years on the Saskatchewan</title>. Battleford,
Saskatchewan: Canadian North-West Historical
Society, 1929.</bibl> <bibl>Sluman, Norma. <title level="m">Poundmaker</title>. Toronto:
McGraw-Hill Ryerson Ltd., 1967.</bibl> <bibl>Stonechild, Blair, and
Bill Waiser. <title level="m">Loyal till Death: Indians and the North-West
Rebellion</title>. Calgary: Fifth House Ltd., 1997.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>