<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ag.056">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Rye</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Dale Reevers</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ag.056</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Reevers, Dale">Dale Reevers</author>. <title level="a">"Rye."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">49</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-12-18</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">RYE</head>

<p>Rye (<hi rend="italic">Secale cereale</hi> L.) is one of the small
grains grown in the Great Plains. It is a winter
annual, planted in the fall, and is the hardiest
of the small grains. Rye does well in cool climates
(optimum temperature 55&#186;F to 65&#186;F)
and tolerates most adverse weather. It is often
grown on light, sandy soil, when weed problems
are present or when the soil is low in
fertility. The major disease problem is ergot,
a fungus that replaces kernels with a hard,
black growth. Rye grain is similar to wheat in
size and composition but is lower in protein.
Bread made from only rye is a small, dark,
compact loaf, so in North America it is generally
blended with wheat to produce a loaf that
is more acceptable to the consumer.</p>

<p>Due to its hardiness, winter rye is commonly
grown in the northern parts of the
Great Plains. Rye was never the dominant
crop, and acreage of rye has declined over the
course of the twentieth century. In Saskatchewan,
for example, the leading rye-producing
province in Canada, acreage fell from 1.2 million
in 1921 to 225,000 in 1993. In Saskatchewan,
North Dakota, and South Dakota (generally
the leading rye producer in the United
States), the crop is grown for its grain.</p>

<p>In general, acreage and production decreases
southward down the Great Plains. In
1992, South Dakota had 55,000 acres under
rye, Nebraska 17,384 acres, and Kansas 6,993.
In Oklahoma and Texas, rye is planted for two
purposes. First, it provides ground cover during
the winter and reduces erosion and loss of
nutrients by leaching. Second, rye provides
considerable winter grazing for cattle. Very little
of this rye is harvested for grain.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Dale Reevers<lb/>
South Dakota State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>