<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ind.042">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Nuclear Waste Sites</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Diane A. Burton</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ind.042</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Burton, Diane A.">Diane A. Burton</author>. <title level="a">"Nuclear Waste Sites."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">427-428</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-04</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">NUCLEAR WASTE SITES</head>

<p>The search for disposal sites for nuclear wastes
in the United States has often turned to the
Great Plains region; there have been no nuclear
waste disposal siting efforts in the Canadian
Great Plains. Nuclear waste is generated
within the Great Plains by way of activities
ranging from nuclear power generation to
medical treatment. There are three nuclear
power generating plants operating within the
Great Plains: Cooper Nuclear Station and Fort
Calhoun Station in Nebraska and Wolf Creek
Generating Station in Kansas. Each of these
serves as a storage location for spent nuclear
fuel and low-level radioactive waste (<hi rend="smallcaps">LLRW</hi>).
The Rocky Flats Nuclear Weapons Plant, located
sixteen miles northwest of Denver, manufactured
components for nuclear weapons
until 1992 but is now scheduled for decommissioning,
waste disposal, and environmental
cleanup. Many of the universities in the
Great Plains dispose of the llrw generated
by their research activities at locations on
campus.</p>

<p>There are three main classifications for nuclear
waste in the United States: high level, low
level, and transuranic. The different waste
forms are defined not only by the composition
of the material making up the waste but
also by the manner by which it is generated
(commercial or defense) as well as by whether
the federal or state government is responsible
for regulating its disposal. High-level and
transuranic wastes are defined by the specific
composition of the wastes; low-level radioactive
waste is defined by what it is not&#8211;high-level
waste. Each of these wastes is regulated
by different laws. Providing disposal capacity
for high-level and transuranic wastes is a federal
government responsibility; providing disposal
capacity for low-level wastes is the responsibility
of the state in which the wastes are
generated. High-level and transuranic wastes
require underground, deep-geologic disposal;
disposal of low-level waste is allowed above
ground and in shallow-burial trenches.</p>

<p>The first government-sponsored nuclear
waste disposal siting effort was in the Great
Plains, conducted by the U.S. Atomic Energy
Commission. Underground disposal of highlevel
and transuranic wastes was investigated
in the Lyons, Kansas, area in 1970. By 1972 it
was determined that the salt mines of the
Lyons area did not meet acceptable requirements
for the isolation of the waste. Subsequently,
an area east of Carlsbad, New Mexico,
was identified for consideration in 1974. Dismayed
by the slow progress in developing disposal
capacity, Congress created the Waste
Isolation Pilot Project (<hi rend="smallcaps">WIPP</hi>) in 1979, directing
that a safe method for the disposal of
wastes generated by defense facilities be developed.
The <hi rend="smallcaps">WIPP</hi> continued to focus on salt
formations near Carlsbad. Following eight
years of studying the geology and hydrology
of the area, construction of the wipp facility
began in 1983; the underground construction
was completed in 1989. In May 1998 the Environmental
Protection Agency announced
that the <hi rend="smallcaps">WIPP</hi> met all applicable federal nuclear
waste disposal standards. The <hi rend="smallcaps">WIPP</hi> began
receiving transuranic waste in March
1999.</p>

<p>Prior to 1980, <hi rend="smallcaps">LLRW</hi> disposal was primarily a
market-driven business. In that year Congress
mandated that the states were responsible for
providing disposal capacity for <hi rend="smallcaps">LLRW</hi> generated
within their borders. States were encouraged
to band together and form compacts to
address this mandate. In 1983 three states of
the Great Plains&#8211;Nebraska, Kansas, and Oklahoma&#8211;
joined with Louisiana and Arkansas
to form the Central Interstate Low-Level
Radioactive Waste Compact. The compact selected
U.S. Ecology, Inc., to site, develop, and
operate a disposal site for the member states.
In December 1987 Nebraska was designated
the host state for a disposal site. Approximately
one year later, three 320-acre candidate
sites in Nebraska were identified for detailed
evaluation. These sites were in Boyd, Nemaha,
and Nuckolls Counties. Following the designation
of the candidate sites, U.S. Ecology discovered
and acknowledged a problem with
wetlands (over forty-six acres) on the Boyd
County site. Nevertheless, in December 1989
the Boyd County site was selected as the preferred
site. An application to construct and
operate a waste disposal site was filed in July
1990 with the Nebraska Department of Environmental
Quality (<hi rend="smallcaps">NDEQ</hi>). In January 1993
the ndeq issued an intent to deny a license
because the site did not meet regulatory requirements,
the presence of wetlands being
the primary reason. Six months later, in an
effort to eliminate the wetland problem, U.S.
Ecology submitted an amended application
for a 110-acre parcel of the original site. Following
extensive review and evaluation of that
application and after public hearings, the
ndeq in August 1998 again issued an intent to
deny the license. By December 1998 a final
denial was made because the proposed site
lacked sufficient depth to the water table and
groundwater discharged to the surface within
the site. In 1999 Nebraska formally withdrew
from the Central Interstate Low-Level Radioactive
Waste Compact, a move that resulted in
continued litigation. After twelve years and
over $90 million spent, the effort to site, construct,
and operate a low-level waste disposal
site in Nebraska had not been successful.</p>

<p>There has been organized opposition by
citizens living in the areas surrounding all of
the proposed nuclear waste disposal sites.
Likewise, there has been organized local support
for the various siting efforts.</p>

<p>While no nuclear waste disposal sites were
operating in the Great Plains at the end of 1998,
the <hi rend="smallcaps">WIPP</hi> began operations in 1999. Additionally,
there are continued efforts to establish
low-level waste disposal sites. In 1993 Sequoyah
Fuels Corporation of Oklahoma began seeking
authorization to dispose of low-level wastes
generated during the operation of its uranium
conversion plant and its decommissioning at
the Gore, Oklahoma, plant site. Waste Control
Specialists of Texas, starting in 1995, has been
pursuing authorization to include disposal of
low-level wastes at a hazardous waste disposal
site in Andrews County, Texas.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Diane A. Burton<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>