<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.na.047">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Indian Removal</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Clara Sue Kidwell</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.na.047</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Kidwell, Clara Sue">Clara Sue Kidwell</author>. <title level="a">"Indian Removal."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">577-578</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-15</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">INDIAN REMOVAL</head>

<p>The policy of the U.S. government to move
Native Americans from their homelands to
other locations was part of the clash of cultures
brought about by the colonization of
North America. There was no such policy of
forcible removals from east to west in Canada;
even within the Prairie Provinces, First Nations
were given considerable choice in the
selection of their reserves. U.S. policy was formalized
in the Indian Removal Act of 1830,
which gave President Andrew Jackson the authority
to make treaties with tribes by which
they would exchange land east of the Mississippi
River for lands to the west. By that
time, however, removals had been taking place
for more than two decades.</p>

<p>President Thomas Jefferson initiated the
idea of removal with the Louisiana Purchase
in 1803. He saw a new western territory where
Native Americans could live their traditional
lifestyles far removed from often deleterious
contact with Americans. The rationale was
that moving Native Americans to this Permanent
Indian Frontier would open up land in
the eastern United States for European American
settlers, while protecting them until such
time as they were willing and able to assimilate
into American society. Jefferson also believed
that consolidating Native Americans in the
Great Plains would create a barrier that would
prevent American settlers from dispersing too
widely. In the 1820s and 1830s, Baptist missionary
Isaac McCoy even campaigned to create
a separate Indian state in the Great Plains,
where Native Americans could be taught the
precepts of American civilization, but the idea
did not receive serious attention in Congress.</p>

<p>As early as 1808 the Sauks and Foxes moved
voluntarily from Illinois to Missouri to escape
the disruption of their lives by white settlers.
From 1817 to 1820 federal agents signed treaties
with the Delawares in Ohio and the Kickapoos
and Weas in Illinois by which the tribes agreed
to exchange their lands for others in Illinois
and Missouri. By 1817 leaders of the Cherokees
in Georgia had agreed to a treaty that provided
individual allotments for those who
agreed to be citizens of the state and remain
on their land, or a tract of land west of the
Mississippi for those who chose to move. The
Choctaws signed a similar treaty in 1820. Removal
policy led to divisions within tribes between
those who agreed to stay in their homelands
and adapt to new ways and those who
decided to move west and try to retain their
cultural identities. Even before formal legislation
for Indian removal, some Choctaw and
Cherokee families were moving west of the
Mississippi to settle on lands guaranteed to
them by treaty.</p>

<p>By the time of Andrew Jackson's election to
the presidency in 1828, the prospect of ridding
the east of Native Americans appealed greatly
to land speculators, and Jackson's strong sense
of nationalism led him to reject the idea that
tribes could exist as sovereign nations within
the confines of American territory. Within ten
years of the passage of the Indian Removal
Act, vast areas of the Midwest and the southeastern
United States had been "cleared" and
the Native American residents removed to
tracts of land in the present-day states of Kansas
and Oklahoma.</p>

<p>North of the Ohio River a great variety of
Native American communities were shifted
west. These included Peorias, Kaskaskias,
Sauks and Foxes, Piankashaws, Weas, Shawnees,
Ottawas, Wyandottes, Potawatomis, Delawares,
and Kickapoos. Many of these groups
suffered multiple removals. The Delawares, for
example, were originally from eastern Pennsylvania.
They subsequently moved to Ohio,
Illinois, Missouri, and, in 1829, to Kansas. The
Kickapoos also ended up in eastern Kansas in
1832, after first being moved from southern
Ohio and then from southwestern Missouri.
By 1841 emigrant Native Americans occupied
squared-off tracts along the eastern portions of
the Great Plains from present-day Nebraska to
Texas. They were settled on land that was purchased
from Indigenous Plains tribes, such as
the Pawnees and Kaws, and frequently conflicts
ensued between the emigrants and the
local Native Americans.</p>

<p>Major removal treaties were also negotiated
with the southeastern tribes. The Choctaws
signed the Treaty of Dancing Rabbit Creek in
1830, in large part because the state of Mississippi
extended its laws over the tribe and
made illegal the operations of the tribal government.
The state of Georgia also sought to
regulate the Cherokees. The Creeks, Seminoles,
and Chickasaws signed treaties in 1832,
and the Cherokees signed the Treaty of New
Echota in 1835. As a result of these treaties,
approximately 60,000 members of these tribes
made the trek west to the land designated as
Indian Territory in the eastern half of what is
now Oklahoma. For the Creeks, Seminoles,
and Cherokees, these were forced marches under
the U.S. Army. It is estimated that approximately
one-quarter of the refugees died along
the trail from illness, exposure, or starvation.</p>

<p>After 1854 the tide of European American
settlement reached the Great Plains, and the
Permanent Indian Frontier fragmented into
reservations, where Indigenous Plains peoples
and emigrant tribes were segregated and
placed under great pressure to acculturate. In
the following three decades, as their reservations
were surrounded by settlers, many of
these Indians, including the Pawnees, Poncas,
Cheyennes, Arapahos, Comanches, Potawatomis,
and Kickapoos, made their final migration
to Indian Territory, where many of their
descendants remain today.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Clara Sue Kidwell<lb/>
University of Oklahoma</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Abel, Annie H. "The History of Events Resulting in Indian
Consolidation West of the Mississippi." In <title level="m">Annual Report
of the American Historical Association for the Year 1906</title>.
Washington <hi rend="smallcaps">DC</hi>: Government Printing Office, 1908.</bibl> <bibl>Foreman,
Grant. <title level="m">Indian Removal: The Emigration of the Five
Civilized Tribes of Indians</title>. Norman: University of Oklahoma
Press, 1953.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>