<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.na.085">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Plains Apaches</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Alfred Chalepah Sr.</author>
<author>Irene Poolaw</author>
<author>Houston Klinekole Sr.</author>
<author>Pamela Innes</author>
<author>Deborah Bernsten</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.na.085</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Chalepah, Sr., Alfred">Alfred Chalepah, Sr.</author>, <author n="Poolaw,Irene">Irene Poolaw</author>, <author n="Klinekole, Sr., Houston">Houston Klinekole, Sr.</author>, <author n="Innes, Pamela">Pamela Innes</author>, and <author n="Bernsten, Deborah">Deborah Bernsten</author>. <title level="a">"Plains Apaches."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">591-592</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-15</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">PLAINS APACHES</head>

<p>According to our legends, we, the Plains
Apaches or Apache Tribe of Oklahoma, have
been here since time began. Our earliest oral
histories record our existence with the Sarcees
(Sarsis) in Canada. These same histories mention
that we split from the Sarcees and established
ourselves in the Black Hills of South Dakota.
At that time, we were known as K&#225;&#322;t'inde,
"Cedar People." This name was given to us by
some other tribe. At that time, the Lakotas
granted us the territory south of the Black Hills,
while they took the territory to the north. We
began to make our way to the south, hunting the
bison.</p>

<p>Because of the second name our people
were given, our elders believe we must have
been very proficient hunters. We again came
to be known by our former name, Bek'áhe, or
‘‘Whetstone,'' given to us by another tribe.
Our elders believe this came about because we
were always honing our knives in order to
butcher the many bison our hunters killed.
The sign for our people, to this very day, is
the sign of honing—moving the outside of the
right hand back and forth over the thumb side
of the left hand. Today we are known in our
own language as N&#225;'ish&#261;, "Stealers or Takers."
We were given this name by the Kiowas, with
whom we have long been closely associated.
It seems that we got this name because of
our ability to steal horses in the prereservation
period.</p>

<p>We also have had multiple English names.
We were first known as the Kiowa Apaches.
Our elders believe this name was given to us in
order to distinguish us from the Fort Sill
Apaches. After the 1867 Treaty of Medicine
Lodge Creek, we shared the Kiowa Reservation
with the Kiowa and Comanche people. In 1894
the U.S. Army brought a number of Chiricahua
Apaches to Fort Sill. At that time, it became
necessary to distinguish us from the Fort
Sill Apaches. Because we had been closely associated
with the Kiowas, we became known as
the Kiowa Apaches. The name Plains Apache
was given to us by anthropologists and government
officials. This name stems from our location
and our mobile lifestyle.</p>

<p>We came to this area of the country by wandering
with the bison, moving south from the
Dakotas. We traveled on the eastern side of the
Rocky Mountains, into the Southern Plains.
We traveled throughout the Plains, from the
northern reaches of the Missouri River to
Chihuahua, Mexico. We traded extensively,
bartering buffalo hides, salt, and meat for produce
and other goods. Through trade, we established
peaceful relationships with a number
of other tribes, including the Pawnees,
Arapahos, and Kiowas. Our people preferred
trading to raiding for goods, but we were not
passive when hostilities occurred.</p>

<p>Warfare and raiding allowed men to gain
power and prestige. To become leaders, men
were expected to have outstanding character.
The leaders were honest, understanding, level-headed
men who had shown valor in war or
had distinguished themselves as providers.
Our tribe was governed by chiefs, a council of
elders, warriors, and medicine people. When a
man appeared to hold the qualities that made a
good chief, the warriors would suggest that the
council consider him for that position. If the
council agreed with the warriors, the man was
made a chief. Occasionally, sons or grandsons
would inherit their father's or grandfather's
positions, but only if the young man had the
qualifications. If a chief abused his position
or acted irresponsibly, he could be run off or
killed.</p>

<p>Women also were important in N&#225;'ish&#261; society.
While women did not hold positions of
power, they were in charge of maintaining
many of the family possessions. Women were
responsible for making and repairing the tipis
and all items associated with them. Gathering
of plant foods and, occasionally, small game,
were women's activities as well. Special skill in
tipi sewing, clothing decoration, and food location
and preparation was recognized by induction
into women's societies, which had
their own dances and songs.</p>

<p>Today, we are recognized as the Apache
Tribe of Oklahoma. This name was established
in 1972 when the Kiowa, Comanche,
and Apache tribes officially separated. While
each tribe had run its own tribal affairs previously,
we all had been supervised by the Bureau
of Indian Affairs. Upon establishing our
independence in 1972, we became an entity
separate from the other two tribes, with our
own tribal name and government. Government
officers are elected in general elections.
There are approximately 1,600 enrolled tribal
members. The majority of tribal members live
in Caddo and Comanche Counties in Oklahoma.
Our tribal offices are located in Anadarko,
Oklahoma.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Alfred Chalepah Sr.</signed>
<signed>Irene Poolaw</signed>
<signed>Houston Klinekole Sr.</signed>
<signed>Apache Tribe of Oklahoma</signed>
<signed>Pamela Innes</signed>
<signed>Deborah Bernsten</signed>
<signed>University of Oklahoma</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Bittle, William. Fieldnotes. Apache Tribe of Oklahoma
Culture Office, Anadarko, Oklahoma. Chalepah, Alfred
Sr., Irene Poolaw, and Houston Klinekole Sr. Oral histories.
Apache Tribe of Oklahoma Culture Office, Anadarko,
Oklahoma.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>