<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.mus.008">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Classical Music</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Bruce Lobaugh</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.mus.008</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Lobaugh, Bruce">Bruce Lobaugh</author>. <title level="a">"Classical Music."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">534-535</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-02</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">CLASSICAL MUSIC</head>

<p>On the Great Plains frontier, classical music
may seem to have disappeared from the milieu
of settlers, and of course its presence was very
much diminished. However, traces of its existence
could be found in the instruction books
and other material to be played on parlor
organs (some of which were to be found in the
sod structures of the Plains) or to be used in
piano instruction for children, an early feature
of the settlement era. Private classical instruction
in other instruments and voice followed
in many communities. A basis for the
classical tradition also existed almost immediately
in the music of many religious services.
Often shortly after the arrival of the railroad,
in some localities church choirs were formed
that undertook the performance of anthems
reflecting the classical tradition if not actually
being composed by Handel or Haydn. Eventually,
in larger communities, building on the
church choir tradition (which still continues),
choral societies were formed that presented
oratorios. Denver's Musical Union (1867) is
among the earliest of these societies. About
the same time, the development of independent
concert orchestras began. Often consisting
of about twenty members, many of these
efforts had an ephemeral existence, lasting
sometimes for only one or two concerts or
perhaps a season before the development of
more durable organizations that in turn may
have been dissolved themselves during times
of depression or war.</p>

<p>The approach of the twentieth century saw
the appearance of classical selections on the
programs of the many wind bands of the era.
Verdi and Wagner were particularly popular,
and of one ensemble, that of Frederick Innes,
it was said in Omaha in 1898 that "there is but
one Wagner, and Innes is his prophet."</p>

<p>With the establishment of railroads came
the appearance of touring artists at communities
along the line. Before the turn of the
twentieth century and after, artists such as
Madam Albani, Madam Melba, the Mendelssohn
Quintette Club, the Metropolitan Opera,
the Theodore Thomas Orchestra, and many
others made their way to larger centers in the
Great Plains. In some cases these appearances
were sponsored by local musical societies,
many of which are still important in the musical
life of communities. In addition, there are
over seventy concert agencies that offer classical
artists to the public.</p>

<p>Before the middle of the twentieth century,
universities began to play an important part,
which still continues, in the public presentation
of classical music, either through their
own series of guest or faculty artists or the
performance of their campus ensembles such
as choirs, orchestras, and wind groups. Most
composers of the region have, during this
time, become situated at universities. Almost
universally, school systems offer experience
and instruction in classical music, both vocal
and instrumental, to students, as do many
hundreds of private instructors.</p>

<p>Prominent artists who have their origins in
the region include clarinetist James Campbell
(Leduc, Alberta), tenor Jon Vickers (Prince
Albert, Saskatchewan), bass Samuel Ramey
(Colby, Kansas), composers Roy Harris (Lincoln
County, Oklahoma) and Howard Hanson
(Wahoo, Nebraska), and composer-critic
Virgil Thomson (Kansas City, Missouri).
Thomson said of his compositions written
during his years abroad: "I wanted Paris . . . to
understand the ways we like to think and feel
on the banks of the Kaw and the Missouri."
Orchestral works reflecting the attributes of
the region include Sowerby's <title>Prairie</title> (1929)
and Thomson's soundtrack to the film <title>The Plow That Broke the Plains</title> (1936).</p>

<p>Well over fifty independent symphony orchestras
are to be found in the region as well
as thirty orchestras maintained by colleges or
universities that in some cases include community
members. Ten of the orchestras&#8211;the
Calgary Philharmonic and the Edmonton
Symphony in Alberta; the Winnipeg Symphony
in Manitoba; the Colorado Symphony
(Denver) and Colorado Springs Symphony
in Colorado; the Omaha Symphony in Nebraska;
the Kansas City Symphony in Missouri;
the Wichita Symphony in Kansas; and
the Oklahoma Philharmonic and Tulsa Philharmonic
in Oklahoma&#8211;have budgets in excess
of $1 million. Many communities also
support wind ensembles over and above those
sponsored by educational institutions. In
more recent times, youth orchestras independent
of educational institutions have been
formed in several larger centers.</p>

<p>Choral ensembles presently flourish in considerable
number either independently, associated
with a symphony orchestra, as a community
function of universities or colleges, or
as an ensemble exclusively for students. A
number of independent children's choruses
are also active. Fifteen professional ballet or
dance companies presently operate in the region.
Larger centers often possess concert facilities
specifically designed for classical music
such as the Jack Singer Concert Hall in Calgary,
the Boettcher Concert Hall in Denver,
and the Century II Concert Hall in Wichita.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Bruce Lobaugh<lb/>
Omaha, Nebraska</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>American Symphony Orchestra League, Washington <hi rend="smallcaps">DC</hi>.
<title level="m">1998–99 North and Central American Directory</title>. New York:
Amateur Chamber Music Players, 1998.</bibl> <bibl><title level="m">Musical America International Directory of the Performing Arts</title>. Hightstown
<hi rend="smallcaps">NJ</hi>: Primedia Information, 1998.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>