<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.med.034">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Nye, Bill (1850-1896)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Charles Vollan</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.med.034</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Vollan, Charles">Charles Vollan</author>. <title level="a">"Nye, Bill (1850-1896)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">518</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-30</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">NYE, BILL (1850-1896)</head>

<p>Edgar Wilson "Bill" Nye was born on August
25, 1850, in Shirley, Maine. His family moved
to Wisconsin when he was two years old. Nye
attempted farming and teaching but was unsuccessful.
He also studied law but did not
pass the bar in Wisconsin. Leaving Wisconsin
in 1876, he made his way to Laramie City, Wyoming
Territory, where he worked as a reporter
for the <title level="j">Laramie Sentinel</title>. Nye next began
a two-year stint as editor of the <title level="j">Laramie Boomerang</title>, a newspaper named after his unpredictable
mule. His satirical editorials and
feature stories soon spread his fame far beyond
Wyoming.</p>

<p>In addition to his work as an editor, Nye
passed the Wyoming bar and practiced law.
He also served as justice of the peace, U.S.
commissioner, and U.S. postmaster. In 1877 he
married Clara Francis Smith, and together
they had seven children. He published two
works while living in Wyoming, <title level="m">Bill Nye and Boomerang</title> (1881) and <title level="m">Forty Liars and Other Lies</title> (1882). In 1883 spinal meningitis forced
him to seek healthier surroundings. Following
a short recuperative period in Greeley, Colorado,
Nye returned to his childhood home of
Hudson, Wisconsin.</p>

<p>In 1885 Nye began a second career as a platform
lecturer. He was wildly successful, rivaling
Mark Twain in popularity. He delivered
his humorous lectures, sometimes alone and
sometimes with other humorists such as James
Whitcomb Riley, until his death in 1896. He
was soon a household name, and his gangly,
bald figure, familiar through both the lecture
circuit and the humorous illustrations included
throughout his books, made him a particularly
well-known celebrity.</p>

<p>Nye continued to write throughout his career
as a lecturer, his style becoming progressively
more refined and containing less of the
jocular humor that had been in vogue during
the previous decades and that reads poorly
today. In 1887 he published <title level="m">Bill Nye's Remarks</title>,
and in 1888 he and his longtime partner, Riley,
published <title level="m">Nye and Riley's Railway Guide</title>, their
take on the popular railroad guides of the era.
In 1887 Nye returned to regular newspaper
work when he became a writer for the Sunday
edition of the <title level="j">New York World</title>. He moved to
New York City in that year, remaining there
until 1891, when his newspaper columns became
syndicated in seventy newspapers.</p>

<p>With his health still frail from spinal meningitis,
Nye left New York City for Asheville,
North Carolina. He continued writing and
lecturing, producing his two best-known
works, <title level="m">Bill Nye's History of the United States</title>
(1894) and <title level="m">Bill Nye's History of England from the Druids to the Reign of Henry VIII</title> (1896).</p>

<p>A gentle wit, Nye himself was often the
focus of his jokes. Regretfully, he also adopted
the prejudices of his day. He specialized in
lampooning the self-important, including
politicians and recent arrivals to the Plains
from back east. Although he spent less than
ten years in the Plains, the experience proved
to be central to his writings. Nye adopted the
western love of play on words, exaggeration,
and a sense of pragmatism. In early 1896 Nye
suffered a series of strokes that finally took his
life on February 22 at his home near Asheville,
North Carolina.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Charles Vollan<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Keterson, David B. <title level="m">Bill Nye: The Western Writings</title>. Boise
<hi rend="smallcaps">ID</hi>: Boise State University Press, 1976.</bibl> <bibl>Nye, Frank Wilson,
ed. <title level="m">Bill Nye: His Own Life Story</title>. New York: Century Company,
1926.</bibl>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>