<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ii.019">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Dodge City, Kansas</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Robert R. Dykstra</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ii.019</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Dykstra, Robert R.">Robert R. Dykstra</author>. <title level="a">"Dodge City, Kansas."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">383&#8211;384</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-09-22</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">DODGE CITY, KANSAS</head>
<figure n="egp.ii.019" rend="granted" type="noclick">
<figDesc>1879 photograph of Dodge City, Kansas</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Untold millions have formed their views of the Old West from American movies and television series. The global popular culture spawned by Hollywood now includes an unassailable belief that the region was uniquely murderous, and no locale holds more importance in this popular belief than frontier <placeName rend="settlement" key="ks.dc" reg="Dodge City, Kansas">Dodge City, Kansas</placeName>.</p>

<p>Today the name of the town that flourished as a <placeName rend="state" key="tx" reg="Texas">Texas</placeName> cattle market from 1876 to 1885 is widely employed as a cultural metaphor for homicide, anarchy, and depravity. Yet only fifteen adults died violently in <placeName rend="settlement" key="ks.dc" reg="Dodge City, Kansas">Dodge</placeName> during its cowboy years. In two livestock seasons and probably a third, no adults died violently, and only once did the annual number reach as high as five.</p>

<p>But before becoming a cattle town Dodge had served as a center for the buffalo-hide trade. During its first year its governmental organization was tied up in court. Lacking formal law enforcement, <placeName rend="settlement" key="ks.dc" reg="Dodge City, Kansas">Dodge</placeName> suffered sixteen to nineteen violent deaths. By mid-1873, however, its county had been organized and a sheriff elected. Not until 1878 is another adult homicide known to have occurred. By then lawmen headquartered there consisted of a deputy U.S. marshal, a sheriff, an undersheriff, as many deputy sheriffs as needed, a city marshal, an assistant marshal, as many policemen as needed, and two town constables. This formidable deployment and the enforcement of gun control largely explain the low body count.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, the anarchy of <placeName rend="settlement" key="ks.dc" reg="Dodge City, Kansas">Dodge</placeName>'s first year lived on in the popular imagination, kept alive by dispatches to eastern newspapers by visitors. <placeName rend="settlement" key="ks.dc" reg="Dodge City, Kansas">Dodge</placeName>'s own lawyer-journalist, <persName reg="Gryden, Harry">Harry Gryden</persName>, also exploited its notoriety in such magazines as <placeName rend="settlement" key="ny.nyc" reg="New York City, New York">New York</placeName>'s <hi rend="italic">Police Gazette</hi>. He proved instrumental in creating the media attention that made <persName reg="Earp, Wyatt">Wyatt Earp</persName> and <persName reg="Masterson, Bat">Bat Masterson</persName> celebrities. During the "Dodge City War" (1883), news stories printed in the <placeName rend="settlement" key="il.chi" reg="Chicago, Illinois">Chicago</placeName>, <placeName rend="settlement" key="ny.nyc" reg="New York City, New York">New York</placeName>, and other eastern papers reinforced Dodge's national image as the "Sodom of the West."</p>

<p><persName reg="Gryden, Harry">Gryden</persName> died in 1884, but <placeName rend="settlement" key="ks.dc" reg="Dodge City, Kansas">Dodge</placeName>'s business community carried on in his spirit, hosting the first "genuine Spanish bullfight" held on American soil&#8211;a stunt eliciting moral outrage and news coverage from around the nation. It also formed the Dodge City Cowboy Band, professional musicians masquerading as off-duty cowhands who played to enthusiastic audiences in <placeName rend="settlement" key="mo.stl" reg="Saint Louis, Missouri">St. Louis</placeName>, <placeName rend="settlement" key="il.chi" reg="Chicago, Illinois">Chicago</placeName>, and <placeName rend="settlement" key="mn.min" reg="Minneapolis, Minnesota">Minneapolis</placeName>. But with the end of the Texas cattle trade, <placeName rend="settlement" key="ks.dc" reg="Dodge City, Kansas">Dodge</placeName>'s fame declined.</p>

<p>Popular writers occasionally renewed <placeName rend="settlement" key="ks.dc" reg="Dodge City, Kansas">Dodge</placeName>'s name recognition in such mass-circulation journals as <hi rend="italic">Everybody's Magazine</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Saturday Evening Post</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Time</hi>. But it was the publication of <persName reg="Lake, Stuart N.">Stuart N. Lake</persName>'s bestseller <hi rend="italic">Wyatt Earp: Frontier Marshal</hi> (1931) that proved decisive in transforming <placeName rend="settlement" key="ks.dc" reg="Dodge City, Kansas">Dodge</placeName> into a modern tourist destination, a position it has retained to the present. Beginning with the movie <hi rend="italic">Dodge City</hi> (1939), a number of films collaborated with this effort. More influential was the long-running (1955-75) television series <hi rend="italic">Gunsmoke</hi>, which gave rise to the metaphoric <placeName rend="settlement" key="ks.dc" reg="Dodge City, Kansas">Dodge</placeName> among U.S. service personnel in <placeName rend="country" key="vn" reg="Vietnam">Vietnam</placeName>: to "get out of <placeName rend="settlement" key="ks.dc" reg="Dodge City, Kansas">Dodge</placeName>" meant to vacate a dangerous area.</p>

<p>The public perception of Dodge seems unchanged today. Probably of most continuing influence has been "Bloody Dodge City" (1992), an episode of the <hi rend="smallcaps">TV</hi> series <hi rend="italic">The Real West</hi>. The program emphasized violence and ignores the old cattle town's paltry body count. A combination of national media attention and the town's energetic self-promotion ensures that the Dodge of myth and metaphor is here to stay.</p>

<closer>
<signed rend="right"><hi rend="italic">Robert R. Dykstra<lb/>
Worcester, Massachusetts</hi></signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1 type="ref">
<bibl>Christian, Shirley. "<title level="a">Where Wyatt Earp Stood Tall</title>." <title level="j">New York Times</title>, January 17, 1999.</bibl> <bibl>Dykstra, Robert R. <title level="m">The Cattle Towns</title>. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1968.</bibl> <bibl>Dykstra, Robert R. "<title level="a">Imaginary Dodge City: A Political Statement</title>." <title level="j">Western Historical Quarterly</title> 31 (2000): 278–84.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>