<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.na.091 SYSTEM "egp.na.091.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.na.091">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Powwows</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Kenton Bales</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.na.091</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Bales, Kenton">Kenton Bales</author>. <title level="a">"Powwows."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">594-595</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-15</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">POWWOWS</head>

<figure n="egp.na.091" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Powwow at Potawatomi Indian Agency, Kansas, ca. 1920</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>The word powwow is derived from the Narragansett
language and refers to a gathering of
Native people for the purpose of singing, dancing,
celebration, and socialization. It consists
of ceremonies, dance competitions, and social
dancing. Many are large, annual events and
have well-established reputations, such as
those held in Calgary, Denver, and Oklahoma
City. Powwows are characterized by the use of
one or more groups of singers, which are called
"drums," and the wearing of elaborate regalia
during the dance portions of the event. The
style of music and dance that has become standardized in many Great Plains powwows is
termed "intertribal" because it is a hybridization
of dance and music from several Native
American groups. Powwows vary in size from
giant affairs attended by people from a wide
variety of locations on the North American
continent, to small, local gatherings where the
population of one community is the primary
audience.</p>

<p>The history of the event demonstrates its dynamic
nature. During the first part of the twentieth
century, there was a great deal of interaction
among Native peoples due to relocation
on reservations and through increased availability
of transportation technology such as the
railroad. Native peoples maintained cultural
identity by preserving traditional music and
dance styles. Participation in World War I,
World War II, and the Korean War gave Native
American men who might have been members
of warrior societies among their own people
the opportunity to become active warriors. Traditional
dances were held and songs were composed
to honor these men. By 1955 there was a
great deal of interest in artistic exchange among
tribal groups in the Great Plains, who continued
to celebrate their warrior societies
through song and dance, especially in
Oklahoma. These songs and dances were
shared with members of neighboring tribes,
and an amalgamation of musical and dance
traits resulted that led to the contemporary intertribal
powwow.</p>

<p>When these intertribal celebrations began,
they did not possess the common elements that
can be found today. Although there is still a
large amount of variation in format, competition,
and participation, many powwows in the
Great Plains have an overall form that is predictable
and understood by all participants.
This form includes a wide variety of events held
for specific reasons and, in many cases, in a
specific order.</p>

<p>The most impressive event of the contemporary
powwow is the Grand Entry, the first part
of any dance session. During this time, all dancers
who are to compete enter the powwow
arena in a specified order. After the Grand Entry,
a special ceremony usually takes place that
includes the singing of a Flag Song and, sometimes,
an Honor Song. After the songs the master
of ceremonies may introduce important
people at the event, and a prayer is frequently
offered. This might be followed by a speech
from a dignitary, such as the powwow princess
or a visiting politician. During all of this ceremony,
the dancers stand quietly in the powwow
arena. At its close, the emcee usually calls for an
intertribal dance, so that everyone may participate.
Several such dances may occur before the
competitions begin.</p>

<p>Competition dancing is divided into categories
according to the type of songs performed
by the drum (the singing group), the type of
dance steps and regalia worn by the contestants,
and the contestants' ages. Men's categories
usually include traditional and fancy
dancers. Women are divided into traditional,
fancy, and jingle dress dancers. All categories
are further classified by age into adult, junior,
and tiny tot divisions. Awards for the competitions
are presented for dancing technique, such
as stopping on the correct foot with the last
beat of the drum and appropriate composure
during the entire powwow. Prizes may include
cash, trophies, and a wide variety of material
objects such as blankets, rifles, food, or household
items.</p>

<p>A great diversity of music may be heard at
any given powwow. Some of the musical styles
include the Omaha dance, social dance, and
intertribal. Songs are not improvised but are
composed by singers who teach them to other
members of the drum. These songs are then
dispersed among the population through performance
at powwows and through recordings.
Songs have appropriate drumbeats that accompany
them, including the parade beat, the
Omaha beat, the social dance beat, accent or
honor beats, and the drum roll. Each of these
beats is distinctive, and aficionados will know
immediately by the drumbeat which type of
song is being performed. The speed of the beat
varies according to the type of dance and the
style of the drum. Distinctive differences exist
between Northern Plains and Southern Plains
styles, and these include a faster beat in the
north and a slower beat in the south. These
differences sometimes make it impossible for a
northern-style dancer, for example, to compete
while a southern-style drum is playing. For this
reason, international drums often perform at
powwows in a neutral style so that dancers
from both the northern and southern traditions
may compete simultaneously.</p>

<p>Competitions are the main focus of the powwow
for some participants, but other types of
activities occur at various points during the
event. Giveaways are common, and intertribal
and special dances are interspersed throughout
the affair, giving noncompetitive dancers a
chance to participate. Raffles are frequently
held to raise money in support of the event or
to help sponsor the next powwow. After the
formal portion of the powwow, young dancers
often get together in the late evening for a
round of "forty-nine dances." The informal nature
of the forty-nines contrasts with the relatively
rigid structure of the other powwow
dances. This is a time for celebration among the
young adults who participate often into the
early hours of the morning.</p>

<p>Contemporary powwows play an important
role in the social and cultural life of Native
Americans. They are a celebration of heritage
and tradition that has survived in a unique
form apart from the daily lives of the participants.
Powwows engender a sense of community
and belonging among the people who participate,
and those who are on the powwow
circuit look forward to making new acquaintances
and renewing old friendships as much as
to the singing, dancing, and competitions. Music
and dance are natural media for dissemination
of cultural information because they are so
visible, and powwows and recordings of powwow
songs disperse important features of Native
American culture not only among Native
American communities but also among members
of other communities.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">SPORTS AND RECREATION</hi>: <ref n="egp.sr.012">Crow Fair</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Kenton Bales</signed>
University of Nebraska at Omaha</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Horse Capture, George P. <title level="m">Powwow</title>. Cody <hi rend="smallcaps">WY</hi>: Buffalo Bill
Historical Center, 1989.</bibl> <bibl>Powers, William K. <title level="m">War Dance:
Plains Indian Musical Performance</title>. Tucson: University of
Arizona Press, 1990.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>