<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.na.010">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Astronomy</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Patricia J. O'Brien</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.na.010</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="O'Brien, Patricia J.">Patricia J. O'Brien</author>. <title level="a">"Astronomy."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">566-567</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-03</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">ASTRONOMY</head>

<p>Like all humans, the Native peoples of the
Plains observed the sky, particularly the night
sky, and created astronomies. Scholars have
used three general methods to describe and
understand pre-European astronomies in
North America: an examination of myth; archeological
data, including astronomical artifacts;
and detailed ethnographic and historic
studies of specific peoples.</p>

<p>In Blackfoot myth, for example, the Pleiades
were small boys who became stars when
their parents would not give them yellow buffalo
calf robes. Very young calves have yellow
hides in May or June, when the Pleiades are
not visible, but become dark around September
when the Pleiades reappear.</p>

<p>Archeology was used by Waldo Wedel to
identify astronomies, when he proposed that
"council circles" in central Kansas might be
solstice registers. These types of data include
the well-known medicine wheels, including
Wyoming's Big Horn Medicine Wheel. Such
sites are also common in the Northern Great
Plains and the Prairie Provinces. The most
important is the Moose Mountain Medicine
Wheel in Saskatchewan, which is aligned to
the summer solstice sunrise. Nearby, others
mark the rising of the major summer stars:
Aldebaran, Rigel, and Sirius.</p>

<p>One of the most important astronomical
artifacts is the Skiri Pawnee star chart, drawn
on a buffalo scalp and associated with the Big
Black Meteoric Star bundle and ceremony.
This star is associated with the northeast star
pillar position and the color black. It has been
proposed that its position is a point north of
the celestial pole, a definite black spot in the
heavens. The chart seems to be a pictograph of
the night sky with key stars and constellations
recorded.</p>

<p>Von Del Chamberlain's elegant analysis of
the cosmology of the Pawnees is one of the
most brilliant ethnographic studies of Native
American astronomy. Chamberlain identifies
major constellations in Pawnee astronomy,
pointing out that they structured the world
around the four cardinal, and especially semicardinal,
positions. Morning and Evening
Stars are associated with the east and west, and
there are North and South Stars and four star
pillar positions: the Northeast, Northwest,
Southwest, and Southeast. Identifying the particular
stars in the heavens with these positions
is difficult, but one association is clear:
Polaris is the North Star. Chamberlain outlines
the problems of identifying the Morning
and Evening Stars with the planets, but he settles
on Mars and Venus, respectively. The sun
and moon are also linked: the Sun is Morning
Star's younger brother and the Moon is Evening
Star's little sister. The semicardinal positions&#8211;
the star pillars holding up the earth
lodge roof and cosmologically the universe.
have several interpretations, including that
they refer to no celestial bodies. One view sees
them linked to planets: Mercury (red) to the
Southeast, Saturn (yellow) to the Northwest,
and Jupiter (white) to the Southwest. Northeast
is a problem, because its color is black and
there is no black star. Another view sees them
as the stars along the ecliptic, representing
Spica (Southwest), Antares (Southeast), Aldebaran
(Northwest), and Regulus (Northeast).
A final interpretation has them as the
brightest stars: Capella (Northwest), Sirius
(Southwest), Vega (Northeast), and Antares
(Southeast).</p>

<closer>
<signed>Patricia J. O'Brien<lb/>
Kansas State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Chamberlain, Von Del. When Stars Came Down to Earth.
Los Altos <hi rend="smallcaps">CA</hi>: Ballena Press, 1982.</bibl> <bibl>Wedel, Waldo R. "The
Council Circles of Central Kansas: Were They Solstice
Registers?" <title level="j">American Antiquity</title> 32 (1967): 54–63.</bibl> <bibl>Wilson,
M. N. "Blackfoot Star Myths—The Pleiades." <title level="j">The American Antiquarian</title> 15 (1893): 149–50.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>