<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.pe.047">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Physiography</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Michael D. Blum</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.pe.047</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Blum, Michael D.">Michael D. Blum</author>. <title level="a">"Physiography."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">636-637</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-22</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">PHYSIOGRAPHY</head>

<p>The Great Plains, as defined in Nevin M. Fenneman's
classic work, <title level="m">Physiography of Western
United States</title> (1931), is a distinct physiographic
region that lies between the Rocky Mountains
to the west and the Canadian Shield, Central
Lowlands, and Gulf Coastal Plain regions to
the east, and stretches from the Canadian
Prairies in the north to the Edwards Plateau in
Texas. Although broadly described as a low
relief part of the North American interior, the
Plains landscape is complex and diverse and
owes its origin to a variety of geologic processes,
with specific subregions dominated by
fluvial, eolian, volcanic, or glacial landforms.
This diversity is best discussed with reference
to traditionally recognized subregions.</p>

<p>The High Plains, stretching from Nebraska
to Texas, can be thought of as the core of the
Great Plains in terms of its geologic history, its
current morphological expression, and the
perception of a vast featureless landscape. The
High Plains's surface is constructional in origin,
representing the accumulation of fluvial
sediments of Tertiary age that were shed from
the Rockies in a series of west-to-east trending
river valleys and alluvial plains, with coeval
eolian (wind-blown) sediments blanketing the
uplands. Following this accumulation phase,
major rivers that rise in the Rockies (Platte,
Arkansas, Canadian, Pecos), plus rivers that
originate on the High Plains surface (Niobrara,
Republican, Smoky Hill, Cimarron,
Red), cut distinct valleys through this former
accumulation surface and formed a series of
downward-stepping terraces. Erosionally isolated
remnants of the High Plains include
Scotts Bluff and Chimney Rock National Monuments,
located along the North Platte River in
Nebraska, that have long served as landmarks
for travelers moving westward. Outside of the
major river valleys, eolian and other processes
dominate the relatively undissected parts of
the High Plains surface. The most notable
eolian landscape is the Nebraska Sandhills, the
largest sand dune field in the Western Hemisphere.
Individual dunes can be more than 300
feet in height and extend for many miles. Although
the dunes are now grass-covered, they
have been active multiple times during the last
few thousand years when regional climates
were drier. At the southern end of the High
Plains in Texas, on the Llano Estacado, thick
accumulations of wind-blown sediments cover
Tertiary fluvial deposits and have produced a
flat landscape, one that is punctuated by tens of
thousands of mostly dry lake basins, or playas,
and a series of narrow ephemeral stream channels
that are locally referred to as draws.</p>

<p>The northern boundary of the High Plains
is defined by the Pine Ridge Escarpment, with
three key Great Plains physiographic subregions
lying farther to the north. Just north
of the High Plains, the Unglaciated Missouri
Plateau of eastern Montana, eastern Wyoming,
and the western Dakotas consists of broad tablelands
where the Tertiary cover has been
mostly stripped by the Missouri River and its
tributaries. The tablelands are punctuated by
a number of isolated mountain ranges and
areas of deeply dissected badlands topography
where the Tertiary cover is still present. Several
mountain ranges in Montana (Highwood,
Bearpaw, Little Rocky, Judith, Big Snowy, Big
Belt, Little Belt, Castle, and Crazy) originated
as masses of intrusive and/or volcanic igneous
rock. The best examples of badlands topography
are the White River Badlands of Badlands
National Park in South Dakota and the Little
Missouri Badlands of Theodore Roosevelt National
Park in North Dakota. The eastern
boundary of the Missouri Plateau is defined by
the Missouri Escarpment, where the landscape
descends 500 to 650 feet to the glaciated Central
Lowlands. The Black Hills of western
South Dakota are often treated as a distinct
subregion. They originated as a folded and
thrusted mass of ancient sedimentary and
crystalline rocks similar to, and geologically
related to, the Rockies farther west. The presidential
faces on Mount Rushmore National
Memorial are carved in granites that make up
the core of this mountain range, whereas Wind
Cave and Jewel Cave were formed by dissolution
of the tilted limestones that encircle the
crystalline core. Devils Tower National Monument
is a near-vertical erosional remnant of an
igneous intrusion on the western periphery of
the Black Hills in Wyoming.</p>

<p>Farther north and east are the Glaciated Interior
Plains of northeastern Montana, northern
and eastern North Dakota, and eastern
South Dakota in the United States and Alberta,
Saskatchewan, and Manitoba in Canada.
For this encyclopedia, the northern limits
of the Great Plains in Canada have been defined
on the basis of a biogeographic boundary,
the Parkland Belt, which roughly corresponds
to the Manitoba Escarpment on the
east-northeast and the North Saskatchewan
River valley on the north. Within this part of
the Glaciated Interior Plains, remnants of Tertiary
fluvial sediments shed from the Rockies
form prominent topographic features, including
the Hand Hills and Swan Hills of western
Alberta, the Cypress Hills of southern Saskatchewan,
Wood Mountain in southern Saskatchewan,
northern Montana, and northern
North Dakota, and Turtle Mountain in southern
Manitoba and northern North Dakota.
Elsewhere, the landscape is mostly underlain
by sedimentary rocks of Cretaceous age and
bears the imprint of the numerous glaciations
of the Pleistocene Ice Ages, especially the most
recent glaciation that ended 10,000 to 12,000
years ago. Accordingly, Cretaceous rocks are
mostly covered by glacial sediments and landforms,
and the landscape is flat to gently rolling
with numerous shallow internally drained
depressions, scattered low-relief hills, and narrow
incised river valleys that originated as
meltwater channels. The Red Deer River valley,
east of Calgary, Alberta, is an example of a
former meltwater channel, with postglacial
dissection having created the extensive badlands
topography that is best known for the
fossils discovered at Dinosaur Provincial Park.
The numerous glacial advances have also disrupted
and diverted the preglacial drainage in
the region, so that major rivers that originate
in the Canadian Rockies, like the North Saskatchewan
and South Saskatchewan, used to
flow to Hudson Bay and the Arctic Ocean, but
now flow into remnants of large glacial lakes
in Manitoba. At an even grander scale, the
upper Missouri River used to flow out of
Montana and North Dakota to Hudson Bay as
well, but it was diverted southeast by the glaciers
to join the Mississippi River and flow to
the Gulf of Mexico.</p>

<p>The western margins of the High Plains remain
connected to the Rockies only along the
Gangplank of southeastern Wyoming and along
a short reach between Denver and Colorado
Springs, which forms the divide between the
Platte and Arkansas River drainages. Elsewhere,
the Colorado Piedmont lies between the High
Plains and the Front Range of the Rockies, at
elevations distinctly lower than the High Plains
surface, and consists of a series of river terraces
on which major urban centers of Colorado
(Colorado Springs, Denver, and Fort Collins)
have developed. These terraces represent
former floodplain levels of the South Platte and
Arkansas Rivers and their principal Rocky
Mountain tributaries and were formed as they
cut down through and removed the old High
Plains's surface and its underlying Tertiary
fluvial deposits. In many places, terrace surfaces
and the surrounding dissected bedrock landscape
are covered by small sand dune fields as
well. The Raton Section, straddling the border
between Colorado and New Mexico, lies between
the High Plains and the Rockies and is a
landscape dominated by recent volcanic activity,
with volcanic rocks covering Tertiary
fluvial deposits and older sedimentary rocks.
Prominent features include lava-capped tablelands
such as Raton Mesa and Mesa de Maya
and a variety of volcanic peaks. Capulin Volcano
National Monument, for example, rising almost
1,000 feet above the surrounding landscape, is
a cinder cone volcano that erupted between
10,000 and 4,000 years ago. Farther south, the
broad Pecos Valley lies between the Sangre de
Cristo Range of the Rockies and the Mescalero
Escarpment, which defines the western boundary
to the Llano Estacado. In addition to the
Pecos River, which originates in the Sangre de
Cristos and flows south through the Edwards
Plateau to the Rio Grande, key elements of the
landscape here include many sinks, depressions,
and caves, referred to collectively as karst topography,
that formed as a result of the dissolution
of ancient limestone bedrock. The bestknown
solution features are found at Carlsbad
Caverns National Park.</p>

<p>Two subregions can be recognized to the
east of the High Plains. The Plains Border of
southern Nebraska, Kansas, and northern
Oklahoma is a more dissected continuation of
the High Plains, as a number of west to east
flowing rivers (Republican, Solomon, Saline,
Smoky Hill, Arkansas, Cimarron, North Canadian)
have cut broad valleys through the Tertiary
cover, which is only preserved along relatively
narrow stream divides in the western
part of this subregion. The Low Rolling Plains
subregion farther south in Oklahoma and
West Texas is even more dissected, cut by the
Canadian, Washita, Red, and Brazos Rivers,
and completely separated from the High Plains
by the prominent Caprock Escarpment. Both
areas have in common westward-dipping pre-
Tertiary sedimentary rocks, the dissection of
which has produced a series of alternating
north–south oriented, relatively featureless
plains developed in easily eroded shales and
prominent east-facing scarps developed in
more resistant sandstones or limestones. In
addition to the dissected and scarped terrain,
other notable features include the Arbuckle
Mountains and Wichita Mountains of southcentral
Oklahoma, where ancient sedimentary
and crystalline rocks were uplifted long ago
and still remain at elevations 650 to 1,000 feet
higher than the surrounding plains.</p>

<p>The southern limits of the High Plains, or
Llano Estacado, merge almost imperceptibly
with the Edwards Plateau, the southernmost
extension of the Great Plains. The landscape
here consists of broad tablelands formed in
pre-Tertiary limestones, punctuated by deeply
incised bedrock valleys of the major rivers. The
Pecos River, for example, flows north to south
until it merges with the Rio Grande, whereas
the Colorado River and its tributaries drain the
northern part of the plateau, and the Nueces,
San Antonio, and Guadalupe Rivers drain the
southern and southeastern margins. The Central
Texas Uplift to the north and east of the
Edwards Plateau is actually a topographic
basin (often referred to as the Llano Basin) that
represents an exhumed landscape of ancient
upwarped sedimentary rocks surrounding a
crystalline core that was exposed as limestones
of the Edwards Plateau were completely removed
by the Colorado River and its tributaries.
Dissected remnants of limestone tablelands,
referred to as the Callahan Divide, occur
north of the Central Texas Uplift and Colorado
Valley and represent the divide between the
Colorado drainage and that of the Brazos
River, whereas more continuous dissected
limestone topography farther east, wholly
within the Brazos drainage, is referred to as the
Lampasas Cut Plain. The southeastern margin
of the Edwards Plateau is deeply dissected and
referred to as the Texas Hill Country, whereas
the Balcones Escarpment, at the foot of which
the major urban centers of San Antonio and
Austin have grown, separates the Hill Country
from the Gulf Coastal Plain Physiographic
Province.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Michael D. Blum<lb/>
Louisiana State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Fenneman, Nevin M. <title level="m">Physiography of Western United
States</title>. New York: McGraw Hill, 1931.</bibl> <bibl>Klassen, R. W.
"Quaternary Geology of the Southern Canadian Interior
Plains." In <title level="m">Quaternary Geology of Canada and Greenland</title>,
edited by R. J. Fulton. Ottawa: Geological Society of Canada,
1989: 97–174.</bibl> <bibl>Thornbury, William D. <title level="m">Regional Geomorphology
of the United States</title>. New York: Wiley, 1965.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>