<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.mus.050">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Western Swing</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Pamela H. Brink</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.mus.050</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Brink, Pamela H.">Pamela H. Brink</author>. <title level="a">"Western Swing."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">550</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-03</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">WESTERN SWING</head>

<p>Western swing is ballroom music, a style with a
constant beat built around a lead fiddle using a
long, smooth bow stroke suitable for two-step
dancing. More than the song or the singer,
western swing is built on instrumental improvisation,
and its strong dance rhythms constitute
a significant departure from the listening
conventions of traditional country music.</p>

<p>The style had its beginnings in 1931 with a
fiddle band that played first over radio station
<hi rend="smallcaps">KFJZ</hi>, then over <hi rend="smallcaps">WBAP</hi> in Fort Worth, Texas,
promoting Light Crust flour for the Burrus
Mill and Elevator Company. Bob Wills played
fiddle, Herman Arnspiger played guitar, and
Milton Brown sang, and they called themselves
the Light Crust Doughboys. The special
talents and distinctive style of this small country
band established Fort Worth as the "cradle
of western swing" and Bob Wills as a significant
musical innovator whose experimentations
changed the course, sound, and audience
of fiddle music forever.</p>

<p>Initially, band members performed for no
fee and worked eight hours a day at the mill,
playing just for the chance to be heard and
maybe hired for dances in and around Fort
Worth. By 1932 they were salaried, and Burrus
Mill's general manager, Wilbert Lee "Pappy"
O'Daniel, was broadcasting the show in San
Antonio, Houston, and Oklahoma, as well as
Forth Worth. For the next twenty years, even
with a rather constant turnover in musicians,
the Light Crust Doughboys remained one of
the most popular radio shows in the Southwest
and helped launch Pappy O'Daniel as a
colorful force in Texas politics.</p>

<p>In late 1932 Milton Brown and his brother
Durwood left the Doughboys to form Milton
Brown and the Musical Brownies, a very successful
band playing in the new western swing
style. Until his death in a 1936 automobile accident,
Milton Brown helped popularize this
new dance music with over 100 recording selections
for Victor and Decca.</p>

<p>Bob Wills only stayed with O'Daniel and
the Doughboys until 1933. By 1934 he and his
band were solidly established in Tulsa, Oklahoma,
as Bob Wills and His Texas Playboys.
For the next twenty-five years they broadcast
over radio station <hi rend="smallcaps">KVOO</hi>, made numerous regional
and national tours, appeared in almost
twenty Hollywood movies, and recorded their
music in abundance with major record labels.
Through all these venues, Bob Wills and His
Texas Playboys established their diverse and
continually changing repertoire and folksy yet
sophisticated style as elemental influences on
American popular music.</p>

<p>Western swing, like traditional country music,
posits "humble folk" as its audience but
radically expands the definition by adding
dance rhythms and mellow vocalists to express
both urban and country musical themes.
Milton Brown's best-selling recording was "St.
Louis Blues." Bob Wills and His Texas Playboys
gave their audiences everything from Bob and
John Wills's poignant country creation "Faded
Love" to Tommy Duncan's crooning rendition
of "Right or Wrong" and "I'll String Along
with You."</p>

<p>In the beginning both Wills's and Brown's
bands were innovative country string bands
relying on the fiddle, guitar, banjo, and bass
for their distinctive style. Wills, however, soon
defied country music conventions and the fiddle
band tradition. By adding saxophones,
clarinets, trombones, drums, and even mariachi
horns to his orchestra, he created a big
band sound that embraced both the brassy
jazz of the era and the lively two-step rhythms
for dancing on the Southern High Plains. Bob
Wills consistently responded to the diverse
musical traditions of his native region, radically
reshaping them to fit his own special
brand of swing orchestra.</p>

<p>As a child, Wills had listened to and admired
the blues sung by African Americans who
worked the cotton harvest with his family in
West Texas. "I slurred my fiddle," he explained,
"in order to play the blues." This slurring of the
strings is a basic characteristic of western
swing string instrumentation. Wills's many experimentations
with the amplified steel guitar
helped intensify these blues rhythms, and,
through his influence, the plaintive whine of
amplified steel soon became a standard in the
expression of country and western music.</p>

<p>Wills also incorporated regional Hispanic
influences into his music. While barbering
and playing fiddle in Roy, New Mexico, in the
late 1920s, Wills composed a piece he called
"Spanish Two-Step." A decade later he rearranged
it into what became his most famous
song, "San Antonio Rose." The Playboys recorded
it as a country instrumental in 1938
and in 1940 as the "New San Antonio Rose,"
with lyrics performed by Tommy Duncan and
mariachi horns added to reinforce the Hispanic
spirit of the tune. In 1941 Bing Crosby
recorded the song, giving Bob Wills's western
swing its first national recognition.</p>

<p>In many ways, western swing music is a
manifestation of the cultural forces that came
together where the geographical isolation and
harsh living conditions of the frontier met the
electronic age. People still living in dugouts
and sod houses on the Southern High Plains
became a part of popular culture through the
radio and the jukebox, mingling their musical
talents and tastes with new sounds introduced
to them through the accessibility of phonographs
and the airwaves.</p>

<p>By applying new, innovative techniques to
playing the fiddle and all the other basic country
string instruments, western swing serves as
a significant crucible in the development of
popular American music, expanding a regional,
rural sound into a dynamic, rhythmic
style that forms a continuum through rockabilly,
rock and roll, crossover country, and
what is now called, specifically because of
western swing, country and western music.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Pamela H. Brink<lb/>
Associated Authors and Editors, Inc.</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Malone, Bill C. <title level="m">Country Music</title> <title level="m"><hi rend="smallcaps">USA</hi>: A Fifty-Year History</title>. Austin: University of Texas Press, 1985.</bibl> <bibl>Mason, Michael,
ed. <title level="m">The Country Music Book</title>. New York: Charles Scribner's
Sons, 1985.</bibl> <bibl>Townsend, Charles. <title level="m">San Antonio Rose: The Life and Music of Bob Wills</title>. Urbana: University of Illinois
Press, 1976.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>