<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.gen.041">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Women in Agriculture</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Barbara Handy-Marchello</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.gen.041</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Handy-Marchello, Barbara">Barbara Handy-Marchello</author>. <title level="a">"Women in Agriculture."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">340-341</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-23</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">WOMEN IN AGRICULTURE</head>

<p>The first women farmers in the Great Plains
were Native Americans who grew corn, beans,
and other crops. Mandan and Hidatsa women
who lived near the Missouri River in the
Northern Plains, and Pawnee women along
the Platte River, tended gardens and controlled
the distribution of the crops. A surplus
of corn contributed to the creation of trade
centers near agricultural villages in the Plains.
Though the wars of the late nineteenth century
and reservation life contributed to the
loss of this important economic role for Indian
women, some continued to farm in the
twentieth century.</p>

<p>Non-Native women who farmed the Plains,
usually with husbands and children, provided
labor or management skills for field crops as
well as a small, stable income from barnyard
and garden surpluses. Women's work in the
wheat fields of the Plains was necessary during
the early years of settlement, though most
American families and some immigrant cultures
considered it a temporary departure
from desirable gender arrangements. Women
plowed, planted, shocked, and pitched wheat
bundles, hoed sugar beets, made hay, and
hauled rocks out of the fields. Rarely did
women have the opportunity to operate early
threshing machinery, but they did operate
tractors and trucks as soon as those machines
became common in the Plains. Some women
preferred fieldwork to housework, but others
were glad to have their growing children take
over in the fields so that they could return
to the house, where they generally asserted
authority.</p>

<p>Housework, however, cannot be distinguished
from farm work. Farm women housed,
fed, and cleaned up after hired helpers. In
the days before combines, a farm woman who
fed the threshing crew, often with the help
of neighboring women working in an informal
labor-exchange system, reduced the per
bushel costs of threshing. Even farm women
who did not work in the fields or feed hired
help had to arrange their work around the
daily and seasonal demands of the farm.</p>

<p>Farmyard work, routine for women until
1945, consisted of planting and tending vegetable
gardens, raising chickens for meat or eggs,
milking a few cows, separating the cream, and
churning butter. In many farm homes these
products served family needs as well as provided
a surplus for trade at the nearest store.
While the income from these commodities
was relatively small, it was a reliable source of
cash when the field crops failed (a common
event on Plains wheat farms) or when crop
prices were low.</p>

<p>Women on Great Plains farms apparently
felt a greater need for this income than farm
women in other parts of the United States,
because they raised more chickens per farm
and increased poultry production at a greater
rate than the U.S. average between 1910 and
1930. They also were more likely to churn butter
in the mid-1920s than were farm women
elsewhere in the country, who by then were
selling milk or cream to commercial creameries.
These activities, vestiges of a frontier
economy, continued to be economically useful
to Great Plains farm families during the
Depression. Farms where women continued
to pursue productive activities tended to be
more prosperous than others and more likely
to enjoy continuity of ownership.</p>

<p>Women in the Great Plains also had more
children than women in most other parts of
the United States. Only the South had consistently
higher birthrates than the Great Plains.
Though data were collected only irregularly
until the 1930s, where figures are available the
birthrate tends to be higher in Plains states
than in the nation as a whole and for the national
rural population specifically. Cultural
traditions of many of the Plains ethnic groups
probably accounted for some of the tendency
toward large families, but large farms requiring
a lot of labor and the availability of inexpensive
land were contributing factors. With
large families, Plains farm women had more
housework and greater need for home gardens
and poultry and dairy products, but they
also more hands to help with the workload.</p>

<p>Plains farm women did not allow distance
and cultural differences to interfere with their
social interests and obligations. Women organized
Ladies Aid societies in rural communities,
often before the organization of the
church congregation. Rural Ladies Aids served
as the social and political center of rural communities,
with whole families attending meetings,
especially during winter months, and
whole communities attending Ladies Aid.
sponsored celebrations. Before automobiles
were available, women walked, drove wagons,
or used farm equipment and draft stock to get
to meetings.</p>

<p>Plains farm women sought to improve their
economic situation as well as to foster social
relationships through organizations such as
the Grange, the Farmers Alliance, Farmers Institutes,
and the County Extension Service.
Though women rarely took a leading role in
these organizations (though since the 1980s,
the Extension Service has seen more female
leadership), they did provide a platform from
which women could challenge the notion that
farmers were always men and assert their own
ideas about women's roles on farms as wives,
producers, and operators.</p>

<p>If widowed, farm women often found
themselves operating the farms they had previously
shared with their husbands. In 1900
farming ranked sixth in a national list of employment
for women. However, in the Northern
Plains, farming was the second most important
job category for foreign-born women.
Most of these women were widows past the
age of forty.</p>

<p>After World War I the Extension Service
encouraged women to give up farmwork and
concentrate on housework and child care. After
World War II, many women sought off-
farm work. In recent years there is a trend
toward women becoming actively involved in
farming once again.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Barbara Handy-Marchello<lb/>
University of North Dakota</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Handy-Marchello, Barbara. "The Main Stay: Women's
Productive Work on Pioneer Farms." <title level="j">North Dakota History</title>
63 (1996): 17-27.</bibl> <bibl>Jellison, Katherine. <title level="m">Entitled to Power: Farm Women and Technology, 1913-1963</title>. Chapel Hill: University
of North Carolina Press, 1993.</bibl> <bibl>Wilson, Gilbert, ed.
<title level="m">Buffalo Bird Woman's Garden: Agriculture of the Hidatsa Indians</title>. St. Paul: Minnesota Historical Society Press, 1987.</bibl>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>