<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.na.088">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Poncas</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Beth R. Ritter</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.na.088</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Ritter, Beth R.">Beth R. Ritter</author>. <title level="a">"Poncas."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">593-594</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-15</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">PONCAS</head>

<p>Since their arrival in the Great Plains, the
Ponca Tribe has always been small in numbers.
Yet their history and experiences are representative
of many of the major themes that have
shaped the lives of the Native inhabitants of the
region. According to the Poncas' oral history,
their original homeland was in the Ohio River
valley. For reasons now unknown, the Siouan
Degiha speakers (Poncas, Omahas, Kanzas,
Osages, and Quapaws) undertook a vast migration:
as they followed the Ohio, Mississippi,
and eventually the Missouri Rivers, one cognate
tribe after another divided off until only
the Poncas and Omahas remained together.
The Poncas eventually separated from the
Omahas and settled in the Niobrara River valley
(in present-day northeastern Nebraska) by
the early eighteenth century. As a consequence,
the Poncas and Omahas speak mutually intelligible
dialects and had similar political and social
organization, including hereditary chiefs
and patrilineal, exogamous clans.</p>

<p>Settling into their new land, the Poncas jettisoned
many of their Woodland adaptations in
favor of the archetypal Plains Village Tradition
of semipermanent earth lodge villages, maize
horticulture, and communal bison hunting. In
the nineteenth century, however, as a result of
epidemic diseases, the Poncas periodically
abandoned horticulture in favor of full-time
nomadic bison hunting. Still, they never abandoned
their homeland near the confluence of
the Niobrara and Missouri Rivers, and they
continued to return to their sacred sites, villages,
and gardens on a regular basis.</p>

<p>The typical seasonal round of the Poncas
was organized around the horticultural calendar:
planting gardens in the spring and harvesting
in the fall, interspersed with communal
bison hunts in the summer and winter
seasons. Hunting and horticulture were supplemented
by gathering wild plants and herbs
for food and healing. The Poncas utilized a
vast area of the Central Great Plains for trading,
hunting, horse raiding, and visiting. In
all, they claimed an area extending from the
Missouri River on the east to the Black Hills
and foothills of the Rocky Mountains to the
west, and from the White River in the north to
the Platte River in the south.</p>

<p>Given their range, the Poncas had to learn
to coexist with their more numerous and
powerful neighbors, the Lakotas and the Pawnees.
The Poncas forged a tenuous alliance
with the Oglala Lakotas, occasionally hunting
together and accompanying them on their
horse raids against the Pawnees. From the
Oglalas the Poncas learned the sacred Sun
Dance, but they modified it to fit Ponca horticultural
traditions by adding an emphasis on
fertility and renewal, consistent with the goals
of a horticultural tribe. The Poncas also practiced
(and still practice) the sacred pipe religion
and expressed a strong belief in their allpowerful
creator, <hi rend="italic">Wakonda</hi>. The Poncas had a
more troubled relationship with the Brul&#233;
Lakotas, however, which would eventually
contribute to their expulsion from their Niobrara
homeland.</p>

<p>The Poncas point with pride to the fact that
they never engaged in armed conflict with the
U.S. government. In all, they signed four treaties,
including a treaty that ceded Aboriginal
title to the majority of their land and established
a reservation near Niobrara, Nebraska,
in 1858. The Poncas tried earnestly to succeed
in their transition to reservation-based farming.
However, those efforts proved futile when
the government ceded away title to the entire
Ponca Reservation to the Sioux in the Treaty
of Fort Laramie in 1868. Overnight, the Poncas
found themselves trespassers on their own
reservation. The Brule Lakotas, under Chief
Spotted Tail, were relentless in their harassment
of the Poncas and eventually weakened
them to the point of desperation. Conditions
were so grave by the 1870s that the Poncas
considered a plan to abandon their homeland
in favor of a new reservation in Indian Territory.
After traveling to the proposed site in the
winter of 1877, a delegation of Ponca chiefs
declined the offer. However, the will of the
chiefs was disregarded by the government,
and the forced removal of the tribe commenced
in the spring of 1877.</p>

<p>This event, known as the Ponca Trail of
Tears, was a disaster. Plagued by bad weather
and inadequate preparations, the Poncas lost
more than one-fifth (158 from 730) of their
population within the first two years of removal.
Dissatisfaction with their circumstances led to a desperate attempt by Chief
Standing Bear to return to the Niobrara
homeland to honor the dying wish of his son
to be buried with his ancestors. On New Year's
Day of 1879, Standing Bear led a small party of
Poncas&#8211;mostly women and children&#8211;back
to Nebraska. They were arrested, and a trial
ensued in federal district court in Omaha, Nebraska.
Judge Elmer Dundy declared that "an
Indian is a person under the meaning of the
law" and that the United States had no authority
to return Standing Bear to Indian Territory.</p>

<p>Standing Bear had won his case, but the
victory was a hollow one for the Ponca Tribe.
The majority of the Poncas, after spending
more than two years settling into their new
reservation in Indian Territory, opted to remain
there. In 1881 the Ponca Tribe was officially
dissolved and legally reconstituted as
two separate entities: the Northern Ponca
Tribe, residing on a portion of the old Ponca
Reservation in northeastern Nebraska, and
the Southern Ponca Tribe, with a reservation
of 101,000 acres in north-central Oklahoma.</p>

<p>The two Ponca tribes, still linked by family,
cultural, and linguistic ties, have faced vastly
different fates in the twentieth century. The
Ponca Tribe of Oklahoma, organized in 1950, is
headquartered in White Eagle, named after the
Poncas' charismatic paramount chief at the
time of removal. In 1996 the Southern Poncas
listed 2,581 enrolled members, of whom more
than half resided in Kay County, Oklahoma.
The Southern Poncas' land base suffered as a
consequence of allotment policy, and they
eventually lost the vast majority of their land-holdings,
including oil-rich lands, to non-
Indian interests, particularly the "101 Ranch."
The Southern Poncas have been active in the
Native American Church, the revitalization of
the <hi rend="italic">Heduska</hi>, or War Dance Society, and the
Plains powwow tradition. The economy of the
Ponca Tribe of Oklahoma is based on a successful
bingo hall, smoke shops, and various
tribal economic development initiatives.</p>

<p>The Northern Ponca Tribe also struggled in
the twentieth century with land loss and the
out-migration of tribal members. The Northern
Ponca Tribe was terminated in 1962, joining
more than 100 tribes that lost their status
as a result of federal termination policy. At the
time of termination, only 442 Northern Poncas
were listed on the tribal roll, and only 847
of their original 27,000 acres remained. Tribal
status was legally restored by Congress in 1990
as a result of a prolonged tribal grassroots
effort led by the nonprofit Northern Ponca
Restoration Committee. The Ponca Tribe of
Nebraska is currently headquartered in Niobrara,
Nebraska, near their first reservation.
The tribe, denied the opportunity to reestablish
their reservation by Congress, delivers services
to tribal members residing in fifteen designated
counties in Nebraska, South Dakota,
and Iowa. Enrollment exceeds 2,000. At the
turn of the twenty-first century the tribe was
engaged in a number of economic developments
and cultural revitalization projects, including
the reintroduction of bison on tribal
trust lands near Niobrara and the establishment
of the Ponca Health and Wellness Center
in Omaha, Nebraska.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">PROTEST AND DISSENT</hi>: <ref n="egp.pd.053">Trial of Standing Bear</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Beth R. Ritter</signed>
University of Nebraska at Omaha</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Howard, James H. <hi rend="italic">The Ponca Tribe</hi>. Washington <hi rend="smallcaps">DC</hi>: Government
Printing Office, 1995.</bibl> <bibl>Ritter, Beth R. "The Politics
of Retribalization: The Northern Ponca Case." <hi rend="italic">Great
Plains Research</hi> 4 (1994): 237-55.</bibl> <bibl>Wishart, David J. <title level="m">An Unspeakable
Sadness: The Dispossession of the Nebraska Indians</title>.
Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1994.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>