<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.tra.030">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Red River Carts</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Pekka H&#228;m&#228;l&#228;inen</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.tra.030</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="H&#228;m&#228;l&#228;inen, Pekka">Pekka H&#228;m&#228;l&#228;inen</author>. <title level="a">"Red River Carts."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">810</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-22</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">RED RIVER CARTS</head>

<p>Developed in the Prairie Provinces in the
nineteenth century by the M&#233;tis, the Red River
cart was a small, two-wheeled wooden rig
drawn by oxen or horses. It had two long
shafts attached to an axle and could be strapped
to a single draft animal. The shafts supported
a platform with wooden rails on two
sides. The cart was well designed for Plains
travel. Constructed entirely of wood and tied
together with leather, it could be easily manufactured
in the Red River country, where
oaks and poplars thrived in river valleys, bison
were abundant, but metal goods were scarce.
Large, spoked wheels made the carts easy to
draw through the tall grasses, rugged terrain,
and shallow streams of the Prairie Provinces.
Thanks to their simple design, the carts could
be easily repaired when long journeys across
the Plains took their toll.</p>

<p>The Metis initially designed the Red River
cart for carrying hides, dried meat, and tallow
from their semiannual bison hunts on the
Plains. Each cart could carry as much as 1,000
pounds&#8211;the hides, meat, and grease of five or
six buffalo. By the late nineteenth century, the
Prairie Provinces were crisscrossed by Metis
cart roads, the most important of which was
the Carlton Trail from Fort Garry, the supply
depot of the Red River settlement, to Fort
Carlton on the Saskatchewan River. Each year,
several hundred carts trundled back and forth
along the road, filling the air with their distinctive
ear-piercing screech, caused by the
rubbing of wooden wheels against wooden
axles. At first, the Metis sold most of their
bison products to the fur trade posts in the
Red River country, but in the 1850s they began
to organize cart brigades to present-day St.
Paul, Minnesota. Primarily a long-distance
transport device, the Red River cart was replaced
in the late nineteenth century by the
steamboat and railway.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">NATIVE AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.na.063">M&#233;tis</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Pekka H&#228;m&#228;l&#228;inen<lb/>
Texas A&amp;M University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>