<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ha.028">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Mexican American Cuisine</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Barbara G. Shortridge</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ha.028</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Shortridge, Barbara G.">Barbara G. Shortridge</author>. <title level="a">"Mexican American Cuisine."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">362</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-02</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">MEXICAN AMERICAN CUISINE</head>

<p>Of the familiar ethnic triad of foods in the
United States, Mexican American dishes far
outdistance those from Italy and China in
the Great Plains. This is true both for locally
owned restaurants and for fast-food franchises.
The cuisine became known because of
the region's proximity to the Southwest, and
it became popular because it is inexpensive,
tastes good, and is filling. The wide diffusion of
Mexicans and Mexican Americans throughout
the Plains in recent decades has meant that
family Mexican restaurants and Mexican grocery
stores have come even to small communities,
diversifying and enriching the culinary
landscape.</p>

<p>What most Plains people are eating is Tex-
Mex, a modified version of Mexican food
originally adapted to please Anglo palates that
preferred less heat and more meat. Some food
items, such as tortilla chips, were actually concocted
for the U.S. market. The preparation
style and ingredient list is different from historic
Mexican cooking in that Tex-Mex has
more cheese and tomato-based sauces. It differs
from Spanish-colonial cooking in its
spices, variety of meats, and wheat-based pastries.
Tex-Mex has its origins as a lower-class or
peasant food, similar in function to Cajun
food within southern Louisiana culture. In
fact, Tex-Mex food represents such a jumbled
mixing of food traditions from several cultures
that it is difficult to untangle the regional
origins and discuss authenticity. It is truly a
hybrid product.</p>

<p>In a restaurant setting, a Tex-Mex meal is
invariably initiated by a basket of tortilla chips
and fresh tomato salsa, with options for varying
degrees of heat. A common meal is a combination
plate that might include a beef taco
served in a crisp corn tortilla, a chicken enchilada
with sauce, a bean burrito wrapped in
a flour tortilla, and sides of refried beans and
Spanish rice. One end of the plate contains a
mound of shredded iceberg lettuce with fresh
tomato chunks, and a layer of grated cheese
covers everything. Dessert might be sopapillas,
while a beverage of choice is often a beer
or margarita. Liquid of some kind is essential,
as the diner does not always know in advance
the heat level of the dish. The ambiance of the
restaurant setting is, of course, dependent
upon the imagination of the owner, but the
decor often includes bright, tropical colors,
<hi rend="italic">ristras</hi> of dried red chiles, painted clay pottery,
and ironwork. Mexican music is almost mandatory
and is important in conveying the upbeat,
festive atmosphere associated with this
cuisine.</p>

<p>Three classic Tex-Mex items&#8211;tacos, nachos,
and chili&#8211;have escaped their ethnic origins
and become "American." Other foods belonging
to this cuisine are more likely to be found in
the Mexican American home, although some
have begun to be incorporated into restaurant
settings as customers demand more variety.
Pico de gallo, chicharron, gorditos, and chalupas
are in the process of making it in the
commercial world. Others, such as tamales, are
often homemade, special-occasion food. Cabrito,
offal food, barbacoa, panocha, chorizo,
bu&#241;uelos, and handmade tortillas all fall
mostly in the category of home consumption
only. As the Mexican American population becomes
more urban, lack of time to prepare
labor-intensive dishes and the inability to
butcher animals and cook outside in a pit are
changing some aspects of the cuisine.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">FOLKWAYS</hi>: <ref n="egp.fol.019">Foodways</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Barbara G. Shortridge<lb/>
University of Kansas</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Bentley, Amy. "From Culinary Other to Mainstream American:
Meanings and Uses of Southwestern Cuisine." <title level="j">Southern Folklore</title> 55 (1998): 238-52.</bibl> <bibl>Graham, Joe S. "Mexican-
American Traditional Foodways at La Junta De Los Rios."
<title level="j">Journal of Big Bend Studies</title> 2 (1990): 1-27.</bibl> <bibl>Pilcher, Jeffrey
M. <title level="m">¡Que vivan los tamales! Food and the Making of Mexican Identity</title>. Albuquerque: University of New Mexico Press,
1998.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>