<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.mus.039">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Polka Music</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Richard March</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.mus.039</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="March, Richard">Richard March</author>. <title level="a">"Polka Music."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">546</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-03</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">POLKA MUSIC</head>

<p>The polka, a couples dance in duple time, was
popular in much of Europe during the second
half of the nineteenth century. Since many immigrants
from Europe settled in the Great
Plains during that period, they brought an affinity
for the polka dance and the associated
music with them as part of their cultural legacy.
Germans and Czechs, in particular, have
tended to be the most active in perpetuating
the polka tradition in the Great Plains, but
Poles, Swedes, Danes, Norwegians, Finns, Italians,
Slovenians, Croatians, and other European
Americans also identify the polka as part
of their ethnic heritage.</p>

<p>The nineteenth-century polka craze also
entered Mexico from Europe, and Mexican
musicians in Texas interacted with musical
German, Polish, and Czech immigrants there
to shape the polka style of the Tex-Mex <hi rend="italic">conjuntos</hi>
(bands). During the twentieth century
Mexican Americans migrated to many areas
of the Great Plains, bringing the conjunto
style of polka music and dancing with them.</p>

<p>Polka musicians in the Great Plains play in
several distinctive styles. The names of the
most influential styles refer to ethnic groups&#8211;
Czech or "Bohemian," German or "Dutchman,"
Polish, Mexican, and Slovenian. There
is a core constituency of dancers and players
from the particular ethnic group in each of the
polka "scenes"; however, people from a variety
of other ethnic backgrounds participate as
well. Mutual influences are common in the
music and dancing.</p>

<p>In rural areas, Czechs and Germans have
been the most active. There are important
concentrations of Czech bands in eastern Nebraska
and central Texas. Both the Czech
and German polka styles tend to emphasize
brass and reed instruments in interaction with
an accordion or concertina. The Dutchman
style of German American music, originally
from southern Minnesota, has also been influential
in the Great Plains. Broadcasts of the
Whoopee John Orchestra over Minneapolis's
clear channel station wcco were avidly followed
on the Plains, and the well-known
Dutchman bands toured westward from Minnesota.
Thus German bands from the Dakotas
to Kansas often use the Chemnitzer type of
concertina played by Whoopee John. The
Czech bands, on the other hand, tend to utilize
the diatonic button box accordion or
modern piano keyboard accordion. The German
bands strive for a smoother blended
brass and reed sound, while the Czech bands
opt for an incisive brassy or reedy tone from
the wind instruments.</p>

<p>Germans from Russia have developed Dutch
Hop, a polka style unique to the Great Plains
and played mainly in western Nebraska and
eastern Colorado. The hammer dulcimer is an
important instrument in Dutch Hop, and the
trombone provides the bass line rather than the
tuba of the Dutchman and Czech bands.</p>

<p>Polish- and Slovenian-style polka bands are
strongest in urban centers like Omaha and
Kansas City, although on the western Plains
there are also Slovenian bands in mining and
mill towns. Polish bands are influenced by
Chicago Polish musicians like Lil' Wally and
Eddie Blazonczyk. They use the Chemnitzer
concertina interacting with brass and reeds
played in a raucous and polyphonic style.
Slovenian bands foreground the accordion accompanied
by tenor or plectrum banjo. Slovenian
and Polish bands avoid the tuba, using a
string bass, bass guitar, or recently a Midi bass
synthesizer played by the accordion player
with his or her left hand.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Richard March<lb/>
Wisconsin Arts Board</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Greene, Victor. <title level="m">A Passion for Polka</title>. Berkeley: University of
California Press, 1992.</bibl> <bibl>Keil, Charles, Angeliki V. Keil, and
Dick Blau. <title level="m">Polka Happiness</title>. Philadelphia: Temple University
Press, 1992.</bibl> <bibl>Leary, James P., and Richard March. <title level="m">Down Home Dairyland: A Listener's Guide</title>. Madison: University
of Wisconsin–Extension, 1996.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>