<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ind.017">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Cotton Industry</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Don E. Ethridge</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ind.017</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Ethridge, Don E.">Don E. Ethridge</author>. <title level="a">"Cotton Industry."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">416</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-02</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">COTTON INDUSTRY</head>

<p>The cotton industry and the Great Plains region
are not often viewed as synonymous, but
the southern portion of the region constitutes
the most concentrated area of cotton production
in the world. Cotton production and the
industrial base associated with it are concentrated
in the southern High Plains of Texas
and eastern New Mexico and the Rolling
Plains of Texas and Oklahoma. The region
consistently produces about 30 to 35 percent
of the cotton output of the United States and 5
to 8 percent of the cotton produced in the
world. The area of greatest concentration is
within 100 miles of Lubbock, Texas, but production
extends from the southernmost part
of the Plains to as far north as Kansas, although
production is extremely sparse north
of Plainview, Texas, and Altus, Oklahoma.</p>

<p>Cotton is a multiproduct crop. The primary
product is cotton lint, which constitutes about
80 percent of the farm value of cotton production,
and the secondary product is cottonseed,
which constitutes about 15 percent of the farm
value. There are also several by-products. The
industry can be characterized as consisting of
sectors: production, ginning, warehousing,
merchandising, oilseed processing, and textile
processing.</p>

<p>The region produces 3.5 to 4.0 million bales
of cotton lint each year (each bale weighs 480
pounds), with more than 4.5 million acres
planted to cotton and almost 4 million acres
harvested each year. The cottonseed production
is 1.6 to 1.8 million tons per year. The
farm value of cotton production in the region
is typically $1.25 to $1.5 billion per year, with a
total regional income generated of over $4 billion.</p>

<p>Production occurs under both irrigated
and nonirrigated conditions within the region.
The crop is typically harvested between
mid-October and mid-December using mechanical
cotton strippers that remove (strip)
all of the material from the cotton stalk, including
complete bolls, any remaining leaves,
and small stems. Some but not all strippers
have field cleaners mounted on them that separate
the burrs in the cotton boll from the lint
and seed and leave them in the field.</p>

<p>Once harvested, the harvested material
(seedcotton) is typically stored in the field
in "modules"&#8211;eight to twelve bale packed
"loaves" of seedcotton of about 20,000 to
25,000 pounds each. These are constructed
using module builders. Modules are then
picked up with module mover trucks and
hauled to a gin for further processing. There
are more than 300 of these gin plants within
the southern portion of the Great Plains region.
They perform the function of separating
the lint, seed, and other organic material in the
seedcotton. The result is baled lint, which is
moved to a warehouse for storage until it is
ready to be shipped to a textile plant, and cottonseed,
which is sold to a cottonseed oil mill
or to a dairy or feedlot for direct consumption
by cattle. There are forty-three cotton warehouses
within the region and six cottonseed
oil–processing plants. The oil mills produce
meal for livestock feed, oil for cooking oils, and
a range of by-products from linters and seed
hulls.</p>

<p>Before cotton leaves the gin, samples are
drawn from each bale and sent to a Classing
Office operated by the U.S. Department of Agriculture.
Each bale is evaluated for fiber
color, foreign matter content, length, strength,
length uniformity, and micronaire (an indicator
of fiber fineness and maturity). The quality
information on each bale's sample is placed
with the bale, and each bale maintains its individual
identity throughout the marketing system
until it is consumed by a textile plant.
This information plays an important role in
determining the most efficient use for the cotton
and its market value.</p>

<p>Cotton merchants/shippers, who have more
than sixty installations in the region (belonging
to a smaller number of firms), perform the
functions of buying, selling, and moving cotton
lint to the textile user. Their concentration
tends to correspond to the location of production.
As much as 45 percent of the cotton
traded occurs through sophisticated computerized
electronic trading systems. Most of the
cotton from the region is shipped to the southeastern
part of the United States or to foreign
buyers. However, there is an expanding textile-processing
industry within the southern portion
of the region. There are some eleven
textile-manufacturing firms within the region,
most of them using cotton. Only about 5 percent
of the cotton grown in the region is processed
into textile products within the region,
but this is an increase from about 1 percent
fifteen years earlier. Manufacturing and transportation
cost advantages in relation to the
expanding West Coast and Mexico markets
will likely support future growth of textile
manufacturing within the region.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">AGRICULTURE</hi>: <ref n="egp.ag.024">Cotton</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Don E. Ethridge<lb/>
Texas Tech University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>