<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.sr.034">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Lucas, Barbara (1902-1990)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Sonja Rossum</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.sr.034</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Rossum, Sonja">Sonja Rossum</author>. <title level="a">"Lucas, Barbara (1902-1990)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">778</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-21</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">LUCAS, BARBARA (1902-1990)</head>

<p>"Rodeo's First Lady" was born Barbara Inez
Barnes on September 1, 1902, on a ranch near
Cody, Nebraska. As the youngest of twenty-four
children (hence the nickname "Tadpole,"
shortened to Tad), she was familiar with competition
from the start. Riding from a very
young age, she was winning steer-riding contests
by the time she was fourteen, and by
twenty she was a full-time professional cowgirl.
She met and married cowboy James Edward
"Buck" Lucas shortly before heading to
London, where she competed in trick riding
for the first time.</p>

<p>The 1920s and early 1930s were a Golden
Age for women in rodeo, giving them the opportunity
to compete as rough stock riders,
trick riders, and relay racers. Fascinated by
trick riding, Lucas mastered stunts such as a
back drag (arching back so her head was just
shy of the galloping hooves) and changing
sides of a running horse by crawling under its
belly. A fearless performer, she was the only
woman ever to ride a Brahma bull in Madison
Square Garden. Her trick-riding skills won
her an assortment of titles across the country,
and starting in 1928 Lucas proved the diversity
of her abilities by winning the all-around
champion at Madison Square Garden three
years in a row, retiring the prestigious ten-thousand-dollar
<hi rend="smallcaps">MGM</hi> Trophy.</p>

<p>During World War II many women's rodeo
competitions were dropped, so in 1948 the
Girls Rodeo Association (now the Women's
Professional Rodeo Association) set out to revive
women's role in the sport. As a charter
member, Lucas added credibility to this new
organization, and her undisputed success and
popularity eventually earned her a place in all
three rodeo Halls of Fame: the National Rodeo
Hall of Fame (1967, first woman elected),
the National Cowgirl Hall of Fame and Western
Heritage Museum's Rodeo Hall of Fame
(1978), and the Pro Rodeo Hall of Fame
(1979).</p>

<p>Lucas retired from her long career at the age
of fifty-six. Her daughter Dorothy hated
rodeo, but second daughter Mitzi loved it
enough to become a respected trick rider herself.
Tad Lucas died on February 23, 1990, in
Fort Worth, Texas. The Tad Lucas Memorial
Award honors women who excel in any field
related to western heritage.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Sonja Rossum<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Lecompte, Mary Lou. <title level="m">Cowgirls of the Rodeo: Pioneer Professional
Athletes (Sport and Society)</title>. Urbana: University
of Illinois Press, 2000.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>