<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fil.023">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Fonda, Henry (1906-1982)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Chuck Berg</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fil.023</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Berg, Chuck">Chuck Berg</author>. <title level="a">"Fonda, Henry (1906-1982)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">267</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-12</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">FONDA, HENRY (1906-1982)</head>
<figure n="egp.fil.023" rend="granted" type="noclick">
<figDesc>Henry Fonda</figDesc>
</figure>     

<p>Henry Jaynes Fonda, one of America's most
beloved screen actors, won the admiration of
film fans around the world with an unassuming
acting style that was engagingly forthright
and sincere. From his Hollywood debut in
<title>The Farmer Takes a Wife</title> (1935) to his Oscarwinning
performance in <title>On Golden Pond</title>
(1981), Fonda projected a clear-eyed integrity
that compelled him to seek the truth and
stand up for the little guy.</p>

<p>Born in Grand Island, Nebraska, on May 16,
1906, Fonda moved with his family to Omaha
when he was six months old. Intent on a career
in journalism, he enrolled at the University
of Minnesota. He dropped out after two
years and returned to Omaha and a job as an
office boy. In 1925 a friend of the family&#8211;the
mother of then one-year-old Marlon Brando
&#8211;asked him to act in an amateur production
at the Omaha Community Playhouse. Entranced
by the theater, Fonda quit his office
job to work with the company for three years.</p>

<p>In 1928 Fonda headed to New York to seek
his fortune as a professional actor. After several
minor Broadway roles, he achieved stardom
in <title>The Farmer Takes a Wife</title>, his first film
role. As a young Hollywood leading man,
Fonda at first played opposite established female
stars such as Bette Davis in <title>Jezebel</title> (1938).
The defining moment for Fonda's career came
in director John Ford's <title>The Young Mr. Lincoln</title>
(1939), a role that allowed the actor's aura of
midwestern honesty and thoughtful compassion
to shine. Other now classic films capitalizing
on Fonda's quiet heroism include <title>The Grapes of Wrath</title> (1940),<title>The Ox-Bow Incident</title>
(1943), <title>My Darling Clementine</title> (1946), <title>Twelve Angry Men</title> (1957), and <title>Fail Safe</title> (1964).</p>

<p>Although his international celebrity was a
result of his status as a Hollywood star, Fonda's
true love was theater, and in 1948 he returned
to Broadway for three long-running hit plays,
<title>Mr. Roberts</title> (1948), <title>Point of No Return</title> (1951), and <title>The Caine Mutiny Court-Martial</title> (1954).
Fonda might never have appeared in movies
again had it not been for John Ford, who insisted
that he reprise his role of Mr. Roberts for
the 1955 film adaptation. Thereafter, Fonda
shuttled back and forth between New York and
Los Angeles. Among his last triumphs were the
one-man Broadway show <title>Clarence Darrow</title> (1974) and his cutting-against-the-grain villain in film director Sergio Leone's epic <title>Once Upon a Time in the West</title> (1969).</p>

<p>In 1981, when he was sick and dying, Fonda
agreed to film the adaptation of <title>On Golden Pond</title>, which costarred and was produced by
his daughter Jane. Teamed with Katharine
Hepburn in what proved to be his final role,
Fonda was hailed by the critics, the public,
and the Academy of Motion Picture Arts and
Sciences, which awarded him a best actor Oscar.
Fonda also is the father of actor-producer
Peter Fonda. Henry Fonda, who was granted a
Life Achievement Award by the American
Film Institute in 1978, died in Los Angeles on
August 12, 1982.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Chuck Berg<lb/>
University of Kansas</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Fonda, Henry. <title level="m">My Life: As Told to Howard Teichman</title>. New
York: New American Library, 1981.</bibl> <bibl>Sweeny, Kevin. <title level="m">Henry Fonda: A Bio-Bibliography</title>. New York: Greenwood Press,
1992.</bibl> <bibl>Thomas, Tony. <title level="m">The Films of Henry Fonda</title>. Secaucus
<hi rend="smallcaps">NJ</hi>: Citadel Press, 1983.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>