<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.tra.007">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Cattle Trails</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Richard W. Slatta</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.tra.007</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Slatta, Richard W.">Richard W. Slatta</author>. <title level="a">"Cattle Trails."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">800-801</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-22</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">CATTLE TRAILS</head>

<p>Ranchers used specific routes, known as cattle
trails, to move their animals from grazing
lands to market. The most famous trails of the
Great Plains ran from Texas northward to
Kansas cow towns or railheads. Trail drives
defined the classic golden age of the cowboy,
as herders drove millions of cattle north from
the mid-1860s through the mid-1880s.</p>

<p>Cattlemen in the Great Plains had an interest
in moving their animals to more profitable
markets to the north and east as early as the
1840s. Edward Piper blazed the first documented
cattle trail in 1846, when he drove a
thousand head from Texas and sold them in
Ohio. Another early route, known initially as
the Kansas Trail and later as the Shawnee Trail,
opened in the 1840s. The full route ran from
Brownsville in southern Texas north through
Dallas. After crossing Indian Territory into
southeastern Kansas, the trail branched to
Missouri railheads at Kansas City, Sedalia, and
St. Louis. Quarantines against Texas cattle carrying
ticks and the interruptions of the Civil
War closed the Shawnee Trail and ended the
first phase of Great Plains trail drives.</p>

<p>During the Civil War untended herds in
Texas multiplied quickly as Union blockades
cut the state off from market outlets. The
Texans knew that their four-dollar-per-head
cattle in Texas could bring $40 to $50 apiece in
eastern markets. Thus, after the war ranchers
looked for ways to move their large herds to
market. In 1866 Charles Goodnight and Oliver
Loving blazed the famous cattle trail that bears
their names. It ran northwest from Palo Pinto
County, Texas, to Pope's Crossing in southeastern
New Mexico, and on north to Fort
Sumner and Fort Bascom. From Fort Sumner,
Loving continued the route northwest through
Raton Pass and on to markets in Colorado. In
1867 the 600-mile Chisholm Trail became the
main trail, and it was used extensively until
1871. Illinois cattle buyer Joseph G. McCoy laid
out the trail along an old trade path initially
developed by merchant Jesse Chisholm. It ran
north from San Antonio to Fort Worth, Texas,
through Oklahoma and ended at Abilene,
Kansas. McCoy built stock pens in Abilene to
hold cattle awaiting shipment on the Kansas
Pacific Railroad. In 1874 he published the first
major account of life on the cattle trail, <title level="m">Historic
Sketches of the Cattle Trade</title>.</p>

<p>Additional cattle trails developed for a
number of reasons. Conflicts with Native
Americans, rustlers, or local farmers and
ranchers fearful of tick-born "Texas fever"
convinced some Texans to seek more peaceful
routes. As railroads proliferated in Kansas and
Nebraska, new cow towns and markets required
new trails to reach them. Ranchers also
tried to find better routes with reliable supplies
of grass and water and with the fewest
major hazards such as major river crossings.</p>

<p>In 1867 ranchers in southern Texas began
moving animals along a route that ran parallel
to but east of the Chisholm Trail. This Eastern
Trail ran through the Cherokee Strip, passed
through Wichita and Newton, Kansas, and
then went on to Abilene. A decade later, Lucien
Maxwell struck out to the northwest from
Belton, Texas. This route, known as the Western
Trail, ran through Fort Griffin northward
to Doan's Store on the Red River and across the
Oklahoma Panhandle. Herds could be marketed
at Dodge City, Kansas, or Ogallala, Nebraska,
or driven to the Northern Great Plains
on the Jones and Plummer Trail. Drovers continued
to utilize the Western Trail until 1892,
when homesteaders settled and fenced off the
route in Oklahoma Territory.</p>

<p>On the Northern Plains, drovers moved cattle
along several routes, including the Bozeman,
Northern, Oregon Cattle, and Jones and
Plummer Trails. John Bozeman, born in Georgia,
aspired to find a shortcut to the Montana
gold deposits. In 1863 he trekked along the
Yellowstone River, turned south toward the Big
Horn Mountains, and arrived at Deer Creek
Settlement. The trail continued in use until it
was abandoned in the summer of 1868. From
1869 until about 1875, cattlemen in the Pacific
Northwest pushed herds eastward into Wyoming
over the Oregon Cattle Trail. Another
route, the Northern Trail, paralleled the Oregon
Cattle Trail from eastern Oregon through
Idaho before joining the latter at South Pass,
Wyoming.</p>

<p>Historian Philip Ashton Rollins estimated
that cattle drives required about one man for
each 250–350 head of cattle. In addition to the
drovers, crews included a trail boss, a cook,
perhaps an assistant foreman, and a horse
wrangler to care for the six to eight mounts
needed by each man. Cattle and horses acted
up more often early on the trail. After a few
weeks the animals became "trail broke" or
"road broke" and easier to handle.</p>

<p>Cattle trails became some of the most storied
places of the Great Plains. Some cowboys,
beginning with Charles A. Siringo in 1885,
penned memoirs of life on the trail. Siringo's
book, A Texas Cow Boy, set off a flood of similar
cattle drive books of variable quality and
veracity. Countless novels and movies such as
<title>Red River</title> (1948), starring John Wayne, would
popularize the lightning storms, stampedes,
rustler attacks, and dangerous river crossings
that cowhands actually endured on the trail.</p>

<p>Cowboys drove some 600,000-700,000 animals
north from Texas during 1871 alone. In
1884, however, Kansas enacted a quarantine
against Texas cattle that effectively killed the
large northern drives. The final blow to the
drives came when railroads pushed trunk lines
southward so that cattle could be shipped directly
from Texas. Sporadic drives continued
on a reduced basis for another decade, but the
great era of the cattle trails had ended.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">CITIES AND TOWNS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ct.011">Cattle Towns</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">FILM</hi>: <ref n="egp.fil.057"><hi rend="italic"><title>Red River</title></hi></ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">FOLKWAYS</hi>: <ref n="egp.fol.041">Siringo, Charles</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">IMAGES AND ICONS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ii.019">Dodge City, Kansas</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Richard W. Slatta<lb/>
North Carolina State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Gard, Wayne. <title level="m">The Chisholm Trail</title>. Norman: University of
Oklahoma Press, 1988.</bibl> <bibl>McCoy, Joseph G. <title level="m">Historic Sketches
of the Cattle Trade of the West and Southwest</title>, edited by
Ralph P. Bieber. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press,
1985.</bibl> <bibl>Skaggs, Jimmy M. <title level="m">The Cattle-Trailing Industry</title>. Norman:
University of Oklahoma Press, 1991.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>