<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.art.044">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Native American Traditional Art</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Mary Jane Schneider</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.art.044</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Schneider, Mary Jane">Mary Jane Schneider</author>. <title level="a">"Native American Traditional Art."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">125</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-22</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">NATIVE AMERICAN TRADITIONAL ART</head>

<p>Before Europeans introduced glass beads,
metal cones, ribbons, and cloth, Plains Indians
decorated themselves, their clothes,
and their household belongings with paint,
stone, bone and shell beads, animal teeth, and
other natural materials. They also carved and
painted human and animal figures and various
symbolic designs on boulders and rock
walls. In the Central and Northern Plains,
some groups used stones to create outline figures
of medicine wheels, humans, and animals.
Shells with faces carved in them and
sculptures of buffalo demonstrate that carving,
although a minor art form, was done before
the introduction of metal tools.</p>

<p>The great diversity in rock-art styles suggests
that there were many different tribes or
groups inhabiting the Plains. Each region
has its own distinct style, and scholars have
named and described the works from each
area. In the northwestern Plains, works believed
to date from between 1000 and 1700
have a recognizable Plains Indian style that
connects well to later art forms. Called "Ceremonial"
by scholars, the early designs consist
of simple outline figures of humans and animals.
Some humans are depicted with rectangular
bodies, V-shaped necklines, and
round heads. Others have large round bodies
with arms and legs. The decorations on the
bodies suggest that they represent shields, and
the designs are referred to as shield-bearing
warriors. Animals are shown with elongated,
rounded bodies with stick legs and welldefined
horns or antlers. Symbolic ribs often
appear inside the animal bodies.</p>

<p>Later rock art continued the stick-figure
techniques but presents them in much more
action oriented scenes. This style has been
called "Biographical." Hunting and battle
scenes seem to tell stories of actual events.
Scenes dating from postcontact times show
rectangular-bodied, round-headed warriors
brandishing guns and riding horses. Similar
scenes appear on the earliest known buffalo
robes and men's shirts. A robe collected by
Meriwether Lewis and William Clark on their
trip up the Missouri River in 1804 shows
the same kind of round-headed, rectangularbodied
stick figures as the rock art.</p>

<p>The earliest art, whether rock art or items
collected by visitors to the tribes, contains the
basic elements of Plains Indian art and shows
that the attitudes and aesthetics were very different
from European art. Unlike European
art, which included large paintings, sculptures,
and buildings designed to be regarded
as art, Plains Indian art was an integral part
of everyday life. Dresses, robes, moccasins,
tipis, and rawhide containers were functional
whether they were decorated or not, but the
decorations enhanced the object and brought
pleasure to the people who saw and used
them. Both men and women took pride in
being well dressed and living among beautiful
things.</p>

<p>The designs that were used on clothing and
household objects often had spiritual or sacred
aspects that connected the creator or the
user to tribal beliefs about the world. Plains
Indian cosmologies were highly complex, and
very simple abstract designs may have had
multiple meanings. One common Northern
Plains design was a circle composed of elongated
triangles painted to look like feathers.
The feathered circle represented both the sun
and the eagle-feather headdress worn by a
successful warrior.</p>

<p>Colors were associated with directions, and
directions were associated with sacred beings,
whose behavior influenced humans. Using the
right color could bring blessings from the
spiritual beings. Many different Plains tribes
believed that the thunderbird, often shown
as a winged, hourglass-shaped figure, caused
thunder by shaking its wings. If the bird appeared
to a man in a vision or dream, the man
could depict the being on a shield, and this
would protect him and increase his chances of
success in hunting and warfare.</p>

<p>Native American art also differed from European
art in its lack of concern with realism.
Today, many people still think that an artist
should be able to make a tree look just like a
tree, but Plains Indians did not think that way.
Because the designs often represented mystical
or cosmological elements, realism was not
a concern. Depicting a thunderbird as an
hourglass had the same meaning as showing a
bird with widespread wings. Nor was realism
necessary to meet the needs of biographical
art. A stick figure wearing a distinctive headdress
or carrying a unique shield was immediately
recognizable. Since realism was not a
goal, European ideas of perspective and spatial
ordering were not a part of Native American
art. When a man painted his war exploits
on his robe, he placed the scenes anywhere he
thought they looked best, paying little attention
to the shape of the robe or how the activities
would be seen by others. Because
Plains Indian art was so different from what
people trained in the European tradition were
used to, they considered the Indigenous art
childlike or primitive and paid little attention
to its meaning.</p>

<p>Another characteristic of Plains Indian art
was the fairly strict division between art made
and used by men and art made and used
by women. Although men and women sometimes
cooperated, women usually painted or
quilled very balanced, controlled geometric
designs on dresses, moccasins, robes, bags,
and containers. Men were responsible for the
human and animal figures that appeared in
the biographical or cosmological art, but
women's art had sacred meanings too. Designs
placed on women's clothes symbolized prayers
for a long life and healthy children. Quillwork
was considered a sacred art that a woman had
to have the right to do, or disaster would result.
Cheyenne and Lakota women gained the
right to do quillwork by becoming members
of societies in which the art was taught. A
woman who excelled in quillwork or other
women's arts was publicly honored in the
same way as a successful warrior.</p>

<p>The advent of glass beads and other new
materials brought changes to the arts, but
these were not as immediate or as far-reaching
as one might think. Traditional ideas about art
were maintained. Women skilled in sewing
porcupine quills found that glass beads were
not much different and continued to use the
old designs. In the Southern Plains, where the
porcupine was not found and quillwork had
not been developed, the tribes made sparing
use of beads and continued to color their
clothes with yellow or green paint. In the Central
and Northern Plains, however, tribes like
the Lakotas and Assiniboines covered large
portions of their garments with beaded designs
reminiscent of quillwork. In painting,
Indian men adopted the European idea of
shading to make forms more realistic but did
not use perspective or focal points in their
work. In the middle to late nineteenth century
men began to use paint, colored pencils, and
crayons on paper to record scenes of tribal
life. Called ledger paintings because many
were done on the lined pages taken from account
books, these works continued the traditions
of earlier times and formed a link to
modern Plains Indian painting.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">GENDER</hi>: <ref n="egp.gen.026">Native American Gender Roles</ref>.</p>


<closer>
<signed>Mary Jane Schneider<lb/>
University of North Dakota</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Berlo, Janet, ed. <title level="m">Plains Indian Drawings, 1865–1935: Pages from a Visual History</title>. New York: Harry N. Abrams, 1996.</bibl>
<bibl>Berlo, Janet, and Ruth B. Phillips. <title level="m">Native North American Art</title>. New York: Oxford University Press, 1998.</bibl> <bibl>Keyser,
James. "A Lexicon for Historic Plains Indian Rock Art:
Increasing Interpretive Potential." <title level="j">Plains Anthropologist</title> 32
(1987): 43–71.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>