<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.ct.027 SYSTEM "egp.ct.027.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ct.027">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">"Hell on Wheels" Towns</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Charles Vollan</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ct.027</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Vollan, Charles">Charles Vollan</author>. <title level="a">""Hell on Wheels" Towns."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">170-171</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-27</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">"HELL ON WHEELS" TOWNS</head>

<figure n="egp.ct.027" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Tent city, 16th Street, Cheyenne, Wyoming, 1867</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>When the Union Pacific Railroad crossed the
Plains, large numbers of workers, hangers-on,
and purveyors of vice congregated in temporary
boom communities known as "Hell on
Wheels." With few towns in existence along
the Union Pacific line, there was little for the
men to do, so professional gamblers, saloon
keepers, and prostitutes filled the void in entertainment,
building a reputation that lasts
to the present. By no means, though, did all
activity revolve around vice. In longer-lived
towns, literary clubs, religious gatherings, theatrical
offerings, and other activities were
common. Two communities coexisted in the
Hell on Wheels towns: the raucous railroad
builders and their followers and the businessoriented
class who hoped to remain and build
permanent communities.</p>

<p>The men building the Union Pacific Railroad
were often Irish immigrants, and many
were Civil War veterans of both Confederate
and Union sympathies. They were young and
often single, a combination that encouraged
violence and the available vices. Besides the
inevitable prostitutes, other female residents
were teachers, actresses, laundresses, cooks,
and hotel operators, but women were still few
in number.</p>

<p>The first "Hell on Wheels" town began near
Fort Kearny, Nebraska Territory, in August
1866, when the Union Pacific line met Dobeytown,
a settlement that existed to provide for
the soldiers' more earthy needs. Fort Kearny
(later just Kearney) and North Platte, Nebraska;
Julesburg, Colorado; Cheyenne, Laramie,
Green River City, and Benton, Wyoming;
and Bear River City and Corrine, Utah, were
among the primary towns.</p>

<p>A Hell on Wheels town was founded when
the line of the railroad became apparent. At
that point, merchants, aided by information
provided by railroad officials, and the more
enterprising residents of the last town moved
to establish a community they hoped would
be permanent but was usually temporary.
Within a few weeks, residents of the last town
would follow, leaving behind a small number
of people who hoped to found a permanent
city&#8211;North Platte declined in this manner
from a population of a few thousand to less
than 200. Sometimes departing residents left
only trash and mud chimneys behind. The
new community sprang to life as merchants of
everything from the mundane to the scandalous
quickly set up shop to receive the workers
they knew would soon arrive. Town populations
could rise from zero to thousands within
a few days.</p>

<p>Few permanent structures were built in
the towns. Most were tents with possibly a
wooden front wall to give the appearance of
solidity. Others were prefabricated and crude,
designed to be taken apart and put together
rapidly. Only in towns like Cheyenne, which
had been earmarked as a repair center, did
lasting buildings rise.</p>

<p>The towns provided virtually every service
a construction worker might want, from dentistry
and legal advice to gambling and prostitution.
Saloons existed in large numbers. A
tent more than 100 feet long, known as the "Big
Tent," provided one notable place to drink and
gamble as it followed the line. Dance houses
provided relatively wholesome contact with
women, while houses of prostitution also
thrived. Vice was lucrative and found a ready
market.</p>

<p>Merchants along the line made large fortunes,
providing goods not only to residents
of the towns but also to military posts and
the established city of Denver. Large capital-intensive
firms, such as dry goods and banking
concerns, followed the line from bases
in Denver, Chicago, and Omaha. Freighting
companies worked to connect the cities on the
line with Denver and with towns ahead of the
track. Some towns, including Cheyenne, featured
multiple newspapers, but most had only
the "Press on Wheels," otherwise known as
the <hi rend="italic">Frontier Index</hi>, which followed the line
from Fort Kearny to Bear River City.</p>

<p>While the towns violated the sexual and
moral codes of the era despite the existence
of law enforcement officers, quasi-legal and
legal courts, and several vigilance committees,
there was far less violence and open disregard
for convention than has been supposed. Newspaper
accounts show that while fights and killings
did occur, they did not do so on a daily
basis, despite repeated references in the historiography
to phrases like "a man for breakfast."</p>

<p>The traditional view that the towns lasted
only one or two months is only correct for the
later towns, built when the speed of construction
was greatest. Several towns endured, including
Kearney and Julesburg, both of which
had already existed in some form, and Cheyenne
and Laramie, which were chosen by the
Union Pacific for repair facilities or terminals
of branch lines. Others, including Bear River
City, disappeared, leaving behind little more
than a lingering reputation.</p>

<p>The Union Pacific's Hell on Wheels towns
seem to have been a unique phenomenon.
They did not exist on the Central Pacific Railroad,
which was built to meet the Union
Pacific from Sacramento, California, to Promontory
Point, Utah. The largely Chinese workforce
of the Central Pacific was less violent,
drunken, and ill behaved than that of the
Union Pacific, and the builders of the Central
Pacific appear to have exerted far greater control
over their line. The contemporaneous
Union Pacific–Eastern Division (later the
Kansas Pacific) likewise was not known for
producing wild construction towns. There
were previously existing towns, however, such
as Wallace and Hugo, Kansas, that provided
similar services.</p>

<p>For the builders of the Union Pacific these
towns were necessary&#8211;supplies and workers
needed to be organized in convenient locations. The theft of Union Pacific property, attempts
to squat on company land, and the
atmosphere of violence and disorder, however,
made the towns an example no other line
would follow.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Charles Vollan<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>