<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.na.117">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Trade</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Mark A. Eifler</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.na.117</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Eifler, Mark A.">Mark A. Eifler</author>. <title level="a">"Trade."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">606-607</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-20</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">TRADE</head>

<p>Native peoples of the Great Plains engaged in
trade between members of the same tribe, between
different tribes, and with the European
Americans who increasingly encroached upon
their lands and lives. Trade within the tribe
involved gift-giving, a means of obtaining
needed items and social status. Trade between
Plains tribes often took the form of an exchange
of products of the hunt (bison robes,
dried meat, and tallow) for agricultural products,
such as corn and squash. European and
American items, such as horses, guns, and
other metal products, were incorporated into
the existing Plains trade system after the seventeenth
century.</p>

<p>Trade among the Plains Indians has a long
history. The archeological record shows an active
trade in Knife River flint in the Northern
Plains beginning before 2000 <hi rend="smallcaps">B.C.</hi> Moreover,
copper, obsidian, and marine shell artifacts
suggest an existence of an early east–west trade
route crossing the Northern Plains and connecting
to the Great Lakes and the Atlantic
Coast in the east and the Rocky Mountains and
the Pacific Coast in the west. Farther south, the
people living along the lower Missouri, Arkansas,
and Red Rivers traded in copper and marine
shells with the Mississippi Valley people
after 2000 <hi rend="smallcaps">B.C.</hi> There is also evidence of local
trade for this period. While the Northern
Plains trade system remained relatively stable
throughout the following centuries, the Southern
and Central Plains trade patterns changed
dramatically around <hi rend="smallcaps">A.D.</hi> 1200, when the ties
between the Mississippi valley and the lower
Missouri, Arkansas, and Red River societies
were cut. Further changes came in the fourteenth
and fifteenth centuries, when the Southern
Plains societies began to trade in corn, pottery,
and bison products with the Pueblos of the
Southwest.</p>

<p>At the time of European contact, there were
two types of Native American trading sites
in the Great Plains. The first was associated
with permanent agricultural villages, including
those of the Mandans and Hidatsas in
present-day North Dakota and the Arikaras in
present-day South Dakota. These sites hosted
trading parties from the Crows, Shoshones
from the west, Assiniboines and Crees from
the north, and Plains Apaches, Cheyennes,
Arapahos, and Pawnees from the south. Lewis
and Clark, who wintered with the Mandans in
1804, noted that traders in the villages obtained
items from as far as Mexico and the Pacific
Coast. In the Southern Plains, the Wichita villages
on the Arkansas and Red Rivers served as
trading sites for Jumanos, Apaches, Comanches,
and Pawnees.</p>

<p>The second type of trading site was a trade
fair, or rendezvous, in which bands met to
exchange goods away from a permanent village,
generally at a point convenient to nomadic
bands. The Dakota rendezvous, held on
the James River in present-day South Dakota,
and the Shoshone rendezvous, held in southwestern
Wyoming, were regular trading fairs
at the beginning of the nineteenth century. A
major trading site&#8211;perhaps as important as
those at the Mandan, Hidatsa, and Arikara
villages&#8211;was operated by the Western Comanches
in the valley of the upper Arkansas
River from the 1740s to around 1830.</p>

<p>An integral part of the trade system was the
middlemen who operated between the various
trade centers. The Cheyennes served as intermediaries
between the upper Missouri villages
and the Southern Plains hunter-pastoralists
and carried firearms and other European
American goods to the south and horses to the
north. The Crows trafficked in horses and firearms
between the central upper Missouri and
the Shoshone rendezvous. The Assiniboines
and Plains Crees carried manufactured goods
to the upper Missouri from Canadian fur
traders and took back horses and corn. In the
Southern Plains, the Jumanos and Apaches
and later the Apaches and Comanches competed
for the lucrative middleman position between
the Wichitas and the Pueblos. By linking
the trade centers, these middleman groups
integrated the Plains tribes into a compact
commercial network that covered the whole
region.</p>

<p>The trade systems were maintained through a
variety of sustaining mechanisms, including
the calumet ceremony, redundancy trading, and
sign language. The calumet ceremony made unrelated
peoples one family through the working
of a fictional kinship. Leaders of different bands
or tribes adopted each other as father or son,
allowing trade to take place even between traditional
enemies. In such exchanges, tribes gained
access to foodstuffs that would otherwise have
been difficult to acquire. However, Native peoples
often exchanged corn for corn, or meat for
meat. The Pawnees, for example, traded corn
for corn with the Arikaras. This redundancy
trading was a security mechanism, setting up
avenues for exchange in case of local crop failure.
Sign language allowed linguistically diverse
tribes to negotiate the terms of the trade.</p>

<p>European traders began to engage in this
trade from the edges of the Plains. Spanish
settlers in Santa Fe exchanged goods of European
manufacture, such as beads, mirrors, and
blades, for hides, foodstuffs and services early
in the seventeenth century. British traders infiltrated
the network from the northeast, and
French and Spanish traders pushed up the Missouri
River from St. Louis in the late eighteenth
century. By the early nineteenth century, American
and British fur companies had created networks
of fixed trading posts throughout the
Missouri and Saskatchewan river drainage basins.
At these points European and American
manufactured products were exchanged for
bison robes, beaver pelts, and other furs and
skins. The Plains Indians became the primary
producers in an international trade system controlled
from New York and London. American
and Canadian traders also sought to bypass the
traditional middlemen and used alcohol as a
means to curry favor. The Indians would not
have participated if they had not valued the
introduced products (especially guns), but a dependency
on outside supplies was created, and
when there no longer were furs to trade the
Indians could not obtain the goods they had
come to rely upon.</p>

<p>The increased market demands resulted in
the collapse of the resource base. By 1840 beaver
had been eliminated from large parts of the
Plains, and the virtual destruction of the bison
herds in the 1870s brought an end to the traditional
Plains Indian trade. Restricted to reservations
in both Canada and the United States,
the Indians' trade was often a sale of annuity
goods, at inadequate prices, at the local trader's
store. Native American conventions of trade
continued, and continues, within tribes and in
contexts like powwows between tribes, but the
traditional Plains trade system that had endured
for so long fell victim to imposed European
American economies.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Mark A. Eifler</signed>
University of Portland</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>H&#228;m&#228;l&#228;inen, Pekka. "The Western Comanche Trade Center:
Rethinking the Plains Indian Trade System." <title level="j">Western
Historical Quarterly</title> 29 (1998): 485–513.</bibl> <bibl>Jablow, Joseph.
"The Cheyenne in Plains Indian Trade Relations 1795–
1840." In <title level="j">Monographs of the American Ethnological Society</title>.
Vol. 19. New York: J. J. Augustin Publisher, 1950.</bibl> <bibl>Swagerty,
William R. "Indian Trade in the Trans-Mississippi West to
1870." In <title level="j">Handbook of North American Indians</title>, 4:351–74.
Washington <hi rend="smallcaps">DC</hi>: Smithsonian Institution, 1988.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>