<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.pg.085 SYSTEM "egp.pg.085.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.pg.085">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Voting Patterns, United States</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>J. Clark Archer</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.pg.085</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Archer, J. Clark">J. Clark Archer</author>. <title level="a">"Voting Patterns, United States."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">693-694</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-05</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">VOTING PATTERNS, UNITED STATES</head>

<figure n="egp.pg.085" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Support for Republicans, as a percentage of total votes, in presidential elections from 1980 to 2000, by county, in the U.S. Great Plains</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>The voting patterns of the residents of the
American Great Plains demonstrate both the
distinctiveness of the political culture of the
Great Plains in relation to the political cultures
of other major regions of the United
States and the existence of discernible local
differences of political attitudes and habits
within the region itself. Such place-to-place
variations in political culture and behavior are
facilitated, and even in some respects encouraged,
by the federal democratic structure of
American governance in which national, state,
and local governments each have distinct
though overlapping roles and responsibilities.
The need for coordination across the three
major levels of the American federal system
has contributed to the predominance of a
two-party system of electoral competition at
federal, state, and local levels, although by
no means are all electoral contests fought under
party labels. The use of single-member-district
plurality-system elections to choose
members of the U.S. Congress, state legislatures,
and many local councils or commissions
also encourages two-party competition,
as does the complex indirect Electoral College
mechanism for electing the U.S. president.
But even so, the pressures toward political diversity
from one region or locality to the next
can and often do outweigh those pressures
that tend toward political uniformity within
the American federal republic.</p>

<p>Thus, coins engraved with the slogan "e
pluribus unum" are legal tender in the American
Great Plains, just as elsewhere within the
United States, but there is not one mind
among Great Plains residents nor among residents
of other regions over issues such as the
proportion of these coins that ought to be collected
in taxes, or the ends toward which the
tax monies ought to be expended. Of course,
elections are meant to provide citizens their
most important means of expressing their
views regarding just these sorts of issues.</p>

<p>When it comes to actually exercising their
rights and obligations of citizenship at the
polls, residents of the American Great Plains
are among the most energetic in the United
States. If national voter turnout in presidential
elections is expressed as a proportion of voting-age
population, which facilitates comparisons,
it can be noted that an average of 52.1
percent of potential voters in the nation as a
whole participated in the six presidential elections
from 1980 to 2000. In comparison, the
state-level average for the ten states of the
Great Plains was a presidential voter turnout
rate of 56.2 percent. Thus, when the ten Great
Plains states are considered together, it is
found that the region's potential voters have
been notably more likely to exercise their electoral
franchise in recent presidential elections
than voters in the nation as a whole.</p>

<p>But it is also important to observe that conspicuous
geographical differences exist within
the region itself. In particular, Central and
Northern Plains states tend to have much
higher turnout rates than do Southern Plains
states. On average for the 1980 to 2000 presidential
elections, more than 60 percent of
potential voters in the northernmost Plains
states of Montana (64.5 percent), North Dakota
(62.2 percent), and South Dakota (62.8
percent) cast ballots, compared with fewer
than 50 percent of potential voters in the
southernmost states of New Mexico (49.3 percent)
and Texas (45.2 percent). And the north-to-south
latitudes of the remaining states almost
perfectly correlate with their average
turnout levels as well, including those of Colorado
(56.6 percent), Kansas (56.7 percent),
Nebraska (56.7 percent), Oklahoma (52.0 percent),
and Wyoming (56.8 percent). This pattern
of lower voter participation in the Southern
Plains has appeared for most presidential
elections of the twentieth century, though differences
have diminished since the Voting
Rights Act of 1965 outlawed overt efforts to
disenfranchise potential minority voters.</p>

<p>The effects and aftereffects of the Civil War
and Reconstruction continued to be manifested
in the geographical patterns of party
preferences within the Great Plains well into
the twentieth century. Voters in former Confederate
or Confederate-leaning states south
of the thirty-seventh parallel, which separates
Colorado and Kansas from New Mexico and
Oklahoma, usually supported Democratic
candidates much more heavily than Republican
candidates. In contrast, voters in former
Union or Union-leaning Great Plains states
north of the thirty-seventh parallel were usually
much more inclined to support Republican
candidates, although there were notable
exceptions during the Greenback and Populist
revolts of the 1880s and 1890s. Roughly twenty
percentage points usually separated voters to
the north and south of this line right through
the New Deal era, when about three-quarters
of Southern Plains voters supported Franklin
D. Roosevelt's Democratic candidacy. In contrast,
Central and Northern Plains voters, who
had given Roosevelt a comfortable majority of
their votes in 1932 and 1936, gave greater preferences
to Republicans Wendell L. Willkie in
1940 and Thomas E. Dewey in 1944.</p>

<p>The second half of the twentieth century
saw significant changes in the geography of
voting within the region. The nomination of
World War II hero Gen. Dwight D. Eisenhower
of Kansas as the Republican presidential
candidate in 1952 served as a catalyst for
change in the Southern Plains. Despite their
traditional Democratic loyalties, small majorities
of voters in New Mexico, Oklahoma, and
Texas joined greater majorities north of the
thirty-seventh parallel to give Eisenhower a
sweeping victory throughout the Great Plains
over his Democratic rival, Adlai E. Stevenson,
in 1952. In 1956 Eisenhower's continued popularity
shrunk the difference in aggregate Republican
voter support north and south of the
thirty-seventh parallel from thirteen to seven
percentage points.</p>

<p>For the remainder of most of the twentieth
century, the aggregate differences in proportions
of popular support for Democratic or
Republican presidential candidates within the
Great Plains remained below seven percentage
points to the north and south of the thirty-seventh
parallel. The exceptions were in 1968,
when George C. Wallace's American Independent
candidacy made a differentially greater
impact among voters in the Southern Plains,
and in 1980, when John B. Anderson's Independent
candidacy made a differentially
greater impact among voters in the Central
and Northern Plains. In striking contrast to
earlier periods, voters in the Southern Plains
gave greater aggregate support to Republican
presidential candidates than to Democratic
ones in every election from 1980 to the close of
the twentieth century. Indeed, only once during
the second half of the twentieth century
did Great Plains voters in the region as a
whole give more of their ballots to a Democratic
than to a Republican presidential candidate.
That was in 1964, when Lyndon B. Johnson
of Texas led the Democratic ticket. In
essence, many voters living in the Southern
Plains lost their traditional aversion to the
Grand Old Party of the Republic during the
second half of the twentieth century. But in
the process there were also parallel changes in
the policy priorities of the national Democratic
and Republican Parties, to the extent
that such issues as civil rights or agrarian support,
which had been mainly Republican priorities
at the start of the twentieth century,
were at least as likely to be Democratic priorities
by the close of the century.</p>

<p>Although a majority of voters in the Great
Plains have supported Republican candidates
in presidential elections in recent years, there
nevertheless exist notable locational variations
in patterns of voter preferences at smaller geographical
scales within the region. As shown
on the map of average Republican support by
county for the six presidential elections from
1980 to 2000 (see p. 693), there is a large and
conspicuous subregion of very high Republican
support that extends northward from the Texas
Panhandle across western Kansas, throughout
central and western Nebraska, and into eastern
Wyoming. Within this zone, which is economically
dominated by ranching and irrigated
agriculture, county-level averages of 65
to 82 percent of voters supported Republican
candidates in the 1980 to 2000 elections. Other
smaller concentrations of very high average
Republican support also can be found in each
of the Great Plains states. Even in New Mexico,
which has been the most Democratic state in
the region, about half of all counties show
average levels of Republican support of 50 percent
or more for the 1980 to 2000 elections.
Indeed, of the total of 824 counties in the Great
Plains states, 626, or about three out of four,
exhibit Republican majorities on average for
the 1980 to 2000 elections. The remaining one
out of four counties that average less than majority
levels of support for Republican presidential
candidates tend to be found along the
margins of the Great Plains proper. The shadings
associated with counties in hillier subsections
of southeastern Oklahoma and eastern
Texas, together with those along the eastern
flank of the Rocky Mountains near the western
margin of the Plains, suggest a tendency toward
greater Democratic support with greater
local topographic relief. Traditional patterns
of party sentiment associated with marginal
agricultural or nonagricultural economic activities
that characterize these areas have perhaps
been reinforced by the in-migration of
persons of retirement age in recent years. In
several states, including the Central Great
Plains states of Kansas, Nebraska, and Colorado,
isolated counties with larger cities or
higher proportions of college or university
populations tend to show lower levels of average
Republican support than do surrounding
agrarian counties. But the counties exhibiting
the very lowest levels of Republican support,
involving averages of 17 to 34 percent Republican
voting in the 1980 to 2000 presidential
elections, usually are those with very high proportions
of Native American or Latino populations.
Indeed, the two Plains counties with
the very lowest levels of Republican support in
1980 to 2000 are Shannon County, South Dakota,
which contains the Pine Ridge Indian
Reservation, and Starr County, Texas, a generally
rural county in the lower Rio Grande Valley.
In these economically depressed counties,
an average of four of five voters cast their ballots
in support of Democratic candidates in
the presidential elections from 1980 to 2000.</p>

<closer>
<signed>J. Clark Archer<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Archer, J. Clark, Stephen J. Lavin, Kenneth C. Martis, and
Fred M. Shelley. <title level="m">Atlas of American Politics, 1960–2000</title>.
Washington <hi rend="smallcaps">DC</hi>: Congressional Quarterly Press, 2002.</bibl>
<bibl>Elazar, Daniel J. "Political Culture on the Plains," <title level="j">Western
Historical Quarterly</title> 11 (1980): 261–83.</bibl> <bibl>Shelley, Fred M.,
J. Clark Archer, Fiona M. Davidson, and Stanley D.
Brunn. <title level="m">Political Geography of the United States</title>. New York:
Guilford Press, 1996.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>