<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ag.040">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Fertilized Acreage</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Jessica G. Davis</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ag.040</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Davis, Jessica G.">Jessica G. Davis</author>. <title level="a">"Fertilized Acreage."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">45-46</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-12-18</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">FERTILIZED ACREAGE</head>

<p>Fertilizer use plays an essential role in maintaining
the agricultural productivity of the
Great Plains. Eliminating fertilizer in just one
year would reduce corn yields by 40 percent
and wheat yields by 10 percent. Fertilizer use
in the region has increased dramatically in recent
decades. From 1975 to 1995, nitrogen fertilizer
(the most commonly used fertilizer on
the Plains) use increased by more than 250
percent, phosphorus fertilizer use by about
50 percent, and potassium fertilizer use by
more than 1,200 percent. The Canadian Prairie
Provinces use about one-third of the total
fertilizer applied in the Great Plains region.
The most common forms of fertilizer used in
the region are urea and anhydrous ammonia
as nitrogen forms, monoammonium phosphate
as phosphorus fertilizer, and muriate
of potash as potassium fertilizer. Manure is
also used as a fertilizer and soil amendment
on cropland located near livestock production
facilities.</p>

<p>Fertilizer utilization practices change from
north to south in the Great Plains. Farmers
tend to apply more fertilizer prior to planting
and to apply more fertilizer through irrigation
systems in the southern part of the region. In
the Northern Great Plains, more fertilizer is
applied at planting or after planting, and applying
the fertilizer in a concentrated band is
more common (as opposed to a broadcast application).
In addition, the use of phosphorus
fertilizer declines in the Southern Plains,
where it is more common for farmers to apply
nitrogen fertilizer at rates that are below those
recommended by agricultural laboratories
and crop consultants. Geographically, areas
where more than 90 percent of harvested
cropland is fertilized include the Red River
Valley of the North and adjacent eastern
North Dakota and many counties in a belt
stretching from central Nebraska through
central Oklahoma.</p>

<p>The type of crops grown has a significant
impact on fertilizer use in the Great Plains.
Farmers tend to apply higher rates of nitrogen
fertilizer and use phosphorus and potassium
more often in corn production than in winter
wheat production. There is good reason for
this: corn removes considerably higher levels
of these nutrients from the soil than does
wheat. Soil testing is recommended as a basis
on which to make fertilizer decisions. Great
Plains farmers tend to use soil testing more
in cornfields (49 percent) than in winter
wheat fields (18 percent). Since corn requires
a higher investment and has higher potential
for economic return, this makes good economic
sense.</p>

<p>Irrigation also has a significant impact on
fertilizer use. Irrigated crops produce higher
yields and remove more nutrients from the
soil than dryland crops. Therefore, farmers
tend to apply phosphorus fertilizer more
often and apply greater amounts of nitrogen
and potassium fertilizer to irrigated crops.
Irrigated corn is soil-tested more commonly
(84 percent) than dryland corn (29 percent).
In general, more profitable crops are usually
managed more intensely and fertilized more
heavily.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Jessica G. Davis<lb/>
Colorado State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>