<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.ea.012 SYSTEM "egp.ea.012.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ea.012">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">German Russians</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Renee M. Laegreid</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ea.012</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Laegreid, Renee M.">Renee M. Laegreid</author>. <title level="a">"German Russians."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">232</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-04</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">GERMAN RUSSIANS</head>

<figure n="egp.ea.012" rend="granted">
<figDesc>German Russians hoeing beets somewhere in western Nebraska, early 1910s.</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>German Russians are a unique group of Germans
who lived in Russia after the 1760s and
began their immigration onto the Great Plains
in the 1870s. In 1762 Catherine the Great of
Russia launched an aggressive campaign to
entice skilled farmers into the Volga region to
turn the area into a productive agricultural
region and to create a human buffer zone
against the persistent threat of Asian marauders.
She offered transportation money
and various privileges: freedom of religion, no
military service, protection of culture and language,
and the option to leave if they became
unhappy with their situation. Approximately
23,184 settlers took advantage of the offer. The
greatest number came from areas heavily
damaged by years of war&#8211;Hess, the Rhineland,
and the Palatinate. Between 1764 and
1768, 104 mother colonies along the Volga
River were settled. Between 1804 and 1824
more Germans, mostly from the Danzig region
of West Prussia, accepted the same privileges
from Czar Alexander I and began farming
colonies along the north littoral of the
Black Sea.</p>

<p>In the late 1860s, as the trend toward nationalism
swept across Europe, Alexander II
began to rescind German Russian privileges;
by 1871 the only privilege left was their opportunity
to leave. The first wave of emigration
out of Russia corresponded with the grace period
before conscription into the Russian
army began. Between 1873 and 1914 approximately
115,000 German Russians immigrated
to the United States and about 150,000 to
western Canada.</p>

<p>German Russians settled in the Great Plains
as they had in Russia, according to their Evangelical,
Catholic, or Mennonite faith. In towns
where German Russians from more than one
village congregated they tended to cluster together,
reproducing their home villages in
Russia, and for the first few generations there
was little intermarriage between groups. The
tradition of large families also continued&#8211;
eight children or more was not uncommon.</p>

<p>Railroad companies were instrumental in
moving the German Russians onto the Plains
with offers of cheap land. The land tenure system
in Russia, however, often determined the
ability to farm in the Plains. Those from the
Volga region lived under the muir system,
where land was held in common by the colony
and distributed according to family size.
Without money from land sales in Russia to
purchase railroad land, and with homesteading
mostly taken, Volga Germans often found
work in Plains railroad towns as day laborers
or as migrant farm workers. Over time, some
families were able to save enough money to
purchase farms.</p>

<p>Terms of immigration to Russia during the
era of Alexander I did allow Black Sea German
Russians to buy and sell land. Although not
wealthy, these German Russians often purchased
farmland or started businesses in town
when they arrived in the Plains. Those who
worked the land found the Plains environmentally
similar to their Russian homeland,
and the crops and agricultural practices they
had developed to cope with those semiarid
conditions worked well on their new Plains
farms.</p>

<p>According to 1910 U.S. census data (here aggregated
by country), of the approximately
101,808 German Russians who lived in the
states that are wholly or partly in the Great
Plains region, nearly 85 percent lived in
the Plains proper. The largest concentration
of German Russians was in North Dakota
(31,910), followed by Kansas (15,311), South Dakota
(13,189), and Nebraska (13,020). Of the
states in which the Great Plains is only partly
included, 5,138 German Russians lived in the
Colorado Plains from a state total of 13,616;
78 percent of Oklahoma's German Russians
(4,159) found land in the Plains after Oklahoma
Territory opened up to white settlement;
and 60 percent of Montana's German Russian
population (1,309), 76 percent of Wyoming's
(578), and 46 percent of New Mexico's (106)
lived in the Plains portions of those states.</p>

<p>Accurate statistical data on German Russians
immigrating to Canada are more difficult
to determine. It is estimated, however,
that by 1910 approximately 44 percent of all
German settlers in western Canada were Germans
from Russia. Movement into Canada
began in 1874 when Mennonite settlers, denied
their request for closed, block settlements
in the United States, chose to settle the Prairies
of southern Manitoba. Although disapproving
of block settlements, the Canadian government
was anxious to populate the new
province and granted the Mennonites their
request. This set the precedent for the creation
of a mosaic of sizable ethnic islands in the
Canadian Prairies. While some mixed-group
settlements were established, most of the German
Russian groups settled in block communities
that were based on religion&#8211;Catholic,
Evangelical, or Mennonite&#8211;and area of origin
in Russia—Black Sea or Volga region.</p>

<p>The success of the Mennonite farmers attracted
the attention of prospective immigrants
from Russia as well as second- and
third-generation German Russians from the
United States. By 1962 Saskatchewan had 132
German Russian settlements, Manitoba had
27 settlements (and also the largest number of
mixed settlements within a province), and Alberta
had 14 German Russian settlements.</p>

<p>Overall, Black Sea Germans found it easier
than Volga Germans to assimilate into Plains
communities. Because of their location in
Russia close to the trade centers of the Black
Sea, they were more familiar with modern
capitalist trends. The Volga Germans, by contrast,
had lived isolated in the interior for almost
100 years. Their lack of familiarity with
capitalist society inhibited assimilation. Their
reluctance to learn English, as well as their
premodern work habits&#8211;pulling children out
of school to work and women working alongside
men in the beet fields&#8211;were significant
factors in the discrimination against them.</p>

<p>Until 1914, as immigrants worked frantically
to bring other family members out of
Russia, the flow of new Germans from Russia
onto the Plains helped to replenish their Old
World culture. World War I effectively ended
immigration and encouraged assimilation;
however, strong German Russian communities
still exist.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">ARCHITECTURE</hi>: <ref n="egp.arc.005">Black Sea German Architecture</ref>; <ref n="egp.arc.051">Volga German Architecture</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Renee M. Laegreid<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Bassler, Gerhard. <title level="m">The German Canadian Mosaic Today and Yesterday: Identity, Roots, and Heritage</title>. Ottawa:
German-Canadian Congress, 1991.</bibl> <bibl>Hale, Douglas. <title level="m">The Germans from Russia in Oklahoma</title>. Norman: University of
Oklahoma Press, 1980.</bibl> <bibl>Koch, Fred C. <title level="m">The Volga Germans in Russia and the Americas from 1763 to the Present</title>. University
Park: Pennsylvania State University Press, 1977.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>