<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fil.015">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Custer Films</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Dan Gagliasso</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fil.015</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Gagliasso, Dan">Dan Gagliasso</author>. <title level="a">"Custer Films."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">263-264</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-12</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">CUSTER FILMS</head>
<figure n="egp.fil.015" rend="granted" type="noclick">
<figDesc>Custer films</figDesc>
</figure>        

<p>Hollywood has never felt particularly compelled
to film its representations of Bvt. Maj.
Gen. George Armstrong Custer's last battle at
the Little Big Horn anywhere near where the
actual epic 1876 battle occurred. But it is surprising
to note that in at least some instances a
few celluloid Custers and Sitting Bulls actually
performed their cinematic battles before the
cameras at various locales somewhere in between
the Rocky Mountains and the muddy
waters of the Missouri River.</p>

<p>On film George Armstrong Custer almost
always has wielded an anachronistic saber,
worn the wrong uniform, flown the wrong
flags, and fired inaccurate pistols. But sometimes,
in spite of a lack of historical accuracy,
Custer's Last Stand on film has created a
unique audience-pleasing celluloid world of
its own making. Most film professionals take
the viewpoint that historical films are more
about the perception of history, not about
documentary duplication of the event. And
these very same directors, producers, writers,
and actors have been more than willing to
knowingly bend, alter, and even fabricate Custer
filmland fiction to further a pet political
viewpoint, give a vicarious thrill, or make a
fast box office buck. Trying to convey a real
sense of the Plains Indians Wars of the 1870s to
an impressionable public has seldom been
their concern.</p>

<p>The very first Custer film, William Selig's
Custer's <title>Last Stand</title> (1909), utilized footage of a
reenactment shot near the real Montana battle
site intercut with scenes done in Selig's Chicago
studio. But it didn't take long for early
producers to discover the balmy climate of
Southern California. The very next Custer
film, Thomas Ince's 1912 production of <title>Custer's Last Fight</title>, was lensed amidst the rolling hills of
Santa Monica. Ince had convinced the 101 Wild
West Show troupe to winter in California so he
could make use of their performers and rolling
stock in a series of frontier-themed films.</p>

<p>Of the sixty-seven motion pictures and
thirty-some television representations of Custer,
at least a handful were actually filmed in
southeastern Montana or nearby South Dakota,
the real-life haunts of the Seventh Cavalry
and their Sioux and Cheyenne adversaries.
<title>In the Days of '75 and '76</title> (1915) was
filmed in South Dakota utilizing a local National
Guard unit to portray Custer's Seventh
Cavalry. Victor Mature's thespian representation
of <title>Chief Crazy Horse</title> in Universal's 1957
film of the same name shot its brief Little Big
Horn sequence right in the middle of the
Black Hills.</p>

<p>Central Oregon was an adequate visual substitute
for the Little Big Horn valley in <title>The Flaming Frontier</title> (1926) and Walt Disney's
<title>Tonka</title> (1958). <title>The Scarlet West</title> in 1925 and <title>The Last Frontier</title> in 1926 opted for the picturesque
mesas of southwestern Colorado and southeastern
Utah. <title>Bob Hampton of Placer</title> (1920)
did an unusual combination of filming on
the Blackfeet Reservation near Glacier National
Park, Montana, and Fort Huachuca in
southern Arizona, where the all-black enlisted
men of the famed Tenth Cavalry stood in
for the Seventh Cavalry in vast panoramic
shots filmed from high atop a hovering signal
balloon.</p>

<p>Cecil B. De Mille's 1936 epic, <title>The Plainsman</title>,
staged most of the film's large-scale battle
scenes with a second unit near the Tongue
River in Montana, only to see most of that
footage then used as back projection for principal
scenes filmed at sound stages on the Paramount
lot in Los Angeles. When Paramount
revisited the Custer battle with <title>Warpath</title> in
1951, the same Tongue River area was used
again along with a partial reconstruction of
Fort Abraham Lincoln built at the Montana
State Fairgrounds in Billings.</p>

<p>The most famous celluloid Custer motion
picture, Errol Flynn's starring vehicle <title>They Died with Their Boots On</title> (1941), was shot exclusively
on the Warner Bros. Studio Ranch in
Agoura, California, a scant twenty miles from
Warner's main lot in the Los Angeles suburb
of Burbank. No film has had more influence
on the public's perception of Custer than this
epic, until the release of <title>Little Big Man</title> in 1970.
If Errol Flynn's Custer is rambunctious and
overzealous, he is also loyal and courageous,
all traits that, whatever else his faults, the real
Custer exhibited time and again. If the film
is incredibly inaccurate history, the tone of
Flynn's characterization still rings quite true
of the real man.</p>

<p>Since 1970 filmmakers have tried to get as
close to filming on the real battlefield as possible. <title>Little Big Man</title> (1970), <hi rend="smallcaps">ABC</hi>'s miniseries of Evan Connell's best-selling book, <title>Son of the Morning Star</title> (1991), and tnt's cable television movie <title>Crazy Horse</title> (1995) were all shot in the Billings and Hardin areas, just a stone's throw away from the hallowed marble markers on the real Custer Hill. But in 1997, when Robert Redford wanted to feature the current Little Big Horn National Battlefield in his contemporary western <title>The Horse Whisperer</title>, he had his art director build a modern-day representation
near Livingston, Montana, 140 miles
west of the actual location.</p>

<p>Perhaps therein lies the magic of Hollywood's
enduring fascination with Custer.
Whether Custer is a hero or a villain, a major
character or a minor supporting player, his
buckskin jacket and long hair are immediately
recognizable. For some these objects represent
the white man's sins; for others they are the
visual representation of heroic legend and
myth. Custer's appeal on a medium like film is
obvious; he is the most adaptable of visual
symbols that represent the American West.
Villain, hero, fool, misunderstood warrior,
whatever the times have called for, filmmakers
have molded George Custer into the figure that
best suited their needs. There is no reason to
think that will change in the future.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">IMAGES AND ICONS</hi>: 
<ref n="egp.ii.017">Custer, George Armstrong</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Dan Gagliasso<lb/>
National Cowboy Hall of Fame</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Dippie, Brian W. <title level="m">Custer's Last Stand: Anatomy of an American Myth</title>. Missoula: University of Montana Press, 1976.</bibl>
<bibl>Gagliasso, Daniel L. <title level="m">The Celluloid Custer</title>. Lincoln: University
of Nebraska Press, 2000.</bibl> <bibl>Hutton, Paul Andrew. "Correct
in Every Detail." <title level="j">Montana, the Magazine of the Western History</title> 41 (1991): 28–54.</bibl>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>