<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.war.001">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">War</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Michael L. Tate</author>
<author>Jo Lea Wetherilt Behrens</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.war.001</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Tate, Michael L.">Michael L. Tate</author> and <author n="Behrens, Jo Lea Wetherilt">Jo Lea Wetherilt Behrens</author>. <title level="a">"War."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">817-822</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-26</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">WAR</head>

<p>The Great Plains has been home to a great
diversity of peoples for thousands of years.
Although coexistence and commerce have
dominated most of the relationships among
these divergent populations, intermittent conflict
has also defined these contacts. Intertribal
warfare among Native Americans involved a
fluctuating pattern of alliances and attacks, as
tribes attempted to protect their resources, attain
powerful positions within trading networks,
and expand their domination over
larger areas. Raids directed against neighboring
peoples also secured wealth, gained
captives for trade and adoption, and allowed
warriors a mechanism for proving their courage
and enhancing their personal honor. Despite
the relative frequency of these raids,
casualties were minimized, except when
groups were fighting for survival, or where
vengeance demanded bloody retribution.</p>

<p>By the early eighteenth century the European
colonial powers of Spain, France, and
Great Britain had established relationships
with Plains tribes through an extended network
of trade. A variety of trade goods was
introduced into Indian communities, but the
horse and gun had the greatest impact. Horses
increased mobility, bringing more tribes into
conflict over resources and producing a new
style of mounted raid and counter-raid. Firearms,
although initially scarce and inferior to
bows and arrows in durability, soon became
highly prized objects for warriors and as barter
items within intertribal trade.</p>


<div2>

<head type="sub">Spanish and Mexican Periods</head>

<p>Because the colonial powers did not attempt
to occupy the Great Plains during the eighteenth
century, their impact there was largely
measured by the strength of their Indian alliances.
In the summer of 1720, when Spanish
authorities learned of an alleged French penetration
of trading zones in the Central Plains,
they dispatched Don Pedro de Villasur with
forty-two soldiers and sixty Pueblo auxiliaries
from Santa Fe to present-day Nebraska. On
August 14, Pawnees and Otoes launched a surprise
attack by firing a volley from muskets.
Only thirteen of Villasur’s men escaped. As a
result the Spaniards withdrew their trading
interests to the Southern Plains.</p>

<p>Thirty-seven years later, Spanish authorities
in Texas attempted to spread their influence
beyond the narrow coastal belt that linked settlements
in the Rio Grande Valley with those
in East Texas. Col. Diego Ortiz Parrilla led
approximately 400 soldiers, settlers, and missionaries
to found the Mission Santa Cruz de
San Sabá and a nearby presidio on the San
Saba River near present-day Menard, Texas.
They hoped to win converts and allies among
the Lipan Apaches and other nomadic Indians
of West Texas, but the mission was too far
southeast to attract many neophytes. Most
importantly, the overt diplomacy between
Spaniards and Lipan Apaches antagonized
Comanche bands, who had a long-standing
feud with the latter and opposed any disruption
in their growing dominance of western
Texas. Two Comanche attacks against the settlement
in 1758 and 1759 left several dozen defenders
dead, crops destroyed, and the mission
burned.</p>

<p>Drawing a force of more than 600 Spanish
soldiers and Indian auxiliaries from as far away
as San Antonio, Ortiz Parrilla attacked the Comanches
and allied Wichitas at their fortified
village of Tawehash on the Red River. The large
numbers of Indians repulsed the attack of October
7, 1759, sent Ortiz Parrilla into a full
retreat, and compelled Spanish authorities to
give up their hopes of a mission settlement on
the periphery of the Texas Plains. Periodic
punitive expeditions dispatched from southern
Texas and the Rio Grande settlements of
New Mexico occasionally inflicted significant
casualties among the Comanches, Kiowas, and
Apaches, but Spain failed to dominate the
Southern Plains at the time of Mexican Independence
in 1821. Mexican leaders inherited
this volatile situation and continued Spanish
strategies of diplomacy, trade, and occasional
military forays with about the same degree of
effectiveness.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">American Military Exploration and Manifest Destiny</head>

<p>As the nineteenth century dawned, Americans
received their first impressions of the Great
Plains through the reports of military explorers
and civilian artists. The 1804-6 reconnaissance
of Capt. Meriwether Lewis and Lt. William
Clark up the Missouri River and to the
Oregon coast whetted America's collective appetite
to learn more about the exotic lands.
Although private traders and trappers made
the first regular transits of the Plains in the
1820s, it was army officers who provided the
best written records of the vast area. Zebulon
Pike's 1806 journey across the Central Plains
and Stephen Long's 1819-20 westward march
along the Platte River and return along the
Canadian River provided important scientific
information. Unfortunately, their complex
conclusions were oversimplified by a popular
literature that emphasized Long's restricted
phrase "Great American Desert" as if it implied
that the entire Great Plains was a vast
wasteland.</p>

<p>Although large numbers of settlers did not
move into the region until after the Civil War,
the Army Topographical Engineers opened
new trails, discovered marketable resources,
and sought to impress resident Native Americans
with American power. Capt. John C. Fr&#233;mont's
major explorations of the Plains and
Far West during the 1840s paved the way for
overlanders to the Pacific Coast and heightened
tensions between the United States and
Mexico. Espousing a philosophy of manifest
destiny, which proclaimed American superior
virtues and moral authority over Hispanic
institutions, proponents of expansionism
viewed the Mexican American War of
1846–48 as a golden opportunity to annex
Mexican territory. Although no battles occurred
in the Plains during this relatively brief
war, the region served as a conduit for moving
soldiers and supplies to arenas of combat in
New Mexico and California.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Plains Indian Campaigns in the 1850s</head>

<p>After the Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo, which
ended the Mexican American War in 1848, the
government turned its attention to Indian affairs
within the Great Plains and the Far West.
The 1850s witnessed a flurry of treaty signings
that placed many Plains Indians on reservations
and limited others to ill-defined hunting
ranges. New military posts were rapidly added
to the Plains, especially in Texas, where an expanding
white population demanded protection,
and in Indian Territory, where the removed
tribes demanded that the nomadic
Comanches and Kiowas be corralled.</p>

<p>Military budgets and troop authorizations
remained too small to meet the growing task.
In 1853 there were only 10,495 men in the army.
Fully four-fifths of them were stationed west of
the Mississippi River, with the majority seeing
service in the Plains. Some posts, such as Fort
Kearny and Fort Laramie, guarded the welltraveled
trail along the Platte River. Others,
such as Fort Leavenworth, Kansas, were rearguard
posts that coordinated the rotation of
men and supplies to more remote places. And
still others, particularly in Texas, were established
in interlocking arrangements of interior
and exterior forts that could protect exposed
frontier settlements against Indian raids. Many
of these stations never achieved more than
temporary status.</p>

<p>Although no sustained Indian wars occurred
in the Plains during the 1850s, significant
military campaigns were launched. Most
of the problems were initiated by white treaty
violations and government misunderstandings
about Indian intentions. In August 1854
an overzealous and inexperienced Lt. John L.
Grattan tried to arrest a Lakota warrior for
killing a Mormon emigrant’s cow near Fort
Laramie. When negotiations with Brule Lakota
leader Conquering Bear failed, Grattan
began firing into the Indian encampment, killing
Conquering Bear. Grattan’s entire command
of thirty men was wiped out. In response,
on September 3, 1855, a 600-man force
commanded by Col. William S. Harney attacked
the village of Little Thunder at Ash Hollow,
killing approximately eighty-five inhabitants
and capturing another seventy women
and children. This overreactive strike only
bred more resentment and retaliatory raids
against innocent Americans passing through
the area to California and Oregon.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Bleeding Kansas and Civil War</head>

<p>In addition to campaigns against Plains Indians,
the army saw service in the slavery conflict
that spilled over into the Great Plains. In
Kansas during the 1850s, proslavery and antislavery
factions vied with each other for control
of county governments and the territorial
legislature. Tirades gave way to civil insurrection
during the era known as "Bleeding Kansas"
between 1856 and 1861. Because federal
officials could not count on an impartial territorial
militia to stand above the contentious
slavery debate, they had to rely on army officers
to separate the feuding factions. This
thankless task garnered enemies on both sides
for the army while simultaneously overtaxing
military strength that was needed in other
frontier areas. For instance, several companies
of the Second U.S. Cavalry had to be rotated
out of northwestern Texas during 1857 for civil
duty in eastern Kansas. This occurred just at
the crucial time when additional soldiers were
needed to protect two newly created Indian
agencies on and near the Clear Fork of the
Brazos. The agencies lay exposed to attacks
by angry frontiersmen who ultimately drove
the peaceful Caddo and southern Comanche
bands into present-day western Oklahoma.</p>

<p>The most significant Civil War battle between
Plains troops occurred in late March
1862 approximately twenty-five miles east of
Santa Fe, New Mexico. Confederate troops
commanded by Gen. Henry Sibley had fought
a series of successful battles and skirmishes up
the Rio Grande Valley as they attempted to
wrest New Mexico from Union hands. This
operation represented the first leg of a Confederate
plan to push their control into Colorado
and as far west as the California coast. At
the Battle of Glorieta Pass, Union regular and
militia forces under Col. John P. Slough and
Maj. John M. Chivington destroyed Sibley’s
supply train and inflicted a major defeat on
rebel forces. This "Gettysburg of the West"
proved decisive not in terms of casualties
(fewer than seventy men were killed in the
battle), but in terms of forcing the supplystarved
Confederates out of New Mexico and
ending their dream of a southwestern empire.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Plains Indian Wars, 1865-1890</head>

<p>Meanwhile, as Americans fought each other,
on November 29, 1864, Col. John M. Chivington
and his Colorado Volunteers massacred at
least 150 Southern Cheyennes and Arapahos
(most of them women, children, and elderly)
belonging to Black Kettle's band at Sand Creek,
Colorado. This massacre propelled the Central
and Northern Great Plains toward a heightened
Indian-American confrontation after the
Civil War.</p>

<p>At the end of the Civil War, the U.S. Army
mustered almost a million men out of service.
By 1874, at the height of the Great Plains Indian
Wars, the entire army consisted of only
25,000 enlisted men and approximately 2,000
o.cers. Inadequate budgets frequently led to
deterioration of quarters and equipment, slow
promotions, poor pay, and a general decline
in morale.</p>

<p>Government policy in the late nineteenth
century aimed at removing Plains Indians
from the path of white settlement, placing
them on isolated reservations, and promoting
an assimilation program designed to wean
them away from traditional ways. Native
Americans resisted this concentrated assault
on their land base and cultures, and the Great
Plains provided the setting for some of the
most determined resistance anywhere in the
nation's history.</p>

<p>Hatreds left from the 1862 Sioux Uprising in
Minnesota and the Sand Creek Massacre still
seethed in the Northern Plains in 1866 when
the government dispatched Col. Henry Carrington
to build three posts in the prime bison
range of the Powder River country. Forts Reno,
Phil Kearny, and C. F. Smith soon guarded the
Bozeman Trail, which led to the mining camps
of western Montana. Lakota Sioux leaders such
as Red Cloud opposed this incursion. On December
21, 1866, Sioux, Cheyenne, and Arapaho
warriors killed eighty soldiers under
Capt. William J. Fetterman near Fort Phil
Kearny. Subsequent attacks against troops
from Fort C. F. Smith (Hayfield Fight, August
1, 1867) and Fort Phil Kearny (Wagon Box
Fight, August 2, 1867) failed only because out-numbered
soldiers were able to maximize their
firepower with rapid fire, breech-loading
Springfield rifles. Unable to adequately protect
the bloody Bozeman Trail, the government
signed the Fort Laramie Treaty in 1868. Among
the guarantees to the Indians was the army's
abandonment of its three new posts.</p>

<p>In the Southern Great Plains, the Medicine
Lodge Treaty of October 1867 unrealistically
assigned specific ranges of land to the Comanches,
Kiowas, Southern Cheyennes, and Arapahos,
but not until after several military
campaigns had forced the issue. Maj. Gen.
Winfield Scott Hancock led the way with a
spring 1867 operation across western Kansas
involving approximately 1,400 soldiers and
militiamen. This huge force did little to stop
the increasing Indian depredations or to convince
the Southern Cheyennes that the government's
word could be trusted.</p>

<p>Following this failure, Gen. Philip Sheridan
organized a winter 1868 campaign across the
western areas of Indian Territory against the
same Southern Cheyenne and Arapaho bands.
This operation culminated in Lt. Col. George
Armstrong Custer's November 27, 1868, attack
on Black Kettle's village on the Washita River.
Black Kettle, who still represented a mostly
peaceful group of people, was killed.</p>

<p>The final chapter in the Southern Plains
confrontations emerged in the Red River War
of 1874–75, which pitted 1,400 soldiers of five
converging columns against the most defiant
bands of Comanches, Kiowas, and Southern
Cheyennes. The purpose of converging columns
was to squeeze the elusive Indians into a
confined area, burn their villages and equipment,
capture part of their large horse herds,
and inflict a major battlefield defeat on them.
Although several dozen engagements occurred
during these operations, the decisive battle
came at Palo Duro Canyon in the Texas Panhandle.
Col. Ranald S. Mackenzie achieved the
element of surprise by moving 450 cavalrymen
from the canyon's dry rim into the verdant
valley where Comanches and Kiowas possessed
adequate food, water, and forage to wait
out their enemy. Mackenzie’s bold strike of
September 28, 1874, resulted in few casualties
on either side, but he burned the camp and
slaughtered more than 1,000 Indian horses and
mules. Without the ability to operate in their
former Panhandle strongholds during the
winter, the various bands gradually headed for
the reservation at Fort Sill in western Indian
Territory. The war in the Southern Plains was
virtually over.</p>

<p>With men and resources now available for a
similar sweep of the Northern Plains, Sheridan
ordered a general campaign against the
Teton Sioux, Northern Cheyennes, and Arapahos
during the summer of 1876. Three converging
cavalry and infantry columns under
Gen. Alfred Terry, Gen. George Crook, and
Col. John Gibbon moved to the Yellowstone
River in eastern Montana. Crook made the
first contact on June 17 in the Battle of the
Rosebud, and although he claimed victory, he
and his 1,200-man command were compelled
to retreat southward into Wyoming to await
reinforcements.</p>

<p>Meanwhile, General Terry ordered his
second-in-command, Lieutenant Colonel Custer
and the Seventh Cavalry, to conduct a reconnaissance
up Rosebud Creek and locate any
signs of an expected Indian encampment.
Scouts reported the village directly west on
Little Bighorn, and the Seventh attacked it on
June 25, 1876. Unlike previous attacks against
lightly defended Plains Indian camps, the soldiers
here faced perhaps 1,500 warriors. Custer
and approximately 250 of his cavalrymen
were killed that day in what Indians referred
to as the Battle of the Greasy Grass, and eastern
newspapers called Custer's Last Stand.</p>

<p>This greatest single victory by Plains Indians
proved to be the beginning of the end
for their freedom. A determined Congress and
Sheridan ordered the army to continue a relentless
winter campaign. One by one, the various
bands found their camps destroyed at
places such as Slim Buttes, South Dakota
(September 9, 1876), and Red Fork of the Powder
River, Wyoming (November 25, 1876). By
May 1877 Crazy Horse had brought some of
the last roaming groups of Oglala Lakotas into
the Pine Ridge Agency, and Sitting Bull found
temporary protection in Saskatchewan, Canada,
for his followers. Dull Knife’s Northern
Cheyennes surrendered and were sent for the
time being to an unhealthy reservation in
western Indian Territory. Most of the Arapahos
were transferred to the Wind River Reservation
in western Wyoming.</p>

<p>During the following thirteen years, Indians
on Plains reservations found themselves
subject to a fast-changing world that was anti-thetical
to their cultural values and threatened
their very survival. In this environment of
poverty and death the Ghost Dance found a
deeply devoted following among the Northern
Plains tribes. Many Sioux converted to the
new teaching, which promised a return to the
old days that existed before the white man had
spread over the land. As the number of faithful
increased, paranoia grew among agents
and settlers bordering the Sioux reservations.
Soldiers began to concentrate in western areas
of Nebraska and the Dakotas during the fall of
1890, just as frontier newspapers stirred up
anti-Indian hysteria.</p>

<p>The December 15, 1890, killing of Hunkpapa
Lakota leader Sitting Bull by tribal police
precipitated the panicked flight of Ghost
Dancers under Miniconjou Lakota leader Big
Foot toward the assumed safety of Pine Ridge
Reservation. They were intercepted by troops
from the Seventh Cavalry, who escorted them
to the hamlet at Wounded Knee to await further
orders. On December 29, 1890, amid a
search of Indian men and women for concealed
weapons, a fight began which led to
desperate hand-to-hand combat. Simultaneously,
rapid-fire Hotchkiss guns rained
down small exploding projectiles. Before the
day was done, more than 250&#8211;and possibly as
many as 300&#8211;Lakotas were dead, including
44 women and 18 children. Others fled into
the cold expanses of the countryside, where
they were killed by pursuing soldiers. The
army lost twenty-five men and thirty-nine
were wounded. The Wounded Knee Massacre
and its followup military operations were
not "the last Indian War" that some books
claimed. Rather, they were a needless anti-climax
to decades of cultural misunderstanding,
land pressure, government deceit, and
countless calls for revenge.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Canadian-Indian Relations in the Plains</head>

<p>Many Canadians have traditionally viewed
their "winning of the West" as a process built
upon consensus rather than conflict. They
point out that in the lands that became the
provinces of Manitoba, Saskatchewan, and Alberta,
Indian-white conflict was infrequent
when compared with the horrific record below
the forty-ninth parallel. They argue that
Canadian policies were relatively fair to Indians,
giving little cause for resistance. More
recent scholarship, however, has challenged
this older view and has identified a long history
of Canadian injustices toward Native
Americans.</p>

<p>Historians such as George Stanley have argued
that in the western United States, pioneers
enveloped the frontier areas before government
authority could be established. In
this unregulated environment, frontiersmen
stirred up numerous controversies with the
tribes as they coveted the land and its resources.
By contrast, the argument goes, Canadians
established governing and enforcement
authorities such as the North-West
Mounted Police well in advance of the influx
of white population. Thus, conflicts could be
minimized by law enforcement officers, and
pioneers could feel relatively safe in their new
environment.</p>

<p>While Stanley’s contention holds merit, it
omits the Indian view of this relationship. Canadian
Plains tribes such as the Bloods, Piegans,
Blackfoot, Assiniboines, Plains Crees,
and Ojibwas repeatedly complained about
treaty violations and delays in shipments of
supplies. Many of these tribes also lived and
hunted on the U.S. side of the border, and they
were concerned that the Americans might extend
their authority to the north. The Boundary
Commission Survey of 1872–74 especially
disturbed tribal leaders who felt that this
might be the opening salvo in a complete
transfer of the Plains. They were likewise concerned
about the frequent movements of the
U.S. Army along the border and its forays into
Canada to capture specific Indians.</p>

<p>The most serious threat to the relatively
peaceful situation in the Prairie Provinces
came from Louis David Riel Jr. and his Metis,
mixed-blood people of Indian and French Canadian
descent who lived in the Red River Settlement
of Manitoba. On the eve of the Hudson’s
Bay Company sale of the Metis’ territory
of Rupert's Land to Canada in 1869, a "Red
River resistance" developed. Riel helped organize
the Comites National des Metis to defend
farm ownership, protect hunting rights, and
ensure the barter economy of the region. They
blocked the new governor, William McDougall,
from entering the territory and briefly
occupied Fort Garry. Col. Garnet Wolseley
marched 1,200 volunteers to the relief of the
post, but because of delays in crossing hostile
terrain, they did not arrive until August 1870.
By then, Riel had withdrawn his followers and
a compromise agreement was being hammered
out.</p>

<p>Riel remained a hunted man even though
he was elected three times to the Canadian
House of Commons by the people of Manitoba.
In 1884 he heeded the call again to help
the Métis people of Saskatchewan who were
resisting the inroads of farmers and the Canadian
Pacific Railway. The initially peaceful
protest turned into the North-West Rebellion,
with Riel proclaiming himself president of the
separatist state. Skirmishes broke out with
North-West Mounted Police near Fort Carlton,
and other Indians joined the conflict near
Frog Lake. Riel gave up on May 15, 1885 and
was hanged for treason on November 16, amid
a national uproar over the injustice.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">From frontier Setting to Internationalism</head>

<p>The 1890s brought a change in military activity
in the Great Plains, as policymakers
shifted their attention from western expansion
to matters of international scope. With
the Indians now on reservations, many military
posts&#8211;Forts Buford and Assiniboine, for
example&#8211;were closed. The shift to international
issues began in 1898 with the Spanish
American War and continued from 1899
through 1902 in the Philippine-American
War. Plains states were affected in two ways by
these conflicts. First, regular army troops were
redeployed from the frontier posts to overseas
duty. At installations across the Plains only
handfuls of civilian employees remained to
guard against pilfering. In some cases, troops
never returned to their previously assigned
posts, which were soon closed.</p>

<p>The second impact in the Plains states came
in the mobilization of state National Guard
units. Many of these units got no further than
training camps, but the First Nebraska Infantry,
for example, made it to the Philippines
and saw active fighting against Spaniards and
subsequently during the Philippine-American
War.</p>

<p>New concerns for the American military began
in 1911 with the outbreak of the Mexican
Revolution. Rebel raids that spilled over into
American territory throughout 1914 and 1915
forced the United States to augment its protection
of the extensive boundary from Texas to
California. On May 9, 1916, President Woodrow
Wilson mobilized the National Guards of
New Mexico, Texas, and Arizona to help defend
the border. Little more than a month
later, the National Guards of all states were
called into action, and by late July, 111,000
guardsmen had moved to the international
boundary, including units from all Plains
states. Sporadic rebel raids obliged the United
States to maintain troops in the region until
1921.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">World War I</head>

<p>American response to the war in Europe sent
repercussions through Plains agriculture virtually
as soon as the struggle began. Immediately
after the German invasion of Belgium
in 1914, Kansans began donating wheat to area
millers who voluntarily ground it into flour
for shipment to Europe. With German supplies
of potash cut off, American farmers had
to look elsewhere for this key fertilizer ingredient.
Ten new potash plants were developed
in west-central Nebraska. This industrial
boom led to the creation of several new communities,
most of which failed when the importation
of cheaper German potash resumed
after the war. The war also stimulated the production
of Great Plains oil. The oil fields of
Wyoming doubled their output after 1916.</p>

<p>After America's entry into the war in April
1917, President Wilson appointed Herbert
Hoover to the newly created U.S. Food Administration.
Needing to stimulate food production,
Hoover initiated programs for federal
subsidies to producers of wheat, corn,
cotton, hogs, and sugar. The prices of corn,
oats, and hay doubled, while the price of
wheat nearly tripled. In Montana, the number
of new homesteads peaked as farmers went
into debt to plow grasslands for crop production.
All across the Plains, patriotic citizens
planted vegetable gardens and observed the
federally encouraged "wheatless" and "meatless"
days.</p>

<p>Military preparations significantly changed
home-front Plains communities. In June 1917
construction began on an enormous training
facility at the Fort Riley, Kansas, military reserve.
Construction of the camp for 50,000
soldiers, and the requisite support services for
men in training, created a nearby "Army City,"
which had four blocks of stores, theaters, barbershops,
and pool halls. A similar site, Camp
Doniphan, grew on the grounds of Fort Sill,
Oklahoma, after 1917.</p>

<p>The new science of "aero-technology" saw its
first use in World War I, and the Plains produced
two balloon-training facilities. As early as
1900 the U.S. Army Signal Corps had organized
a Balloon Detachment, eventually locating all its
dirigible activities at Fort Omaha, Nebraska.
The program was abandoned in 1909, but when
the United States entered the war, the military
began using piloted balloons to make more accurate
battlefield observations. Fort Omaha was
the logical place to expand training operations
since the hangar and its companion hydrogen
plant were still operational. In July 1917 the Fort
Omaha Balloon School received the first of the
16,000 men it would eventually train in balloon
skills. A second Plains balloon school opened at
Fort Sill, Oklahoma, in September 1917. The
Fort Sill balloon operation remained functional
into the 1930s, but all the equipment and staff of
the Fort Omaha school were moved to Belleville,
Illinois, in 1921.</p>

<p>There was little tolerance for anyone appearing
un-American during World War I.
Montanans’ harassment of German Americans
and Scandinavians, who preferred that
the United States remain neutral, led to considerable
unrest. "Liberty Committees" were
created in some towns to police suspected
antiwar activities. In Glendive a mob nearly
lynched a German Mennonite minister who
favored peace. In February 1918 the Montana
Defense Council, which had already banned
any use of the German language, convinced
the governor to call a special legislative session,
which passed the Montana Sedition Law,
making it illegal to criticize the federal government,
the armed services, or state government
in wartime. This became the model for
the federal Sedition Law of 1918.</p>

<p>In the Canadian Prairie Provinces, the outbreak
of war in 1914 also improved the farm
economy, which had plummeted into debt
and depression after 1912. Farmers quickly responded
to war needs with sizable quantities
of horses, oats, and flour. Acres were rushed
into production and nearly 40,000 new farms
were created by 1921. The price of land rebounded,
wages for farm laborers rose, and
unemployment dropped.</p>

<p>World War I also produced economic
changes in the postwar Plains. Because many
cavalry animals remained to be cared for after
the war, the U.S. War Department created the
Remount Board in 1919 to establish remount
depots, which would condition horses and
mules for military use as well as train necessary
personnel in animal care and management.
With funding in 1921, two permanent remount
depots were established in the Great Plains&#8211;one
at Fort Robinson, Nebraska, and another at
Fort Reno, Oklahoma. Fort Robinson quickly
became the world’s largest remount station,
housing 17,000 horses and mules by the late
1930s.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">World War II</head>

<p>The outbreak of war in Europe in September
1939 marked the beginning of the end of the
Great Depression. Although the United States
continued to maintain its isolationist stance
against military participation during the first
two years of the conflict, the government's
"cash and carry" policy of allowing Great Britain
and France to purchase necessary supplies
meant increased production and employment
in most sections of the country, including
the Great Plains. The upsurge of production,
coupled with the need for soldiers in the
armed forces, gradually reduced the surplus of
labor. By 1942 the labor pool was drained, and
an exhaustive search for manpower was under
way in the military, agricultural, industrial,
and service sectors of the American economy.
Women entered the workforce in record numbers.
Forty percent of the employees at Omaha's
Martin Bomber Plant and one-half of
Remington Arms Company personnel in Denver
were women. Prisoners of war were used to
bolster the labor force in nonthreatened regions
of the country such as the Plains.</p>

<p>After Pearl Harbor the Great Plains benefited
greatly from war production and from
numerous sectors of the economy that were
tied to military expansion. Most of the expansion
monies were funneled through the Defense
Plant Corporation, a subsidiary of the
New Deal's Reconstruction Finance Corporation,
created in August 1940. Plains states created
their own booster groups to lobby for
federal contracts. For example, North Dakota's
businessmen organized two groups&#8211;the
North Dakota War Resource Committee
and the Greater North Dakota Association&#8211;to
procure some of the lucrative government
contracts.</p>

<p>During the war, the remoteness of parts of
the Great Plains became a virtue that attracted
new industries. Most Plains states benefited
from the tremendous growth of the wartime
aviation industry. Plains spaces were defensibly
secure and wide open for the creation
of landing strips and for the testing of armaments.
Texas established forty air bases, including
Avenger Field at Sweetwater, which
trained women for the Women Air Force Service
Pilots. The clear skies over Midland Army
Air Field proved to be an excellent location for
the training of aerial bombardiers. The national
headquarters of the Air Force Training
Command was housed at Fort Worth's Carswell
Field, and aircraft factories were also built
in the Dallas–Fort Worth area.</p>

<p>In 1942 Montana became the site of Malmstrom
Air Force Base, constructed by the
Army Air Corps near Great Falls. The Air
Corps also established Lowry Field near Denver
after the city donated the land from an old
sanatorium site. Buckley Field, east of Denver,
and Peterson Field, near Colorado Springs,
were added to the growing list of Plains airfields.
In Wyoming, the Casper Army Air Base
was built in the summer of 1942, and Cheyenne
became the new home of United Air
Lines pilot training. The city was also the site
of a modification center that installed new armaments
and instruments on thousands of
<hi rend="smallcaps">B</hi>-17s and smaller bombers. The economic impact
of these installations on the local economies
was tremendous.</p>

<p>The Prairie Provinces were just as appealing.
The British Commonwealth Air Training
Plan (<hi rend="smallcaps">BCATP</hi>) was formulated in the months
before Canada declared war on Germany in
September 1939 and was intended to train aircrews
for the British armed forces. The bcatp
served as Canada's primary contribution to
the war effort and drew trainees from Britain,
Canada, Australia, New Zealand, and India, as
well as recruits from nations that fell to German
forces. Administered by the Royal Canadian
Air Force, the plan established training
schools and runways at more than thirty sites
in the Prairies, from Edmonton and Penhold,
Alberta, to Winnipeg and Portage la Prairie,
Manitoba. By August 1945, 131,553 pilots and
aircrew members had been trained in the
Prairie Provinces.</p>

<p>To the south, Wichita, Kansas, became a
center in the aviation industry during the war
and continues as such to the present day. In
1940 Boeing Aircraft Corporation received a
government contract to expand the Beech Aircraft
Company in Wichita. By early 1942 Boeing
was turning out parts for their <hi rend="smallcaps">B</hi>-17 Flying
Fortress, and the government had established
the National Defense Training School to train
aircraft workers. The aircraft industry and its
associated schools brought thousands of job
seekers to Wichita. Pratt Airfield was completed
with government funds in 1943 and became
home to heavy bomber groups. All totaled,
aircraft plants in Wichita and Kansas
City, Kansas, turned out 24,000 planes during
the war.</p>

<p>In September 1940 Offutt Field at Bellevue,
Nebraska (near Omaha), was selected as a site
for the production of <hi rend="smallcaps">B</hi>-26 bombers. Construction
of the plant immediately brought
3,000 new residents to the sleepy village. The
plant opened in early 1942 and employed
14,572 people at its peak. Traffic in and out of
the plant led to construction of the first divided
highway in Nebraska. During the course
of the war, the Bellevue plant produced 1,500
<hi rend="smallcaps">B</hi>-26s and more than 500 <hi rend="smallcaps">B</hi>-29s, including two
modified <hi rend="smallcaps">B</hi>-29s&#8211;the <hi rend="italic">Enola Gay</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Bock's
Car</hi>&#8211;which dropped the atomic bombs on
Hiroshima and Nagasaki to end the war in the
Pacific.</p>

<p>The mobilization of thousands of guardsmen
during the last quarter of 1940 had a major
impact in the Great Plains. Facilities could
not be constructed rapidly enough. Near
Cheyenne, Fort Warren was expanded to 284
buildings at a cost of more than $5 million.
The Wyoming post housed 19,000 men and
women at its peak. Soldiers' dependents lived
in the city itself and spent millions of dollars
annually. The monthly payroll for Fort Warren
alone was greater than that of any of the
state's industries. In Kansas, Fort Leavenworth
expanded its facilities by becoming a training
site that pumped $50 million into the Kansas
economy in 1940 alone. Other army training
sites at Salina's Camp Phillips and nearby Fort
Riley as well as naval air corps training facilities
at Hutchinson and Olathe forced the
prices of consumer goods in those areas to
increase by 25 percent between 1939 and 1944.</p>

<p>Defense industries boomed. Again, the relative
security of Plains isolation proved to be the
drawing card that brought rocket, mine, and
bomb production facilities to Sidney, Grand
Island, Hastings, and Mead, Nebraska. In Denver,
Remington Arms manufactured smallcaliber
ammunition, the Kaiser Company finished
artillery shells, and Rocky Mountain Arsenal
produced poisonous gases. Most of these
expansive facilities closed within weeks of the
war's end in 1945, but some found new uses
after the war. The Remington Arms Company
buildings ultimately became Denver's Federal
Center. The Grand Island Cornhusker Ordnance
Plant was reopened for service during
the Korean and Vietnam conflicts, finally closing permanently in 1973. However, lack of waste
disposal standards throughout their years of operation
has endowed a legacy of soil and water
pollution for residents presently living near
many wartime Plains ordnance plants.</p>

<p>War needs extended into other areas of the
home front as well in the early 1940s. In Denver,
foundries that once manufactured mining
equipment and sugar refining gear began to
make oil production machinery. In general,
the Plains oil industry expanded. But the
Plains industries most positively affected by
the war were agriculture and livestock production.
The pressure to mechanize increased
as much of the traditional farm labor force
was pressed into military service. Improved
financing for farm machinery allowed many
farmers to acquire tractors, which subsequently
displaced some two million horses
and mules between 1941 and 1945, while increasing
the amount of arable land in the
Plains by 5 percent. Farmers' cash receipts rose
throughout the Plains during the war years,
doubling, for example, in Wyoming.</p>

<p>The war touched the Plains in yet another
way. As Allied forces made gains against the
Axis powers in southern Europe and northern
Africa through 1941, guarding and housing the
enemy prisoners became a tremendous burden
for Allied troop commanders. Beginning
early in 1942, the War Department ordered the
transfer of all captured enemy personnel to
detention camps in the United States. By late
1944 forty-six prisoner-of-war (<hi rend="smallcaps">POW</hi>) camp
networks were in place in the Great Plains.
As replacement labor in United States industries,
prisoners were not permitted to undertake
any degrading work, nor were they permitted
within ten miles of sensitive military
installations. Prisoners in a network of nineteen
camps in Nebraska and northern Kansas
picked beets and corn. <hi rend="smallcaps">POWS</hi> in Wyoming’s
system of eleven camps also undertook agricultural
jobs, as they did in Texas.</p>

<p>Another kind of detention camp in the
Great Plains revealed America's insensitive
treatment of her own citizens&#8211;Japanese
American internment camps. In February 1942
President Franklin Roosevelt directed that all
Japanese Americans were to be evacuated from
sensitive areas in the West. Construction of the
Amache internment camp near Granada, Colorado,
was a boost to the local economy, employing
1,000 men at a cost of $4.2 million. But
a total of 7,567 Japanese, over two-thirds of
whom were American citizens, were housed in
deplorable conditions&#8211;cardboard houses,
few lights, and no running water. The site was
not completely evacuated until October 1945.</p>

<p>In February 1942 the Canadian government
undertook similar measures against all people
of Japanese extraction living in the "defense
zone," a 100-mile-wide strip along the coast of
British Columbia. By June 1942 nearly 2,250
Japanese Canadians had been deported to
southern Alberta, where they took up residence
in the inadequate housing formerly
used by seasonal beet workers. Canada faced
the same labor shortages found in the United
States, and displaced Japanese Canadians harvested
Alberta's sugar beets and worked in the
Broder Canning Factory at Lethbridge.</p>

<p>Despite the Great Plains’s remoteness from
both coasts, the Japanese managed to "bomb"
several Plains locations with balloon bombs&#8211;incendiary
devices intended to terrorize Americans
and set forests and cities ablaze. Between
November 1944 and August 1945, 6,000 armed
balloons were launched from Honshu by
the Japanese military. Only 300 of them
ever reached the United States, most of them
exploding on the Pacific Coast. But a sizable
number of the balloons drifted inland and
exploded over the Plains. South Dakota,
for example, reported at least nine balloon
explosions.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Cold War</head>

<p>The cold war was born in the sniping between
the new superpowers of the United States and
the Soviet Union at the Potsdam Conference
in July 1945. One month later, the United
States unleashed the force that remained for
nearly fifty years the primary ingredient of the
cold war&#8211;the atomic bomb. The ever-present
threat of a nuclear holocaust compelled the
U.S. Army Air Force to create the Strategic Air
Command (<hi rend="smallcaps">SAC</hi>). In 1948 <hi rend="smallcaps">SAC</hi>'s central operations
were placed at Offutt Air Force Base,
near Omaha, Nebraska, making the Central
Plains "ground zero" in any nuclear confrontation
and ushering in a new age of defense
spending throughout the Great Plains.</p>

<p>The federal government felt obliged to challenge
the American public into steadfastly supporting
its tough national security measures.
The defense plan adopted in 1950 by the Truman
administration contained two components:
national prevention of nuclear war and
public management of atomic war should it
ever occur. Government leaders in the Plains
responded to the challenge, and in early 1951
Nebraska and South Dakota met with four
other midwestern states to outline plans for
civilian defense and mutual aid. Practice drills
were encouraged on a community level, and
on December 5, 1954, Denver residents evacuated
the city in a mass preparedness drill designed
to make sure that citizens could quickly
take shelter in surrounding rural counties.</p>

<p>Over the next two decades, concern for protection
from nuclear fallout led some Americans
to build their own fallout shelters. In June
1962 Artesia, New Mexico, dedicated the first
school building built entirely underground to
protect inhabitants from fallout. Eventually,
the belowground levels of many public buildings
were designated as fallout shelters. Similarly,
in 1961 an eastern Nebraska dairy built a
thirty-five-thousand-dollar shelter designed to
protect 200 head of dairy cattle from fallout.
But despite strong federal encouragement and
the dissemination of copious amounts of construction
"how-to" data, only 1,500 private
bomb shelters had been built by 1960.</p>

<p>The threat of Soviet attack drew the American
and Canadian portions of the Great Plains
closer together. Alberta was located on the
flight path of any Soviet bomb squadron
headed for either eastern Canada or the United
States. Thus, in 1947 Canada appointed a national
civil defense coordinator to encourage
provincial civil defense. Alberta’s civil defense
plans were well ahead of those of other Prairie
Provinces, and by 1952 the province was using
forest fire spotters to watch for enemy aircraft.
By 1955 Alberta had trained 25,000 civil defense
volunteers to assist in the event of a Soviet
attack.</p>

<p>The United States and Canada joined parts
of their ground defense forces early in the
postwar era, and in 1948–49 Canada created
the Mobile Striking Force and placed its joint
army–air force headquarters in Winnipeg.
In 1958 the two countries formally created a
continental network of anti-aircraft defenses.
The North American Aerospace Defense
Command (<hi rend="smallcaps">NORAD</hi>) set up radar defenses as
far north as the Arctic Circle and coordinated
the system from headquarters at Colorado
Springs, Colorado. The headquarters facility,
which was built deep inside Cheyenne Mountain,
was completed in 1966 at a cost of $142.4
million.</p>

<p>Colorado Springs was the recipient of more
Department of Defense dollars after the air
force was created as a separate branch of the
armed forces. Established in 1948, the air force
originally drew from a variety of sources for
its officers, but in 1954 Congress granted approval
for the creation of an Air Force Academy
at Colorado Springs. The government
authorized $126 million to purchase the 15,100
acres of ranch land and to construct the buildings.
Until the academy was completed, Lowry
Air Force Base in Denver was the temporary
facility, and the government spent $1 million
to ready the base for its role.</p>

<p>Linking the continent together in a web of
communications became vital in the postwar
era, and in view of those needs, pressure to
construct an interstate highway system increased.
Although such a network had been
envisioned as early as 1944, federal funds had
not materialized, and the Korean War only
increased the strain on existing highways. Despite
the tremendous costs involved, President
Dwight Eisenhower signed legislation in 1956
authorizing a twenty-five-billion-dollar interstate
highway system. Between 1956 and 1974
construction of the interstate system connected
the Great Plains, greatly boosting local
economies.</p>

<p>Cold war industrial output in the Plains
centered on the manufacture of military aircraft,
and Wichita, Kansas, became a major
Great Plains component in the militaryindustrial
complex. The end of World War II
had meant closure of one of the city's Boeing
Aircraft plants, reducing Boeing’s Wichita
workforce of more than 29,000 by 50 percent.
But as cold war tensions increased in the late
1940s, Boeing reopened its Wichita plants to
build 1,371 <hi rend="smallcaps">B</hi>-47s&#8211;the revolutionary Stratojet.
Another Wichita aerospace manufacturer,
Loadcraft, built carriers for the Honest John
missile throughout the 1950s. Nearby McConnell
Air Force Base was activated in 1951 to
train the <hi rend="smallcaps">B</hi>-47 pilots. The base continued its
service into the late twentieth century as part
of the Strategic Air Command.</p>

<p>The greatest contribution of the Great
Plains to America's cold war defenses was its
service as a permanent home for the Strategic
Air Command's air defense missile system.
The construction of intercontinental ballistic
missile (<hi rend="smallcaps">ICBM</hi>) sites in Wyoming, as well as in
adjacent areas of Nebraska and Colorado,
pumped $100 million into the regional economy.
Similar economic benefits were reaped
from the installation of Atlas missile sites in
eastern Nebraska and Kansas, and at Altus
<hi rend="smallcaps">AFB</hi>, Oklahoma, Dyess <hi rend="smallcaps">AFB</hi> in Texas, and
Walker <hi rend="smallcaps">AFB</hi> in eastern New Mexico.</p>

<p>Missile technology continued to evolve
through the Titan series of missiles, and by
1960 the advanced Minuteman series was ready
for deployment. Upon testing, the missile's
range was shy of its intended 5,500-mile reach,
so selection of missile sites was confined to the
Northern Plains because of the region’s closer
proximity to the Soviet Union. The first location
chosen for installation of the Minuteman
missiles was Malmstrom Air Force Base near
Great Falls, Montana. The Cuban missile crisis
of October 1962 forced the rapid completion of
the first ten missile sites and their manned
launch-control facility.</p>

<p>The second site chosen for deployment of
150 Minuteman missiles was Ellsworth Air
Force Base east of Rapid City, South Dakota.
Construction required approximately 3,000
workers who needed housing and other facilities.
By the end of 1967, 600 Minuteman missiles
had been installed. During the 1970s
newer Minuteman II and Minuteman III missiles
augmented or replaced Minuteman I
ICBMS at 1,000 sites in the Northern Plains.</p>

<p>In 1983 the Reagan administration announced
its intention to replace fifty Minuteman
III missiles assigned to Warren Air Force
Base in Wyoming with the advanced <hi rend="smallcaps">MX</hi> Peacekeeper
missiles, which could carry more warheads
and had greater range and targeting flexibility.
The project was completed in 1989 at a
cost of $16.6 billion nationally for installation,
evaluation, and research. The economic impact
on the region was phenomenal: $232 million
alone for hardened-silo upgrades.</p>

<p>The cold war faded with the fall of the
Berlin Wall in November 1989. In July 1991
President George H. W. Bush and Soviet
leader Mikhail Gorbachev signed the Strategic
Arms Reduction Treaty, placing limits on the
worldwide number of intercontinental ballistic
missiles. In September of that year President
Bush announced that all 450 operational
Minutemen II missiles would be withdrawn,
including all those at South Dakota's Ellsworth
Air Force Base. The bomb wing there
also closed in late 1995, but the base remained
open. Because of the <hi rend="smallcaps">ICBM</hi>'s importance to
America's cold war defenses, two missile sites
at Ellsworth <hi rend="smallcaps">AFB</hi> are being considered for possible
historic preservation.</p>

<p>Reduced federal spending due to the end of
the cold war had a negative economic impact
on many parts of the Great Plains. Near Lubbock,
Texas, Reese Air Force Base was closed,
with the loss of an estimated $82 million to the
local economy. Also closed was Lowry
Force Base in Denver, which had served as a
Titan missile site and as a training center for
aircraft maintenance and weapons loading.
More than 10,000 military and civilian employees
had worked at the base, creating a
positive economic impact greater than $600
million annually. Closing the base in 1992 cost
6,000 jobs in the metropolitan area.</p>

<p>At the beginning of the twenty-first century,
the Great Plains continues to play an important
role in North America's military activities.
The wide-open vistas still evoke images of a
not-so-distant frontier past in which the Plains
served as a military corridor to the Far West
and as a place of conflict between immigrant
peoples and Native Americans. Cities spread
rapidly into those vistas in the twentieth century,
and many served as production sites for
the new technology that put military strategy
into the air. Men and women from the very
ethnic groups whose confrontations are part of
Plains history now work together in military
activities at home during times of natural disaster,
or as far away as Haiti and Bosnia in their
attempts to restore peace instead of waging
war.</p>
</div2>
</div1>
<div1>
<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">ARCHITECTURE</hi>: <ref n="egp.arc.009">Cold War Architecture</ref>
/ <hi rend="smallcaps">ASIAN AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.asam.002">Amache Internment Camp</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">EDUCATION</hi>: <ref n="egp.edu.039">United States Air Force Academy</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">EUROPEAN AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ea.041">Villasur, Pedro de</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">HISPANIC AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ha.017">Guadalupe Hidalgo, Treaty of</ref>; <ref n="egp.ha.039">San Sab&#225; Mission and Presidio</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">IMAGES AND ICONS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ii.017">Custer, George Armstrong</ref>; <ref n="egp.ii.042">Missile Silos</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">INDUSTRY</hi>: <ref n="egp.ind.002">Aerospace</ref>;
<ref n="egp.ind.051">Potash</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">LAW</hi>: <ref n="egp.law.038">North-West Mounted Police</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">NATIVE AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.na.008">Assimilation Policy</ref>;
<ref n="egp.na.063">M&#233;tis</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">PROTEST AND DISSENT</hi>: <ref n="egp.pd.047">Riel, Louis</ref> /
<hi rend="smallcaps">RELIGION</hi>: <ref n="egp.rel.023">Ghost Dance</ref>.</p>
</div1>

<div1>
<p/>
<closer>
<signed>Michael L. Tate<lb/>
Jo Lea Wetherilt Behrens<lb/>
University of Nebraska at Omaha</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Clendenen, Clarence C. <title level="m">Blood on the Border: The United
States Army and the Mexican Irregulars</title>. Toronto: Macmillan
Publishing Company, 1969.</bibl> <bibl>Conrad, Peter C. <title level="m">Training
for Victory: The British Commonwealth Air Training
Plan in the West</title>. Saskatoon, Saskatchewan: Western Producer
Prairie Books, 1989.</bibl> <bibl>Goetzmann, William H. <title level="m">Army
Exploration in the American West, 1803-1863</title>. New Haven
<hi rend="smallcaps">CT</hi>: Yale University Press, 1959.</bibl> <bibl>Haley, James L. <title level="m">The Buffalo
War: The History of the Red River Indian Uprising of 1874</title>.
New York: Doubleday and Co., 1976.</bibl> <bibl>Hoig, Stan. <title level="m">The Sand
Creek Massacre</title>. Norman: University of Oklahoma Press,
1961.</bibl> <bibl>Holsinger, M. Paul. "Amache." <title level="j">Colorado Magazine</title> 41
(1964): 50-60.</bibl> <bibl>Hutton, Paul Andrew, ed. <title level="m">Soldiers West:
Biographies from the Military Frontier</title>. Lincoln: University
of Nebraska Press, 1987.</bibl> <bibl>Larson, T. A. <title level="m">Wyoming's War
Years, 1941-1945</title>. Stanford <hi rend="smallcaps">CA</hi>: Stanford University Press,
1954. Reprint, Cheyenne: Wyoming Historical Foundation,
1993.</bibl> <bibl>Leckie, William H. <title level="m">The Buffalo Soldiers: A Narrative
of the Negro Cavalry in the West</title>. Norman: University
of Oklahoma Press, 1967.</bibl> <bibl>McGinnis, Anthony. <title level="m">Counting
Coups and Cutting Horses: Intertribal Warfare on the
Northern Plains, 1738-1889</title>. Evergreen <hi rend="smallcaps">CO</hi>: Cordillera Press,
Inc., 1990.</bibl> <bibl>Nash, Gerald A. <title level="m">The American West Transformed:
The Impact of the Second World War</title>. Bloomington:
Indiana University Press, 1985.</bibl> <bibl>Rickey, Don, Jr.
<title level="m">Forty Miles a Day on Beans and Hay: The Enlisted Soldier
Fighting the Indian Wars</title>. Norman: University of Oklahoma
Press, 1963.</bibl> <bibl>Smith, Sherry L. <title level="m">The View from Officers'
Row: Army Perception of Western Indians</title>. Tucson: University
of Arizona Press, 1990.</bibl> <bibl>Stanley, George F. G. <title level="m">The Birth
of Western Canada: A History of the Riel Rebellions</title>. Toronto:
University of Toronto Press, 1960.</bibl> <bibl>Thompson, John
Herd. <title level="m">The Harvests of War: The Prairie West, 1914-1918</title>.
Toronto: McClelland and Stewart Ltd., 1978.</bibl> <bibl>Utley, Robert
M. <title level="m">Frontier Regulars: The United States Army and the Indian,
1866-1891</title>. New York: Macmillan Publishing Company,
1973.</bibl> <bibl>Utley, Robert M. <title level="m">Frontiersmen in Blue: The
United States Army and the Indian, 1848-1865</title>. New York:
Macmillan Publishing Company, 1967.</bibl> <bibl>Wooster, Robert.
<title level="m">The Military and United States Indian Policy, 1865-1903</title>.
New Haven <hi rend="smallcaps">CT</hi>: Yale University Press, 1988.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>