<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.na.019">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Cheyennes</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Mark A. Eifler</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.na.019</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Moore, John H.">John H. Moore</author>. <title level="a">"Cheyennes."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">569-570</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-15</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">CHEYENNES</head>

<p>Between 1820 and 1869 the Cheyenne nation
was the most powerful Indian military force
in the Central Great Plains, despite comprising
only about 3,500 people. They achieved a
dominant military position by allying with the
Arapahos and Lakotas, then driving the Shoshones
toward the northwest and the Kiowas
and Comanches to the south, while keeping
the Crows and Pawnees at bay by continual
attacks against their villages. Thus, they gained
control of the prime bison-hunting areas between
the forks of the Platte and on the upper
reaches of the Republican and Smoky Hills
Rivers, and achieved preferred access to trading
posts on the Arkansas and South Platte
Rivers.</p>

<p>The Cheyennes were also successful during
this period in their warfare against the U.S.
Army, which could not catch them on the
open Plains, or was often sorry when it did, as
at the Fetterman Fight in Wyoming in 1866
and the Battle of Beecher's Island in Colorado
in 1868. The military success of the Cheyennes
can be attributed mainly to four factors: they
could mobilize up to 1,500 warriors, all the
active men in the tribe, for a single engagement;
their bands were dispersed most of the
year so that they could observe anyone entering
their territory; their warriors traveled light
and took along spare horses for attack, pursuit,
and escape; and they maintained ferocious
war traditions, which included suicide
warfare, dog ropes, medicine lances, and a
complex system of war honors that encouraged
quick and decisive combat.</p>

<p>The Cheyennes, who speak a language of
the Algonquian family and call themselves
<hi rend="italic">Tsistsistas</hi>, did not see themselves as primarily
a militaristic people, however, but as a religious
people. Even today their traditional
culture is organized around the annual Sun
Dances, performed on their Oklahoma and
Montana reservations, and the Arrow Renewal
Ceremony, performed in Oklahoma. In
addition, most Cheyennes are involved in the
Native American Church, or peyote religion,
as well as Christian denominations, especially
the Catholic Church in Montana and the
Mennonite Church on both reservations.</p>

<p>The Cheyennes entered written history
during the seventeenth century in Minnesota
around the shores of Mille Lacs, where they
collected wild rice and made occasional trips
to the Plains to hunt bison on foot. By 1766,
however, some Cheyenne bands had acquired
horses and moved their base to the Minnesota
River to become mounted bison hunters,
while at least one other band occupied an agricultural
village on the Sheyenne River in
North Dakota, a river that bears the name applied
to them by their Dakota neighbors,
meaning "red talkers," or people of foreign
language. Several decades later the various
Cheyenne bands were reunited along the middle
Missouri River, where they pursued an
economy of mixed agriculture and hunting,
based in fortified villages on the riverbanks.</p>

<p>Later still, probably about 1790, the Cheyenne
bands moved to the vicinity of the Black
Hills, where they acquired more horses, which
ultimately enabled them to give up agriculture
for a nomadic life of full-time bison hunting.
They were urged to do this by their prophet
Sweet Medicine, who was given four medicine
arrows by sacred persons whom he met in a
cave at Bear Butte in South Dakota, known to
the Cheyennes as <hi rend="italic">Nowahwas</hi>, or Sacred Mountain.
Two of the arrows were for killing bison
by magical means, and two for killing their
enemies.</p>

<p>The Cheyenne political system had two aspects,
war and peace, and two kinds of chiefs,
war chiefs, or <hi rend="italic">notxevoe</hi>, and peace chiefs, or
vehoe. The peace chiefs led the nation's ten
or so bands, supervised their trade, and adjudicated
disputes. When war threatened, they
gave control of the nation to the war chiefs,
who planned strategy and tactics and led the
attacks. Ideally, there were forty-four peace
chiefs in the Chiefs' Council, four of whom
were senior, or "Old Man Chiefs," and each of
the seven to ten military societies was led by
one to four "Big War Chiefs" and four to sixteen
"Little War Chiefs."</p>

<p>Most of the daily work in Cheyenne society
was done by women, organized along matrilineal
lines. A woman usually worked alongside
her mother and mother's sisters, her own
sisters, her daughters, and her sisters' daughters
for her entire life. Women "ruled the
camp" and owned the tipis and furnishings, as
well as a number of horses. As workers, they
organized guilds that honored women who
had made tipi covers and liners, clothing,
quillwork, and beadwork. Honorable women
received the privilege of smoking a pipe after
menopause.</p>

<p>Young women were married by ages sixteen
to eighteen, the oldest daughter first. Because
of warfare, there were more women than men
in Cheyenne society, so if possible a second
sister was married to her older sister's husband
(sororal polygyny). If a man died, his
brother was required to marry his widow to
maintain ties between the two extended families.
If a woman died, an unmarried sister was
required to marry the widower, to take care of
the children and maintain ties between the
families. If there were no unmarried sisters,
then a married sister or other woman related
in the female line adopted the children. Modern
Cheyenne women often "co-mother" their
children, playfully calling the practice "Cheyenne
health insurance.</p>

<p>The military societies founded in Aboriginal
times are still active. They sponsor dinners
and powwows to honor their members and
families and raise money for the annual ceremonies.
Also in existence are local groups of
"War Mothers," which were first organized
during World War I to honor servicemen and
-women and veterans.</p>

<p>Concerning treaties, the U.S. government
now admits its failure to live up to the treaties
of Fort Laramie (1851) and Fort Wise (1861),
and in 1968 paid compensation of approximately
$2,000 to each Cheyenne, far less than
the actual value of the land taken and annuities
not received. In addition, the government
has admitted to defrauding Cheyennes
of their reservation land through the Jerome
Commission, which was certified by the infamous
Lone Wolf decision in 1903. The Cheyennes
were never compensated for that fraud
or for the 200 noncombatants killed and
horses and belongings stolen in 1864 during
the Sand Creek Massacre. The descendants of
those attacked were promised indemnities under
the Treaty of the Little Arkansas in 1865,
which have not yet been paid as of 2001, although
the Cheyenne Sand Creek Descendants
Association continues to make legal
efforts to collect the funds.</p>

<p>On their reservations, beginning in the 1870s,
the Cheyennes were subjected to an unending
series of programs, ostensibly intended to better
their condition. Missionary and government
schools were set up, and some have continued to
modern times. After the passage of the Indian
Reorganization Act in 1934 and the Oklahoma
Indian Welfare Act in 1936, Cheyennes were able
to organize an o.cial government on each reservation
and to practice their religion and speak
their language freely.</p>

<p>In recent years, the Cheyennes have taken
steps to achieve economic self-sufficiency.
They have inaugurated bingo halls in Oklahoma
and tourist facilities in Oklahoma and
Montana. They are presently negotiating with
private corporations to bring manufacturing
jobs to the reservation areas. Their present
population consists of approximately 7,000
Northern Cheyennes enrolled on their reservation
in southeastern Montana and another
7,000 Southern Cheyennes enrolled on their
reservation in west-central Oklahoma.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">GENDER</hi>: <ref n="egp.gen.026">Native American Gender Roles</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">LAW</hi>: <ref n="egp.law.027"><hi rend="italic">Lone Wolf v. Hitchcock</hi></ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">WAR</hi>:
<ref n="egp.war.039">Sand Creek Massacre</ref>.</p>


<closer>
<signed>John H. Moore<lb/>
University of Florida</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Berthrong, Donald J. <title level="m">The Southern Cheyennes</title>. Norman:
University of Oklahoma Press, 1963.</bibl> <bibl>Grinnell, George B.
<title level="m">The Cheyenne Indians</title>. New York: Cooper Square, 1962.</bibl>
<bibl>Moore, John H. <title level="m">The Cheyenne Nation</title>. Lincoln: University
of Nebraska Press, 1987.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>