<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.ag.008 SYSTEM "egp.ag.008.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ag.008">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Alfalfa</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Martin A. Massengale</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ag.008</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Massengale, Martin A.">Martin A. Massengale</author>. <title level="a">"Alfalfa."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">34-35</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-12-10</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">ALFALFA</head>

<figure n="egp.ag.008" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Alfalfa harvest, Huntley Irrigation Project, Montana, 1914</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Alfalfa (<hi rend="italic">Medicago</hi> sp.), a valuable forage crop,
is grown widely throughout the Great Plains
under both irrigated and dryland conditions.
Alfalfa is a perennial with a deep-penetrating
taproot, which gives it considerable resistance
to drought. The plant needs a deep, welldrained
soil with a pH level that is near neutral
or slightly above for maximum production.
When planting alfalfa into soils that have
not grown the crop for many years, the seeds
are commonly inoculated with an effective
strain of <hi rend="italic">Rhizobium</hi> bacteria for nodulation
and thus nitrogen fixation.</p>

<p>Alfalfa is often characterized into northern,
southern, or intermediate types based on their
degree of winter hardiness. The less winterhardy
types produce higher yields because
they recover and grow more rapidly after cutting,
but they will not survive the cold winters
of the Northern Plains. In the Southern Great
Plains, where there is a long growing season,
five to seven cuttings may be taken per year,
whereas in the north there may be only two or
three cuttings. In the Northern Plains, where
winter killing could be a problem, the last cutting
occurs about four weeks before the first
killing frost in order for the plants to manufacture
and store sufficient carbohydrates and
to develop cold resistance. With the availability
of new disease-resistant cultivars, better
adapted to wider climatic conditions, and
with high levels of soil fertility, greater flexibility
in fall cutting schedules is possible.</p>

<p>Alfalfa is grown primarily for hay, but it
is also widely used for pasture. Additional
uses include ensilage, green chop, dehydrated
meal, green manure, and seed production. Alfalfa
hay&#8211;if harvested to preserve its nutritive
value&#8211;is a highly nutritious and palatable
feed for livestock. To maintain the high nutritive
value of the stems and leaves and produce
high yields, fields are harvested when about
one-tenth of the stems have open flowers. Alfalfa
is a superior pasture legume for numerous
classes of livestock because of its high
quality, high yield, and wide adaptation. It
is an economical source of protein and provides
a greater degree of flexibility in use than
most forage plants. Grazing-type alfalfa cultivars
have been developed more recently.
Compared to cultivars grown for hay, these
cultivars have broader and deep-set crowns,
more branched rooting, and do not release all
regrowth buds at the same time. One disadvantage
of alfalfa for pasture is that it can
cause bloat in cattle and sheep; however, bloat
can be minimized by certain practices, such as
growing alfalfa in combination with grasses.</p>

<p>Alfalfa is susceptible to various diseases
and insects. Resistance to many of these pests
has been incorporated into the new cultivars.
Most other insects and some diseases
of economic importance can be controlled
through the careful use of pesticides and harvest
management.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Martin A. Massengale<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Graber, L. F. "A Century of Alfalfa Culture in America."
<title level="j">Agronomy Journal</title> 42 (1950): 525–33.</bibl> <bibl>Hanson, A. A., ed.
<title level="m">Alfalfa and Alfalfa Improvement</title>. Madison <hi rend="smallcaps">WI</hi>: American
Society of Agronomy, 1988.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>