<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.arc.019">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Earth Lodges</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>John R. Bozell</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.arc.019</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Bozell, John R.">John R. Bozell</author>. <title level="a">"Earth Lodges."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">77-78</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-12</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">EARTH LODGES</head>

<p>The earth lodge was the dominant dwelling of
Central and Northern Great Plains village Indians.
Earth lodges were circular, domeshaped
dwellings with heavy timber superstructures
mantled by thick layers of earth.
The type emerged in the 1500s and persisted
into the reservation era. Tribes most frequently
associated with earth-lodge architecture
include the Mandans, Hidatsas, Arikaras,
Pawnees, Otoes, Kansas, Omahas, and Poncas,
although several other groups also adopted
the style.</p>

<p>The origins of the earth lodge are not entirely
clear, although it was certainly a Northern
Plains innovation. Between <hi rend="smallcaps">A.D</hi>. 1000 and
1400, horticultural villagers in the Central
Plains built square houses. During the same
time, Northern Plains villagers constructed
rectangular structures. Although these types
of houses are frequently called earth lodges,
they were not; rather, they were vertical walled
with thin coverings of wattle and daub or
thatch. A few oval to circular structures appeared
in northern Nebraska and central
South Dakota in the 1400s, but their floor
plans do not reflect the fully developed earthlodge
style. The earliest true earth lodges were
built in central North Dakota and northern
South Dakota Missouri River villages in the
early 1500s by the ancestors of the Mandans
and Arikaras. The earth lodges were thicker
and more insulated than the earlier square or
rectangular dwellings and were a response to
the cooling temperatures of the Neoboreal
("Little Ice Age") climatic regime.</p>

<p>The Mandans, Hidatsas, and Arikaras all
constructed earth lodges in the sixteenth century.
This architectural style rapidly diffused
from the upper Missouri as additional sedentary
tribes migrated onto the Plains from the
south and east and adopted the form. To the
south the Pawnees were firmly established in
central Nebraska by 1600 and living in earthlodge
villages. Archaeological and ethnohistorical
evidence establishes that the Otoes,
Omahas, and Poncas were living in earthlodge
villages on the eastern margins of the
Central Plains by 1700. The Cheyennes briefly
adopted earth-lodge architecture in the mid-
eighteenth century during their occupancy of
eastern North Dakota. Some circular floorplan
structures encountered by archaeologists
working at seventeenth- and eighteenth-century
villages of Central Plains tribes such
as the Wichitas and Kansas are most likely
not earth lodges but grass- or thatch-covered
houses. Mississippian sites in the southeastern
United States occasionally yield earth
lodge-type ceremonial structures. The most
fully documented are at Ocmulgee National
Monument, Georgia. The relationship, if any,
between these and the Plains dwellings is
unclear.</p>

<p>Earth-lodge construction began with the
excavation of a shallow circular area typically
less than one foot in depth with a diameter
varying between twenty and sixty feet. Heavy
vertical timbers served as central roof supports.
The Northern Plains earth lodges almost
always had four center posts. The Pawnees,
Omahas, Otoes, and other Central Plains
tribes used four, six, eight, ten, and even twelve
center posts. Center posts were forked at the
top and connected by horizontal beams. A secondary
row of posts was set around the perimeter
of the floor pit several feet inside the
wall. These were shorter than the center posts
but also connected at the top by a series of
horizontal cross-stringers. A series of closely
spaced sloping posts spanned the area from
the top of the stringers to the ground outside
the house pit. Rafters extended in spokelike
fashion from the top of the wall stringers to
the horizontal beams connecting the center
posts. The rafters did not extend across the
full radius of the house in order to allow room
for construction of a fireplace smoke hole.
Thatching and then layers of thick sod and
grass covered the sturdy superstructure. A
sloping or vertical-walled short entry passage
extended from one side of the lodge, typically
the south or east.</p>

<p>Interior features included a central fire basin,
one or more deep food storage chambers,
and altars. Storage chambers were bell shaped,
narrow at the lodge floor and expanding to
three to five feet at their bases, and were five to
eight feet deep. Such pits were later used for
trash disposal. The Hidatsas called the space
between the outer vertical posts and the exterior
leaners an <hi rend="italic">atuti</hi>. This area was used for
placement of beds and storage of firewood,
tools, weapons, and other personal items.
Beds were either on the ground or on elevated
platforms. Sleeping quarters were generally on
the ledge between the outside of the house pit
and the edge of the leaners. The central portion
of the earth lodge was used for food preparation
and social activities. The back wall
opposite the entry passage often featured an
altar or sacred area. One or more extended
families occupied the earth lodge, which
could house up to sixty people. Villages consisted
of at least a dozen earth lodges and in
many cases of more than a hundred. It was not
uncommon for villages to be home to several
thousand people. Earth lodges were often
closely spaced, and during times of conflict an
earth or timber fortification wall surrounded
the community.</p>

<p>The earth lodge formed the central focus of
many aspects of Plains horticultural village
life. For some tribes, at least, the structures
held important symbolic religious, astronomical,
and social significance. In Pawnee cosmology
the earth lodge was symbolically considered
the heavens. Mandan and Hidatsa
lodges also had sacred symbolism attached to
them, and special earth lodges were reserved
for ceremonial activities such as the Mandan
Okipa (a four-day ceremony of renewal).</p>

<closer>
<signed>John R. Bozell<lb/>
Nebraska State Historical Society</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Ahler, Stanley A., Thomas D. Thiessen, and Michael K.
Trimble. <title level="m">People of the Willows: The Prehistory and Early History of the Hidatsa Indians</title>. Grand Forks: University
of North Dakota Press, 1991.</bibl> <bibl>Nabokov, Peter, and Robert
Easton. <title level="m">Native American Architecture</title>. New York: Oxford
University Press, 1989.</bibl> <bibl>Wilson, Gilbert L. <title level="m">The Hidatsa Earthlodge</title>. Anthropological Papers of the American Museum of Natural History 33 (1934).</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>