<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ct.023">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Fort Worth, Texas</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Ben Procter</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ct.023</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Procter, Ben">Ben Procter</author>. <title level="a">"Fort Worth, Texas."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">167-168</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-27</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">FORT WORTH, TEXAS</head>

<p>On June 6, 1849, Maj. Ripley A. Arnold positioned
forty-two men of Company F of the
U.S. Second Dragoons on the Clear Fork of
the Trinity River, his mission that of guarding
East Texas settlers against Indian incursions.
Within two months he relocated his men to a
more advantageous spot, a high bluff overlooking
the river, and designated this site as
Camp Worth in honor of Brig. Gen. William
Jenkins Worth, who had distinguished himself
in the recent Mexican War. Three months
later, on November 14, 1849, the War Department
o.cially named this area Fort Worth,
thereby establishing a permanent outpost on
the north-central Texas frontier.</p>

<p>During the 1850s Fort Worth struggled to
survive. Even though the army evacuated the
area for a string of forts farther west in 1853,
residents John Peter Smith opened a school,
Julian Field a flour mill, and Henry Daggett
and Archibald Leonard department stores. In
1856 these early settlers also persuaded the
Butterfield Overland Mail and the Southern
Pacific Stage Line to use the town as a western
terminus on the California route, and they
waged a bitter but successful fight in 1860 to
have Fort Worth replace the nearby town of
Birdville as the county seat.</p>

<p>Then came the Civil War and the aftermath
of Reconstruction (1861–74)&#8211;and even
greater struggle. With young men joining the
Confederate army, with money a scarcity on
the Texas frontier, and with food and supply
shortages increasingly apparent, the citizenry
barely survived. By 1866 the population had
dropped to a low of 175. As a result, Fort
Worth soon assumed the title of "Panther
City," suggesting that its environs were so
placid and its ambience so dull that citizens
had discovered a panther sleeping on the
streets.</p>

<p>After 1873 this image changed. Because of
the efforts of merchants Jacob Samuels, William
Jesse Boaz, and William Henry Davis,
banker Khleber M. Van Zandt, and newspaperman
Buckley B. Paddock, Fort Worth
was incorporated, and, with a mayor-council
form of government, the city began to grow.
In 1876 the Texas and Pacific Railway designated
Fort Worth as its eastern terminus, in
part because cowboys rested there before continuing
to drive cattle northward along the
Chisholm Trail to railheads in Kansas and
Missouri. As a consequence, meatpacking became
the principal local business, culminating
with the establishment of Swift and Armour
meatpacking plants in 1902. This, together
with other economic enterprises that prospered
because of the city's eight railroads,
stimulated growth, so that by 1900, with a
population of 26,668, Fort Worth was the fifth
largest city in the state. Residents proudly proclaimed
Fort Worth as the "Queen City of the
Prairies."</p>

<p>Fort Worth continued to expand and prosper
in the first half of the twentieth century. It
became a military and defense center, benefiting
from military contracts and associated
personnel. During World War I the U.S. Army
established Camp Bowie in the western part of
the city, where 100,000 soldiers received instruction
and training; the U.S. Air Force
also converted three airfields into aviationtraining
establishments. In 1942, after the outbreak
of World War II, Consolidated Vultee
Aircraft Corporation (later bought out by
General Dynamics and still later by Lockheed-
Martin) became the largest aircraft manufacturer
in the area; and in 1948 a bomber military
operation became Carswell Air Force
Base, home to the Strategic Air Command's
b-36 bombers.</p>

<p>Other ingredients also guaranteed continued
growth. With the discovery of oil in
West, Central, and East Texas prior to and after
World War I, oil-refining corporations
such as Sinclair, Texaco, and Humble (later
Exxon) selected Fort Worth as a home base
and made it a center for oil exchanges and
field equipment. Equally important was the
leadership of Amon G. Carter, who directed
the economic and political fortunes of the
city. Besides building the <title level="j">Fort Worth Star-Telegram</title> (its logo is "Fort Worth, Where the
West Begins"), he directed the construction of
Casa Mañana (theater-in-the-round) and of
the Texas Frontier Centennial in 1936 to rival
the state fair in nearby Dallas. As a result of
his forceful guidance, the city received muchneeded
federal funds during the Depression.
Carter was largely responsible for a number of
Public Works Administration and Work Projects
Administration projects, most of which
still exist: Will Rogers Memorial Center (an
auditorium), the Botanical Gardens, the John
Peter Smith Hospital, a public library, fortyeight
public schools and playgrounds, lowcost
housing, a high school gymnasium, and
the largest high school football stadium in the
state (Farrington Field). Carter also promoted
the Southwestern Exposition and Livestock
Show (initiated in 1896), which has continued
to grow in popularity.</p>

<p>After the death of Amon Carter in 1955,
James Claude "Jim" Wright assumed the political
mantle for Fort Worth. In 1954 he was
elected to the Twelfth Congressional District,
encompassing Fort Worth and surrounding
cities. In 1977 he became Democratic majority
leader and in 1987 Speaker of the House
of Representatives. As a result, Fort Worth
received favorable congressional attention.
Through his initiatives in the 1960s, federal
funds helped rejuvenate and preserve the historic
north side, where unemployment had
risen to more than 20 percent after the Swift
and Armour meatpacking plants closed in
1962. During the 1960s and 1970s Wright also
effectively championed Fort Worth as a military
center by maintaining and expanding
Carswell Air Force Base and by securing lucrative
Pentagon contracts for companies such
as General Dynamics and Bell Helicopter.
Through his leadership, Fort Worth obtained
federal and state funds for significant floodcontrol
projects, for the construction of U.S.
highways (I-20, I-30, and I-35) that crisscrossed
the city, and for the Federal Center in
the downtown area, which in turn attracted
other government agencies. In 1974 Wright,
together with local and state officials, dedicated
the Dallas-Fort Worth International
Airport, the fourth largest air terminal in the
world.</p>

<p>As a result of such leadership, continuing
with businessmen such as Perry Bass and his
four sons, Fort Worth has continued to expand
significantly. From 1950 to 2000 the population
increased from 277,047 to 534,694,
making Fort Worth the fourth largest city in
the state.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">INDUSTRY</hi>: <ref n="egp.ind.047">Petroleum, United States</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">MEDIA</hi>: <ref n="egp.med.019"><title level="j"><hi rend="italic">Fort Worth Star-Telegram</hi></title></ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Ben Procter<lb/>
Texas Christian University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Knight, Oliver. <title level="m">Fort Worth: Outpost on the Trinity</title>. Norman:
University of Oklahoma Press, 1953.</bibl> <bibl>Pate, J'Nell.
<title level="m">Livestock Legacy: The Fort Worth Stockyards, 1887–1987</title>.
College Station: Texas A&amp;M University Press, 1988.</bibl> <bibl>Sanders,
Leonard. <title level="m">How Fort Worth Became the Texas-most City</title>.
Fort Worth: Amon Carter Museum, 1973.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>