<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ha.004">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main"><hi rend="italic">Betabeleros</hi></title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Rebecca Berru Davis</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ha.004</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Davis, Rebecca Berru">Rebecca Berru Davis</author>. <title level="a">"<hi rend="italic">Betabeleros</hi>."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">351-352</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-25</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main"><hi rend="italic">BETABELEROS</hi></head>

<p>Throughout the twentieth century Mexican
and Mexican American migrant workers were
instrumental in the success of the sugar beet
industry in the Great Plains. Beginning as
early as 1915, corporations such as the Holly
Sugar Company and the Great Western Sugar
Company increasingly depended upon reliable,
experienced, and low-cost labor to cultivate
and harvest sugar beets. Recruited from
Texas, California, and Mexico, these workers
came to be known as <hi rend="italic">los betabeleros</hi>, the sugar
beet workers.</p>

<p>Government-sponsored research and construction of irrigation systems in the 1890s,
combined with a sharp rise in the national
consumption of sugar at the turn of the century,
made the sugar beet industry one of the
fastest growing and most successful in the
Great Plains. Main growing areas were, and
are, eastern Colorado and western Nebraska,
the Yellowstone and Bighorn Valleys of Montana
and Wyoming, and the Red River Valley
of the North. Government and industry cooperated
to provide farmers with the muchneeded
labor in these sparsely populated
areas. Two groups of laborers became the
working backbone of the industry: German
Russians and Mexicans. For example, in 1924
the Great Western Sugar Company brought to
Montana's Yellowstone Valley 3,604 Mexicans
and 1,231 German Russians to harvest a record
31,000 acres.</p>

<p>While the German Russian immigrants
were supported by the sugar beet companies in
purchasing their own farms and settling their
families permanently, the Spanish-speaking
workers were initially hired only as seasonal
workers. Before World War I, this strategy kept
wages down and eased European American
fears of "foreigners" settling permanently in
their midst. But by 1922, as the need for field
labor increased, the corporations began to recognize
that attracting families to "winter over"
assured a stable and experienced workforce. In
Billings, for example, the Great Western Sugar
Company, enlisting the labor of Mexicans, arranged
for the construction of up to forty
small adobe homes. By 1927 hundreds of these
low-cost settlements, known as <hi rend="italic">colonias</hi>, had
been established by the sugar beet companies
throughout the Great Plains.</p>

<p>Within the colonias, residents raised animals
and planted gardens to supplement their
diets, and during the winter those with limited
earnings shared resources. But while the colonias
provided Latinos with a sense of community
and support, they also isolated them from
the larger community. Latinos were often
banned from public swimming pools, segregated
in theaters, and not allowed in certain
stores and restaurants. Sugar beet companies
worked to allay fears and prejudice directed at
the Mexican laborers by citing in their annual
reports and publications how essential they
were to the success of the industry. Despite the
discrimination, the economic hardship, and
the backbreaking labor experienced by the
<hi rend="italic">betabeleros</hi>, many returned to work the fields
each spring, often renewing previous associations
with farmers. Some beet workers even
remained with the farmer throughout the
year, tending to animals and fences during the
winter.</p>

<p>In the Northern Great Plains, the sugar beet
season began in mid-April with planting.
Workers hoed and thinned from late May to
mid-July, weeded through the summer, and
harvested and topped the beets in the fall.
Stoop labor for planting, weeding, and harvesting,
a short-handled hoe for thinning, and
a curved knife for topping made for arduous
work. For the women, in addition to the work
in the fields, the regular household duties of
cooking and cleaning made for a "double day."
Children, by ages eight or nine, were encouraged
to help out and were regularly pulled out
of school to help plant and harvest.</p>

<p>The Depression economy of the 1930s created
an atmosphere of opposition to the migrant
worker. The Great Western Sugar Company
elected to hire local workers before those
from outside the area, thus discouraging Latino
families from remaining. But with the onset
of World War II western growers and industries
faced serious labor shortages. Congress
responded by creating the Bracero Program,
which allowed farmers to employ Mexican nationals.
From 1943 to 1946 Great Western's Billings
district relied on Mexicans to thin and
top most of its crop. After 1963, when Congress
terminated the Bracero Program, companies
continued to rely on Mexican nationals.</p>

<p>In the 1950s, as agriculture was becoming
more mechanized, many Latinos began to
seek out better-paying, steadier jobs. In Billings,
jobs with the railroad or the packing
plants offered a positive alternative to working
the beet fields. While establishing permanent
homes in Billings, Latinos also began working
to improve educational opportunities for
their children. As early as 1929, associations
like the <hi rend="italic">Comision Honorifica Mexicana</hi> were
formed to organize social and cultural events
and assist Latinos in need. In the 1960s <hi rend="italic">Concilio
Mexicano</hi> helped to advocate for jobs and
education in the community. In 1971 the Migrant
Council was established to provide
health, educational, and labor assistance to
migrant families.</p>

<p>Despite farm mechanization, increased use
of herbicides, and continued restrictions on
migrant workers, beet growers still depend on
some hand labor. By 1976 the Great Western
Sugar Company handed over the job of recruiting
and providing migrant workers to the
beet growers. Today, migrant workers, mostly
Mexican Americans from Texas, still come to
the Yellowstone Valley each spring to work the
beets. These seasonal workers follow a route
that takes them on to other states in the region
to pick apples, top and bag onions, and harvest
beans before returning to Texas in late
fall. The migrant workers of the past, including
those who have elected to make a home in
this region and those who choose to return
each year, continue to make a vital contribution
to the economy as well as to enrich the
culture of the Great Plains.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">AGRICULTURE</hi>: <ref n="egp.ag.064">Sugar Beets</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">EUROPEAN AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ea.012">German Russians</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Rebecca Berru Davis<lb/>
Western Heritage Center</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Mercier, Laurie. "Creating a New Community in the
North: Mexican Americans of the Yellowstone Valley." In
<title level="m">Stories from an Open Country: Essays on the Yellowstone River Valley</title>, edited by William L. Lang. Billings <hi rend="smallcaps">MT</hi>: Western
Heritage Press, 1995: 127–47.</bibl> <bibl>Valdes, Dennis N. "Settlers,
Sojourners, and Proletarians: Social Formation in
the Great Plains Sugar Beet Industry, 1890–1940." <title level="j">Great Plains Quarterly</title> 10 (1990): 110–23.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>