<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.wat.001">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Water</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>James E. Sherow</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.wat.001</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Sherow, James E.">James E. Sherow</author>. <title level="a">"Water."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">845-850</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-26</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">WATER</head>

<p>People have always struggled to adapt their
water uses to the windswept, periodically dry
Great Plains. This simple fact has remained
true for Native Americans, Europeans, and
Americans. Cultural values determine how
people view water, and consequently how they
use and develop it. Native Americans on the
Plains stressed the spiritual and communal aspects
of water. European Americans, on the
other hand, conceived of water mainly in
terms of economic development, with the result
being an escalating manipulation of the
water resources of the Great Plains. First surface
irrigation, then dam building, and, most
recently, extensive groundwater pumping
have furnished the key resource for agriculture
and towns, but these processes have also
altered the ecosystems of the region to such an
extent that environmentalists have sounded
alarms. Ultimately, the success or failure of
human societies on the Plains has always depended
upon how well each developed a sustainable
form of water use.</p>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Great Plains Hydraulics</head>

<p>The sources of most major rivers in the Great
Plains are in the Rocky Mountains. In the
Prairie Provinces, the South and North Saskatchewan,
Red Deer, Bow, and Frenchman
Rivers flow generally northeastward from the
mountains. On the Northern Great Plains the
Missouri and its major tributaries, the Milk
and Yellowstone Rivers, flow, respectively,
on easterly, southeasterly, and northeasterly
courses from the Rockies. The Assiniboine,
Qu'Appelle, and Souris Rivers are the main
exceptions to the hydrogeography in that they
rise within the Prairie Provinces.</p>

<p>Farther south, the North and South Platte
and Arkansas Rivers rise toward the Rocky
Mountains of Colorado before taking their
gentle descent eastward. These rivers, and irrigation
dependent upon them, benefit from
the melt of snowpack in the mountains that
sends water to the Central Plains when it is
needed most, during the growing season. Farther
south again, the Canadian River has its
source in the Sangre de Cristo Range, then
flows south along its eastern slope before
crossing the High Plains of Texas into Oklahoma.
The Pecos River folds around the
southern edge of the same range, then cuts a
trench southward to join the Rio Grande. In
Texas the Brazos and Colorado Rivers gather
force on the Llano Estacado before following
courses to the Gulf of Mexico.</p>

<p>Underlying approximately 174,000 square
miles of the Central and Southern Great
Plains is a precious resource, the Ogallala (or
High Plains) Aquifer. Today this underwater
reservoir, "fossil" water that is the remnant of
ancient glacial melts, contains more than 3.25
billion acre-feet of drainable water that is
tapped by about 200,000 irrigation wells. The
aquifer is thickest and most extensive in Nebraska.
In its southern reaches, in southwest
Kansas and the Texas Panhandle, excessive
pumping has exceeded rates of recharge and
lowered levels by more than 200 feet.</p>

<p>Precipitation accounts for surface flows and
a significant amount of groundwater recharge.
Rainfall and snowfall generally increase from
west to east from around fourteen inches annually
near the Front Range to more than
twenty inches by the 100th meridian, and
more than forty inches in southeastern Kansas
as the rain shadow of the Rocky Mountains is
left behind. Variability of rainfall is great
everywhere, with extended periods without
rain each year and a longer, more widespread
drought occurring every twenty years or so.
The drought hazard is greatest in winter.
Moisture availability for plants is also hampered
by the torrential nature of rainfall and
its rapid runoff. It is not uncommon for as
much as one-quarter of the annual precipitation
to be delivered locally in a single storm.</p>

<p>Evaporation and temperature also influence
people's adaptations to their hydraulic
environments. Evaporation rates, which during
the growing season vary from thirty-six
inches in the northern reaches of the Plains to
more than fifty inches in the Southern Plains,
help produce a relatively similar vegetation in
both areas despite variance in precipitation.
But temperature diãerences mean shorter
growing seasons from south to north. The
Southern Plains have an average of more than
200 frost-free days, whereas the Northern
Plains often have fewer than 100.</p>

<p>These climatic differences from north to
south and west to east have many repercussions
for water development. The paucity of
reliable streams in the south hindered irrigation
until the invention of center pivots that
tap the Ogallala Aquifer. The Central Plains
proved most conducive to water development
because of the favorable combination of water
availability (from both surface and groundwater
sources) and relatively lengthy growing
season.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Native American Use and Spanish Influence</head>

<p>Long before European Americans built their
hydraulic society in the Great Plains, Native
Americans understood the crucial importance
of the limited and variable water resources in
the region. The water uses of Plains Indians
were founded upon deep spiritual beliefs, but
they were also adaptations to variations in
precipitation. The ancestors of the historic
Pawnees, for example, moved their villages
westward along the stream courses of the Solomon
and Republican Rivers during times of
increased rainfall, and when precipitation levels
fell they removed eastward toward the Missouri
River. According to Pawnee Indian cosmology,
water formed the fourth creation,
preceded by the earth, life, and timbers, and
followed by cultivated seeds and people. To
the Pawnees, failure of rains and stream flows
implied broken bonds in the reciprocal relationship
between people and water. The Pawnees
gave respect to water to maintain the agriculture
that was so important in the annual
cycle of their lives.</p>

<p>Water was equally important in terms of the
bison hunt. Twice a year the Pawnees conducted
the Great Cleansing Ceremony before
leaving on their hunts. Sacred objects of Pawnee
Indian cosmology were taken to the river
near their villages and symbolically washed.
Afterward the villagers cleaned their dwellings
and the streets, then themselves. The priests
had a sweat lodge constructed for them, then
called all the people to race to the river. The
priests followed, entered the stream, and then
returned to their sweat lodge for a steam bath.
Then the remaining villagers leaped into the
stream, bathing and playing in the water, so all
were cleansed for the hunt.</p>

<p>Horse-mounted bison hunters like the Arapahos,
Blackfeet, Cheyennes, Comanches, Kiowas,
and Sioux also gave great consideration to
the water resources of the Great Plains. They
often made their winter camps and sheltered
their vast horse herds in riparian ecosystems
where timber and grass, as well as water, were
available. The small ponds and springs scattered
throughout the Plains were also essential
resources, places to camp or to water horses
on long journeys. Historically, on the High
Plains there were few areas more than fifteen
miles from a spring. During dry spells many
of these ponds evaporated. Rivers and streams
became sandy beds or flowed intermittently.
Such times exacted terrible tolls on both people
and their animal herds.</p>

<p>When the Spanish colonized the Southwest,
beginning in 1598, they practiced a communal
form of irrigation by combining their
own with Pueblo Indian practices. All people
shared in the governance and maintenance of
the <hi rend="italic">acequia madre</hi>, the mother canal, which
the community owned in common. Hispanics
were still practicing this form of irrigation at
the site of present-day Pueblo, Colorado, during
the 1840s and early 1850s.</p>

<p>As a result of the Spanish and Pueblo influences,
Plains Indians attempted irrigation
practices in the region before 1700. In 1637,
Taos Indians rose up against the Spanish, then
fled eastward into the Great Plains. There they
found support among the Plains Apaches, and
together they built a small pueblo with irrigation
works at a spring in western Kansas, near
the present-day town of Scott City. The Spanish
called the place <hi rend="italic">El Curatelejo</hi>, or distant
quarter. After the Pueblo Revolt of 1680, more
refugees joined the people at El Curatelejo,
but an expedition by Juan de Ulibarri forced
them back to New Mexico in 1706. The Plains
Apaches tried to retain the village and the
practice of irrigated agriculture, but eventually
Comanches forced them to abandon it
sometime after 1750.</p>

<p>Irrigated agriculture was connected to the
Spanish attempt to control the Comanches,
and later to the U.S. attempt to change the
Southern Cheyennes and Arapahos into sedentary
farmers. In the summer of 1787, the
Spanish tried to convince Comanches under
the leadership of Paruanarimuco to relinquish
bison hunting and embrace irrigated agriculture.
The Spanish located a village site where
the San Carlos (Saint Charles) River emptied
into the <hi rend="italic">Rio de Napestle</hi> (today called the Arkansas
River) and began constructing housing
and irrigation works, tilling land, and planting
crops while simultaneously instructing the Comanches
in agricultural practices. By January
1788, under the supervision of master craftsman
Manuel Segura, the <hi rend="italic">Jupe</hi> band of Comanches
occupied their new homes. But Parunarimuco's
wife died that same month, and in
accordance to Jupe custom, the Comanches
abandoned the site. Governor Fernando de la
Concha briefly considered having the pueblo
colonized by New Mexicans but decided that
the expense of protecting the village would be
too costly. So ended the first, and only, attempt
of the Spanish to convert Plains Indian peoples
to irrigation.</p>

<p>Hispanic water practices contributed to the
development of Mormon communal irrigation
systems. Beginning in 1846, a group of
Mormon emigrants observed Hispanic agriculture
around present-day Pueblo, Colorado,
where they learned to integrate their utopian
values with communal irrigation practices.
The Mormons moved to Salt Lake City two
years later and most likely introduced cooperative
irrigation in the "Wasatch Oasis."</p>

<p>Hispanic community irrigation also influenced
Native Americans in the Plains in the
two decades before the American Civil War.
Traders and Native Americans in the Central
and Southern Great Plains recognized the depletion
of game animals. Yellow Wolf, a Southern
Cheyenne, sought an economic alternative
to the fur trade and, with the aid of the Indian
agents in the Upper Arkansas Agency, petitioned
the U.S. government to build an irrigation
colony for the Southern Cheyennes and
Arapahos who wanted to farm. Provisions for
building an irrigation system and support facilities
were part of the Fort Wise Treaty of
1861. Little came of this project, however, as the
Civil War diverted federal resources away from
the initial work near Fort Lyon in southeastern
Colorado. By 1864, the Bureau of Indian Affairs
had enough of the project operational to
grow a small corn crop. But in the early fall
of that year, Southern Arapahos, outraged by
ill treatment by the United States, raided the
works, stole the stock, and killed some of
the bureau's employees. The experiment came
apart in the aftermath of the Sand Creek Massacre
in November 1864. Later the abandoned
system became the foundation of an irrigation
system for European American settlers.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Conceptions of Water</head>

<p>Soon after the creation of Colorado Territory
in 1859, Coloradans began establishing an
elaborate system of water law and regulation.
Although some did attempt to create communal
irrigation works, they treated water differently
than the Spanish, Mormons, and
Plains Indians. The United States used law to
transform water into a marketable commodity
to serve the needs of an economic system
based on individual opportunity and gain.
The aggressive attitude toward water, and toward
environment in general, made possible
the resettlement of the Great Plains by Europeans
and Americans, but it also resulted in
escalating pressures on ecosystems.</p>

<p>When prospectors flocked to the goldfields
of Colorado in the early 1860s, they created a
demand for agricultural products. Some miners
left the hard rock of the mountains for the
soft soils of the river valleys in the Colorado
Piedmont, where they flourished by supplying
food to the miners and ranchers. David Hall
and William Brantner developed small, but
highly successful, irrigation systems on the
South Platte River. Others, like George Washington
Swink, constructed lucrative irrigation
systems along the Arkansas River, supplying
ranchers in the Central Great Plains. Horace
Greeley, the famous editor of the <title level="j">New York
Tribune</title>, eschewed market-oriented irrigation
and tried to perfect utopian, communal irrigation
at Union Colony in the city that bore his
name, Greeley, Colorado. But even the utopians
of Greeley soon set aside their agenda
of social reform for an emphasis on market
agriculture.</p>

<p>As irrigation systems multiplied, draining
watercourses on the western edge of the Plains,
the need arose for water diversion regulatory
laws. It also became apparent that the traditional,
common-law-based doctrine of riparian
rights, which formed the foundation
of water laws in the eastern United States,
was an inadequate method for allocating water
resources in the semiarid Great Plains. According
to this doctrine, water rights were restricted
to people who owned land along
watercourses. In addition, all riparian owners
were entitled to receive an equal amount of
water flow. These principles caused numerous
problems when applied in the Great Plains.
The restriction of the use of water to riparian
lands hampered the development of agriculture
in areas that were not adjacent to rivers
or streams. Even riparian owners themselves
could not use the water for intensive irrigation
because they were not allowed to diminish the
downstream flow of water. Finally, by giving all
riparian owners equal claims to the water resources,
the doctrine made it impossible to
allocate water on the basis of priority needs
during droughts, which frequently plagued the
Plains.</p>

<p>A solution to these problems was provided
by the prior appropriation system of water
rights, which many historians argue originated
in the California goldfields. The miners
created codes to protect the rights of any person
who first developed a "beneficial" water
use, known otherwise as "first in time, first in
right." A miner had a right only to the water
that he could use in his operations and, as
the first to develop his right, could divert this
amount of water before anyone else along the
watercourse.</p>

<p>Coloradans developed the first system of
prior appropriation in the Great Plains. Colorado
lawmakers may have incorporated some
elements of Hispanic traditions in defining
water as a public, rather than a private, resource.
However, they relied to a great extent
upon a commodity notion of water rights in
defining "beneficial use" solely in terms of domestic,
agricultural, and industrial applications.
Moreover, prior appropriation encouraged
the rapid economic development of
stream flows by giving people priority to divert
water in the chronological order in which
each perfected his or her right. Anyone who
waited too long to acquire a water right may
have received little, if any, actual water because
of the priority given to people with earlier
dated rights.</p>

<p>The Colorado Doctrine of water rights relied
upon the courts to determine individual
rights. A person petitioned the state courts for
a right, and the judge granted and recorded
the right once he or she had presented the
appropriate documentation. In 1881 the state
legislature created a state engineer's office
to regulate water rights. The office was also
responsible for dam and irrigation system
safety. Locating the origin of rights within the
courts, and the regulatory duties in the state
engineer's office, made water conflicts in Colorado
a highly litigated realm and underwrote
a flourishing cadre of water lawyers.</p>

<p>A more centralized system of water doctrine
and management developed in Wyoming.
Elwood Mead, a civil engineer who was
guided by an ethic of conservation stressing
the scientific management of natural resources,
formulated a more centralized notion
of water regulation than that of Colorado. The
Wyoming legislature implemented his plans,
which called for a state engineer's office that
not only regulated the operation of a prior
appropriation system of water rights, but also
granted all water rights applications in the
state. In Wyoming the whole focus of water
regulation fell upon the state engineer's office,
whereas in Colorado the state engineer's office
and the state courts shared the responsibility.
In time, the other Great Plains states adopted
some form of the prior appropriation system
and the creation of an engineer's office along
either the Wyoming or Colorado lines, both of
which established the legal basis for putting
water to economic use.</p>

<p>In the Canadian Prairie Provinces ownership
and regulation of water resources (and other
resources, such as land) was, and is, derived
from British Common Law. In practice this
meant that the federal government had authority
to use or alienate water resources in the
three Prairie Provinces until 1930 when such
rights passed to the provincial governments.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">The Irrigation Crusade</head>

<p>As irrigation promoters planned their works,
they had to move quickly to perfect their water
rights. Many promoters envisioned grand irrigation
systems crisscrossing the Great Plains.
In 1872 William Jackson Palmer dreamed of an
irrigation system beginning near Pueblo, Colorado,
and terminating somewhere well within
western Kansas. In 1873 President Ulysses S.
Grant delivered a speech in Denver outlining
an extraordinary plan for building a canal
from where the South Platte River exits the
Rocky Mountains eastward hundreds of miles
to a juncture with the Missouri River. In 1889
Willis R. Bierly, a North Dakota newspaper
editor, advocated constructing a 230-mile canal
from Fort Stevenson on the upper Missouri River to Grand Forks, and from there to
Upper Red Lake in Minnesota, then south to
Grand Rapids, and eventually emptying into
Lake Superior near Duluth. None of these
plans materialized.</p>

<p>Others with similar grandiose schemes
launched projects designed to transform the
shortgrass prairie into a garden. Promoters felt
a sense of urgency because they needed to perfect
viable water rights for their systems, and
this meant laying claim to a flow of water for
beneficial uses before anyone else. Failing in this
meant the ruin of many projects, as western
water courses became "over-appropriated,"
meaning that people had attached more rights
to a stream than its flow could accommodate.
Among the notable promoters between 1870
and 1900 were Theodore C. Henry in Colorado,
Joseph M. Carey in Wyoming, Asa Soule
in Kansas, W. R. Akers in Nebraska, the lawman
Pat Garrett in New Mexico, and S. B.
Robbins in Montana.</p>

<p>One plainsman in particular achieved notoriety
for promoting irrigation as a solution
for social and economic problems. William
Ellsworth Smythe, from Worcester, Massachusetts,
heeded Horace Greeley's call for
young people to head west. Trained as a newspaperman,
Smythe became the editor of <title level="j">The
Enterprise</title> in Kearney, Nebraska. He noted
how farm families were broken during the
droughts that prevailed on the Plains in the
early 1890s. He toured New Mexico and observed
how Hispanic community-based irrigation
systems provided successful crops regardless
of the dry climate. When he returned
to Nebraska he organized a convention to advertise
the virtues of irrigation, and later
he took his mission throughout the West. He
convened a national forum on irrigation in
Salt Lake City in 1891, bringing delegates from
all the western states and territories. The attendees
returned to their homes full of enthusiasm
for irrigation. Also in 1891, Smythe began
publishing <title level="j">Irrigation Age</title>, a journal
dedicated to trumpeting the benefits of irrigation
throughout the West. The "republic of
irrigation," Smythe pronounced, was at hand.</p>

<p>Infected with irrigation fever, several irrigation
promoters rushed into poorly conceived
ventures, overestimated water users' needs,
and recklessly invested their own and others'
funds. T. C. Henry's massive irrigation system
in southeast Colorado failed to provide water
for the 100,000 acres it was supposed to serve.
By the early 1890s the farmers of the La Junta
and Lamar Irrigation Company, Henry's enterprise,
were in desperate straits. In populistic
zeal they turned to the courts of Colorado,
where they found a sympathetic forum.
By 1896 they had wrestled control of the system
away from Henry and collectively acquired
possession of the system and the right
to govern it according to their mutual selfinterest.</p>

<p>Asa Soule, a New York–born traveling salesman,
failed even faster than Henry. He underwrote
the building of the 100-mile-long Eureka
Ditch, constructed in 1884 near Dodge City,
Kansas. Soule invested more than $750,000 of
his own money, but the system never succeeded
in delivering enough water to the farmers
tapping the main canal. In just a couple of
years Soule, his investors, and irrigators had
lost their fortunes on the shortgrass prairies of
southwest Kansas. No one ever attempted to
revitalize Soule's dream, and only the grass-covered
canal banks mark his failed dream of
transforming the semiarid grasslands into
lush, water-intensive croplands.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Enter the Government</head>

<p>Spectacular failures like those of T. C. Henry
and Asa Soule along with the high costs involved
in launching irrigation systems ushered
the federal government into the irrigation
business. The Carey Act of 1894 was the first of
a series of federal laws that regulated Plains
irrigation practices. Joseph M. Carey, a senator
from Wyoming, together with notable investors
like Francis E. Warren, a powerful state
politician, organized the Wyoming Development
Company. In 1883 the company began
constructing a system that eventually irrigated
about 60,000 acres near Wheatland in southeastern
Wyoming. The company completed
more than 100 miles of the main canal by 1885,
but farmers, recognizing the company's lack of
title to the public land, refused to invest. The
Carey Act, unsurprisingly, addressed the needs
of the Wyoming Development Company very
well by allowing the state to select one million
acres for reclamation and to receive patents to
the land once irrigators were making use of it.
The sale of the land to the irrigators either
repaid the state or a private company for building
the irrigation works, and any remainder
returned to the state treasury for the purchase
of other reclamation lands. In the case of Wyoming,
the state held the land patents in trust for
the Wyoming Development Company, and the
company received compensation for its construction
costs through the land sales and for
maintenance through water delivery charges.
The act, however, had little effect beyond the
borders of Wyoming.</p>

<p>John Wesley Powell, director of the U.S.
Geological Survey (<hi rend="smallcaps">USGS</hi>), was determined to
bring greater federal control and planning to
the development of irrigation in the West, including
the Great Plains. In 1878, Powell published
his famous <title level="m">Report on the Lands of the
Arid Region of the United States</title> in which he
proposed a radically changed federal land policy
that called for regional planning around
river basins. Under Powell's plan, farmers
would acquire 80 acres designated for irrigation,
ranchers 2,560 would get acres for their
stock, and regulated timber companies could
harvest the watershed forests. In 1888 Congress
provided Powell with funding to survey public
lands and assess their suitability for irrigation.
State engineers, state politicians, and business
people feared that this centralized mapping
and planning would eliminate any lucrative
possibilities for local developers. Senator
Carey from Wyoming and E. S. Nettleton, a
former state engineer of Colorado and an employee
in the usgs, worked with Elwood Mead
to undermine Powell's political support in
Congress. Their unwillingness to embrace
Powell's notions of ecological planning, which
included criticism of the prior appropriation
system, led to Powell's downfall. The end of
Powell's survey, however, did not mark the
end of government aid to irrigation on the
Plains; rather it presaged further governmental
support after the creation of the Reclamation
Service.</p>

<p>In 1902 Congress passed the Reclamation
Act to subsidize irrigation in the West and to
build new projects. Renamed the Bureau of
Reclamation in 1927, the service bolstered and
expanded water developments such as the Elephant
Butte project on the Rio Grande south
of Albuquerque, New Mexico. The bureau,
however, had little effect on High Plains irrigation
before 1940. The region lacked the
grand dam sites like those in the steep-walled
canyons of the West, and by the twentieth century
little suitable public land remained in the
Plains for the federal government to develop.</p>

<p>The bureau did attempt one innovative irrigation
project: a pump irrigation system near
Garden City, Kansas. J. W. Gregory, an influential
participant in Smythe's irrigation crusade
and the editor of a Garden City newspaper,
spearheaded a campaign to secure
governmental support for a pumping project.
Charles S. Slichter's survey of the groundwater
resources in the vicinity of Garden City enabled
the realization of Gregory's aspirations.
Irrigators formed the Finney County Water
User's Association in order to contract for water
from the service. By 1905 all of the paperwork,
studies, and organization had been
completed, and the bureau was ready to build.</p>

<p>The bureau anticipated having the pumps
ready for the 1908 growing season, but the
only result was conflict with local irrigators
over the operation of the system. The farmers
of the association received little benefit from
the project because the pump machinery
broke down and the government's ditches
leaked. Moreover, in 1909 the Arkansas River
was so full that farmers refused to contract for
any pump water from the bureau. This resulted
in a protest from Frederick Newell, director
of the project, who accused farmers of
reneging on their repayment pledges to the
bureau. In 1910 an angry Newell wrote off the
whole pumping experiment as a failure, and
the federal government never again ventured
into pump irrigation projects.</p>

<p>In the early twentieth century, the federal
courts and the growth of the sugar beet industry
did more to regulate irrigation on the
Plains than the Bureau of Reclamation. The
U.S. Supreme Court established the most important
national precedents regulating interstate
water rights and federal rights to water.
Two cases stand out: <title>Kansas v. Colorado</title> (1907),
which established the doctrine of equity; and
<title>Winters v. United States</title> (1908), which defined
reserved rights.</p>

<p><title>Kansas v. Colorado</title> stemmed from the artificial
division of the Arkansas River by the
Kansas-Colorado state line. This boundary inhibited
the development of a cooperative approach
in using the resources of the river basin
as advocated by John Wesley Powell in his Report
on the Lands of the Arid Region of the
United States of 1879. Instead, Kansans and
Coloradans on each side of the state line
worked hard to put the flow of the river to
economic use without regard for the needs and
plans of the other. Coloradans, of course, had
the advantage because of their upstream position.
As early as the 1890s, Kansans, including
the irrepressible irrigation promoter Charles
"Buffalo" Jones, noted dwindling flows as diversions
proliferated in Colorado. Jones was
unable to finance interstate litigation before
the Supreme Court to remedy the situation.
Marshall Murdock, a powerful newspaper editor
from Wichita, Kansas, possessed the political
clout that Jones lacked, and he persuaded
the Kansas legislature to support a case of original
jurisdiction in the Supreme Court against
Colorado. Kansas attorneys filed their opening
briefs in May 1901, initiating the largest interstate
suit to have ever reached the Court. In
May 1907 Justice David Brewer, a native Kansan,
wrote the Court's opinion, later known as
the "doctrine of equity." Brewer had tallied
economic gains made throughout the Arkansas
River valley and noted how the economies
in both states had steadily grown regardless of
the decreasing river flows into Kansas. Consequently,
he ruled that Kansans had not made a
case for restraining Colorado's water uses.
Kansans, Justice Brewer noted, would have a
case only when they could connect economic
distress with decreasing river flows. From this
time on, the doctrine of equity, the weighing of
relative economic gains made through the use
of water, governed nearly all interstate water
suits.</p>

<p>The court took a completely different tack
in deciding how to protect Native American
water rights. In the case Winters v. United
States, known also as the Winters Doctrine,
Justice McKenna defined "reserved rights."
The case was a result of the Bureau of Indian
Affairs's effort to develop farming on the Fort
Belknap Reservation in northern Montana.
Non-Native farmers built irrigation works
along the Milk River, and by 1905 Native
American farmers on the Fort Belknap Reservation
had little flow to divert for their own
lands. The U.S. Attorney General's office came
to their aid and won the suit in both district
and appeals courts. The Supreme Court upheld
the Native Americans's "reserved" rights,
those rights inherent in the creation of a reservation.
Secondly, the Court's decision preserved
Native American water rights even if
unused, and it allowed for an unquantified
amount of Indian water so long as the flows
were used to pursue economic goals on the
reservation. Ever since, the Winters Doctrine
has guided Supreme Court decisions relating
to Native American water rights.</p>

<p>Even more than Supreme Court decisions,
sugar beets gave stability to the irrigation
economy in the Great Plains. In 1890 Henry
Oxnard, a Bostonian who had learned sugar
cane refining in the South, but later turned to
beet refining, built a large refining factory at
Grand Island, Nebraska. Soon after, he built
another at Norfolk, Nebraska. His American
Crystal Sugar Company became a dominant
economic enterprise on the Central Great
Plains. In 1900 he built the Rocky Ford factory,
and in 1907 the Las Animas factory, in
the Arkansas River valley of Colorado. Other
sugar beet companies, like the Holly Sugar
Company of eastern Colorado and the United
States Sugar and Land Company near Garden
City, Kansas, offered Oxnard all the competition
he could handle. By the 1950s, however,
the beet economy had fallen on hard times,
and most of the factories stood idle. Nonetheless,
sugar beet growing, which requires irrigation,
anchored a regional farm economy before
advances in pump irrigation made other
crops economically feasible.</p>

<p>Irrigation in the Great Plains received an
additional boost during the 1930s. When the
Great Depression struck, the federal government
responded with water projects for the
farm economy. The states needed bureaus that
could coordinate state water planning with
these federal relief projects. In 1936 Montanans
were the first to create such a board, the Montana
Water Conservation Board, with wide
powers to coordinate state planning with the
largess of the federal government. Soon after,
other Great Plains states followed suit with the
creation of their own water boards. A professional
class of water lawyers serving private
irrigation companies, and hydraulic engineers
serving both as consultants and bureaucrats,
grew alongside these state agencies, and together
they guided a complex and highly fractionalized
hydraulic society. Water lawyers
such as Judge Watson McHendrie and engineers
such as Steven Reynolds, Michael Creed
Hinderlider, and George Knapp became regional
household names. Even though water
development in the Great Plains has been a
male-dominated enterprise, women have also
made their marks. During the 1930s and 1940s,
Vena Pointer worked as an effective water lawyer
in the Arkansas River valley of Colorado,
and at the time of this writing Anne Bleed
serves as the chief hydrologist for the state of
Nebraska.</p>

<p>A new development involved the allocation
of water resources through the writing of interstate
compacts and international treaties. Frederick
Newell first proposed compacts while giving
testimony during <title>Kansas v. Colorado</title>, and
Delph Carpenter, a capable and shrewd water
lawyer from Colorado, developed the idea.
Through these means the hydrologists, engineers,
irrigators, and lawyers from the states
involved devised the system to regulate interstate
water flows to their mutual benefit. During
the 1930s and 1940s negotiators concluded
compacts on several Great Plains rivers including
the Arkansas, Republican, and Canadian.
The International Joint Commission,
representing the United States, the western
states, the Prairie Provinces, and the national
government of Canada, negotiated treaties to
develop the Milk River, which flows in and
out of Montana and Alberta. Compacts and
treaties worked simultaneously to promote
economic individualism, to stabilize and augment
the water supply to existing systems, and
to develop new water projects. The Bureau of
Reclamation contributed by building massive
transmountain water diversion projects for
the plains of eastern Colorado. Powerful irrigation
interests around Greeley promoted the
construction of the Big Thompson Transmountain
Water Project. Coloradans in the
Arkansas River valley massed enough political
clout to have Congress underwrite the Frying
Pan Transmountain Water Project. Both of
these projects tap the alpine tributaries of the
Colorado River and divert flows to the semiarid
plains of Colorado rather than heading
toward the Pacific.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">The Pick-Sloan Plan</head>

<p>No one federal project, however, transformed
the Great Plains hydraulics as much as the
Pick-Sloan Plan. In 1927 the Mississippi River
overflowed its banks and destroyed property
from Minnesota to Louisiana. As a result,
Congress authorized the Army Corps of Engineers
to study flood control for its entire
drainage basin. The corps's studies stretched
to the upper reaches of the Missouri River,
and, empowered by the Omnibus Flood Control
Act of 1936, the corps began constructing
a series of "flood control" projects throughout
the Great Plains in the watersheds of the Missouri,
Arkansas, Canadian, and Pecos Rivers
among others. The corps initiated its building
spree on the Missouri River with the Fort Peck
Dam on the northern reaches of the plains of
Montana. This project was completed in 1940.
In 1943 the Missouri River flooded, and this
gave additional impetus to the corps to "control
the Missouri River." The corps leader, Col.
Lewis Pick, emphasized flood control and
paid little heed to irrigation.</p>

<p>The Bureau of Reclamation, fearful of being
outdone by the corps, devised its own plans
for the Missouri River. In his design, William
G. Sloan, a bureau planner, paid particular
attention to hydroelectric power production
and irrigation. Congress had two contending
plans from which to choose, but President
Franklin Roosevelt settled the score by endorsing
basinwide planning for the Missouri
River premised on the Tennessee Valley Authority.
Troubled that a regional agency could
put them out of business, the bureau and the
corps merged their designs and won over
Congress by appealing to representatives and
senators who disliked centralized planning on
the lines of the <hi rend="smallcaps">TVA</hi>.
Congress backed the Pick-Sloan Plan and began
funding in earnest in the late 1940s.</p>

<p>Great Plains residents have expressed great
ambivalence about the merits of the Pick-Sloan
Plan. The Mandans, Arikaras, and Hidatsas
who live on the Fort Berthold Reservation
in North Dakota came to rue the day they
ever heard of the Garrison Dam, one of the
major dams on the mainstem of the Missouri
River. The Pick-Sloan project flooded and
destroyed their best grassland pastures and
ruined their lucrative ranches. The final terms
by which these tribes relinquished their lands
denied them the right to fish in the reservoir,
to water their cattle from it, or to graze their
animals near it. "The members of the tribal
council sign this contract with heavy hearts,"
said George Gillette, the tribal business council
president, when he put his name on the bill
in 1948. Canadians also vigorously protested
the Garrison Dam. They claimed that the dam
would introduce parasites and fish species
from the Missouri into the streams feeding
Lakes Winnipeg and Manitoba and consequently
destroy the trout and pike fishing in
those lakes.</p>

<p>In another case, environmentalists and
farmers gathered to protest the bureau's plans
for an irrigation project to tap the Oahe Reservoir
on the Missouri in South Dakota. One
reason that Senator George McGovern lost his
bid for reelection in 1980 was because of his
rigorous support of the project. The bureau
has not attempted to build this system. In general,
the bureau has trimmed its ambitious
planning as cost overruns became all too common.
For example, the bureau promised
Montanans that 368,000 acres of irrigation
would come their way, when, in actuality,
Montana irrigators had only benefited from
an additional 48,000 acres by 1987. Critics
have even questioned the value of the Pick-Sloan
Plan for flood protection. For example,
hydrologists remain divided as to whether or
not this mass of dams and reservoirs aggravated
or ameliorated the effects of the floods
of 1993. Whatever the case, the Missouri River
has been so drastically altered by dams and the
creation of large "prairie lakes" that it would
be unrecognizable to Lewis and Clark.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Groundwater</head>

<p>Even more than the federal government's direct
subsidy of surface irrigation, it was center
pivots that made irrigated agriculture
a paying proposition throughout the Great
Plains. From the 1880s and 1890s, when hydrologists
first began exploring the various levels
of groundwater beneath the Plains, irrigators
understood that with the right technology
they could bring these waters to the surface.
Windmills provided a start, but the feeble lift
of the machines limited the ways in which
farmers could use them. Irrigators could draw
only from alluviums and shallow groundwater
depths and supply only five acres with a single
windmill. After World War II, efficient natural
gas and gasoline-powered engines drove powerful
pumps that could lift deep groundwater.
Still, farmers found even this technology limiting
in that they had to level their fields carefully
for drainage, monitor siphons, and watch
the progress of water flowing down furrows. In
1949 a Colorado tenant farmer, Frank Zybach,
patented his center-pivot irrigation system in
hopes of alleviating much of the handwork
and costly field preparation associated with
pump irrigation. These aluminum pipe megamachines
mounted to A-frame towers riding
on tandem wheels circle a center-post swivel
where ground pipes tap the water that is
drawn to the surface by pumps. A contemporary
system can irrigate about 133 acres out of a
160-acre quarter section.</p>

<p>Center pivots made possible the extensive
use of the Ogallala Aquifer. Essentially, the
aquifer is the collection of Ice Age runoffs entombed
by the accumulations of soil and sand.
The total "drainable" aquifer holds enough
water to fill Lake Huron, third largest of the
Great Lakes. The saturated thickness of the
aquifer varies, so that some irrigators have
very deep sources beneath their land. Saturated
thickness is an important indicator
given the slow recharge of the aquifer. For example,
some farmers around Lubbock, Texas,
have completely pumped all of the water below
their feet and have been obliged to return
to dryland farming. By contrast, in the mid-
1980s in Nebraska, where the saturated thickness
of the aquifer is at its greatest, irrigators
had used less than 1 percent of the water that
was available in the aquifer prior to pumping.
By one estimate at least, with 1980 pumping
rates, center-pivot systems will be unable to
supply 80 percent of the area presently irrigated
through this system by the year 2020.</p>

<p>Great Plains irrigators and state legislatures
have taken steps to regulate their use of the
aquifer through laws and institutions. In 1927,
for example, New Mexico became the first of
the Great Plains states to bring groundwater
(defined as a public rather than private resource)
under state control; the state engineer
regulates the depletion rates within declared
groundwater basins. Elsewhere, management
systems vary from state to state, but all the
states from Nebraska to Texas that are fortunate
enough to have this underground water
endowment have institutions and regulations
to manage its exploitation.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Irrigation in the Prairie Provinces</head>

<p>As in the American Great Plains, the first irrigation
systems in the Prairie Provinces were
developed by private individuals and local
communities. The beginning of irrigation in
the Prairie Provinces is often attributed to
John Gleen, who, in 1879, began to irrigate his
claim near Calgary. The first major irrigation
systems were introduced to the region, in
southwestern Alberta, by Mormon emigrants
from Utah in the late nineteenth century. After
the passage of the Northwest Irrigation Act in
1894, the federal government assumed a more
active role in promoting irrigation projects.
The central role of the federal government was
made possible by the fact that it held jurisdiction
over natural resources in the three Prairie
Provinces until 1930; other Canadian provinces
had received rights to their resources
through the British North American Act of
1867 and several subsequent court decisions.</p>

<p>Lacking financial assets, the federal government
at first used its extensive rights in the
Prairie Provinces by giving huge land grants to
the railway companies. The Canadian Pacific
Railway, for example, was granted 25 million
acres under its own charter in 1881 and acquired
about 7 million additional acres from
charters of other companies it took over. The
rationale behind the policy was that the companies
would promote settlement on their
lands, and this in turn would result in increased
use of their transportation facilities.
Under their charters, in 1894 the Pacific Railway
Company selected a huge area of land in
southwestern Alberta with the intention of introducing
irrigation. The plan involved a diversion
of the Bow River near Calgary in order
to irrigate an enormous, three-million-acre
"irrigation block." Although the Bow River Irrigation
Project never materialized in its entirety,
in 1914 it resulted in the construction of
the huge Bassano Dam, which made available
a supply of water for the irrigation of nearly
247,000 acres and helped to create a new agricultural
hinterland for Calgary.</p>

<p>Such subsidies exemplify the federal government's
early, primarily indirect, attempts
to promote irrigation in the Prairie Provinces.
A period of more direct involvement began in
the 1930s when the double disaster of economic
recession and prolonged drought hit
the Prairie Provinces. In 1935 as large numbers
of people migrated from Alberta, Saskatchewan,
and Manitoba to other parts of Canada,
the federal government established the Prairie
Farm Rehabilitation Administration (<hi rend="smallcaps">PFRA</hi>)
to improve the farm economy and to arrange
more efficient use of the limited water resources.
At first, <hi rend="smallcaps">PFRA</hi> launched several smallscale
emergency projects, including building
of on-farm "dugouts" (shallow, rectangular
excavations designed to hold water), small
dams to conserve local runoff, and irrigation
works for gardens and small fields. Later, <hi rend="smallcaps">PFRA</hi>
also assisted in more extensive water projects
such as construction of large reservoirs for
water storage in the Milk, Red Deer, Bow, and
South Saskatchewan River basins.</p>

<p>By far the most ambitious water projects in
the Prairie Provinces have focused on river
diversions and dam constructions. These
large-scale, long-term projects have had at
least a triple purpose: to create hydroelectrical
power, to limit flood damages, and to increase
irrigation acreage. Due to heavy capital costs, a
policy was adopted in 1942 that encouraged
cooperation between the federal and provincial
governments in planning and construction.
In general, the federal government has
been responsible for the building of the main
dams and reservoirs, while the provincial governments
have undertaken the construction of
distributive networks. Of the three Prairie
Provinces, the most extensive cost-shared water
projects have taken place in Alberta, which
has, for example, Canada's largest irrigation
project, the St. Mary River Irrigation District.
Saskatchewan and Manitoba, which lack Alberta's
advantageous location along the eastern
slope of the Rocky Mountains, where
snowmelt feeds numerous streams, have been
involved with fewer and less ambitious water
projects. Nevertheless, both provinces, together
with the federal government, have
launched several significant developments, the
most notable of which are the Red River Floodway
in Manitoba, which is aimed to prevent
flooding in the Winnipeg area, and the multipurpose
Gardiner Dam in Saskatchewan.</p>

<p>Thanks to the federal and provincial governments'
extensive river diversion and dam
construction projects, surface water has supplied
most of the irrigation water in the Prairie
Provinces. However, recent years have also
witnessed a notable increase in the use of
groundwater. Between 1973 and 1986, irrigation
acreage in the Prairie Provinces increased
from more than 620,000 acres to nearly 1.4
million acres. Center-pivot irrigation is now
extensively developed, drawing from groundwater
as well as canals, ditches, and reservoirs.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Environmentalism and Water</head>

<p>Conservation of groundwater does not address
the serious and mounting problem of
water pollution in the Great Plains. People
throughout the region face growing levels of
nitrates in their groundwater. This poses a
special health threat to infants and children.
Surface irrigation has also contributed to high
levels of salinity in stream flows in the Southern
Plains. Riparian soils, abundantly impregnated
with salts, produce poor crops when
converted to dryland farming. In fact, these
soils will not even support the growth of former
indigenous grasses like buffalo grass, blue
grama, or short bluestem. Along the streams
in the Southern Plains, salt cedar, a tree imported
to the United States as an ornamental
in the mid-1800s, flourishes in the salt-rich
soils and has significantly altered former plant
and animal communities. Almost 2,000 miles
to the north, the St. Mary Dam in Alberta has
destroyed the cottonwood riparian ecosystem
below the dam. In other places, oil well drilling
has created saltwater incursions into fresh
groundwater supplies. Minimum or zero tillage,
introduced to conserve moisture, has also
increased pollution because chemicals are
now used to control weeds that had previously
been eliminated through the cultivation process.
This situation poses a future threat to
many urban water supplies. Pesticides such as
atrazine are present at high levels in many
stream courses as a result of modern farming
practices.</p>

<p>Beginning in the 1970s, wetland and wildlife
preservation added another aspect to debates
swirling around the environmental effects of
water use and development in the Great Plains.
For example, according to a Kansas Geological
Survey report in 1986, more than 600 miles of
streams in the state rarely flowed. As streams
dry up, wetlands rapidly disappear throughout
the Great Plains. In 1980 Canadian environmentalists
estimated that the Prairie Provinces
had lost 40 to 70 percent of its wetlands. Consequently,
farmers and environmentalists
often find themselves embroiled in controversies
over the preservation of these ecosystems.
In one case the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service
has taken an active stance in working to preserve
the Prairie Potholes, millions of depressions
in glacial drift formed more than 12,000
years ago by retreating glaciers. These hollows,
which cover large areas of Alberta, Saskatchewan,
North Dakota, and South Dakota, hold
precipitation and are important to migrating
fowl. The formation of the Platte River Whooping
Crane Maintenance Trust in 1979 represented
concerns for the protection of wildlife
by maintaining the flow of the Platte River. In
1992, the Kansas chief engineer, David Pope,
restricted pump irrigation in favor of the prior
"recreational" water rights of Cheyenne Bottoms,
a crucially important wetland along the
Central Flyway. Environmentalists in Texas
have become alarmed at the depletion of the
Playa Lakes in the Panhandle. Questions of
wildlife preservation are di.cult to resolve as
they call into question the historical practices
and ideology of water development in the
Great Plains.</p>

<p>The struggles over water uses have surely
reflected the social and economic realities of
the Great Plains. Undoubtedly, some Plains
people have wrung fabulous riches from water
development. Many others have persisted on
the land because of advances in water use.
However, water development has also created
degraded river basins, giving rise to growing
environmental demands for the preservation
of free-flowing streams. Environmentalists, irrigation
companies, urban planners, and Native
Americans face great di.culties as they
grapple with the consequences of a century of
escalating water uses in the Great Plains.
Critics doubt the viability of a legal system
that accords water mainly as a commodity
value subject to technological manipulation
while aquifers and rivers disappear. They
point to the erosion of not only an environment,
but also of a quality of life as water
continues to flow uphill to money in the Great
Plains. Advocates, on the other hand, note the
critical role irrigation has played in the economy
of the region. While they may recognize
some of the shortcomings of irrigation, they
place great faith in water conservation through
technological advances in sprinkler systems
and in the development of new, less waterintensive,
crops. The future of water development
in the Great Plains is unclear, but change
is in the air.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">AGRICULTURE</hi>: <ref n="egp.ag.064">Sugar Beets</ref>; <ref n="egp.ag.053">Prairie Farm Rehabilitation Administration</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">LAW</hi>: <ref n="egp.law.009">Brewer, David</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">NATIVE AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.na.082">Pawnees</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT</hi>: <ref n="egp.pe.019">Climate</ref>.</p>
</div2>

<closer>
<signed>James E. Sherow<lb/>
Kansas State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Clark, Ira G. <title level="m">Water in New Mexico: A History of Its Management
and Use</title>. Albuquerque: University of New Mexico
Press, 1987.</bibl> <bibl>Dunbar, Robert G. <title level="m">Forging New Rights in Western
Waters</title>. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1983.</bibl>
<bibl>Green, Donald. <title level="m">Land of the Underground Rain: Irrigation
on the Texas High Plains, 1910–1970</title>. Austin: University of
Texas Press, 1973.</bibl> <bibl>Howard, Stanley W. <title level="m">Green Fields of Montana:
A Brief History of Irrigation</title>. Manhattan <hi rend="smallcaps">KS</hi>: Sunflower
University Press, 1992.</bibl> <bibl>Kromm, David, and Stephen
E. White, eds. <title level="m">Groundwater Exploitation in the High Plains</title>.
Lawrence: University Press of Kansas, 1992.</bibl> <bibl>Kuzelka,
Robert, et al., eds. <title level="m">Flat Water: A History of Nebraska and Its
Water</title>. Lincoln <hi rend="smallcaps">NE</hi>: Conservation and Survey Division and
Institute of Agriculture and Natural Resources, 1993.</bibl>
<bibl>"North Dakota Water History: Politics and Dreams." <title level="j">North
Dakota History: Journal of the Northern Plains</title> 59 (1992).</bibl>
<bibl>Opie, John. <title level="m">Ogallala: Water for a Dry Land: A Historical
Study in the Possibilities for American Sustainable Agriculture</title>.
Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1993.</bibl> <bibl>Reisner,
Marc. <title level="m">Cadillac Desert: The American West and Its Disappearing
Water</title>. New York: Viking Penguin, 1986.</bibl> <bibl>Sherow,
James E. <title level="m">Watering the Valley: Development along the High
Plains Arkansas River, 1870–1950</title>. Lawrence: University
Press of Kansas, 1990.</bibl> <bibl><title level="m">The State of Canada's Environment</title>.
Ottawa: Minister of the Environment, 1991.</bibl> <bibl>Tyler, Daniel.
<title level="m">The Last Water Hole in the West: The Colorado-Big Thompson
and the Northern Colorado Water Conservancy District</title>.
Niwot: University Press of Colorado, 1992.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>