<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.arc.050">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Trading Posts</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>William J. Hunt Jr.</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.arc.050</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Hunt Jr., William J.">William J. Hunt Jr.</author>. <title level="a">"Trading Posts."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">97-98</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-14</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">TRADING POSTS</head>

<p>During most of the fur trade era in the Great
Plains, trading post architecture typically followed
a ground plan ultimately derived from
military fortifications, thus the common use
of the word "fort" in trading post names. The
strong, defensive nature of trading posts was a
by-product of the very nature of the trade. For
the (typically) European American builders,
the fortified post provided asylum from a
rough and dangerous world far from the comforts
of home. The fortified architecture also
afforded protection for valuable trade goods
and provided sanctuary from sometimes hostile
Native American trading partners. Native
American traders coming to the post may have
perceived conflicting messages of promise and
threat in the strong defensive character of the
fort. The structures were a source of seemingly
endless material goods, but the goods could
only be acquired from heavily armed and
sometimes incomprehensible traders.</p>

<p>Trading posts typically incorporated a
structural assemblage encompassed by a
square or rectangular palisade. This enclosure
was generally constructed of vertical timbers
set in a trench and about twelve to eighteen
feet in height. Two square bastions or blockhouses
were often built on opposing corners
of the palisade. More rarely, these had a circular
floor plan. The bastions generally had a
pitched roof and loopholes from which small
cannon and shoulder arms could be fired. To
impede hostile intruders from climbing over
the top, palisade pickets were occasionally
sharpened or surmounted with chevaux-defrise
(crossed, pointed sticks). A gallery (or
building roofs in smaller posts) was usually
built about four to five feet below the top of
the pickets to allow sentries to patrol and fire
from the palisade perimeter.</p>

<p>Inside the palisade, buildings were raised
around a commons area or open courtyard
outfitted with cannon and flagpole. In smaller
forts, buildings were constructed directly
against the palisade's interior walls. Larger
posts usually had structures set out from the
palisade with the space between the palisade
and structures frequently used for storage or
as stables. A house, or "mansion," for the
bourgeois or fort superintendent, generally
the most imposing structure in the complex,
was usually placed opposite the main entrance
to the post and would have been the first
structure seen by those entering. It often displayed
painted wooden siding. Aside from
serving as a home for the superintendent,
clerks, and guests, the mansion would house
the post's business office and dining hall. A
separate kitchen was placed behind or near
this building. The remaining three sides of the
courtyard incorporated ranges of lesser structures.
These were usually constructed more
crudely without siding and left unpainted.
Earth or sod was most commonly the roofing
material of choice for these buildings. Structures
in the ranges served the trading company
as icehouse, powder magazine, employee
residences, fur storage, trade and dry goods
storage, blacksmith shop, and trade store.</p>

<p>With rare exceptions, trading posts were
constructed according to vernacular building
traditions common to the region in which
they were raised. Aside from typical notchedlog
structures, vernacular French M&#233;tis construction
methods were commonly employed
in the Canadian Plains. <hi rend="italic">Poteaux en terre</hi> (posts
in earth) structures utilized a wall or building
frame of vertical whole or split timbers placed
into trenches in the ground. A more challenging
construction method was <hi rend="italic">poteaux sur sole</hi>
(posts on sill), which placed vertical posts on
wood or stone sills to prevent wood rot and
thus provide greater structural endurance.
Spaces between vertical framing were packed
with mud and grass (<hi rend="italic">bouzill&#233;es</hi>) or stone and
plaster mortar (<hi rend="italic">pierrott&#233;es</hi>).</p>

<p>Another common construction method
seen on the Canadian Plains was Red River
frame, or pi&#232;ce sur pi&#232;ce (timber on timber).
Like poteaux sur sole, this French M&#233;tis construction
method used vertical logs raised on
a wooden sill. In this instance, however, the
vertical members were grooved. Spaces between
vertical members were filled with horizontal
logs whose tongues or tenons were inserted
into the vertical grooves to make a wall.
Interior walls were commonly plastered and
whitewashed.</p>

<p>Occasionally, adobe was used in the construction
of trading posts on the Northern
Plains (e.g., Fort William, North Dakota).
This building material was more commonly
used on the Southern and Central Plains, reflecting
the greater Hispanic influence in these
regions. Examples of adobe trading posts include
Fort John (later Laramie) in Wyoming,
Fort John in Nebraska, and Bent's Fort in Colorado.
Adobe provided an excellent substitute
for wood in the relatively dry climate of the
High Plains, an area with few trees. Aside
from its excellent insulating qualities, adobe
construction allowed more free-form structures.
Bent's Fort, for example, had circular
bastions and generally displayed an abundance
of curved structural elements. As such,
it had a less forbidding look to it than Fort
Union in North Dakota, for example.</p>

<p>Trading posts in the Great Plains were generally
of three types, their structural complexity
reflecting their position in the fur trade
business hierarchy. At the pinnacle of the hierarchy
was the major post. These fortified complexes
(such as Fort Union, North Dakota,
and Fort Garry, Manitoba) functioned as the
regional headquarters of a company or trading
outfit. They supplied and directed the
trade of a number of subsidiary trading posts
and wintering posts. Like posts subsidiary to
them, however, major posts also served as a
center for trade over an extensive area with
one or more Native American bands. Major
posts were usually quite large, imposing in appearance,
and designed to last for a relatively
long period of time.</p>

<p>Subsidiary posts such as Fort McKenzie,
Montana, and Fort Qu'Appelle, Saskatchewan,
were under the administration of a major
post. Subsidiary posts were located in the
general wintering area of an individual tribal
group or band and operated year-round. Although
usually smaller in size than the major
posts, they were fortified similarly. In keeping
with their secondary status, subsidiary posts
were constructed more simply and usually
built to last for a much shorter duration.</p>

<p>Wintering houses were the smallest and
most temporary of trading posts. Administratively
situated under one of the other two
kinds of posts, they tended to be unfortified
and often consisted of little more than a rude
log cabin or even a skin lodge. Wintering
houses generally formed the "front line" of
the fur and bison robe trade, and as such they
were usually placed in or near the village of a
nomadic group. Since the nomads rarely wintered
in exactly the same place from year to
year, these establishments typically served the
trade for a single trading season. Small-scale
independent trading companies tended to resort
to this type of post as a necessity, their
financial resources being too meager to allow
construction of larger palisaded posts.</p>

<p>Fortified trading posts in the Central and
Southern Plains were largely replaced by small
entrepreneurial operations during the 1840s.
The large trading posts of the previous era
were similarly reduced in scale to small log or
adobe structures. On the Northern and Canadian
Plains, however, large enterprises continued
to operate fortified trading posts for
several decades past the demise of their southern
cousins. By 1870, however, even that region's
elaborate trading posts were being replaced
by small posts comprised of simple,
unfortified log structures similar to those that
had been built on the Southern Plains in previous
decades.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">INDUSTRY</hi>: <ref n="egp.ind.022">Fur Trade</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>William J. Hunt Jr.<lb/>
National Park Service</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Burley, David V., Gayle Horsfall, and John Brandon.
<title level="m">Structural Considerations of M&#233;tis Ethnicity: An Archaeological, Architectural, and Historical Study</title>. Vermillion:
University of South Dakota Press, 1992.</bibl> <bibl>Chittenden,
Hiram M. <title level="m">The American Fur Trade of the Far West</title>. Lincoln:
University of Nebraska Press, 1986.</bibl> <bibl>Moore, Jackson
W., Jr. <title level="m">Bent's Old Fort: An Archeological Study</title>. Denver:
State Historical Society of Colorado, 1968.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>