<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.fol.001.01 SYSTEM "egp.fol.001.01.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY egp.fol.001.02 SYSTEM "egp.fol.001.02.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY egp.fol.001.03 SYSTEM "egp.fol.001.03.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY egp.fol.001.04 SYSTEM "egp.fol.001.04.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fol.001">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Folkways</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Timothy J. Kloberdanz</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fol.001</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Kloberdanz, Timothy J.">Timothy J. Kloberdanz</author>. <title level="a">"Folkways."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">285-290</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-09</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">FOLKWAYS</head>

<p>Folkways, the unofficial traditions of a people
that are passed on informally from person to
person or from one generation to another,
are an integral part of the cultural heritage
of every group of human beings. Yet no matter
how carefully they are passed on, many
folkways tend to assume variant forms with
each successive performance or retelling. Even
members of the same family who know a favorite
story will relate the narrative in slightly
different ways. Folkways mirror the forces
of tradition, but they also reflect the everchanging
nature of culture and the predilections
of each new generation of storytellers.</p>

<p>The diverse number of Great Plains folkways
matches the diversity and vastness of the
region itself. To be sure, many folkways have
gone unstudied or unrecorded. Some undoubtedly
have vanished without a trace. Others
exhibit incredible resilience and have persisted
for centuries and even millennia.</p>

<p>Among the earliest known inhabitants of
the Great Plains were hunters and gatherers
who lived at least 11,500 years ago. These early
folk, who pursued mammoths and prehistoric
bison, tipped their spears with exquisitely
fashioned stone points. Other than their
stone-age technology, relatively little is known
about the ancient people archeologists refer to
as Clovis. Yet there are intriguing hints of
Clovis folkways, including the use of stone
tool caches, incised bone rods, and red ochre.
At the Anzick site near Wilsall, Montana, a
whole cache of Clovis projectile points and
other artifacts came to light that were colored
with red ochre. The Anzick discovery helps us
appreciate not only the possible existence of
ancient Great Plains folkways but also their
time-depth, which extends back many thousands
of years.</p>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Definitional Considerations</head>

<p>In 1906 American sociologist William Graham
Sumner published <title level="m">Folkways</title>, a volume that
focused attention on a society's common
usages, manners, customs, mores, and morals.
To his credit, Sumner deemed such modes of
expression as worthy of study. But Sumner did
not fully comprehend the complexity of the
beliefs and customs that he tried to analyze. He
was hindered by both his apparent lack of familiarity
with non-American folkways and
other prevailing schools of thought that also
focused on "folk" phenomena. Nonetheless,
Sumner's <title level="m">Folkways</title> proved influential, especially
in the disciplines of history, psychology,
and sociology. The influence extended into
many nonacademic areas and even business
ventures. In 1949, for example, Folkways Records
was established and the company produced
numerous recordings that became
known all over the world. The term "folkways"
soon was heard in many parts of the Great
Plains as well. Today, Plains dwellers who never
heard of William Graham Sumner or Folkways
Records sometimes characterize their traditions
as "folkways."</p>

<p>A much older term, and one that is most
often used today, is "folklore." This term can
be traced back to 1846 in England, and it
gained a foothold in North America with the
founding of the American Folklore Society in
1888. The parameters of folklore study have
been debated and discussed for decades by
folklorists. In <title level="m">The Study of American Folklore</title>
(1986), folklorist Jan Harold Brunvand provides
an inclusive but straightforward definition:
"Folklore comprises the unrecorded traditions
of a people; it includes both the form
and content of these traditions and their style
or technique of communication from person
to person." Brunvand divides the subject matter
of folklore into three main categories: oral
folklore (e.g., folk narratives, folk speech,
proverbs, riddles, traditional rhymes and poetry,
folk songs, folk music); customary folklore
(e.g., folk beliefs, folk customs and festivals,
folk dances and dramas, gestures, folk
games); and material folk traditions (e.g., folk
architecture, crafts, arts, costumes, and food).
Brunvand is well aware that many folk phenomena
overlap (as in the case of a folk festival
that incorporates folk songs and traditional
foods), and thus his divisions serve
more as a useful guide rather than a rigid system
of classification.</p>

<p>Still another term that is frequently used
by contemporary folklorists is "folklife." The
word has its counterpart in the Swedish <hi rend="italic">folkliv</hi>,
which dates from 1847. Unlike the terms
"folkways" and "folklore," the Europeaninspired
"folklife" emphasizes traditional life
within a particular society. In 1976, with the
establishment of the American Folklife Center
at the U.S. Library of Congress, a new definition
of folklife emerged that stressed "traditional
expressive culture" as found in a variety
of groups: familial, ethnic, occupational, religious,
and regional.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Ethnic and Occupational Folklife</head>

<p>Popular misconceptions about the Great
Plains abound. One still hears comments that
the region is unusually monotonous, in terms
of both landscape ("There's not a hill in
sight!") and culture ("They all look like northern
Europeans!"). Such criticism is in the
same vein as much earlier impressions of the
region that characterized the Great Plains
as the "Great American Desert," where nearly
everything (wood, water, people) was found
to be sorely lacking.</p>

<p>To the Plains Indians the region was and
remains a powerful place for dreams and visions.
When European explorers arrived in the
Plains, they encountered many Native peoples
who were either village-based horticulturalists
or nomads who pursued bison and other animals
on foot. By the late 1800s, well after the
advent of the horse and other, often imposed,
changes, the lifestyles of Plains Indian groups
had changed dramatically. Despite forced confinement
on reservations, and concerted efforts
by Americans to destroy their belief systems,
Plains Indian peoples and folkways have
survived. Beadworking, quillworking, and the
making of star quilts are just a few examples of
the varied traditional Plains Indians arts and
crafts that have passed down from generation
to generation. Many oral traditions, like trickster
tales and stories of legendary and supernatural
beings, are still told by tribal and clan
elders, often in the Native language, or sometimes
in English with a sprinkling of Native
terms to accommodate listeners who have not
learned their native tongue.</p>

<p>Spanish-speaking groups in the Great
Plains also have preserved many of their folk
traditions, most notably in the Southern
Plains. Mexican American folklife is enriched
by use of the Spanish language, numerous
folk beliefs, festive events, and folk religious
practices that exist alongside Roman Catholicism,
mainstream medicine, and other formal
institutions.</p>

<p>On the Northern Plains, where Frenchspeaking
fur traders were among the first Europeans
to encounter Native peoples, a distinct
racial and social group emerged known
as the M&#233;tis. Ojibwa and Cree traditions
mingled with those of the French and with
other European folkways as well, most notably
Irish, Scottish, and English. The "Michif " language
resulted, as did a fondness for fiddling
and dancing (in mocassined feet) to the "Red
River Jig" and other folk tunes. Today, M&#233;tis
identity remains strong, and families still converge
on "Li Zhour di Lawn" (New Year's Day)
and other festive occasions to play music,
share stories, and feast on traditional M&#233;tis
foods like "bullets" (meatballs) and "bangs"
(pieces of fry bread).</p>

<figure n="egp.fol.001.01" rend="granted">
<figDesc>A M&#233;tis group performs the Red River Jig</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Numerous ethnic groups have settled in the
Great Plains and added to the diversity and
richness of prairie folklife. Following the
Homestead Act of 1862 in the United States
and the Homestead Act of 1873 in Canada, and
promotional campaigns by the railroads and
other companies, thousands of families took
up residence in the Great Plains. Some of
these families were Anglo-Americans and
Anglo-Canadians who simply migrated west,
but many newcomers were immigrants who
came from distant lands. One of the largest
ethnic groups to settle in the Great Plains were
the Germans. Their surnames and accents
may have sounded similar to outsiders, but
the Germans were unusually heterogeneous in
terms of religious and regional traditions.
German-speaking Catholics, Lutherans, Baptists,
Mennonites, and Hutterites from German
and eastern European states, for example,
formed separate communities and seldom
intermingled.</p>

<p>In the mid 1870s the first Germans from
Russia entered the Great Plains. Experienced
with growing wheat and living on the treeless
steppes of Russia, these settlers soon put down
roots in many areas of the Plains. The Black
Sea Germans settled primarily in the Dakotas
while the Volga Germans established communities
in Kansas and other Central Plains
states. Russian Mennonites also came to the
Great Plains and settled in great numbers in
the prairie lands of Manitoba and Saskatchewan.
Hutterites (Hutterite Brethren) started
out in what is now South Dakota, but many
migrated to Canada due to anti-German persecution
(mainly because of their refusal
to serve in the military) and wartime hysteria
in 1918. Today, the Hutterites are the most
conservative of all the Germans from Russia.
They still live in colonies, use German as
their primary language, and their lives are
steeped in the folk traditions of their Anabaptist
forebears.</p>

<p>The Great Plains also attracted large numbers
of English, Irish, Scottish, and Welsh settlers
who were influential in the development
of many towns and small businesses. The Norwegians,
Swedes, Finns, and Icelanders were
most numerous in the Dakotas and other
areas of the Northern Plains, while groups like
the Czechs and Poles settled mainly in Nebraska
and elsewhere in the Central Plains.</p>

<p>African Americans were in many parts of
the Plains as early as the 1860s but a real impetus
for settlement occurred in the late 1870s.
Thousands of former slaves known as "Exodusters"
headed west and established African
American communities like Nicodemus, Kansas,
and Dearfield, Colorado. As with so many
other ethnic groups, those who came later
often took up residence in the more densely
populated areas of the Great Plains.</p>

<p>Many British and French settlers put down
roots in the Canadian Prairie Provinces, but
Ukrainian, Hungarian, Romanian, and many
other immigrants also established viable communities.
When agricultural lands were no
longer available for settlement, immigrants
continued to stream into Canadian towns and
cities. Prairie urban centers such as Calgary,
Regina, and Winnipeg all include diverse ethnic
communities where folk traditions are integral
parts of everyday life. A walk through
Winnipeg's historic North End, for example,
will take you past the Ukrainian Catholic
Saints Vladimir and Olga Cathedral, past the
Wawel Meat Market with its displays of buckwheat
sausage, and past Gunn's counters of
bagels and knishes.</p>

<p>Asian Americans settled in various parts of
the Great Plains and have operated farms and
businesses for generations. Early Japanese
immigrants, for example, worked as manual
laborers in the sugar beet fields of eastern Colorado,
western Nebraska, and southern Alberta
until they accumulated enough money to
acquire farms of their own. More recently,
Vietnamese, Cambodian, and East Indian immigrants
have moved into Great Plains communities,
where they keep alive such folkways
as silk embroidery, traditional storytelling,
and Kathak (Indian) folk dance.</p>

<p>Many ethnic groups of the Great Plains
often found it difficult to maintain their folk
traditions due to the small number of families
involved. In the late 1800s, for example, Russian
and Romanian Jews established agrarian
colonies in Kansas, Nebraska, North Dakota,
and Saskatchewan. Most of these agricultural
experiments proved unsuccessful, but the recollections
of such endeavors are still kept alive
in the folklore of countless families. Linda
Mack Schloff, in her book And <title level="m">Prairie Dogs Weren't Kosher</title> (1996), reveals a wealth of oral history material and photographs relating to
Jewish farmers in the Great Plains.</p>

<p>Just as the Plains attracted many ethnic and
religious groups, it also provided a home for
individuals of varying occupations. Fur traders,
scouts, soldiers, blacksmiths, ranchers,
sheepherders, rainmakers, railroad workers,
stoop laborers, Canadian Mounties, oil field
roughnecks, and a host of other occupational
groups all have left their mark on the Great
Plains. In the 1800s and early 1900s the most
common occupation was that of farmer. But
in a region as diverse and vast as the Great
Plains, the occupation of farming greatly varied.
A person engaged in farming in the Great
Plains might be a dryland farmer, an irrigation
farmer, a truck farmer, or a part-time
farmer or rancher. Farming usually involved
families who, during harvest and at other
times of the year, pitched in to keep things
running smoothly. Farming was a way of life,
not merely an activity. And this type of labor-intensive
occupation gave rise to an incredible
number of folk traditions. The traditions were
most often seasonal in nature and ranged
from planting rituals and barn cleanings in
the spring, to ditch burnings and hog butcherings
in the fall.</p>

<p>Surely no occupational group in the Great
Plains has received as much attention as cowboys.
This is to be expected when one remembers
how important ranching is in the Great
Plains. Cowboys have been an integral part of
Plains life going back to the great cattle drives
of the 1860s and 1870s. Since that time, the
image of the cowboy has been romanticized in
countless books, television shows, and motion
pictures. Seldom is there an opportunity for
cowboys to be seen for who they really are&#8211;
hardworking men and women involved in a
folk tradition that brings them into daily contact
with cattle and horses. Much of what they
know was taught to them by other cowboys&#8211;
grandparents, parents, friends, or coworkers.
Cowboy folklife manifests itself in countless
ways, ranging from well-worn cowboy boots
and leather chaps to community rodeos and
"cowboy lingo."</p>

<p>Although there are many well-known cowboy
songs, the popular image of the "singing
cowboy" does not fit every Great Plains buckaroo.
Like members of other groups, there are
those cowboys who sing, others who simply
sit and listen, and still others who would prefer
to do something like drive cattle rather
than serenade them. Recently, there has been
great public interest in cowboy poetry, which
has ties to the balladlike pieces recited by trail
hands a century ago and more. In the 1980s
folklorists turned their attention to contemporary
cowboy poetry, and there has been a
virtual outpouring of published and recited
work relating to cowboy folklife. Anthologies
of cowboy poetry also have appeared, including
Teresa Jordan's <title level="m">Graining the Mare: The Poetry of Ranch Women</title> (1994).</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Oral Folklore</head>

<p>One of the richest sources of published material
relating to Great Plains folkways is oral
folklore. This does not mean that there has
always been more oral folklore in the Plains
than customary folklore or other folk traditions.
Instead, it may reflect the interests of
early collectors of folklore who emphasized
oral forms of traditional expression (e.g., legends,
myths, tall tales). In their zeal to collect
certain stories, many other traditions went
completely unnoticed. This is unfortunate, as
the folklore of a group is best understood and
appreciated within its cultural context, and
this requires the serious investigator to pay
close attention to the totality of traditional life.</p>

<p>In terms of oral folklore, one of the best
indicators of group identity is folk speech. Native
Americans, African Americans, Hispanic
Americans, Asian Americans, and European
Americans all contributed to linguistic diversity in the Great Plains. Yet over time the
Plains experience gave rise to a distinct form
of folk speech that revealed an emerging regional
identity, no matter what the ethnic or
racial background of the speaker. Winfred
Blevins, in his <title level="m">Dictionary of the American West</title>
(1993), includes many examples of Great
Plains folk speech: "prairie lawyer" (a coyote);
"prairie strawberries" (a humorous name for
beans, an old standby); "prairie wool" (another
name for buffalo grass); and "prairie
cocktail" (a salted and peppered raw egg in
liquor or vinegar).</p>

<p>Published collections of Great Plains proverbs
and folk expressions are unfortunately
rare. Nonetheless, examples of these types of
oral folklore can be found in various regional
compilations like S. J. Sackett and William E.
Koch's <title level="m">Kansas Folklore</title> (1961) and Louise
Pound's <title level="m">Nebraska Folklore</title> (1987). In an essay
on Nebraska snake lore, Louise Pound includes
a number of folk expressions dealing
with snakes, varying from "As crooked as a
snake" to "Madder than snakes in haying."
Great Plains riddles also are a much-neglected
genre, but examples of riddles told and enjoyed
by prairie dwellers can be found in
<title level="m">Kansas Folklore</title> and in more comprehensive
collections such as John Greenway's <title level="m">Folklore of the Great West</title> (1969). Greenway includes a
number of traditional riddles that reflect the
realities of rural life: "What walks in the water
with its head down?" (Answer: "The nails in a
horse's shoe when he walks through the water")
and "What goes 'round the house with a
harrow after her?" (Answer: "A hen with her
chickens&#8211;all engaged in scratching up the
ground").</p>

<p>Unlike proverbs and riddles, folk narratives
have received considerable attention, for the
Great Plains is a region of great stories and
great storytellers. Among the earliest collections
of Great Plains folk narratives are those
compiled by anthropologists and other researchers
who did fieldwork for the Bureau
of American Ethnology. Numerous narratives
were recorded in the native languages of Plains
Indian storytellers, and these texts comprise a
valuable folkloristic and linguistic resource
even today. Early writers like George Bird
Grinnell, who were intimately familiar with
Plains Indian folkways, added richly to narrative
collections. Grinnell's early books, including
<title level="m">Pawnee Hero Stories and Folk-Tales</title> (1889)
and <title level="m">Blackfoot Lodge Tales</title> (1892), are still in
print and widely read.</p>

<p>Plains Indian folk narratives continue to be
a focus of interest, both on the part of scholars
and the general public. In recent years, collections
have appeared that include contemporary
narratives told by Native storytellers. An
example of one such collection is Keith Cunningham's
<title level="m">American Indians' Kitchen Table Stories</title> (1992). Native writers also have published
a growing number of works that include
folk narratives. In many cases, Native
American writers provide the all-important
cultural context for understanding the role of
narratives in contemporary Plains Indian life.
A recent example is Delphine Red Shirt's <title level="m">Bead on an Anthill: A Lakota Childhood</title> (1998), in
which she describes the influential way that
Plains Indian stories about "Double Woman"
and "Iktomi" (Spider) inspired and strengthened
her.</p>

<p>For the many ethnic and occupational
groups who make the Great Plains their
home, folk narratives serve as a rich source of
local knowledge that strengthens group identity.
But the Great Plains also has folk narratives
that transcend ethnic and occupational
boundaries. Legends are clearly a case in
point. These folk narratives are localized and
are related in a conversational style as "true
stories." They range from narratives about
haunted farmhouses and prairie ufos to
much more mundane subjects, such as cattle
theft and runaway tractors. One legend heard
all over the Great Plains concerns a rancher
who traps a troublesome coyote. He suspects
the coyote is a predator and so he ties a stick of
dynamite to the coyote's leg, lights the fuse,
and quickly releases the animal from the trap.
The coyote, confused and frightened, runs under
the rancher's new pickup truck. Legend
expert Jan Harold Brunvand, in his book <title level="m">The Choking Doberman</title> (1984), refers to this folk
narrative as "The Coyote's Revenge" and notes
its similarity to Native American stories in
which the coyote is a perennial trickster.</p>

<p>Another genre of folk narrative that is common
to the Great Plains is the tall tale. While
not confined to the American and Canadian
Plains, the tall tale is completely at home in
the land of big skies, baseball-size hailstones,
and sizzling summer temperatures. But unlike
the legend that elicits gasps and a sense of
dread, the tall tale prompts chuckles and belly
laughter. The telling of tall tales enables Plains
dwellers to poke fun at the larger-than-life
forces that face them almost daily. When
asked if they are getting enough rain, sunblackened
Great Plains farmers might reply:
"No, not much at all. Even the carp and crawdads
are down to their last canteen." Folklorist
Roger Welsch relates this favorite Great Plains
tall tale: "Three farmers all died at the same
time. All of them wanted to be cremated. One
was from Texas, one from Kansas, and the
third from Nebraska. The guy from Texas was
ashes in two hours&#8211;ditto for the Kansan. But
they left the guy from Nebraska in for two
days, and when they opened the door he
jumped out and said, 'My God, two weeks
more like this and there won't be any corn
crop this year.'" A number of tall-tale publications
dealing with the Great Plains and the
American West have appeared. Roger Welsch's
<title level="m">Shingling the Fog and Other Plains Lies</title> (1972)
and Robert E. Gard's Canadian classic <title level="m">Johnny Chinook</title> (1945) are among the most amusing
and comprehensive.</p>

<p>Prairie dwellers have sung songs for centuries
and danced to the sound of many musical
traditions. Although Native American folk
music in the Plains is extremely diverse, intertribal
powwow celebrations have done much
to bring Native peoples of different backgrounds
together. At such gatherings, Indians
from the Canadian Prairies and those from
the Southern Plains come into contact and
realize there are many similarities they share
in common. Numerous powwows take place
throughout the Great Plains each year. One of
the largest is the Crow Fair at Crow Agency,
Montana, which attracts thousands of participants
and spectators.</p>

<p>The folk musical traditions of the Great
Plains often reveal evidence of cultural borrowing
and sharing. In the sugar beet region
of the Central Plains states (western Nebraska,
northeastern Colorado, and southeastern Wyoming),
a distinct type of polka music known
as "the Dutch Hop" is still popular. The fastpaced
music represents a Volga German folk
tradition that exhibits many Russian and
other eastern European influences. One of the
central Dutch Hop symbols is the <hi rend="italic">hackbrett</hi>
(hammered dulcimer), a handcrafted instrument
with eighty wires that the player strikes
with two wooden "hammers." The Dutch Hop
is perhaps most pronounced in northern Colorado,
where, despite an influx of population
and unparalleled urban growth, the folk tradition
continues to hold its own.</p>

<p>In Spanish-speaking areas of the Central
and Southern Plains, many folk musical traditions
are in evidence. One of these traditions
reflects interesting cultural borrowings. The
Mexican American music known as <hi rend="italic">conjunto</hi>
is characterized by a reliance on the button
accordion. Those who dance to the lively music
of conjunto cannot fail to recognize its
similarity to German-style polkas and schottisches
that are interspersed with the other
numbers. Although conjunto is perhaps most
popular in Texas, its influence in the Great
Plains extends at least as far north as the prairie
lands bordering the Red River in North
Dakota, Minnesota, and Canada.</p>

<p>While the musical tastes of Great Plains residents
are rich and varied, there are folk songs
that have come to be strongly identified with
the region. A classic example is the song
"Home on the Range," which has its roots in
the heart of Kansas. Oceanlike images of a
huge, waving sea of grass sometimes appear in
the folk songs of the Great Plains. "Bury Me
Not on the Lone Prairie," for example, is based
on the old English folk song "Ocean Burial."</p>

<p>Many folk songs of the Great Plains have
undergone modification to make them more
suited to specific locales. Inspired by the tune
"Beulah Land," Plains folksingers simply
change the opening line (depending on where
they reside) and sing something like:</p>


<l>Nebraska Land, Nebraska Land,</l>
<l>As on thy desert soil I stand</l>
<l>And look away across the plains,</l>
<l>I wonder why it never rains. . . .</l>

<p>In the Plains of Saskatchewan, a similar folk
song is sung and lyrics are added that give it a
distinctive local flavor. Michael Taft, in his
<title level="m">Discovering Saskatchewan Folklore</title> (1983), includes
this verse:</p>

<l>Saskatchewan, the land of snow,</l>
<l>Where winds are always on the blow,</l>
<l>Where people sit with frozen toes.</l>
<l>And why we stay here no one knows. . . .</l>

</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Customary Folklore</head>

<p>Folk beliefs ("superstitions"), folk customs,
weather lore, folk medicine, folk games, seasonal
traditions, and life-cycle customs are a
few of the many phenomena folklorists refer to
as "customary folklore." While these often involve
elements of oral lore and even material
folk culture, customary folklore typically manifests
itself in traditional belief or behavior.</p>

<p>One of the largest collections of Great
Plains customary folklore is William E. Koch's
<title level="m">Folklore from Kansas</title> (1980). This unusually
detailed compilation, which includes more
than 5,000 individual folklore texts, focuses
on folk customs, beliefs, and superstitions.
Koch's material covers a wide range of topics:
illnesses, making wishes, dreams, luck, plants
and planting, hunting and fishing, and even a
section detailing beliefs and customs relating
to domestic animals and wildlife. Some of the
latter traditions reflect an intimate familiarity
with cattle country and the Plains environment
(e.g., "If you grease a fence after a cow
gets cut on it, the cow won't get an infection";
"During a storm, horses always stand with
their tails to the wind, and cattle stand with
their heads to the wind"; and "Grasshoppers
come only in dry years").</p>

<p>Koch also presents many examples of
weather lore, and this is indeed a rich source
for Great Plains folklore. Plains residents read
a variety of "signs" in natural phenomena of
all kinds: phases of the moon, the color of the
Great Plains sky, the shape of thunderheads
and other approaching clouds, even the sudden
appearance of bubbles on a stream or
pond (which are believed to portend an approaching
rainstorm). Louise Pound, in <title level="m">Nebraska Folklore</title>, includes a fascinating section
on rain lore and rainmaking. From time to
time, Great Plains residents believed that rain
could be coaxed from the sky by plowing acres
of prairie, planting trees, shooting explosives
into the sky, and even by setting fire to the
prairie itself. Pound does not overlook perhaps
one of the most common folk beliefs relating
to rainmaking: "Wash and polish your
car and you may be sure rain will follow."</p>

<p>Folk medicine also is an important and
integral part of customary folklore. Home
remedies, herbal recipes, and traditional
faith-healing techniques are examples of folk
medicine found in the Great Plains. It is not
uncommon to find Plains residents who treat
certain ailments at home while seeking treatment
for other ailments from either folk healers
or licensed medical practitioners. Evidently,
a range of factors comes into play
when deciding how to treat an ailment and
whom to seek for appropriate treatment.
David E. Jones, for example, worked with a
Comanche medicine woman in western Oklahoma.
The resulting study, <title level="m">Sanapia</title> (1972),
provides a fascinating glimpse into the world
of a Plains Indian healer who combines elements
of Christianity and peyotism alongside
traditional Comanche beliefs relating to
guardian spirits and vision quests.</p>

<p>In the southern portions of the Great Plains,
one still finds much evidence of the Mexican
American folk-healing tradition known as <hi rend="italic">curanderismo</hi>.
Unlike the medical care provided
by hospitals and licensed practitioners, the
Spanish-speaking world of curanderismo is
more accessible and personal. Formal appointments
and office paperwork are unnecessary
and "payments for services" are never demanded.
Patrons who are comfortable with
the mix of natural remedies and spirituality
that the <hi rend="italic">curanderos</hi> (healers) provide typically
leave a donation.</p>

<p>Far to the north, in the Dakotas, a folkhealing
tradition very similar to curanderismo
is found among the Germans from Russia.
<hi rend="italic">Brauche</hi> is a type of folk healing that makes use
of prayers, religious verses, herbs, massage, the
"laying on of hands," and other faith-healing
techniques. Much like Mexican American curanderos,
German Russian "brauchers" accept
donations but never demand payment.</p>

<p>Games and traditional forms of recreation
in the Great Plains are subjects not overlooked
by scholars. Jim Hoy and Tom Isern, in their
volume <title level="m">Plains Folk</title> (1987), devote attention to
many prairie traditions, including folk games
and other favorite pastimes. Among them are
"Dare Base" (also called "Prisoner's Base"),
recess games (like throwing a ball over the
schoolhouse and referring to it as "Annie
Over" or a similar term), "Fox and Geese,"
and six-man football.</p>

<p>Seasonal customs and celebrations are common
throughout the Great Plains and often
are linked with specific ethnic and religious
groups. In Lindsborg, Kansas, for example,
Swedish Americans celebrate the feast day of
Santa Lucia (on the second Saturday of December)
with ethnic food, Old Country fiddling,
roving carolers, the crowning of Santa
Lucia, as well as a number of other activities.
Folklorist Larry Danielson offers a richly
detailed description and analysis of the celebration
in his essay, "St. Lucia in Lindsborg,
Kansas" (1991). In Texas especially, but also
in Oklahoma, African Americans celebrate
"Juneteenth" on June 19, commemorating the
Emancipation Proclamation that was read in
Galveston on that day in 1865. Public speeches,
picnics, parades, ball games, displays of African
American arts, and musical entertainment
are all part of the celebration.</p>

<p>Life-cycle customs also are found wherever
there are families and traditional communities
in the Great Plains. An incredibly diverse number
of folk traditions surround the various
stages of the human life cycle: conception,
birth, infancy, childhood, adolescence, adulthood,
old age, and death. Sometimes, certain
life-cycle events provide an occasion for family
members and friends to come together and
celebrate, as in the case of christenings, bar
mitzvahs, Mexican American <hi rend="italic">quincea&#241;era</hi> (fifteenth
birthday) festivities, weddings, and funerals.
Not uncommon in the Great Plains is
the tradition of mock weddings, a form of folk
drama linked to life-cycle celebrations such as
anniversaries and weddings. The mock wedding
is characterized by individuals who dress
up in old wedding attire and reverse gender
roles. Thus, a man may don a bridal gown
and tattered veil while a woman will wear a
man's oversized suit and even paste on a funny-looking
mustache or sideburns. A folk parody
of the marriage ceremony takes place, often
with some rather colorful and even risqu&#233;
components.</p>

<p>Michael Taft has documented the mock
wedding tradition in his lively and richly illustrated
study "Folk Drama on the Great Plains:
The Mock Wedding in Canada and the United
States" (1989). Taft discovered that while the
mock wedding tradition can be found in other
parts of North America, this particular folkway
has found fertile ground in the Great
Plains. One explanation Taft offers for this
rather unusual regional phenomenon is that
the mock wedding provides a way for Plains
women to "express their ambivalent and conflicting
roles as farm wives." By means of a
humorous and even outrageous parody, the
traditional roles of men and women in agricultural
communities are turned upside down,
played with, and thus reexamined.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Material Folk Traditions</head>

<p>Unlike oral and customary folklore, material
folk traditions manifest themselves in tangible
ways that can be touched, measured, and even
photographed. Yet folklorists do not concern
themselves only with the tangible results&#8211;or
artifacts&#8211;for there is always a much larger
body of tradition that surrounds a Plains Indian
flute, a Doukhobor spinning wheel, or an
African American family quilt. Material folk
culture takes many forms and includes such
wide-ranging traditions as foodways, folk architecture,
folk crafts, and folk art.</p>

<p>Traditional foodways of the Great Plains
vary tremendously and reflect a rich mosaic of
ethnic and occupational tastes. Roger Welsch,
in <title level="m">A Treasury of Nebraska Pioneer Folklore</title>
(1984), includes examples of many regional
and ethnic dishes, including "corn coffee,"
buckwheat cakes, Indian meal mush, wild
rabbit, green corn pudding, currant jam, and
rhubarb tarts. Traditional foodways serve not
only to provide bodily nourishment but also
to evoke and maintain a strong sense of group
identity. Thus, while certain foods like Bohemian
pressed blood sausage, Mexican menudo
(tripe soup), or the cowboy dish "prairie
oysters" (fried calf testicles) might repulse
outsiders, these same culinary creations serve
to reinforce feelings of group uniqueness on
the part of those who willingly&#8211;and happily
&#8211;indulge themselves.</p>

<p>In terms of Great Plains folk architecture,
one of the most enduring symbols of the region
is the sod house of the homesteader. This
dwelling, as befits its name, was constructed
from strips of prairie sod. The thick earthen
walls ensured that the occupants would be
comfortable during sweltering summers and
brutally cold winters. The sod house has its
counterpart in the earth lodge of early Plains
Indian settled peoples, including the Pawnees,
Arikaras, Mandans, and Hidatsas. Adobe-style
houses can be found in the Southern Plains,
and they remain an integral part of Mexican
American folk architecture. In the Northern
Plains, the Black Sea Germans and the Ukrainians
built homes of sun-dried clay brick that
served them especially well during the long
cold winters. These homes usually were low
earthen structures that blended in well with
their grassland surroundings.</p>

<figure n="egp.fol.001.02" rend="granted">
<figDesc>"House-barn" structure in a small Mennonite community in southern Manitoba</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>In Manitoba and Saskatchewan, Mennonites
from South Russia often built long wooden
"house barns." This unique type of prairie
dwelling consists of a house, barn, and stable&#8211;
all connected under one roof. In some cases, a
"summer kitchen" is built between the main
dwelling and the barn, thus connecting the
structures in a slightly modified fashion. This
type of folk architecture was particularly well
suited to the rigors of a northern climate, for
the settlers could tend to their horses and other
livestock during fierce winter storms without
leaving the safety of the connected buildings.
Today, a number of these "house barn" dwellings
still can be seen in the Canadian Prairies.</p>

<p>Individuals knowledgeable in folk crafts can
be found in every Great Plains community. At
one time, of course, folk crafts enabled many
families to be as self-su.cient as possible. Agricultural
tools, cooking utensils, branding
irons, wagon wheels, and various other items
were made by hand or were crafted by local
blacksmiths and wheelwrights. When the desired
items were made by folk artisans or other
specialists, barter often was possible.</p>

<p>Great Plains ranchers and farmers came up
with ingenious devices for making life easier
and more satisfying. One such innovation is
the cattle guard, which simultaneously serves
as both a gate and a fence. While people and
vehicles can pass over the horizontal metal
bars of the cattle guard fairly quickly, cattle
refrain from crossing. Jim Hoy, in his book
<title level="m">The Cattle Guard</title> (1982), convincingly demonstrates
that cattle guards first appeared in
the Great Plains about 1905. Like so many folk
crafts and folk innovations, the name of the
original craftsman who made the first Great
Plains cattle guard is unknown.</p>

<p>Just as the makers of various folk crafts
often remain anonymous, the same holds true
for many types of folk art. There is a thin
dividing line between folk craft and folk art,
but many scholars argue that in the realm of
folk craft, the utilitarian function outweighs
aesthetic considerations. A quilt might be
considered an example of folk craft if the item
is used for purely utilitarian purposes. Yet a
quilt that is displayed only on special occasions
and is the object of much admiration
may be considered folk art. As is so often the
case with folklore, the cultural and situational
contexts are vitally important in determining
the true nature of a folk tradition.</p>

<p>Folk art in the Great Plains takes many
forms. Plains Indian artistic traditions, for
example, manifest themselves in items like
drums, porcupine quillwork, carved pipes,
parfleches, and in numerous other ways.
Quite often all or most of the raw materials
come from natural materials within the Great
Plains. Groups who later moved into the
Plains, especially European Americans, often
had to adapt their artistic traditions to the
new surroundings.</p>

<p>Throughout the Great Plains, from the
Mexican border to the Prairies of Alberta,
Manitoba, and Saskatchewan, numerous examples
can be found of a distinctive form of
folk art: wrought-iron grave crosses. Usually
made by blacksmiths or other metal specialists,
these crosses range in size from small children's
markers to elaborately crafted iron
crosses that stand several feet in height. Although
iron grave crosses can be found in
many parts of the world, they seem particularly
striking when viewed against the open,
uncluttered horizon of the Great Plains.</p>

<figure n="egp.fol.001.03" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Wrought-iron cross on the plains of southwestern North Dakota</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>In the Southern Plains, iron crosses are most
common in Mexican American cemeteries. In
Kansas, they are numerous in the many Volga
German settlements around Hays. In the Dakotas
and Prairie Provinces, the so-called iron
spirits are associated with the Germans from
Russia, Ukrainians, M&#233;tis, and other ethnic
groups. As might be expected, handcrafted
iron crosses include an array of ethnic-based
and religious symbols, but some crosses also
include decorative features strongly reminiscent
of the Great Plains: symbols of the sun,
sparkling stars, abundant open space, and
waving wheat. Most wrought-iron crosses are
unsigned and include few words other than the
names and dates of the deceased. Yet, like other
works of art, the "iron spirits" of the Great
Plains compel travelers to stop, take a closer
look, and ponder the great mysteries.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Conclusion</head>

<p>Great Plains folkways are so diverse that it is
difficult to summarize the region's traditions
in a comprehensive fashion. Yet one theme
does run through many of the songs and stories
of Great Plains people, no matter what the
ethnic or occupational background of the
folksingers and storytellers. In a land of big
skies and seemingly endless horizons, there is
a tendency to celebrate and even exaggerate
the immensity of the region itself, as well as
the numerous challenges it poses to all who
call the prairie their home.</p>

<p>Rather than ignore the harsh side of Great
Plains life, prairie dwellers tend to confront
and even "play up" such hardships as blizzards,
droughts, severe heat, extreme cold,
hailstorms, and other realities. This tendency
manifests itself in a number of distinctive
folkways, including the telling of tall tales and
the singing of humorous folk parodies about
life in the Great Plains.</p>

<p>This emphasis on hyperbole in Great Plains
folklore also manifests itself in the large number
of "roadside colossi" that can be found
throughout the region. As Karal Ann Marling's
book <title level="m">The Colossus of Roads</title> (1984) illustrates,
roadside sculptures are not unique to
the Great Plains, but they do assume humorous
and rather spectacular forms there.
From the Texas Hill Country to the Canadian
Rockies, various types of folk monuments can
be found along Great Plains highways.</p>

<p>All of this perhaps is to be expected when
one considers a Great Plains state like South
Dakota, which includes such visual wonders as
Mount Rushmore, the Crazy Horse Monument
(near Custer), the Corn Palace (Mitchell),
and Dinosaur Park (Rapid City). Other
Great Plains states are not to be outdone. Near
Alliance, Nebraska, numerous old automobiles
and other vehicles form "Carhenge," a
gigantic circle of iron and steel that is hauntingly
reminiscent of the ancient Stonehenge in
England. In Fort Stockton, "Paisano Pete," a
statue of a twenty-foot-long roadrunner, welcomes
travelers to West Texas.</p>

<p>In Wyoming, a huge likeness of the mythical
jackalope (a jackrabbit with antlers) can
be viewed in downtown Douglas. Near Rothsay,
Minnesota, "the world's largest prairie
chicken" stands guard at the eastern edge of
the Great Plains. In Jamestown, North Dakota,
"the world's largest buffalo" dwarfs a
herd of live buffalo that graze nearby. East
of New Town, North Dakota, an eye-catching
statue of the tall, lanky cowboy Earl Bunyan&#8211;
the legendary Great Plains brother of the lumberjack
Paul Bunyan&#8211;waves a branding iron
and braces himself against the strong northern
winds with a walking cane.</p>

<p>Folk monuments also dot the Canadian
Plains, ranging from the twenty-two-foothigh
western painted turtle in Boissevain,
Manitoba, to the gigantic replica of a Ukrainian
<hi rend="italic">pysanka</hi> (decorated Easter egg) in Vegreville,
Alberta. One of the most unusual Canadian
folk monuments is the "World's Largest
Bunnock" that rises more than thirty feet
above the rolling prairies near Macklin, Saskatchewan.
The curious onlooker soon learns
that a "bunnock" is one of fifty-two horse anklebones
that are used in a centuries-old folk
game transplanted from the Russian steppes
to western Canada. To create the World's
Largest Bunnock, the image of an actual horse
anklebone was enlarged nearly 100 times and
then formed into shape out of metal pipe,
chicken wire, and fiberglass. The bunnock
monument is illuminated at night and is visible
for miles around. As one might expect,
Macklin is also the site of the "World Championship
Bunnock Tournament," which has
been held yearly since 1993.</p>

<p>The presence of so many roadside colossi
and folk monuments in the Great Plains
should come as little surprise. Plains dwellers
know their region is often referred to as "tall
tale country." Instead of fighting such a label,
many storytellers chuckle and quickly share
some favorite "windies" of their own.</p>

<p>Great Plains folkways are as diverse and as
dynamic as the region itself. The traditions
mirror the experiences of many different
groups who have grown accustomed to the
great vistas and the even greater uncertainties
that surround Plains dwellers on an almost
daily basis. Through it all, Plains folk have
developed a fierce and begrudging appreciation
for their home. The numerous tall tales
and humorous folk songs and roadside monuments
reflect something else: the ability of
Great Plains folk to laugh at adversity and, on
occasion, to laugh most heartily at themselves.</p>


<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">ARCHITECTURE</hi>: <ref n="egp.arc.040">Roadside Architecture</ref>;
<ref n="egp.arc.042">Sod-Wall Construction</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">EUROPEAN
AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ea.011">German Russians</ref>; <ref n="egp.ea.021">Jews</ref> / 
<hi rend="smallcaps">IMAGES AND ICONS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ii.015">Cowboy Culture</ref> / 
<hi rend="smallcaps">LITERARY TRADITIONS</hi>: <ref n="egp.lt.012">Cowboy Poetry</ref>; 
<ref n="egp.lt.054">Oral Traditions</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">MUSIC</hi>: <ref n="egp.mus.022">Hispanic Music</ref>; 
<ref n="egp.mus.039">Polka Music</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">NATIVE AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.na.063">M&#233;tis</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">SPORTS AND RECREATION</hi>: <ref n="egp.sr.012">Crow Fair</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">WATER</hi>: 
<ref n="egp.wat.023">Rainmaking</ref>.</p>
</div2>

<closer>
<signed>Timothy J. Kloberdanz<lb/>
North Dakota State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Blevins, Winfred. <title level="m">Dictionary of the American West</title>. New
York: Facts on File, 1993.</bibl> <bibl>Brunvand, Jan Harold. <title level="m">The Study of American Folklore: An Introduction</title>. New York: W. W.
Norton Co., 1986.</bibl> <bibl>Cunningham, Keith. <title level="m">American Indians' Kitchen Table Stories: Contemporary Conversations with Cherokee, Sioux, Hopi, Osage, Navajo, Zuni, and Members of Other Nations</title>. Little Rock ar: August House Publishers,
1992.</bibl> <bibl>Danielson, Larry. "St. Lucia in Lindsborg, Kansas."
In <title level="m">Creative Ethnicity: Symbols and Strategies of Contemporary Ethnic Life</title>, edited by Stephen Stern and John Allan
Cicala. Logan: Utah State University Press, 1991: 187-203.</bibl>
<bibl>Gard, Robert E. <title level="m">Johnny Chinook: Tall Tales and True from the Canadian West</title>. London: Longmans, Green and Company,
1945.</bibl> <bibl>Greenway, John. <title level="m">Folklore of the Great West</title>.
Palo Alto <hi rend="smallcaps">CA</hi>: American West Publishing Company, 1969.</bibl>
<bibl>Hoy, James F. <title level="m">The Cattle Guard: Its History and Lore</title>. Lawrence:
University Press of Kansas, 1982.</bibl> <bibl>Hoy, James F., and
Isern, Tom. <title level="m">Plains Folk: A Commonplace of the Great Plains</title>. Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1987.</bibl>
<bibl>Jones, David E. <title level="m">Sanapia: Comanche Medicine Woman</title>.
New York: Holt, Rinehart and Winston, 1972.</bibl> <bibl>Jordan,
Teresa, ed. <title level="m">Graining the Mare: The Poetry of Ranch Women</title>. Salt Lake City: Peregrine Smith, 1994.</bibl> <bibl>Kloberdanz,
Timothy J. "The Daughters of Shiphrah: Folk
Healers and Midwives of the Great Plains." <title level="j">Great Plains Quarterly</title> 9 (1989): 3-12.</bibl> <bibl>Marling, Karal Ann. <title level="m">The Colossus of Roads: Myth and Symbol along the American Highway</title>.
Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 1984.</bibl> <bibl>Pound,
Louise. <title level="m">Nebraska Folklore</title>. Lincoln: University of Nebraska
Press, 1987.</bibl> <bibl>Red Shirt, Delphine. <title level="m">Bead on an Anthill: A Lakota Childhood</title>. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press,
1998.</bibl> <bibl>Sackett, S. J., and William E. Koch, eds. <title level="m">Kansas Folklore</title>. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1961.</bibl>
<bibl>Schloff, Linda Mack. <title level="m">"And Prairie Dogs Weren't Kosher": Jewish Women in the Upper Midwest Since 1855</title>. St. Paul:
Minnesota Historical Society Press, 1996.</bibl> <bibl>Sumner, William
Graham. <title level="m">Folkways: A Study of the Sociological Importance of Usages, Manners, Customs, Mores, and Morals</title>.
New York: Arno Press, 1979.</bibl> <bibl>Taft, Michael. <title level="m">Discovering Saskatchewan Folklore: Three Case Studies</title>. Edmonton, Alberta:
NeWest Press, 1983.</bibl> <bibl>Taft, Michael. "Folk Drama on
the Great Plains: The Mock Wedding in Canada and the
United States." <title level="j">North Dakota History</title> 56 (1989): 17-23.</bibl>
<bibl>Welsch, Roger L. <title level="m">Shingling the Fog and Other Plains Lies: Tall Tales of the Great Plains</title>. Chicago: Swallow Press, 1972.</bibl>
<bibl>Welsch, Roger L. <title level="m">A Treasury of Nebraska Pioneer Folklore</title>.
Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1966, 1984.</bibl>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>