<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ag.054">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Ranches</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Paul D. Travis</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ag.054</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Travis, Paul D.">Paul D. Travis</author>. <title level="a">"Ranches."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">48-49</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-12-18</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">RANCHES</head>

<p>The day of the cattlemen, of trail drives and
open range, lasted only about two decades,
from 1866 to about 1887, in the Great Plains.
The cattlemen then adjusted to the new era of
fence laws, barbed wire, and quarantine laws
by gaining control of vast areas of rangeland
in the Texas Panhandle, the Nebraska Sandhills,
eastern Wyoming, and other parts of the
Plains, which, because of aridity and isolation,
were not attractive to homesteaders. By manipulating
land laws such as the Timber Culture
Act (1873) and the Forest Lieu Act (1897),
they were able to own the land along the water
courses and lakes and, therefore, have undisturbed
use of the intervening range. On the
U.S. Plains, at least, ranchers sometimes used
violence to maintain their operations; more
often, however, they relied on the abilities of
their ranch managers to adapt to the changing
times, and some of the early enterprises continue
to prosper.</p>

<p>In the Texas Panhandle, the <hi rend="smallcaps">XIT</hi> ("ten counties
in Texas") Ranch, run by a Chicago business
coalition, eventually extended over more
than three million acres and had a herd of
more than 150,000 head, watched over by
more than a hundred ranch hands. The huge
spread was gradually sold to ranchers and
farmers over the course of the first half of
the twentieth century. The King Ranch in
southeast Texas, founded by Richard King and
Mifflin Kennedy, who later divided their holdings,
covered one million acres in 1852. King's
widow, Henrietta, operated the ranch after
1885. Other large Texas ranches, founded
in the decades after the Civil War, include the
<hi rend="smallcaps">JA</hi>, the Pitchfork, and the 6666. The <hi rend="smallcaps">JA</hi> was
founded by Charles Goodnight in 1877, with
financial backing from Irishman John G.
Adair (hence the name and brand). The <hi rend="smallcaps">JA</hi>
encompassed 1.3 million acres in Palo Duro
Canyon and grazed 100,000 cattle in the early
1880s. It remains a working ranch today. So
too do the Pitchfork and 6666 Ranches, which
are both headquartered near Guthrie, Texas,
and known for their quality cattle and American
quarter horses.</p>

<p>George Washington Miller and his sons'
101 Ranch in northeastern Oklahoma, with
110,000 acres, rodeos, and Wild West shows, is
another famous Plains ranch. The 101 remained
intact until surviving son Zach was
obliged to sell at a bankruptcy auction in 1931.
In northwestern Kansas, C. P. Dewey and his
son Chauncey controlled 700,000 acres, about
half of which they owned and the remainder
they leased from private owners or the federal
government. Other notable Central Plains
ranches include the Colorado spread operated
by John Iliff until his death in 1878 and the
150,000-acre Spade Ranch in the Nebraska
Sandhills. Iliff's methods reveal how ranchers
in the United States controlled large amounts
of territory in the nineteenth century. Iliff
owned 105 scattered parcels of land, totaling
only 15,588 acres, but by strategically locating
his parcels along rivers and streams he was
able to control a ranching territory of about
6,000 square miles, extending from Greeley to
the eastern border of Colorado.</p>

<p>The Swan Land and Cattle Company, headquartered
at Chugwater, Wyoming, which operated
for more than seventy years and at its
peak held as many as 110,000 head of cattle,
serves as an example of the strong-arm techniques
sometimes used by ranchers to control
large amounts of land. In 1894 Alexander
Swan hired noted gunman Tom Horn to kill
rustlers and homesteaders, both of whom
threatened Swan's large operation. Other cattlemen
used equal or even greater violence,
the best-known example being the infamous
Johnson County War (1892) in north-central
Wyoming, when vigilantes, hired by largescale
ranchers who were members of the Wyoming
Stock Growers Association, "invaded"
Johnson County, searching out, and in two
cases killing, small operators who were suspected
of rustling. The Swan Land and Cattle
Company has since been divided into
smaller ranches, and its original buildings are
in disrepair.</p>

<p>The Matador Land and Cattle Company,
founded by five Americans in northwest Texas
along the Pease River in 1879, was taken over
in 1882 by Scottish investors. Scottish ownership
continued until the 1950s (with Murdo
Mackenzie particularly influential), as the
company acquired grazing lands throughout
the Northern Great Plains and into Saskatchewan.
The huge estate was divided into smaller
holdings and sold after the 1950s.</p>

<p>In the Prairie Provinces, adapted land laws
and low population densities made ranching a
more regulated enterprise than it was south of
the forty-ninth parallel. Under the Land Act
of 1881 ranchers could make twenty-one-year
leases of up to 100,000 acres at one cent per
acre, provided that the rancher kept one cow
for every twenty acres of land. Alberta's Bar U
Ranch, operated by George Lane, one of Canada's
Big Four ranchers, served as the center of
an empire that consisted not only of shortgrass
ranches, but also farms, meatpacking
factories, and flour mills. It was renowned for
breeding cattle and Percheron horses. The Bar
U Ranch, under new ownership, remains an
active ranch more than 120 years after its
founding.</p>

<p>Today Great Plains ranchers drive the rough
terrain of their spreads in air-conditioned
four-wheel drive pickups or sport-utility vehicles.
At holding pens and feeder yards
eighteen-wheelers take on cattle then speed
down interstates en route to distant markets
or slaughterhouses. Ranchers watch price
fluctuations and futures markets on television
monitors linked to satellites. They express
concern about new cattle afflictions, such as
the dreaded mad cow disease. Membership in
cattle associations and beef producer organizations
is a necessity. Yet most carry the spirit
and tradition of nineteenth-century ranches
in their hearts, and ranching remains as much
a way of life as a business.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Paul D. Travis<lb/>
Texas Woman's University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Dary, David. <title level="m">Cowboy Culture: A Saga of Five Centuries</title>.
New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1981.</bibl> <bibl>Jordan, Terry G. <title level="m">Trails to Texas: Southern Roots of Western Cattle Ranching</title>. Lincoln:
University of Nebraska Press, 1981.</bibl> <bibl>Starrs, Paul F. <title level="m">Let the Cowboy Ride: Cattle Ranching in the American West</title>. Baltimore
MD: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1998.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>