<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ag.032">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Farm Conslidation</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Bradley H. Baltensperger</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ag.032</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Baltensperger, Bradley H.">Bradley H. Baltensperger</author>. <title level="a">"Farm Conslidations."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">44-45</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-12-18</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">FARM CONSOLIDATION</head>

<p>Although the Great Plains region of North
America was largely settled by 1900, farm
numbers continued to grow during the first
third of the twentieth century, peaking at
nearly 1.7 million in 1935. Average farm size
was 355 acres in the U.S. Great Plains, and 221
acres (in 1941) in the Canadian Prairie Provinces.
During the ensuing six decades, farms
grew larger and fewer in number. By 1992 only
646,000 farms remained; there were 502,000
farms in the ten U.S. Plains states, averaging
1,020 acres, and 144,000 Prairie Province
farms averaging 952 acres in 1991. This process
of farm consolidation was the product of
a number of economic and environmental
forces that affected all of North America. The
effect on Great Plains farms varied considerably
from place to place, both in timing and
intensity.</p>

<p>Farm expansion was primarily a product of
scale economies, mostly related to the impact
of mechanization and technological change
in agriculture and in the national economy.
Increasingly during the twentieth century,
farmers had to compete with the booming
manufacturing sector for workers. Laborsaving
technologies, particularly tractors, were
adopted mostly because farmers were unable
to secure a sufficient labor supply at an affordable
cost. However, machinery was most cost-effective when fully used. A new tractor or hay
baler could be more easily paid for if the
farmer had more land on which to use it.
Thus, machinery purchased to solve a labor
supply problem put upward pressure on farm
size, as farmers sought to maximize their return
on investment.</p>

<p>Farm consolidation was mostly a product
of the expansion of some family-owned operations
and the demise of others. In the last
thirty years of the twentieth century some
high-profile corporate farming operations
were established in the Great Plains. Most
were associated with cattle feedlots, confinement
hog production, or center-pivot irrigation.
However, the role of nonfarm corporations
in agriculture is considerably less
important in the Great Plains than elsewhere
in North America: corporate farming in the
Plains is mostly conducted by family corporations.</p>

<p>The pressure to expand was exacerbated by
drought and depression during the 1930s. As
crop yields and prices fell and as some marginal
cropland was abandoned, farmers in the
most drought-stricken areas either had to expand
their operations to maintain adequate
income or drop out of farming. In the western
and southern Great Plains states, farm numbers
plummeted between 1935 and 1959. New
Mexico lost more than 60 percent of its farms
in that twenty-four-year period; Oklahoma
and Texas lost 55 percent; Colorado and Wyoming
lost more than 45 percent. Farm consolidation
was not confined to these states.
Farmers dependent on livestock production
were especially hard hit. In some counties in
the Nebraska Sandhills and in southwestern
Kansas average farm size had more than doubled
by 1950, and farm numbers had decreased
accordingly.</p>

<p>In Oklahoma and Texas, the Depression put
almost unbearable pressure on tenant farmers.
Farm numbers in these two states dropped by
23 percent between 1935 and 1945, but the
number of tenant farmers was cut almost in
half. Whereas 58 percent of all farms were operated
by tenants in 1935, only 38 percent were
tenant-operated in 1945. A few of those tenants
became owners, but most were squeezed out
of agriculture altogether.</p>

<p>Farmers in the more humid eastern reaches
of the Plains were less affected by expansionary
pressures because they were able to counter
the "cost-price squeeze" by intensifying
their operations. In humid, crop-producing
areas the adoption of tractors during the 1930s
and 1940s freed up land that had been used to
feed horses. Increased use of fertilizer and improved
seed varieties raised total production
without adding more acres to the farm. These
options, largely unavailable to livestock producers
who dominated the drier sections of
the Plains, resulted in only modest changes in
farm numbers and size in the eastern third of
the Dakotas and Nebraska, and northeastern
Kansas. Average farm size increased less than
20 percent in many eastern counties before
1950.</p>

<p>Subsequently, however, and especially after
1959, this area experienced rapid farm expansion,
and consolidation shifted dramatically
from the livestock counties of the south and
west toward the cash-crop and mixed agriculture
region of the Central and Northern
Plains. Corn Belt farmers had already adopted
most of the yield-enhancing technologies and
had converted pastureland to crops. Farm expansion was the only means remaining to increase
farm output and income.</p>

<p>Farms reliant on corn production were particularly
affected. Between 1959 and 1978
nearly all counties in this formerly stable
area saw farm size increase by 40 to 80 percent.
A typical example is Hall County, a cornproducing
county in east-central Nebraska.
Between 1930 and 1950, average farm size grew
by only 12 percent, from 199 acres to 222 acres;
but between 1959 and 1978, farm size jumped
46 percent, from 262 acres to 382 acres. The
1,628 farms in the county in 1930 had been cut
nearly in half to 860 by 1978.</p>

<p>Meanwhile, with the recovery from the
1950s drought, ranchers had some opportunities
to intensify use of marginal lands, and
technological change did not produce the
same pressures to expand operations as was
the case in the Corn Belt counties. After 1959,
farm expansion was quite modest in western
and southern Plains counties, and in some
areas, farm size actually decreased and farm
numbers increased.</p>

<p>After the mid-1970s farm numbers changed
relatively little in the Great Plains. Prior to
1974, farm numbers dropped by 10 percent or
more in nearly every five-year period. As of
1992, there were only 9 percent fewer farms in
the U.S. Plains states than there had been in
1974. Certain external factors may have reduced
expansionary pressures in the last third
of the twentieth century. Center-pivot irrigation
technology provided some farmers with
intensification opportunities, which reduced
the need to acquire more land. Rural industrialization
and other nonfarm employment opportunities
resulted in a dramatic increase in
the number of farm women holding jobs off
the farm. The number of farm men employed
in nonfarm enterprises much or all of the year
grew substantially in this period. Nonfarm
wages provided many families with additional
income even without farm expansion and allowed
some smaller farms to stay in business.</p>

<p>This is not to say that farm consolidation is
a thing of the past. Low commodity prices,
larger machinery, and limited opportunities
to expand revenues without more land all put
pressure on farms to expand. In a region
where most land is already in farms, expansion
of one farm necessarily comes at the expense
of others. Larger farms translate into
fewer farms. Whether the forces that provide
alternatives to consolidation will continue to
stabilize farm size and numbers is difficult to
predict. Technological changes in food production
and the market prices of agricultural
products will certainly affect whether smaller
farms will survive or sell out to their expanding
neighbors.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Bradley H. Baltensperger<lb/>
Michigan Technological University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Baltensperger, Bradley H. "Farm Consolidation on the
Northern and Central Great Plains." <hi rend="italic">Great Plains Quarterly</hi>
7 (1987): 256–65.</bibl> <bibl>Baltensperger, Bradley H. "Larger
and Fewer Farms: Patterns and Causes of Farm Enlargement
on the Central Great Plains, 1930–1978." <hi rend="italic">Journal of
Historical Geography</hi> 19 (1993): 299–313.</bibl> <bibl>Shover, John L.
<hi rend="italic">First Majority, Last Minority: The Transforming of Rural
Life in America</hi>. DeKalb: Northern Illinois University
Press, 1976.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>