<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.rel.023">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Ghost Dance</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Todd M. Kerstetter</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.rel.023</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Kerstetter, Todd M.">Todd M. Kerstetter</author>. <title level="a">"Ghost Dance."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">746</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-18</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">GHOST DANCE</head>
<figure n="egp.rel.023" rend="granted">
<figDesc>"The Ghost Dance by the Ogallala Sioux at Pine Ridge-Drawn by Frederic Remington from sketches taken on the spot." (Harper's Weekly, December 6, 1890, p. 960-961)"</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>The Ghost Dance, a messianic Native American
religious movement, originated in Nevada
around 1870, faded, reemerged in its bestknown
form in the winter of 1888–89, then
spread rapidly through much of the Great
Plains, where hundreds of adherents died in
the 1890 Wounded Knee Massacre.</p>

<p>In 1869 or 1870, Tävibo, a Northern Paiute
and first Ghost Dance prophet, preached that
white people would disappear from the earth
and dead Indians would return to enjoy a utopian
life. He also claimed to communicate with
the dead and taught followers to perform a
ceremonial circular dance that contributed to
the movement earning the Ghost Dance label.
The movement spread through Nevada and to
parts of California and Oregon but subsided
after the prophecies failed to materialize. Another
Paiute prophet, Wovoka, revived the
movement in 1889. Rumored to be Tävibo's
son, and certainly influenced by his teachings,
Wovoka experienced a vision of the Supreme
Being in 1889, after which he preached peaceful
coexistence and a strong work ethic and taught
ceremonial songs and dances to resurrect dead
Indians. According to the vision, if Indians
followed these practices, they would be reunited
with the dead and whites would disappear.
Indians who had already subscribed to
the first Ghost Dance tended to reject Wovoka's
version, but the second Ghost Dance
found acceptance among Plains tribes as far
east as the Dakotas, Nebraska, Kansas, Oklahoma,
and Texas.</p>

<p>The Ghost Dance affected no group more
than the Lakota Sioux bands who adopted it.
Several Lakota bands sent emissaries to interview
Wovoka about his teachings. They reported
in early 1890 Wovoka's message that
performing Ghost Dance ceremonies and
songs would bring back dead Indians, return
plentiful buffalo herds, and induce a natural
disaster that would sweep away whites, thus
restoring the Indian way of life that had existed
prior to European contact. The Ghost Dance
provided a hopeful message to all Indians, but
it proved particularly enticing to Lakotas suffering
poor conditions on reservations and to
Lakota leaders such as Sitting Bull (Tantanka
Iyotanka), who had resisted U.S. Indian policy.
Lakota participants added vestments known
as ghost shirts to the ceremonies and songs
brought by the emissaries. They believed these
white muslin shirts, decorated with a variety of
symbols, protected them from danger, including
bullets. The Lakotas' white neighbors and
reservation officials viewed the movement as a
threat to U.S. Indian policy and believed the
Ghost Dance ceremonies and ghost shirts indicated
that the Lakotas intended to start a war.
Reservation officials called on the U.S. government
to stop the dancing. The government
dispatched the U.S. Army and called for the
arrest of key leaders such as Sitting Bull and Big
Foot (Si Tanka). Indian police killed Sitting
Bull while arresting him. Two weeks later, on
December 29, 1890, members of the Seventh
Cavalry killed Big Foot and at least 145 of his
followers (casualty estimates range to higher
than 300) in the Wounded Knee Massacre, thus
eliminating key leaders most opposed to the
United States and its Indian policy. Many historians
have pointed to Wounded Knee as the
closing episode in the West's Indian wars.</p>

<p>The Ghost Dance died out among the Lakotas
after Wounded Knee, but it survived
elsewhere in the Plains. A Dakota Sioux community
in Canada, for instance, practiced the
Ghost Dance into the 1960s. During the 1970s,
Leonard Crow Dog, an Oglala Lakota holy
man affiliated with the American Indian
Movement, revived the Ghost Dance as part of
the Red Power movement. To many, the Ghost
Dance represented resistance to U.S. Indian
policy and American culture and was a rallying
point for preserving traditional Indian
culture.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">NATIVE AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.na.109">Sitting Bull</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">PROTEST AND DISSENT</hi>: <ref n="egp.pd.005">American Indian Movement</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">WAR</hi>: <ref n="egp.war.056">Wounded Knee Massacre</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Todd M. Kerstetter<lb/>
Texas Christian University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Hittman, Michael. <title level="m">Wovoka and the Ghost Dance</title>. Lincoln:
University of Nebraska Press, 1997.</bibl> <bibl>Kehoe, Alice Beck. <title level="m">The
Ghost Dance: Ethnohistory and Revitalization</title>. New York:
Holt, Rinehart and Winston, 1989.</bibl> <bibl>Mooney, James. <title level="m">The
Ghost-Dance Religion and the Sioux Outbreak of 1890</title>,
Fourteenth Annual Report of the Bureau of American
Ethnology, 1892-93, pt. 2. Washington <hi rend="smallcaps">DC</hi>: Government
Printing Office, 1896.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>