<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fol.025">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Hunting Lore</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Lynda Wolfe Coupe</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2009</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fol.025</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2009</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2009 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Coupe, Lynda Wolfe">Lynda Wolfe Coupe</author>. <title level="a">"Hunting Lore."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">305</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-16</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">HUNTING LORE</head>

<p>The hunting lore of the Great Plains can be
exemplified by three major figures: William F.
"Buffalo Bill" Cody (1846-1917), Theodore
Roosevelt (1858-1919), and Natty Bumppo, the
main character of the Leatherstocking tales by
James Fenimore Cooper (1789-1851).</p>

<p>Of course, the myriad tribes of Native
Americans were the first inhabitants and hunters
of the "Great American Desert," as it was
described in some quarters throughout the
nineteenth century. The buffalo was their crucial
game, providing food and many other
products for survival. No part of the animal
was wasted, and the symbiotic relationship between
the tribe and the buffalo connoted a
spiritual link, reflected in many beliefs and
legends.</p>

<p>One such legend, related by Buffalo Bill in
his autobiography, centers on a creation myth.
According to Cody, one night a group of Pawnees
came into camp bringing with them a
number of large bones, one of which a doctor
with Cody's expedition identified as a human
thighbone. The Pawnees maintained that the
bones belonged to an ancient race of men who
inhabited the country and were three times the
size of human beings of the day. Any one of
these giants could run down a buffalo and tear
off its leg with one hand and then eat it as he
walked. However, these giant men did not believe
in the Great Spirit; they were not intimidated
by the thunder and lightning and
laughed at it. This angered the Great Spirit,
and he sent a great rainstorm that drove the
giants to the hills. But the water rose and covered
the mountaintops as well, and the conceited
giants were drowned. Once the floodwaters
receded, the Great Spirit considered that
he had made men too large and powerful, and
he would henceforth re-create them smaller
and weaker. The Pawnees maintained that this
was Indian history handed down to them from
time out of mind. This explains why men are
not like the giants of old and have to work
harder to hunt and to live. Cody adds an interesting
note to this episode. He remarked that
since their expedition had no wagons with
them and the thighbone was very large, it had
to be left behind.</p>

<p>Probably the most famous account of Buffalo
Bill relates how he earned his name. In
a contest with William Comstock, who was
chief of scouts at Fort Wallace, Kansas, Cody
killed sixty-nine buffalo in an eight-hour day,
while Comstock shot only forty-six. Cody
maintained that during his service to provide
meat for the men building the Kansas Pacific
Railroad in 1867, he killed 4,280 buffalo. However,
Cody's "accomplishments" as a buffalo
hunter remain a subject for debate, for the
facts are clouded by myth.</p>

<p>Theodore Roosevelt was another hunter figure
whose exploits are legendary. He spent two
years in the Dakotas, following the deaths of
his mother and his first wife, Alice, on the same
day in February of 1884. He became a gentleman
cattle rancher and found consolation in
the hard work and austere landscape. In 1885
Roosevelt wrote an essay on "The Lordly Buffalo"
for his book <title level="m">Hunting Trips of a Ranchman</title>
(1885). He regretted the excesses of the 1870s
when the buffalo herds were reduced to nearextinction,
but he saw their demise as necessary
for the progress of the nation. He also
enthusiastically hunted buffalo in a more controlled
manner, which he described in great
detail in his essay, and sought to preserve them
for hunting as a sport. He founded the Boone
and Crockett Club and served as its first president.
One goal of the club was to preserve large
game in America for hunting.</p>

<p>Natty Bumppo, the hero of James Fenimore
Cooper's five Leatherstocking tales, is to a large
extent a fictional portrayal of Daniel Boone. In
<title level="m">The Prairie</title> (1827), Natty was an old man in his
eighties who had moved ever westward over
the course of his life and would die in the Great
Plains. He spent the last stage of life in a forest
of grass on the Plains, his hunting years at an
end. This was a time of American expansion
across the continent. The pioneers were seeking
new lives as Natty was ending his. He represented
a way of life that had all but disappeared,
just as his youth and strength were
nearly gone. However, he was freed from the
confines of time because his hold on mortal life
was tenuous. He came to symbolize a nation
that had developed and reached out across
a continent of dramatic landscapes, unconstrained
by any boundaries. He was the hunter
scout who opened the path for the march of
pioneers who followed.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Lynda Wolfe Coupe<lb/>
Pace University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Cody, William F. <title level="m">The Life of Hon. William F. Cody, Known as Buffalo Bill, the Famous Hunter, Scout, and Guide: An Autobiography</title>. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press,
1978.</bibl> <bibl>Cooper, James Fenimore. <title level="m">The Prairie: A Tale</title>. New
York: Rinehart, 1960.</bibl> <bibl>Roosevelt, Theodore. <title level="m">Hunting Trips of a Ranchman: Sketches of Sport on the Northern Cattle Plains and the Wilderness Hunter: An Account of the Big Game of the United States and Its Chase with Horse, Hound, and Rifle. 1885</title>. New York: Modern Library, 1996.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>