<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.art.045">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">O'Keefe, Georgia (1887-1986)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Ellen Bradbury</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.art.045</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Bradbury, Ellen">Ellen Bradbury</author>. <title level="a">"O'Keefe, Georgia (1887-1986)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">125-126</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-22</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">O'KEEFE, GEORGIA (1887-1986)</head>

<p>Born in Sun Prairie, Wisconsin, in 1887, Georgia
O'Keefe was the second child of Francis
O'Keefe and Ida Totto O'Keefe. Perched
on the prairie, Sun Prairie was a typical nineteenth-
century farming community. O'Keefe
lived on her family dairy farm until she was
twelve, when she went away to school, first
to Chatham Academy in Virginia and then to
the Chicago Art Institute in 1905 and the
New York Art Students League in 1907. The
O'Keefe family fortunes declined, and in 1915
she was forced to leave school in New York and
take a teaching job in Columbia, South Carolina.
While she was there, O'Keefe revised her
work, using simple abstract forms and a limited
palate. Her goal was to express emotion or
emotional states using abstraction.</p>

<p>O'Keefe's first experience of the Great
Plains came in 1912, when she took a position
as an art educator in the Amarillo public
schools. After less than a year she left after
battling with the state education commission
over textbooks. But her love for the land had
been established. In 1916 O'Keefe moved to
Canyon, Texas, and became the head of (and
the only faculty member in) the art department
at West Texas State Normal School. She
disliked the small town, but she was inspired
by the wide horizons and the overarching sky.
The openness of the space changed her work,
and she began to paint the infinite variations
of light coming onto the Plains, especially
at sunrise and sunset. The clouds of
dust that arose from the herds of cattle being
herded through town gave her new sources of
abstract shapes.</p>

<p>The imagery of these paintings in Texas
ranged between realistic and abstract forms
with allusions to the land. She produced them
on whatever paper was available as she wandered
the land, inspired by the power and
beauty of the Plains. North Texas, she would
write in 1919, was the only place she really felt
at home.</p>

<p>O'Keefe's mature style was fully developed
when she moved back to New York in the
summer of 1918. In 1924 she married Alfred
Stieglitz, the influential photographer and
owner of Gallery 291. Critics at the time discussed
O'Keefe's work in terms of feminine
forms, but many of the allusions were to landforms.
Other critics pointed to evidence of
Orientalism and Art Nouveau, the dominant
art movements of her youth, and to the influence
of her most important teacher, Arthur
Wesley Dow, whose dictum, that all things
must be done beautifully, stayed with her all
her life. All these influences are important, but
landscape, especially the Plains landscape, was
vital to her art.</p>

<p>After 1929 O'Keefe began spending her
summers in New Mexico, eventually (in 1949)
buying property in the village of Abiquiu,
near Santa Fe. Her love of the land is evident
in the New Mexico paintings, in which, once
again, landforms are dominant. After her
death on March 6, 1986, O'Keefe's estate
formed the basis of the Georgia O'Keefe
Foundation. In 1997 the Georgia O'Keefe Museum,
dedicated solely to O'Keefe's legacy,
opened in Santa Fe. She is one of a few women
artists in the world to be so honored.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT</hi>: 
<ref n="egp.pe.016">Caprock Canyonlands</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Ellen Bradbury<lb/>
Santa Fe, New Mexico</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Giboire, C. Lovingly, <title level="m">Georgia: The Complete Correspondence of Georgia O'Keeffe and Anita Pollitzer</title>. New York:
Simon and Schuster, 1990.</bibl> <bibl>O'Keefe, Georgia. <title level="m">Canyon Suite</title>. New York: George Braziller, 1995.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>