<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.na.025 SYSTEM "egp.na.025.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.na.025">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Dull Knife (ca. 1810-1883)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Joe Starita</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.na.025</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Starita, Joe">Joe Starita</author>. <title level="a">"Dull Knife (ca. 1810-1883)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">572</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-15</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">DULL KNIFE (ca. 1810-1883)</head>

<figure n="egp.na.025" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Dull Knife (Wo'he Hiv')</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>He was born in the rugged mountain country
of Montana's Rosebud Valley at the beginning
of the nineteenth century and died there near
century's end. In between, the trajectory of his
life encompassed the full sweep of Indian experience
on the nineteenth century Northern
Great Plains: warrior, chief, signatory to the
Fort Laramie Treaty, statesman, reservation
citizen, Cheyenne Outbreak leader, hunted
quarry, starving survivor, tribal elder.</p>

<p>To his people, the Northern Cheyennes, he
was called <hi rend="italic">Wo'he Hiv'</hi>, or Morning Star. As
a boy, it is said that he showed uncommon
bravery and leadership. As a young man, he
joined in raids against the Crows, Arikaras,
Snakes, and Shoshones, earning a reputation
for fierceness and courage. On December 21,
1866, he and Lakota war chief Crazy Horse led
a decoy party that helped wipe out Capt. William
J. Fetterman and all eighty-one of his
men. But not long afterward he began to believe
war against the whites was hopeless. A
gifted orator and skilled negotiator, he visited
the forts, talked to the soldiers, and attended
peace parleys, looking for a way out for his
people.</p>

<p>In 1868 he was among the chiefs who signed
the Treaty of Fort Laramie, agreeing he would
never again "sharpen his knife" against the
whites. Dull Knife, as he was now known, kept
his word. Col. George A. Woodward, commander
of Fort Fetterman, recalled an 1871
visit to the fort: "Of the three head-men of the
Cheyennes, Dull Knife was, I think, greatly the
superior. . . . His manner of speech was earnest
and dignified, and his whole bearing was
that of a leader with the cares of state."</p>

<p>In June 1876, while others left for the Little
Bighorn, Dull Knife stayed in his camp a few
miles southwest of the battle. Exactly five
months after the Custer fight, a surprise predawn
army attack wiped out much of his village.
On April 21, 1877, after a winter sharing
meager supplies in Crazy Horse's camp, Dull
Knife and 553 of his people surrendered at
Fort Robinson, Nebraska.</p>

<p>Five weeks later, Dull Knife and his Northern
Cheyenne were forcibly marched to a reservation
in Indian Territory. After a year enduring
starvation, disease, death, and acute
homesickness, Dull Knife and Little Wolf, another
chief and the tribe's most capable warrior,
decided to lead about 300 of their people
north on a 1,000-mile freedom flight back to
their Montana homeland. They left on September
9, 1878. Six weeks and more than 500
miles later&#8211;exhausted, hungry, cold, an estimated
2,000 troops in pursuit&#8211;they had made
it deep into the Sandhills of northwest Nebraska,
where the chiefs made a decision: Little
Wolf and the stronger ones would continue to
Montana; Dull Knife and the weaker ones
would look for Red Cloud's nearby camp.</p>

<p>On October 23, the cavalry caught up with
the weaker group, marching Dull Knife and
148 prisoners on a twenty-eight-mile trek to
Fort Robinson. The post commander, Capt.
Henry Wessells, told Dull Knife and four sub-chiefs
on January 3, 1879, that a decision had
been made: the Northern Cheyenne must return
immediately to their Indian Territory
reservation. "I am here on my own ground,"
Dull Knife replied, "and I will never go back.
You may kill me here, but you cannot make
me go back." On January 5, Wessells ordered
all food and heating fuel withheld from the
defiant Northern Cheyennes. Two days later,
he cut off the water supply. Still, Dull Knife
and his people refused to leave their barracks.</p>

<p>Shortly before 10 <hi rend="smallcaps">P.M.</hi> on the evening of January
9, with the temperature below zero and
half a foot of snow on the ground, the Northern
Cheyennes broke out of the barracks, fleeing
for the protective bluffs across the White
River. Skirmishes between the Northern Cheyennes
and cavalry troops continued for two
weeks. When the shooting ended on January
23, thirty-nine Northern Cheyenne men and
twenty-five women and children had been
killed. Dull Knife was not among them. He and
several family members eventually made it to
the safety of Pine Ridge Agency about sixty
miles away, surviving the last few nights by
eating the soles of their moccasins.</p>

<p>Later that year Dull Knife, then about seventy,
was allowed to return to Montana. In
November he rejoined Little Wolf, who&#8211;after
a journey of seven months and more than
1,000 miles&#8211;had made it safely back. Dull
Knife died of natural causes in his Rosebud
Valley homeland in 1883. About a year later, on
March 26, 1884, the U.S. government officially
set aside a tract of Montana land as the permanent
home of the Northern Cheyennes.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">WAR</hi>: <ref n="egp.war.014">Crazy Horse</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Joe Starita<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Starita, Joe. <title level="m">The Dull Knifes of Pine Ridge: A Lakota Odyssey</title>.
New York: Putnam, 1995.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>