<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.asam.021">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Territory of New Mexico v. Yee Shun</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>John R. Wunder</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.asam.021</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Wunder, John R.">John R. Wunder</author>. <title level="a">"Territory of New Mexico v. Yee Shun."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">146-147</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-22</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">TERRITORY OF NEW MEXICO V. YEE SHUN</head>

<p><title>Territory of New Mexico v. Yee Shun</title> (1884) is
a landmark case that established the right
of Chinese Americans to participate in the
American constitutional system. For the first
time, an American court of last resort guaranteed
non-Christian Chinese and other Asian
Americans the right to testify in courts of law.</p>

<p>On the evening of February 24, 1882, a
young Chinese man, Yee Shun, exited a train in
Las Vegas, New Mexico Territory, and walked
to a nearby laundry. He had been on his way to
a job at a Las Vegas hotel but had decided instead
to travel on to Albuquerque. He stopped
in Las Vegas because he wanted to make sure
that his mail could be forwarded, and so he
sought to find his local contact. There were
four Chinese men gathered at the laundry. The
owner indicated that he could escort Yee Shun
to meet his friend, but before he could do so,
another Chinese man, Jim Lee, came into
the room from the back and two shots rang
out. Jim Lee was shot dead, the owner was
wounded, and the others, including Yee Shun,
escaped. Yee Shun was apprehended and
charged with second-degree murder.</p>

<p>At the trial, crucial testimony came from
Jo Chinaman, one of the men who had been
present inside the laundry. He testified that
he had seen Yee Shun pull out a gun and shoot
Jim Lee. Before his damning testimony, Jo
Chinaman had been asked if he was a Christian
and whether he understood the oath to
tell the truth. He replied that he was not a
Christian and that he did not understand the
oath, but that he would tell the truth. The
judge deemed this sufficient to allow the testimony,
and a jury of twelve Mexican Americans
found Yee Shun guilty of murder. Yee
Shun's attorney appealed the verdict to the
New Mexico Territory Supreme Court on the
basis that Chinese witnesses who were not
Christians could not take the oath, and therefore
their testimony could not be allowed. It
should also be noted that Jo Chinaman had
been at the laundry to force the owner to sell,
and when the police arrived he said he knew
nothing about the murder.</p>

<p>The territorial Supreme Court heard the
case and decided that Chinese could in fact
testify in New Mexico's courts as long as the
court inquired as to the custom the witness
would invoke in his culture when testifying
and confirmed that the witness believed an
oath to be binding on his conscience. After <title>Yee Shun</title> more states and territories soon began to
allow Chinese to testify in their courts. Prior
to the decision, only Nebraska, Colorado, and
Texas in the Great Plains protected the Chinese
right to testify, and they did so through
their state constitutions. The only other western
states guaranteeing Chinese testimony
were Nevada and Oregon. Only Kansas continued
to question whether Chinese Americans
might testify at all. In 1909 Nebraska used
the <title>Yee Shun</title> decision to guarantee the right
of Japanese Americans to testify in American
courts, the first such decision made by a state
or federal court.</p>

<p>For Yee Shun, this important breakthrough
in Asian American civil rights was of no avail.
He was sentenced to life in prison and transported
to Leavenworth, Kansas (New Mexico
did not have a secure prison and contracted
with the state of Kansas to hold its prisoners).
Yee Shun then lost his appeal, and sometime
after being informed of this decision, in the
early morning hours of September 11, 1884, he
committed suicide by hanging himself in his
cell with a rope fashioned from his bed linens.</p>

<closer>
<signed>John R. Wunder<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Wunder, John R. "Chinese in Trouble: Criminal Law and
Race on the Trans-Mississippi West Frontier." <title level="j">Western Historical Quarterly</title> 17 (1986): 25–41.</bibl> <bibl>Wunder, John R.
"<title>Territory of New Mexico v. Yee Shun</title> (1882): A Turning
Point in Chinese Legal Relationships in the Trans-
Mississippi West." <title level="j">New Mexico Historical Review</title> 65 (1990):
305–18.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>