<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ha.014">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main"><hi rend="italic">Gen&#237;zaros</hi></title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Thomas D. Hall</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ha.014</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Hall, Thomas D.">Thomas D. Hall</author>. <title level="a">"<hi rend="italic">Gen&#237;zaros</hi>."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">356</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-25</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main"><hi rend="italic">GEN&#205;ZAROS</hi></head>

<p><hi rend="italic">Gen&#237;zaro</hi> was a term used in eighteenth- and
nineteenth-century New Mexico for "detribalized
Indians," a variety of individuals of
mixed Native American, but not Pueblo, parentage
who had adopted at least some Hispanic
styles of living. They were most common
in areas of New Mexico adjacent to the
Southern Plains. Gen&#237;zaros, many of whom
were descendants of Native Americans who
made their home in the Great Plains, are a
little-studied group. They appear to have been
a transitional group that appeared and then
disappeared as part of the opening, and later
closing, of a particular set of frontier relations
in New Mexico. Even the origin of the term
gen&#237;zaro is controversial.</p>

<p>The more commonly claimed origin is
from the term for captive Christians who were
forcibly converted to Islam and served as
troops in the Turkish army, called <hi rend="italic">yeni-cheri</hi>,
anglicized as janissary. Because of the close
phonetic equivalence and because of similar
roles played by genizaros in New Mexico, this
is assumed to be the genesis of the term. Steven
Horvath argues persuasively for a different
origin. To the root <hi rend="italic">geno</hi>-, meaning lineage
or race, are added suffixes -<hi rend="italic">izo</hi> and -<hi rend="italic">aro</hi>,
yielding the Spanish word. It referred to people
who were the children of parents from two
nations, for example France and Spain, or in
New Mexico, Comanches and Pawnees. Writing
in 1872, Fray Juan Augustin Morfi explained,
"This name is given to the children of
the captives of different nations who have
married in the province." The term became
generic for Native Americans who had been
born among nomadic groups, but who lived
in New Mexico.</p>

<p>There were two sources of genizaros. First,
they might have been taken captive in the many
fights with surrounding nomadic groups. Second,
they might have been traded (or "rescued")
from friendly Indian groups who had
taken them captive in their raids on enemies.
Typically, they were children or women and
were used as servants and laborers. To skirt
the legal ban on slavery, they were officially
designated as under the protection of a Spanish
household, whose head was to train them
in Christianity and Spanish culture generally.
In practice they were often slaves. They were
desirable because of labor shortages, especially
in frontier areas. Consequently, their
initial commonality was that they had been
born Native Americans but lived in Hispanic
society and occupied the lowest social strata.
Because they often grew up in captivity, they
knew little of their natal culture and hence
were often described as "detribalized Indians."</p>

<p>Some gen&#237;zaros eventually earned their freedom
and worked as day laborers; a few became
landowners or craftsmen. Two avenues to improved
status were open to them. They could
settle new areas where the Spanish government
sought to expand control. Also, men could
serve in militia units to fight hostile nomadic
Indians. Because of their origins their loyalty
was suspect, but they were deemed particularly
adept at dealing with or fighting nomadic Indians
because of their putative fierceness and
because some had at least rudimentary knowledge
of one or more languages of nomadic
Indians. (This same quality allowed them to
participate in locally lucrative but illegal trade
with Plains Indians.) Their military role is one
basis for the common assumption that <hi rend="italic">gen&#237;zaro</hi>
was a Spanish term for janissary.</p>

<p>Gen&#237;zaros who stood out in battles eventually
could own land or enter occupations
other than day laborer or soldier. Land grants
to gen&#237;zaro settlers typically were along frontiers
where fighting was heaviest. Through
time others of ambiguous ancestry might join
such communities. Thus, gen&#237;zaro came to refer
to anyone of ambiguous ancestry and/or
lower status. Eventually, more successful gen&#237;zaros
passed into the general Hispanic population.
By the late nineteenth century the term
gradually fell into disuse. The term is seldom
used today except by historians and genealogists
studying New Mexico history.</p>

<p>Determining the number or proportion of
genizaros is difficult. First, it was a status individuals
sought to hide. Second, it changed
through time for individuals and for families.
Finally, as both social relations and the terms
for various groups evolved, just who should
be counted as genizaro changed. Estimates
range from less than 10 percent of the settled
population to as high as one-third&#8211;enough
to be an important social component of Hispanic
society in colonial New Mexico, especially
in its interactions with Native Americans
who lived in the Great Plains.</p>

<p>For some individuals genizaro might be a
multigenerational transitional status in a passage
from Indian to Spaniard. Collectively,
they were a buffer group created by the combination
of a need for labor and a supply of
captives from nomadic Indians. When the
flow of captives slowed, and finally ceased, the
group was no longer refreshed by new members
and gradually disappeared.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Thomas D. Hall<lb/>
DePauw and Colgate Universities</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Gut&#237;errez, Ram&#243;n A. <title level="m">When Jesus Came, the Corn Mothers Went Away: Marriage, Sexuality, and Power in New Mexico, 1500–1846</title>. Stanford CA: Stanford University Press, 1991.</bibl>
<bibl>Horvath, Steven. "The Social and Political Organization
of the Gen&#237;zaros of Plaza de Nuestra Se&#241;ora de los Dolores
de Bel&#233;n, New Mexico, 1740–1812." Ph.D. diss., Brown
University, 1979.</bibl> <bibl>Magnaghi, Russell M. "Plains Indians in
New Mexico, the Gen&#237;zaro Experience." <title level="j">Great Plains Quarterly</title> 10 (1990): 86–95.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>