<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.arc.045">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Stone Masonry</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>L. Carl Brandhorst</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.arc.045</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Brandhorst, L. Carl">L. Carl Brandhorst</author>. <title level="a">"Stone Masonry."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">95-96</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-14</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">STONE MASONRY</head>

<p>During the early years of settlement, from the
Provinces of Canada to the Edwards Plateau
in Texas, the lack of timber forced settlers
to construct their buildings and fences from
other local materials. Though sod houses and
dugouts served in some places, stone, when
available, was the material of choice.</p>

<p>In central Kansas a Cretaceous limestone
(Fencepost limestone) lies near the surface on
the divides and is exposed in stream valleys. It
forms a layer of uniform thickness of about
nine inches and, when freshly quarried, is soft
enough to be sawed, carved, notched, drilled,
or otherwise worked with simple hand tools.
The stone's standard thickness and coloration
and its almost universal use impart to the entire
region an element of uniformity and a
unique folk character that have survived to
the present. Many houses and barns, churches
and stores, outbuildings and bridges, fences
and curbstones display the same characteristics
of color, texture, and dimension.</p>

<p>Quarrying required nothing beyond simple
hand tools and strong backs. First the overburden
was removed and the level face of the
stratum exposed. The drilling buck, a homemade
rig with sawhorse legs at one end and a
hand-pedaled drill at the other, was used to
bore holes into the stratum. Next, wedges,
called plugs, were driven into the drill holes to
cleave the rock from its stratum. Once cloven,
the stone blocks were finished with dressing
hammers and frequently textured with a variety
of chisels into a number of simple designs.
Smooth-textured finishes were ordinarily applied
to stones to be used in chimneys, window
and door lintels, and building corners.
Often the stone for these applications was
simply scraped smooth and offered an interesting
contrast to the rough-hewn quality of
the natural face used for the remainder of
the building. Occasionally, the face was pitted
with a punch, imparting a primitive decorative
feature. Stones were laid one tier upon
another mortar; powdered shale was used for
chinking the joints.</p>

<p>The stone houses of central Kansas fall into
several basic design classes. These include
the simple cabin, the two-story L or T plan,
and the one- or two-story square design with
either mansard or pyramidal roof. Many variations
appear within these generalized classes,
but character, individuality, and ethnic affinity
were achieved by the treatment of the
appurtenances rather than by any overt distinction
of the basic design. Stone houses were
common to most ethnic groups.</p>

<p>With the completion of local rail service
lines, lumber became competitive with stone,
and in the late 1920s the use of stone was generally
discontinued. When it was replaced, the
old stone house was often left standing to be
put to a variety of uses. It was, after all, nearly
as difficult to remove as it had been to build.</p>

<closer>
<signed>L. Carl Brandhorst<lb/>
Western Oregon State College</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Brandhorst, L. Carl. "Settlement and Landscape Change
on a Subhumid Grassland: Lincoln County, Kansas."
Ph.D. diss., University of Nebraska, 1974.</bibl> <bibl>Muilenburg,
Grace, and Ada Swinford. <title level="m">Land of the Postrock</title>. Lawrence:
University Press of Kansas, 1975.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>