<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ag.060">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Soil Bank</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Edward J. Deibert</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ag.060</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Deibert, Edward J.">Edward J. Deibert</author>. <title level="a">"Soil Bank."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">50-51</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-12-18</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">SOIL BANK</head>

<p>The Soil Bank Program was conceived in the
early 1950s when grain storage facilities full of
crop surpluses dotted rural America. Surpluses
lowered prices and reduced farm income,
and a program was needed to stabilize
the market. In 1956, Congress passed the Soil
Bank Act to reduce surpluses by lowering
acres of the major crops, thus keeping production
in line with demand, and to encourage
conservation of soil, water, and forest resources.
Spring and winter wheat, corn, grain
sorghum, and cotton were the majors crops
targeted for reduction in the Great Plains.</p>

<p>One part of the program, acreage reserve,
was a temporary measure to reduce surpluses
by making cash payments for crops taken out
of production. These yearly set-aside acres
were left idle and could not be cropped,
hayed, or pastured. The program also included
a voluntary conservation effort, often
referred to as the Soil Bank, which was a longterm
process aimed at diverting crop production
land to conservation uses.</p>

<p>Under the Soil Bank Program, the Agricultural
Stabilization and Conservation Service
(<hi rend="smallcaps">ASC</hi>) entered into three- to ten-year contracts
with landowners to set aside planted acres.
The farmers received in return an annual payment
based on the quality of the land (average
payment was around $12 per acre). They
agreed to maintain the land in an approved
conservation practice (predominantly grass in
the Great Plains) and not harvest a crop, cut
timber or hay, or graze the area. Nearly 29
million acres were placed in the Soil Bank program,
the majority of which were located in
the Great Plains. Texas and North Dakota had
the highest participation in the program, putting
aside as much as 10 percent of their total
cropland. More than 300,000 contracts with
an annual payment exceeding $300 million
occurred in some years.</p>

<p>The Soil Bank provided a guaranteed, riskfree
farm income with little work. Because the
amount of acres that could be contracted was
not limited, the program had negative social
and economic effects on many parts of the
Plains. Decreased agricultural production resulted
in reduced crop handling services and
processing activities. Landowners in the Soil
Bank Program often moved outside the area,
taking along spendable income, or sometimes
competed for off-farm employment. Local resentment
developed against Soil Bank farmers
who retired all their land and received payment
for doing nothing. The positive impacts
included crop surplus reduction, conservation
of soil and water, and development of
wildlife habitat.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Edward J. Deibert<lb/>
North Dakota State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>