<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.pe.056">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Soil Erosion</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Mark Kuzila</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.pe.056</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Kuzila, Mark">Mark Kuzila</author>. <title level="a">"Soil Erosion."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">639-640</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-27</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">SOIL EROSION</head>

<p>Soil erosion is the removal of soil from a position
on the landscape. The two main agents of
soil erosion are wind and water. The type of
erosion that occurs is generally related to climate.
Because the climate of the Great Plains
is relatively dry, and strong winds are common,
wind erosion is widespread throughout
the region. On May 12, 1934, for example,
winds carried an estimated 200 million tons of
soil from the Southern Great Plains over 1,500
miles to the Atlantic Ocean. Ideal conditions
for wind erosion are loose, finely divided and
dry soil on a bare, smooth surface.</p>

<p>Wind erosion moves soil in three ways: suspension,
saltation, and surface creep. Very fine
particles (less than 0.05 mm in diameter) can
be blown into the air and carried in suspension
for long distances. The particles fall out of suspension
when the wind velocity is reduced or
they are washed out by rain. Soil grains between
0.05 mm and 0.5 mm in diameter are too
heavy to be suspended. These grains are lifted
briefly in the air, move a short distance, and fall
back to the surface. Most soil eroded by wind
moves by this type of motion (saltation). Saltating
grains generally bounce along the surface
of the soil until the wind velocity lessens or
they meet some obstruction. These grains may
knock other grains into the air. Soil grains between
0.5 mm and 1 mm in diameter are too
large to be lifted into the wind stream. They are
bumped along the soil surface by saltating
grains in a movement called surface creep. Soil
grains moving by saltation are the keys to wind
erosion. Saltating grains increase the number
of smaller and larger particles that move in
suspension or by soil creep.</p>

<p>Water erosion is more prominent in humid
regions. It does, however, occur in the Great
Plains especially on sloping landscapes. In
1992 the average annual water erosion rate on
cropland was estimated at 3.1 tons per acre.
The movement of soil by water is a complex
process that is influenced by the amount, duration,
and intensity of rainfall, as well as by
the nature of the soil, ground cover, and slope
of the land. Raindrops play a substantial part
in the movement of soil by water. Soil grains
are detached from the soil mass by the force of
raindrops striking the soil grains. The soil
grains may then be splashed, rolled, slid, or
carried in suspension along the land surface.</p>

<p>There are three types of water erosion:
sheet, rill, and gully. Sheet erosion is the rather
uniform removal of thin layers of soil over the
entire soil surface. Sheet erosion is the least
recognizable type of erosion. It probably occurs
rarely because minute channeling usually
takes place soon after erosion begins. Rill erosion
occurs in small well-defined channels or
streamlets where there is a concentration of
flow. These rills are large and stable enough to
be seen. However, they can be removed by
normal tillage operations. Most rill erosion
occurs on recently cultivated soil. Gully erosion
produces large channels that cannot be
erased by normal tillage operations.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Mark Kuzila<lb/>
Conservation and Survey Division<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Schwab, G. O., R. K. Frevert, K. K. Barnes, and T. W.
Edminster. <title level="m">Elementary Soil and Water Engineering</title>. New
York: John Wiley and Sons, Inc. 1957.</bibl> <bibl>Stallings, J. H. <title level="m">Soil
Conservation</title>. Englewood Cliffs <hi rend="smallcaps">NJ</hi>: Prentice-Hall, Inc.
1957.</bibl> <bibl>Troeh, F. R., J. A. Hobbs, and R. L. Donahue. <title level="m">Soil and
Water Conservation</title>. Englewood Cliffs <hi rend="smallcaps">NJ</hi>: Prentice-Hall,
Inc. 1980.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>