<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.pg.073">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Saskatchewan</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Robert M. Bone</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.pg.073</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Bone, Robert M.">Robert M. Bone</author>. <title level="a">"Saskatchewan."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">687-688</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-05</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">SASKATCHEWAN</head>

<p>Saskatchewan, lying between the forty-ninth
and sixtieth parallels, is located on the northern
edge of the Great Plains. While Saskatchewan
extends over 251,700 square miles, only
part of this region falls within the Great
Plains. Geographically, the province is divided
into two equal parts: the southern part belongs
to the Great Plains, while the northern
part lies in the Canadian Shield. Saskatchewan's
southern neighbors are the states of
Montana and North Dakota. To its west lies
the province of Alberta and to the east, the
province of Manitoba. At the sixtieth parallel,
Saskatchewan ends and the Northwest Territories
begins.</p>

<p>The province of Saskatchewan came into
being on September 1, 1905. The province's
name, which was originally used as a district
of the Northwest Territories, is based on the
Cree word for swift-flowing water, or <hi rend="italic">Kis-is-ska-tche-wan</hi>. Saskatchewan's agriculture has
dominated its economy and defined its political
culture. The dry climate provides a challenge
to farmers, who mostly grow wheat. Perhaps
because of the dry climate and resulting
crop failures, creating periodic economic
crises, the people of Saskatchewan have sometimes
rejected the two leading parties, the Liberals
and Progressive Conservatives, and
sought to create their own parties. The Liberal
Party dominated Saskatchewan's politics until
1944, with only a short interlude (1929–34)
of Conservative rule. In 1944, under the leadership
of T. C. Douglas, the Cooperative
Commonwealth Federation (<hi rend="smallcaps">CCF</hi>) won the
provincial election, forming the first social
democratic government in Canada. The ccf
governed until 1964. In 1961 the ccf became
the New Democratic Party, which subsequently
formed the governments in Saskatchewan
from 1971 to 1982 and from 1991 to 1999.
Intervening governments were formed by the
Liberal Party from 1964 to 1971 and by the
Progressive Conservative Party (after a long
period of quiescence) from 1982 to 1991. In
1995 the Saskatchewan Party replaced the Progressive
Conservative Party.</p>

<p>In the early part of the twentieth century,
most of the population was rural. Today, most
of the population is urban. While the shift of
population from rural areas to urban ones has
eroded the political power of rural Saskatchewan,
agricultural concerns, ranging from inadequate
rainfall to low prices, can still dominate
the political agenda. However, rural Saskatchewan
no longer holds the political reins
in Saskatchewan.</p>

<p>Like other Canadian provinces, the government
of Saskatchewan is modeled after the
British parliamentary system. It has an elected
legislative assembly, a party system, and a premier
and cabinet. The premier is the head of
the executive council or cabinet. Each member
of the cabinet is a minister with assigned
specific powers and responsibilities. For the
government to pass a bill, the Saskatchewan
Legislative Assembly must approve the bill by
a simple majority vote. The largest opposition
party forms the Official Opposition. In 1997
there were fifty-eight elected members of the
legislative assembly. The largest party, the New
Democratic Party, had forty seats; the Saskatchewan
Party had nine seats; the Liberal
Party had five seats; one member sat as independent;
and three seats were vacant. Premier
Roy Romanow was the leader of the New
Democratic government. Because of Canada's
past colonial status, each province has a lieutenant
governor who originally represented
the British Crown but who now performs ceremonial
functions. In 1999 Jack Wiebe was the
lieutenant governor of Saskatchewan.</p>

<p>Canada is a federal state with political powers
divided between the federal and provincial
governments. The powers held by the provincial
government are named in the Canadian
Constitution of 1982, which superseded the
British North America Act of 1867. Saskatchewan
is responsible for its cultural and educational
institutions, highways, medical services,
natural resources, and social services. To meet
these obligations, the Saskatchewan government
has the power to tax its citizens and businesses
and to receive fees (royalties) from
firms exploiting its natural resources. Saskatchewan
has never been represented in large
numbers in Ottawa, but the province has produced
important national political leaders,
such as John Diefenbaker, who was prime
minister from 1957 to 1963, and "Jimmy" Gardiner,
who was minister of agriculture from
1935 to 1957.</p>

<p>While the duration of a government is five
years, most call for a new election in the fourth
year, especially if conditions for winning the
next election appear favorable. But elections in
Saskatchewan are never a sure thing. Past experience
shows that few governments have held
office for more than ten years, and rarely has
the winning party garnered more than 50 percent
of the votes. The volatility of the Saskatchewan
voter is less a swing from the left to the
right than a reaction to "good" government.
No matter what the ideology of the party in
power, eventually the government loses favor
with the electorate.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Robert M. Bone<lb/>
University of Saskatchewan</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Bone, Robert M. <title level="m">The Regional Geography of Canada: A
Country of Regions</title>. Toronto: Oxford University Press,
1999.</bibl> <bibl>Dyck, Rand. <title level="m">Provincial Politics in Canada</title>. Scarborough,
Ontario: Prentice-Hall, 1991.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>