<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ag.052">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Native American Agriculture</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>R. Douglas Hurt</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ag.052</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Hurt, R. Douglas">R. Douglas Hurt</author>. <title level="a">"Native American Agriculture."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">47-48</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-12-18</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">NATIVE AMERICAN AGRICULTURE</head>

<p>Prior to white contact, Native American agriculture
in the Great Plains differed little from
farming practices east of the Mississippi River.
On the Northern Plains the Mandans and
Hidatsas cultivated corn, beans, and squash
for their essential food needs. Women, who
were expert geneticists, cleared the land and
planted, cultivated, and harvested the crops,
then stored the surplus in jug-shaped pits.
They and other village-based Plains Indians,
such as the Pawnees, used floodplain terraces
for cropland. The tough prairie sod prevented
cultivation of the uplands. Family fields were
small, generally less than four acres. Nomadic
Plains tribes, such as the Crows and Lakotas
(Sioux), traded buffalo meat and hides to the
farming peoples for vegetables.</p>

<p>During the nineteenth century the acquisition
of Native American lands by the federal
government, and its distribution to settlers,
led to the creation of reservations where missionaries
and government agents attempted to
teach Native Americans European American
agricultural traditions. A similar policy was
instituted in Canada on reserves created in the
1870s and 1880s. Agents often violated Indian
culture by providing instruction to men, who
viewed agriculture as women's work. Agency
farmers also promoted wheat over traditional
crops and insisted on row cultivation rather
than the intercultivation methods that had
traditionally been used.</p>

<p>Often reserves and reservations were located
in areas where land could not support
agriculture beyond the subsistence level. Both
governments also failed to provide adequate
equipment, seeds, and training to enable the
transition to the new system. On the Canadian
reserves, for example, farmers who were supposed
to instruct Native Canadians were generally
from Ontario and knew nothing of the
conditions in the Prairie Provinces.</p>

<p>By the 1880s, in the United States, pressure
by settlers for reservation lands became acute
and Congress responded with the General Allotment
Act (also known as the Dawes Act) in
1887, which provided for the allotment of land
to individual tribal members. Under this legislation,
each head of household received a
plot of land, generally 160 acres, leaving the
remainder of the reservations to be sold as
surplus lands. Individuals who took allotments
would receive title to their land after a
trust period of twenty-five years. The Canadian
reserves were also allotted. The U.S. and
Canadian governments proposed to teach Native
peoples to become self-su.cient farmers
on their allotments, but they failed to back the
policy with the necessary resources. In 1906
Congress passed the Burke Act, which enabled
the secretary of the interior to declare an allotted
farmer competent to manage his or her
own affairs before the end of the trust period.
Landowners who were declared competent received title to their lands and often sold it, a
process that further hindered the successful
development of Native American agriculture.</p>

<p>During the 1930s the federal government
attempted to aid Plains Indian farmers by providing
cattle to help build tribal herds, and
several tribes organized livestock associations
to improve breeding and marketing practices.
By the end of World War II, however, high
crop and livestock prices accelerated white demands
to lease or purchase Indian lands because,
it was claimed, they were not being
cultivated or grazed to capacity. After 1945
only the white farmers who could command
the necessary capital and credit, and who had
access to new forms of science and technology
and large acreages, could earn a profit from
commercial agriculture. Native Americans in
the Great Plains remained subsistence farmers,
if they practiced agriculture at all. In
1970, for example, only 9 percent of Native
Americans on the North Dakota reservations
of Fort Berthold, Fort Totten, Turtle Mountain,
and Standing Rock were farmers or farm
managers.</p>

<p>At the beginning of the twenty-first century,
on many reserves and reservations in
the Great Plains, Native American agriculture
has nearly ceased. There are important exceptions,
of course, such as Montana Reserve in
Alberta, which has a successful ranch and feed
operation. But many tribes have leased their
reservation lands to white farmers and ranchers,
and millions of acres of allotted lands have
been sold and passed from Indian control.
The problems of government-imposed inheritance
laws, which divided land holdings into
tracts too small for profitable cultivation, and
inadequate capital, credit, and education, as
well as insufficient machinery, seeds, fertilizer,
irrigation, and managerial experience, remain
unresolved. As a result, most Native Americans
in the Great Plains live in rural areas but
are not farmers.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">LAW</hi>: <ref n="egp.law.015">Dawes Act</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>R. Douglas Hurt<lb/>
Iowa State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Baillargeon, Morgan. "Native Cowboys on the Canadian
Plains." <title level="j">Agricultural History</title> 69 (1995), 547–62.</bibl> <bibl>Hurt, R.
Douglas. <title level="m">Indian Agriculture in America: Prehistory to the Present</title>. Lawrence: University Press of Kansas, 1987.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>