<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ea.042">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Welsh</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Wayne K. D. Davies</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ea.042</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Davies, Wayne K. D.">Wayne K. D. Davies</author>. <title level="a">"Welsh."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">251-252</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-09</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">WELSH</head>

<p>The Welsh are one of the least numerous of
the ethnic groups that settled in the Great
Plains. The peak of immigration of the Welsh
to America was at the beginning of the twentieth
century, but the ten American states of
the Great Plains showed only 7,259 people
born in Wales at this time, with another 542 in
the Canadian Prairies, but as the latter area
was settled the Canadian numbers grew to
3,597 in 1911 and 5,980 in 1921. However, all
these figures are probably underestimates
since the Welsh were often grouped with the
English or British ethnic categories. In recent
censuses the numbers of Welsh recording a
single ancestry are among the lowest of all ethnic
groups, due to high levels of intermarriage
with other peoples and cultural absorption.</p>

<p>Although the numerical contribution is
small, the Welsh have made important contributions
to the development of the region. Several
of the earliest European pioneers in the
exploration and mapping of the northern
reaches of the Great Plains, including David
Thompson and John Thomas Evans, came
from Wales. But it was the development of
agricultural settlement in the region that attracted
significant numbers of Welsh people.
The largest and most persistent of the agricultural
concentrations are in Emporia, Kansas,
beginning in 1856–58, and Edmunds County,
South Dakota, beginning in 1883, with several
other smaller clusters, such as Arvonia, Kansas,
and Richardson County, Nebraska, forming
in the 1860s and 1870s. Small concentrations
of Welsh miners were also attracted to
Coal and Pittsburg Counties in Oklahoma after
1880 and Cambria County in Wyoming after
1867.</p>

<p>In Canada also, two rural settlement areas
associated with the Welsh stand out. The
Wood River area east of Ponoka in Alberta
developed in 1900–1905 and attained a peak of
around 200 people in 1910. Although some of
the settlers had been born in Wales, many were
American-born (mainly in Kansas and Nebraska),
so the Wood River settlement was
largely a Welsh American initiative. Of the two
original Welsh chapels, Zion still survives, although
regular services ended in 1995. Another
Welsh area, of approximately the same
size, was established near Bangor, Saskatchewan,
in 1902–3, but again these were largely
first- and second-generation Welsh, this time
from Patagonia, Argentina. The concentration
of names of Welsh origin still survives in the
area, and services are still held in two of
the original four churches, Llewellyn Bethel
United and St. David's Anglican, although
the use of Welsh died out in the 1930s.</p>

<p>The fact that these two primary rural settlements
in the Canadian Prairies were settled by
Welsh from outside Wales indicates the pull of
other areas upon potential Welsh immigrants
to the Great Plains. However, the negative
comments about working conditions in western
Canada from a group of young Welshmen
who worked on the construction of the Crowsnest
Pass railway line west of Lethbridge in
1897–98 might have also discouraged potential
Welsh immigrants. Their complaints received
wide publicity in Britain and led immigrant
agents to try to cover up the bad news. Nevertheless,
small numbers of Welsh continued
to immigrate to the coal-mining areas and also
to the bigger cities, many of which had Welsh
churches by the 1920s.</p>

<p>Vestiges of the Welsh cultural heritage still
survive in many areas, such as the celebration
of St. David's Day on March 1 in Emporia,
Kansas, and the annual Gymanfa Ganu, a
chapel-based singing festival in Ponoka, Alberta,
in August. In mining areas the Welsh
often played an important part in political
and workforce activity, for many of the Welsh
had known the value of union activity in their
homeland. But many of the Welsh were also
known for their piety, so in most settlement
areas and the bigger cities Nonconformist
chapels were built and became the focus of
Welsh cultural life.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, the small size of most of the
Welsh rural settlements, their distances apart,
and the inability to reinforce cultural heritage
through continued emigration from the
homeland led to the decline in cultural separateness.
In addition, the loss of the Welsh
language in many of the industrial areas of
Wales and the decline of the Nonconformist
religion provided a further blow to the distinctiveness
of Welsh immigrants. In industrial
areas, the limited economic life of most
mines exacerbated the problem of cultural
survival, for people were forced to move on
once the mine was exhausted. In most large
cities in the region the same decline in cultural
identity can also be seen, and the Welsh
churches that were the focus of communities
closed in the decades before and after World
War II. However active Welsh societies can
still be found in most large cities, while the
Welsh passion for rugby led many immigrants
to promote the game, especially in Canada.
But it is new immigrants from Wales in the
cities, often in teaching or skilled worker positions,
who have helped keep the Welsh heritage
alive, while many Welsh societies have
been reinvigorated or even re-created in the
last two decades because of a greater interest
in cultural heritage.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Wayne K. D. Davies<lb/>
University of Calgary</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Davies, Wayne K. D. "The Welsh in Canada: A Geographical
Overview." In <title level="m">The Welsh in Canada</title>, edited by M.
Chamberlain. Swansea <hi rend="smallcaps">UK</hi>: Canadian Studies in Wales
Group, 2002: 1–48.</bibl> <bibl>Williams, J. G. <title level="m">Songs of Praise: Welsh Rooted Churches beyond Britain</title>. Clinton <hi rend="smallcaps">NY</hi>: Gwenfrewi
Santes Press, 1996.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>