<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ind.061">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Wind Energy</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Ernest Callenbach</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ind.061</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Callenbach, Ernest">Ernest Callenbach</author>. <title level="a">"Wind Industry."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">437</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-04</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">WIND ENERGY</head>

<p>The Great Plains has been called the "Saudi
Arabia of Wind Energy" because its resources
for wind power are so immense, but development
of those resources has been slow. Several
important long-term factors favor extensive
development of the industry in the Plains:
wind power is independent of the fluctuations
of the world energy market, which many analysts
expect to become more extreme; it has a
low impact on the environment; and, because
wind towers need very small footprints and
wind farm wires are underground, it is compatible
with grazing, farming, and other
Plains land uses. Indeed, for individual farmers
and ranchers, wind farm lease royalties can
greatly surpass other income.</p>

<p>Through sophisticated engineering of blades
and other turbine components, the costs per
kilowatt-hour of wind power have been dropping
steadily for many years. Only natural
gas-burning turbines now produce cheaper
power, and high-tech wind turbines are predicted
to soon equal their costs&#8211;sooner if fossil
fuel costs rise, as many expect. In some
parts of the Great Plains, wind power is already
effectively cheaper than gas when all
costs, for example, transportation of fuel, are
taken into account. However, Plains state governments,
universities, and private utilities
have all been slow in recognizing the manifold
advantages of wind power for the region.
Wind facilities are presently concentrated
where state governments have acknowledged
the potential of wind power (Texas primarily,
but Colorado and Kansas have also offered incentives
for "green" power). As of 1999, wind
turbine installations also exist in Wyoming,
Nebraska, and North Dakota.</p>

<p>According to prospectors who have assessed
the Plains winds, North Dakota alone has wind
resources that, if harnessed, could provide
about a third of the entire country's electricity
demand, and the Plains as a whole could provide
all the power the country could foreseeably
need. However, because of the economics
of the electrical industry, wind power is likely
to evolve as a largely local institution in the
thinly settled Plains. As utilities planners have
recently recognized, electrical distribution is
more costly than electrical generation. This
fact has implications both for generating strategies
and for grid planning. For the Plains, it
means that wind farm development is likely to
be relatively decentralized, a pattern that will
minimize grid investment needs. It is also
likely to suit the desire of Plains people for local
control rather than dependence on distant
powerful forces. Because transmission costs
and losses favor consumption of power nearer
points of generation, state-scale or local generating
facilities are probable. They will also have
the advantage of increasing local grid reliability
in case national power shortages occur. A
Danish-owned, thirteen-employee wind machine
blade factory has recently been set up in
Wisconsin, and other manufacturing and installing
companies should follow in the Plains
proper. Wind farms provide more numerous
jobs per million dollars of investment than any
other means of generating power—and without
the boom-and-bust pattern of oil and coal.
Individual farmers and ranchers with their
own turbines will also find themselves able in
especially windy spells to sell excess power to
the grid through reverse metering.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT</hi>: <ref n="egp.pe.068">Wind</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Ernest Callenbach<lb/>
Berkeley, California</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Righter, Robert W. <title level="m">Wind Energy in America: A History</title>.
Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1996.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>