<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fol.029">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Mythical Animals</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>James F. Hoy</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2009</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fol.029</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2009</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2009 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Hoy, James F.">James F. Hoy</author>. <title level="a">"Mythical Animals."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">306-307</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-16</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">MYTHICAL ANIMALS</head>

<p>The most pervasive mythical animal of the
Great Plains is undoubtedly the jackalope.
Mounted jackalopes are most often seen hanging
from the walls of cafes, taverns, and filling
stations throughout the region, while jackalope
postcards are a popular tourist item.
Most jackalopes have the body and head of a
jackrabbit and the antlers of a deer or elk or
the horns of a pronghorn antelope, although
the "warrior rabbit" of Nebraska and the Dakotas
also has pheasant wings and tail feathers.
The New Mexico version is sometimes called
an "antelabbit."</p>

<p>A large statue of a jackalope is located in
Douglas, Wyoming, which claims to be the
home of this fabulous beast, the brainchild of
two taxidermist brothers, Ralph and Doug
Herrick, who created their first one in the
1930s. The antecedents of the jackalope, however,
are much older, going back to the Bavarian
<hi rend="italic">wolpertinger</hi> and the French <hi rend="italic">dahout</hi>.
These beasts combine crow or hawk wings,
rabbit ears, deer antlers, boar tusks, duck forefeet,
rooster hind feet, a foxtail, and a coxcomb,
all on a woodchuck body.</p>

<p>A body of lore has grown up around the
jackalope: it can mimic the human voice and
in earlier times would often sing along with
night-herding cowboys; jackalopes mate during
flashes of lightning; and jackalope milk is
credited with the ability to cure everything
from rheumatism to snakebite. An exhibit at
the Dyche Museum of Natural History on the
campus of the University of Kansas displayed
not only mounted jackalope and postcards
but also a number of mounted cottontail rabbits
aÄicted with Shope's papillomas, a viral
infection that causes skin growths similar
to that which forms the outer sheath of the
pronghorn on an antelope. Other fabulous
creatures reported in the Great Plains include
Bigfoot, sighted near McLaughlin, South Dakota,
during the early 1980s, and a water monster,
nicknamed "SinkHole Sam," which supposedly
arose in the early 1950s from an
underground cavern in McPherson County,
Kansas, when a small lake there was drained.</p>

<p>Most mythical creatures from the Plains are
actual animals that have achieved exaggerated
proportions, such as stories of snakes the size
of boa constrictors. Obvious hoaxes are the
postcard versions of giant grasshoppers or
saddled jackrabbits being ridden by cowboys,
while stories of giant catfish that reside in the
deepest waters of the reservoirs that dot the
Plains are told for truth. Also told for truth are
reports of animals that were once prevalent
before being hunted to regional extinction in
parts of the Plains, such as bear or mountain
lions or wolves.</p>

<p>Finally, individual animals have sometimes
taken on mythic status, such as the elusive
white mustang that roamed the Central Plains
in the last century, or the "Murder Steer" of
the southwestern Plains celebrated in folk
song. Apparently based on an actual quarrel
and gunfight that resulted from an ownership
dispute during a roundup, the steer was
branded murder and set free, whereupon for
decades it roamed the range from Texas to
Montana, a grim reminder of the consequences
of greed and anger.</p>

<closer>
<signed>James F. Hoy<lb/>
Emporia State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Dance, S. Peter. <title level="m">Animal Fakes and Frauds</title>. Maidenhead
<hi rend="smallcaps">UK</hi>: Sampson Low, 1975.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>