<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ct.002">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Abilene, Texas</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>B. W. Aston</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ct.002</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Aston, B. W.">B. W. Aston</author>. <title level="a">"Abilene, Texas."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">158</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-22</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">ABILENE, TEXAS</head>

<p>Abilene, Texas, a town of 117,111 in 1999, is
located 150 miles west of Fort Worth at the
junction of Interstate 20 and U.S. Highways
277 and 83. It was one of many towns that
came into existence as the Texas and Pacific
Railway made its way west to California. What
made Abilene different from and more successful
than other railroad towns was the aggressiveness
of the people who lived there.
From the beginning, they promoted Abilene
as the "Future Great City of West Texas." Local
ranchers and businessmen C. W. Merchant,
John Merchant, John N. Simpson, and John T.
Berry persuaded H. C. Withers, town-site locator
for the railroad, to select a site in northeastern
Taylor County for the new town, ignoring
the already established community and
county seat, Buffalo Gap. A tent city of 300
was already established when the first town
lots were auctioned on March 15, 1881. Some
200 people spent $51,000 to become a part of
the new city. Before long, Abilene had two
newspapers, an imported sheriff (John J. Clinton
from Dodge City, Kansas), public schools,
and churches. In 1883 Abilene won the election
to become the new county seat.</p>

<p>Religion has always been an important part
of the community. In 1891 the first of three
church-related universities, Simmons College
(later Hardin-Simmons University), was established.
Abilene Christian University originally
opened in 1906 as Childers Classical Institute
and was followed in 1923 by McMurry
University. Subsequently, they were joined
by branches of Cisco College and Texas State
Technical College. The abundance of Christian
universities has led some to say that Abilene
is the buckle on the Bible Belt of the
South. There is no doubt that the universities
have had their impact on the city; they are a
major economic asset and help make Abilene
an education center.</p>

<p>In the late nineteenth century, as the Texas
Plains were being settled, Abilene boosters unashamedly
promoted their city, running promotional
trains from Fort Worth to give people
the opportunity to settle in this "Eden of
the West." This boosterism made Abilene the
center of what is called today the "Big Country."
By the early twentieth century, Abilene
had developed an ample water supply, public
utilities, streetcars, and a fairly dependable
economy based on farming and ranching, including
sheep. The Abilene Epileptic Asylum,
known today as the Abilene State School, was
built in 1899 and, along with the West Texas
Rehabilitation Center and two major hospitals,
made Abilene a major medical center for
the region. Abilene also quickly developed
into a center for wholesale and retail trade,
transportation, media, and cultural events as
well as the headquarters for independent oil
operators after the oil boom of the 1920s,
which had more than doubled the population
to 23,175 by 1930.</p>

<p>However, it was World War II that put Abilene
on the map. The arrival of Camp Barkeley
and Tye Army Air Field in 1940 brought 1.5
million soldiers as well as millions of dollars
into the city. The closing of Barkeley at the end
of World War II spurred civic leaders to diversify
Abilene's economic base, but they never
lost sight of what a military installation had
done for the economy. In 1952 their lobbying
efforts proved successful when Congress approved
the construction of Dyess Air Force
Base in Abilene. The air force base, along with
the Nike and Atlas missile installations in the
early sixties, put Abilene into another economic
boom that only temporarily subsided
in the late sixties before resuming once again
during the oil crisis of the 1970s. The oil industry
stimulated a rapid growth in manufacturing,
banking, and construction. Oil, however,
has always been a fickle economic base,
and declining prices in the 1980s once again
set Abilene scrambling to shore up its economic
livelihood.</p>

<p>In the 1990s Abilene turned the declining
downtown area into a historic district, anchored
by the Grace Cultural Center and Museums
of Abilene complex and promoted by
an art walk. Old railroad buildings have been
transformed into a restaurant, candy factory,
and tourist information and Chamber of
Commerce center. Minor-league baseball and
hockey teams have complemented the strong
Abilene Philharmonic Orchestra, opera association,
ballet company, and theater groups as
entertainment attractions. The LaJet Classic,
held at the Fairway Oaks Golf and Racquet
Club since 1981, was on the PGA tour for
about ten years. The Abilene Convention Center
brings all types of organizations to the
downtown area, while the Taylor County Coliseum
has become the center for horse shows
and rodeos. The ruins of Fort Phantom Hill
north of Abilene and Buffalo Gap Historic
Village just south of the city add to the cultural
attractions.</p>

<closer>
<signed>B. W. Aston<lb/>
Hardin-Simmons University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Downs, Fane, ed. <title level="m">The Future Great City of West Texas, Abilene, 1881-1981</title>. Abilene <hi rend="smallcaps">TX</hi>: Richardson, 1981.</bibl> <bibl>Duff, Katharyn,
and Betty Kay Seibt. <title level="m">Catclaw Country: An Informal History of Abilene in West Texas</title>. Burnet <hi rend="smallcaps">TX</hi>: Eakin, 1980.
Lack, Paul, Paul Jungmeyer, Robert Sledge, and Fane
Downs. <title level="m">The History of Abilene</title>. Abilene <hi rend="smallcaps">TX</hi>: McMurry, 1981.</bibl>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>