<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fil.029">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Hollywood Indians</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Jacquelyn Kilpatrick</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fil.029</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Kilpatrick, Jacquelyn">Jacquelyn Kilpatrick</author>. <title level="a">"Hollywood Indians."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">269</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-12</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">HOLLYWOOD INDIANS</head>
<figure n="egp.fil.029" rend="granted" type="noclick">
<figDesc>Hollywood's Indian: The Portrayal of Native Americans on Film, by Peter C. Rollins and John E. O'Connor, eds.</figDesc>
</figure>      

<p>In more than a century of film history, the
"Hollywood Indian" has rarely reflected the
actual Native Americans of the Great Plains.
During the years of silent film production,
Native Americans were often played by members
of the Sioux Nation. "Extras" were
brought in by busload for the films, and producer
and director Thomas Ince had a Sioux
settlement of "Ince Indians" on the California
coast. Even during those years, however, Native
American roles of importance were generally
played by non-Native actors, and the dress
and customs of Native American peoples were
depicted in whatever costumes suited the director
or set designer's taste and rarely reflected
the individual tribes. However, the
Hollywood Indian from the 1920s through the
1980s was more likely to resemble a Plains Indian
than any other, largely because the American
audience quickly grew accustomed to the
exotic look of Plains headdresses and breastplates.
In 1914, Alanson Skinner, assistant curator
of the Department of Anthropology at
the American Museum of Natural History,
wrote the <title level="j">New York Times</title> to complain about
these inaccuracies in film costuming, describing
the movies as "grotesque farces" in which
Delawares were dressed as Sioux and eastern
Indians were shown dwelling in skin tipis of
the type used only in the trans-Mississippi
West.</p>

<p>In 1940 a Cherokee actor named Victor
Daniels (aka Chief Thunder Cloud) led a
group of actors in applying to the Bureau of
Indian Affairs for recognition as the "De Mille
Indians," a new tribe composed only of Native
Americans who worked in the film industry.
While humorous, the application was also an
attempt to show the artificiality of the stereotypes
found in the film images. The Western
imagination is largely visual, and American
audiences have over the course of film history
generally accepted as reality the Hollywood
Indian, whether Noble Savage or Bloodthirsty
Savage.</p>

<p>The Native American has often been used
as the metaphorical foe in Westerns. For instance,
when the Colonel William F. Cody
(Buffalo Bill) Historical Pictures Company
made <title>The Indian Wars</title> in 1914, the secretary of
state sent troops and equipment for the filming,
Gen. Nelson Miles agreed to appear in the
film, and the War Department put the Pine
Ridge Sioux (Lakota) at Cody's disposal. Such
overwhelming support was due, presumably,
to the fact that the film was to be used for War
Department records and to enlist recruits to
fight in World War I. Later, films such as <title>Northwest Passage</title> (1939) would be similarly used to
engender a patriotic response in World War II,
with the Hollywood Indian standing in for the
German soldiers once more.</p>

<p>During the 1950s the images were more
likely to be those of the Noble Savage, as
Hollywood, experiencing the effects of Mc-
Carthyism, used the Native American to represent
the oppressed Other. <title>Broken Arrow</title>
(1950) and <title>Cheyenne Autumn</title> (1964) showed
the Native American as gallant and dignified
in the face of oppression by the dominant culture.
<title>Little Big Man</title> (1970) and <title>Soldier Blue</title>
(1970) used Native Americans as metaphors
for the Vietnamese, with the message that innocent
and noble people were being killed in
an unjust war.</p>

<p>Perhaps the most obvious Hollywood Indian
appeared in Elliot Silverstein's 1970 film <title>A Man Called Horse</title>, which was intended and
well publicized as a "sympathetic and accurate
portrayal" of the Plains Indians, particularly
the Lakota Sioux. However, according to
Ward Churchill, a Native American scholar,
the film depicted Indians whose language was
Lakota, whose hairstyles ranged from Assiniboine
to Nez Perce to Comanche, whose tipis
were Crow, and whose Sun Dance ceremony
was Mandan. Other important distortions include
sending an old woman out into a blizzard
to die because her only means of support,
her son, was killed in a raid. This is in direct
opposition to the reverence with which the
Sioux peoples hold the elderly.</p>

<p>The Hollywood Indian of the 1980s and
1990s is more likely to be an actual Native
American than in previous decades, and a few
films have been made that depict Native Americans
less stereotypically, although many still
include stereotypes old and new (the Natural
Ecologist is among the new ones). Although
most films that include Native Americans still
take place in the past with tribes that are vanishing
or have vanished (as the scroll at the end
of Kevin Costner's 1990 <title>Dances with Wolves</title>
indicates), the images of Native America are
occasionally more human than stereotypical.
Also, more films are being made by Native
American filmmakers, so perhaps it is the Hollywood
Indian tribe that will soon vanish.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Jacquelyn Kilpatrick<lb/>
Governors State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Bataille, Gretchen, and Charles L. P. Silet, eds. <title level="m">The Pretend Indians: Images of Native Americans in the Movies</title>. Ames:
Iowa University Press, 1980.</bibl> <bibl>Churchill, Ward, and Annettee
Jaimes. <title level="m">Fantasies of the Master Race: Literature, Cinema and the Colonization of American Indians</title>. Monroe <hi rend="smallcaps">ME</hi>:
Common Courage Press, 1992.</bibl> <bibl>Kilpatrick, Jacquelyn. <title level="m">Celluloid Indians: Native Americans in Film</title>. Lincoln: University
of Nebraska Press, 1999.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>