<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.law.035">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Native American Rights Fund</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Ray Ramirez</author>
<author>Walter Echo-Hawk</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.law.035</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Ramirez, Ray">Ray Ramirez</author> and <author n="Echo-Hawk, Walter">Walter Echo-Hawk</author>. <title level="a">"Native American Rights Fund."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">458-459</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-05</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">NATIVE AMERICAN RIGHTS FUND</head>
<figure n="egp.law.035" rend="granted" type="noclick">
<figDesc>Logo for Native American Rights Fund</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>The Native American Rights Fund (<hi rend="smallcaps">NARF</hi>),
based in Boulder, Colorado, is the oldest and
largest nonprofit national Indian rights organization
in the country. Since its establishment
in 1970, <hi rend="smallcaps">NARF</hi> has grown from a three-lawyer
staff to a firm of forty full-time staff members,
with fourteen attorneys. Most of the attorneys
and nearly all support staff personnel are Native
American. <hi rend="smallcaps">NARF</hi> has represented more
than 200 Indian tribes located in thirty-one
states, including many Native people who are
Indigenous to the Great Plains. The hundreds
of cases it has handled have involved every
major problem and issue in the field of Native
American law. The Native American Rights
Fund is governed by a thirteen-member board
of directors composed entirely of Native people.
This board charts the direction of <hi rend="smallcaps">NARF</hi>'s activities
by setting priorities and policies. Board
members are chosen on the basis of their involvement
in Native affairs, their knowledge
of the legal problems facing Native Americans
throughout the country, and, most importantly,
their dedication to the well-being and survival
of Native Americans.</p>

<p>Today, more than fifty-five Indian tribes are
an important and integral part of the economic,
political, and cultural life of the Great
Plains. Most have treaties with the United
States that set forth property, political, and
legal rights. Each Great Plains state contains
Indian reservations that were established by
treaties or other federal action and are governed
by tribal governments. From legal and
political standpoints, each reservation in the
United States is a nation within a nation. The
power of tribal governments and the jurisdiction
over reservation lands among tribal,
state, and federal governments are integral aspects
of Great Plains governance and are continually
being refined by litigation or legislation.
At the same time, the protection of and
control over the natural resources located on
Indian reservations such as water, oil, and natural
gas are vitally important to Indian owners.
Tribal people are citizens of their respective
Indian tribes, the United States, and their
respective states, and they aspire to rights of
self-determination, tribal sovereignty, cultural
rights, and human rights similar to those
sought by other Indigenous peoples throughout
the world.</p>

<p><hi rend="smallcaps">NARF</hi> attorneys work to tear down barriers
to the fulfillment of these rights in Great
Plains courtrooms and legislatures. For example,
<hi rend="smallcaps">NARF</hi> has worked to restore land and federal
recognition to the Alabama-Coushatta
Tribe, the Kickapoo Tribe, and the Ysleta del
Sur Pueblo in Texas and to restore tribal jurisdiction
to the Winnebago Tribe in Nebraska.
In Oklahoma, <hi rend="smallcaps">NARF</hi> has worked to recognize
the reservation status of Pawnee lands, to clarify
Osage tribal government status, and to
confirm Cheyenne and Arapaho tribal oil and
gas taxation authority. In the area of human
rights, <hi rend="smallcaps">NARF</hi> has represented Native American
inmates in jails and prisons in North and
South Dakota, Nebraska, Kansas, and Oklahoma.
It provided legal representation to
tribes located in Oklahoma and North Dakota
to protect tribal burial grounds from desecration
and to repatriate human remains that
had been removed from tribal graves and carried
away to museums, historical societies,
and other institutions. <hi rend="smallcaps">NARF</hi> has also represented
tribes and students in South Dakota,
North Dakota, Oklahoma, and eastern Colorado
on education issues relating to public,
tribal, and Bureau of Indian Affairs schools.
<hi rend="smallcaps">NARF</hi> has represented traditional religious
practitioners in protecting their freedom of
worship at sacred sites in eastern Wyoming, in
prisons, and during the worship ceremonies
of the Native American Church. These issues
illustrate the problems that confront Great
Plains Indian tribes in the United States today
as Native peoples strive to live according to
their traditional ways of life and the aspirations
of their forefathers.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">NATIVE AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.na.096">Reservations</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Ray Ramirez<lb/>
Walter Echo-Hawk<lb/>
Native American Rights Fund</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Dobler, Lavinia. <title level="m">Esther Morris: First Woman Justice of the Peace</title>. Riverton <hi rend="smallcaps">WY</hi>: Big Bend Press, 1993.</bibl> <bibl>Larson, T. A.
<title level="m">History of Wyoming</title>. Lincoln: University of Nebraska
Press, 1978.</bibl> <bibl>Massie, Michael A. "Reform Is Where You
Find It: The Roots of Woman Suffrage in Wyoming." <title level="j">Annals of Wyoming</title> 62 (1990): 2-21.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>