<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.rel.049">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Unitarianism</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Phillip Hewett</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.rel.049</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Hewett, Phillip">Phillip Hewett</author>. <title level="a">"Unitarianism."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">758-759</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-19</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">UNITARIANISM</head>

<p>The Unitarian movement originated in
sixteenth-century Europe among radical Christians
who affirmed the undivided unity of
God and promoted a form of religion in
which human unity would be based upon individual
freedom and reliance upon reason
and conscience. In New England the movement
emerged early in the nineteenth century,
but it was slow in spreading westward, being
predominant among the middle class and well
educated, and therefore ill adapted to frontier
conditions. The same was not true of a parallel
movement, the Universalists, but by the time
they reached the Great Plains in the 1860s,
they had already lost much of their momentum.
In 1961 the Unitarians and Universalists
merged to form the Unitarian Universalist Association,
though most individual congregations
retained their single name.</p>

<p>Early Unitarian attempts at extension into
the Great Plains bore fruit only in the major
cities, all of which had congregations by the
end of the nineteenth century. The first was at
Omaha in 1869; the largest, that in Tulsa, was
exceptional in not having been founded until
1921. Fellowships that now exist in smaller
communities have all been established or reestablished
since 1950. The congregation in
Sioux Falls may serve as an example. It mushroomed
in 1887, erecting a fine stone church,
but was forced by the economic depression to
disband ten years later, bequeathing its building
to the city as a public library. The present
congregation dates from 1961. The inclusion
of both Unitarians and Universalists in the
original Sioux Falls congregation was typical
for the Great Plains but unusual elsewhere. So
also was the fact that it was founded and led
by women ministers at a time when these constituted
no more than a tiny fraction of the
active ministry in either denomination as
a whole.</p>

<p>A third characteristic shared by all congregations
in the Plains was that they were
from the outset much more theologically radical
than their coreligionists on the East Coast,
who continued to maintain a more or less exclusively
Christian emphasis. Thus, the new
"Bond of Union" adopted by the Omaha congregation
in 1890 simply affirmed moral and
religious purpose rather than making any specific
statement of belief. Such openness paved
the way for the strong emergence of nontheistic
humanism in the congregations of the
Great Plains during the twentieth century.</p>

<p>Unitarians have typically worked in projects
for the betterment of the entire community.
An outstanding leader in this field was
Arthur L. Westerly, a minister in Lincoln, Nebraska
(1908–19 and 1929–42), who was active
in a wide variety of civic projects and social
reforms. The Joslyn family in Omaha likewise
contributed heavily to the artistic and musical
life of the community.</p>

<p>The congregations have been composed
chiefly of persons coming from other parts of
North America rather than from overseas.
The only exceptions were small-scale movements
among Scandinavian immigrants and a
much more substantial one among the Icelanders
who settled in North Dakota and the
Prairie Provinces of Canada. The Icelandic
Unitarian Church in Winnipeg was founded
in 1891, and until the 1920s most Unitarians in
Manitoba and Saskatchewan attended services
conducted in Icelandic.</p>

<p>Unitarians have been large in influence but
not in numbers, and this has been markedly
true in the Great Plains. Figures from 1998
show between 8,000 and 9,000 congregational
members, of whom about 750 are in Canada.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Philip Hewett<lb/>
Unitarian Church of Vancouver, British Columbia</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Gudmundson, V. Emil. <title level="m">The Icelandic Unitarian Connection</title>.
Winnipeg: Wheatfield Press, 1984.</bibl> <bibl>Lyttle, Charles H.
<title level="m">Freedom Moves West</title>. Boston: Beacon Press, 1952.</bibl> <bibl>Tucker,
Cynthia Grant. <title level="m">Prophetic Sisterhood</title>. Boston: Beacon Press,
1990.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>