<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.arc.021">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Finnish Architecture</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Arnold R. Alanen</author>
<author>Carolyn Torma</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.arc.021</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Alanen, Arnold R.">Arnold R. Alanen</author> and <author n="Torma, Carolyn">Carolyn Torma</author>. <title level="a">"Finnish Architecture."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">79</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-12</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">FINNISH ARCHITECTURE</head>

<p>In common with the architecture of other ethnic
groups that settled in the Great Plains, Finnish
architecture included a mixture of old
and new: traditional Finnish uses and techniques
were often combined with American
building practices and needs. Distinctive Finnish
log construction techniques were only
manifested in areas with suitable timber resources,
which were quite rare on the Plains.</p>

<p>The earliest Finnish settlers were no different
from their fellow pioneer settlers who
chose to settle in the Great Plains: many lived
in "soddies" and dugouts until they could
construct more substantial residences. The
majority of structures were of frame construction
that followed American building
practices, and a few were of stone. In areas of
abundant timber, Finns built in the traditional
Nordic manner&#8211;with closely fitted,
horizontally stacked logs held together by
wooden pins and elegant corner-notching
systems&#8211;as they did throughout Finland and
the Great Lakes region of North America. Significantly,
no farm or ranch site was a direct
transplant of Finnish architecture to North
American soil; instead, contemporary building
methods and prefabricated materials and
features were commonly combined with Nordic
construction techniques. For a period of
time, there appears to have been some attempt
to lay out the buildings on farms and ranches
in open courtyard arrangements, a feature
common in some areas of Finnish migration.</p>

<p>One building traditional and unique to
Finns was the sauna; it flourished in a variety
of materials, including frame, earth, metal,
concrete block, railroad tie, and traditional
log. Early Finnish immigrants are known to
have heated their saunas with buffalo and cow
chips. In towns, the sauna was built as a communal
commercial building and revealed the
greatest variety in form and materials. Many
surviving family saunas are frame and followed
the traditional two-room layout for
bathing and changing purposes. A few adaptations
included attached chicken coops to keep
valuable poultry warm in the harsh Plains
winters. Evidence also survives of a few older
smoke (<hi rend="italic">savu</hi>) or chimneyless saunas.</p>

<p>Surveys conducted to date reveal that the
most important concentrations of traditional
log structures were built in the Black Hills of
South Dakota and the Little Belt Creek valley
of Montana, the latter area termed Korpivaara
(wilderness hill) by local Finns. These regions
provided pine, spruce, and cedar logs for
building construction. Less information is
available about Finnish architecture in the
Prairie Provinces, but Saskatchewan's New
Finland community is known for the number
of poplar or aspen log buildings constructed
by early immigrants.</p>

<p>The Buskala ranch, located in the Black
Hills, is an excellent example of Finnish log
architecture. Henry and Anna Buskala and
their two sons moved to the site in 1901 after
residing in several mining towns. The ranch
structures, most built prior to 1910, were organized
around two yards. The domestic
yard included a two-story house, the original
sauna, a privy, and a root cellar, while the
larger animal yard consisted of a cow and hay
barn, a calf barn/stable, and the corral. Hay
bins and a field hay barn (<hi rend="italic">lato</hi>) were situated
half a mile from the house, whereas the other
buildings show a mixture of American and
Finnish features; the lato not only was a very
rare architectural feature in the Great Plains,
but it was a direct transplant from Finland.
By 1918 the Buskalas had added a blacksmith
shop, a granary, and a new sauna to the building
ensemble. The rather large number of individual
structures, most of relatively modest
size, also reflected agricultural practices in
Finland.</p>

<p>Finnish settlement in Montana's Korpivaara
community followed a similar pattern:
after working in mining towns, some Finns
developed homesteads along the three-milelong
valley. Korpivaara includes evidence of
six ranches displaying sophisticated Nordic
building methods; many structures reveal frequent
use of the toothed-corner notch, a type
seldom found elsewhere in America. During
the early period of homesteading (1895–1915),
Finns typically constructed three or four small
log buildings and cleared six to thirty-five
acres of land for cultivation. During the subsequent
development phase (1915–30), the
cultivated acreage increased, a large dwelling
unit replaced the initial residence, and as
many as ten log buildings were added.</p>

<p>Farther north, the buildings in New Finland,
Saskatchewan, were constructed of poplar
logs cut from the Qu'Appelle River valley.
Because poplar proved difficult to shape and
work, chinking made of clay and straw was
used between the logs. The earliest buildings
included sod roofs covering a layer of birch
bark, while the houses often were distinguished
by their whitewashed exteriors and
interior walls. Locally available ocher was
mixed with kerosene or turpentine to make
red barn paint. Although many of New Finland's
log buildings have disappeared, several
farms and ranches&#8211;some of which now embrace
three or more sections of land&#8211;still display
at least one extant structure.</p>

<p>Churches and ethnic halls were common
features of many ethnic settlements on the
Plains. Finns constructed a variety of these
buildings, many in frame. Temperance and
workers halls and cooperative stores, mills,
creameries, and grain elevators were common
features in the Finnish settlement landscape.
Finns, along with their Nordic neighbors on
the Plains, were somewhat more prone than
other groups to develop cooperative businesses,
including threshing companies, which
have left no material remains. In rural South
Dakota Finnish Apostolic Lutheran churches
developed a new religious architecture, most
likely in response to the ecclesiastical independence
afforded them in America. Simple
and austere, the remaining early Apostolic
church at Savo Township, South Dakota, reflects
the simplicity and antiliturgical beliefs
of its members.</p>

<p>Finnish settlement in the Great Plains is
distinguished by its simultaneous maintenance
of tradition and adaptation to American
and Canadian architectural practices. In
most areas Finns replicated the pattern of
other immigrant groups: they put up buildings
identified as American or Canadian,
but beneath them lies an ethnic pattern of
communal settlement, economic interdependence,
religious and political affiliation,
and family association. In rural areas with
abundant timber, however, Finns constructed
buildings that reflected their Nordic background,
a practice that continued well into the
1920s. Today, the only Finnish architectural
tradition to survive is the ever-adaptable
sauna, which has moved from a singularly
ethnic tradition to a common international
fixture of wealthy homes, hotels, and spas.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">EUROPEAN AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ea.009">Finns</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Arnold R. Alanen<lb/>
Nebraska State Historical Society<lb/>
Carolyn Torma<lb/>
American Planning Association></signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Sanford, Dena Lynn. "Finnish Homesteads in Montana's
Little Belt Creek Valley: Korpivaara's Vernacular Building
Tradition." Master's Thesis, University of Oregon, 1991.</bibl>
<bibl>Sutyla, Charles M. <title level="m">The Finnish Sauna in Manitoba</title>. Ottawa:
Canadian Centre for Folk Culture Studies, National
Museums of Canada, 1977.</bibl> <bibl>Torma, Carolyn. "The Architecture
of Finnish Settlement in South Dakota." In <title level="m">Finns in North America</title>, edited by Michael G. Karni, Olavi
Koivukangas, and Edward W. Laine. Turku, Finland: Institute
for Migration, 1988: 99–119.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>