<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.na.054">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Kaws</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Benjamin Y. Dixon</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.na.054</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Dixon, Benjamin Y.">Benjamin Y. Dixon</author>. <title level="a">"Kaws."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">579-580</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-15</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">KAWS</head>

<p>The Kaw, or Kanza, Indians refer to themselves
collectively as the Kaw Nation. The
names Kaw and Kanza appear on the tribe's
national seal, but Kaw is the identity used
by members. Kaw means "Wind People." The
Kaws are part of the Dhegiha branch of the
Central Siouan-speaking peoples, a group that
includes Quapaws, Osages, Omahas, and Poncas.
According to their histories, these tribes
once lived together along or near the lower
Ohio Valley. They began to migrate westward
around 1300 <hi rend="smallcaps">A.D.</hi>, and by the 1700s the Kaws
were firmly situated in present northeastern
Kansas and northwestern Missouri.</p>

<p>From the late eighteenth century until the
late 1820s, the Kaws, numbering about 1,500,
lived in a single village near present Manhattan,
Kansas. Their territory extended throughout
most of the Kansas Valley and the lower
reaches of its tributaries from about the Delaware
River west to the Solomon and Smoky
Hill Rivers. Within this core, the Kaws exercised
nearly total territorial control. Their
hunting range extended west to the upper Republican
River and south to the saline plains of
the present Kansas-Oklahoma border.</p>

<p>The Kaws' subsistence operated on an annual
cycle of hunting, horticulture, raiding,
and trading. Beginning in April, Kaw women
planted corn, beans, pumpkins, melons, and
squash in small fields around the village. They
also gathered nuts, berries, roots, tubers, and
wood in the riparian forest adjacent to the
Kansas and Blue Rivers. Kaw males pastured
their horses on nearby upland prairie and
hunted (mostly elk and deer) along the Kansas
River. After planting ended in early May, the
Kaws left for their annual summer bison hunt.
Along the way to the bison grounds, they
hunted deer and elk, and small war parties
frequently left to raid Pawnee villages. The
Kaws primarily hunted along the middle Solomon,
Smoky Hill, and Arkansas Rivers, where
vast herds of bison sought water in summer.
They returned to their village in mid-August to
harvest their crops. In winter, the Kaws left
their village again and traveled to the woodlands
along the Missouri River in present
northeastern Kansas and northwestern Missouri.
There they scattered into small parties
and hunted beaver, deer, elk, turkey, and other
smaller game. The furs from these animals
were exchanged for goods from French and
American traders who regularly traveled the
Missouri River. During this season, Kaw war
parties raided Otoe, Iowa, Sauk, Fox, and Missouria
villages. The Kaws reconvened at their
village in mid-March.</p>

<p>This subsistence pattern also provided the
Kaws with their material culture (dress, tools,
utensils, weapons, and housing). Kaw dress,
for instance, consisted of moccasins and leggings
(made from deerskins), a breechcloth
and girdle (acquired through trade), and a
blanket or bison robe. Male warriors often
wore necklaces of animal claws or of shells,
beads, and metal ornaments (acquired through
trade), and they carried a wire apparatus to keep
their arms, chins, eyebrows, and scalp plucked
(except for a strip of hair on the top of their
heads). Both men and women used vermilion to
dye their hair.</p>

<p>Circular earth lodges were the most common
form of village housing. A lodge measured
from thirty to sixty feet in diameter and
housed an average of two families (or about
ten persons). Each lodge consisted of an outer
ring of wooden posts and four taller central
posts that were then covered with a frame of
stick or twig bundles, over which they laid
grass or reed mats, tree bark, and earth. Inside
a lodge they maintained a central fire pit (and
a hole in the roof's center for smoke to escape)
as well as storage pits for dried corn, beans,
and other foods. When the Kaws were on the
hunt, they lived in portable skin-covered tipis.</p>

<p>Kaw society was patrilineal, and it was divided
into two halves, or moieties, each composed
of eight clans, or gentes (consisting of
several families each), whose members descended
from a common ancestor. Politically,
the Kaws were organized around a loose confederation
headed by several chiefs. There
were five civil chiefs, drawn from each of the
five leading gentes. There were also several war
chiefs, established warriors who ruled in matters
of war. Chiefs were elected by a common
council of the people because of their demonstrated
wisdom, bravery, and generosity. Office
was for life and succession was hereditary.
Despite the chieftainships, usually no solid
ruling authority was recognized. Most matters
were still decided through common council,
and some degree of factionalism was characteristic
of Kaw politics.</p>

<p>In 1825 the U.S. government convinced the
Kaws to cede their land and placed them on a
reservation in present northern Kansas. For
the next two decades, the Kaws were hemmed
in by thousands of relocated Indians from the
eastern United States. The influx of emigrant
Indians and the expansion of the fur trade
depleted small game in the region, and missionaries
and government employees on the
reservation introduced disease. The Kaws intensified
their bison hunting, raided enemies
with increasing frequency, and stole crops and
animals from neighboring reservations and
white settlements.</p>

<p>The Kaws maintained their population of
1,500 persons until midcentury, after which
their numbers plummeted. The U.S. government
restricted the Kaws to progressively
smaller reservations (in 1846, 1859, and 1873).
When officials opened Kansas Territory in
1854, settlers pushed the bison farther west,
depleted grass and wood, peddled whiskey,
and brought more disease to the tribe. Starvation
was chronic, and frequent outbreaks of
smallpox, cholera, and other illnesses continued
to plague the tribe. When the Kaws were
removed to Indian Territory in 1873, they numbered
500. By 1900 barely 200 full-blooded
Kaws remained. Tragedy extended beyond
death. Since religious knowledge was preserved
within each gente, the demise of entire
gente populations meant the loss of beliefs and
customs. By the early twentieth century, much
understanding of Kaw society, religion, and
history was lost forever.</p>

<p>Congress dissolved the last Kaw reservation
in 1902, and the lands were divided into individual
allotments. Four years later the former
reservation became part of Kay County, Oklahoma.
Today, many Kaw descendants still reside
in Kay County. According to the 1997
tribal enrollment, there are 2,269 Kaw Nation
members. The last Kaw full-blood, William A.
Mehojah Sr., died in Omaha, Nebraska, on
April 23, 2000.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Benjamin Y. Dixon<lb/>
University of Oklahoma</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Unrau, William E. <title level="m">The Kansa Indians, A History of the
Wind People, 1673–1873</title>. Norman: University of Oklahoma
Press, 1971.</bibl> <bibl>Wedel, Waldo R. "The Kansa Indians." <title level="j">Transactions
of the Kansas Academy of Science</title> 49 (1946) 1–35.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>