<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.fol.024 SYSTEM "egp.fol.024.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fol.024">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Humor</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Roger L. Welsch</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2009</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fol.024</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2009</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2009 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Welsch, Roger L.">Roger L. Welsch</author>. <title level="a">"Humor."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">304-305</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-16</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">HUMOR</head>

<figure n="egp.fol.024" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Example of Great Plains humor, Yates Center, Kansas, 2001</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Without question, the most common form of
folk and popular humor in the Great Plains,
and in North America in general, especially
in recent decades, is the joke. The form of
the joke changed dramatically through the
nineteenth and twentieth centuries, the emphasis
falling away from style, narrative, and
language, sometimes lengthy and humorous
throughout, to an almost total reliance on
a "punch line," a surprising last line without
which the story has little or no humor.
That very characteristic is itself parodied and
thereby showcased in the so-called shaggy-dog
story, in which the requisite punch line is absent
or is an execrable pun, less funny than
painful. That is, this distortion of the prevailing
joke form clarifies and accentuates its
usual form. Indeed, at the turn of the millennium,
the predominant form of American
joke is little more than a punch line ("Did
you hear about the blond who . . . ?") or a
"riddling" joke, a curious question with a surprise
or punning answer, both provided by the
joke teller: "What's Polack surf 'n' turf ? Carp
and kielbasa. How many psychiatrists does it
take to change a light bulb? Only one, but the
bulb has to want to be changed." Plains peoples
participate fully in every dimension of
humor fashion, from ethnic slurs like the
above (which, however, almost inevitably have
evolved from esoteric expressions within the
derogated ethnic group to become a flag of
internal identity and pride) to political slanders,
sexist barbs, and topical commentary.</p>

<p>It is impossible to quantify humor in degree,
quality, or quantity, but it is suggested
here that the Great Plains is distinctive in the
cultivation of at least two forms of the joke:
the tall tale and the form that is here called
"civil ribaldry." Both forms have their longest
and strongest traditions in the rural Plains.</p>

<p>The tall tale is of course an ancient art,
widely spread throughout the world. Alice
Fletcher recorded the form during her early
observations of the Omaha tribe, and non-
Native invaders carried the form with them
on horseback and in wagon trains. The true
tall tale is not a tale at all, rarely having a
narrative element. Nor, strictly speaking, is it a
lie, since its exaggerations are so utterly preposterous
that no one of normal intelligence
or humor could conceivably mistake a true
tall tale for a legitimate report—for example,
"It was so cold folks went to church just to
hear about hell; . . . so dry I saw two cottonwood
trees chasing a dog; . . . too windy to
load rocks."</p>

<p>Nor are such complaints to be mistaken as
true laments. The faces of persons reciting tall
tales like the above actually reveal a kind of
perverse pride. Indeed, one could legitimately
consider them traditional brags: "Living on
the Plains is like being hanged . . . the initial
jolt is fairly sudden but after you hang there a
while, you kinda get used to it" is a manner of
bringing attention to one's own courage and
strength even while modestly denigrating the
geography in question. "Modestly" because
the exaggerations and extensions are largely
true, if slightly overdrawn! While the tall tale
is not unique to the Plains by any stretch of
the imagination (so to speak), the form may
well have flourished there as nowhere else.
This may be because the dramatic extremes of
the Plains have driven the boaster to ever
greater&#8211;and funnier&#8211;extremes to match, yet
outdo, the truth.</p>

<p>The tall tale is nurtured primarily in rural
contexts but finds wider distribution through
press releases from elusive tall-tale "contests."
(Innocent souls sometimes try to organize
formal tall-tale "contests," which almost inevitably
fail because the true tall-tale contest
never happens and is itself a fiction.) The traditional
tall tale, however, falls far short of the
shock value demanded by modern folk and
popular culture humor and is appreciated
only as a quaint, even childish form.</p>

<p>Far less well known to the general American
public, and more clearly a Plains survival,
is a humor type that lacks a formal label but
may be called "civil ribaldry." These jokes take
the form of extraordinarily subtle, distinctly
rural narratives. While there is a punch line,
unlike the riddling joke, for example, "civil
ribaldry" does contain a clear narrative element.
The stories, while slightly off-color, can
be, and are, told in mixed company, even with
children present, without much danger of being
understood by the innocent.</p>

<p>Two examples recently collected in the vicinity
of Dannebrog, Nebraska, are as follows:</p>

<p rend="indented1">You'll never believe this, Rog, but yesterday
I was on the gravel between here and
Grand Island and I spotted Kenny L. out
disking his fields on his old John Deere . . .
and he was stark naked from the waist
down. Not a stitch of clothes on below the
belt, not even underwear. So, I stopped at
the edge of the field and waited until he
came back down the row. I waved him
down and asked him, "What's this, naked
from the waist down like that, Kenny?" He
replied, "Yesterday I worked out here on
the tractor all day without a shirt on and
came home with a stiff neck. This is the
wife's idea . . ." (related by Eric Nielsen).</p>

<p>Only a few weeks ago I entered the Dannebrog
tavern and found an old friend sitting
morosely at the bar. I asked him what the
problem was and this is what he said:</p>

<p rend="idented1">I can't rightly say for sure. You know that
black mare I was trying to sell? Well, a guy
offered me $500 for her, but he said he
needed to have a 15 percent discount for
paying cash. Well, that was all right by me,
but I'm not too good with ciphering, so I
couldn't for the life of me figure out 15 percent
of $500. So, I took a quick run over to
the schoolteacher's house, knocked at her
door, and asked her, "Now, if I was to give
you $500 for something but need a 15 percent
discount for paying cash, how much
would you be taking off?" And she said,
quick as you can think, "Everything but
my socks and earrings." Rog, I'm still trying
to figure that one out (name of narrator
withheld).</p>

<closer>
<signed>Roger L. Welsch<lb/>
Dannebrog, Nebraska</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Fletcher, Alice C. <title level="m">Indian Story and Song from North America</title>.
Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1995.</bibl> <bibl>Welsch,
Roger. <title level="m">Shingling the Fog and Other Plains Lies</title>. Lincoln:
University of Nebraska Press, 1980.</bibl> <bibl>Welsch, Roger, and
Linda K. Welsch. <title level="m">Catfish at the Pump: Humor and the Frontier</title>. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1986.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>