<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.mus.037">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Orbison, Roy (1936-1988)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Burt Kaufman</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.mus.037</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Kaufman, Burt">Burt Kaufman</author>. <title level="a">"Orbison, Roy (1936-1988)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">545</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-02</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">ORBISON, ROY (1936-1988)</head>
<figure n="egp.mus.037" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Roy Orbison</figDesc>
</figure>      
    
<p>Roy Kelton Orbison was born in Vernon,
Texas, on April 23, 1936, and grew up in nearby
Wink (population 1,000), where his father
worked in the oil fields. Surrounded by the
sounds of western swing and honky-tonk, he
began singing for audiences at the age of ten.
His first band, the Wink Westerners, played
pop songs and western standards around West
Texas before adapting to the times and, as the
Teen Kings, moving into rockabilly. This was a
short-lived phase for Orbison, who turned to
ballads after 1958 and, recording for Monument,
moved into the ranks of leading stars
alongside Elvis Presley and Buddy Holly.</p>

<p>Between 1958 and 1964 a Roy Orbison bigbeat
ballad was rarely absent from the record
charts. His often melancholy songs, including
"Only the Lonely," "Running Scared," "Crying,"
"It's Over," and "Oh, Pretty Woman,"
sung in an operatic style that often crescendoed
to a high note, were standard accompaniments
to teenage angst. Working with
producer Fred Foster, Orbison pioneered the
use of violin backing and abandoned the standard
"verse-chorus" song structure in favor
of a more complex symphonic style. He was
equally popular in the United Kingdom as in
the United States, and when he toured the uk
in 1963 with the Beatles, who idolized him,
Orbison was the main act.</p>

<p>Orbison's career plummeted after 1964, as
hard rock displaced the softer, more sentimental
songs of the early 1960s. A move to
mgm did nothing to rescue declining sales,
and, more drastically, Roy's life was struck by
tragedy: in 1966 his first wife, Claudette, was
killed in a motorcycle accident, and, just over
two years later, his two oldest sons, Tony and
Roy, died in a house fire while Roy was on tour
in Europe.</p>

<p>By 1970 Orbison was virtually forgotten in
the United States, though he continued to
turn out albums for <hi rend="smallcaps">MGM</hi> and later Mercury.
Married again in 1969 to a German, Barbara
Welhoner, he spent more and more of his time
in Europe, where he was still a popular figure.
But his mystique was enduring: his black
clothes, black shades, and motionless presence
on stage still captivated audiences. He continued
to tour, playing small towns like the
ones he had known in his youth on the Plains.</p>

<p>Moreover, a newer generation of rock artists
had not forgotten Roy Orbison. Bruce Springsteen
introduced him at his induction into the
Rock and Roll Hall of Fame in 1987, and sales of
his record "In Dreams" revived after it was
featured in David Lynch's bizarre movie <title>Blue Velvet</title> (1986). Further new exposure came in
the <hi rend="smallcaps">HBO</hi> special <title>Roy Orbison and Friends: A
Black and White Night</title>, in which he was joined
and honored by Springsteen, Elvis Costello,
Bonnie Raitt, and other rock luminaries whose
careers had been so influenced by him. Orbison's
career rose to a new zenith in 1988,
when he recorded with Bob Dylan, George
Harrison, Tom Petty, and Jeff Lynne as a member
of The Traveling Wilburys. His new solo
album, <title>Mystery Girl</title>, shot up the charts in early
1989, but by that time the gentle Texan with the
ethereal voice had died on December 6, 1988,
in Hendersonville, Tennessee.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Burt Kaufman<lb/>
Oakland, California</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Clayson, Alan. <title level="m">Only the Lonely: Roy Orbison's Life and Legacy</title>. New York: St. Martin's Press, 1990.</bibl> <bibl>Kaufman, Burt.
"Spotlight on Roy Orbison." <title level="j">Rockin' 50's</title> 31 (1991): 8–16.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>