<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ag.043">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Goats</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Kenneth C. Dagel</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ag.043</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Dagel, Kenneth C.">Kenneth C. Dagel</author>. <title level="a">"Goats."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">46</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-12-18</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">GOATS</head>

<p>It is safe to say that goat production has never
been a major enterprise in the United States
or Canada. Goats can be generally classified
based largely on their function, including fiber
types (Angora and Cashmere), dairy types
(Alpine breeds plus Nubian), those kept primarily
for meat production (Spanish or brush
goats, and more recently the Boer), and those
kept as laboratory animals or pets (Dwarf or
Pygmy).</p>

<p>In the United States the goat population
reached its high point around 1965, when Angoras
numbered approximately six million.
The termination of an incentive program,
coupled with a declining demand for Mohair,
has decimated the industry in recent years,
with numbers in 1998 at less than one million.
There has, however, been an increase in the
number of goats kept for meat production.
This increase has been fueled by a need to
replace the Angora for use in grazing management
and the identification of a growing ethnic
market for goat meat. Recent immigrants
from goat-consuming regions (such as the
Middle East) to the Prairie Provinces, for example,
have stimulated the goat meat industry
there. About one-third of Canada's goat population
is now in the Prairie Provinces. In
the United States it is expected that the major
concentration of goats on the Plains will continue
to be in the Edwards Plateau and adjacent
regions of Texas, where they are an important
component of the grazing system and
make a significant contribution to ranching
income.</p>

<p>The goat, along with certain game species,
represents the best ecological fit in the semiarid
regions of the Great Plains, and the potential
for their exploitation in this region is
great. However, this potential is not likely to
be realized unless some serious problems can
be solved. These include fencing, predation,
and grazing policy on federal lands. Finally, if
these regions were used to their potential to
produce meat or fiber from goats, the supplies
would far exceed present known market outlets
or demands.</p>

<p>The use of goats in the larger Great Plains
region will likely be restricted to smaller private
landholdings or to strategic uses for vegetative
management. There is a great potential
for use of the goat (and to a lesser extent
sheep) for reducing fire hazards in forest areas
by removing a part of the fuel base, reducing
vegetative competition in reforestation efforts
(especially conifer forests), and controlling
certain noxious plant species, such as leafy
spurge (<hi rend="italic">Euphorbia esula L</hi>.).</p>

<closer>
<signed>Maurice Shelton<lb/>
Texas Agricultural Experiment Station<lb/>
San Angelo, Texas</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Shelton, Maurice. "Goat Production." In <title level="m">Encyclopedia of Agricultural Science</title>, edited by Charles J. Arntzen. San
Diego: Academic Press, 1994.</bibl> <bibl>Walker, John W., S. L. Kronberg,
S. L. Al-Rowaily, and N. E. West. "Comparison of
Sheep and Goat Preferences for Leafy Spurge." <title level="j">Journal of Range Management</title> 47 (1994): 429–34.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>