<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ag.027">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Dryland Farming</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Michael J. Grant</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ag.027</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Grant, Michael J.">Michael J. Grant</author>. <title level="a">"Dryland Farming."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">42-43</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-12-10</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">DRYLAND FARMING</head>

<p>Dryland farming is practiced in the semiarid
American Great Plains and Canadian Prairies
whereby the soil is cultivated in ways that conserve
precious moisture. For generations European
Americans coming to the Great Plains
of North America labored to squeeze the most
out of a land often short on rainfall.</p>

<p>In the late nineteenth century various factors
combined to make the Plains a more attractive
agricultural base. The "closing of the
American frontier in 1890" (according to the
Bureau of the Census), rising land prices, and
subsequent fears of a food shortage led to
a drive to settle new lands. The populist unrest
of the 1890s convinced some that lower
farming costs on cheaper lands could support
a prosperous class of pioneers. In the United
States, before World War I, railroads, banks,
grain elevators, and businesses used modern
advertising methods to attract farmers to
new lands in the Plains. In the Canadian Prairies
the government actively encouraged settlers
to semiarid lands as well. Higher grain
prices, and increased land costs in more
humid areas, propelled thousands of early-twentieth-century pioneers into the Great
Plains to attempt dryland farming.</p>

<p>Dryland farming theories varied, but at the
heart of the publicity were claims that farmers
could cultivate the land to capture and conserve
the scarce moisture in the Plains soil. It
was billed as a "climate-free" system of agriculture.
Dryland farmers used deep plowing
in the fall to enable grain roots to use the
moisture, harrowing after rains to allegedly
conserve moisture under the top soil, packing
the subsoil to prevent infiltration, and leaving
fields fallow in the summer. Drought-resistant
grains, such as Turkey Red wheat and sorghums,
were promoted. Without conclusive
proof, supporters publicized dryland-farming
methods as scientifically feasible. Proponents
such as Hardy Webster Campbell of South Dakota
and the Dry Farming Congress assured
settlers that the western Plains and Prairies
could be broken and profitably farmed using
this system. In 1909 and 1910 Congress passed
the Enlarged Homestead Acts, giving each settler
320 acres of free land on which to build a
dry-farming empire. Marginal areas in North
Dakota, eastern Montana, and the western
Southern Plains exploded with settlers, cattle,
and acreage brought into cultivation.</p>

<p>Dry-farming methods offered a mixed performance
after World War I. During the early
1920s some farm experts believed that, despite
the harsh climate and irregular rains, farmers
could use drought-resistant wheat strains, relatively
cheap operating costs (enabled by new
machines), and large-scale acreages to make
profits. However, after World War I the hazards
of pushing conventional farming into the
semiarid zones of the Plains became increasingly
apparent. Periodic drought and low
grain prices bankrupted thousands of dryland
farmers. Up to three-quarters of those who
homesteaded in some areas of the Northern
Plains before World War I left their claims by
the early 1920s. The ensuing drought and depression
of the 1930s were also disastrous as
thousands more farm families, lured by the
promise of cheap lands and quick profits in
the 1910s and 1920s, were forced off the land.
Many of these farms were simply deserted. In
Garfield County, for example, in the rangeland
and dry farming country of eastern Montana,
the population dropped from 5,368 in
1920 to 4,252 in 1930 and 2,641 in 1940, and it
has been going down ever since.</p>

<p>Today, much of the land opened for dryland
farming before World War I has reverted
back to grazing or has been added to the national
grassland system. However, adaptive
farm families on large acreages using modern
machinery and methods can still reap
large crops of wheat, even in years affected by
drought. Those who have the savings, capital,
and are supported by government agricultural
programs can manage some profits and stability.
Despite the marginal environment and
fluctuating grain prices, dryland farming still
supports Plains farm families, but their numbers
are dwindling.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Michael J. Grant<lb/>
Lincoln, Nebraska</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Hargreaves, Mary W. M. <title level="m">Dry Farming in the Northern
Great Plains, 1900–1925</title>. Cambridge: Harvard University
Press, 1957.</bibl> <bibl>Hargreaves, Mary W. M. <title level="m">Dry Farming in the
Northern Great Plains: Years of Readjustment, 1920–1990</title>.
Lawrence: University Press of Kansas, 1993.</bibl> <bibl>Jones, David
C. <title level="m">Empire of Dust: Settling and Abandoning the Prairie Dry
Belt</title>. Edmonton: University of Alberta Press, 1987.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>