<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.lt.009">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Cather, Willa (1873-1947)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Matthew Hokom</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.lt.009</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Hokom, Matthew">Matthew Hokom</author>. <title level="a">"Cather, Willa (1873-1947)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">475-476</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-23</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">CATHER, WILLA (1873-1947)</head>
<figure n="egp.lt.009" rend="granted" type="noclick">
<figDesc>Photograph of Willa Cather</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>In her essay "My First Novels [There Were
Two]," Willa Cather recalls a New York critic
who responded to <title level="m">O Pioneers!</title> by claiming, "I
simply don't care a damn what happens in
Nebraska, no matter who writes about it."
One of Cather's foremost achievements has
been to make readers care about the "distinctly
d&#233;class&#233;" Nebraska and the Great
Plains. Indeed, Cather's own complex ties to
the Great Plains underlie much of her best
writing.</p>

<p>A quintessential Great Plains writer, Cather
lived in Nebraska only thirteen years but was
later to claim that her deepest feelings were
rooted in her childhood ties to this place.
Born in the Back Creek Valley of Virginia on
December 7, 1873, Cather migrated with her
relatives to Red Cloud, Nebraska, in 1883. Her
first experience of "a country bare as a piece of
sheet iron" was a traumatic one, memorably
retold through the eyes of Jim Burden in <title level="m">My &#193;ntonia</title>. After a brief but fierce struggle,
Cather grew to love the land and the people
she came to know. As an adult she recalled her
early years on "the Divide" as among the most
important and fulfilling periods of her life. It
is also true that a young woman as intelligent,
ambitious, and unconventional as Cather felt
compelled to explore the world outside Red
Cloud, and as soon as she graduated from
high school she left her hometown to attend
the University of Nebraska. After six years in
Lincoln, during which she received her undergraduate
degree and established a national
reputation as a theater and music critic for the
local papers, Cather headed east.</p>

<p>She moved to Pittsburgh in 1896 and worked
as a journalist, editor, and teacher while also
actively publishing short stories. In 1906 she
joined the staff of <title level="j">McClure's Magazine</title> and began
a residence in New York City. She stayed
with <title level="j">McClure's</title> for six years, writing her first
novel, <title level="m">Alexander's Bridge</title> (1912), while also
serving as managing editor. Convinced by
Sarah Orne Jewett that she could not serve two
masters, Cather quit her job at <title level="j">McClure's</title> and
embarked on a career as a professional novelist.
Over the next eleven years she wrote five
novels set, completely or in part, in the Great
Plains&#8211;<title level="m">O Pioneers!</title> (1913), <title level="m">The Song of the Lark</title>
(1915), <title level="m">My &#193;ntonia</title> (1918), <title level="m">One of Ours</title> (1922),
and <title level="m">A Lost Lady</title> (1923). After the publication of
A Lost Lady, Cather turned to other settings in
her next four novels. However, late in her career,
with the publication of <title level="m">Lucy Gayheart</title>
(1935) and her best collection of short stories,
<title level="m">Obscure Destinies</title> (1932), she returned to Nebraska
for her artistic material.</p>

<p>Since her death in New York on April 24,
1947, Cather's reputation has grown with an
increased recognition of the complexity and
allusive depth of her work. No longer classified
as a "mere" regional writer, she is now
viewed as a regionalist in the tradition of Jewett,
Twain, and Faulkner. Her writing provides
fertile ground for feminist, lesbian, and gender
critics, while the deceptive simplicity of
her prose conceals a host of biographical, historical,
political, biblical, and literary references. With the recent inclusion of <title level="m">A Lost Lady</title>
in <title level="m">Encyclopedia Britannica's</title> list of great books
and the adaptation of <title level="m">The Song of the Lark</title> for
Masterpiece Theater's American Collection
series, Cather is now considered not only a
Great Plains but a great American writer.</p>

<p><ref target="http://cather.unl.edu/">Willa Cather Archive</ref> website.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Matthew Hokom<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Rosowski, Susan J. <title level="m">The Voyage Perilous: Willa Cather's Romanticism</title>.
Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1986.</bibl>
<bibl>Urgo, Joseph R. <title level="m">Willa Cather and the Myth of American Migration</title>. Champaign: University of Illinois Press, 1995.</bibl>
<bibl>Woodress, James. <title level="m">Willa Cather: A Literary Life</title>. Lincoln:
University of Nebraska Press, 1987.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>