<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.afam.045">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">West, Cornel (b. 1953)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>D. A. Masolo</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.afam.045</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>
 
<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Masolo, D. A.">D. A. Masolo</author>. <title level="a">"West, Cornel (b. 1953)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">23-24</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-12-08</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">WEST, CORNEL (b. 1953)</head>
<figure n="egp.afam.045" rend="granted" type="noclick">
<figDesc>Cornel West in 2008</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Theologian, public intellectual, and formerly
professor of Afro-American Studies and religion
at Harvard University, Cornel West is
also highly regarded as a philosopher. In July
2002 West returned to Princeton University,
where he received his doctorate, as Class of
1943 University Professor of Religion. Part of
a group of influential contemporary African
American scholars, Cornel West strives to
close those gaps he perceives in the work of
the older generation of African American intellectuals
and political activists. This accounts
for the eclecticism of his work and for
his mix of academic scholarship with activist
immersion in the matters of everyday life or,
as he calls it, the human condition.</p>

<p>The grandson of a Baptist minister, West
was born in Tulsa, Oklahoma, on June 2, 1953,
and brought up under the religious influence
of the Baptist Church. His religious upbringing
opened his eyes early to the theme of justice
in an unjust world. The marginalization
of Native Americans and African Americans
to the racially and economically defined periphery
of Oklahoma provided him with the
existentialist notions of tragedy in the American
social-political landscape.</p>

<p>By the time West arrived at Harvard in 1970,
he was already an emboldened and eloquent
young man who felt no restraint in expressing
his opposition to injustice and criticizing the
ideas of preceding leaders of the black movement.
West has been particularly critical of
W. E. B. Du Bois, who had argued that the way
for African Americans to break out of oppression
and marginalization was to embrace the
values of white America. At Harvard, West
majored in religion while also studying philosophy.
Graduating in 1973, he pursued a
doctoral degree in philosophy at Princeton
where he came under the influence of Richard
Rorty and the new trajectory of pragmatism.
Two of West's works, <title level="m">Post-Analytic Philosophy</title>
(1985) and <title level="m">The American Evasion of Philosophy</title>
(1989), reflect Rorty's belief that the dominant
American academic practice operates, at best,
with cynicism about the social conditions of
the nation and evades the real problems at the
heart of American society. In the latter work,
West explores the history of American pragmatism
stretching from Ralph Waldo Emerson
to Richard Rorty as a response to the social
problematic of American society. He
returns to these themes frequently in his later
writings, notably in <title level="m">Keeping Faith: Philosophy
and Race in America</title> (1993).</p>

<p>But West's wide popularity comes mainly
from his speeches and writings for a general
audience, themselves the result of his mission,
like his mentor Rorty's, to see philosophy
break free from the privileged confines of the
academy. Philosophy, in his view, must engage
the social tragedies of suffering and despair
faced everyday by those who are alienated
from society and dispossessed of their fundamental
material, social, and spiritual rights.</p>

<p>The greatest influence on West, as he himself
admits, is Anton Pavlovich Chekhov. Like
Chekhov, the Russian physician and writer,
West steps outside his exclusive professional
engagements in order to embrace the plight of
everyday folks by using the privileges of his
own public image and visibility. West's concern
is first and foremost with the shifting
yet unending bondage of African Americans&#8211;
from the hot sun of the plantations in a quasifeudal
system to the proletariat conditions of
an industrialized America. It is this condition
that, in his view, brings forth the idea of community
and the necessity of oppositional intellectual
groupings within the academy.</p>

<closer>
<signed>D. A. Masolo<lb/>
University of Louisville</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Gordon, Lewis R. <title level="m">Existentia Africana: Understanding Africana
Existential Thought</title>. New York: Routledge, 2000.</bibl>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>