<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.fil.055 SYSTEM "egp.fil.055.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fil.055">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main"><hi rend="italic">The Plow That Broke the Plains</hi></title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Michael W. Schuyler</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fil.055</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Schuyler, Michael W.">Michael W. Schuyler</author>. <title level="a">"<hi rend="italic">The Plow That Broke the Plains</hi>."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">276-277</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-12</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main"><hi rend="italic">THE PLOW THAT BROKE THE PLAINS</hi></head>

<figure n="egp.fil.055" rend="granted">
<figDesc>The Plow That Broke the Plains</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>In May 1936, as the people of the Great Plains
battled against the combined effects of over-production, drought, and depression, the federal
government released <title>The Plow That Broke the Plains</title>. The film was part of a massive campaign
by the federal government to convince
farmers and ranchers that the search for
windfall profits in the West had resulted in
misplaced settlement, misuse of the land, and
ultimately the great dust storms that ravaged
the Great Plains in the 1930s.</p>

<p>In 1935 Rexford Tugwell, the head of the
Resettlement Administration, recruited Pare
Lorentz to produce a film that would explain
the causes of the Dust Bowl. The film also
made a strong case for resettling destitute
farmers, for retiring marginal farmland from
production, and for restoring grasslands in the
West. The twenty-eight-minute film, which
cost $19,260 to produce, included a highly
emotional musical score by Virgil Thomson
and was narrated by Thomas Chalmers. Although
the movie industry complained about
competition from a government-produced
film, <title>The Plow That Broke the Plains</title> was shown
in independent theaters, school auditoriums,
and other public meeting places throughout
the country. It was seen by 10 million people in
1937 alone and would become one of the most
widely viewed films in American history. The
film is still shown to audiences throughout the
country to explain the economic and ecological
disasters that struck the Plains during the
1930s. The film was, however, instantly controversial.
It has since become part of an enduring
historical debate about the past and the future
development of the Great Plains.</p>

<p>The heart of the controversy about the film,
then and now, was the interpretation by Lorentz
and other New Deal farm experts that
much of the Great Plains was unsuited for agriculture.
While soft music plays in the background
and scenes of acres of lush, billowy
grassland appear on the screen, the film's narrator
explains how beautiful the unspoiled
Plains had been before the period of European
American settlement. Then, as the music
grows louder with increasingly harsh tones,
the film shows the movement of cattlemen
onto the Plains, the coming of railroads and
land speculators, and finally waves of homesteaders
and farmers with horses and gang
plows breaking up Great Plains grasslands.
The film then moves to the World War I era,
when farmers enjoyed high prices and seemingly
unlimited prosperity. As the music
reaches a feverish pitch, the film shows giant
plows, often lined up side by side in rows,
plowing under millions of additional acres of
grassland. Then, after the screen goes momentarily
black, the film shifts to the 1930s. The
music becomes dirgelike; the Plains are now
pictured as a desolate wasteland. A steer's skull,
bleached white by the sun, is shown wedged in
the dirt. Poor farmers, their homes nearly covered
by mounds of dust, are shown running to
ramshackle houses to escape the relentless dust
storms that sweep across the Plains.</p>

<p>While many contemporaries blamed farmers
and ranchers for exploiting, without regard
for the environment, the resources of the
West to their own advantage, Lorentz focused
the blame for the ecological disaster on mechanized
agriculture rather than unthinking
greed. Still, the message of the film was clear:
the great plow-up was a terrible mistake. At
the end of the film, as thousands of refugees
flee the Plains, the narrator concludes that 40
million acres of land have been totally ruined
and another 200 million acres badly damaged.
The film ends with a troubling question:
"What is America going to do about it?"</p>

<p>While the film was generally hailed as a cinematic
triumph, many contemporaries questioned
Lorentz's understanding of the history
of the Great Plains. First, critics pointed out
that Lorentz had deemphasized the impact of
the drought and had exaggerated the importance
of agricultural expansion to explain the
origins of the Dust Bowl. Second, critics contended
that Lorentz had created a false impression
that the entire Great Plains area was a
Dust Bowl. In their view Lorentz had overlooked
the diversity and vitality of the Great
Plains economy and had undervalued the
quality of farm life, even in the Dust Bowl
areas, to make the case that substantial areas
of the Great Plains should be turned back to
grassland. Finally, although Lorentz had generally
pictured farmers as victims of modern
technology, his critics insisted that he had presented
a negative and unfair image of Great
Plains farmers, who were, they argued, conscientious
stewards of the land. The film's critics
insisted that the Plains was suitable for agriculture
in spite of the dust storms and that
prosperity would return to the farm economy
with the return of rain.</p>

<p>It can be argued that the most important
impact of the film was that it focused discussion
on the future of the Great Plains and underscored
the need for a comprehensive soil
conservation program. The film, however, obviously
did not settle the question about
whether land in the Great Plains region, and
particularly in the western Plains, should be
used for agriculture. The same questions that
were debated in the 1930s are still debated today,
particularly during periods of drought
and low farm prices.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">MUSIC</hi>: <ref n="egp.mus.045">Thomson, Virgil</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT</hi>: <ref n="egp.pe.022">Dust Bowl</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Michael W. Schuyler<lb/>
University of Nebraska at Kearney</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Hurt, R. Douglas. <title level="m">The Dust Bowl: An Agricultural and Social History</title>. Chicago: Nelson Hall, 1981.</bibl> <bibl>Snyder, Ralph.
<title level="m">Pare Lorentz and the Documentary Film</title>. Norman: University
of Oklahoma Press, 1968.</bibl> <bibl>Worster, Donald. <title level="m">Dust Bowl: The Southern Plains in the 1930s</title>. New York: Oxford University
Press, 1979.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>