<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.art.026">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Gilder, Robert (1856-1940)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Martha H. Kennedy</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.art.026</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Kennedy, Martha H.">Martha H. Kennedy</author>. <title level="a">"Gilder, Robert (1856-1940)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">117</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-15</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">GILDER, ROBERT (1856-1940)</head>

<p>Robert Fletcher Gilder once identified himself
as a journeyman printer by trade, despite the
fact that he had a successful career as a professional
journalist in Omaha, Nebraska, and
achieved lasting recognition as an artist and
archaeologist. He painted many Nebraska and
western landscapes that were admired, exhibited,
and collected during his lifetime.
Gilder's paintings capture many aspects of the
beauty and subtle variety of the Plains landscape
and contribute notably to the region's
artistic legacy.</p>

<p>Born October 6, 1856, the son of a minister,
in Flushing, Long Island, New York, Gilder
attended public schools in Newark and New
Jersey and the Gunnery School in Washington,
Connecticut. He studied painting under
August Will, a Jersey City painter of urban
scenes who directed a school in New York
City. After arriving in Omaha in 1887, Gilder
worked at the <title level="j">Omaha World Herald</title>, first as a
typesetter, then as a reporter and editor for the
newspaper during a career of nearly twentyfive
years before he retired in 1919.</p>

<p>The extent of Gilder's formal artistic training
with Will remains unknown; he may have
been largely self-taught. Friend and fellow Nebraska
artist Augustus Dunbier (1888–1977)
believed Gilder may have been influenced by
Omaha artist J. Laurie Wallace. He often
worked outdoors and drew inspiration primarily
from the Missouri River basin, especially
the Fontenelle Forest area. He also made
many paintings of the desert landscape of Arizona
as well as scenes in California and Connecticut.
His technique can be described as
impressionist in that he concentrated on the
atmosphere or feel of particular places, sought
to capture their natural appearances during
brief periods of time, and used bright pigments
in broken, broad brushwork. In an untitled
winter landscape of 1914 he sensitively
rendered the season's cold pale light, which
casts faint shadows of trees on a riverbank. In
<title>Shadow of the Bridge</title> (n.d.), a view of Omaha
seen from across the Missouri River, the blue
shadows of the bridge cut bold diagonals
across the canvas to the blue horizontal of
the river, above which the city skyline rises.
Known especially for his winter landscapes,
which were avidly collected by Omahans,
Gilder also painted autumn and spring scenes.
An example such as <title>Passing Storm</title> (c. 1916),
with its heavy lavender gray clouds lifting to
disclose clear sky, reveals his skillful use of
color, brush strokes, and composition to depict
rapidly shifting atmospheric conditions.
Broad and broken brushwork, strong but not
overstated color, and tight composition characterize
many of his best paintings.</p>

<p>Gilder exhibited regularly at Whitmore's
Art Gallery in Omaha and had his work shown
in Arizona, California, St. Paul, Minnesota,
and New York City. Modest, energetic, and
consistent in the quality of his work even late
in his life, he produced thirty-four paintings
the summer before he died in Omaha on
March 7, 1940. Nebraska's major art museums,
private collections, and several public schools
hold examples of his work, in addition to
Amherst College and the St. Paul Institute.</p>

 <p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">MEDIA</hi>: 
<ref n="egp.med.035"><hi rend="italic">Omaha World-Herald</hi></ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Sarah Erwin<lb/>
Gilcrease Museum</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Gerdts, William H. <title level="m">The Plains States and the West: Art across America: Regional Painting in America</title>. New York:
Abbeville Press, 1990.</bibl> <bibl>Geske, Norman A. <title level="m">Art and Artists in Nebraska</title>. Lincoln: Sheldon Memorial Art Gallery in Association
with the Center for Great Plains Studies, 1983.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>