<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.ct.048 SYSTEM "egp.ct.048.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ct.048">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Sioux Falls, South Dakota</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Kermit L. Staggers</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ct.048</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Staggers, Kermit L.">Kermit L. Staggers</author>. <title level="a">"Sioux Falls, South Dakota."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">184</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-28</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">SIOUX FALLS, SOUTH DAKOTA</head>

<figure n="egp.ct.048" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Sioux Falls, South Dakota</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Strategically located in southeastern South
Dakota at the junction of Interstates 29 and
90, the city of Sioux Falls is positioned for
the future to take advantage of the expanding
trading opportunities with Canada via I-29
and the coast-to-coast trade between Boston
and Seattle by way of I-90. The city takes its
name from a series of falls on the Big Sioux
River located north of the present downtown
area.</p>

<p>It is believed that Native Americans inhabited
the falls area for at least 1,500 years before
the arrival of European explorers. The first
verified visit of non-Indians to the specific site
was not by European explorers but by members
of the U.S. Army led by Capt. Joseph Allen
on September 12, 1844. Several years later,
in 1856 and 1857, land speculators from Iowa
and the territory of Minnesota arrived at the
falls to lay out town sites. This early attempt
at settlement proved premature because the
Sioux Uprising of 1862 forced the abandonment
of the area. Only with the building of
Fort Dakota in 1865 did the settlers feel safe
to return.</p>

<p>The reestablishment of Sioux Falls did not
lead to a dramatic increase in population, but
it did result in the town becoming the county
seat of the newly created Minnehaha County
in 1868. Not until the first railroad arrived in
Sioux Falls in June 1878 did the town's population
begin to grow dramatically; by 1890 there
were 10,177 inhabitants in the city. At the same
time Sioux Falls earned the distinction of being
the largest city in South Dakota, a title the
city has since held; in 2000 the city's population
was 124,000.</p>

<p>The city's economy has always been intertwined
with the agricultural economy of the
region. In 1909 this relationship was made
manifest when John Morrell and Company
established a large meatpacking plant in Sioux
Falls, and in 1917 the Sioux Falls Stockyards
were created. With the reputation of having
built Sioux Falls, the Morrell Company provided
good-paying jobs and served as the major
employer of the community for most of
the twentieth century.</p>

<p>Beginning in the 1980s, the dominance of
the Morrell Company in the Sioux Falls economy
began to fade as the city started a conscientious
effort to diversify and expand its
economy. In 1981 the New York City-based
Citibank Corporation moved its credit card-
processing center to Sioux Falls because of the
city's favorable business climate and the passage
of special banking legislation by the state
legislature. Following the example of Citibank,
other financial institutions soon followed.
The 1980s also witnessed the expansion
of the local hospitals, Sioux Valley and Avera
McKennan, transforming Sioux Falls into a
regional medical center. At the end of the decade,
Hutchinson Technology, a computer
technology company, arrived in Sioux Falls.</p>

<p>The city gained national recognition for its
economy and quality of life when Money magazine
in 1992 declared Sioux Falls to be the
number one community in the United States.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">MEDIA</hi>: 
<ref n="egp.med.003">Argus Leader(Sioux Falls)</ref>. </p>
</div1>

<div1> <p/>

<closer> 
<signed>Kermit L. Staggers</signed>
University of Sioux Falls</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Fanebust, Wayne. <title level="m">Where the Big Sioux River Bends: A Newspaper Chronicle</title>. Sioux Falls, SD: Minnehaha County
Historical Society, 1985.</bibl> <bibl>Olson, Gary D., and Erik D.
Olson. <title level="m">Sioux Falls, South Dakota: A Pictorial History</title>. Virginia
City, VA: Donning Company Publishers, 1985.</bibl> <bibl>Smith,
Charles A. <title level="m">A Comprehensive History of Minnehaha County, South Dakota</title>. Mitchell, SD: Educator Supply Company,
1949.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>