<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.ag.014 SYSTEM "egp.ag.014.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ag.014">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Branding</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Steven F. Stanec</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ag.014</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Stanec, Steven F.">Steven F. Stanec</author>. <title level="a">"Branding."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">36-37</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-12-10</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">BRANDING</head>

<figure n="egp.ag.014" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Branding a calf, Fort Berthold Indian Agency, North Dakota, 1948</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Livestock branding was introduced to the
Americas in 1520 by the Spanish explorer Hernando
Cortez. Branding, like ranching practices
in general, spread to south Texas and
the Great Plains from Mexico and the southeastern
United States. At that time the southern
method, which used British-derived designs
of block letters and Arabic numbers,
prevailed. Spanish designs became so rare
in the Great Plains that the term "Mexican
brand" was the only description needed to locate
stray animals.</p>

<p>In the open-range system on the Plains,
brands were burned into the cattle, usually
at the spring roundup. A small September
roundup was the time to brand the mavericks,
cattle that had been missed in the spring.
Brands were registered at the county seats in
the districts where the cattle were pastured.</p>

<p>A number of different methods, from paint
to acid branding, have been tried in applying a
brand to live animals. The hot-iron brand and
the freeze brand are the methods most commonly
used today. The hot-iron method uses
an iron heated by fire or electricity to burn
the hide, leaving a permanent scar. Freeze
branding creates a brand by depigmentation,
whereby the pigment-producing cell in the
hide of an animal is destroyed by the application
of intense cold, leaving the hair to grow
out white. Generally, the hot-iron branding
method is the preferred form of identification
on cattle. The freeze branding method is used
more often to brand horses.</p>

<p>A livestock brand is considered a nonreplaceable
form of permanent identification
of ownership and a deterrent to theft. A hot
iron brand is highly visible and difficult to
alter; a freeze brand is also highly visible but is
more easily altered. In the early days of branding
livestock, a running iron, a straight piece
of heated metal, was commonly used to legitimately
brand livestock. However, it was also
used to alter an original brand on stolen or
strayed animals. The running iron was used
to draw the brand on the animal, unlike the
present-day preshaped branding iron, which
merely stamps the brand on the animal.</p>

<p>State livestock agencies, livestock associations,
and Canadian provinces are now responsible
for recording brands in the respective
state or province. Only one brand of a
particular design, configuration, and location
is allowed in each state or province, except in
Texas, where brands are recorded county by
county. A brand may be composed of capital
letters, numbers, characters, and/or pictures
in many different combinations and locations.
The location on the animal where a brand
may legally be applied is generally limited
to the shoulder, rib, and hip. A properly recorded
brand is considered personal property
and is subject to sale, assignment, transfer, devise,
and descent as personal property. Brands
are a road map of an animal's history and tell
a story of its owners. They are considered
an animal's only return address home. Brands
are usually read from left to right, top to bottom.
The livestock brand "B-V" would be read
and defined as a "B bar V straight away."</p>

<p>It is important to properly register a livestock
brand and keep it in good standing, as
state and province laws require brands to be
renewed on a regular basis. Presently, New
Mexico is the only state in the Plains that has
a mandatory cattle-branding law, requiring
each cattle owner to brand all cattle in his or
her possession with their properly recorded
livestock brand. Livestock branding continues
to be vital in determining ownership, returning
strays or stolen livestock to their rightful
owners, and serving as a deterrent to theft.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Steven F. Stanec<lb/>
Nebraska Brand Committee</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Jordan, Terry G. <title level="m">North American Cattle-Ranching Frontiers</title>.
Albuquerque: University of New Mexico Press, 1993.</bibl>
<bibl>Yost, Nellie Snyder. <title level="m">The Call of the Range</title>. Denver: Sage
Books, 1966.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>