<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.war.022">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Indian Scouts</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Thomas W. Dunlay</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.war.022</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Dunlay, Thomas W.">Thomas W. Dunlay</author>. <title level="a">"Indian Scouts."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">829</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-28</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">INDIAN SCOUTS</head>

<p>From the time of the conquest of Mexico onward,
Native American–European American
conflicts in North America were seldom clearcut;
some Native Americans almost always
participated on the side of the European
Americans, and in conflicts between colonizers,
they were likely to be present on both
sides. This pattern held true in the campaigns
fought in the Great Plains. Pueblo auxiliaries
helped Spanish forces in New Mexico defeat
the Comanches in the 1780s. Lakota Sioux
auxiliaries cooperated with Col. Henry Leavenworth's
expedition against the Arikaras in
1823, and Cheyenne and Crow scouts rode
with the regular army in the Ghost Dance
troubles of 1890–91, the last "Indian war" in
the West, though they were not present at the
Wounded Knee Massacre.</p>

<p>The very idea of Native Americans assisting
European Americans in their conquest has always
seemed incongruous to some, leading to
distrust by whites at the time, and later to
charges by Native Americans that Indian
scouts and auxiliaries were mercenaries consciously
betraying their own people. In most
cases the scouts themselves would have found
such accusations meaningless and irrelevant.
They often saw themselves as fighting, beside
the best available allies, against bitter&#8211;and
frequently stronger&#8211;enemies who constituted
the greater immediate menace. This was
the situation with the Pawnees, Arikaras,
Crows, and Shoshones who joined the U.S.
Army against their enemy, the Sioux, in the
1860s and 1870s. When some Sioux joined up
to fight other Sioux who were resisting the
United States, they did so hoping for favorable
terms for their own bands and for an eventual
reduction of further suffering by the "hostile"
bands.</p>

<p>The earliest sustained conflicts between European
Americans and Plains Indians began
in Texas in the 1830s. There, frontiersmen and
Texas Rangers, however bitterly they might
fight the Kiowas and Comanches, still enlisted
the aid of Tonkawas, Lipans, and Delawares,
following a pattern set by frontier rangers and
Indian fighters in colonial times. As the U.S.
Army became increasingly involved in conflict
with the Plains tribes after 1848, they followed
the frontiersmen's example. The rising tide of
conflict during and after the Civil War led in
1866 to a congressional act authorizing the enlistment
of Indians as scouts, on the same
terms as regular army soldiers, but for shorter
terms. As soldiers they could receive pay, rations,
weapons, and noncommissioned rank,
and a few received the Medal of Honor for
bravery. They served not only as individual
trackers and intelligence gatherers but often in
large contingents of company or even battalion
strength. A few units served for extended
periods of time, notably the Pawnee
scouts under Maj. Frank North, who took the
field in 1864 and 1865, served through the
Sioux and Cheyenne campaigns of the late
1860s, and campaigned for the last time in the
Sioux War of 1876–77. They were admired and
praised by the army commanders they served.</p>

<p>Scouts were valued because of their specialized
skills and knowledge acquired over a
lifetime: knowledge of how to follow a trail
and observe the enemy without being seen,
knowledge of the country, and ability to identify
vital information from tracks. These skills
made it possible for soldiers operating in an
alien environment to locate and surprise elusive
enemies in their own country and greatly
enhanced the ability of the military to carry
out their mission.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Thomas W. Dunlay<lb/>
Lincoln, Nebraska</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Dunlay, Thomas W. <title level="m">Wolves for the Blue Soldiers: Indian
Scouts and Auxiliaries with the United States Army, 1860–98</title>.
Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1982.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>