<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ag.057">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Saskatchewan Wheat Pool</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Brett Fairbairn</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ag.057</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Fairbairn, Brett">Brett Fairbairn</author>. <title level="a">"Saskatchewan Wheat Pool."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">50</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-12-18</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">SASKATCHEWAN WHEAT POOL</head>

<p>Created in 1924, the Saskatchewan Wheat Pool
has for decades been Canada's largest agricultural
enterprise. The company is democratically
controlled by Saskatchewan farmers. The
history of the Saskatchewan Wheat Pool can
be divided into four phases. First was the
founding era of 1924–31, when the cooperative
bought and marketed to overseas customers a
large proportion of the Prairie wheat crop.
The Depression and the 1940s were a period
of readjustment, during which the company
largely surrendered its original role as a marketer
of grain to the Canadian Wheat Board,
an organization whose history is intertwined
with that of the pool. The war was followed by
a long period of dominance and growth as a
grain handler, marketer of livestock and specialty
crops, and general-interest farm organization.
A new phase in the company's history
began in 1996 when most of its stock was converted
to publicly traded shares.</p>

<p>Activist farmers who were upset with existing
grain companies and cooperatives organized
the pool in 1923-24. Most farm organizations
at the time favored a government-run
wheat board to market their crops, but they
turned to cooperative action when governments
were unresponsive. A faction invited
Aaron Sapiro, a California-based lawyer and
advocate of pooling, to visit the Prairies in
1923. Sapiro's speeches and ideas proved to
be the catalyst for the organization of three
wheat pools in Alberta, Manitoba, and Saskatchewan.
The 1923 pooling drive in Saskatchewan
failed, perhaps due to lukewarm
support from provincial leaders and to the formidable
contracts that required farmers to
pledge all their wheat for a five-year period to
the pool and which were void unless 50 percent
of acreage was signed up. The second
drive in 1924 was a mass effort of community
mobilization: 45,725 farmers pledged their
6,433,779 acres of wheat, meeting the target
and bringing the pool into existence. From
1924 to 1931, the pool worked with its sister organizations
in Alberta and Manitoba through
the Central Selling Agency to market a majority
of the Prairie wheat crop, wherever possible
directly to overseas customers, and to build or
purchase networks of storage elevators.</p>

<p>The stock market crash of 1929 caught the
pools overextended, as grain prices fell below
the level already advanced to farmers; the
pools made matters worse by buying more
grain in an attempt to influence prices. In 1931
the Canadian government intervened to provide
financial guarantees for the pools and
took over the sale of their inventories. Government
involvement eventually culminated in
the creation of the modern Canadian Wheat
Board—ironically, what farmers had wanted
in the first place. The pool, meanwhile, was
converted from a world grain trader to a
heavily indebted Saskatchewan elevator company.
The pool's response not only preserved
the cooperative, but it cemented its place as the
province's most important agricultural institution.
While repaying its debts, the pool became
a crucial agent of adult education. Pool
field staff gave talks, showed films, and helped
set up consumer cooperatives and credit
unions in small towns across Saskatchewan.</p>

<p>From the 1940s to the 1980s, the pool extended
its elevator network (handling up
to two-thirds of the annual grain crop),
branched out into new or expanded lines of
business such as livestock marketing and farm
supply, and consolidated its position as the
spokesperson for Saskatchewan farmers. The
pool's model system of member education
and delegate democracy was studied by cooperatives
around the world; pool annual meetings
were a kind of farmers parliament where
important issues of provincial, federal, and international
policy were debated. Since the
pool was both Saskatchewan's largest business
corporation and a farm interest group with
60,000 members, it developed considerable
influence in provincial politics. Its weekly
newspaper, the <title level="j">Western Producer</title>, remains the
most important farm paper in Canada.</p>

<p>The cooperative could not, however, escape
the dominant agricultural trends. Low farm
incomes created pressure to operate on low
margins; rural depopulation left the pool with
fewer and aging members. Pool managers and
leaders became concerned in the late 1980s
with the cooperative's debt burden, resulting
from an aging membership entitled upon retirement
to share payouts. At the same time,
they saw a need for investment and expansion
to meet the challenges of transnational
competitors and new agricultural markets.
As a result, the cooperative, with the approval
of farmer delegates, transformed its
ownership structure in 1996. Voting shares&#8211;
class A shares&#8211;were retained only by farmermembers,
but virtually the entire capitalization
of the company was converted into
nonvoting class B shares that were tradable on
the Toronto Stock Exchange. The pool remained
farmer-controlled, but its owners
were now a noncongruent body of investors.
Along with the share conversion, the pool undertook
an ambitious program to consolidate
its handling facilities in a smaller number of
larger and more modern elevators, to invest in
value-added processing subsidiaries and joint
ventures, and to expand outside Saskatchewan
and outside Canada.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">MEDIA</hi>: 
<hi rend="italic"><ref n="egp.med.048">Western Producer</ref></hi>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Brett Fairbairn<lb/>
University of Saskatchewan</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Fairbairn, Garry. <title level="m">From Prairie Roots: The Remarkable Story of Saskatchewan Wheat Pool</title>. Saskatoon: Western
Producer Prairie Books, 1984.</bibl> <bibl>Fowke, V. C. <title level="m">The National Policy and the Wheat Economy</title>. Toronto: University of
Toronto Press, 1957.</bibl> <bibl>MacPherson, Ian. "Missionaries of
Rural Development: The Fieldmen of the Saskatchewan
Wheat Pool, 1925–1965." <title level="j">Agricultural History</title> 60 (1986):
73–96.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>