<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.pg.012">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Clark, Joe (b. 1939)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>John C. Courtney</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.pg.012</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Courtney, John C.">John C. Courtney</author>. <title level="a">"Clark, Joe (b. 1939)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">658</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-29</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">CLARK, JOE (b. 1939)</head>

<p>Born June 5, 1939, in High River, Alberta, Joe
Clark was the first Canadian prime minister to
have been born in the Prairies. At age thirty-six
he was chosen as the youngest person ever
to lead the Progressive Conservative Party.
Sworn to office the day before his fortieth
birthday, he became his country's youngest
prime minister. His government, defeated in
the House of Commons on its first budget and
by the Liberals in the ensuing general election,
remained in office only nine months, from
May 1979 to February 1980, one of the briefest
governments in Canadian history. From 1984
to 1993 he served first as Canada's minister for
external affairs, then as constitutional affairs
minister, in the government of Brian Mulroney,
the man who had successfully challenged
him for the leadership of the Progressive
Conservative Party in 1983.</p>

<p>Joe Clark was raised in a Tory (Conservative)
and Catholic family, an unusual mix by
Canadian standards for much of the twentieth
century. His grandfather had published a
small-town newspaper in Ontario, and his father
moved to Alberta where, just four months
after the creation of the province in 1905, he
established the weekly paper in High River.</p>

<p>Clark was educated at the University of Alberta,
earning bachelor's and master's degrees
in political science. Although he spent the
greatest part of his adult life in public affairs
(either in an elected or behind-the-scenes
party position), Clark listed journalism as his
chosen profession in his official biographies.
Known to cite passages from Wallace Stegner's
Wolf Willow about the poignant beauty of the
Great Plains and about the spirit and virtues
imbued by the harsh Prairie environment, Joe
Clark was profoundly shaped by the geographic
and social diversity of the foothills
country south of Calgary in which he spent the
first eighteen years of his life. His later championing
of the view of Canada as a "community
of communities" (dismissed by his political
nemesis, Pierre Trudeau, as an affront to
the principle of a single Canadian nationhood)
was drawn from his early experiences in that
part of Alberta.</p>

<p>First elected to parliament in 1972, he was
reelected in the five succeeding Canadian general
elections. His unexpected victory over ten
other candidates for the Tory leadership in
1976 led the press to dub him "Joe Who?"
That, together with his badly handled budget
vote in 1979 and open dissension within the
Tory party over his leadership in the early
1980s, led his opponents to launch an "Anyone
But Clark" movement aimed at his removal
from the party's top position. When the challenge
to his leadership succeeded in 1983, with
Brian Mulroney's selection to lead the Progressive
Conservative Party, many commentators
speculated openly that Joe Clark's political
career had come to an end. However, he
proved them wrong with his loyalty to his
party and its leader in the decade that followed,
combined with his handling of the External
Affairs ministry and his stewardship of
the constitutional affairs portfolio during difficult
(and ultimately unsuccessful) consultations
and negotiations over Canada's constitutional
arrangements. He demonstrated an
understanding of foreign policy and Canadian
society that helped to remove a measure of the
tarnish from his leadership of the Progressive
Conservative Party from 1976 to 1983.</p>

<p>Withdrawing from national politics at the
time of the 1993 election, Clark established a
political consultancy firm in Calgary. With clients
in Canada and abroad, the business enabled
him to draw on contacts established
during his twenty-one years in elected politics.
The attractions of public life surfaced once
again, however, when in 1998 he successfully
sought the national leadership of his party.
By then the Conservatives had been reduced,
with only twenty members of Parliament, to
fifth place in the House of Commons and
were heavily in debt. Clark's considerable
challenge at that point, made more burdensome
because he held no seat in Parliament
from which he could attempt to gain daily
media exposure, was to rebuild the Tory Party
into a national force similar to what it had
been during his earlier period in Canadian
politics.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">LITERARY TRADITIONS</hi>: <ref n="egp.lt.074">Stegner, Wallace</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>John C. Courtney<lb/>
University of Saskatchewan</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Courtney, John C. <title level="m">Do Conventions Matter? Choosing National
Party Leaders in Canada</title>. Montreal: McGill-Queen's
University Press, 1995.</bibl> <bibl>Graham, Ron. <title level="m">One-Eyed Kings:
Promise and Illusion in Canadian Politics</title>. Toronto: Collins,
1986.</bibl> <bibl>Humphreys, David L. <title level="m">Joe Clark: A Portrait</title>.
Toronto: Deneau and Greenberg Publishers Ltd., 1978.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>