<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.tra.018">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Indian Trails</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Donald J. Blakeslee</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.tra.018</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Blakeslee, Donald J.">Donald J. Blakeslee</author>. <title level="a">"Indian Trails."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">803</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-22</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">INDIAN TRAILS</head>

<p>Plains Indians traveled long distances to hunt,
trade, make war, and visit sacred places. To do
so, they used trails such as the Great North
Trail that ran south from Canada along the
eastern front of the Rocky Mountains into
New Mexico. A trail that crossed it on the
north bank of the Arkansas River ran east to
the vicinity of Kinsley, Kansas, then overland
to cross the southern part of Missouri to the
mouth of the Ohio River. These and many
other trails created a web across the face of the
Great Plains.</p>

<p>The trails were designed to meet the needs
of pedestrian travelers. The most important of
these needs was water. People using pack dogs
can only travel about ten miles per day, and
the most heavily used trails had water holes
spaced no farther apart than ten miles. Stream
crossings and steep hills were avoided whenever
possible; as a result, many trails ran along
the divides between stream valleys. Although
they were sinuous, these routes had the additional
advantage of allowing the traveler to see
long distances while passing by the headwater
springs of numerous creeks.</p>

<p>Trails converged at good fords across streams
and at the rare groves of trees in the High Plains.
In some instances, such as the ford across the
Kansas River in the Flint Hills, the geologic stratum
underlying the divide along which a trail
ran created a rocky ford where the ridge was cut
by a river. Groves provided shade, vegetable
foods, fuel for shelter, and a variety of game
animals to hunt. The "Big Timbers" of the Arkansas
in Colorado, of the Smoky Hill River in
western Kansas, and of the Republican River in
southwestern Nebraska were some of the favored
campgrounds.</p>

<p>Operating in cultures that lacked systems of
writing and mapmaking, Plains Indians took
advantage of natural landmarks whenever
possible. This was especially necessary because
massive bison herds could erase in a single day
pathways worn by decades of human travel.
When natural landmarks were absent, stone
or sod cairns were sometimes built. Cairns
had varied functions. In some spots they
marked the main course of a trail, in others
they marked a good spring not visible from
the trail itself, while in still other places they
indicated the route to be used to regain the
trail after a river crossing. Some cairns acted
as shrines at which travelers added a stone as a
prayer.</p>

<p>Well-designed Indian trails had a pronounced
effect on the early European American
history of the Great Plains. Native guides
led explorers along them, traders built their
posts beside them, and battles were fought
near them. Emigrant trails such as the Oregon
and Santa Fe Trails developed from Indian
trails, although wagon traffic sometimes necessitated
modifications to the routes. The
well-spaced water holes and gentle grades of
many trails led to the use of some as cattle
trails and railroad routes. Thus their effects
continue to be felt today.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Donald J. Blakeslee<lb/>
Wichita State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Blakeslee, Donald J., and Robert Blasing. "Indian Trails in
the Central Plains." <title level="j">Plains Anthropologist</title> 33–119 (1988):
17–26.</bibl> <bibl>Mead, J. R. "Trails in Southern Kansas." <title level="j">Transactions
of the Kansas State Historical Society</title> 5 (1896): 88–93.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>