<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.law.009">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Brewer, David (1837-1910)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Harold S. Herd</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.law.009</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Herd, Harold S.">Harold S. Herd</author>. <title level="a">"Brewer, David (1837-1910)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">447-448</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-04</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">BREWER, DAVID (1837-1910)</head>

<p>David J. Brewer was born in Smyrna, Asia
Minor, on June 20, 1837, the fourth child of
Josiah and Amelia Brewer. Josiah was a Congregational
missionary; Amelia was from the
Field family of Massachusetts, one of the nation's
prominent legal families. At the age
of fourteen David entered Wesleyan College,
then transferred to Yale after two years. He
graduated fourth in his class in 1856. His focus
was on becoming a lawyer, which led him to
his uncle David's office in Albany, where he
read law for a year. He then enrolled in Albany
Law School and graduated in February 1858.</p>

<p>During law school, David Brewer became
sympathetic to the abolitionist cause and opposed
to the Kansas-Nebraska Act. The Dred
Scott decision added to his frustration. He decided
to forgo the security of his uncle's law
office and seek his destiny at the focal point
of the free-state/slavery conflict&#8211;Kansas Territory.
He chose the thriving frontier town
of Leavenworth as the place to practice law.
Brewer's judicial career commenced with his
election to probate judge in 1862. After two
years in that office, he was elected district
judge of Leavenworth and Wyandotte Counties.
He took a two-year break from the judiciary
in 1868 to be the county prosecutor, then
was elected justice of the Kansas Supreme
Court in 1870, serving until 1884. Justice
Brewer wrote opinions on fraudulent county
elections; fraudulent bonds in Comanche
County issued before it was populated; bond
issues for building railroads; railroad regulation;
and the criminal conviction of a cattle
rustler captured by Bat Masterson, sheriff at
Dodge City. In a child custody case he established
the precedent that the welfare of the
child was controlling. He also fostered woman's
rights by ordering that a woman could
hold an elective office even though she could
not vote.</p>

<p>David Brewer's work in courts and in the
communities of Kansas brought him such favorable
attention that in 1884 President Chester
A. Arthur appointed him federal circuit
court judge for the eighth circuit, comprising
the states of Nebraska, Minnesota, Iowa,
Missouri, Kansas, Colorado, and Arkansas.
He served there until 1889. As circuit judge,
Brewer handled a variety of cases. His most
controversial decisions were the Wabash Railroad
receivership and the injunctions he issued
against labor unions. His most high-profile
decisions were the Maxwell Land Company
cases in New Mexico and Colorado.</p>

<p>When Justice Stanley Matthews of the U.S.
Supreme Court died in 1889, President Benjamin
Harrison appointed Brewer to the vacancy.
He served on the Supreme Court until
1910, writing 533 majority opinions and 57 dissents
and concurring in 8 cases. One of his
most important decisions was in the Plains
case <hi rend="italic">Kansas v. Colorado</hi> (1904), the beginning
of a continuing dispute over Arkansas River
water. Here Brewer established some interstate
common law in prescribing an equitable
apportionment of benefits.</p>

<p>As a noted public speaker in great demand
across the country, Justice Brewer was an outspoken
advocate for peace. He made exceptions
for the Civil War and Spanish-American
War on the grounds they were for the noble
causes of freeing the slaves and Cubans. He
gave unselfishly of his time and dedicated his
life to his beliefs. He was complex and sometimes
paradoxical, but his faith in the individual
was consistent. He thought the true end of
government was the protection of the individual,
since the majority has the power to take
care of itself. He died on March 27, 1910, and
was buried in Mount Muncie Cemetery, Leavenworth,
Kansas.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Harold S. Herd<lb/>
Washburn University School of Law</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Broadhead, Michael J. <title level="m">David J. Brewer: The Life of a Supreme Court Justice, 1837–1910</title>. Carbondale: Southern Illinois
University Press, 1994.</bibl>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>