<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.law.036">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main"><hi rend="italic">Nebraska Press Association v. Stuart</hi></title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>James W. Hewitt</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.law.036</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Hewitt, James W.">James W. Hewitt</author>. <title level="a">"<hi rend="italic">Nebraska Press Association v. Stuart</hi>."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">459</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-05</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main"><hi rend="italic">NEBRASKA PRESS ASSOCIATION V. STUART</hi></head>

<p>The potential conflict between society's First
Amendment right to a free press and a criminal
defendant's Sixth Amendment right to a
fair trial was addressed by the U.S. Supreme
Court in the landmark decision of <hi rend="italic">Nebraska
Press Association v. Stuart</hi>. The grisly case began
on the evening of October 18, 1975, when
Erwin Simants walked into the home of Henry
Kellie, just outside the village of Sutherland,
Nebraska, carrying a rifle. Once inside, Simants
brutally raped and then murdered Kellie's
ten-year-old granddaughter. Later, when other
members of the Kellie family arrived home,
they found Simants waiting for them. After
killing both Henry and his wife, their son, and
two other grandchildren, Simants, an unemployed
alcoholic, calmly visited both of Sutherland's
two bars and then spent the rest of the
night outside the Kellie house.</p>

<p>The next morning, Simants was quickly arrested
and charged with six counts of firstdegree
murder. Just as quickly, television and
newspaper articles describing the horrific
events began to appear. Even before the bodies
were removed from the Kellie home, news
agencies from around the country had focused
on Sutherland, reporting the multiple homicide.
Such widespread media coverage caused
concern that public disclosure of highly prejudicial
information revealed in Simants's preliminary
pretrial hearing would taint potential
jurors and prevent a fair trial. As a result,
Lincoln County District Judge Hugh Stuart
granted the prosecuting attorney's request to
gag the press. He strictly prohibited the media
from publishing reports of confessions and
other details that strongly implicated Simants.</p>

<p>The press complied with Stuart's order but
appealed to the Nebraska Supreme Court,
claiming the order violated the press's constitutional
right to report information disclosed
in open court. The media contended that the
First Amendment right to a free press necessarily
included the right to cover events both
in and outside of the courtroom and that this
ability was essential to prevent judicial abuse
of authority. In contrast, Stuart's counsel argued
that Simants could not receive a fair trial
without the restrictions. Allowing the press to
publish extremely prejudicial information, his
defense asserted, would bias potential jurors
and preclude their ability to base their decision
solely on evidence received in court.
Prior exposure to the case through the media,
it was argued, would make it impossible to
find an impartial jury as guaranteed by the
Sixth Amendment.</p>

<p>The Nebraska Supreme Court, after modifying
Stuart's order, affirmed it. Eventually,
the suit was brought before the U.S. Supreme
Court, which reversed the decision, holding
that the order did impermissibly restrict free
press. The Court acknowledged that prior restraints
may be necessary in certain rare circumstances,
but the court went on to explain
that the presumption against the use of prior
restraints can only be overcome by showing
that less restrictive alternatives cannot sufficiently protect a defendant's rights. <hi rend="italic">Nebraska
Press</hi> is often characterized as the most significant
First Amendment ruling emanating from
Nebraska, and it essentially closed the question
of prior restraints in criminal law. As a
result, the media enjoy nearly complete discretion
over what and when to publish concerning
judicial proceedings.</p>

<closer>
<signed>James W. Hewitt<lb/>
Lincoln, Nebraska</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Larson, Milton R. "Free Press v. Fair Trial in Nebraska: A
Position Paper." <title level="j">Nebraska Law Review</title> 55 (1976): 543–71.</bibl>
<bibl>Younger, Eric C. "The Sheppard Mandate Today: A Trial
Judge's Perspective." <title level="j">Nebraska Law Review</title> 56 (1977): 1–22.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>