<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ct.034">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Odessa, Texas</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Linda D. Brown</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ct.034</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Brown, Linda D.">Linda D. Brown</author>. <title level="a">"Odessa, Texas."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">175</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-27</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">ODESSA, TEXAS</head>

<p>Odessa is a city of 95,700 inhabitants, located
centrally in the Permian Basin of West Texas.
It sits nearly equidistant from both El Paso
and Fort Worth and serves as the county seat
for Ector County. The city, which shares its
name with Odessa, Ukraine, started as 640
acres in Survey 27 in 1876. Jay Gould's Texas
and Pacific Railroad Company, which reached
the survey in 1881, provided the impetus for
further settlement. In 1886, when the population
was only sixty, the Texas and Pacific
transferred the acreage to John Hoge of Ohio,
who then formed the Odessa Land and Townsite
Company. Advertising in 1888 about the
new town of Odessa on the Staked Plain of
West Texas ensured eastern readers of cheap
homes, provisions for religious and educational
facilities, and the intentional absence of
saloons. By 1890 there were 224 inhabitants;
thirty-five years later, there were still only 750
residents of Odessa.</p>

<p>Population growth accelerated with the
1926 discovery of oil in Ector County and subsequent
discoveries in nearby counties. The
industry that emerged had its origins in
the Permian Sea, which covered the area before
dinosaurs made their appearance on the
earth. As the waters eventually receded, the
decaying plant and animal life became over
time the future oil reserves. It was not until
after the worst of the Depression that the burgeoning
petroleum industry came into its real
strength. Odessa's proximity to the oil fields
and railroad made it the choice location to
service and supply the wells, and Odessa and
Midland together are jointly referred to as
the Petroplex. Additionally, Odessans have experimented
since initial settlement with livestock
ventures. Early attempts at sheep raising
failed due to barbed wire, which closed off the
range. Cattle ranching strengthened over time
and remains a vibrant business today. Football
was introduced to the town in 1923 to encourage
young men to stay in school. Today,
Odessa is nationally known for its highly competitive
football program: Permian High captured
the Texas state high school title six
times from 1964 to 1991, and Odessa High was
champion in 1946.</p>

<p>In 1927 the town became a city when it incorporated,
receiving its charter and electing
its first mayor. But its development and growth
still came in spurts, largely dependent on the
oil economy and available accommodation.
Such booms and busts continue to influence
the area. It was during one such boom in 1948
that President George H. W. Bush and his family
lived and worked in Odessa. They spent one
year in the city before moving to Midland.</p>

<p>Modern Odessa, while still dependent on
oil and cattle, continues to evolve. The Permian
Basin International Oil Show, first begun
in 1940, continues to be held biennially,
but Odessa is also working to diversify its
economy by attracting other businesses and
industries. And although the city's first college
was burned to the ground in 1892, possibly in
response to the saloon debate, today there are
two thriving institutions of higher learning:
Odessa College and the University of Texas of
the Permian Basin. Possibly, the area's oldest
point of interest is the meteor crater created
some 20,000 years ago but only declared a national
landmark in 1965: the Odessa Crater
measures 550 feet in diameter and is purported
to be the second largest in the country.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">IMAGES AND ICONS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ii.025">Friday Night Football</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">INDUSTRY</hi>: <ref n="egp.ind.047">Petroleum, United States</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Linda D. Brown<lb/>
Odessa College</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Justice, Glenn. <title level="m">Odessa: An Illustrated History</title>. Chatsworth
<hi rend="smallcaps">CA</hi>: Windsor Publications, 1991.</bibl> <bibl>Sheppard, John Ben.
<title level="m">Odessa 100: An Informal History</title>. Odessa <hi rend="smallcaps">TX</hi>: Exchange
Club, 1981.</bibl> <bibl><title level="m">Texas: The New Town of Odessa</title>. Odessa <hi rend="smallcaps">TX</hi>:
Odessa Land and Townsite Company, 1888.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>