<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.wat.007">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Doctrine of Equity</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Theron Josephson</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.wat.007</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Josephson, Theron">Theron Josephson</author>. <title level="a">"Doctrine of Equity."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">851-852</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-29</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">DOCTRINE OF EQUITY</head>

<p>The doctrine of equity is a principle of inter-jurisdictional
water allocation developed by
the U.S. Supreme Court in response to interstate
water conflicts. It is a doctrine of necessity
because of the juxtaposition of the legal
theory allowing each state to develop its own
form of water law against the physical reality
that streams flow from one state to another.
The doctrine states that when there is a disagreement
over the water use of an interstate
stream, the court must fashion an equitable
apportionment of the water that serves the
needs of water users in both states. Equitable
apportionment of the water is not based on
any mathematical formula but on a fair consideration
of all the interests involved.</p>

<p>The doctrine originated in the Great Plains,
where water flows not only from west to east
but also from appropriation water law jurisdictions to riparian water law jurisdictions.
Water allocation and consumptive uses of water
by an upstream state have significant consequences
when downstream states seek to use
water of the same stream. Such was the case
with the states of Colorado and Kansas. In 1901
Kansas sued Colorado on behalf of water users
of the Arkansas River in western Kansas, alleging
that Colorado, through its appropriation
law, had encouraged its citizens to consume
the water of the Arkansas to the detriment of
the people in Kansas. Colorado countered,
maintaining that as an independent state it had
the right to use all the water it needed, even to
the detriment of Kansas residents. By 1904, the
case, <title>Kansas v. Colorado</title>, had reached the U.S.
Supreme Court. In 1907 the Supreme Court
rejected both positions. Justice David Brewer, a
native of Kansas, wrote the court's opinion.
While the Court did not find that Colorado
had injured residents of southwestern Kansas
to any great degree, it did establish the principle
of the "equality of right," which fashioned a
remedy requiring courts to ensure each state
an equitable opportunity to use interstate
stream water. This balancing of relative economic
advantages continues to determine decisions
on interstate water disputes.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">LAW</hi>: <ref n="egp.law.009">Brewer, David</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Theron Josephson<lb/>
Ferris State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Dunbar, Robert G. <title level="m">Forging New Rights in Western Water</title>.
Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1983.</bibl> <bibl>Hutchins, W.
A. <title level="m">Water Rights in the Nineteen Western States</title>. Washington
<hi rend="smallcaps">DC</hi>: Government Printing Office, 1974.</bibl> <bibl>Trelease, Frank
J., and George A. Gould. <title level="m">Cases and Materials on Water
Law</title>, 4th ed. St. Paul <hi rend="smallcaps">MN</hi>: West Publishing Company, 1986.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>