<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.art.040 SYSTEM "egp.art.040.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.art.040">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Jones, Joe (1909–1963)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Louisa Iarocci</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.art.040</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Iarocci, Louisa">Louisa Iarocci</author>. <title level="a">"Jones, Joe (1909–1963)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">122-123</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-22</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">JONES, JOE (1909–1963)</head>

<figure n="egp.art.040" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Joe Jones. American Farm, 1936. Oil and tempera on canvas. 30 x 40 inches (76.2 x 101.6 cm).</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Although not well known today, Joe Jones
rose to national prominence as an artist during
the Great Depression in the United States.
Born in St. Louis on April 7, 1909, this grandson
of a stonemason and son of a house
painter used his humble beginnings and political
beliefs to fashion a persona as a working-class
hero that befitted the times. In the early
1930s the twenty-year-old was working alongside
his father painting houses when he began
to draw attention in local art circles for his
works on canvas, produced without the benefit
of formal training. But his middle-class
backers began to retreat as the young artist
became as notorious for his controversial political
activities as he was for his paintings.
Jones's flight to New York to escape local prosecution
on a charge of spreading Communist
propaganda proved to be a wise career move.</p>

<p>His first one-man show in the spring of 1935
at the American Contemporary Art Gallery
received rave reviews. His social protest paintings
such as We Demand, which depicts a
workers' demonstration, and <title>American Justice</title>,
which features a lynching, garnered the most
attention. However, his next exhibition, <title>Paintings of Wheatfields</title>, at the Walker Gallery in
January 1936, showed him moving in a less
controversial direction. These tranquil scenes
of farmers at work in their fields brought
the self-proclaimed "professor of wheat" five
prestigious federal contracts for murals in
post offices in the Midwest and the Great
Plains, commissioned by the Treasury Section
of the Fine Arts, a New Deal program that
sought to bring art to the public while employing
struggling artists.</p>

<p>While he was in the Plains Jones painted the
oil on canvas works <title>Turning a Corner</title> (1939) in
Anthony, Kansas, and <title>Men and Wheat</title> (1940)
in Seneca, Kansas. Deftly balancing the restraints
of the administration's guidelines,
the local postmaster's needs, and the awkward
constraints of the site, Jones produced typical
regionalist rural scenes, depicting man,
machine, and landscape working together in
harmony. But beyond the mythic ideal of
a bountiful nature, Jones's compositions
frankly reveal humanity's mark upon the
environment&#8211;the lush fields are being thoroughly
stripped by the anonymous workers,
their figures merging with the dominating
forms of modern machinery. The artist expressed
his desire to portray both the importance
of wheat to Kansas and the image of
people at work in the murals. But as social
realism fell out of fashion in the 1940s, Jones
abandoned the working hero, focusing instead
on the portrayal of the landscape for corporate
clients such as <hi rend="italic">Fortune</hi> magazine and
Standard Oil. He died of a heart attack in New
Jersey on April 9, 1963.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</hi>: <ref n="egp.pg.054">New Deal</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Louisa Iarocci<lb/>
Boston University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Marling, Karal Ann. "Joe Jones: Regionalist, Communist,
Capitalist." <title level="j">Journal of the Decorative and Propaganda Arts 1875-1945</title> 4 (1987): 46-58.</bibl> <bibl>Marling, Karal Ann. <title level="m">Wall-to-Wall America: A Cultural History of Post-Office Murals in the Great Depression</title>. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota
Press, 1982.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>