<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.sr.040">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">National Parks</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Charles I. Zinser</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.sr.040</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Zinser, Charles I.">Charles I. Zinser</author>. <title level="a">"National Parks."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">781-783</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-21</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">NATIONAL PARKS</head>

<p>The Great Plains has thirty units of the U.S.
National Park System, three Canadian national
parks, and fifteen national historic sites. The
thirty U.S. units total slightly over 500,000
acres, which is only 0.6 percent of the 376-unit,
83,431,000-acre U.S. National Park System. In
Canada the Great Plains is much better represented
in the 38-unit, 55 million–acre Canadian
National Park System.</p>

<p>To most people it is the unit classified as
"national park" that comes to mind when
thinking of the U.S. National Park System.
There are fifty-four national parks across
the country that cover 47 million acres. Badlands
National Park (242,756 acres) in South
Dakota occupies almost 50 percent of the total
National Park System acreage in the Great
Plains. The three other national parks in the
U.S. Great Plains are relatively small: Theodore
Roosevelt National Park (70,477 acres),
North Dakota; Carlsbad Caverns National
Park (46,766 acres), New Mexico; and Wind
Cave (28,295 acres), South Dakota.</p>

<p>Badlands National Park, located in southwestern
South Dakota, consists of sharply
eroded buttes, pinnacles, and spires that blend
with the largest protected mixed-grass prairie in
the United States. The prairie grasslands support
bison, bighorn sheep, deer, and pronghorn
antelope. Much of the 100-mile-long Badlands
Wall, a prominent physiographic feature, is located
within the park. Carved by the erosive
force of water, this scenic landscape contains the
world's richest Oligocene epoch fossil beds, 23 to
35 million years old. Established as Badlands
National Monument in 1939, the area was redesignated
a national park in 1978. The park is
surrounded by the Buffalo Gap National Grassland
on the north and the Pine Ridge Reservation
on the south. One-quarter (64,000 acres) of
the park has been designated as a unit (Sage
Creek Wilderness) of the National Wilderness
Preservation System and is the site of the reintroduction
of the black-footed ferret, the
most endangered land mammal in North
America. Most visitors experience the North
Unit of the park, which is conveniently located
near Interstate 90, and drive the Badlands
Loop; the Ben Reifel Visitor Center is located
along this route. The South Unit is more remote
and is almost entirely undeveloped. Despite
temperatures that can reach above 100&#186;F,
summer is the most popular season to visit
Badlands National Park. Lodging is available
within the park at the Cedar Pass Lodge and
at the one developed campground, the Cedar
Pass Campground. The park receives approximately
a million visitors per year, but most
visitors stay only about four hours.</p>

<p>Theodore Roosevelt National Park is located
in the extreme west-central portion of North
Dakota in the colorful North Dakota Badlands
along the Little Missouri River and is unique
among the national parks in that it not only
preserves an extraordinary landscape but also
serves as a living memorial to a president of
the United States and his enduring contribution
to the conservation movement. The park
was originally established in 1947 as Theodore
Roosevelt National Memorial Park but was redesignated
a national park in 1978. Roosevelt
first came to the area in 1883. The following
year he established the Elkhorn Ranch, where
many of his attitudes about nature and conservation
were shaped and refined. Almost half
(29,920 acres) of this park has been designated
by Congress as the Theodore Roosevelt Wilderness
Area. The park consists of two main
units (the North and South Units) and the
Elkhorn Ranch Site and is almost completely
surrounded by the largest national grassland in
the United States, the Little Missouri National
Grassland. Nearly fifty miles separate the
North and South Units. Interstate 94 borders
and passes through the South Unit; the Painted
Canyon Visitor Center and the Medora Visitor
Center are located there. A major feature of the
South Unit is a paved, thirty-six-mile scenic
loop with interpretive signs that explain some
of the park's historical and natural phenomena.
The North Unit is more scenic but due to
its isolation is more lightly visited. It also has a
scenic drive (twenty-eight miles). The Elkhorn
Ranch Site is located thirty-five miles north of
the Medora Visitor Center. The ranch buildings
no longer exist. Although the park is open
all year, some of the park roads may close in the
winter. There are developed campgrounds in
each unit of the park. The park attracts about
500,000 visitors every year.</p>

<p>Carlsbad Caverns National Park is located at
the southern end of the Guadalupe Mountains
in the Chihuahuan desert in southeastern New
Mexico. The park contains seventy-six separate
caves, including the nationfs deepest (1,567
feet) and third longest. Originally proclaimed
as Carlsbad Caverns National Monument in
1923, it was established as Carlsbad Caverns
National Park in 1930. Seventy percent of this
park has been designated as part of the National
Wilderness Preservation System. Visitors
have a choice of two diãerent tours in
these spectacular caverns. The Blue Tour begins
at the surface and goes belowground at the
cavefs natural entrance. It is three miles and
about three hours long and ends at the Big
Room. The Red Tour is one and a quarter miles
long and takes about an hour and a half. During
this tour an elevator ride descends 755 feet
to the edge of the Big Room. The Big Room,
1,800 feet at its longest, 1,100 feet at its widest,
and 255 feet at its highest, is one of the largest
underground chambers in the world. The
chamber is resplendent with cave formations,
including the sixty-two-foot-high Giant Dome,
Carlsbad's biggest stalagmite. One of the park's
most spectacular sights is the mass exodus at
dusk of thousands of Mexican free-tailed bats,
which fly from the Big Room for a night of
feasting on insects. On the surface the 9.25-mile
Walnut Canyon Desert Drive is a gravel, one-way
loop through dramatic desert mountain
scenery. There is no lodging or developed
campground within the park. The park receives
about 500,000 visitors a year.</p>

<p>Only four national parks are smaller than
the Wind Cave National Park, established in
1903. It is located at the edge of the Black Hills
of southwestern South Dakota and is bordered
on the west by the Black Hills National
Forest and on the north by Custer State Park.
Wind Cave contains fifty-five miles of passages,
making it one of the longest caves in the
world. It received its name from the strong air
currents that flow in and out of its mouth. The
cave contains many unusual mineral formations
called boxwork, which are thin calcite
fins resembling honeycomb. Above-ground,
the park serves as a wildlife sanctuary for the
restoration of bison, elk, and pronghorn antelope
to the Black Hills. Starting with fourteen
bison donated by the Bronx Zoo in 1913, the
herd now numbers about 350. Seventy-five
percent of the surface of the park is open
grassland, and the rest is forested with ponderosa
pine. The Elk Mountain Campground
is the only option for those who want to stay
overnight. Although the park receives 700,000
visitors a year, most of these visits are very
short. Among the fifty-four national parks,
only urbanized Hot Springs National Park
(Arkansas) has shorter average visits.</p>

<p>The establishment of Tallgrass Prairie National
Preserve in 1996 in the Flint Hills region
of east-central Kansas filled a major void in
the National Park System by including the first
unit whose major ecosystem is tallgrass prairie.
Tallgrass Prairie National Preserve is a new
kind of park with a unique public/private
managing concept. It is approximately 11,000
acres in size, but most of that land will remain
under the ownership of the National Park
Trust, which purchased the Z Bar/Spring Hill
Ranch in 1994. The National Park Service will
own 180 acres, yet the legislation calls for the
entire acreage to be managed cooperatively by
the National Park Service and the National
Park Trust.</p>

<p>Of the ten units of the National Park System
in the Great Plains classified as national monuments,
four are geological and six are historical
in nature. Devils Tower National Monument
(1,350 acres) in the northeastern corner of Wyoming
is an 865-foot tower of columnar rock,
the remains of a volcanic intrusion. It was proclaimed
by President Theodore Roosevelt as
the first national monument in 1906. Capulin
Volcano National Monument (800 acres) is a
nearly perfectly shaped cinder cone that stands
1,200 feet above the surrounding High Plains
of northeastern New Mexico. A two-mile
paved road spiraling to the volcano rim makes
this one of the most accessible volcanoes in the
world. Jewell Cave National Monument (1,300
acres) is located in the Black Hills of southwestern
South Dakota and is the third longest
cave in the world. It is known for spectacular
formations of various types. Agate Fossil Beds
National Monument (2,700 acres) in northwestern
Nebraska contains numerous wellpreserved
Miocene mammal fossils. Alibates
Flint Quarries National Monument (1,100
acres) is located in the Texas Panhandle adjacent
to Lake Meredith National Recreation
Area. For more than 10,000 years, Native
Americans dug agatized dolomite from quarries
here to make projectile points, knives,
scrapers, and other tools.</p>

<p>Salinas Pueblo Missions National Monument
(1,071 acres) is located at the western edge
of the Great Plains in central New Mexico. This
park preserves and interprets the best remaining
examples of seventeenth-century Spanish
Franciscan mission churches and conventos. At
Fort Union National Monument (720 acres) in
northeastern New Mexico, three U.S. Army
forts were built during the second half of the
nineteenth century; they were key supply
points along the Santa Fe Trail. The largest
visible network of wagon ruts on this trail can
be seen here. Little Bighorn Battlefield National
Monument (765 acres) in southeastern
Montana is the site of the Battle of the Little
Bighorn between the Seventh Cavalry and the
Sioux and Northern Cheyenne Indians in 1876.
Homestead National Monument of America
(195 acres) in southeastern Nebraska was established
to commemorate the Homestead Act
of 1862. The massive promontory of Scotts
Bluff that rises 800 feet above the valley floor in
Scotts Bluff National Monument (3,000 acres)
in the western Nebraska Panhandle was a
prominent natural landmark for emigrants on
the Oregon Trail. This site preserves the memory
of the Oregon, California, and Mormon
Trails. The Summit Road allows visitors to
drive to the top of Scotts Bluff for a spectacular
view of the North Platte River valley.</p>

<p>Three national recreation areas in the National
Park System are located within the Great
Plains. Chickasaw National Recreation Area
(9,900 acres), named to honor the Chickasaw
Indian Nation, is located in south-central Oklahoma
at the eastern edge of the Great Plains.
This area was originally designated as Sulphur
Springs Reservation in 1902, then redesignated
as Platt National Park in 1906. In 1976 Platt
National Park and Arbuckle National Recreation
Area were combined, and the area was
renamed Chickasaw National Recreation Area.
The partially forested rolling hills and the
springs, streams, and lakes are the setting for a
diverse number of outdoor recreation activities
that attract 1.5 million visitors per year.
Two reservoirs in Texas serve as important centers
for water-based recreation, with each recording
1.5 million visits annually: Amistad
National Recreation Area (58,500 acres), in
the U.S. section of the Amistad Reservoir along
the Rio Grande near Del Rio, and Lake Meredith
National Recreation Area (46,000 acres),
which surrounds Lake Meredith on the Canadian
River in the Texas Panhandle.</p>

<p>There is one unit in each of the classifications
of national historical park and national
memorial in the Great Plains. Lyndon B.
Johnson National Historical Park (1,570 acres)
is located in the Texas Hill Country of southern
Texas north of San Antonio and consists
of the birthplace, boyhood home, and ranch
of the thirty-sixth president, his grandparents'
log cabin, and the Johnson family cemetery.
The humble nature of Lyndon Johnson is reflected
in this simple cemetery under the live
oaks on the banks of the Pedernales River,
with his pet beagles buried nearby. At Mount
Rushmore National Memorial (1,250 acres) in
the Black Hills of southwestern South Dakota
colossal heads of Presidents George Washington,
Thomas Jefferson, Abraham Lincoln, and
Theodore Roosevelt were sculpted by Gutzon
Borglum on the face of a granite mountain.
The memorial has a new visitor center and the
Presidential Trail, which runs along the base
of the mountain.</p>

<p>The ten units of the National Park System
in the Great Plains that are classified as national
historic sites vary in size from the 1.85-acre
Brown v. Board of Education National
Historic Site (Kansas) to the 1,750-acre Knife
River Indian Villages National Historic Site
(North Dakota). Six of these national historic
sites are forts that relate to key events in westward
expansion: Bent's Old Fort (Colorado),
Fort Larned (Kansas), Fort Scott (Kansas),
Fort Union Trading Post (North Dakota,
Montana), Fort Davis (Texas), and Fort Laramie
(Wyoming). Two of these parks are dedicated
to Native American themes: Knife River
Indian Villages (North Dakota) and Washita
Battlefield (Oklahoma). Two parks are dedicated
to African American themes: Brown v.
Board of Education (Kansas) and Nicodemus
(Kansas).</p>

<p>Linear units of the National Park System in
the Great Plains that are located in the region
for at least part of their extent include seven
trails in the National Trail System and one
national river. The trails are North Country
National Scenic Trail (North Dakota),
Lewis and Clark National Historic Trail (Nebraska,
South Dakota, North Dakota, Montana),
Mormon Pioneer National Historic
Trail (Nebraska, Colorado), Santa Fe National
Historic Trail (Kansas, Colorado, Oklahoma,
New Mexico), Oregon National Historic Trail
(Kansas, Nebraska, Wyoming), Pony Express
National Historic Trail (Kansas, Nebraska,
Wyoming), and California National Historic
Trail (Kansas, Nebraska, Wyoming). The Missouri
National Recreation River (Nebraska,
South Dakota) is one of the last free-flowing
stretches of the river, extending from Gavin's
Point Dam near Yankton, South Dakota, to
Ponca, Nebraska.</p>

<p>In Canada, Parks Canada manages the three
national parks in the Great Plains. Riding
Mountain National Park (741,312 acres) is located
on the eastern edge of the interior Plains,
west of the Canadian Shield in southwestern
Manitoba. The park occupies part of the rugged
landscape of the 500-mile-long Manitoba Escarpment
west of Lake Manitoba, standing 1,500
feet above the surrounding plains. In 1895 the
federal government designated the Riding
Mountain area as a timber reserve. It was redesignated
as a national park in 1930, taking
its name from the park's dominant landform
feature&#8211;Riding Mountain. The park has three
distinctive vegetation zones, creating some of
the greatest natural diversity in Canada. The
park is essentially an area of boreal forests surrounded
by aspen parkland. A third major forest
type, eastern deciduous forest, occupies the
lowest and warmest areas in the park on the
rich soils that have built up along the base of
the escarpment. The park is known for the
number of its wildlife species. Large mammals
include black bears, moose, elk, wolves, and
coyotes. Waterfowl and beavers are plentiful
along the waterways, and a herd of bison is
kept in a large enclosure near Lake Audy. The
seventy-eight-mile road system allows access
throughout the park for sightseeing, wildlife
viewing, and canoeing. There are 250 miles of
hiking, biking, and horse trails in the park. The
main area of recreational development is at
Wasagaming on Clear Lake, a Victorian-style
resort that features one of the finest collections
of log buildings in Canada. Five campgrounds
with a total of 600 sites are located in the park.
There are also two group campsites that can
accommodate a maximum of 100 people. Although
the park is open all year, complete facilities
are available only from mid-May to
mid-October. On the escarpment in the east is
located Agassiz Ski Hill for downhill skiing in
the winter.</p>

<p>Grasslands National Park is located in
southwestern Saskatchewan near the
Saskatchewan-Montana border. This is one of the
largest pieces of virtually undisturbed mixed-grass
prairie in North America. It may be several
years before the park is fully established, so
interim management guidelines have been established
to direct the management of park
lands, visitor activities, and sensitive resources.
The park, when fully established, will encompass
350 square miles in two distinct blocks.
The West Block includes the Frenchman River
valley. This glacial meltwater channel features
deeply dissected plateaus, coulees, and the
conspicuous Seventy Mile Butte. The park's
East Block features the Killdeer Badlands of the
Rock Creek area and is representative of the
Wood Mountain Upland. The Killdeer Badlands,
untouched by glaciation, reveal the multicolored
hues of 60,000 years of eroded strata
and are the location of the first recorded discovery
of dinosaur remains in Canada (1874).
Among the wildlife species found in the park
are prairie dogs, golden eagles, prairie rattlesnakes,
badgers, mule deer, and pronghorn
antelope. Ranching operations are still ongoing
in much of the area that is in private ownership.
There are no designated campgrounds
within the park boundaries. Only primitive,
random tent camping is available. Limited essential
services and a fully developed campground
are located in Val Marie, just outside
the boundary of the West Block. Near the East
Block of the park, the town of Wood Mountain
provides very limited services.</p>

<p>The 48,000-acre Elk Island National Park,
located in the Beaver Hills region twenty-eight
miles east of Edmonton, Alberta, is an oasis
for rare and endangered species attracted by
its lakes, ponds, forests, and meadows. Originally
established in 1906 to protect a herd of
twenty elk, the park is home to moose, bear,
beaver, and coyote. The park is also a special
venue in which to enjoy spectacular prairie
sunsets. It is open all year, and most recreation
facilities center on Astotin Lake. Sixty miles
of trails are popular with hikers and crosscountry
skiers.</p>

<p>Parks Canada administers the following national
historic sites in the Great Plains: in Manitoba,
Linear Mounds, Riding Mountain Park
East Gate Registration Complex, Riel House,
The Forks, St. Andrews Rectory, and Lower
Fort Garry; and in Saskatchewan, Frenchman
Butte, Fort Battleford, Batoche, Battle of Fish
Creek, Fort Livingstone, Fort Pelly, Motherwell
Homestead, and Fort Esperance.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">IMAGES AND ICONS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ii.036">Homestead National Monument of America</ref>; <ref n="egp.ii.043">Mount Rushmore National Memorial</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT</hi>:
<ref n="egp.pe.007">Badlands</ref>; <ref n="egp.pe.017">Carlsbad Caverns</ref>; <ref n="egp.pe.049">Prairie Preservation</ref>.</p>

<p><ref target="http://www.nps.gov/index.htm">National Park Service</ref> website.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Charles I. Zinser<lb/>
Pittsburgh State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Zinser, Charles I. <title level="m">Outdoor Recreation: United States National
Parks, Forests and Public Lands</title>. New York: John
Wiley and Sons, 1995.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>