<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.pd.015">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Cowboy Strike of 1883</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Art Chapman</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.pd.015</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Chapman, Art">Art Chapman</author>. <title level="a">"Cowboy Strike of 1883."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">708-709</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-06</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">COWBOY STRIKE OF 1883</head>

<p>From 1880 to 1883 a new corporate ownership
spread throughout the Texas Panhandle. Ranch
cowboys no longer knew the owners by name,
had any particular trust in the new company, or
saw any signs of loyalty or tradition. The cowboy
lost his place as a valued member of the ranch
family and became only an employee.</p>

<p>The country was in transition. Large urban
populations needed to be fed. Cattle were
cheap, grass free, and the railroads made
transportation possible. But the corporations
and cattle syndicates who bought their way
into the Plains didn't figure on the cost of
freezing winters and stifling drought. General
ignorance of livestock became their biggest liability,
and the only controllable cost they
could find was the cowboy.</p>

<p>Even before the new owners came, a cowboy's
job was never easy. Aside from working
roundups twice a year, they rode the fence
line, branded cattle, and doctored sick animals.
They slept in a dank dugout, or perhaps
a tent, if anything. Everything they ate came
out of one pot. But a ranch hand could take
part of his pay in calves, or if he was lucky, he
could round up enough maverick cows to begin
his own small herd. He was furnished several
horses to do his work, and the longer he
worked for the ranch, the better the horses he
was given.</p>

<p>The new owners decided to claim the orphaned,
unbranded cattle as their own, and
they put strict limits on the use of ranch
horses. No one got more than two horses, and
they were to be left in the corral when the day
was done. Perhaps even worse, the corporate
ranches decided that their men could not
carry any weapons, play cards or gamble in
any other way, nor could they take a drink of
alcohol while in the employment of the ranch.</p>

<p>In the spring of 1883 the cowboys went on
strike. Wagons and men from three of the biggest
ranches in the Canadian River valley
came together for a meeting. The three wagon
bosses were not malcontents. They were all
respected top hands who had earned their
positions only to see their influence diminished.
They took a bold step, writing the following
proclamation:</p>

     <p rend="indent2">We, the undersigned cowboys of Canadian
     river, do by these presents agree to
     bind ourselves into the following obligations:
     First, that we will not work for less
     than $50 per month, and we furthermore
     agree no one shall work for less than $50
     per month, after 31st of March.</p>

     <p rend="indent2">Second, good cooks shall also receive $50
     per month.</p>

     <p rend="indent2">Third, anyone running an outfit shall
     not work for less than $75 per month. Anyone
     violating the above obligations shall
     suffer the consequences. Those not having
     funds to pay board after March 31st will be
     provided for 30 days at Tascosa.</p>

<p>Twenty-four men signed the proclamations.
Five copies were made, and each one
was delivered to a large ranch.</p>

<p>It was a foolish move. Many of the better
cowboys already made more money than the
petition called for, and the cowboys reluctantly
admitted that some among their ranks
were not worth the prescribed $50 a month.
Also, there was no shortage of labor in the
Panhandle. The cattle business in the lower
part of the state was in disarray, and South
Texas cowboys were willing to make the long
ride for a solid job. As the "scab" crews were
put together, the strikers were ordered off the
ranches and told that they would never work
again on the Texas Plains. In thirty days, the
strike was over and the cowboys had lost.
Many of them left the Panhandle; those who
stayed took jobs in town.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Art Chapman<lb/>
Fort Worth, Texas</signed>
</closer>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>