<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.na.105">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Shoshones</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Christopher Loether</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.na.105</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Loether, Christopher">Christopher Loether</author>. <title level="a">"Shoshones."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">600</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-20</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">SHOSHONES</head>

<p>"Shoshone" comes from the Shoshone word
<hi rend="italic">sosoni</hi>', which is a plural form of sonipe, a type
of high-growing grass. Several tribes on the
Plains referred to the Shoshones as the "Grass
House People," and this name probably refers
to the conically shaped houses made of native
grasses (sosoni') used by the Great Basin Indians.
The more common term used by Shoshone
people is Newe, or "People." The name
Shoshone was first recorded in 1805 after Meriwether
Lewis encountered a group of "Sosonees
or snake Indians" among the Crows and
noted them in his diary. The Shoshones were
also called the "Snake People" by some Plains
Indians. The origin of the term Snake People
is based on the sign, in Indian sign language,
that the Shoshone people used for themselves.
The hand motion made during the sign represents
a snake to most signers, but among
the Shoshones it referred to the salmon, a fish
unknown to the Great Plains. Today, many
Shoshones have adopted the term Sosoni' to
refer to other groups of Shoshones besides
themselves. The Shoshone language is spoken
by approximately 5,000 people across Nevada,
Idaho, and Wyoming. It belongs to the
western branch of the Numic group of Uto-
Aztecan languages.</p>

<p>Since the Shoshones are widespread across
the West, anthropologists have divided them
into three groups based on where they live: the
Western Shoshones of Nevada, the Northern
Shoshones of Idaho, and the Eastern Shoshones
of Wyoming. The different bands of
Shoshone speakers share many cultural traits.
The Eastern Shoshones are the only band that
has adopted a Great Plains way of life.</p>

<p>The prehistory of the Shoshone people&#8211;
how their ancestors (the Numa) were able to
occupy a large portion of the Great Basin (Nevada
and Utah), in addition to the contiguous
areas of Idaho and Wyoming&#8211;is a debated
topic. The origin of the Numa is believed to be
the southwestern corner of the Great Basin. By
1500 Shoshones had crossed the Rocky Mountains
and begun their expansion toward the
northwestern Plains. By 1700 a group of Shoshones
had moved into the Southern Plains
and eventually developed their own identity as
the Comanches. The current location of the
Eastern Shoshones in central Wyoming is the
result of a period of intense warfare from
1780 to 1825 against the Blackfeet, Crows, and
Assiniboines.</p>

<p>The Eastern Shoshones divided themselves
into two groups, based on geographical location
and primary food resource. Shoshones
living in the Green River and Wind River valleys
of Wyoming were known as the Buffalo
Eaters (<hi rend="italic">Guchundeka'</hi>) or the Sage Grass People
(<hi rend="italic">Boho'inee'</hi>). Shoshones living in the Rocky
Mountains and Lake Yellowstone areas were
known as the Sheep-eaters (<hi rend="italic">Dukundeka'</hi>) or
the Mountain People (<hi rend="italic">Doyahinee'</hi>).</p>

<p>The subsistence cycle of the Eastern Shoshones
in the winter involved the tribe breaking
into bands, each loosely associated with a
particular mountain or valley. In early spring
these bands reunited in the Wind River valley
before going to the bison grounds for the
spring hunt. After the spring hunt, most Eastern
Shoshones spent their early summer in
the Wind River valley. Then, in late June and
early July, the intertribal rendezvous (or trade
fair) was held at Fort Bridger. After the fair the
Shoshones broke up into family groups until
the fall bison hunt, when the tribe would
come together one last time before the winter.</p>

<p>Bison meat played an extremely significant
role culturally and economically in the lives of
the Eastern Shoshones, accounting for about
50 percent of their diet at the height of the
Plains horse culture in the 1700s. Fish caught
during the spring and early summer were the
second most important resource. Elk, mule
deer, beaver, jackrabbit, and mountain sheep
were also important sources of protein. Berries
were either eaten raw, made into soup, or
mixed with dried, powdered meat and fat to
produce pemmican. Also, roots were eaten after
being baked in earthen ovens.</p>

<p>Shoshone arts and industries exploited
wood resources, animal products such as
leather, sinew, bone, and minerals such as obsidian,
flint, steatite, and slate. Leather working
was done mostly by women, except for
bowstrings, shields, drums, and rattles, which
men produced. Iron, only available through
trade, became an important material used in
making arrow and spear points as well as
knives.</p>

<p>The roles of men and women in Shoshone
society were strictly regulated. Women were
traditionally in charge of plant gathering,
butchering and preparing bison, household
chores, crafting items such as tipis and clothing,
and child care. Men were in charge of
hunting, warfare, and the political and economic
decisions for the tribe.</p>

<p>The tribal chief (<hi rend="italic">daigwahni</hi>) was an older
man who had distinguished himself in warfare
and possessed supernatural power. The chief
controlled collective hunts and the tribe's
movements. During times of warfare a special
war chief was chosen. There were two Shoshone
military societies: the Yellow Brows
and the Logs. The Yellow Brows were young
warriors who were the advanced forces in battle,
whereas the Logs were older men who
brought up the rear. These military societies
also acted as a police force when the tribe
gathered together.</p>

<p>The Shoshone religion is based on belief in
supernatural power (<hi rend="italic">boha</hi>) that is acquired
primarily through vision quests and dreams.
A shaman (<hi rend="italic">boha gande</hi>) is a person who uses
supernatural power to cure others and also
leads special group ceremonies, especially at
"Round Dances." The Eastern Shoshones also
adopted two pan-Indian religions, the Sun
Dance and the Native American Church. The
Sun Dance was introduced to the Eastern Shoshones
by a Comanche named Yellow Hand
around 1800. Originally the Eastern Shoshones
had rejected the missionary activities
of the peyote religion of the Comanches, but
the Native American Church gained influence
after it was reintroduced by Arapahos in the
early part of the twentieth century.</p>

<p>In 1868 the Shoshones of the Plains ceded
their ancestral lands and were placed on a reservation
in the lee of the Wind River Range of
Wyoming. The Wind River Reservation now
extends over 2,268,000 acres and is shared by
Eastern Shoshones (who live mainly in the
west and northwest) and Arapahos (who live
mainly in the east and southeast). The Shoshone
population on the reservation was 1,185
in 1988, following years of out-migration in
response to dire poverty and high unemployment
rates.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Christopher Loether</signed>
Idaho State University</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Shimkin, Demetri. "Eastern Shoshone." In <title level="m">Handbook of
North American Indians</title>, edited by William C. Sturtevant,
11:308–35. Washington <hi rend="smallcaps">DC</hi>: Smithsonian Institution, 1986.</bibl>
<bibl>Trenholm, Virginia Cole, and Maurine Carley. <title level="m">The Shoshones:
Sentinels of the Rockies</title>. Norman: University of Oklahoma
Press, 1964.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>