<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.wat.002">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Appropriation Doctrine</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Theron Josephson</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.wat.002</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Josephson, Theron">Theron Josephson</author>. <title level="a">"Appropriation Doctrine."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">850-851</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-29</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">APPROPRIATION DOCTRINE</head>

<p>The appropriation doctrine is a system of water
rights that gives an individual the right
to use a quantifiable amount of water. The
appropriation doctrine is also referred to as
prior appropriation because the right to use
water is prioritized on the basis of the date
the use was established. This characteristic is
often summed up in the phrase "first in time,
first in right." Under appropriation law, the
first person to obtain an appropriation right
receives the right to use a fixed amount of
water without regard for other water users. In
the case of a water shortage, the holder of the
first prioritized right receives his or her entire
amount to the possible exclusion of all others.
Subsequent appropriative rights are filled
based on the order of the dates of acquisition,
until there is no more water available.</p>

<p>Traditionally there are three elements necessary
to acquire an appropriative right: intent to
use the water, a physical diversion of the water
from the natural stream course, and an application
of the water diverted to a beneficial
use. Once acquired the right can be bought and
sold. Water obtained under the appropriation
doctrine can be used in a manner not consistent
with the use existing at the time the right
was acquired, so long as it is considered a "beneficial"
use. An appropriative right is a usufructuary
right, or right to use the water, as
opposed to owning the water itself. There is no
requirement that the water be applied to riparian
land or even to land within the same
watershed. Thus the appropriation doctrine
promotes the consumptive use of water as a
commodity, without regard to the location of
the use or location of the source.</p>

<p>The rationale of the doctrine comes from
personal property law theory. Traditionally,
society is deemed enriched as individuals
transform nature into usable economic commodities.
For example, the law gave individuals
incentives to capture wild animals or to
mine gold by giving the person title to that
which he or she had brought into possession.
In like manner, water meandering through the
Great Plains was captured by individuals and
transformed into an economic commodity
usable to settlers.</p>

<p>The appropriation doctrine originated in
California as nineteenth-century miners looked
for ways to augment the supply of water needed
for mining operations. The doctrine first became
law in the Great Plains in 1882 as a remedy
for conflicts arising from agricultural water use
in northeastern Colorado. Promoted by agricultural
interests in the Great Plains, the appropriation
doctrine was widely adopted as an
alternative to riparian rights because of a
common vision of future growth and a perception
of water scarcity in the region. The
doctrine promoted settlement because it allowed
water to be detached and used in areas
remote from the stream. Appropriation law
rewarded those who had diverted water for
use in a dry environment by giving them a
secure right to a quantifiable amount of water
upon which to base their operations. In North
Dakota, South Dakota, Nebraska, and Kansas,
appropriation is now the exclusive means of
acquiring water rights, and in Oklahoma the
conflicting doctrine of riparian rights is restricted
to household and livestock uses.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Theron Josephson<lb/>
Ferris State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Dunbar, Robert G. <title level="m">Forging New Rights in Western Water</title>.
Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1983.</bibl> <bibl>Hutchins,
W. A. <title level="m">Water Rights in the Nineteen Western States</title>. Washington
<hi rend="smallcaps">DC</hi>: Government Printing Office, 1974.</bibl> <bibl>Trelease,
Frank J., and George A. Gould. <title level="m">Cases and Materials on
Water Law</title>, 4th ed. St. Paul <hi rend="smallcaps">MN</hi>: West Publishing Company,
1986.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>