<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ag.071">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Taylor Grazing Act</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Laurence A. Clement Jr.</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ag.071</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Clement Jr., Laurence A.">Laurence A. Clement Jr.</author>. <title level="a">"Taylor Grazing Act."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">55</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2009-01-12</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">TAYLOR GRAZING ACT</head>

<p>Public agency management of the federal
grazing lands began with the passage of the
Taylor Grazing Act on June 28, 1934, as dust
from the worst storms in the nation's history
settled on Washington <hi rend="smallcaps">DC</hi>. Enacted after decades
of rangeland deterioration, conflicts between
cattle ranchers and migratory sheepherders,
jurisdictional disputes, and states'
rights debates, the act and its amendments
ended free access to the range. The purposes
of the act were to stop injury to the public
lands; provide for their orderly use, improvement,
and development; and stabilize the livestock
industry dependent on the public range.
The new law effectively closed the rangelands
to homesteading in the Dakotas and western
states.</p>

<p>The act as amended in 1936 established
grazing districts on the vacant, unappropriated
and unreserved lands of the public domain:
fifty-nine districts encompassing 168
million acres of federal land and 97 million
acres otherwise owned. The act, as amended
in 1939, established grazing advisory boards,
primarily composed of livestock owners.
Board duties included the allocation of permits
and the determination of boundaries,
seasons of use, and the carrying capacity of the
range. This gave rise to the Federal Range
Code and the criticism by some commentators
that the advisory boards constituted a private
government.</p>

<p>A new permit system granted grazing privileges
by preference to ranchers who had actually
used a grazing district's land during a priority
period before 1934. Owners of land or
water rights who could support livestock on
base ranches during seasons when herds were
not on the grazing districts were favored;
those without property were not. Technically,
the grazing permit is a revocable license under
the law, not creating any right, title, interest,
or estate in or to land, but it is considered
by many to be a unique form of ownership,
constituting a property right of the utmost
importance.</p>

<p>The act created the Grazing Service, but inadequate
funding prevented effective observation
and evaluation of range use. Permitted
animal unit months were set at preexisting
1934 stock levels. Efforts to reduce stock levels
inevitably failed. The Grazing Service and
General Land Office were consolidated in 1946
to form the Bureau of Land Management,
which continues today to administer grazing
lands not in the national forests.</p>

<p>The basis for grazing fees has always been
controversial. Initially fees were set to cover
only administrative costs. Western senators
have opposed increasing the fees, despite obvious
shortages of administrative resources,
arguing that costs are higher on lower quality
lands and fees comparable to those charged by
the Forest Service would be unfair. Other legislators
and groups interested in conservation
and recreation have called for increased fees
as a condition for larger appropriations. The
1970 Public Land Law Review Commission
and a 1986 study by the General Accounting
Office recommended raising the fee to fair
market value. Efforts in the Department of the
Interior to increase fees, however, were abandoned
after the 1994 election.</p>

<p>Subchapter IV of the Federal Lands Policy
and Management Act of 1976 and the Public
Rangelands Improvement Act of 1978 have
superceded the Taylor Grazing Act. Measuring
carrying capacity, determining a viable
basis for grazing fees, incorporating public
participation into land management decisions,
and balancing competing demands
for access all continue to challenge rangeland
policymakers.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</hi>: <ref n="egp.pg.054">New Deal</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Laurence A. Clement Jr.<lb/>
Kansas State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Clawson, Marion, and Burnell Held. <title level="m">The Federal Lands: Their Use and Management</title>. Lincoln: University of Nebraska
Press, 1957.</bibl> <bibl>Coggins, George Cameron, and Robert
L. Glicksman. <title level="m">Public Natural Resources Law</title>. St. Paul:
West Group, 1998.</bibl> <bibl>Foss, Phillip O. <title level="m">Politics and Grass: The Administration of Grazing on the Public Domain</title>. Seattle:
University of Washington Press, 1960.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>