<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.arc.044">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">State and Provincial Capitols</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>William Paul Thompson</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.arc.044</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Thompson, William Paul">William Paul Thompson</author>. <title level="a">"State and Provincial Capitols."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">95</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-14</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">STATE AND PROVINCIAL CAPITOLS</head>

<p>Capitols in the Great Plains region include
eight in the United States and three in Canada.
They range in date of design from 1866 to 1932,
spanning the Gilded Age, the neoclassicism of
the American Renaissance, and international
modernism. All three of the Canadian capitols
are unicameral, as is the Nebraska State Capitol,
the only example in the United States. The
others are bicameral.</p>

<p>Soon after becoming a state, the Kansas legislature
formed a Capitol Commission in 1866
and elected Col. J. G. Haskell to the post of
state architect. He provided a design to be
built in parts (it took nearly fifty years to complete)
in Topeka based largely on the plan of
the United States Capitol. It included two
wings, one each for House and Senate, and a
central block topped by a dome on a columned
drum. The same model was used in
1886 for Elijah E. Myers's Colorado Capitol in
Denver; for David W. Gibbs's plan for the capitol
in Cheyenne, Wyoming, completed in
1890; for Charles E. Bell and J. H. Kent's design
used in 1898 in Helena, Montana; and for
Charles E. Bell's plan for the South Dakota
Capitol in Pierre in 1907. The model was followed
in Oklahoma City in a 1914 design by
Solomon Layton and S. Wemyss Smith, although
that capitol lacked the planned dome
until 2002. The neoclassical vocabulary and
central dome of these plans were also used
in the three Canadian provincial legislative
buildings: by Edward and William S. Maxwell
in 1907 in Regina, Saskatchewan; by A. M.
Jeffers and John Chalmers in Edmonton, Alberta,
in 1908; and by Frank W. Simon in Winnipeg,
Manitoba, in 1912.</p>

<p>The two capitols to break with this tradition
are those designed by Bertram Grosvenor
Goodhue in Lincoln, Nebraska, in 1922 and by
John Holabird and John W. Root Jr. in Bismarck,
North Dakota, in 1932. Each uses an
office-tower block above a base block rather
than a dome. Each breaks with neoclassicism,
the former in a style that combines ancient,
Byzantine, classical, and Gothic elements and
the latter in a strongly modernist idiom, the
International Style.</p>

<p>A key problem for all the architects of capitols
was how to represent the unique identity
of the state or province. The most common
method was to use local materials.stone for
both interiors and exteriors and sometimes
wood for interiors. Despite a legislature's preference
for the fashionable architectural styles
of the era and a respect for precedents in British,
American, and French political traditions,
architects did not want to repeat their predecessors,
especially their own earlier designs.
Thus, Bell in South Dakota and Myers
in Michigan in 1871, Texas in 1882, and finally
Colorado in 1886 developed, varied, and refined
earlier efforts.</p>

<p>Another key means of state identity was
ornamentation. Sculptures (e.g., oil wells,
wheat, bison), adorn these architectural
frames. Murals are the most popular means
of presenting the stories of the pioneers. A
key element in most capitols is a figure atop
the dome. Golden men and women are most
common, especially those representing classical
deities; in some cases, Native peoples are
also depicted, usually in postures of nobility.
All plans provide a variety of ways for visiting
citizens to be impressed by the grandeur of
their political entity while allowing politicians
and bureaucrats to work largely unseen by the
public.</p>

<p>Great Plains capitols are unique in three respects.
First, because the three Canadian Prairie
buildings were designed within five years of
each other, they are different from other earlier
or later provincial capitols. Second, the
materials and ornamentation reflect each capitol's
regional identity. Finally, originality is
greatly evident in the Great Plains capitols,
especially in Oklahoma City, Bismarck, and
Lincoln. State legislatures preferred to choose
local architects. Despite the fact that the most
renowned architects of their day were not chosen,
some of the most exuberant and innovative
capitols in North America were erected.</p>

<closer>
<signed>William Paul Thompson<lb/>
University of Manitoba</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Hitchcock, Henry Russell, and William Steele. <title level="m">Temples of Democracy</title>. New York: Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, 1976.</bibl>
<bibl>Kalman, Harold. <title level="m">A History of Canadian Architecture</title>. Toronto:
Oxford University Press, 1994.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>