<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.law.015">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Dawes Act</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Mark R. Scherer</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.law.015</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Mark, Scherer R.">Mark R. Scherer</author>. <title level="a">"Dawes Act."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">450-451</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-04</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">DAWES ACT</head>

<p>Formally titled the General Allotment Act of
1887, the Dawes Act (also commonly referred
to as the Dawes Severalty Act) authorized the
president of the United States to subdivide
tribal reservations into private parcels of land
that would then be "allotted" to individual
members of each tribe. Designed to detribalize
Indians and assimilate them into mainstream
white society by transforming them into selfsupporting
farmers and ranchers, the Dawes
Act became one of the most far-reaching and,
for Native Americans, disastrous pieces of Indian
legislation ever passed by Congress. By
the time the allotment process was stopped in
1934, the amount of Indian-held land in the
United States had dropped from 138 million
acres to 48 million acres, and, of the remaining
Indian-owned land, almost half was arid or
semiarid desert.</p>

<p>Under the act, heads of families received
quarter-section parcels of 160 acres, while
other individuals were granted smaller tracts
of up to 80 acres. Allotments deemed to be
suitable only for grazing were doubled in size.
Once the president directed that a particular
reservation be broken up pursuant to the act,
tribal members were given four years to select
their specific allotment. If no such selection
was made, the government made the selection
for the individual. Each allotted tribal member
received a patent, or trust deed, which
provided that the United States would hold
title to the land in trust for the benefit of
the nominal Indian "owner" for a period of
twenty-five years. Proponents of the legislation
envisioned that during the trust period
Indian allottees would adapt to the farming
lifestyle and become increasingly self-reliant
through the ownership and control of private
property. Perhaps most significantly, the act
further provided that tribal lands that were
unallocated and therefore deemed "surplus"
could be offered for sale to non-Indians, with
the revenues to be held in trust by the government
for the benefit of the tribes.</p>

<p>The Dawes Act affected reservations
throughout the Great Plains, except in Indian
Territory, which was not subject to allotment
until the establishment of the Dawes Commission
in 1893 and the passage of the Curtis Act
in 1898. For example, the Devils Lake Sioux
Reservation in North Dakota was allotted in
1904 over the objections of many of its residents.
The allotments amounted to about
136,000 acres, leaving 92,000 surplus acres to
be sold to non-Indians. It was through the
allotment process that Plains reservations became
"checkerboarded" in complex patterns
of white-owned private property and Indian
trust lands.</p>

<p>Most modern commentators concede that
the proponents of the Dawes Act, including its
primary legislative sponsor and namesake,
Senator Henry L. Dawes of Massachusetts,
were motivated by a sincere interest in the
well-being and future prosperity of Native
Americans. "Reformers" inside and outside
the government viewed tribalism and traditional
Indian cultural practices as impediments
to the long-term survival and "advancement"
of Native Americans&#8211;obstacles
that could only be overcome by breaking up
the reservations and forcing Indians to adopt
a more "civilized" lifestyle. Other analysts insist
that allotment was never intended to be
anything more than a disingenuous legal
cover for whites who coveted Indian lands.
Whatever the appropriate interpretation of
the motivations behind the Dawes Act, the allotment
era that the act ushered in is today
universally viewed as one of the darkest chapters
in the annals of federal-Indian relations.
Individual landownership was and is contrary
to most traditional Native American beliefs
and practices. Moreover, many Indians had
no desire to become sedentary farmers and
were woefully unprepared and ill equipped to
succeed in that occupation even if they had
wanted to. The value of the parcels of thousands
of allottees was quickly dissipated or lost
entirely through tax foreclosures, distressed
sales, or unfavorable lease arrangements. Millions
of surplus acres were sold or leased away
by the government as well, and the ultimate
effect of the allotment program was to separate
Native Americans from millions of acres
of their lands without accomplishing any of
the "reforms" intended by the act's proponents.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">NATIVE AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.na.002">Allotment</ref>; <ref n="egp.na.008">Assimilation Policy</ref>; <ref n="egp.na.096">Reservations</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Mark R. Scherer<lb/>
University of Nebraska at Omaha</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Prucha, Francis Paul. <title level="m">The Great Father: The United States Government and the American Indians</title>. Lincoln: University
of Nebraska Press, 1986.</bibl> <bibl>Washburn, Wilcomb. <title level="m">The Assault on Indian Tribalism: The General Allotment Law (Dawes Act) of 1887</title>. Philadelphia: J. B. Lippincott, 1975.</bibl>
<bibl>Wunder, John R. <title level="m">Retained by the People: A History of American Indians and the Bill of Rights</title>. New York: Oxford
University Press, 1994.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>