<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.sr.028">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Hogan, Ben (1912-1997)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Mark R. Ellis</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.sr.028</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Ellis, Mark R.">Mark R. Ellis</author>. <title level="a">"Hogan, Ben (1912-1997)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">776</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-21</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">HOGAN, BEN (1912-1997)</head>

<p>William Benjamin "Bantam Ben" Hogan,
America's premier golfer during the 1940s and
1950s, was born on August 13, 1912, in Dublin,
Texas. At the age of nine his father committed
suicide, forcing the family to move to Fort
Worth. As a youngster Ben helped supplement
the meager family income by selling newspapers
and working as a caddie at Glen Garden
Country Club. Hogan began playing on
his days off and quickly became a proficient
golfer after switching from a left- to a right-handed
swing.</p>

<p>He turned professional at the age of seventeen
but struggled for the first decade of
his golfing career due to a propensity for slicing
the ball. Throughout his early golfing career
he was forced to take odd jobs to support
his wife, Valerie, whom he had married in
1937. By 1940, however, after countless hours
at the driving range perfecting his swing,
Hogan finished the year with five tournament
wins and was the country's leading money
winner. His professional career was put on
hold between 1942 and 1945 due to military
service in the Army Air Corps, but he returned
to the professional tour in 1946 and
won the Professional Golfers' Association
(<hi rend="smallcaps">PGA</hi>) Championship.</p>

<p>Hogan's career and life nearly ended in 1949
when a bus hit his car head-on and it seemed
that he would never walk again. Determined
to prove his doctors wrong, Hogan recovered
and returned to the tour in 1951, winning the
U.S. Open and the Masters tournaments that
year. Lingering injuries, however, limited
Hogan to only seven tournaments a year. In
1953, arguably his finest year, Hogan won five
of six tournaments, including his fourth U.S.
Open title, his second Masters, and the British
Open. Hogan continued to win tournaments
until his retirement in 1960.</p>

<p>Hogan was known as a fierce competitor.
With his signature white visor pulled low over
his eyes, he intimidated opponents by blocking
out everything around him as he drove
toward the green. Hogan ended his career
with sixty-three tournament wins (third all-time),
including four U.S. Opens and two
Masters titles. He was a four-time <hi rend="smallcaps">PGA</hi> player
of the year and is a member of every golf Hall
of Fame, including the <hi rend="smallcaps">PGA</hi> Hall of Fame.</p>

<p>After retiring Hogan focused on the golf
equipment business that he had established
in Fort Worth during the 1950s. Although he
sold the company in 1960, he remained as the
chairman and played an important role in golf
club design for the next twenty years. Hogan
died on July 25, 1997, in Fort Worth, Texas.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Mark R. Ellis<lb/>
University of Nebraska at Kearney</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Sampson, Curt. <title level="m">Hogan</title>. Nashville: Rutledge Hill Press,
2001.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>