<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.arc.056">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Wooden Frames</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Fred W. Peterson</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.arc.056</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Peterson, Fred W.">Fred W. Peterson</author>. <title level="a">"Wooden Frames."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">100-101</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-14</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">WOODEN FRAMES</head>

<p>Wooden-frame structures are among the oldest
made by human beings for physical shelter,
storage of goods, and protection of livestock.
Immigrants from the forested regions of western
and northern Europe brought traditions
of building with wood to North America in
successive waves of immigration from the seventeenth
through the twentieth centuries. Pioneer
settlement of the Great Plains by Americans,
Canadians, and European immigrants
occurred from the 1850s to the 1920s, just as
new American industries directly facilitated
the construction of wooden buildings.</p>

<p>After about 1870, steam-powered sawmills
in the upper Midwest were mass-producing
building materials for wooden-frame structures,
supplanting low-production lumber
mills powered by local streams and rivers. Beginning
in the 1830s eastern manufacturers
produced iron nails, and by the 1890s wire
steel nails were available. Transport of these
construction materials on navigable waterways,
mainly the Missouri, supplied major
distribution centers in the region. Then, after
1860, railroad lines diffused building materials
to new communities throughout the Great
Plains. Every fledgling railroad town on the
Plains had its lumberyard.</p>

<p>European American settlers often followed
traditional methods of building learned in
eastern Canada and the United States or in
Europe. Timber-frame structures were typically
composed of eight-by-eight-inch corner
posts, three-by-five-inch studs, and four-by-four-
inch rafters. Builders used hand tools to
prepare each unit of the frame according to
proportionate size and scale, finished the units
with appropriate mortise-and-tenon cuts, and
joined sections of the frame with these joints.
Timber-frame structures required at least one
year for the thick members of the frame to
cure, weeks for skilled carpenters to cut joints,
and a crew of five to six workers to set sections
of the frame in place. Plains settlers used
this framing technique for houses, inns, commercial
buildings, and larger outbuildings on
farms, especially barns.</p>

<p>Braced-frame structures were used for
buildings of two or more stories such as
stores, warehouses, and imposing dwellings.
A braced-frame structure consisted of moderate-
size milled-lumber members of six-by-six-
inch posts, two-by-six-inch studs, and
two-by-four-inch rafters. Posts and studs were
usually mortised into a heavy sill and plate
and, like other sections of the frame, nailed in
place. To reinforce the structure, carpenters
installed a diagonal brace at the top and bottom
of the frame at each corner of the external
wall. This method of framing satisfied conservative
builders' preferences for a strong timber
frame while taking advantage of some of
the e.ciencies of building with milled lumber
and nails.</p>

<p>Balloon-frame construction developed
when dimension lumber became available
throughout the region during the 1860s. A
balloon-frame structure is composed of light-weight
four-by-four-inch corner posts, two-by-
four-inch studs, and two-by-four-inch rafters
nailed together at every joint, creating a
basketlike network of components that reinforce
and strengthen each other in an integrated
series of structural relations. Balloon-frame
buildings are identified by an uninterrupted
rise of the two-by-four-inch vertical
studs nailed to the sill at the foundation and to
the plate at the top. Studs are doubled at the
corners and at door and window openings to
reinforce these sections of the frame. The interval
between each stud is sixteen inches on
center in order to receive forty-eight-inchlong
lath used as support for the interior plaster
walls and ceilings. Door and window openings
are usually thirty-two inches wide to
preserve the sixteen-inch spacing of the studs.
Carpenters nail floor joists measuring two by
eight inches or two by ten inches to the studs
along the exterior side walls. First-story joists
are positioned on the sill; second-story joists
are supported by a horizontal ledger or ribbon
that is nailed to the vertical studs. In order
to stiffen these parts, builders nail diagonal
bridging between each joist. A subfloor layer
of rough boards of one by eight inches, surfaced
with one-by-six-inch clear pine boards
or narrow strips of hardwood, serves as the
flooring. Builders enclose the exterior of
the frame with a layer of one-by-eight-inch
to one-by-ten-inch boards and cover that
sheathing with shiplap siding. Rafters measuring
two by six inches or two by four inches,
nailed to the plate at twenty-four-inch intervals,
are covered with roof boards and surfaced
with shingles made of wood or asphalt.</p>

<p>Wall and roof surfaces of balloon-frame
structures enclose a rectangular space covered
by a saddle roof or a square space spanned by
a pyramidal roof. Elevations of balloon-frame
houses vary from one to two and a half stories.
Scale ranges from simple one- or two-room
structures to elaborate asymmetrical extensions
of enclosed spaces. This type of wooden
frame best suits the needs for economical
houses and the skills of local carpenters and
builders. Balloon-frame commercial structures
that fit narrow business lots can rise
from one to three stories and are shaped as
extended rectangles spanned by a saddle roof.
This sloping roofline is usually concealed by
a false-front street facade that rises to the
full height of the structure and is crowned
with a horizontal cornice the full width of the
facade to give the impression of a building
constructed according to traditional classical
design.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">INDUSTRY</hi>: <ref n="egp.ind.036">Lumberyards</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Fred W. Peterson<lb/>
University of Minnesota, Morris</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Peterson, Fred W. <title level="m">Homes in the Heartland: Balloon Frame Farmhouses of the Upper Midwest, 1850–1920</title>. Lawrence:
University Press of Kansas, 1992.</bibl> <bibl>Rempel, John I. <title level="m">Building with Wood and Other Aspects of Nineteenth-Century Building in Central Canada</title>. Toronto: University of Toronto
Press, 1980.</bibl> <bibl>Upton, Dell. "Traditional Timber Framing."
In <title level="m">Material Culture of the Wooden Age</title>, edited by Brooke
Hindle. Tarrytown NY: Sleepy Hollow Press, 1981: 33–96.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>