<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fol.034">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Plant Lore</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Kelly Kindscher</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2009</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fol.034</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2009</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2009 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Kindscher, Kelly">Kelly Kindscher</author>. <title level="a">"Plant Lore."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">309</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-17</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">PLANT LORE</head>

<p>The uses of native plants of the Great Plains
for food, medicine, and utilitarian purposes
were many and of profound importance to
the Native Americans. Plant lore has declined
dramatically since European American settlement,
and the majority of foods and virtually
all medicines today are imported into the region.</p>

<p>The Great Plains has more than 3,000 plant
species. All Native American tribes of the region
used numerous plant species, totaling in
the hundreds. Most of the knowledge of their
uses for food, medicine, and utilitarian purposes
was held in oral histories, and many Native
American uses continue today on Plains
reservations. Anthropologists and ethnobotanists
have recorded much information on the
topic. Not surprisingly, most plants utilized
were prairie plants, although some trees and
shrubs also had important uses.</p>

<p>More native prairie plants (over 200) have
been documented as being used by Plains Indians
for medicine than for any other use.
Some, such as yarrow (<hi rend="italic">Achillea millefolium</hi>)
and the purple coneflower (<hi rend="italic">Echinacea angustifolia</hi>),
were widely used for their general
medicinal qualities. Others, such as locoweed
(<hi rend="italic">Astragalus</hi>), with its toxic amounts of alkaloids
and selenium, were used more successfully
to treat both internal and external
maladies. Most people knew the many common
uses of plants, but there were also highly
trained individuals, medicine men and medicine
women, who had very specific knowledge
about plants and used them in spiritual ceremonies
for healing.</p>

<p>In most cases, the belief system was that the
spirit healed the individual, and that the plant
was a vehicle for this process. The major medicinal
plant cures of Plains Indian tribes have
plausible scientific explanations for their use
and effectiveness. Most of them contain active
medicinal constituents. It is extraordinary
that many of these uses were discovered. Certainly,
much learning occurred through trial
and error, but Native Americans also believed
that knowledge could be gained through
dreams and visions, and plant lore was of
course handed down, orally, over generations.
In fact, the healing systems of Native Americans
are ancient and suggest links to Asia. For
example, the Pawnees burned the stems of
yarrow and leadplant (<hi rend="italic">Amorpha canescens</hi>) as
short punks placed on rheumatic points to
relieve pain, a practice known as "moxabustion,"
which today is almost completely associated
with Asian medicine. Only a very few
medicinal plants used by Native Americans
were adopted by European American immigrants,
primarily because the traditions were
vastly different and few European Americans
were willing to give credence to Native American
learning. One that was adopted was the
purple coneflower, which has been imported
into Europe and more recently been made
available commercially in the United States as
an immune system stimulant, used primarily
to ward off colds.</p>

<p>Food uses of native plants were vitally important
to the Great Plains Indians, and played
an essential dietary role. More than 120 native
prairie plants were used for food. Many plants
were used for seasoning, flavors, tea, or nutritional
needs (greens in the spring were used to
ward off scurvy). The most important native
food plant was the prairie turnip (<hi rend="italic">Psoralea esculenta</hi>).
This starchy, leguminous root was
eaten as a staple or added to bison stew. It was
also dried and traded or stored. The prairie
turnip was so important to the Omahas that
they determined the route of their summer
buffalo hunt in the High Plains by the locations
where the women could find the plant. Since
wild food procurement was primarily women's
work, little of this knowledge was passed
on to European immigrants because interaction
between Native American women and
women settlers rarely occurred.</p>

<p>Native Americans had many other uses for
wild plants, such as cattails and rushes for
mats, white sage (<hi rend="italic">Artemisia ludoviciana</hi>) and
eastern redcedar (<hi rend="italic">Juniperus virginiana</hi>) for
ceremonial incense, and trees for lodges and
firewood. Of course, Native American women
had long cultivated corn, beans, squash, sunflowers,
and other crops. With European
American settlement, large numbers of new
cultivars were introduced for farming and gardening,
but the diversity and variety have dramatically
decreased over the decades, and
farmers now only grow a handful of crops (and
indeed only a few genetic varieties of a small
number of crops). Only a small number of the
native plants originally used by Plains Indians
&#8211;wild plums (<hi rend="italic">Prunus americana</hi>), chokecherries
(<hi rend="italic">Prunus virginiana</hi>), wild grapes (<hi rend="italic">Vitis
riparia</hi>), and other&#8211;are now used for jams,
jellies, and wine by the wider population.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Kelly Kindscher<lb/>
University of Kansas</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Kindscher, Kelly. <title level="m">Edible Wild Plants of the Prairie: An Ethnobotanical Guide</title>. Lawrence: University Press of Kansas,
1987.</bibl> <bibl>Kindscher, Kelly. <title level="m">Medicinal Wild Plants of the Prairie: An Ethnobotanical Guide</title>. Lawrence: University Press of
Kansas, 1992.</bibl> <bibl>Moerman, Daniel E. <title level="m">Native American Ethnobotany</title>.
Portland <hi rend="smallcaps">OR</hi>: Timber Press, 1998.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>