<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.pe.005">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Audubon, John James (1785-1851)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Daniel J. Philippon</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.pe.005</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Philippon, Daniel J.">Daniel J. Philippon</author>. <title level="a">"Audubon, John James (1785-1851)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">619</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-22</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">AUDUBON, JOHN JAMES (1785-1851)</head>
<figure n="egp.pe.005" rend="granted" type="noclick">
<figDesc>John James Audubon</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>John James Audubon, the artist and naturalist,
was born at Les Cayes, Santo Domingue
(now Haiti), on April 26, 1785, the illegitimate
son of a French sea captain and a French
chambermaid. Audubon moved to Philadelphia
when he was eighteen to manage his father's
property. There he first developed his
interest in birds and his career as a naturalist
began. To this expertise he added painting after
1810, and by the 1830s he was recognized as
the foremost American naturalist.</p>

<p>His encounter with the Great Plains came
relatively late in his life, when he was fiftyeight.
In fact, it was his last expedition. In 1843,
Audubon embarked on what he called his
"Great Western Journey," traveling by steamboat
up the Missouri River from St. Louis to
Fort Union, near what is now the Montana–
North Dakota border. He took the trip to fulfill
a lifelong dream to see the Great Plains and
also to collect specimens and gather information
about the mammals of the American West
for <title level="m">The Viviparous Quadrupeds of North America</title>
(1845–54), which he was preparing with
John Bachman. Traveling with Audubon were
his friend Edward Harris, an ornithologist;
John G. Bell, a taxidermist; Isaac Sprague, an
artist; and Louis M. Squires, who served as
Audubon's secretary.</p>

<p>The party left St. Louis on April 25 aboard
the <hi rend="italic">Omega</hi>, a small steamer belonging to the
American Fur Company, on which they were
joined by more than a hundred hunters and
trappers, also bound for Fort Union, the company's
principal trading post. Throughout the
trip, Audubon and Harris both kept regular
journals and wrote fact-filled letters, which
collectively provide a detailed record of their
observations and activities. (Audubon's journal,
lost for more than fifty years, was discovered
in 1896 by two of his granddaughters,
one of whom published it the following year.)
As the boat made its way upriver, stopping to
visit settlements and cut wood for fuel, Audubon
drew pictures of the landscape and
sketched the rabbits, squirrels, woodchucks,
and other small animals and birds his party
collected on their occasional hunting trips.
Audubon also expressed disappointment at
the Native Americans he encountered along
the way, believing they fell short of the romantic
descriptions and idealized paintings offered
by George Catlin. On June 13, after fifty days and
1,400 miles, the <hi rend="italic">Omega</hi> finally reached Fort
Union. It then returned downriver, leaving Audubon
and the others to explore the area around
the fort, where they remained throughout the
summer.</p>

<p>During that time, Audubon observed hunters
and trappers at work; he made an overnight
trip up the Yellowstone River; he collected
specimens of wolves, elk, antelope, deer,
and bighorn sheep; and he noted the "immense
numbers" of buffalo, which he saw in
their natural habitat for the first time. He also
mourned the senseless destruction of the buffalo,
though that did not prevent his party
from hunting these animals at every opportunity.
At the end of two months, on August
16, the expedition left Fort Union on a fortyfoot
mackinaw and returned to St. Louis. "I
have no less than 14 New Species of Birds,
perhaps a few more," Audubon wrote to Bachman
upon his return. "The variety of Quadrupeds
is small in the Country we visited, and
I fear that I have not more than 3 or 4 New
ones." But, he added, "I have brought home
good Sketches of Scenery, Drawings of flowers,
and also the heads of Antilopes, Big horns,
Wolves and Buffaloes."</p>

<p>Audubon's health began to fail in the mid-
1840s, but with the help of his sons and Bachman,
he completed <title level="m">Quadrupeds</title>. Audubon
died in New York on January 27, 1851.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Daniel J. Philippon<lb/>
University of Minnesota, Twin Cities</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Audubon, Maria R., ed. <title level="m">Audubon and His Journals</title>. New
York: Scribner's, 1897.</bibl> <bibl>McDermott, John Francis, ed. <title level="m">Audubon
in the West</title>. Norman: University of Oklahoma
Press, 1965.</bibl> <bibl>McDermott, John Francis, ed. <title level="m">Up the Missouri
with Audubon: The Journal of Edward Harris</title>. Norman:
University of Oklahoma Press, 1951.</bibl>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>