<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.na.020">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Comanches</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Thomas W. Kavanagh</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.na.020</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Kavanagh, Thomas W.">Thomas W. Kavanagh</author>. <title level="a">"Comanches."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">570-571</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-15</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">COMANCHES</head>

<p>The Comanches were the first Native people
to adopt the classic horse-mounted lifestyle of
the Plains. The ethnonym Comanche probably
derives from the Ute word <hi rend="italic">komantsia</hi>&#8211;
"anyone who wants to fight me all the time."
Their name for themselves is <hi rend="italic">Nemene</hi>, or "Our
People."</p>

<p>Shoshone speakers, including proto-Comanches,
probably moved to the Northern
Plains in the sixteenth century. In the late seventeenth
century the proto-Comanches began
a southward movement, and by the early eighteenth
century, if not before, they were in contact
with the Spaniards of New Mexico. The
earliest mention of Comanches in Texas came
in the 1740s. By the 1840s Comanches were
regularly crossing the Rio Grande into Mexico
on horse raids.</p>

<p>The Comanche economy can be characterized
in three modes: a domestic economy of
hunting and gathering, a commercial economy
of trade and raid, and a political-diplomatic
economy. In the domestic economy, Comanches
used both individual stalking of bison
and group methods. Group hunts usually occurred
in late summer and fall when the animals
were fat, robes were good, and there were
few flies. Group hunts began with scouts locating
a herd. After the scouts reported the
herd's location to the chiefs, the hunters were
admonished to stay together. The actual hunt
was under the direction of the chief or a noted
warrior. However, once the chase began, each
hunter acted separately. Hunters identified
their kills by arrow marks. Other men could
claim a portion of the meat by counting coup
on it, but the hide remained the property of
the killer.</p>

<p>There were three general trade contexts:
formal and informal trade fairs and bartering
in European settlements; trading posts; and
exchange with <hi rend="italic">viageros</hi> or "travelers," later
called <hi rend="italic">comancheros</hi>. Comanches traded horses
and the products of the hunt with neighboring
peoples for agricultural products and,
in postcontact times, European industrial
products.</p>

<p>Political relations with other peoples probably
always included gift exchanges. Political
relations with European Americans developed
into an economy with significant ramifications.
Items in this economy included elite
goods such as silver-headed canes, flags, and
uniforms. They also included items that could
be redistributed downward through the social
structure such as foodstuffs, cloth, and metal
goods.</p>

<p>Details of Aboriginal clothing are scanty,
but it seems that summer dress was minimal.
Men wore perhaps only a shirt, a breechcloth,
possibly leggings, and moccasins. By the reservation
period, photographs and museum collections
show mid-thigh-length shirts decorated
with twist fringe at the shoulder and
elbow. Some side-seam leggings are represented
in museum collections, although late-nineteenth-
century photographs also show
front-seam style, attached by thongs to the belt
at the waist and tied with garters below the
knee. From knee to ankle, leggings were decorated
with long twist fringe. Moccasins were of
the two-piece, hard-sole variety. A long triangular
vamp was decorated with fringes and
tin cone tinklers. The earliest examples of
women's apparel are two-part dresses, consisting
of a skirt suspended by straps from the
shoulders and a separate poncholike blouse;
some mid-nineteenth-century photographs
show a separate wrap fastened with broaches.
In hot weather, or when nursing or in mourning,
the blouse could be removed. The later
style was a single-piece dress. By the mid– to
late nineteenth century, both men and women
wore a cloth about the waist outside both leggings
and skirt.</p>

<p>Comanche tipis were distinct, with a four-pole
base, but with the rest of the poles set
in as in a three-pole tipi. The cut of the
skins forming the cover was also apparently
unique.</p>

<p>Comanche relations with the supernatural
were considered to be an individual's concern,
and despite a range of variation in belief and
practice, there were broad features common
to Comanche religion. Religious practice centered
on <hi rend="italic">puha</hi>, personal power obtained from
the supernatural. Power was available to both
men and women, both of whom could become
<hi rend="italic">puhacut</hi>, or a "possessor of power."</p>

<p>In prereservation times, there were four
levels of sociopolitical organization: simple
family, extended family, local band, and division.
The simple family consisted of a man,
his wife or wives, and various dependents—
children, parents, or parents-in-law. The basic
social unit was the bilaterally extended family,
or <hi rend="italic">nemenakane</hi>, "people who live together in a
house(hold)." Local bands were composed of
one or more extended families, as well as attached
simple families and individuals, and
were called <hi rend="italic">rancher&#237;as</hi> by the Spaniards. The
highest level of Comanche political organization
was the division, the tribally organized
group of local bands linked by ties of kinship
and men's societies. The names and numbers
of these groups have changed greatly over the
course of Comanche history.</p>

<p>The Comanches were assigned a reservation
in southwestern Oklahoma following the
Treaty of Medicine Lodge Creek in 1867, but
not all the bands were on the reservation until
1876. The reservation was allotted after the
General Allotment Act of 1887. Most Comanches
now live in the vicinity of Lawton, Oklahoma.
They are active, although often partial,
participants in the mainstream economy. Fort
Sill in Lawton, Tinker Air Force Base in Oklahoma
City, and Altus Air Force Base in Altus,
as well as several other federal installations,
provide employment. As a tribe the Comanches
have few independent resources. In 1984
a bingo operation was opened, although it has
been the focus of much controversy, and its
contribution to the Comanche economy is
uncertain.</p>

<p>Although more than half of the 1901–6 Comanche
allotments are still in Indian hands,
few Comanches actively work them. Rather,
allotments are held as undivided joint property
by multiple heirs of the original allottee
and are leased to non-Indian farmers or stockmen.
A number of oil wells have been drilled
on allotments, and several Comanches have
become quite wealthy through such revenues.</p>

<p>There are no reliable Aboriginal population
estimates; similarly, details of epidemic diseases
are scanty and contradictory. In 1870 it
was estimated that there were 3,742 Comanches,
including possibly 1,000 off-reservation.
In 1875, 1,556 Comanches were reported on the
reservation south of the Washita River. In 1900
there were 1,499 Comanches, but a year later
measles took ninety-eight lives. The low point
of 1,399 was reached in 1904, and it was not
until the 1930s that the population again surpassed 2,000. In 1990 the tribal population
was approximately 9,000.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">HISPANIC AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ha.010"><hi rend="italic">Comancheros</hi></ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Thomas W. Kavanagh<lb/>
Indiana University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Kavanagh, Thomas W. <title level="m">Comanche Political History: An
Ethnohistorical Perspective, 1706–1875</title>. Lincoln: University
of Nebraska Press, 1996.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>