<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ct.050">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">T-Towns</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>R. Alton Lee</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ct.050</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Lee, R. Alton">R. Alton Lee</author>. <title level="a">"T-Towns."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">185-186</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-28</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">T-TOWNS</head>

<p>T-towns were founded in the Great Plains in
the second half of the nineteenth century as
market centers for farmers. They developed in
the shape of a T, with the railroad constituting
the top bar and Main Street and the commercial
area the perpendicular.</p>

<p>As Americans pushed westward in the nineteenth
century the shape and format of their
settlements changed along with their needs
and the environment. In the Old Northwest
and the South the pattern of town development
usually took the form of a square. If
the town was the county seat, the courthouse
stood in the center; if not, the municipal hall
or some other civic institution was located
there. Commercial buildings surrounded the
square, and residential areas developed on a
grid pattern following the survey lines laid
out in the Basic Land Ordinance of 1785. Some
courthouse-square towns are found in the
Great Plains in areas such as southeastern Nebraska,
where some settlement preceded the
railroads, but most Plains settlements accompanied
or followed the rail lines and took the
T-town shape.</p>

<p>As the rail lines extended westward, opening
the Plains to grain farming and ranching,
there was a need for market centers. Developers
followed the team-haul principle for determining the location of these centers: a team
could haul a wagonload of wheat five miles
round-trip in one day; a ten-mile distance required
an overnight stay. Thus elevators and,
subsequently, towns sprang up across the
Great Plains along the railroad right-of-ways
approximately every ten miles. On the Rock
Island line in Kansas, for example, from its
division point in Herington eastward, Latimer,
White City, Dwight, and AltaVista lie approximately
ten miles from each other. In
White City, also on the Kansas-Texas (Katy)
division of the Missouri Pacific Railroad, the
rails with the elevator near the depot provided
the link with the outside world. Its primary
street, McKenzie, ran westward from the depot,
and commercial buildings sprang up on
both sides of this main thoroughfare. When
the Rock Island built northeast to southwest
on the western edge of the town some fifteen
years after the Katy, it confirmed the future of
McKenzie as the "downtown" artery, with a
depot at each end. In other towns with only
one railroad in the early period, the end of the
commercial zone was often marked by a public
building, perhaps the county courthouse,
as in the case of Council Grove, Kansas, and
Bismarck, North Dakota.</p>

<p>The T-towns were outlets for the farmers'
grain and service centers for their needs.
Farmers hauled their wheat to market during
the cold winter months and returned with a
load of lumber and groceries. The lumberyard
was second only to the grain elevator as a
dominant feature of these towns, because almost
all of the lumber had to be imported by
rail to construct Plains town and country
buildings. The local bank that financed both
rural and urban needs often was the sole brick
or stone structure in town, a sign of its security
and stability. Most of the wooden commercial
buildings, including the requisite
hotel for drummers and transients and the
mercantile stores, were standardized so that
as needs changed over the years different
kinds of merchants could utilize them. A
smithy might be converted into a creamery, a
lodge hall, an automobile garage, and finally a
movie theater.</p>

<p>With the advent of the internal combustion
engine, the technological revolution in agriculture,
and the closing of many rail lines,
many T-towns lost their economic foundation.
Farmers were able to travel to the county
seat or other larger centers for machinery
parts, and while they were there they did their
shopping in the supermarket and, eventually,
the regional Wal-Mart. The team-haul principle
had given rise to many Plains towns during
the nineteenth century, but by the mid–
twentieth century many of these towns had
become obsolete, and they dwindled along
with their commercial outlets. A few of them
survived by aggressively seeking light industry
or by fostering tourism through a museum
and antique shops. Some, like Lincoln, Nebraska,
thrived as government and university
centers. Most that had blanketed the Plains,
though, went the way of the horse and buggy
and became relics of Great Plains settlement,
standing as a mute reminder to the old-timers
of dreams gone awry.</p>

<closer>
<signed>R. Alton Lee<lb/>
University of South Dakota</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Hudson, John C. <title level="m">Plains Country Towns</title>. Minneapolis:
University of Minnesota Press, 1985.</bibl> <bibl>Lee, R. Alton. <title level="m">T-Town on the Plains</title>. Manhattan <hi rend="smallcaps">KS</hi>: Sunflower University Press,
1999.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>