<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fol.039">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Seasonal Celebrations</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Nikki Bado-Fralick</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2009</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fol.039</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2009</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2009 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Bado-Fralick, Nikki">Nikki Bado-Fralick</author>. <title level="a">"Seasonal Celebrations."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">313</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-17</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">SEASONAL CELEBRATIONS</head>

<p>Seasonal celebrations and festivals are among
humanity's most ancient and enduring traditions.
It is often no accident that many of the
world's oldest and most important religious
holidays coincide with, or are directly related
to, the cycles and seasons of the natural world.
We have always observed the changing seasons
with a mixture of anticipation and dread,
knowing that our very survival&#8211;a bountiful
harvest, plentiful herds, or a successful hunt&#8211;
depends largely on the whims of Mother Nature.
We have always celebrated the seasons
with occasions of ritual and festival, both expressing
relief and giving thanks for the bounty
of the land, brought forth by time and our
own hard work.</p>

<p>Similar to the range and variety of its folk
beliefs, the seasonal celebrations and festivals
of the Great Plains reflect the customs and
traditions of the many groups contained within
its vast boundaries, taking on a regional
flavor through the response of people to their
immediate natural world. Like others around
the world, the folk of the Great Plains have
worked to the rhythms of the land, sometimes
confronting unexpectedly harsh and even brutal
conditions. Both religious and secular festivals
typically mark "seasons of work" having
to do with agriculture or the care of animals:
hunting, planting, harvesting, breeding stock,
moving animals from one pasture to another,
shearing sheep, and butchering animals that
will not be "wintered over." Agricultural survival
in the Great Plains requires not only hard
work but delicate timing. Tasks of planting and
harvesting seldom can wait but must be timed
to the whims of rain and sun.</p>

<p>Hard work, harsh conditions, and delicate
timing notwithstanding, the seasons in the
Great Plains are also accompanied by equally
hard play and merry socializing, especially after
the work is done. Special foods, songs,
games, and customs attend each seasonal celebration.
Food and drink are absolutely necessary
elements, along with music and dancing.
Historically, Plains folk seemed to enjoy just
about any excuse to get together and have fun:
parades, races, speeches, contests, dressing up
(even cross-dressing), role reversals, and general
carousing typically accompany seasonal
festivals.</p>

<p>Spring in the Plains is a time not only for
planting but also for celebrating the end of
winter and reveling in the sheer joy of being
alive. Although seasonal customs change and
sometimes pass away with time, children in
parts of the Great Plains still dance and sing
around the maypole and make May baskets of
spring flowers for their neighbors. Bonfire
dancing also once accompanied general spring
festivities, especially among Swedes, usually at
Easter. Ethnic groups such as the Swedes and
the Finns contributed their own unique festivals&#8211;
such as the celebration of Midsummer's
Day&#8211;to the cultural mix of the Great Plains.</p>

<p>Seasonal work affords plenty of occasions
for festive socializing. Often this is a matter
of necessity: it takes more than one hand or
one family to finish a harvest on time, and
the fruits of that harvest provide the means
for socializing. Once-common activities such
as cornhusking bees, bean picking, pea shelling,
and watermelon feeds provided opportunities
for women and children to both work
and socialize. The women exchanged news
and information and checked out prospective
mates for their daughters and sons. Seasonal
activities and festivals were, and still are, an
important part of community building for
Plains folk.</p>

<p>Additionally, seasonal work itself is often
intertwined with play in the form of games or
contests: Who can pick the most corn or harvest
the most wheat? Who's the fastest sheep
shearer, the best cowpoke? Who makes the
best fruit pie or jam? Who can grow the largest
pumpkin? Both rodeos and state and local
fairs have evolved as premier events in the
Great Plains, designed to demonstrate the
level of one's skills and to showcase the bounty
of the harvest. Even local churches are lovingly
decorated with the fruits of the harvest season.
The late summer and fall harvest seasons
still provide numerous opportunities for both
work and festive play, ending with the final
twin harvest celebrations of Halloween, with
its puckish and unruly mischief, and Thanksgiving,
with its solemn and grateful sharing of
harvest bounty.</p>

<p>Although many seasonal celebrations of the
Great Plains are similar to those found in
other parts of the country, Plains folk nevertheless
put their own distinctive stamp on
the fun. Independence Day has not been the
same in Lewistown, Montana, since two desperados
tried to hold up the town in 1884.
Each year, the whole town reenacts the dastardly
crime, complete with the mock shooting
of "Rattlesnake Jake" and his partner, and
the unfortunate shooting death of the unlucky
citizen who just happened to be in the way.</p>

<p>Christmas celebrations also undergo interesting
transformations in the Plains. While
Santa Claus normally wears a jolly red suit, he
is just as likely to be dressed as a rowdy, rollicking
cowboy in the Plains. Good little girls
and boys leave cookies and milk for Santa.
German children in the Plains make sure to
leave three ears of corn, one for each of the
Three Wise Men, for Santa's reindeer. Christmas
dinner is a lovingly prepared feast, but for
Swedes in the Great Plains it is literally a smorgasbord,
a custom that dates back at least to
the time of the Vikings. Where pines and evergreens
are plentiful, expect to find Christmas
trees with all the usual trimmings. But in Kansas,
where such trees were absent, early Plains
settlers creatively wove a "Christmas arch"
from which to hang their Christmas stockings
and gifts.</p>

<p>Above all, the settlers of the Great Plains
were "make do" people when it came to
seasonal celebrations and festivals, adapting
to the demands of the land and crafting new
traditions to honor and celebrate the never-ending
transformation and renewal of life in
the Plains.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Nikki Bado-Fralick<lb/>
Iowa State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Johnson, Dorothy M. "Independence Day, 1884!" <title level="j">Montana</title>
8 (1958): 2–7.</bibl> <bibl>Sackett, S. J., and William E. Koch, eds.
<title level="m">Kansas Folklore</title>. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press,
1961.</bibl> <bibl>Welsch, Roger L. <title level="m">A Treasury of Nebraska Pioneer Folklore</title>. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1966.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>