<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.tra.001">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Transportation</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>H. Roger Grant</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.tra.001</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Grant, H. Roger">H. Roger Grant</author>. <title level="a">"Transportation."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">793-798</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-19</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">TRANSPORTATION</head>

<p>Although transportation has played a vital
role in the history of every American region, it
has been especially important in the Great
Plains. Having few navigable bodies of water
and limited overland roads, the region desperately
needed a replacement technology for the
river steamboat and the covered wagon and
benefited enormously from the appearance of
the "iron horse." The Railroad Age solved
most of the Great Plains’s chronic transport
problems and gave the region some of its distinctive
characteristics. The thousands of
communities spawned and nurtured by the
rails often sported a flavor of standardization
that the later network of all-weather roads
with its automobiles, buses, and trucks helped
to sustain.</p>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Native American Transportation</head>

<p>For the Native peoples, the Great Plains was
a world of enormous distances. All Indigenous
groups of the Plains, whether nomads or
seminomads, spent much of their time following
the wide-ranging bison herds. In addition,
the scarcity of streams and scattered distribution
of springs, the primary sources of
water, forced these peoples to cover enormous
distances on a daily basis. Finally, most Plains
tribes were engaged in long-distance commerce
at trade centers such as the Arikara and
Mandan-Hidatsa villages on the upper Missouri
River, which, for some tribes, meant
covering hundreds of miles.</p>

<p>The primary reason that made the distances
so demanding was the lack of e.cient transportation
facilities in the period before contact
with Europeans. Native Americans lacked
large beasts of burden such as camels and
horses. Their only domesticated animal was
the dog, which was used to carry loads and to
draw the travois. Native peoples employed the
travois to transport household utensils, weapons,
tools, tipi covers, firewood, and meat, but
a dog could haul only about sixty pounds,
which meant that human beings, particularly
women, did most of the carrying themselves.</p>

<p>Most Plains rivers were dry for too long
each year to be useful channels for water
transportation. As a result, only a few Plains
tribes, including the Assiniboines, Blackfoot,
and Crees, used canoes, while others relied
only on land transportation. The Assiniboines,
Blackfoot, and Crees were particularly
skillful in using the canoe. In the early eighteenth
century, for example, the Blackfoot canoed
to the Hudson Bay to trade with the
British. More locally, the tribes along the Missouri
River developed bullboats&#8211;small, light,
bowl-shaped vessels made of bison hides&#8211;for
transportation of goods.</p>

<p>The event that changed the traditional
transportation system was, of course, the introduction
of the horse to the Plains by the
Spanish. (Actually, the proper term would be
reintroduction, for horses had lived on the
Plains until they became extinct around 8000-6000
<hi rend="smallcaps">B.C.</hi>) Coronado and other early Spanish
conquistadors explored the Southern Plains
on horseback in the sixteenth century, but
horses did not begin to spread among the Indians
until the Spanish established a permanent
colony, New Mexico, at the southwestern
edge of the Plains at the end of the sixteenth
century. Gradually, through trade and theft,
horses spread from the New Mexican ranches
in all directions, so that by the end of the eighteenth
century all Plains tribes were mounted.</p>

<p>In time, the introduction of the horse was
to have far-reaching cultural, economic, and
political effects among the Plains Indians, but
the most immediate consequence was a transportation
revolution. The horse was about
eight times as e.cient as the dog: it could
carry on its back or haul on a travois a load
four times heavier than the load a dog could
manage, and it could travel twice as far in a
day. Thus, horse transport allowed Indians to
carry more tools and utensils, extra foodstuffs,
and larger tipis, and suddenly nomadism did
not require giving up all but the bare minimum
of possessions. It also made it possible
for Indians to hunt bison more effectively, and
this enticed horticulturists&#8211;the Omahas, for
example&#8211;to increase the role of hunting in
their economies. Interaction between tribes
increased as sheer distance became less of an
obstacle. In short, like railroads in the late
nineteenth century, horses reduced the friction
of distance, opened new economic possibilities,
and raised the standards of living on
the Plains.</p>

<p>The adoption of horses also resulted in the
abandonment of canoes, usually within a generation
after the Indians received their first
horses. Dogs, on the other hand, continued to
be used for transportation throughout the
prereservation period. This was particularly
the case on the Northern Great Plains, where
distance from the source of horses and cold
winters, which made herding more di.cult
and labor intensive, reduced the availability
and numbers. The Southern Plains Indians,
who had the largest herds, continued to use
dogs to carry small items such as moccasins
and household utensils.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Waterways</head>

<p>When European Americans entered the Great
Plains, they often paddled or floated along
thousands of miles of meandering waterways.
In the late eighteenth century, when the rival
Hudson's Bay and North West Companies extended
their fur-trading hinterlands to the
Prairies and Parkland Belt, they introduced to
the region the water transportation systems
they had developed in the Petit Nord (the area
bounded by Hudson Bay, Lake Superior, and
Lake Winnipeg) during the preceding century.
The trading posts were linked to the Hudson
Bay and the St. Lawrence River by annual brigades
traveling primarily by birch-bark canoes.
Paddling along the Saskatchewan River
to Lake Winnipeg, then either to the Hudson
Bay along the Nelson or Hayes Rivers or to the
St. Lawrence along the Winnipeg River and
the Great Lakes, the brigades moved furs and
other cargoes effectively. The light, maneuverable
birch-bark canoe had a cargo capacity of
almost 3,000 pounds and allowed a crew of
five or six men to achieve a speed of five or six
miles per hour. Such swiftness was crucial, because
the northern rivers were navigable for
only a few months between the spring thaw
and fall freeze.</p>

<p>In contrast to their canoe-using counterparts,
the American fur companies along the
Missouri River system were able to use larger
vessels such as keelboats and mackinaws.
Powered by oars, sail, or cordelle (that is,
pulled by a rope by men who laboriously
walked the bank), keelboats could cover a distance
of fifteen to twenty miles a day upstream,
carrying a load of twenty to thirty tons of
cargo. The broad, flat-bottomed mackinaws,
which were used only for downstream shipments,
were up to twenty feet long and carried
a crew of five or six men and as many as 2,500
bison robes. Driven by the current, they could
achieve up to 100 miles a day. For low-bulk and
short-distance carriage, the American traders
used pirogues (a construction of two canoes
fastened together with planks), dugout canoes,
and bullboats.</p>

<p>Although mackinaws, canoes, and bullboats
continued to be used by fur traders and
others at least until the 1870s, the advent of the
steamboat on the Missouri River in 1831 revolutionized
navigation. By the 1860s, paddle
wheelers served as great beasts of burden
along the principal streams, particularly the
churning 2,285 miles of the Missouri River
from its mouth near St. Louis to Fort Benton,
a military post in present-day Montana. Supplies
for farmers, miners, ranchers, soldiers,
and trappers moved by water, as did cargoes
of cattle, grain, furs, and mining machinery.</p>

<p>Steamboating posed challenges. Rivers on
the Plains were generally unreliable, as they
were often braided and shallow, and most
flowed through areas of comparatively light
annual precipitation. Melting winter snows,
spring freshets, and sometimes-heavy autumn
rains swelled portions of these streams, but
during much of the year they contained inadequate
water levels. The Missouri, for example,
could be continuously navigated only
from mid-March to late June. Even if ample
depths existed, snags and sawyers often cluttered
the waterways. Rocky shoals, rushing
rapids, and shifting channels commonly hindered
passage. High prairie winds, too, buffeted
vessels, blowing them onto sandbars
or into the banks or even causing them to
capsize.</p>

<p>A special type of steamboat facilitated navigational
ventures. Boats on Plains rivers were
ideally suited for the di.cult conditions. The
use of compact, high-pressure, yet powerful
steam engines, which permitted construction
of inexpensive and easily maintained crafts
with shallow drafts, allowed these vessels to
ply relatively shallow streams. Some boats allegedly
required only a "heavy morning dew"
to navigate.</p>

<p>During the heyday of steamboating on
Plains rivers, traffic could be brisk. An individual
vessel might handle scores of passengers
and considerable quantities of freight. In
the late 1870s boats traveling the waters of the
Red River of the North between Fargo and
Fort Garry carried settlers with their possessions
and supplies northbound and pushed
barges loaded with buffalo hides and wheat
southbound.</p>

<p>Yet commercial steamboating on Plains rivers
was largely ephemeral. Service on some streams
ended as soon as a railroad penetrated the territory.
Residents along the Brazos River, for example,
benefited from limited navigation from the
Gulf of Mexico northwestward to Washington,
Texas, a distance of approximately 250 miles. By
the Civil War, the Houston and Texas Central
Railroad had siphoned away nearly all of the
river tra.c, mostly bales of cotton. Even along
the Missouri River stagecoaches and later passenger
trains quickly attracted travelers, but
steamboat freight movements continued, albeit
in diminishing amounts. By the 1920s service
was nearly gone, lost to railroads and emerging
motor carriers. In subsequent years federal
dams made long-distance commerce impossible
on the upper Missouri, although towboats
and barges continued to serve customers between
Sioux City, Iowa, and other downriver
points. More recently, commercial inland water
operators could call at the Port of East Tulsa,
Oklahoma, the western terminus of the "canalized"
Arkansas River.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Early Roadways</head>

<p>The trails and traces used by roaming herds of
bison and traveling Native Americans provided
the earliest practical avenues for European
Americans who traversed the supposedly
"trackless wilderness" of the Great Plains. Yet
these original land routes, particularly in Canada,
were immeasurably inferior to water
routes. They were superceded by an array of
"quasi" roads on which ox, mule, and horse
power provided practical transport. By the
close of the Civil War, immigrants, prospectors,
soldiers, traders, and others could move
along principal arteries such as the Central
Overland Road (or Oregon-California Trail),
parts of which were used by the Pony Express;
the Smoky Hill Road, which traversed Kansas
and Colorado between communities along the
Missouri River and Denver; and the old Santa
Fe Trail, the direct link between Missouri and
New Mexico, first established in the 1820s. Farther
north, an extensive oxcart trail system
that crisscrossed the Prairie Provinces in the
late nineteenth century was the closest Canadian
equivalent of the famous American overland
routes.</p>

<p>Other roads also became important arteries
for commerce. Some were maintained by the
military; others were largely private affairs.
Several routes in the Dodge City, Kansas, region
illustrate the less-remembered byways.
The Dodge City.Fort Supply Trail (also called
the Military Road), the Tascosa-Dodge City
Trail, and the Jones and Plummer Trail connected
the famous Kansas cow town and trading
center with areas to the south. While
coach and horse travel flourished for about a
score of years after the Civil War, construction
of railroads like the Rock Island and the Santa
Fe brought changes. The "iron horse killed
off stagecoach service, which federal mail contracts
had heavily subsidized, and took over
freighting activities, which also had depended
upon federal payments for drayage to military
posts.</p>

<p>The history of the first major phase of roads
on the Plains roughly paralleled the saga of
steamboating. Both forms were largely transitory.
The stagecoach era lasted but a generation
or two for the transport of passengers, mail, and
express. However, in the West River Country of
South Dakota, stagecoaches rumbled over the
mostly unimproved roads until the early part of
the twentieth century. As with freight moving
on water, overland freight transport by wagon
usually enjoyed a longer existence. Significantly,
intermodal dimensions developed for both
transportation forms. Stagecoach drivers met
steamboats at their wharfs and, later, passenger
trains at local depots; likewise, wagon teamsters
traveled to dock facilities and then to railway
freight stations.</p>

<p>Surely the most romantic form of land commerce
on the Plains was the cattle trail of the
post-Civil War era. For a brief period, a network
of these unimproved paths across the
grasslands linked the Southern Plains with
railheads on the Central Plains, army posts in
the Rocky Mountain West, Indian reservations,
and other commercial destinations. Altogether,
more than six million head of cattle
were driven north from Texas from 1866 to
1885. This was one of the few times during
the European American period of settlement
when the region was integrated lengthwise instead
of being laterally connected from east to
west. By the 1880s this latter orientation had
been reestablished when the barbed-wire fences
of settlers closed off the open range. As this grid
was laid across the Plains, the cattle trails were
dislodged westward: the Chisholm Trail to Abilene,
Kansas, gave way to the Western Trail to
Dodge City, Kansas, and points north and finally
to the Goodnight-Loving Trail, which
traced the eastern flank of the Rockies from
Texas to Cheyenne, Wyoming. Facing the inevitable
closure of the open range, Texas cattle interests
made a last, unsuccessful attempt to preserve
their industry in 1885 when they proposed
a National Cattle Trail linking Texas and Canada,
a six-mile-wide cattle highway that would
be kept out of private ownership. The day of the
cattleman was over, though it still has a powerful
place in the American historical imagination.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Railroads</head>

<p>The railroad metamorphosed life in the Great
Plains, penetrating the isolation of the region
and making possible modern life. Railroad
companies did more than penetrate the Plains
with a plethora of main, secondary, and branch
lines; they peddled land, some from public land
grants; they established towns, usually through
town-site subsidiaries; and they vigorously (and
at times misleadingly) promoted their service
territories as ideal places for settlement.</p>

<p>The Railway Age began much later in the
Great Plains than in most parts of the United
States and Canada, but it lasted longer. While
the 1850s witnessed extensive railroad building
in New England, the South, the Old Northwest,
and Atlantic Canada, little happened in
the West. The 1860s saw some construction on
the Plains, most notably the strategic Union
Pacific–Central Pacific transcontinental system
that sliced through the heart of the region.
The first great wave of railroad construction
did not begin in the United States in
earnest until after depressed conditions, triggered
by the Panic of 1873, lifted. During the
1880s railroad expansion boomed. The Chicago
and North Western and the Chicago, St.
Paul and Milwaukee, for example, covered
eastern South Dakota like a web; the two roads
spiked down nearly 2,000 miles of track, and
this building spree brought the "steam car civilization"
to the emerging state.</p>

<p>In the Prairie Provinces, additional incentives
for rail building included the desire to
consolidate the newly born Dominion of Canada
(1867) and the need to confront the rapid
&#8211;and threatening&#8211;westward expansion of
the United States. Transcontinental railroads
became a national imperative. The Canadian
Pacific Railway was chartered in 1881 and completed
four years later with the aid of generous
government cash and land grants, tax concessions,
and rights-of-way. The building of the
Canadian Pacific across the Prairies involved
a fierce dispute between Edmonton and Calgary.
The initial route was planned to follow
the northern fringes of the Prairies, but eventually,
to Edmonton’s bitter disappointment, a
more southerly route was chosen. A larger debate
focused on whether the Canadian Pacific
should be built along a circuitous and expensive
route across the inhospitable and sparsely
populated terrain north of Lake Superior or a
more direct and profitable course through
American territory. The company opted for
the all-Canadian route, reflecting the nationalistic
policies of the period, but it also
created an expensive freight rate structure that
was disadvantageous for the Prairie farmers.</p>

<p>The hard times of the late 1880s and much of
the 1890s halted rail construction, but a second
great building boom marked the period from
the turn of the century to World War I. This
was particularly the case in the Prairie Provinces.
Between 1905 and 1914, two competing
and partly parallel transcontinental systems&#8211;the
privately owned Canadian Northern Railway
and the Grand Trunk Pacific Railway, a
joint attempt by the federal government and
the Grand Trunk Railway to break the Canadian
Pacific’s unpopular monopoly in the West
&#8211;were constructed to the region’s northern
sector, which had been left vacant by the Canadian
Pacific’s decision to take the southerly
route across the grasslands. Moreover, the
competing transcontinentals launched extensive
branch line programs in the Prairie Provinces,
covering the region with a thick local
track network by 1915.</p>

<p>Even though the railroad map of the Great
Plains had largely crystallized by 1920, additional
trackage still appeared, especially in the
Prairie Provinces of Canada. A third wave of
rail building took place in the 1920s and continued
in some places into the early 1930s, a
century after the railroad’s debut in North
America. "From all corners of the state come
the predictions that South Dakota, within the
next few years will see another era of rail
building," editorialized a Huron, South Dakota,
newspaper in May 1929. "That era, from
indications, is now upon us." Indeed, it was.</p>

<p>Rail building in the Great Plains went quickly
because it was usually affordable. The generally
flat or rolling terrain made construction
costs much less per mile than they were in most
other sections of the continent. Some Plains
pikes were merely rails and untreated ties laid
on a gently graded dirt roadbed. When crews
of the Union Pacific pushed across Nebraska in
the 1860s, they wisely followed the nearly level
valley of the Platte River. Shaping the roadbed
required little more than the use of inexpensive
farm equipment, which semiskilled laborers
could easily handle. Only the occasional bridge
work posed many financial and engineering
challenges. Developmental carriers like the
Canadian Northern and the Kansas Pacific
built inexpensive lines and made improvements
later after revenues increased. Unlike
construction in Europe or in eastern North
America, most original Plains lines were
hardly built for unborn generations. Some exceptions
existed, notably the Canadian Pacific,
which by 1885 possessed a quality "Dominion
from Sea to Sea" route.</p>

<p>Few residents of the Plains ever challenged
the notion that the magic touch of a railway,
well built or not, promised a bright future for
everyone in the surrounding areas. The arrival
in 1887 of the Fort Worth and Denver City
Railway in the Texas Panhandle village of
Quanah prompted a local journalist to predict
that the community and its trade area were
headed "toward the <hi rend="italic">Ultima Thule</hi> of commercial
and financial success." Such sentiments
were ubiquitous.</p>

<p>Yet a love-hate relationship developed between
residents of the Great Plains and railroads.
The largest companies, usually the
transcontinentals, often held local or even regional
monopolies. In Nebraska, for example,
distinct Burlington and Union Pacific territories
had evolved by the latter part of the nineteenth
century. Both roads tried to prevent
other firms like the Missouri Pacific, North
Western, and Rock Island from entering their
"spheres of influence." Although railroad
freight rates generally dropped during this period,
public perceptions were frequently negative
about most carriers.</p>

<p>Antirailroad sentiment on the Plains was
expressed in various ways. These feelings frequently
led to popular support for construction
of additional routes; local governments
especially subscribed to issues of stocks and
bonds. Individuals similarly responded. They
also might make gifts of real estate to the future
projects. South of the forty-ninth parallel
but most of all in the Dakotas, much talk and
some action occurred in the 1890s and later
for the creation of "farmers' railroads." Disgruntled
shippers (or those who lacked adequate
rail facilities) would incorporate the
company, publicize organizational meetings,
survey the route, and direct construction.
Since capital would be limited, farmers and
townspeople&#8211;anyone who lived along the
projected line&#8211;would be asked to donate
rights-of-way and to contribute their labor.
Animal teams would shape the roadbed, and
crossties would be harvested from nearby
stands of trees. When grading was completed
and ties had been furnished, the infant road
would be bonded to raise funds to purchase
the cheapest suitable rail and rolling stock.
The ultimate fate of the finished project usually
remained flexible. The road might be sold
or leased to a major trunk carrier with the
understanding that customers would receive
the lowest possible rates and best service. Or,
more likely, the line would be operated indefinitely
as a cooperative enterprise. Except for
several pikes, most notably the Farmers' Grain
and Shipping Company and the Fairmount
and Veblen, the movement at best produced
only "paper" or "hot-air" schemes in the
United States. In the Prairie Provinces, the
"farmers' railways" played an even more limited
role. Prairie farmers suffered from high
freight rates, but they were partly mitigated by
the dense branch line system, which left few
areas in need of rail facilities.</p>

<p>The failure of self-help in the railroad sector,
reminiscent of the earlier collapse of state
exchanges of the Farmers Alliance (which
sought to put control of selling farm produce
and buying supplies in the hands of farmers),
prompted the disaffected residents of the
Great Plains to flock to the standard of the
People's Party (Populists) and to make loud
demands for public ownership of the railroad
enterprise. Not all residents of the Plains,
however, considered the railroad industry to
be a public enemy. In Nebraska, for instance,
townspeople frequently refrained from confrontation
with the carriers, realizing that an
all-out assault on them might damage their
abilities to attract outside capital and therefore
hinder development.</p>

<p>While differences emerged between residents
of the Great Plains about how they should respond
to railroad policies and practices, nearly
everyone endorsed industry efforts to develop
what once had been considered the "Great
American Desert." Railroad companies, which
usually worked through their affiliated townsite
firms, helped to create communities that
benefited the general populace, whether urban
or rural. Although railroads sought to profit
from lot sales, they primarily wanted to settle the
territory along their routes. "There is no attempt
to make large sums from the sale of these
town sites," explained an official of the Atchison,
Topeka and Santa Fe Railway, "but rather to
build up the country and serve the general interests
of the railway company." Settlers on the land
meant boxcars filled with grain. A similar sentiment
prevailed in the Prairie Provinces, where,
in the early nineteenth century, the Canadian
Pacific launched elaborate irrigation projects to
promote the region's agricultural capacity and
settlement.</p>

<p>Railroads left an indelible mark on the
Great Plains from Canada to the Rio Grande.
Since rails usually preceded settlement, carriers
and their town-site satellites selected the
station locations, usually every five to fifteen
miles along their lines; acquired the necessary
real estate; and surveyed lots and streets. A
public auction might take place for the sale of
the commercial and residential parcels, and
newspaper, pamphlet, and broadside advertising
would follow to "boom" the infant community,
surely a "New Chicago" or a "New
Toronto." Sometimes, as in the case of Winnipeg,
the reality was more astounding than
even the boosters had dared to dream. Situated
on the eastern edge of the Prairies, midway
between the Atlantic and Pacific Oceans,
Winnipeg was the natural focus of trunk lines.
The transcontinentals made Winnipeg the
most important interior transportation point
and launched the city into an economic and
political boom that is unequaled in Canadian
urban history: between about the mid-1880s
and the end of the century, Winnipeg matured
from an unimpressive cluster of wooden sheds
and shacks into the leading industrial, financial,
and administrative center of the Prairie
Provinces.</p>

<p>Railroad-created communities in the Great
Plains often had a look-alike appearance. Author
Hamlin Garland called them "flimsy little
wooden towns.’’ On the Plains, especially the
northern sections, it became common to have
Main Street run at a right angle to the depot and
tracks. The resulting ‘‘T-town’’ was immensely
practical. The retailing core stood directly adjacent
to the depot, and beyond were the seat of
government (if the community won the bid to
become the county seat), churches, and houses.
The other side of the tracks likely became the
locus of major commerce: grain elevators, coal
and lumberyards, and the like. This configuration
meant that patrons of these businesses,
with their carts and wagons, would not clog
the commercial thoroughfare and principal
residential streets. Thus the railroad corridor,
which sliced through the town, sported a practical
symmetry: side tracks beyond the main
line for local industries and retail and residential
sections segregated for their own functions.
Hundreds of these T-towns appeared at
trackside, including future state and provincial
capitals such as Bismarck, North Dakota,
Cheyenne, Wyoming, Lincoln, Nebraska, and
Regina, Saskatchewan.</p>

<p>Once the railroad network in the Great Plains
was set by the early 1930s, it remained stable
until the 1960s, particularly to the south of the
forty-ninth parallel. Although several carriers,
including the Katy, North Western, and Rock
Island, fell into bankruptcy during the Great
Depression, court-supervised reorganizations
revamped these victims of hard times. The
enormous tra.c generated by World War II
energized virtually every road. After the war
years companies mostly enjoyed a sizable financial
reserve to carry them through forthcoming
downswings in the economy. Moreover, a replacement
technology, the diesel-electric locomotive,
which had been widely adopted by the early 1950s,
further aided the balance sheet.</p>

<p>Yet all was not well with the railroads that
served the Great Plains. Tough and at times
unreasonable regulation, products of aggressive
and well-meaning progressive reforms
early in the twentieth century, forced companies
to maintain hundreds of unnecessary
small-town depots with agents who might
work only a few minutes a day. Companies
also had to operate money-losing local and
branch line passenger trains. With farm-to-market
roads and other highway construction
and improved waterways, numerous rail appendages,
especially ones that handled mostly
seasonal grain tra.c, became financial liabilities.
And "full crew" laws, actually "excess
crew" statutes, escalated labor costs. A Nebraska
measure, for example, required an extra
flagman on every intrastate passenger
train.</p>

<p>Change, however, was forthcoming. The
Transportation Act of 1958 and other reforms
permitted carriers to reduce their fixed costs,
including closing scores of rural depots (eventually
nearly all of them), eliminating most
passenger service with the creation of Amtrak
in 1971, and abandoning thousands of miles of
lightly used trackage. Then, in the 1960s, railroad
mergers greatly affected the region. Some
roads, for example, the North Western and Soo
Line, expanded by acquiring smaller properties,
and efforts began for megamergers. That
phenomenon struck the region in 1970 with
the formation of Burlington Northern, an
amalgamation of the Burlington, Great Northern,
and Northern Pacific Railroads. Enactment
of the Staggers Act in 1980 further relaxed
regulation and gave railroad managers more
flexibility, especially in matters of rate setting.
New labor accords were also reached with the
unions. By the 1990s the roads that served the
Plains were in good financial health, with supercarriers
Burlington Northern-Santa Fe
and Union Pacific dominating the region. In
1995 the latter announced that it would acquire
the Southern Pacific, a major carrier in Texas
and owner of the former Rock Island's Tucumcari
line between New Mexico and Kansas City.
Trackage unwanted by the rail giants yet still
economically viable commonly emerged as a
short line or larger "regional" operation. After
the early 1980s companies like the Dakota,
Minnesota and Eastern; Farmrail; Kiamichi;
Kyle; and Red River Valley and Western appeared
on the rail map of the Plains. Throughout
the Great Plains, abandoned rail routes
were transformed into a new, more recreational
transportation system: bike paths.</p>

<p>Although drastic changes occurred in the
railway systems in the United States in the
twentieth century, they pale in significance
compared to the developments in the Prairie
Provinces. Intense competition, overexpansion
of lines, and financial exigencies during
World War I wrecked the two transcontinental
companies, the Canadian Northern and
Grand Trunk Pacific. These companies, together
with three other financially troubled
railroads, were amalgamated between 1918 and
1923 into the government-owned Canadian National
Railway. Further changes occurred in the
1930s, when the Canadian Pacific and Canadian
National, distressed by the economic depression,
began to cut back their dense branch line
network in the Prairies, a process that has continued.
The railroads also responded to the economic
stress by systematically diversifying their
activities. The Canadian National expanded its
holdings into marine operations, resource industries,
hotels, and radio (early on, the company
had launched Canada’s first radio network),
while the Canadian Pacific extended its
operations to fields such as mining, real estate,
and telecommunications, some of which have
been much more profitable than the rail operations.
Moreover, the two railway companies established
the two largest airlines operating in
Canada today. The Trans-Canada Airline (since
1964 Air Canada) began in 1937 as a wholly
owned subsidiary of the Canadian National,
while Canadian Pacific Airlines was founded in
1942 by the Canadian Pacific.</p>

<p>The growing public ownership of railways
and increasing government regulation of
transportation companies have given rise to
intense ideological debates. One of the most
controversial issues has been the regulation of
freight rates, which in 1903 became the responsibility
of the Board of Railway Commissioners,
an independent, quasi-judiciary regulation
agency. Reorganized in 1938 as the
Canadian Transport Commission, the board
has faced the difficult task of finding a balance
between the railway companies, which have
demanded higher rates as a compensation for
their loss of patronage and rising costs, and
the Prairie farmers, who have pressed for
lower rates. More recently, the debate has
shifted to the privatization of the Canadian
National, which was accomplished in 1995.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Electric Interurban Railways</head>

<p>While the Great Plains could never claim to be
the heartland of the electric interurban railway,
promoters from Manitoba to Texas made
numerous efforts from the late 1890s until the
early 1920s to realize their traction dreams.
Distinct from the electric street railway, commonly
found in the major towns and cities on
the Plains after 1890, which provided local service
and possibly a short extension into the
nearby countryside to serve an amusement
park, cemetery, or special facility, the interurban
was designed to connect two or more
communities with services similar to those
provided by steam railroads, hauling passengers,
express, and often carload freight.</p>

<p>Interurban enthusiasts believed that their
alternative transport form held advantages, at
least for modest distances, over their steam
railroad competitors. Unlike the railroad, the
electric car promised "no cinders, no dirt, no
dust, no smoke." Electric roads could be operated
with greater frequency than steam lines,
since interurbans had generally lower operating
costs. Most passenger interurbans ran on
hourly or semihourly schedules and stopped
virtually anywhere, while steam trains usually
made only several daily trips, pausing at a limited
number of points. There was also the attraction
of transportation at cheaper rates.
Typical charges for interurban travel were less
than those of steam carriers. This made intercity
traction particularly attractive in a period
of intense consumer unrest throughout the
Plains in the late nineteenth and early twentieth
centuries.</p>

<p>In the Great Plains, electric interurbans appeared
mostly in the central and southern sections.
Only one interurban served the Prairie
Provinces. The Winnipeg, Selkirk and Lake
Winnipeg Railway, partially built in 1904 as a
steam road, became electrically powered four
years later and developed into a nearly fortymile
traction system. No "true" interurban
ever operated in North Dakota, although in
1912 the state claimed twenty-six miles of urban
trolley lines. South Dakota received only a
small interurban in the Black Hills and about
twenty miles of electric street railways. Nebraska
fared better. Although residents never
rode a bona fide interurban, three electric railways
with interurban names actually appeared:
Omaha, Lincoln and Beatrice Railway; Omaha
and Southern Interurban; and the Omaha and
Lincoln Railway and Light Company. These
firms in reality were urban trolleys with rural
extensions, part of nearly 250 miles of streetcar
operations in the state. Kansas, Oklahoma, and
Texas, however, built a host of interurbans. Kansas
carriers, with about 250 miles of intercity line
under wire, chiefly served metropolitan Kansas
City, or the Tri-State Mineral Belt of the southeast.
A smaller mileage, about 150 miles, laced
sections of Oklahoma, but Sooner state companies
were more scattered. The principal system,
the seventy miles owned by the Oklahoma
Railway, radiated out of Oklahoma City in three
directions: north to Guthrie, west to El Reno,
and south to Norman. Texas had the most interurbans
and the greatest mileage. Eleven companies
built approximately 500 miles, about 350
miles of which were in the greater Dallas area.
Complementing the interurban mileage in
these three states were nearly 900 miles of electric
street railways.</p>

<p>Scores of interurbans were projected
throughout the Great Plains. These "paper"
projects proliferated during the two boom periods
immediately preceding and following
the Panic of 1907. Some schemes were monumental.
Early in the century a group of promoters
suggested a high-speed electric railway
from Winnipeg to the Gulf of Mexico. The
mileage of unbuilt interurbans in Texas alone
exceeded 20,000 route miles, the most projected
in any American state.</p>

<p>An important characteristic of interurbans
on the Plains was their relative durability.
They often developed carload freight capabilities
and could interchange rolling stock with
connecting steam roads. Interurbans like the
Arkansas Valley Interurban, Kansas City–Kaw
Valley, Northeast Oklahoma, and Texas Electric,
generally built to steam road standards,
became viable freight short lines or switching
operations and lasted long after the general
demise of the interurban industry during the
late 1920s and early 1930s. Several segments of
track continue to serve freight consumers. But
in general, electric roads failed to develop a
competitive freight business and died because
of the onslaught of motor, especially automobile,
competition.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Autos, Buses, and Trucks</head>

<p>Even though the Great Plains possessed an ample
network of rail lines, the appearance of
internal combustion vehicles in the early part
of the twentieth century prompted residents to
demand better public roads. By World War I,
good roads associations were pushing hard to
lift the region out of the mud and dust. During
the 1920s, extensive programs of road improvements,
especially paving projects, had
been implemented. By the midtwenties the
federal government had embarked upon road
improvements, and pioneer endeavors such as
the 3,331-mile coast-to-coast Lincoln Highway,
the "Main Street across America," became part
of the national system of highways. Whether
for short trips or to take an "auto vacation," a
rapidly growing number of citizens made car
travel part of their daily routine.</p>

<p>More than motorists drove the roadways of
the Great Plains. Motor truck operators,
largely unregulated by the states until the
1920s and not by the federal government until
1935, siphoned off lucrative shipments that
previously had moved by rail. Yet some executives
of mid-American railroads applauded
the coming of the truck. After all, these versatile
vehicles could feed tra.c to important
rail arteries, allowing carriers to abandon
money-losing appendages and eliminating the
need for further branch line construction.
This position was, for example, advocated by
Ralph Budd, president of the Great Northern
Railway.</p>

<p>Bus operators made their debut about the
same time in the Great Plains. Resembling
early providers of trucking services, these firms
were usually small affairs, often mom-and-pop
enterprises. But that changed quickly. While
trucking remained highly atomized until after
World War II, buses in the region tended to be
operated by large concerns. The Greyhound
Corporation emerged during the formative
years of the bus and by 1930 provided coast-to-coast
and interregional service.</p>

<p>Railroads, too, played a major role in the
bus business. The Union Pacific Railroad is
a good example. In 1929 the company purchased
Interstate Transit Lines, which mostly
served communities in Nebraska, and used
the firm to launch a series of interstate passenger
routes in the Great Plains and to destinations
such as Chicago (with a Chicago and
North Western bus affiliate), California, and
the Pacific Northwest. Entry by the Union Pacific
into bus transportation generated profits
and gave residents of the Central Plains even
better public transportation. As other carriers
did, the Union Pacific used some of its bus
routes to make its case to regulators that unprofitable
passenger trains could be removed,
since patrons had an alternative public transit
choice.</p>

<p>After World War II the level of bus service
started to decline in the Great Plains and elsewhere.
Railroads sold off their bus routes and
equipment to other bus carriers, usually to the
Trailways System, or else liquidated their assets.
Yet, unlike in some parts of the country,
some national, regional, and local bus companies
remained on the Plains. This usually
happened because alternative forms of public
transportation were frequently lacking and
also because the percentage of elderly customers
who could not or would not drive was
high.</p>

<p>All forms of motor transport, private and
public, benefited from updated highways. By
the early 1950s inadequate roadways troubled
and even angered residents of the Great Plains.
Bridges and roads did not meet travel requirements;
often they were too narrow, at times
they were clogged with vehicles, and they regularly
suffered from physical deterioration
caused in part by the same freezing and thawing
that produced annual spring breakups.
Construction of the Trans-Canada Highway in
the 1950s and 1960s (the longest national highway
in the world) and, in the United States, an
extensive system of interstate highways made
possible by the National Defense Highway Act
of 1956 best typified this massive modernization.
These improvements instantly gave motorists
and truckers the power to drive at much
higher speeds for longer unbroken stretches.
Traffic boomed accordingly. Better roads did
not create a transportation utopia, but they were
extremely popular.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Aviation</head>

<p>Because of long distances between major regional
centers, residents of the Great Plains
early on enthusiastically embraced commercial
aviation and quickly developed airmindedness.
While barnstormers had been
visiting fairs and other outdoor events to perform
their daring acts of aerial wizardry since
before World War I, commercial aviation
emerged only during the mid-1920s. In 1925
Congress passed the Kelly Act, under which
the federal government turned over operation
of airmail routes from the army to private parties.
With mail contracts in hand, commercial
passenger operators had the opportunity to
make their services financially viable. Since pioneer
aircraft could carry few people, subsidies
were essential.</p>

<p>Within a decade the Great Plains arguably
was enjoying better air service than any other
region in the United States. The Plains benefited
from stops by the newly established transcontinental
carriers, American Airways, Transcontinental
and Western Air, and United Airlines.
After all, the range of the era's propeller craft
was limited, and nonstop flights for major distances
were impossible. By the early 1930s
nearly a dozen distinctly Plains airlines complemented
the ever-expanding network of
commercial routes. For example, Braniff Airways
linked Bartlesville, Oklahoma, Kansas
City, Oklahoma City, and Tulsa; Reed Airline
tied Oklahoma City with Wichita Falls; and US
Airways connected Denver with Kansas City
and provided intermediate stops at the Kansas
communities of Goodland and Salina. Canadian
carriers, too, bound the country from
coast to coast, and firms like Air Canada tied
together interior places such as Winnipeg and
Brandon, Manitoba.</p>

<p>As with other commercial transportation
forms, the aviation industry hardly remained
static. Companies emerged, expanded, merged,
and failed. Establishment in 1938 of the Civil
Aeronautical Authority (later the Civil Aeronautics
Board or <hi rend="smallcaps">CAB</hi>), which controlled airline
routes and fares, brought general stability
to the industry. Service in the Great Plains
continued to be good after federal intervention,
but other regions, especially the Far
West, offered better financial opportunities
and therefore received greater attention.</p>

<p>When partial federal deregulation occurred
in 1978, inhabitants of the American Plains
quickly felt this opening shot in the regulatory
revolution. The phenomenon took several
forms. Trunk carriers like Northwest and
United often reduced the number of flights or
ended service outright, particularly to less-populated
destinations like Jamestown, North
Dakota, and North Platte, Nebraska. These
large carriers concentrated on maximizing the
profit potentials that were inherent in jet aircraft,
introduced in the late 1950s. To fill the
void, residents of the Plains frequently saw
formation or expansion of a host of commuter
airlines. Air Midwest, launched in 1965
and based in Wichita, Kansas, for example,
moved from being a largely Kansas operation
into serving other parts of the Central and
Southern Plains. Air Midwest was more successful
than most firms; some airline companies
have histories that can be measured in
months rather than years. With the dissolution
of the cab, entry into commercial aviation
became relatively easy, but financial risks
were frequently high and failures common.</p>

<p>By contrast, in the Prairie Provinces, particularly
in Alberta, commercial aviation has
grown much more steadily. For example, Calgary
and Edmonton experienced the largest
increases in passenger tra.c among all major
Canadian cities in the 1970s, and Pacific Western
Airlines, with headquarters in Calgary,
emerged as the largest regional airline in Canada.
This growth can largely be attributed to
the favorable overall economic development
of the region, although the aviation industry
in the Prairie Provinces has also benefited
from increasing air traffic to northern centers
such as Yellowknife since World War II.</p>

<p>The early development of aviation in the
Great Plains led to another facet of this transportation
form: extensive aircraft manufacturing.
Wichita emerged early as an important
center for airplane building. By 1928 the city
could proudly proclaim itself as the "Air Capital."
Companies such as Beech Aircraft Corporation
(1932–present), Boeing Wichita (1934–present),
Cessna Aircraft Company (1927–present), and Learjet (1962–present) became
nationally, even internationally, famous. Beech
Aircraft, for one, supplied airplanes to individuals,
companies, and commuter airlines like
Air Midwest. Kansas aircraft manufacturers
between 1908 and 1993 produced approximately
266,500 aircraft, including kits, for the
commercial market.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Conclusion</head>

<p>Transportation has been and will continue to
be a vital part of life in the Great Plains. A
palimpsest of sorts can readily be detected.
The region is dotted with remnants of its water,
road, rail, and aviation past: the ruts of the
Oregon Trail, for example, are still etched into
the landscape in places a century and a half
after the last wagons headed west. These physical
remains underscore the evolving nature of
transport. With great distances to conquer,
Plains residents repeatedly have demonstrated
their willingness to embrace the best and most
practical technologies. It is hardly surprising
that dependability and speed have been the
factors in regional transportation that have
enjoyed widespread public support.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">CITIES AND TOWNS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ct.050">T-Towns</ref>; <ref n="egp.ct.055">Wichita, Kansas</ref>; <ref n="egp.ct.057">Winnipeg, Manitoba</ref> /
<hi rend="smallcaps">INDUSTRY</hi>: <ref n="egp.ind.002">Aerospace</ref>; <ref n="egp.ind.006">Automotive</ref>; <ref n="egp.ind.010">Canadian Pacific Railway</ref>; <ref n="egp.ind.022">Fur Trade</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">NATIVE AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.na.038">Horse</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">WATER</hi>: <ref n="egp.wat.027">Rivers</ref>.</p>
</div2>

<closer>
<signed>H. Roger Grant<lb/>
Clemson University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Athearn, Robert G. <title level="m">Union Pacific Country</title>. Chicago: Rand
McNally, 1971.</bibl> <bibl>Gard, Wayne. <title level="m">The Chisholm Trail</title>. Norman:
University of Oklahoma Press, 1954.</bibl> <bibl>Grant, H. Roger. <title level="m">The
North Western: A History of the Chicago and North Western
Railway System</title>. De Kalb: Northern Illinois University
Press, 1996.</bibl> <bibl>Hidy, Ralph, et al. <title level="m">The Great Northern Railway:
A History</title>. Boston: Harvard Business School Press,
1988.</bibl> <bibl>Hofsommer, Don L. <title level="m">Katy Northwest: The Story of a
Branch Line Railroad</title>. Boulder <hi rend="smallcaps">CO</hi>: Pruett Publishing
Company, 1976.</bibl> <bibl>Hunter, Louis. <title level="m">Steamboats of the Western
Rivers: An Economic and Technological History</title>. Cambridge:
Harvard University Press, 1949.</bibl> <bibl>Lamb, W. Kaye.
<title level="m">History of the Canadian Pacific Railway</title>. New York: Macmillan
Publishing Company, 1977.</bibl> <bibl>Martin, Albro. <title level="m">James J.
Hill and the Opening of the Northwest</title>. New York: Oxford
University Press, 1976.</bibl> <bibl>Quastler, I. E. <title level="m">Air Midwest: The First
Twenty Years</title>. San Diego: Airline Press of California, 1985.</bibl>
<bibl>Regehr, T. D. <title level="m">The Canadian Northern Railway: Pioneer
Road of the Northern Prairies, 1895–1918</title>. Toronto: Macmillan
Publishing Company, 1976.</bibl> <bibl>Rhodes, Jack. <title level="m">Intercity
Bus Lines of the Southwest</title>. College Station: Texas A&amp;M
University Press, 1988.</bibl> <bibl>Stevens, G. R. <title level="m">History of the Canadian
National Railways</title>. New York: Macmillan Publishing
Company, 1973.</bibl> <bibl>Winther, Oscar Osburn. <title level="m">The Transportation
Frontier: Trans-Mississippi West, 1965–1890</title>. New York:
Holt, Rinehart and Winston, 1964.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>