<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.tra.002 SYSTEM "egp.tra.002.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.tra.002">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Automobiles</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Michael D. Green</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.tra.002</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Green, Michael D.">Michael D. Green</author>. <title level="a">"Automobiles."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">798-799</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-22</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">AUTOMOBILES</head>

<figure n="egp.tra.002" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Fritchie Electric on cross-country trip, Denver, Colorado, 1908</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Automobility revolutionized life in the Great
Plains. Marked by vast distances and low population
widely scattered on farms and ranches,
the region was characterized by isolation, loneliness,
and provincialism. Before 1900, railroads
controlled transportation on the Plains.
To be viable, farms had to be close to rail lines.
Crops and cattle went to market on the rails;
goods and equipment arrived the same way.
Residents of the Plains, on horseback or in
carriages and wagons, rarely traveled outside
a ten- or twelve-mile radius. Automobility
meant personally controlled freedom to travel,
and for Plains families, cars and trucks opened
new economic and social worlds.</p>

<p>Rural Americans were initially suspicious of
automobiles. Expensive, fast, noisy, unreliable,
dangerous, the playthings of the urban rich, it
was hard to imagine that they could ever have
value in the lives of country folk. The town
council of Mitchell, South Dakota, expressed
the thoughts of many when it banned automobiles
from within town limits. But by 1905
cars had become more reliable and less expensive.
Henry Ford, who had founded his car
company two years before, concluded that the
secret to success in the automobile business
lay in the production of a light, rugged,
powerful, inexpensive car that virtually anyone
could afford. In 1908 he introduced the
Model T.</p>

<p>The touring car, a five-passenger vehicle
with a canvas top and side curtains, was the
staple of Model T production. With 22 horsepower
to pull 1,200 pounds, the car could go
virtually anywhere and do practically anything.
Cowboys ran cattle in Model Ts, and
farmers carried grain and calves to market in
them. Model Ts put Plains farmers and ranchers
on wheels and introduced them to a whole
new world.</p>

<p>Throughout its production, from 1908 to
1927, virtually the only thing that changed
about a Model T was its price, which declined
from $850 to $290. Other models were available,
including the popular two-seat runabout,
which was even less expensive, and a
much more costly sedan, but the touring car
outsold them all and became by far the most
common car on the roads.</p>

<p>Great Plains farmers and ranchers, enjoying
remarkable prosperity prior to the 1920s,
snapped cars up in numbers that astonished
everybody. In 1910 the ratio of adult population
to cars was 65 to 1 in Nebraska and 72 to 1
in North Dakota, ranking them fourth and
fifth in the nation. Kansas and South Dakota
were fourteenth and nineteenth. In the early
1920s, after millions of cars had been sold, the
rankings told a similar story&#8211;Nebraska and
Kansas were third and fourth, South Dakota
was seventh. By 1936 five Great Plains states
were in the top ten in car ownership as a proportion
of population, with Wyoming in third
place with a population to motor vehicle ratio
of 3 to 1. The national average in 1936 was
nearly 5 to 1. Such figures document the extraordinary
popularity&#8211;and necessity&#8211;of
motor vehicles among the residents of the
Great Plains. Purchasing cars and trucks in
much larger numbers than buyers elsewhere,
they were targeted by the automakers as the
best market in the country.</p>

<p>Prior to 1930, over half of these vehicles
were Fords. Chevrolet rapidly gained preeminence,
however, thanks to the introduction in
1929 of a six-cylinder engine that came in
four-door sedan trim for only $675. Ford
never regained its earlier dominance of the
market, even with its introduction in 1932 of
an efficient and powerful <hi rend="smallcaps">V</hi>8. Between the two
there was little room left for other makes, although
hopeful Great Plains entrepreneurs
entered the automobile business. At least 142
firms organized to manufacture cars and
trucks for sale in the exploding local market.
Some, such as the Great Smith of Topeka and
the Patriot of Lincoln, enjoyed brief success,
but none could effectively compete.</p>

<p>Car ownership liberated Plains residents
from the isolation and loneliness of life and
expanded their world beyond the limitations
imposed by horse-drawn travel and stationary
rails. At the same time, the freedom of movement
drastically changed Great Plains society.
One-room schools gave way to consolidated
county schools; country doctors moved to
towns, opened offices, and associated themselves
with local hospitals; and crossroads general
stores closed while farm families whizzed
by on their way to department stores in town.
Town churches absorbed rural members while
country churches withered. Indeed, towns became
the focus of rural life.</p>

<p>At the same time, fertile land too distant
from rail lines to be profitable could now be
farmed, and with acreage once devoted to keeping
horses put into market production, yields
soared. The overproduction and collapsing
prices of the 1920s were, in part, also the result
of automobility. The transformation of the
Plains was the result of the desires of thousands
of individuals to free themselves from the
dreary loneliness of life in isolation. Automobiles
made that transformation possible.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">INDUSTRY</hi>: <ref n="egp.ind.006">Automotive</ref> /
<hi rend="smallcaps">SPORTS AND RECREATION</hi>: <ref n="egp.sr.044">Riding Around</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Michael D. Green<lb/>
University of North Carolina</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Berger, Michael L. <title level="m">The Devil Wagon in God's Country: The
Automobile and Social Change in Rural America, 1893–1929</title>.
Hamden <hi rend="smallcaps">CT</hi>: Archon Books, 1979.</bibl> <bibl>Flink, James J. <title level="m">The
Automobile Age</title>. Cambridge <hi rend="smallcaps">MA</hi>: <hi rend="smallcaps">MIT</hi> Press, 1988.</bibl> <bibl>Wik,
Reynold M. <title level="m">Henry Ford and Grass-Roots America</title>. Ann
Arbor: University of Michigan Press, 1972.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>