<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.law.012">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Cattle Codes</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Ray August</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.law.012</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="August, Ray">Ray August</author>. <title level="a">"Cattle Codes."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">449-450</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-04</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">CATTLE CODES</head>

<p>Cattle laws on the Great Plains trace their
origins and their defining elements to similar
laws in the eastern United States. The main
cattle laws, which are interdependent rules
regulating the raising and marketing of livestock,
govern fencing, branding, rustling, recording,
and strays.</p>

<p>Fencing laws are of two types. The oldest of
these, used in northern Europe as early as the
fifth century, requires farmers to fence out animals
to protect crops. The newer laws, which
were adopted in more populated livestock
areas beginning in the seventeenth and eighteenth
centuries, require livestock owners to
fence in their animals. At the time the United
States became independent, fencing-in laws
had been adopted in England as well as in
Spain and its colonies but not in the former
English colonies. When American cattlemen
came to the Great Plains in the nineteenth
century, they brought with them the fencingout
laws of the eastern United States, and they
ignored the fencing-in laws that had previously
prevailed under Spanish and Mexican
rule in Texas and New Mexico.</p>

<p>Although branding was never followed in
England, it was a common practice in the English colonies and in the eastern United States
after independence. It was similarly used in
the Spanish colonies and in Mexico after its
independence. However, unlike the practice in
Spain and Mexico, livestock owners in the
eastern United States were required to use a
system of town brands, in addition to their
own personal brands, to identify the origin of
their animals. Cattle in Salem, Massachusetts,
for example, had to be branded with an "S."
This same system was adopted on the Great
Plains; for instance, the first branding law
adopted in Colorado required cattle from
Arapaho County to carry an "A" brand.</p>

<p>The parentage of the Great Plains cattlerustling
laws can be traced to the eastern
United States because of an anomaly originally
peculiar to the rustling law of North
Carolina. To convict an individual of altering
a cattle brand, North Carolina required a
prosecutor to first prove that the original
brand was recorded. This same requirement
was later adopted in Texas, Colorado, and
other parts of the American West. Laws in
Texas similarly made illegal the stealing of
"neat cattle" and the "altering or defacing" of
another's brand. Both of these expressions
were copied from statutes in the East.</p>

<p>Early Great Plains recording statutes followed
procedures used in the East. As the English
had done since medieval times, easterners
relied on a toll system for proving
ownership of livestock. Anyone moving cattle
from one county to another had to register his
individual brands in the county he was moving
them to. Also, driving cattle without a certified
bill of sale (one endorsed by certain
town, county, or state officials) was similarly
illegal.</p>

<p>Estray statutes, like fencing laws, are of two
kinds: those that require finders to advertise
found animals and those that require owners
to advertise lost animals. In 1747 South Carolina
adopted the first estray statute requiring
finders to advertise in newspapers of general
circulation, a requirement common to all later
American estray statutes, including those
adopted by Great Plains states. The Spanish
colonies and Mexico after its independence
used the second kind of estray statute, with
one exception. When the Mexican state of
Coahuila and Texas adopted a new estray statute
in 1835, it required finders to advertise,
a procedure familiar to the many American
colonists who had recently moved to Texas.
When Texas became independent the next
year, it kept the "finders must advertise" statute
adopted by Coahuila and Texas the year
before.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">AGRICULTURE</hi>: <ref n="egp.ag.014">Branding</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Ray August<lb/>
Washington State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>August, Ray. "Cowboys v. Rancheros: The Origins of
Western American Livestock Law." <title level="j">Southwestern Historical Quarterly</title> 96 (1993): 457–88.</bibl> <bibl>Myres, Sandra L. "The
Ranching Frontier: Spanish Institutional Backgrounds of
the Plains Cattle Industry." In <title level="m">Essays on the American West</title>,
edited by Harold M. Hollingsworth and Sandra L. Myres.
Austin: University of Texas Press for University of Texas at
Arlington, 1969: 19–39.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>