<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fil.031">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main"><hi rend="italic">Hud</hi></title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Samuel J. Umland</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fil.031</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Umland, Samuel J.">Samuel J. Umland</author>. <title level="a">"<hi rend="italic">Hud</hi>."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">270</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-12</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main"><hi rend="italic">HUD</hi></head>
<figure n="egp.fil.031" rend="granted"  type="noclick">
<figDesc>Hud DVD Cover, Widescreen Collection</figDesc>
</figure>      

<p>The motion picture <title>Hud</title> (1963), released by
Paramount, directed by Martin Ritt, and starring
Paul Newman, Melvyn Douglas, Patricia
Neal, and Brandon de Wilde, was based on an
early novel by Larry McMurtry, <title>Horseman, Pass By</title> (1961). Hud was filmed in and around
Claude, a small town a few miles east of Amarillo
in the Texas Panhandle, and its extraordinary
power can be explained by the fact that it
is a morality play cast in the form of a family
drama about Texas cattlemen.</p>

<p>At the center of the drama is Lon (de Wilde),
a parentless teenager who has been raised by
his grandfather, Homer Bannon (Douglas),
and his uncle, Hud Bannon (Newman), two
male role models whose values and ethics are
in collision. Alma (Neal), the housekeeper, a
woman of quiet beauty and dignity, serves as a
surrogate mother for Lon. The dramatic tension
resides in the decision Lon will make regarding
his role model and hence the set of
ethical values and principles represented, on
the one hand, by his grandfather Homer and
on the other by Hud. The decision to cast
Brandon de Wilde, the little boy who so idolized
Shane in <title>Shane</title> (1953), as Lon underscores
the dramatic tension, as <title>Hud</title> is largely about
the passing of heroes of mythic proportions
and the epigones who follow them. Indeed,
<title>Hud</title> resonates with this particular theme of the
Western film, specifically, the passing of a generation
that saw itself and the land as inseparable,
represented by the laconic Homer and his
cattle, and the arrival of a belated, pragmatic
generation, represented by the epigone Hud in
his misguided desire to drill oil wells.</p>

<p>The film garnered Academy Awards for Patricia
Neal, Melvyn Douglas, and cinematographer
James Wong Howe. Paul Newman and
director Martin Ritt were also nominated for
awards, as were the writers of the screenplay,
Irving Ravetch and Harriet Frank Jr. The film
was nominated for best art direction and set
decoration as well.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">LITERARY TRADITIONS</hi>: <ref n="egp.lt.044">McMurtry, Larry</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Samuel J. Umland<lb/>
University of Nebraska at Kearney</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Wiley, Mason, and Damien Bona. <title level="m">Inside Oscar: The Unofficial History of the Academy Awards</title>, edited by Gail Mac-
Coll. New York: Ballantine Books, 1988.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>