<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.sr.022">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Gaming</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Erin Hogan Fouberg</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.sr.022</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Fouberg, Erin Hogan">Erin Hogan Fouberg</author>. <title level="a">"Gaming."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">774</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-20</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">GAMING</head>

<p>Gambling was common in mining towns in
South Dakota and Colorado during the late
nineteenth century. Gambling, or gaming, reappeared
in the Great Plains in response to
antitaxation sentiments in the 1980s, when state,
provincial, and local governments sought an
alternative source of revenue. Many states and
provinces began with lotteries to supplement
their general revenue funds. Today, six Plains
states (Colorado, Kansas, Montana, Nebraska,
South Dakota, and Texas) and all three of the
Prairie Provinces operate lotteries.</p>

<p>Following the adoption of state lotteries in
the United States, local, tribal, and private interests
turned toward gambling as well. In the
late 1980s the city of Deadwood, South Dakota,
looked to its colorful gambling history
to revitalize its economy. The Deadwood You
Bet Committee used the state's initiative process
to introduce a constitutional amendment
to allow gambling in Deadwood. To sell gambling
as a revenue source, the Deadwood progambling
movement focused on gambling's
entertainment value and pledged any revenues
to historic preservation. In 1988 64.3 percent
of voters in South Dakota approved limited
stakes gambling, and in November 1989 gaming
began in Deadwood. Deadwood expected
100 new jobs and $2 million in bets in the first
year. However, even with betting limits of $5,
there were an estimated 1,183 new jobs and $93
million in bets generated during the first six
months.</p>

<p>On the heels of Deadwood's revenue success,
three historical mining communities in
Colorado pushed for gaming. The Central City
Preservation, Inc. Committee used Colorado's
initiative process and won a constitutional
amendment to allow limited stakes gaming in
the cities of Black Hawk, Central City, and
Cripple Creek. By 1995 Deadwood, Black
Hawk, Central City, and Cripple Creek had
forty-seven, nineteen, thirteen, and twentythree
casinos, respectively. All four cities noted
increased congestion and higher property values;
the Colorado cities reported losing local
services and local establishments to tourism
development. One year into gaming in Colorado
and three years into gaming in Deadwood,
respondents to a survey in all four cities
perceived the gaming industries as having an
influence over local government greater than
that of citizens. Only Deadwood respondents
reported a significant increase in historic preservation
efforts.</p>

<p>The gaming landscape of the Great Plains
also includes at least twenty-two casinos (Class
III gaming) on Indian reservations. Most of
the tribal casinos are in South Dakota and
North Dakota, with eight and six each, respectively.
Tribal casinos closer to urban centers
and those casinos that can draw visitors from
nearby states where gaming is not legal have
been particularly successful. For example,
tribal gaming endeavors in western Iowa have
benefited from tighter laws in Nebraska. Riverboat
casinos in Sioux City and Council Bluffs,
Iowa, as well as the pari-mutuel gaming and
slots available in Council Bluffs have also
gained. Riverboat casinos in St. Joseph and
Kansas City, Missouri, also lure visitors from
the population centers of Kansas City, Kansas,
and Omaha, Nebraska.</p>

<p>Unlike the privately run casinos in the
United States, gaming and casino operations
in Canada fall to the provincial governments.
Charitable gaming began in Canada in 1969,
and in 1985 the provinces gained exclusive
control over gaming. All three Prairie Provinces
have lotto, video lottery, and Indian casinos.
Manitoba and Saskatchewan also have
government-operated casinos, and both Saskatchewan
and Alberta have casinos run for
charity. The widespread availability of gaming
in Manitoba, Saskatchewan, Alberta, Montana,
and North Dakota has discouraged the
growth of gaming towns along the Canadian-U.S.
international border.</p>

<p>The spatial distribution of gaming in the
Great Plains ranges from an absence of casino
and Class III tribal gaming in the Southern
Plains to widespread gaming in the Northern
Plains and Prairie Provinces. The difference in
gaming availability between states as well as
the location of population centers at the eastern
periphery of the Plains have encouraged
the growth of several gaming towns and attractions
along state borders. Whether presented
as a way to revive the past and preserve
history, as a harmless form of entertainment,
or as a way to generate revenue without additional
taxation, gaming is changing the economic,
political, social, and cultural landscapes
of the Great Plains.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">IMAGES AND ICONS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ii.018">Deadwood, South Dakota</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Erin Hogan Fouberg<lb/>
Mary Washington College</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Campbell, Colin S., and Garry J. Smith. "Canadian Gambling:
Trends and Public Policy Issues.'' <title level="j">Annals of the American
Academy of Political and Social Science</title> 556 (1998): 22–35.
Fouberg, Erin Hogan. "South Dakota Gaming: A Regional
Analysis." <title level="j">Great Plains Research</title> 5 (1996): 179–212.</bibl>
<bibl>Long, Patrick T. "Early Impacts of Limited Stakes Casino
Gambling on Rural Community Life." <title level="j">Tourism Management</title>
17 (1996): 341–53.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>