<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.gen.037">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Suffrage Movement</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Karen M. Morin</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.gen.037</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Morin, Karen M.">Karen M. Morin</author>. <title level="a">"Suffrage Movement."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">337-338</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-23</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">SUFFRAGE MOVEMENT</head>

<p>The suffrage movement&#8211;the campaign to secure
women's right to vote in federal (presidential)
elections&#8211;comprised the "first wave"
of feminist activism in North America. Several
of the Great Plains states (or former territories)
and the Canadian Prairie Provinces
were the first in their nations to obtain women's
suffrage. This largely white middle-class
movement constituted one of the hardestfought
struggles for equality in the region.
Along with their demand for the vote, suffragists
advanced a number of social and moral
issues to the forefront of North American political
debate.</p>

<p>Many Canadian provinces and U.S. states
had granted partial or limited voting rights
to women on school, taxes, and bond issues
prior to universal suffrage. Canadian women
were federally enfranchised in 1918 (women in
or connected to the armed forces obtained
voting privileges the previous year). In Canada,
women's formal enfranchisement began
in the Prairie Provinces, largely under the
leadership of Nellie McClung. In January 1916
Manitoba became the first province to guarantee
women the right to vote and hold provincial
office, followed by Saskatchewan, Alberta,
and Ontario later that same year.</p>

<p>In the United States, Wyoming Territory led
the way by passing presidential suffrage legislation
in 1869 (with full women's suffrage ensured
with Wyoming's statehood in 1890).
This was fifty-one years before ratification
of the Nineteenth Amendment (the women's
suffrage amendment to the U.S. Constitution).
Neighboring states in the Great Plains
followed Wyoming, granting full women's
suffrage either by constitutional amendment
or by legislative enactment: Colorado (1893),
Kansas (1912), Montana (1914), North Dakota
and Nebraska (1917), and Texas, South Dakota,
and Oklahoma (1918). Thirteen out of
the fifteen states that had ratified a full suffrage
amendment in their state constitutions
prior to the federal constitutional amendment
were in the western half of the country.</p>

<p>The patterns of the women's suffrage movement,
with its roots in eastern cities but its
concrete expression in the Plains, Prairies, and
other points west, were the result of a number
of demographic, political-economic, and social
processes. One way of understanding the
success of suffrage in Wyoming, for example,
is that suffrage was seen as having the potential
to attract women settlers and thereby stabilize
family life and, eventually, the frontier
economy. (Beyond that, the Wyoming territorial
legislative body that passed suffrage
consisted of only fourteen people!) But while
opportunistic politicians may have used suffrage
to promote the Prairies and Plains in this
way, there is no evidence that the women's
vote actually attracted any settlers.</p>

<p>The suffrage movement began in the United
States and Canada in conjunction with a number
of other moral reform movements of the
1830s and 1840s, including abolition, temperance,
and health reform. As middle-class white
women's domain was confined more and more
exclusively to the home, activism in reform
movements became one of the few accepted
"careers" open to them. Women's participation
in reform movements in many ways did
not challenge the division of society into separate
spheres, since many women's involvements
drew on an ideology of women's superior moral character and virtue in the fight for
better schools, health care, and other public
social services. Women's suffrage, like these
other involvements, was expected to reform
politics and thus "civilize" communities.</p>

<p>In Canada, women's service to society, such
as their help in settling the Prairies or their
sacrifices for the war effort, was a primary argument
for women's suffrage. The Woman's
Christian Temperance Union (<hi rend="smallcaps">WCTU</hi>) was active
in Manitoba, where women's "moral authority"
to speak for prohibition lent validity
to their arguments for the vote. The situation
in Kansas was similar: women's struggle for
the vote there was tied to their moral arguments,
especially to the very active wctu
and abolitionist movements. In Kansas, however,
it was also suffrage's identification with
prohibition that provoked much hostility toward
it and delayed its passage far longer than
expected.</p>

<p>The suffrage movement in the Plains and
Prairies was also tied to women's participation
in rural agrarian reform movements such as
the Grange, the Farmers Alliance, and the
Populist Party. Colorado's rural populist
roots, for instance, combined with its urban
radical labor movement, led to the related
movement for women's suffrage. When suffrage
passed in Colorado in 1893, a wide coalition
of support had been established among
white middle-class suffrage leaders, men and
women in organized labor (such as the Labor
Union Party), and rural supporters of agricultural
reform.</p>

<p>On one hand, suffrage was a clear indicator
of women's rights; many women perceived it
as such, and some American women even died
for it. Certainly, early suffragists saw voting
rights as having a clear political purpose. They
managed to establish a feminist discourse in
North America that paved the way for a more
nuanced feminism later in the twentieth century
that was concerned with human rights
more broadly. On the other hand, suffrage
was not necessarily granted as a "women's
rights" issue but was often a cynical and opportunistic
political gesture by elite men.
"Women's rights" were not necessarily advanced
by suffrage, either. In fact, not all
women were granted suffrage (Native American
and Mexican American women, for example,
were not); women's voting patterns
turned out to be similar to men's; and the
social improvement suffragists fought for
largely failed to materialize.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Karen M. Morin<lb/>
Bucknell University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Beeton, Beverly. <title level="m">Women Vote in the West: The Woman Suffrage Movement, 1869-1896</title>. New York: Garland Publishing,
Inc., 1986.</bibl> <bibl>Cleverdon, Catherine L. <title level="m">The Woman Suffrage Movement in Canada</title>. Toronto: Toronto University
Press, 1974.</bibl> <bibl>Flexner, Eleanor. <title level="m">Century of Struggle: The Woman's Rights Movement in the United States</title>. Cambridge:
Harvard University Press, 1975.</bibl>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>