<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fol.004">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Blizzard Stories</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Eric F. Grelson</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2009</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fol.004</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2009</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2009 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Grelson, Eric F.">Eric F. Grelson</author>. <title level="a">"Blizzard Stories."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">291-292</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-16</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">BLIZZARD STORIES</head>

<p>The ferocity of blizzards in the Great Plains
has entered into the region's folklore through
countless stories of tragedy and of survival.
The word "blizzard" originated in the Northern
Plains during the mid–nineteenth century,
perhaps derived from the German blitzartig,
meaning lightninglike, which accurately
portrays the power and swiftness of Great
Plains blizzards.</p>

<p>The first documented Plains blizzard in
which large numbers of people lost their lives
was the January 1872 Buffalo Hunters' Storm,
which swept up so quickly that unprepared
buffalo hunters, many just arrived from the
East, were found dead from the Platte River of
Nebraska to the Texas Panhandle. The Easter
Storm of April 1873 saw the deaths of not only
ranchers and thousands of cattle in the open
country of the Central Plains but also a boy in
Central City, Nebraska, who died trying to
reach a print shop one block away. In the
Great Blizzard of 1886, 100 people and 100,000
cattle died in western Kansas during a series of
storms that struck less than a week apart. In
southwestern Kansas, a man froze to death in
a light linen overcoat with a flyer in his pocket
advertising Kansas as the Italy of America. A
young woman in Clark County, Kansas, became
separated from her family on a half-mile
journey and died within an arm's length of the
door of her brother's house, her hands tangled
in her hair.</p>

<p>Arguably the most tragic blizzard of the
Plains was the School Children's Storm of January
1888, which struck following an exceptionally
warm period. The blizzard hit the
Central Plains when schools were letting out,
and some teachers, new to the Plains, discounted
stories of death during blizzards as
simply tall tales and let their children walk
home. Other teachers released their students
early, hoping they would arrive home before
its full fury. However, temperatures quickly
plummeted to nearly 40&#186; below zero, and
sixty-mile-per-hour winds with snow as fine
as sifted flour reduced visibility to practically
zero on the open prairie. In Pierce County,
Nebraska, a teacher with three students became
hopelessly lost walking 200 yards to her
boarding place, and they spent the night huddled
in a haystack. The children died and the
teacher lost both feet to amputation. In Bon
Homme County, Dakota Territory, the wind
scattered a teacher and her nine students.
They all died and were not found until the
snow had melted months later. An old-timer
of the community advised watching for circling
buzzards to locate the bodies. More than
200 people perished from Saskatchewan to
Texas, most of them children of the Central
Plains and their parents who went out searching
for them.</p>

<p>Although these blizzards brought tragedy to
many Plains settlers, stories of survival also fill
the pages of Great Plains history. A man in Clay
County, Nebraska, survived the Easter Storm
of April 1873 by housing his eight-person family,
one hog, one dog, all his chickens, and four
head of cattle in the same room. In Hastings,
Nebraska, during the same blizzard, people
needing supplies followed a rope tied between
a store and the city well. During the Great
Blizzard of 1886, a wandering range steer in
Lane County, Kansas, burst through the wall of
a sod house and was skinned on the spot, providing
steaks to a family running low on food.
In the same county, a woman checking on the
family cow 100 yards from the house became
disoriented, so she tied her shawl to the cow
and let it lead her home, where both comfortably
waited out the rest of the storm.</p>

<p>The School Children's Storm of 1888 also has
heroic stories of survival. In Jerauld County,
Dakota Territory, a group of schoolchildren
and their teacher held hands to travel the 100
yards to a farmhouse. Missing the house by six
feet, they fell into a small ravine but clambered
back out to reach a straw pile, where they all
survived the night. In Hanson County, Dakota
Territory, two men spliced together several
coils of clothesline and tied one end to the local
mercantile establishment to walk to the schoolhouse,
three blocks away, and guide the children
back to safety. Although many children
died in the storm, others lived, thanks to the
efforts of their teachers who sheltered the children
safe in the schoolhouse, staying awake all
night to keep the stove warm, burning books
and furniture when the woodpile ran out. After
the wind ripped away part of a sod schoolhouse
roof in Valley County, Nebraska, the
teenage teacher tied her sixteen students together
and safely led them to the house where
she boarded, nearly a mile away, prompting
the writing of a song Nebraska children still
sing in elementary school.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT</hi>: <ref n="egp.pe.013">Blizzards</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Eric F. Grelson<lb/>
Barksdale Air Force Base</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Dick, Everett N. <title level="m">The Sod-House Frontier, 1854–1898</title>. Lincoln:
University of Nebraska Press, 1979.</bibl> <bibl>Miner, Craig.
<title level="m">West of Wichita: Settling the High Plains of Kansas, 1865– 1890</title>. Lawrence: University Press of Kansas, 1986.</bibl> <bibl>Sandoz,
Mari. <title level="m">Love Song to the Plains</title>. New York: Harper Brothers,
1961.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>