<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.art.041.01 SYSTEM "egp.art.041.01.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY egp.art.041.02 SYSTEM "egp.art.041.02.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.art.041">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Kane, Paul (1810-1871)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Louisa Iarocci</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.art.041</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Lister, Kenneth R.">Kenneth R. Lister</author>. <title level="a">"Kane, Paul (1810-1871)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">123-124</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-22</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">KANE, PAUL (1810–1871)</head>

<figure n="egp.art.041.01" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Paul Kane. Cree Indians Travelling. Plains Cree. North Saskatchewan River, 1848–1856. Oil, (912.1.49).</figDesc>
</figure>

<figure n="egp.art.041.02" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Paul Kane. Cree Indians Travelling. Plains Cree. North Saskatchewan River, September 1846. Pencil on paper</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Paul Kane is regarded as one of the founding
fathers of Canadian art. Born at Mallow, Ireland,
on September 3, 1810, he immigrated to
Upper Canada with his family around 1819.
He started his artistic career in the 1820s as a
decorative furniture painter and later advertised
as a coach, sign, and house painter. By
the second half of the 1830s he was making his
living as an itinerant portrait painter in a
number of American cities, including Detroit,
Michigan, and Mobile, Alabama. Kane traveled
in Europe from 1841 through 1843 studying
great art, a tour that was the fulfillment of
a long-cherished dream. Following a brief return
to portrait work in the United States,
Kane arrived back in Canada in 1845 with a
mission that would remain his passion for the
remainder of his life.</p>

<p>Between 1845 and 1848 Kane undertook two
westward journeys from Toronto to sketch the
western landscape and the manners and customs of the First Peoples. He returned to
Toronto with more than 500 landscape and
cultural heritage sketches and within one
month opened an exhibition of 240 sketches.
This display was Kane's first solo exhibition
and one of the first public one-person exhibitions
to be held in Canada. He received high
praise in newspaper reviews, and the exhibition
increased public appreciation for Canadian
painting.</p>

<p>Field sketches, however, were only the first
step toward the fulfillment of Kane's vision.
That vision was realized through the patronage
of the Honorable George William Allan,
barrister, senator, mayor of Toronto, and
president of the Western Canada Savings and
Loan Company who gave Kane the resources
he needed to produce a cycle of 100 paintings
to serve as his record of mid-nineteenth-century
landscapes and Indigenous life.</p>

<p>Kane's second journey, from 1846 to 1848,
took him as far west as the Pacific Ocean. He
spent thirteen months on the Plains sketching
the Métis, Sioux, Crees, Assiniboines, and
Blackfoot. More than 160 sketches executed in
pencil, watercolor, and oil on paper represent
invaluable documents of mid-nineteenthcentury
Plains Indian culture and landscape.
The sketches also inspired the oil paintings
that he later executed in his Toronto studio,
but these, rendered in the contemporary European
romantic style, are considerably less
important as historical records.</p>

<p>In June 1846 Kane arrived at the Red River
Settlement on the Red and the Assiniboine
Rivers. Kane's sketch of the settlement represents
a view from the bank of the Red River
and depicts a number of significant landmarks,
such as the St. Boniface Cathedral and
Upper Fort Garry. The oil painting (1848–56)
represents a similar scene, although the viewer
has been securely placed back from the river.
The cattle shed and log raft in the foreground
and the distant buildings of settlement and
commerce in the middle ground embody
"progress" and a tamed landscape.</p>

<p>The oil painting <title>Indian Summer on the Saskatchewan</title> (1848–56) exemplifies Kane's
desire to represent the scenery of the Plains.
The oil image is inspired by nature, and details
are taken from field sketches; however,
the balanced placement of the trees and valley
banks, the easy slope into the distance, and the
pervasive yellow glow endow the painting
with a melancholy, retrospective cast characteristic
of romantic artistic conventions.</p>

<p>Kane's tendency to depict the romantic is
likewise shown in the oil painting <title>Cree Indians Travelling</title> (1848–56). The 1846 sketch of the
same title is the basis for the oil painting, although
in the painting Kane made a number
of changes to the overall composition. The
vegetation and human activity in the foreground
as well as the middle-ground break of
color between the landscape and the sky are
conventions in the picturesque style and illustrate
Kane's subjective vision and his rendering
of the imaginative truth.</p>

<p>In his oil paintings, although they are informed
by his sketches, Kane harmonized
with expressions of current artistic conventions.
In his field sketches, on the other hand,
Kane left a record rich with depictions of
Plains landscape and cultural history. The artist
died in Toronto on February 20, 1871.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Kenneth R. Lister<lb/>
Royal Ontario Museum</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Harper, J. Russell. <title level="m">Paul Kane's Frontier</title>. Fort Worth: Amon
Carter Museum of Western Art, 1971.</bibl> <bibl>Kane, Paul. <title level="m">Wanderings of an Artist among the Indians of North America</title>.
Mineola <hi rend="smallcaps">NY</hi>: Dover, 1996.</bibl> <bibl>MacLaren, I. S. "Journal of Paul
Kane's Western Travels." <title level="j">American Art Journal</title> 21 (1989):
23–62.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>