<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ag.012">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Barley</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Patricia Juskiw</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ag.012</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Juskiw, Patricia">Patricia Juskiw</author>. <title level="a">"Barley."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">35</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-12-10</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">BARLEY</head>

<p>Fields of barley are an increasingly common
sight in the Northern Great Plains. The major
barley-growing provinces and states include
Alberta, Saskatchewan, Manitoba, North Dakota,
and Montana. In Alberta, for example,
in 1997 5.6 million acres were seeded to barley,
a crop acreage exceeded only by wheat. North
Dakota, with 2 million acres under barley
in 1998, produces almost one-third of the national
output.</p>

<p>Barley is most famous for its use as malt in
the brewing and spirits industries. But due
to high-glucan and dietary fiber fractions in
some types of barley, there is a growing interest
in barley in the food industry. Barley is also
widely used as a feedgrain and for silage (conserved
green matter). Beef cattle fed on barley
have similar rates of weight gain as those fed
on corn, and dairy cows fed barley silage have
similar gains as those fed alfalfa silage.</p>

<p>There are two main types of barley, sixrowed
and two-rowed. Six-rowed barley has
three kernels at each node of the head, and
with two sides to every head, appears to have
six kernels in a row around the head. Tworowed
barley has one kernel at each node, appearing
to have only two kernels in a row. Barley
comes in both hulled and hulless forms.
Hulless barley is similar to wheat in that the
hull is removed, exposing the kernel, during
threshing. Hulless barley is associated with reduced
manure production, an important consideration
for intensive livestock production
where disposal of manure is costly and difficult.
From the beer in your glass to the meat
on your plate, barley has an important role to
play in its production.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Patricia Juskiw<lb/>
Alberta Agriculture, Food and Rural Development Field Crop Development Centre</signed>
</closer>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>