<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ea.035">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Spaniards</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Jeffrey S. Smith</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ea.035</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Smith, Jeffrey S.">Jeffrey S. Smith</author>. <title level="a">"Spaniards."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">247-248</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-09</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">SPANIARDS</head>

<p>From the Andean highlands and central Mexico
to the northern reaches of the upper Rio
Grande, Spanish citizens worked to meet
the crown's unquenchable thirst for mineral
wealth, new lands, and Catholic converts.
However, while Spain's efforts proved successful
elsewhere, they were met with sound defeat
in the Great Plains. The story of Spaniards
in the Great Plains, therefore, is mainly one of
Spanish explorers.</p>

<p>The first Spaniards to reach the Great Plains
(the specific geography of their route is unknown)
were &#193;lvar N&#250;&#241;ez Cabeza de Vaca,
Andr&#233;s Dorantes, and Castillo Maldonado,
along with Estevan, an African Arab. They
were the only survivors of the disastrous Panfilo
de Narv&#225;ez expedition. Their eventful
journey&#8211;from about 1529 to 1536&#8211;back to
what is now Mexico took them across the
Southern Plains of Texas. Cabeza de Vaca and
his men arrived in Mexico City claiming to
have seen such marvels as herds of buffalo and
cities of gold. The reports quickly led the
Spanish crown to commission an expedition
to secure the purported riches.</p>

<p>In the same manner as other Spanish conquistadors
before him, Francisco V&#225;squez de
Coronado set out north from Mexico in 1540
with hopes of attaining great wealth and fame.
His initial goal was to find the fabled Seven
Cities of Cíbola. He found instead Pueblo villages
lacking in any great wealth. Disillusioned
at not finding the seven golden cities, he was
easily persuaded (by the stories of an Indian
slave) to continue his search in a more easterly
direction. In 1541 Coronado and thirty of
his men struck out across the Llano Estacado
looking for Quivira, another illusionary place
of wealth. Quivira turned out to be only the
grass lodges of the Wichitas, near Great Bend,
Kansas. Disappointed again, he retreated to
New Mexico. His report to the crown indicated
that while the country was of great agricultural
potential and similar to Spain, it held
no place for Spaniards; simply put, there was
no gold.</p>

<p>It was almost two centuries after Coronado
before Spaniards again pushed deep into the
Great Plains. In 1720 Don Pedro de Villasur
was sent to investigate French activities in the
Central Plains. His expedition took him as far
north and east as the Platte River in central
Nebraska, where his party was attacked and
defeated by Otoes and Pawnees. This disaster
marked the end of the Spanish presence in the
Central Plains, except for fur traders, most
notably the Missouri Fur Company under
Manuel Lisa, who pushed up the Missouri
River from St. Louis in the late years of the
eighteenth century and early years of the nineteenth
century. Spain primarily focused its attention
on maintaining sovereignty over the
Southern Plains of New Mexico, Colorado,
Oklahoma, and Texas.</p>

<p>While Spaniards persevered as explorers,
they failed miserably as Great Plains settlers.
Permanent Spanish settlement on the
Plains did not begin until 1757. In a deceptive
ploy aimed at forming an alliance against
their archenemy the Comanches, the Lipua
Apaches petitioned the Spanish government
to establish a mission on the banks of the San
Saba River near present-day Menard, Texas.
The settlement was a failure, however, because
few Apaches converted to Catholicism, and on
March 16, 1758, the Comanches attacked the
village, killing all but four residents and burning
the mission buildings to the ground. For
approximately ten years the Spanish government
tried to resurrect the mission community,
but to no avail. The settlement was finally
abandoned in 1770, thus ending Spain's attempt
at founding a mission settlement in the
territory of the Plains Indians. In 1786 the
Spanish entered into a treaty with the Comanches,
which ushered in a period of accommodation
and trade, rather than settlement,
on the Southwestern Plains.</p>

<p>By 1821, the year in which political control
of the Southern Plains was transferred to
the newly formed Mexican government and
the Santa Fe Trail opened, the region was still
unsettled by Spaniards. Hispanos (Spanish
Americans) had spread their sheep operations
east into the Great Plains from the upper Rio
Grande, occupying a territory that would, by
1900, extend out into the Texas and Oklahoma
Panhandles, but that was the extent of the
Spanish influence.</p>

<p>Despite the best efforts of the Spanish
crown, permanent Spanish settlements in the
Great Plains failed for at least four reasons.
First, there was little to attract Spanish citizens
to the Great Plains. Expeditions became
tedious marches through a vast, seemingly
empty land, where nothing of value was found
to warrant the price of settlement. Second, the
Spanish system of employing Indian labor
could not be applied to the mobile people of
the Plains. The Plains Indians were too nomadic
and too independent to be restricted to
settlements. Third, the Plains Indians quickly
and violently opposed Spanish infiltration.
After the Apaches acquired the horse in 1684
and the Comanches in about 1714, they no
longer tolerated the Spaniards invading their
land. Finally, despite the fact that they alone
among European colonizers were accustomed
to arid climates, Spaniards regarded the physical
environment as too inhospitable. The barren
Llano Estacado of west Texas, for example,
was perceived as nothing more than a transition
zone, a land to be politically controlled
but not necessarily settled. Spain preferred to
use the Great Plains as a buffer zone protecting
its northern colonies from French and,
later, American interference.</p>

<p>Today, the Spanish legacy in the Great
Plains has all but faded. Hispanos still live,
as minorities, in Plains towns such as Roswell,
New Mexico, and Pueblo, Colorado, but
their numbers have been surpassed by the inmigration
of Latinos since World War II.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi>: <hi rend="smallcaps">HISPANIC AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ha.021">Hispano Homeland</ref>; <ref n="egp.ha.039">San Sab&#225; Mission and Presidio</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Jeffrey S. Smith<lb/>
Kansas State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Vigil, Ralph H., Frances W. Kaye, and John R. Wunder.
<title level="m">Spain and the Plains: Myths and Realities of Spanish Exploration and Settlement on the Great Plains</title>. Niwot: University
Press of Colorado, 1994.</bibl> <bibl>Webb, Walter Prescott. <title level="m">The Great Plains</title>. New York: Grosset and Dunlap, 1931.</bibl> <bibl>Weber,
David J. <title level="m">The Spanish Frontier in North America</title>. New
Haven <hi rend="smallcaps">CT</hi>: Yale University Press, 1992.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>