<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ea.009">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Fidler, Peter (1769-1822)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Barbara Belyea</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ea.009</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Belyea, Barbara">Barbara Belyea</author>. <title level="a">"Fidler, Peter (1769-1822)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">229-230</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-02</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">FIDLER, PETER (1769-1822)</head>

<p>Peter Fidler's service to the Hudson's Bay
Company spanned the three most important
periods of the fur trade. He was the last of the
company's winterers; later he faced the cutthroat
opposition of the North West Company
in its richest fur region; and in the last
years of his life he helped to organize and sustain
the Red River colony.</p>

<p>In 1788 nineteen-year-old Fidler left his native
Derbyshire, signed on as a laborer with
the Hudson's Bay Company, and traveled that
summer to York Factory. A year later he accompanied
William Tomison up the Saskatchewan
River and spent the winter as "writer" at
South Branch House, the position filled by
David Thompson three years before. Philip
Turnor, the company's surveyor since 1778,
taught Fidler and Thompson the elements of
navigation and cartography at Cumberland
House during the winter of 1789–90. These
months of intensive instruction were to be
Turnor's most important contribution to the
scientific knowledge of the continental interior.
From that moment to the end of their
active lives, his two students would keep detailed
journals, map the vast extent of the British
fur trade, and survey for new communities
at the edges of its settled occupation.</p>

<p>The following year Fidler paddled with
Turnor as far as the North West Company
post of Ile &#224; la Crosse, where they stayed as
guests of the rival company and then pushed
on to survey access to Great Slave Lake. In
1791–92 Fidler wintered with a band of Chipewyans,
learning their language and sharing
their way of life. The following winter he spent
almost five months with the Peigans as they
moved along the front ranges of the Rocky
Mountains. The Hudson's Bay Company practice
of sending young employees alone or in
pairs to live with Native bands dated from Anthony
Henday's inland journey from York Factory
in 1754–55. By Fidler's time, trading posts
extended European organization to the Athabaska
region and the upper Saskatchewan watershed.
These inland posts, rather than York
Factory, were Fidler's points of departure, and
his time with each band was much shorter than
for previous generations of winterers, from
Henday to Tomison. After 1793 the practice was
discontinued.</p>

<p>Fidler spent the next nine years, from 1793
to 1802, at posts west of Lake Winnipeg and
along the Saskatchewan River. Slowly he gathered
information from his own surveys and
from Native cartographers, which he compiled
in a large map of the Plains. Fidler's own
map, sent to the company's London Committee
and then forwarded to Aaron Arrowsmith,
has not survived; Arrowsmith probably discarded
it when he copied its line of the
Rockies south to Chief Mountain, and its delineation
of the upper Missouri watershed,
onto the 1802 version of his <title level="m">Map Exhibiting all the New Discoveries of the Interior Parts of North America</title>. Three years later Lewis and
Clark consulted Arrowsmith's map on their
way up the Missouri; they were dismayed that
the map did not seem to show the river and
the mountains accurately. Since they knew the
source of Arrowsmith's information, the captains
instantly doubted Fidler's "varacity." But
the tracing of the Missouri watershed was
conjectural, as clearly shown by Arrowsmith's
dotted lines. And the Rockies that Fidler
had in constant view from November 1792 to
March 1793 do form a band of parallel ranges
quite unlike the uplands and outcrops of the
mountains to the south. Fidler's navigational
skills as he made a running survey of the front
ranges were in no way inferior to those of the
Corps of Discovery.</p>

<p>Fidler spent four winters, from 1802 to 1806,
at Lake Athabaska, sandwiched between posts
of the North West Company and Alexander
Mackenzie's <hi rend="smallcaps">XY</hi> Company. Although his winterer's
knowledge of the Chipewyans' language
and customs was an advantage, Fidler
suffered brutal harassment from the other
companies and traded few furs. The next few
years spent at Cumberland House and Ile a la
Crosse were more peaceful for him, although
rivalry intensified and the resources of each
company were strained by the need to manage
trade across the continental divide as well as
the difficult access to Athabasca.</p>

<p>The Hudson's Bay Company responded to
the competition by cautiously following established
routes and by attempting to diversify
its trade (lumber, foodstuffs, and mining, as
well as furs). Lord Selkirk's scheme of a colony
at Red River seemed to fit well with this new
policy: it could provide pemmican for brigades
traveling long distances and it could be a
center of farming and some manufacturing as
well as administration of "northern" trade
(the Athabaska and Saskatchewan districts).
In 1812, after a year in England, Fidler led settlers
from York Factory to Red River. The following
year he began to survey lots, and from
1814 to 1816 he worked hard to keep the settlement
going despite Metis hostility and opposition
from the North West Company. In the
summer of 1817 a treaty was signed extinguishing
Aboriginal rights to the colony's surveyed
territory in return for a yearly rent to be paid
to the bands of Cree and Ojibwa who had
formerly lived there. Fidler made a copy of the
treaty and continued to survey lots in the
colony. The settlers now numbered more than
200, and the colony's existence was no longer
threatened.</p>

<p>Fidler spent the remaining years of his life
at posts west of the colony. He was offered
retirement with no diminution of his salary of
&#163;100 but preferred to continue as a clerk. He
met George Simpson, just arrived from London
as governor of Rupert's Land, and lived to
see the collapse of the North West Company
in 1821. Just before his death at Fort Dauphin,
on December 17, 1822, Fidler formally married
the mother of his fourteen children, of whom
eleven survived him. His complicated will was
broken in 1827 and his carefully amassed fortune
of &#163;1,900 was distributed among these
survivors. The numerous descendants of Peter
Fidler now form one of the leading M&#233;tis families
of western Canada.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">INDUSTRY</hi>: <ref n="egp.ind.029">Hudson's Bay Company</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Barbara Belya<lb/>
University of Calgary</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Belyea, Barbara. "Mapping the Marias." <title level="j">Great Plains Quarterly</title> 17 (1997): 165–84.</bibl> <bibl>J. G. MacGregor. Peter Fidler,
<title level="m">Canada's Forgotten Surveyor, 1769–1822</title>. Calgary: Fifth
House, 1998.</bibl>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>