<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.art.042">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Kiowa Six</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Lydia L. Wyckoff</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.art.042</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Lydia, L. Wyckoff">Lydia L. Wyckoff</author>. <title level="a">"Kiowa Six."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">124</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-22</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">KIOWA SIX</head>

<p>The Kiowa Six, sometimes erroneously called
the Kiowa Five, had a profound impact on the
development of Native American easel painting.
The five most commonly known artists in
the group are Jack Hokeah (1900–1969), Monroe
Tsatoke (1904–37), Spencer Asah (1906–
54), James Auchiah (1906–74), and Stephen
Mopope (1900–1974). The sixth member was
a woman, Lois Smoky (1907–81).</p>

<p>Painting was an important and honored aspect
of traditional Kiowa culture. Men painted
calendars, chronological records of important
events that affected the group as a whole,
and records of an individual's heroic deeds.
Women usually confined their artistic expression
to beading. These early Kiowa artists all
spoke Kiowa and were actively involved in traditional
Kiowa culture, despite the forced acculturation
of the period.</p>

<p>In order to "civilize" and Christianize the
Kiowas and turn them into American capitalists,
the Kiowa reservation in western Oklahoma
was allotted in 1900. Each tribal member
received 160 acres. The remaining 480,000
acres of "excess" land were sold to white settlers
in 1906. European American education
became mandatory. The six Kiowa artists attended
St. Patrick's Mission School near Anadarko,
Oklahoma. There they were given English
names and taught English and how to
do manual service jobs. Upon leaving school
these artists returned to their community.</p>

<p>At this time Susie Peters was the Indian Service
field matron at Anadarko. She is still
remembered there for her concern for and
support of many Kiowas. By 1920 she had organized
a group of Kiowa artists that included
the Kiowa Six. She did not give them lessons
in art but encouraged them in their work. She
also provided them with paints and drawing
paper, which, for the most part, they had not
had access to previously. During this period
these six artists developed what is commonly
referred to as the Kiowa style. Like traditional
Kiowa painting, the figures in these paintings
were drawn on a plain background. Within
the lines color was used as a flat filler. This
opaque paint was more solid than traditional
vegetable dyes or pencil and ink. Partly because
of this technique, Kiowa-style paintings,
commonly of individual dancers or ceremonies,
emphasize design.</p>

<p>Susie Peters also attempted to market the
works of the Kiowa artists in both Oklahoma
and New Mexico, and she brought them to the
attention of Oscar Jacobson, director of the
art department at the University of Oklahoma. In 1927 Jacobson arranged for Stephen
Mopope, Monroe Tsatoke, Spencer Asah, and
Jack Hokeah to use facilities and supplies at
the University of Oklahoma under the guidance
of Edith Mahier. Jacobson, however, insisted
that they be given no formal instruction.
Later, these four artists were joined by
Lois Smoky and James Auchiah.</p>

<p>Jacobson, in contrast to Susie Peters, had
the contacts to successfully market the artists
and their works. Six months after the arrival
of the first group of Kiowa artists at the University
of Oklahoma, a traveling sales exhibition
was organized. Within a year the artists'
works had been sold, and an even larger
exhibition was mounted. A mere eighteen
months after he came to know the artists Jacobson
arranged for thirty-five watercolors
to be exhibited at the International Congress
in Prague, Czechoslovakia, and for a folio of
their work to be published in France.</p>

<p>Starting with an exhibition in New York in
1931, the decade of the 1930s was a period of
further recognition by European Americans
of the beauty of early Kiowa easel painting.
The artists were also commissioned under the
Public Works of Art Project (<hi rend="smallcaps">PWAP</hi>) to paint a
number of murals, a medium ideally suited to
the Kiowa style with its flat color areas. Other
murals were commissioned for the State Historical
Building in Oklahoma City and the
Department of the Interior Building in Washington
<hi rend="smallcaps">DC</hi>. The five Kiowa men were involved
in these mural projects. Lois Smoky
was not. After marrying and having children,
she turned her artistic talent to the traditional
Kiowa woman's art of beadwork.</p>

<p>The Kiowa Six were among the first Native
American painters to be recognized by the European
American community. Their work was
the model for what is commonly referred to as
the traditional flat style, which was refined
and developed by Dorothy Dunn at the Indian
School in Santa Fe, New Mexico.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">GENDER</hi>: <ref n="egp.gen.013">Field Matrons</ref> / 
<hi rend="smallcaps">NATIVE AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.na.055">Kiowas</ref>.</p>


<closer>
<signed>Lydia L. Wyckoff<lb/>
Philbrook Museum of Art</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Wyckoff, Lydia L., ed. <title level="m">Visions and Voices: Native American Painting</title>. Albuquerque: University of New Mexico Press,
1996.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>