<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.ha.009 SYSTEM "egp.ha.009.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ha.009">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main"><hi rend="italic">Ciboleros</hi></title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Jerry A. Padilla</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ha.009</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Padilla, Jerry A.">Jerry A. Padilla</author>. <title level="a">"<hi rend="italic">Ciboleros</hi>."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">354</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-25</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">CHAVEZ, LINDA (b. 1947)</head>

<figure n="egp.ha.009" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Cibolero</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Hispanic New Mexican hunters and plainsmen,
or <hi rend="italic">ciboleros</hi> (from the New Mexican
Spanish <hi rend="italic">c&#237;bolo</hi>), learned to hunt bison from
Native American neighbors in order to provide
winter meat for their home villages. Like
the Pueblos and Plains Indians, New Mexican
Hispanos depended on bison during the late
Spanish colonial, Mexican, and territorial
eras. The volume and extent of the ciboleros'
hunts peaked in the first half of the nineteenth
century and declined thereafter as the bison
were taken to the brink of extinction.</p>

<p>Ciboleros traditionally hunted bison twice
a year. The large-scale autumn hunt took
place after crops were harvested. Expeditions
from settlements in north-central New Mexico
and southern Colorado usually took six
weeks to reach the Southern Great Plains, encounter
herds, barter with Comanches or
Kiowas, hunt, secure and preserve meat, and
return before heavy snowfalls. During these
autumn hunts, bison were taken for their
thick robes as well as for their meat.</p>

<p>The summer hunt took place in June, after
spring planting, by which time meat supplies
procured the previous autumn were exhausted.
Bison meat was of utmost importance
for the common people, allowing them to save
goat herds for milk and roast kid for special
occasions. Only the wealthier classes regularly
partook of domestically raised meats.</p>

<p>Each village had an individual hunter who
specialized in running bison on horseback.
Specially trained horses were ridden only by
the ciboleros and used for only that purpose.
The lance and bow and arrow were the main
weapons of the hunt; firearms were few and
far between in New Mexico until the late nineteenth
century. It was a skill and profession
that was handed down from father to son, and
certain New Mexican families were specialists.
Hunters from various villages prepared supplies
for the journey and for barter and furnished
skinners and camp helpers. The hunters
gathered at a predesignated place and
chose a <hi rend="italic">mayordomo</hi>, or foreman, and the expedition
proceeded in caravans of oxcarts.
Often Hispanos and Pueblos traveled together
for mutual safety and cooperation.</p>

<p>The Southern Plains was dominated by the
Comanches and Kiowas, who maintained
generally good relations with the Pueblos and
Hispanos after 1785, when New Mexico governor
Juan Bautista de Anza decisively defeated
the Comanches, led by Cuerno Verde, and established
peace. Barter of New Mexican agricultural
products with the Native Americans
created goodwill and allowed the ciboleros to
enter their traditional hunting lands.</p>

<p>After the bison herds were encountered, each
cibolero tied a long rope around his waist in
order to remount if thrown during the chase.
Commending their souls to God and Santiago
(Saint James), they rode into the herds. Selecting
choice animals, they lanced the bison or
shot arrows, bringing down only as many as
their villages needed. This was a dangerous
undertaking, and some ciboleros died from
being trampled, while others were killed by
Indians, especially the Cheyennes, who by 1850
were competing for the diminishing herds.
The late Cleofes Vigil of San Crist&#243;bal, New
Mexico&#8211;poet-troubadour, historian, rancher,
and retired railroad worker&#8211;often performed
ballads about such fatal accidents.</p>

<p>After enough bison were brought down,
<hi rend="italic">agregadores</hi> (helpers) and hunters pitched in,
skinning, slicing, and salting meat. After drying,
meat was packed in oxcarts for the return.
All the bison parts were used. Aside from the
meat, hides were tanned for robes or leather,
smoked tongues were traded in Mexico, horns
and bones were made into utensils, and the
wool was spun into rough cloth or stuffed in
mattresses.</p>

<p>The late Cipriano Solano (1870–1967) of
Springer, New Mexico, a retired rancher, recalled
that near the end of the nineteenth century
there were remnant bison herds near
Loma Parda, New Mexico, and he described
how he had taken a burro to haul the meat
back after hunting, and how one cibolero
would provide meat for several families for a
year. Ciboleros are still remembered in New
Mexican folk songs, cultural events, and family
oral traditions.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Jerry A. Padilla<lb/>
Taos, New Mexico</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Gregg, Josiah. <title level="m">Commerce of the Prairies</title>. Norman: University
of Oklahoma Press, 1954.</bibl> <bibl>Kenner, Charles L. <title level="m">A History of New Mexican Plains Indian Relations</title>. Norman: University
of Oklahoma Press, 1969.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>