<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.edu.033">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Pound, Louise (1872-1958)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Evelyn Haller</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.edu.033</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Haller, Evelyn">Evelyn Haller</author>. <title level="a">"Pound, Louise (1872-1958)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">211-212</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-02</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">POUND, LOUISE (1872-1958)</head>

<p>Louise Pound was a scholar, teacher, and athlete
who established the scholarly study of
American speech and folklore. Pound signed
her letters with the symbol for the British
pound sterling with a likely sense of self-approbation.
She was a pragmatic woman
who chose to remain at the University of Nebraska
in the city of her birth (June 30, 1872)
for half a century despite an international
reputation.</p>

<p>At a time when ambitious women were not
welcome in the academy, Pound was aware
that a strong social and familial base in a relatively
new western city like Lincoln would give
her a grounding as firm as the three-story
house in which she continued to live with her
sister, Olivia. They had inherited the house
from their father, Stephen Bosworth Pound, a
lawyer, district court judge, and state senator,
and their mother, Laura Biddlecomb Pound.
The sisters, together with their brother, Roscoe
(who became a leading legal theorist),
had been educated at home by their mother,
whose special interests were German language
and literature as well as botany, to which she
contributed by finding previously unidentified
prairie flowers in the company of her children.
After two years at the university's preparatory
Latin school, Pound enrolled as a
freshman at the university, from which she
received a bachelor's degree with a diploma in
music (piano) in 1892, having been class orator
and poet. Pound earned her master's degree
from the University of Nebraska in 1895.</p>

<p>Reinforcing her sense of self-worth was
Pound's astonishing ability at a variety of
sports, including figure skating. As an undergraduate
Pound became women's state tennis
champion and university champion in men's
singles and doubles, for which she earned a
man's varsity letter. Pound also earned a string
of bars for "century runs" (cycling 100 miles
in twelve hours) and was variously coach, captain,
and member of a women's basketball
team that she strongly encouraged to play
to win. (She later took issue with Mabel Lee
over women's physical activity for fitness
rather than for competition.) For more than
twenty-five years Pound was a ranking women's
golfer, and in 1955 she became the first
woman elected to the Nebraska Sports Hall of
Fame.</p>

<p>Pound's academic capabilities as well as her
impatience to get things done were signaled
by her decision to get her doctorate from a
German university. She went to Heidelberg,
where she acquired the degree in two semesters
rather than the usual seven. A considerable
portion of Pound's academic work may
be described as taxonomic in methodology (a
familiar mode for her time), but she was also
alert to and influenced by what was happening
in adjacent fields such as botany as it
was being redefined by Charles Bessey. Despite
a heavy teaching load at the University
of Nebraska, Pound published an impressive
amount of scholarly work distinguished by
common sense, as can be seen in her amusing
piece on "Lovers' Leaps" in the posthumously
published Nebraska Folklore (1959). H. L.
Mencken acknowledged his debt to her in <hi rend="italic">The
American Language: An Inquiry into the Development
of English in the United States</hi> (1962)
when he wrote that her "early work put the
study of current American English on its legs."
That Pound was an advocate of women's education
is demonstrated by her willingness
to speak to women's groups throughout the
state, and she probably influenced many
mothers to send their daughters to the university.
As a gadfly she strove to improve the position
of women at the University of Nebraska.
In 1955, at eighty-two, she was also elected the
first woman president of the Modern Language Association, which may have assuaged
her disappointment at never having been
chair of the English department, although
outsiders often assumed she was. Pound died
in Lincoln on June 28, 1958.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">LAW</hi>: <ref n="egp.law.043">Pound, Roscoe</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Evelyn Haller<lb/>
Doane College</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Haller, Evelyn. "Louise Pound's Work in Nebraska Folklore."
<hi rend="italic">Nebraska Humanist</hi> 7 (1984): 44–47.</bibl> <bibl>Louise Pound
Papers, Nebraska State Historical Society, Lincoln.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>