<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.rel.035">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Morning Star Ceremony</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Byron Cannon</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.rel.035</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Cannon, Byron">Byron Cannon</author>. <title level="a">"Morning Star Ceremony."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">752</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-19</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">MORNING STAR CEREMONY</head>

<p>The Morning Star bundle ceremony among
the Skiri Pawnees (who lived in what is now
central Nebraska) reasserted devotion to the
power of the rising Eastern Star (Mars). It was
their only ritual involving human sacrifice
and was one of only a few not tied to seasonal
cycles. For the ceremony to occur, a male
member of the tribe had to announce that he
had seen Morning Star in a dream and, upon
awakening, perceived it rising in the east. Ritual
tradition then called for dispatch of the
dreamer (now deemed the "warrior leader")
to secure a girl captive by raiding neighboring
villages. The power of the ceremony was to
provide for success in war and for fertility.</p>

<p>Preparation for the ceremony, which ended
in a ritual feast and dance by the entire village,
involved several stages and sacred songs. After
being dressed by the Morning Star priest in
sacred raiments from the Morning Star bundle
and anointed with red ointment, the captive
stayed with the Wolf man, who brought
her daily to the warrior leader for meals eaten
with utensils from the Morning Star bundle.</p>

<p>On the appropriate predawn morning, the
Wolf man led the captive to the scaffold, constructed
of different symbolic species of wood.
The killing was carried out with a ceremonial
bow and arrow. Immediately a stone knife incision
was made near the heart, and specially
prepared buffalo meat held to receive drops of
the victim's blood before being prepared for
feasting. Before the body was removed and
placed in the prairie facing east, the entire village,
including children, lodged dozens of arrows
in the victim's back. The Skiris believed
that this ceremony allowed the victim's spirit
to ascend to the sky to become a star, while her
body returned to the earth.</p>

<p>The last known Morning Star Ceremony
sacrifice took place on April 22, 1838, with the
killing of Haxti, a fifteen-year-old Lakota girl.
The United States subsequently suppressed
the ceremony, but it also seems that some
Skiris themselves wished to stop the human
sacrifice.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">NATIVE AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.na.082">Pawnees</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Byron Cannon<lb/>
University of Utah</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Dorsey, George A., and James Murie. <title level="m">Notes on Skidi Pawnee
Society</title>. Chicago: Field Museum of Natural History,
1940.</bibl> <bibl>Murie, James. <title level="m">Ceremonies of the Pawnee</title>. Lincoln:
University of Nebraska Press, 1989.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>