<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.na.098">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Reserves</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>D. Aidan McQuillan</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.na.098</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="McQuillan, D. Aidan">D. Aidan McQuillan</author>. <title level="a">"Reserves."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">598-599</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-20</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">RESERVES</head>

<p>Indian (First Nations) reserves on the Canadian
Prairies were the outcome of a series of
treaties negotiated between the new Dominion
of Canada and Indian leaders whose peoples
had occupied the Prairies for generations.
Canada's top priority, when it acquired Rupert's
Land from the Hudson's Bay Company
in 1870, was to extinguish Indian title to the
land and to stabilize the Indian population in
anticipation of white agricultural settlement.
The Indians' priority was to preserve their way
of life in the face of inevitable changes on the
Canadian Prairies. Consequently, government
officials and Indian leaders held very different
views on the purpose of the treaties and
reserves.</p>

<p>Treaties numbered 1 through 7 were negotiated
between 1871 and 1877 and covered the
Prairies of the present-day provinces of Manitoba,
Saskatchewan, and Alberta. Treaties 1
and 2 were similar in that each Indian band
would receive an inalienable reserve of land
using a ratio of 160 acres per family of five and
an annuity of $15 per family. Liquor sales were
prohibited, and schools would be built by the
government on the reserves. Gifts of livestock,
farming equipment, and clothing, as well as
hunting and fishing rights, were mentioned
verbally during negotiations but were not
written into the treaties. Subsequently, these
two treaties were amended in 1875 to bring
them into line with Treaty 3, which set precedents
for later treaties. Its terms were: 640
acres per family of five, annuities of $5 per
person, a gratuity of $12, a suit of clothes every
three years, salaries for chiefs and band officers,
plus gifts of medals and flags. Hunting
and fishing rights in unsettled areas were formally
acknowledged, and reserves were to be
supplied with livestock, farming equipment,
and seed. Agricultural instruction would be
provided by the government. The only subsequent
change was the provision in Treaty 6 of
a "medicine chest"&#8211;a provision that was then
extended to the other treaty areas. Provision
was also made for American Sioux (Lakota)
refugees from the Battle of the Little Bighorn:
they received reserves based on eighty acres
per family of five but no annuities, as they had
no lands in Canada to cede. The size of all
reserves was based on population levels during
the 1870s; no provision was made for subsequent
population expansion.</p>

<p>Although the government's declared policy
was assimilation, in practice it was segregation.
The very concept of a reserve is one of segregation.
Indians were supposed to select the location
of their reserves, but government agents
often intervened and clustered the reserves to
facilitate bureaucratic administration. In 1882
all the southern reserves except those in southern
Alberta were moved north of the Canadian
Pacific Railroad to avoid further cross-border
raids with American bands. Agents were to
terminate the Indians' roaming over the Prairies,
to teach them farming, and to settle them
on reserves where they would not interfere
with white settlement. After the North-West
Rebellion of 1885, agents increasingly took
control of affairs on the reserves as the power
of Indian chiefs was reduced and Indians became
wards of the government. In the area of
education the government's practice was indeed
assimilationist. Schools on the reserves
were run by Christian missionaries who sought
to "civilize" and Christianize Indian children
by stamping out Aboriginal cultural influences.
These practices worked against the Indian ideal
of preserving as much of their culture as they
could on their reserves.</p>

<p>Refusal of the reserve system was scarcely
an option for Prairie Province Indians in the
1870s. A smallpox epidemic in the early 1870s,
followed by rapid disappearance of the bison,
reduced Indian bands to starvation and dependence
on government rations for survival.
Their plight was desperate by 1880, and despite
the pleas of several chiefs such as Big
Bear, who argued for Indian unity and renegotiation
with the government, many accepted
the government's terms. Big Bear even
favored clustering of reserves as a step toward
creating Indian solidarity and preservation of
Indian culture. But even their hunting and
fishing rights along the northern margins of
the Prairies were ignored, as agents sought to
restrict Indian mobility and to seclude them
on their reserves. The Indians' distinctive way
of life was subjected to the crushing pressures
of starvation: sheer survival was possible only
on the government's terms. Nevertheless, Indians
retained significant elements of their
cultures on these small, inalienable reserves of
land that had been set aside for them in the
early 1880s.</p>

<p>Major changes to the reserve system came
after World War II, in which Indians fought
bravely in the Canadian armed forces. Veterans
refused to accept second-class citizenship,
and a revised Indian Act in 1951 gave
Indian bands a measure of control for the first
time. Although the policy of assimilation continued,
Indians were no longer wards of government
but were to advance to full rights
as citizens. Indians now determined who belonged
to Indian bands and who could live on
reserves. The Indian Act of 1876 had declared
that only "status" Indians could reside permanently
on reserves, and the government reserved
the right to determine who was a "status
Indian." Men who lived off the reserve
could lose their status, and the position of
women was even more precarious, especially
those who married non-Indians. Resolution
of these issues now became a matter for Indian
bands, although the troublesome problem
of women's status was not finally resolved
until 1982, when many women were reinstated
as band members.</p>

<p>Other changes came more easily. Schools
were secularized during the 1960s, and by 1970
Indian bands began to take direct control of
education. Bands also took financial control
and increasingly policed their reserves&#8211;public
consumption of alcohol, for example, was permitted
in 1970. By the 1980s a pan-Indian
movement had been established, which linked
Indian reserves on the Prairies with other reserves
across Canada, and, as the drive toward
Aboriginal self-government was launched, Big
Bear's dream of a century earlier became a
possibility.</p>

<p>The Canadian government had been determined
to treat Indians better than the United
States had. Those lofty goals were never
achieved, partly through lack of commitment
by the government in Ottawa and partly
through internal contradictions in policy, but
mostly because Indians' wishes were ignored.
The result was a marginalization of Canadian
Prairie Indians through segregation similar to
that of their American cousins for more than
a century.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">EDUCATION</hi>: <ref n="egp.edu.020">Indian Residential Schools, Canada</ref> 
/ <hi rend="smallcaps">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</hi>: <ref n="egp.pg.032">Indian Agents</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>D. Aidan McQuillan</signed>
University of Toronto</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Canada Royal Commission on Aboriginal Peoples. <title level="m">For
Seven Generations: An Information Legacy of the Royal
Commission on Aboriginal Peoples</title>. Ottawa: Libraxus, 1997.</bibl>
<bibl>Dickason, Olive P. <title level="m">Canada's First Nations: A History of
Founding Peoples from Earliest Times</title>. Toronto: McClelland
and Stewart Ltd., 1992.</bibl> <bibl>McQuillan, D. Aidan. "Creation
of Indian Reserves on the Canadian Prairies, 1870–
1885." <title level="j">Geographical Review</title> 70 (1980): 379–96.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>