<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.art.020">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Evans, Terry (b. 1944)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Martha H. Kennedy</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.art.020</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Kennedy, Martha H.">Martha H. Kennedy</author>. <title level="a">"Evans, Terry (b. 1944)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">116</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-15</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">EVANS, TERRY (b. 1944)</head>

<p>Terry H. Evans has been photographing the
landscape and people of the Plains for much
of her adult life. She lived in Salina, Kansas,
for twenty-six years before moving to Chicago,
where she currently resides. Best known
for her photographs of the prairie in both its
pristine and its altered states, she continues to
develop, expanding the geographic and aesthetic
parameters of her art.</p>

<p>Evans was born on August 30, 1944, in
Kansas City, Missouri. From the age of four
she loved to draw and paint, and she was encouraged
in these interests by her parents,
Norman and Dale Holt, who had a photography
studio in Kansas City for many years.
Evans completed a bachelor of fine arts degree
in drawing and painting at the University of
Kansas, Lawrence, but not until her last semester
in college did she begin to take photographs.
At that time she had the rare opportunity
to photograph presidential candidate
Robert F. Kennedy during his 1968 visit to
the campus. From this experience Evans perceived
the extraordinary access that photography
gives viewers to special situations. She
never had a formal course in photography and
cites her father as her main teacher. The work
of Charles Harbutt and James Enyeart was
also influential.</p>

<p>In her first decade as a photographer, Evans
concentrated on exploring the life conditions
of poor people, farm people, her own family,
and the inhabitants of her hometown in Kansas.
In the years since, her work has been
shaped mainly by the landscape of the Plains,
an environment characterized by unexpected
beauty and shaped by often overwhelming
natural forces and human activity. In building
her understanding of this complex environment,
Evans has employed varied approaches
that range from close-ups of diverse prairie
plant and animal life, including root systems
of grasses, to vistas framed at ground level, to
stunning aerial views.</p>

<p>Within Evans's aerial photographs, which
capture current conditions of the Plains landscape,
the viewer can also catch sight of historic
alterations of the land. These include
paths worn by animal movements, indentations
made by long-abandoned dwellings,
patterns wrought by agriculture and military
shooting ranges, and many more irregular
forms and lines made by forces of nature. The
conjunctions of such telling details in her
aerial views highlight relationships between
the past and present and between nature and
humans, sometimes resulting in striking abstract
designs. Believing that a single image
can never su.ce to represent her subject,
Evans makes images of forms and visual
rhythms that stretch to the edges of and sometimes
beyond the frame in both her aerial and
other scenes. For example, <title>Chase County, South of Matfield Green</title>, Kansas, 1993, presents
a panoramic view of a prairie landscape in
three images that are not strictly continuous
yet appear harmoniously connected: late afternoon
sunlight burnishes stands of Indian
grass in the foreground; across all three panels
autumnal light throws the land behind the
grasses into a deep horizontal shadow; the
same light also illuminates the gentle golden
rise of land in the far distance; contrasting
bands of shadow and light unify the three
panels and reinforce the horizontal character
of the grassland, which is bereft of human
presence and nearly reduced to essentials that
verge on the abstract. Evans takes care, however,
to include details such as the slightly
mounded landforms in the background of the
frame on the far right, details tied inextricably
to the land's subtle beauty.</p>

<p>Evans's photography has been exhibited
widely. Recently, the Smithsonian's Museum
of Natural History organized In <title>Place of Prairie</title>,
a nationally touring solo exhibition of her
work. Her books are <title level="m">Prairie: Images of Land and Sky</title> (1986), <title level="m">Disarming the Prairie</title> (1998),
and <title level="m">The Inhabited Prairie</title> (1998). Her works
are held in, among others, the National Museum
of American Art, Washington <hi rend="smallcaps">DC</hi>; the
Museum of Modern Art, New York; the Baltimore
Museum of Art; the Chicago Art Institute;
the San Francisco Museum of Art; the
Sheldon Memorial Art Gallery, University of
Nebraska–Lincoln; and the Spencer Museum
of Art, University of Kansas at Lawrence. She
received a John Simon Guggenheim Memorial
Fellowship in 1996. Recently, Evans has been
making a photographic study of Matfield
Green and is completing an aerial survey
of the prairie from Canada to Texas. Evans
distinguishes herself as a photographer by
the sheer volume of outstanding images she
has made that collectively embrace a photographic
vision of Plains landscape that is extraordinarily
and appropriately broad.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Martha H. Kennedy<lb/>
Library of Congress</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Brown, Turner, and Elaine Partnow, eds. <title level="m">Macmillan Biographical Encyclopedia of Photographic Artists and Innovators</title>.
New York: Macmillan Publishing Company, 1983.</bibl>
<bibl>Kinsey, Joni L. <title level="m">Plain Pictures: Images of the American Prairie</title>.
Washington <hi rend="smallcaps">DC</hi>: Published for the University of Iowa
Museum of Art by the Smithsonian Institution Press,
1996.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>