<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.ne.001.01 SYSTEM "egp.ne.001.01.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY egp.ne.001.02 SYSTEM "egp.ne.001.02.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY egp.ne.001.03 SYSTEM "egp.ne.001.03.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.na.001">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Native Americans</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Philip J. Deloria</author>
<author>Christopher K. Riggs</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.na.001</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Deloria, Philip J.">Philip J. Deloria</author> and <author n="Riggs, Christopher K.">Christopher K. Riggs</author>. <title level="a">"Native Americans."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">555-561</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-03</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">NATIVE AMERICANS</head>

<p>The Plains Indian has been one of the most
important and pervasive icons in American
culture. Imagine him, for example, as a young
man on horseback. Almost without effort, the
image conjures up full-blown narratives of
buffalo hunts and mounted warfare. Make the
"he" into a young woman and imagine romantic
tragedies of forced marriage and unrequited
love. Make the Indian a wizened elder
and see if you don't think of spiritual wonder
and almost superhuman ecological communion.</p>

<p>But don't forget that real people peer up
from the depths of such timeless images. And
while the images can be easily moved to the
Hollywood backlot, those real people are not
so easily detached from the Great Plains themselves,
for this difficult environment framed
ongoing historical transformations in Native
political organization, social relations, economy,
and culture. Along with the nomadic
bison hunting popularized in the movies, Native
Americans engaged in raiding, trading,
pastoralism, agriculture, diplomacy, politics,
religious innovation and syncretism, warfare,
migration, wage labor, lawsuits, lobbying, and
gaming. Through these adaptive strategies,
the Plains peoples worked to protect and enhance
their political power and their ability to
sustain themselves economically, and to maintain
their cultural distinctiveness.</p>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Longevity in the Plains</head>

<p>Although some peoples came to the Plains
earlier than others, Native Americans have
lived there for a long time. Evidence from the
Agate Basin site in eastern Wyoming, for example,
indicates that humans lived in the
Plains at least as early as 8500 <hi rend="smallcaps">B.C.</hi> Radiocarbon
dating of material from the Lewisville
site near Dallas, Texas, suggests Indians and
their precursors may have been in the Plains
for at least 38,000 years. The oral histories of
some tribes refer to long-extinct mammoths
and other megafauna. "Star charts" suggest
that the Lakota Sioux have associated parts
of the Black Hills in South Dakota with astrometrical
phenomena since ancient times.
Some scholars assert that the Sioux peoples
originated in the Great Lakes region and only
began moving onto the Plains in the late seventeenth
and early eighteenth centuries. Many
Lakotas, however, trace the origins of their
people to Wind Cave in the Black Hills and
suggest that they were simply in the middle of
a long, slow migration home after living elsewhere
for a time. Clarity on this issue will
probably not be forthcoming.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Environmental Adaptations</head>

<p>Their extended tenure in the Plains allowed
Native peoples to experience significant alterations
in the environment. Between 11,500 and
11,000, precipitation declined,
the range of temperatures increased, and free-flowing
streams began to turn into small lakes
and marshes, eventually becoming part of the
expanding grassland. Species adapted to the
wetter world&#8211;such as mammoths, camels,
and horses&#8211;died out, opening ecological
niches in the Plains grassland. Most of these
niches were filled by bison, which were becoming
smaller and more mobile in order to
be more effective in the drier climate.</p>

<p>Plains peoples adjusted to these changes as
well. Around the time that the larger game
disappeared, nomadic hunters shifted from
Clovis-style spear points and arrowheads to
the smaller Folsom points and heads, which
were used until about 8000 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> Like more
recent Native peoples, Folsom hunters and
their successors depended heavily upon the
bison and relied upon the more sophisticated
social organization necessary for group hunting.
Such organization allowed for the creation
and use of "buffalo jumps," a large funnel
of trees, rocks, poles, and people designed
to channel stampeding bison over a cliff.
Plains hunters used buffalo jumps like the
Head-Smashed-In site in southwestern Alberta
as early as 5,500 years ago. Along with
the bison, Indian hunters' prey included deer,
elk, and other smaller game.</p>

<p>Plains residents began experimenting with
pottery and more sedentary villages at least as
early as 2,000 years ago. Ancestors of the Mandans
and Hidatsas eventually settled in fortified
villages along the Missouri River, where
they raised corn, beans, and squash. These villages
generally ranged in size from ten to
ninety lodges and were built from bracing
poles and packed earthen cover. Between
spring planting and fall harvest, the villagers
probably left the river's bottomland to hunt
bison.</p>

<p>Some of the crops these villagers grew became
part of the extensive trade networks that
linked the horticulturalists with Plains hunters
and with peoples outside the Plains. The
Caddo and Wichita trade networks included
some of the Pueblos in present-day New Mexico,
Cahokia (a city built by the Illinois people
near the confluence of the Mississippi and
Missouri Rivers), Hiwasee Island on the Tennessee
River, Etowah near the Chattahoochee
River, and the Platte River Pawnee communities.
The Mandans, Hidatsas, and Arikaras
traded with peoples from what is today the
American Southwest and with more nomadic
Plains hunters like the Crows, Assiniboines,
Plains Crees, Cheyennes, Arapahos, Kiowas,
and Comanches. Both material goods (agricultural
products, dried meat, flint, and animal
hides) and cultural products (songs and
dances) traded hands.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Migrations</head>

<p>While the rise of sedentary villages and agriculture
stood out as a key way that Plains peoples
adapted to and shaped their environment,
migration played an equally important
role in the lives of many Indians. It seems that
Plains societies were both amalgamating and
splitting apart, and that mobility constituted a
common response to both social and environmental
factors. The groups that came to be
known as Apaches, for example, separated
from people in the Northern Plains as early as
600 <hi rend="smallcaps">A.D.</hi> They moved south, sojourning in
Nebraska before moving into the Southern
Plains between 1450 and 1525. By the late 1600s
they and their Kiowa allies had staked out a
territory ranging from northwestern Texas to
Wyoming and the Black Hills. At the same
time, Shoshones moved east from the Great
Basin to eastern Montana. Separating from
the Hidatsas and Missouri River horticulture,
the Crows migrated west to the Montana-
Dakota area.</p>

<p>Such migrations accelerated after 1700, as
some groups left the Plains and others entered
the region. Moving from what is now eastern
Montana, a branch of Shoshones that would
come to be known as Comanches swept the
Apaches south and by 1775 forced them from
the Plains entirely. Cheyennes and Arapahos
migrated west from the Great Lakes region.
Crees and Assiniboines gradually moved into
the Canadian Prairies. Iowas, Missourias,
Omahas, Osages, Otoes, Poncas, and Quapaws
all came to the Plains after living for
some time in what is today Arkansas, Missouri,
and Iowa.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Horses, Guns, and Diseases</head>

<p>Migrations also brought Europeans to the
Plains, beginning in the sixteenth century. The
newcomers brought both opportunities and
perils for the Plains peoples in the forms of
trade and disease. Horses and firearms were
the most important European trade items. The
Spanish reintroduced horses into the Plains, in
part through trading networks that connected
Plains peoples with the Pueblos and Apaches.
(Horses had existed in the Americas at one
time, but they had become extinct.) Indians
acted as middlemen and traded horses to more
distant Plains peoples. By the late 1600s, for
example, Kiowas and Kiowa Apaches traded
horses to the Caddos. Comanches often acquired
horses by raiding Spanish and Apache
settlements and then traded the animals to
other tribes. Utes, Cheyennes, and Arapahos
moved horses to the north. Because Spanish
law forbade the selling or trading of firearms to
Natives, the Plains peoples turned to the English
and French for guns, and middleman
relationships developed with both mobile
traders and trade centers in the Arkansas, Missouri,
and Red River valleys.</p>

<p>Access to horses and weaponry came at a
high cost. European traders brought European
epidemic diseases to which Plains Indians
had not been exposed and to which they
had limited immunity. Even Natives who had
never met a European became ill as a result of
contact with Native middlemen in the trade
who inadvertently exposed them to smallpox,
measles, whooping cough, and many other
diseases. Regardless of the source, European
diseases spread through the Plains and decimated
Native populations, especially those
concentrated in villages. Epidemics during the
late eighteenth and early nineteenth centuries
reduced the Arikaras' population by an estimated
80 percent. The Hidatsas, Mandans,
Omahas, Poncas, and other relatively sedentary
tribes also suffered great losses.</p>

<p>The combination of European diseases and
trade items had a complex impact upon the
Plains. Access to horses allowed for the more
effective killing and transportation of bison.
Consequently, many tribes&#8211;such as the Lakota
Sioux&#8211;rejected a sedentary and horticultural
lifestyle and devoted less time to
trapping beaver and more time to the hunting
of bison. Tribes with the greatest access to
horses and firearms could expand their territory
and power at the expense of those tribes
with fewer guns and horses. The Osages' access
to both guns and horses, for example,
helped to make them the main power in the
region between the lower Missouri and lower
Red Rivers by the mid-1700s. The Comanches'
control of the horse trade and their alliance
with the Kiowas gave them command over the
area between the Arkansas and Red Rivers by
the end of the eighteenth century. By the mid.
nineteenth century, the Sioux, aided by the
Arapahos and Cheyennes, dominated the region
bounded by the Minnesota and Yellowstone
Rivers in the north and the Republican
River in the south. The relative power of the
nomads was actually increased by disease:
they suffered losses, of course, but their dispersed
lifestyles made them less vulnerable
to epidemics than the concentrated village
populations.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Europeans</head>

<p>Unlike their horses, guns, and pathogens, Europeans
themselves initially had a relatively
limited presence in the Plains. The Spanish
first penetrated the region between 1540 and
1542 looking for "cities of gold." When they
failed to find the riches they expected, they
withdrew and only slowly established missions
and colonies in New Mexico and Texas
during the seventeenth century. Spain did
sponsor an expedition to the Plains under
Pedro de Villasur in 1720, but it suffered a
military defeat at the hands of the Pawnees
and Otoes.</p>

<p>The French expanded into the Southern
and Central Plains by the early eighteenth
century from bases in the Mississippi Valley.
They negotiated commercial and military
agreements with Plains tribes. Through these
agreements, the French traded with Indians
for furs, while using Plains peoples as a defense
against rival Europeans and Indians.
Few in number and often nomadic themselves,
the French posed no threat to Indian
autonomy.</p>

<p>In the late eighteenth century, British fur
traders from Canada pushed into the Prairie
Provinces. Unlike the individualistic French
traders, the large British companies built numerous
trading posts among the Assiniboines,
Plains Crees, Blackfoot, and Gros Ventres,
drawing them into market relations. Alcohol,
the credit system, and intermarriage created
strong linkages and dependencies, but the
number of the British and the volume of their
trade were too small to dramatically alter the
Native cultures. Like the other Plains groups,
the Indians of the Canadian Prairies managed
to keep their subsistence, political, and cultural
systems largely intact until the second
half of the nineteenth century.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Americans</head>

<p>When the British, French, and Spanish entered
the Plains, they tended to seek peaceful
relations with Indian people. In truth, Europeans
lacked the power to do otherwise. The
same cannot be said, however, of the United
States. American expansion into the Plains in
the nineteenth century involved the purposeful
or incidental destruction and control of
those Plains resources upon which Native
Americans depended. To be sure, Plains people
adopted various responses to the Americans'
actions. Nevertheless, by the end of the
century, Native peoples had seen their populations
decline precipitously, had lost control
over much of their land and other economic
resources, and faced the prospect of seeing
their societies and cultures forcibly annihilated
by outsiders.</p>

<p>Fur traders were the first Americans to enter
the Northern and Central Plains in significant
numbers in the first four decades of the
nineteenth century. In the 1840s large numbers
of emigrants passed through the Great
Plains on their way to Oregon, Utah, and the
California goldfields. The construction of railroads
across the Plains after the Civil War
made accessible a region with limited navigable
rivers, and the Homestead Act of 1862 and
other laws drew settlers to the Plains by providing
land at a relatively small cost.</p>

<p>The influx presented significant problems
for the Plains peoples. Many migrants took
old Indian routes across the Plains and codified
them for other Americans as "trails"&#8211;the
Overland or Oregon Trail, which traced the
Platte River, and the Santa Fe Trail, which ran
along part of the Arkansas River. Migration
along these trails destroyed the ecosystems of
the Platte and Arkansas Valleys. The emigrants
drove the bison away, churned the
grasslands into mile-wide dust swathes,
stripped wood from river bottoms, and polluted
water sources&#8211;often with diseases such
as cholera. Native peoples who depended
upon the resources of these areas, such as the
Sioux and Pawnees in the north and the Comanches
and Kiowas in the south, demanded
compensation for this damage and sought
substitutes for the lost game. The Comanches
and Kiowas, for example, took to raiding for
cattle and other items. This led to an escalating
series of threats, a cycle of raids, and occasional
reprisals by whites.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Treaties, Diplomacy, and Dispossession in the United States</head>

<p>Throughout much of the nineteenth century
the U.S. government sought to deal with the
conflicts between Indians and non-Indian migrants
and settlers through treaties that restricted
Native peoples to certain areas. In
1825 the federal government created a Permanent
Indian Frontier. Encompassing much of
modern-day Nebraska, Kansas, and Oklahoma,
it was to serve as a home for displaced
eastern tribes. Tribes already in the area, such
as the Kansas, Wichitas, Osages, and Pawnees,
ceded lands to make room for tribes removed
from the east, such as the Delawares and Kickapoos.
But this was not a Permanent Indian
Frontier. In 1854 the Kansas-Nebraska Act
opened up vast areas for American settlement.
In a flurry of treaty signing in the second
half of the 1850s many Indigenous groups
ceded their ancestral lands, retaining only
small reservations.</p>

<p>On their reservations Plains Indians were
placed under great pressure to change. They
experimented with new strategies of resistance
but enjoyed limited success. Pawnees in Nebraska
and Osages in Kansas, for example,
found their livelihoods threatened by Sioux
raids and by non-Indian migrants who drove
off game. The Indians responded by trying to
levy tolls of sugar and coffee on emigrants and
by occasionally resorting to harassment and
cattle raids. American settlers, crowding in
around the reservations, called for the Indians'
removal. By the mid-1880s the Pawnees
and many of the other Native peoples in Kansas
and Nebraska had been relocated to Indian
Territory (now Oklahoma), the remnant of
the Permanent Indian Frontier.</p>

<p>Many Plains peoples engaged in diplomacy
with the United States and other tribes as a
strategy to deal with the American newcomers.
In 1851, at Fort Laramie, federal agents
negotiated a treaty with the Arapahos, Arikaras,
Assiniboines, Cheyennes, Crows, Hidatsas,
Mandans, Lakota Sioux, and others.
Two years later the government entered into
a treaty with the Comanches, Kiowas, and
Kiowa Apaches at Fort Atkinson. In 1855,
along the Judith River, representatives of the
Bloods, Piegans, Siksikas, and Gros Ventres
made their agreements with the United States.
These treaties called for peaceful relations, delineated
which tribes got which lands, and
stipulated that tribes would be given supplies
and services to make up for the destruction of
game by non-Indians.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Wars</head>

<p>The treaties did not end threats to Indian lifeways
and thus failed to forestall violence for
long. The Americans' destruction of game intensified
competition among the tribes for the
remaining bison and other animals. The U.S.
military fought several engagements with the
Lakota Sioux, Cheyennes, and Arapahos in the
mid-1850s. In the two years after the 1858 discovery
of gold in Colorado, thousands of gold
seekers flocked into Arapaho territory, violating
the 1851 treaty. Some Arapahos responded
by moving north of the Platte. For the southern
bands who remained, relations with the
trespassers deteriorated, and on November 29,
1864, white militiamen massacred Black Kettle's
and White Antelope's Cheyennes and
Arapahos at Sand Creek, Colorado. In response,
members of these tribes, along with
some Sioux, Comanches, and Kiowas, resorted
to war. They launched a series of attacks
against posts along the immigrant trails. Relative
peace was restored when the Southern
Arapahos, some Cheyenne bands, Comanches,
and Kiowas agreed in 1865 and 1867 to
treaties that would confine them to reservations.
In exchange, federal officials guaranteed
that the Indians would be protected from attacks
by settlers and soldiers and that they
would receive goods to offset the destruction
of the bison and other game. When the Comanches
and Kiowas resumed raiding because
the government failed to provide adequate rations,
the army destroyed the Indians' winter
camps and forced them back to their reservation
along the Red River.</p>

<p>In the Central and Northern Plains, bands
of Cheyennes, Arapahos, and Lakota Sioux
also waged war to protect themselves. The discovery
of gold in Montana in 1862 brought
large numbers of non-Indians into and through
the area. When the federal government built
forts to protect the settlers and the route to the
goldfields, the Bozeman Trail, Native Americans
laid siege to the forts and forced the
United States to negotiate a settlement. In the
1868 Treaty of Fort Laramie, federal negotiators
agreed to evacuate the forts, to provide a
large reservation (the "Great Sioux Reservation")
in South and North Dakota, and to
guarantee Indian hunting rights.</p>

<figure n="egp.na.001.01" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Sitting Bull (Tatanka Iyotanka), 1885</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Nevertheless, the Sioux and their allies ultimately
suffered the same fate as the Comanches
and Kiowas. When Americans discovered
gold in the Black Hills area of the
Great Sioux Reservation in 1874, the federal
government unsuccessfully attempted to get
the Sioux to sell or lease the land. War broke
out between the army and the Sioux and
Northern Cheyennes in 1876. The Indians, led
by Gall and Sitting Bull (both Hunkpapa
Sioux), defeated forces under Gen. George
Armstrong Custer at the Battle of the Little
Bighorn, but the military's winter campaign
of 1876.77 forced most of the Sioux and Cheyennes
to return to their reservations or to flee
to Canada. Among the latter, those led by Sitting
Bull returned to the reservation in 1881,
while some others settled in Canada permanently.
By the time of Sitting Bull's return,
all of the Plains peoples had been settled on
reservations.</p>

<p>The army's successes over some Plains tribes
stemmed in large measure from the assistance
of other Plains Indians as scouts and auxiliaries.
Pawnees, Arikaras, and Crows helped the
American military fight against the Lakotas,
while Pawnees, Caddos, and Wichitas allied
with the United States against the Comanches.
Military service represented a means for some
Indians to adapt to changing conditions. By
serving as a scout or auxiliary, an Indian could
provide himself and his family with material
benefits, including extra rations, food, money,
and horses captured in battle. Some Plains Natives
saw the United States as a lesser threat
than tribes like the Sioux. Service in the army
also provided an avenue of escape, albeit temporary,
from reservation life and an opportunity
to gain honor and status through combat.
Similar motivations would later prompt
Plains Indians to serve in the U.S. Armed
Forces in subsequent conflicts, such as World
Wars I and II, Korea, and Vietnam.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Treaties, Dispossession, and War in Canada</head>

<p>On the Canadian Prairies, the fur trade remained
the principal medium of interaction
between the Indians and whites until the late
1860s. A "middle ground" emerged there between
the Blackfoot, Gros Ventres, Assiniboines,
and Plains Crees on the one side, and
fur traders on the other. Interchange of ideas
reduced racial prejudices, gifts created fictive
kinship ties, intermarriage bonded companies
and bands together, and sexual interaction
produced a large M&#233;tis (persons of mixed Native,
French, and British heritage) population.
This cultural accommodation came to an end
with the decline of the fur trade in the 1860s.
In 1870, after years of deteriorating resources
and decreasing profits, the Hudson's Bay
Company sold Rupert's Land to the Dominion
of Canada.</p>

<p>Like their counterparts in the United States,
Canadian officials wanted to move Plains Indians
and M&#233;tis out of the way of non-Indians
who settled the Prairie Provinces in greater
numbers following the construction of the Canadian
Pacific Railway. Hoping to learn from
the United States and avoid a series of financially
costly wars, Ottawa officials negotiated a
series of seven numbered treaties with the
Plains peoples between 1871 and 1877. The Natives
agreed to the treaties after a movement led
by M&#233;tis Louis Riel to establish an independent
M&#233;tis government in 1869 was crushed and
because they wanted government aid to offset
the loss of the bison. Plains groups with which
the government signed treaties included the
Red River Anishinaabes (Chippewas), Plains
Crees, Plains Anishinaabes, Siksikas (Northern
Blackfoot), Bloods, Northern Piegans,
Sarcees, and selected Assiniboines. Generally,
the treaties stipulated that the Natives would
agree to accept reserves and individual allotments
of land in exchange for government aid
and assistance in agriculture.</p>

<p>Like their counterparts farther south, Canadian
Plains peoples found diplomacy did
not produce desired results. Construction of
the Canadian Pacific Railway destroyed most
of the Blackfoot's hunting territory. Canadian
officials often failed to provide adequate aid
and sometimes withheld promised aid as
punishment for those who called for alterations
to treaty provisions. Efforts by leaders
such as Crowfoot (Siksika Blackfoot) and Big
Bear (Cree) to keep the peace between Natives
and whites ultimately proved unsuccessful. In
1884 starving Indians robbed government
storehouses and killed several local officials.
Crees, Assiniboines, and M&#233;tis fended off an
attack by troops at Cut Knife Hill, but several
key Indian leaders were later arrested.</p>

<figure n="egp.na.001.02" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Chief Poundmaker (P&#299;tikwahanapiw&#299;yin)</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Troops also crushed the North-West Rebellion
of M&#233;tis. In March 1885 in Saskatchewan
a group of M&#233;tis, led once again by Louis
Riel, took control of the village of Batoche,
arrested the Indian agent, and declared the
existence of a new government for the area.
Hundreds of Crees and Assiniboines under
Big Bear and Poundmaker joined Riel. Government
troops recaptured Batoche and eventually
forced many of the M&#233;tis and Indians,
including Riel, Poundmaker, and Big Bear, to
surrender (although some escaped to Montana).
After a series of trials, the Canadian
government hanged Riel and eight others.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Reservations, Allotments, and Assimilation</head>

<p>As a result of the loss of economic resources
and military defeats, Plains peoples found
themselves confined to reservations in the
United States and reserves in Canada. Reservation
life represented a radical departure from
the Indians' prior existence. Some groups,
such as those Cheyennes and Arapahos who
had been resettled in Oklahoma, found themselves
far from their homelands, where the environment
was unfamiliar and adjustment was
difficult. Even for those who remained in relatively
familiar territory, the mobility integral to
their bison-hunting way of life had been lost.
Even if Indians were allowed to leave the reservation
or reserve to hunt, their main prey, the
bison, was virtually extinct by the early 1880s.
For the Caddos, Wichitas, and other Plains
peoples who depended on agriculture, the reservation
lands often proved inadequate for
cultivation. Plains peoples, who had once
drawn their existence from the soil and the
bison, had in many ways become economically
dependent upon United States.</p>

<p>For all of the problems with the reservations
and reserves, however, they represented
homes for peoples and contexts for their cultures.
In the United States especially, humanitarian
"reformers" worked to take away even
this single saving grace. These reformers and
their advocates in the government argued that
Americans had an obligation to "civilize"
assimilate&#8211;Indians by breaking down tribal
bonds and absorbing them into white society
as individuals.</p>

<p>Several factors helped reformers win support
for their ideas. In the context of the
Plains Wars and expanding white settlement,
absorbing Indians into white society seemed
to be the only way to prevent their extinction.
Evangelical Christians' desire to create a "righteous
empire" in the United States made conversion
of the "red heathens" an important
goal. Industrialization and increasing immigration
of eastern European Catholics and
Jews seemed to threaten traditional rural
Anglo-Saxon values and fueled a desire to
"Americanize" the first Americans. Reformers
also felt that assimilation would end the dependence
of many Native Americans upon
government rations and annuities.</p>

<p>The 1887 General Allotment Act (along
with subsequent acts and amendments) ultimately
became the vehicle through which reformers
sought to eradicate Indian cultures
and societies. Sponsored by Massachusetts
senator Henry Dawes, the act provided for
ending the tribes' communal landownership
and allotting reservation land into individually
owned plots. Dawes and the reformers argued
that the legislation would sever the peoples'
bonds with their "backwards" tribal
cultures and societies while forcing them to
become hardworking farmers. Unallotted reservation
land would then be sold as "surplus
lands" to non-Indians. This would further
facilitate assimilation by reducing the land
available for Indians to use for hunting and
would allow Indians to learn from their white
neighbors.</p>

<p>Allotment did not become such a significant
(and damaging) aspect of Indian policy
in Canada. The 1869 Indian Act granted band
councils the right to assign full title of specific
reserve lands to individuals, who subsequently
were allowed to sell, rent, or lease their land
only to other band members. Hence, non-
Indians simply did not have the same opportunities
to buy nonallotted "surplus" lands or
to eventually gain access to allotted lands.</p>

<p>Canadians did follow the Americans' lead
in using education as a means of assimilation.
By the mid-1890s both the U.S. and Canadian
governments funded a network of Indian day
and boarding schools to foster assimilation.
These schools provided academic and vocational
education while forbidding students
from engaging in such Indian cultural activities
as speaking Native languages and practicing
Native religions.</p>

<p>O.cials in Washington and Ottawa suppressed
Plains Indian cultural practices in
other ways as well. In Canada, the 1876 Indian
Act (with subsequent amendments) outlawed
traditional tribal and band governments and
banned various religious and cultural practices
such as the Sun Dance and Thirst Dance.
In the United States, federal agents forced Native
Americans to attend Christian services, to
adopt "citizens'" clothing and hairstyles, to
follow only federally approved Indian leaders,
and to abstain from such cultural practices as
the Sun Dance and polygamy.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Cultural and Economic Adaptations</head>

<p>Native Americans did not passively accept such
strictures, and they found many ways to resist.
Sometimes such resistance led to violence, as
when conflict with some Lakota Sioux over the
Ghost Dance religion ended in the Wounded
Knee Massacre in December 1890. Emerging in
the late 1880s, the Ghost Dance religion anticipated
the destruction of the Earth and the creation
of a new world occupied by abundant
game and deceased relatives. Many Lakotas, including
Sitting Bull, embraced the Ghost Dance
and began performing the requisite songs and
dances. Some believed that certain "Ghost
Shirts" would protect them from harm. Fearing
that the dances portended an uprising, the Indian
agent at Standing Rock Reservation ordered
the arrest of Sitting Bull, who had remained
a powerful advocate of Lakota resistance.
During the arrest an intense fight
ensued, and Indian policemen killed the respected
leader. Fearing more violence, Miniconjou
leader Big Foot and his band fled south
to the Pine Ridge Reservation. There, on December
28, 1890, at Wounded Knee Creek, soldiers
attempted to disarm the Indians, and
gunfire was exchanged. Who pulled the trigger
first remains unclear, but the army's superior
firepower turned the encounter into a massacre:
from 150 to 250 Sioux men, women, and
children died, as did twenty-five soldiers. Still,
the Ghost Dance continued to attract adherents
from the Plains, including Oklahoma
Kiowas and Comanches, Saskatchewan Sioux,
and Wyoming Shoshones.</p>

<p>Some Plains Indians accepted at least some
white ways and policies. Big Tree, a Kiowa war
leader imprisoned for a time for his raiding
activities, converted to Christianity and became
a farmer on his Oklahoma allotment.
Others resisted assimilation while adapting
to the new world that was being thrust upon
them. Omaha half-siblings Susette and Francis
La Flesche attended white educational institutions
and used their education to conduct
a campaign to win public support for allowing
the Poncas to return to their home in Nebraska.
Susan La Flesche graduated from
medical school (making her one of the few
American women and the only Native American
woman in the nineteenth century to do
so) and used her training to treat her people.</p>

<p>Religion was a primary means of preserving
cultural distinctiveness. Many Indians became
involved with peyotism in the late nineteenth
and early twentieth centuries. Involving the
ingestion of the peyote plant, peyotism is a
syncretistic belief system that combines aspects
of Christian and traditional Indian spirituality.
A Caddo expression of peyotism, the
Big Moon ceremony (later known as Cross
Fire ritual) incorporated Jesus Christ, the
Bible, and other Christian elements.</p>

<p>Multitribal gatherings pointed toward new
"pan-Indian" identities that coexisted with
more discrete tribal identifications. Native
peoples in the Plains came to share certain
kinds of cultural display. The Grass Dance,
originating with the Pawnees, became a regular
part of the growing number of intertribal
gatherings across the Plains. Native peoples in
the United States and Canada got permission
to perform the dance on their home reservations
by billing it as a "tribute" to the nation
on American Independence Day (July 4) or
Canadian Dominion Day (July 1).</p>

<p>Economically, Plains Indians' adaptations
varied. The Osages and a few other tribes generated
income from oil or other mineral resources.
A growing number depended upon
seasonal and wage labor. Some Indians reconciled
wage labor with more traditional economic
enterprises. Cheyenne women, for example,
continued to produce moccasins for
other Indians and non-Indians, just as they
had since before Lewis and Clark. By the end
of World War I Cheyennes and Arapahos
served as seasonal agricultural laborers harvesting
Oklahoma wheat. Many Sioux helped
harvest potatoes in Nebraska. Plains peoples
experimented with cattle ranching, which
looked to be on the path to success until
agents and other non-Indians pressured Indians
to sell off their herds during World War
I. The Gros Ventres, Pine Ridge Sioux, Comanches,
and other Indian ranchers sold or
leased much of their land to whites.</p>

<p>The Indian cattle industry temporarily
fared better on the Canadian Prairies. In an
effort to diversify Native economies, Ottawa
o.cials encouraged the Prairie groups to become
stock raisers by issuing large numbers of
cattle to them. The cattle industry was well
established on the Prairie reserves by 1900, but
a long dry spell in the 1920s, together with
extensive leasing of grazing lands to non-
Indians, subsequently decreased the importance
of ranching.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">The Indian New Deal in the Plains</head>

<p>By the end of the 1920s many Americans had
concluded that allotment and assimilation
had not been successful. Nationally, the sale
of surplus lands and allotments from 1887 to
1934 reduced the Indian's land base by twothirds,
from 138 million to 52 million acres.
Ironically, a policy designed to foster selfsupport
produced dispossession and dependency
instead. Such economic devastation undoubtedly helped account for Indians' low
incomes and high rates of infant mortality
and disease.</p>

<p>The growing recognition of these failures
led to a shift in U.S. Indian policy that once
again changed the environment in which Indians
operated. The new changes, like the old
ones, created both opportunities and problems
for Indians. In 1933 John Collier, a New
York social worker and longtime critic of federal
Indian policy, became the commissioner
of Indian affairs. Collier believed that white
society had become too individualistic and
had much to learn from Native Americans'
community-oriented cultures. He came to office
determined to reverse the assimilation
policy and to restore an Indian economic
base. Collier's reforms, contained in the 1934
Indian Reorganization Act (<hi rend="smallcaps">IRA</hi>), ended allotment,
increased tribally owned land, and authorized
tribes to organize constitutional governments
empowered to negotiate with their
federal, state, and local counterparts. The act
also allowed greater access to economic resources
through the establishment of a revolving
credit fund from which tribes could finance
economic development projects and by
making Indians eligible for social welfare programs
available to other citizens.</p>

<p>Many Plains peoples availed themselves of
the <hi rend="smallcaps">IRA</hi>'s political and economic provisions.
The Cheyenne-Arapahos of Oklahoma, Caddos,
Pawnees, Poncas, Iowas, Blackfeet, Pine
Ridge Sioux, and other Plains groups adopted
written constitutions under the Indian New
Deal. The Blackfeet developed a new law code
that provided for wildlife conservation. With a
two-million-dollar loan, the Northern Cheyennes
developed a livestock enterprise. Thousands
of Indians found temporary employment
through New Deal work programs like
the Indian Civilian Conservation Corps and
the Works Project Administration. Funds
from the latter agency paid for Shoshones to
tan elk hides, while the Civilian Conservation
Corps and other relief programs provided
work for 85 percent of Rosebud Reservation
males. The Indian New Deal facilitated the return
of millions of acres of land to Native
American control as well.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, the Indian New Deal had its
share of problems. The <hi rend="smallcaps">IRA</hi>'s provisions for
organizing tribal governments were based on
Collier's understanding of the Pueblos and
on European American models and thus were
often different from tribes' conceptions of
government. The secretary of the interior had
the power to "review" many decisions made
by the new tribal governments. The money in
the credit fund usually proved inadequate and
only went to the best credit risks and not to
those who most needed money. The question
of whether tribes should organize under the
act often proved divisive. On the Rosebud and
Pine Ridge Reservations, for example, more
acculturated residents tended to favor the act
for its economic provisions, whereas traditional
residents advocated basing relations
with the United States on past treaties and
thus tended to oppose it.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">World war II and Termination</head>

<p>Like the New Deal, World War II had an enormous
impact upon Plains Indians. Thousands
served in the armed forces of the United States
and Canada, and wartime activities promoted
economic opportunities. The Sioux, for example,
helped build military facilities in the
Northern Plains. In other cases, Indians migrated
to urban areas to work in war industries,
an out-migration from reservations that
has continued to some degree ever since. In
Canada, many Indians who served in World
War II gained citizenship and political rights,
giving them more leverage to fight for religious
rights and better education, housing,
and health programs. Many of these efforts
came to fruition with the 1951 Indian Act,
which granted the Natives greater freedom to
practice religious and cultural ceremonies and
the right to raise political funds and consume
alcohol outside reserves.</p>

<p>In 1946 Congress passed the Indian Claims
Commission Act, which created the Indian
Claims Commission. Through the commission
Native Americans could win compensation
from the federal government for past
mistreatment, such as violations of treaties
and land seizures. Numerous Plains Indian
groups filed claims with the commission. The
Pawnee, for example, were awarded $7.3 million
by the Indian Claims Commission in 1962
in recognition of past "unconscionably low"
payments for their lands.</p>

<p>The Indian Claims Commission, however,
was also a mechanism for clearing the backlog
of Indian claims as a prelude to severing federal
obligation to the tribes. The success that Indians
had had serving in World War II, as well
as desires to cut federal spending and to promote
national unity during the cold war, convinced
many that Indians no longer needed
special protection and that they should be "rewarded"
through integration into the "mainstream."
These views produced the "termination"
policy between 1953 and the early 1960s.
Termination sought to end Indians' eligibility
for certain federal services and to abolish the
federal trust status of Indian lands. The latter
move would subject reservations to state laws
and state taxes and other forces that would
presumably erode and destroy Native Americans'
distinct cultural status. One Plains tribe,
the Northern Poncas, was declared terminated.
The federal government also funded a
voluntary relocation program to encourage
Indians to move to urban areas, such as Denver,
where they would supposedly have more
employment opportunities and would more
readily assimilate.</p>

<p>In some ways, relocation to urban areas
could be seen as a revival of the old Plains
Indian strategy of physical mobility. The results
of relocation often proved mixed, however.
As much as 40 percent of relocatees
eventually returned to their home communities.
City life caused or exacerbated such ills
as alcoholism, spouse abuse, and poverty.
Nevertheless, some relocatees did find employment,
and the interaction of people from
different tribes helped foster a "pan-Plains"
and "pan-Indian" consciousness.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Native Political Adaptations</head>

<p>Whether they migrated to cities or stayed in
their home communities, Plains Indians increasingly
utilized intertribal organizing and
political tactics&#8211;direct lobbying and public
protests, for example&#8211;to protect and advance
their interests. Even before World War II
ended, Native peoples met in Denver to form
the National Congress of American Indians
(<hi rend="smallcaps">NCAI</hi>). Osages, Gros Ventres, Blackfeet,
Oglala Sioux, Cheyenne-Arapahos, and other
representatives of the Plains tribes secured important
positions in the organization. Helen
Peterson (Oglala Sioux) was executive director
from 1953 to 1961. Plains Indians also often
proved successful in using their positions to
lobby Congress to reject or alter several termination
bills during the 1950s. Ironically, termination&#8211;
designed to break down tribal structures&#8211;
probably strengthened Plains tribes
and organizations by providing a coherent
threat that united many Indians in opposition.</p>

<p>Native American lobbying and organization
ultimately forced a change in federal policy. Instead
of termination, federal policy by the early
1960s came to emphasize "self-determination,"
which involved allowing tribes greater control
over their own affairs. Self-determination
was facilitated by the 1960s War on Poverty,
which gave local organizations access to federal
funds and opportunities to administer
antipoverty projects. Indians' inclusion in
War on Poverty legislation stemmed largely
from the 1964 Indian Capital Conference on
Poverty held in Washington <hi rend="smallcaps">DC</hi>. Plains Indians
played prominent roles in the conference, including
ncai executive director Robert
Burnette (Rosebud Sioux), congressional representative
Benjamin Reifel (Brul&#233; Sioux),
honorary conference chairman Walter Wetzel
(Blackfoot), and archdeacon Vine V. Deloria
Sr. (Standing Rock Sioux).</p>

<p>Many Plains peoples utilized the federal resources
that the War on Poverty made available.
The Anishinaabe and Cree residents
of the Rocky Boy's Reservation in Montana
started a crafts cooperative that produced and
sold leather goods to customers throughout
the country. The Rosebud Sioux used federal
assistance to provide prefabricated housing to
reservation residents. Indians not only improved
their economic situations, but the experience
of managing programs and funds
strengthened tribal governments and provided
a training ground for Indian leaders.</p>

<p>Sometimes, Plains Indians worked for self-determination
through more assertive protest.
The organization most commonly associated
with this approach in the late twentieth century
was the American Indian Movement
(<hi rend="smallcaps">AIM</hi>). Although originally founded in Minneapolis
in 1968 as an outgrowth of the pantribal
Indian communities that developed in
urban areas, the group established chapters
throughout the Plains states. In South Dakota
in 1970, <hi rend="smallcaps">AIM</hi> members occupied the Sheep
Mountain area&#8211;taken from the Pine Ridge
Sioux during World War II&#8211;and staged another
protest at Mount Rushmore. In 1973, the
year after the Trail of Broken Treaties caravan
to Washington <hi rend="smallcaps">DC</hi> and the seizure of the Bureau
of Indian Affairs building, Dennis Banks
(Anishinaabe), Russell Means (Oglala Sioux,
or Lakota), and other AIM members occupied
the Pine Ridge Reservation town of Wounded
Knee for more than two months. The occupation
grew out of a conflict with tribal chairman
Richard Wilson, who was seen by aim as
a corrupt puppet of the United States. The
occupation was, in some ways, a rejection of
both America's Indian policy and of the tribal
council form of government itself.</p>

<p>Since the late 1960s, Canadian Indian strategies
of protest, lobbying, and lawsuits have
forced Ottawa policymakers to acknowledge
increased self-government for the Native peoples
of the Plains and elsewhere. By the end of
the 1960s a growing number of functions once
handled for bands by the Canadian government&#8211;
such as housing and education&#8211;had
been taken over by Indian councils. Native
protests forced the government to reject a
termination-style policy recommended by a
1969 White Paper. Indian lobbying and protest
also convinced Ottawa policymakers to set up
an Office of Native Claims to investigate and
negotiate settlements with individual Indians
and Native groups who claimed to have lost
land because of the government's failure to
honor its treaty obligations to the tribes. The
government, as part of the 1982 Constitution
Act, recognized for the first time Native peoples'
title to the land based on Aboriginal status
and treaties. However, the measure failed
to spell out what such rights entailed, and it
did not settle the issue of Natives' relationship
with the rest of the country. This became clear
in 1990 when Elijah Harper, a Cree and the
only Native member of the Manitoba Legislative
Assembly, helped block the Meech Lake
Accord, which classified French-speaking
Quebec as a "distinct" society but failed to
recognize the distinct status of Natives. What
the future holds for the Plains peoples of Canada
and their relationship with other Canadians
remains unclear, although legal decisions
of the late 1990s point to positive changes
in views toward Indian land management and
the validity of oral history.</p>

<p>The same uncertainty holds true for the
United States as well. In many respects, Plains
peoples' adaptive strategies have succeeded
in enhancing their opportunities for political
power and economic self-sufficiency.
Federal legislation such as the Indian Self-
Determination and Education Act (1975) and
the Self-Governance Project Demonstration
Act (1991) have allowed many tribes greater
control over their own political affairs. Several
Plains Indians&#8211;like Northern Cheyenne Ben
Nighthorse Campbell, the first Native American
to serve in the U.S. Senate&#8211;have filled
important government positions. Economic
development projects, especially the creation
of Indian gaming establishments, have increased
the incomes of some groups. On the
Pine Ridge Reservation, for example, the Prairie
Wind Casino was generating several thousand
dollars a month in the mid-1990s.</p>

<p>Such political and economic progress has
been accompanied by an even greater success
among North American Plains peoples in
maintaining distinct identities. Spiritual practices
like the Sun Dance are experiencing a
revival in both the United States and Canada.
By the mid-1990s Buffy Sainte-Marie&#8211;a Cree
from the Piapot Reserve in Saskatchewan&#8211;
had recorded several albums of Indian and
popular music, written several pieces for Indian
publications, and authored a children's
book incorporating Indian themes. aim cofounder
and musician John Trudell, a Santee
Sioux, mixed Northern Plains Indian musical
forms with blues and rock and roll. Trudell,
Floyd Westerman, Russell Means, and other
Plains Indian actors have appeared in several
films. The American Indian Religious Freedom
Act (1978) and the Native American
Graves Protection and Repatriation Act (1990)
&#8211;enacted as a result of Indian demands&#8211;have
provided a legal basis for the protection of
Native American religious practices and for
the repatriation of Indian remains and cultural
items held by museums.</p>

<p>Furthermore, the 2000 census shows that
Native Americans in the U.S. Great Plains are
increasing significantly in numbers, while
most Plains counties are losing population.
The overall Native American population in
North Dakota grew 20 percent from 1990 to
2000, in South Dakota 23 percent, and in
Montana 18 percent. During the same years
forty-seven of North Dakota's fifty-three
counties lost population. The resurgence of
Native American population is a result of high
birth rates but also of a significant return
to the reservations, partly because of job opportunities
at casinos. The reservations and
surrounding counties stand out on the 2000
census map as places having more than 25 percent,
and often more than 50 percent, of their
population Native American.</p>

<figure n="egp.na.001.03" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Native American population in the U.S. Great Plains as a percentage of total population, by county, in 2000</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>In many ways, however, the Plains peoples
of the twenty-first century face significant
challenges. Large numbers of Natives in Canada
and the United States continue to experience
poverty, ill health, substandard housing,
and poor health care at rates well above the
national average. In the mid-1990s unemployment
on the Pine Ridge Reservation ranged
from 65 to 85 percent, 1,800 families lacked
adequate housing, and many people suffered
from alcoholism. Cuts in funding for U.S. Indian
programs during the 1980s and 1990s have
exacerbated such problems and threaten to
cancel out recent gains in self-determination
and quality of life. States and private concerns
have launched concerted attacks on Indian
gaming.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Conclusion</head>

<p>Assertions of a "Native renaissance" may be
premature. Nevertheless, Plains Native peoples
have proven skilled at adapting to hardship
and change while making the most of
available opportunities. They have traded and
raided, farmed and hunted, ranched and
worked for wages, negotiated and made war,
danced and prayed, lobbied and protested.
Such adaptive strategies have allowed Plains
Indians to maintain themselves as distinct
peoples despite significant obstacles. One
could argue that Plains Indian history has
been a succession of "Native renaissances," always
coming in response to hard times and
always changing the nature of Plains cultures.
Native peoples are and will continue to be an
integral part of life in the Plains for a long
time to come.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">FILM</hi>: <ref n="egp.fil.029">Hollywood Indians</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">LAW</hi>:
<ref n="egp.law.015">Dawes Act</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">LITERARY TRADITIONS</hi>: <ref n="egp.lt.026">Hogan, Linda</ref>; <ref n="egp.lt.047">Momaday, N. Scott</ref>; <ref n="egp.lt.079">Welch, James</ref> /
<hi rend="smallcaps">MUSIC</hi>: <ref n="egp.mus.041">Sainte-Marie, Buffy</ref>; <ref n="egp.mus.046">Trudell, John</ref> /
<hi rend="smallcaps">PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT</hi>: <ref n="egp.pe.010">Bison</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">PROTEST
AND DISSENT</hi>: <ref n="egp.pd.005">American Indian Movement</ref> /
<hi rend="smallcaps">RELIGION</hi>: <ref n="egp.rel.023">Ghost Dance</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">WAR</hi>: <ref n="egp.war.022">Indian Scouts</ref>;
<ref n="egp.war.032">North-West Rebellion</ref>; <ref n="egp.war.044">Sioux Wars</ref>.</p>
</div2>

<closer>
<signed>Philip J. Deloria<lb/>
University of Michigan<lb/>
Christopher K. Riggs<lb/>
University of Colorado at Boulder</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Comeau, Pauline, and Aldo Santin. <title level="m">The First Canadians: A Profile of Canada's Native People Today</title>. Toronto: University
of Toronto Press, 1990.</bibl> <bibl>Deloria, Vine, Jr., and Clifford
M. Lytle. <title level="m">The Nations Within: The Past and Future of American Indian Sovereignty</title>. Lincoln: University of Nebraska
Press, 1984.</bibl> <bibl>Fixico, Donald L. <title level="m">Termination and Relocation: Federal Indian Policy, 19451960</title>. Albuquerque:
University of New Mexico Press, 1986.</bibl> <bibl>Holm, Tom. <title level="m">Strong Hearts, Wounded Souls: Native American Veterans of Vietnam</title>.
Austin: University of Texas Press, 1996.</bibl> <bibl>Hoxie, Frederick
E. <title level="m">Parading through History: The Making of the Crow Nation in America, 18051935</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge
University Press, 1995.</bibl> <bibl>Josephy, Alvin M., Jr., ed. <title level="m">America in 1492: The World of the Indian People before the Arrival of Columbus</title>. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, Inc. 1992.</bibl>
<bibl>McNickle, D'Arcy. <title level="m">Native American Tribalism: Indian Survivals and Renewals</title>. London: Oxford University Press,
1973.</bibl> <bibl>Philp, Kenneth R. <title level="m">John Collier's Crusade for Indian Reform, 19201954</title>. Tucson: University of Arizona Press,
1977.</bibl> <bibl>Smith, Paul Chaat, and Robert Allen Warrior. <title level="m">Like a Hurricane: The Indian Movement from Alcatraz to Wounded Knee</title>. New York: New Press, 1996.</bibl> <bibl>Trigger, Bruce,
and Wilcomb E. Washburn, eds. <title level="m">The Cambridge History of the Native Peoples of the Americas</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge
University Press, 1996.</bibl> <bibl>Van Kirk, Sylvia. <title level="m">Many Tender Ties: Women in Fur-Trade Society, 16701870</title>. Norman: University
of Oklahoma Press, 1983.</bibl> <bibl>Wood, W. Raymond, and
Thomas D. Thiessen, eds. <title level="m">Early Fur Trade on the Northern Plains: Canadian Traders among the Mandan and Hidatsa Indians, 17381818</title>. Norman: University of Oklahoma
Press, 1985.</bibl>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>