<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.sr.030">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Howe, Gordie (b. 1928)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Kent M. Krause</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.sr.030</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Odgaard, Nathan E.">Nathan E. Odgaard</author>. <title level="a">"Howe, Gordie (b. 1928)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">777</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-21</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">Howe, Gordie (b. 1928)</head>

<p>Like many boys growing up in the Prairie Provinces
(he was born at Floral, Saskatchewan, on
March 31, 1928), Gordie Howe dreamed of
someday playing in the National Hockey
League (<hi rend="smallcaps">NHL</hi>). At the age of eighteen, Howe's
dreams were fulfilled when he took to the ice
with the Detroit Red Wings. Over the next
thirty-four years, including six in the World
Hockey Association (<hi rend="smallcaps">WHA</hi>), Howe would enjoy
a spectacular, durable career, wreaking
havoc on the opposition with his tenacious
style of play.</p>

<p>Considered one of the greatest players of all
time, Howe was a six-time scoring champion
and six-time Hart Memorial Trophy winner,
awarded to the league's most valuable player,
during his twenty-five-year stint as a Red
Wing. Only Wayne Gretzky has won more
scoring titles (seven) and has accumulated
more mvp awards (nine) than Howe.</p>

<p>As a right-wing forward, Howe amassed 801
goals and 1,850 points in his <hi rend="smallcaps">NHL</hi> career, both
of which are second to Gretzky's record totals.
He helped guide Detroit to four Stanley Cups
in six years, from 1950 to 1955, and seven consecutive
regular-season titles (1948–54). He
dominated the league in the 1951–52 and 1952–53
seasons, racking up eighty-six and ninetyfive
points, respectively. His forty-seven goals
in the 1951–52 season were sixteen more than
the second-leading scorer (Chicago's William
Mosienko), and he tallied thirty-nine assists,
which tied for third best in the league. The
next year he recorded a career-high forty-nine
goals. But Howe's best year, statistically, occurred
in 1968–69 at the age of forty, when he
established a career high in points (103), eight
more than his previous high. He recorded
forty-four goals and fifty-nine assists, his all-time
best, and finished third in the scoring
race.</p>

<p>Howe's vigor and resiliency were keys to his
longevity on the ice. He holds the <hi rend="smallcaps">NHL</hi> record
for most seasons played (26) and most games
played (1,767). However, in his third year,
Howe's career was nearly cut short when he
collided with Toronto's Ted Kennedy during a
play-off game and crashed head-on into the
sideboards, suffering a severe brain injury.
The injury left him with a slight facial tic,
which occasionally caused his eyes to blink
uncontrollably. Thus, his teammates nicknamed
him Blinky.</p>

<p>At six feet and 205 pounds, Howe was powerful
and fearless. He racked up 2,418 career
penalty minutes. In 1959 he broke Lou Fontinato's
nose in a game against the New York
Rangers and caused other extensive damage to
Fontinato's face, which required reconstructive
surgery.</p>

<p>Howe retired with the Red Wings in 1971,
having been named to the nhl all-star team
twenty-one times in twenty-five years, and
was inducted into Toronto's Hockey Hall of
Fame in 1972. He returned to the game in 1973
to join sons Marty and Mark with the <hi rend="smallcaps">WHA</hi>
Houston Aeros. He closed out his career in
1979 at the age of fifty-two, playing one last
year in the <hi rend="smallcaps">NHL</hi> with the Hartford Whalers.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Nathan E. Odgaard<lb/>
Kansas City Kansan</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Gale Research, Inc. <title level="m">The Complete Encyclopedia of Hockey</title>.
Detroit: Associated Features, Inc., 1993.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>