<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.mus.052">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Wills, Bob (1905-1975)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Charles R. Townsend</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.mus.052</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Townsend, Charles R.">Charles R. Townsend</author>. <title level="a">"Wills, Bob (1905-1975)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">551-552</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-03</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">WILLS, BOB (1905-1975)</head>
<figure n="egp.mus.052" rend="granted" type="noclick">
<figDesc>Bob Wills</figDesc>
</figure>      
    

<p>James Robert Wills was born in the "black
belt" of East Texas near the town of Kosse on
March 6, 1905. He grew up in a musical family
of fiddle players and in an area famous for
African American music that produced Scott
Joplin, Victoria Spivey, and Blind Lemon
Jefferson. From his family he learned to play
frontier fiddle music, which had been part of
frontier cultural life from the East Coast to
West Texas. From the African Americans he
learned blues and jazz. By the time Wills
played his first dance as a fiddler at a ranch in
West Texas at the age of ten, he had already
begun to add blues and jazz idioms to traditional
fiddle music. This combination was
eventually called western swing and became
one of the most distinctive sounds in all of
American music. There was hardly an American
musical expression that could not be
heard at one time or another in Wills' music:
ragtime, New Orleans jazz, blues, rhythm and
blues, rock, country, and big band swing.
Wills blended it all into a swinging dance music
that remained popular for seventy-five
years.</p>

<p>Wills performed his music for years at
country and ranch dances in West Texas before introducing it to the general public on
radio stations in Fort Worth. He organized the
Light Crust Doughboys, broadcast over the
Texas Quality Network in 1933, and soon revolutionized
music in Texas. His greatest success
was with his band the Texas Playboys in Tulsa,
Oklahoma, between 1934 and 1942. During
those years he added brass, woodwinds, and
drums and developed a band that by 1940
numbered eighteen members. The band could
play anything from a fiddle breakdown to a
George Gershwin composition and give it a
swinging rhythm and solid beat. His recordings
sold in the hundreds of thousands and his
"San Antonio Rose" in the millions. Wills began
making movies in Hollywood in 1940, and
when he was discharged from the army in 1943
he moved the Texas Playboys to California.
There he was more successful, at least financially,
than at any time in his career. Huge
crowds at his dances and big-selling records
made him one of the highest paid bandleaders
in America.</p>

<p>After the war, Wills gave up most of the
brass and reeds in his band and used more
fiddles, guitars, steel guitars, and mandolins.
This emphasis on strings helped him maintain
his popularity even after the age of the big
bands was over, and he influenced the two
musical forces that were destined to dominate
American music down to the present, rock
and roll and country and western. Western
swing had a marked impression on early rockabillies
such as Bill Haley and the Comets,
Buddy Holly and the Crickets, and Elvis Presley.
Wills's greatest influence, however, was on
country and western. The Country Music Association
gave him its highest honor in 1968,
naming Wills to the Country Music Hall of
Fame. In 1999 Bob Wills was inducted into the
Rock and Roll Hall of Fame in the category of
"early influences."</p>

<p>What was it that gave Wills's music such
lasting appeal? His music and style had many
good qualities, but mainly, his music made
people happy. Bob Wills practiced what President
Franklin D. Roosevelt had advocated
early in the Great Depression&#8211;that the right
kind of music could help us sing and whistle
our way out of hard times or at least live better
with them. In this sense, Bob Wills and His
Texas Playboys were more than entertainers,
they were therapists. They played a practical
role in American life during the Great Depression
and later during World War II.</p>

<p>When Bob Wills died in Dallas on May 13,
1975, he left the world a much richer place. His
compositions like "Faded Love," "Maiden's
Prayer," and "San Antonio Rose" are part of
the repertoire of country and pop artists and
Americana itself. He helped bridge the gap
between black and white musical cultures
when he began combining them as a boy. Out
of that came Bob Wills's richest legacy, his
own musical style, the happy lilting rhythms
and moving beat of western swing.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Charles R. Townsend<lb/>
West Texas A&amp;M University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Sheldon, Ruth. <title level="m">Hubbin' It: The Life of Bob Wills</title>. Tulsa:
Privately published, 1938.</bibl> <bibl>Townsend, Charles R. <title level="m">San Antonio Rose: The Life and Music of Bob Wills</title>. Urbana: University
of Illinois Press, 1976.</bibl>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>