<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.pe.045">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Paleoenvironments</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Kenneth P. Cannon</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.pe.045</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Cannon, Kenneth P.">Kenneth P. Cannon</author>. <title level="a">"Paleoenvironments."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">635-636</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-22</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">PALEOENVIRONMENTS</head>

<p>The most recent geologic period in Earth's history
has been labeled the Quaternary, extending
back approximately two to four million
years. This period has been divided into
two geologic epochs&#8211;the Pleistocene, which
ended approximately 12,000 years ago, and the
Holocene since that time. Over the course of
the Quaternary, dramatic climatic shifts occurred
that, to a great extent, shaped the rolling
landscape and vegetation of today's Great
Plains. Since the Late Pleistocene, three major
trends have dominated the environmental history
of the region. First, between about 18,000
and 10,000 years ago, glaciers began to waste,
and climatic amelioration significantly altered
the biota and landscape; second, during the
early and middle portions of the Holocene, the
climatic trend was toward increased dryness
and warmth; and third, there followed a period
of greater moisture and cooling in the late
Holocene. It should be noted, however, that
the climate is "time-transgressive," meaning it
does not change simultaneously everywhere,
and therefore its effects on Plains biota would
have varied over the years and across space.</p>

<p>In recent simulation models large-scale climatic
shifts have been shown to be the result
of changing atmospheric circulation patterns
caused by shifts in the orientation of the earth's
axis. At 18,000 years ago, the Laurentide ice
sheet, while cooling temperatures across North
America, caused a split in the jet stream. A deflection
of the southern branch of the jet stream
brought moister conditions to what is now the
southwestern United States, while anticyclonic
winds, generated by the ice sheet, brought prevailing
easterlies and dry air to the northwest,
instead of the usual moisture-laden westerlies.
Shifts in the jet stream also appear to have been a
major factor in changing climatic patterns during
the Holocene.</p>

<p>Individual faunal species and communities
were greatly affected by the Pleistocene climatic
and vegetation shifts. Late Pleistocene faunal
communities have been referred to as "disharmonious,"
"intermingled," and "nonanalog
assemblages" to describe the heterogeneous
nature of the species composition. R. Dale
Guthrie, a mammalian biogeographer, described
these communities as a "patchy mosaic"
that allowed for increased numbers and
diversity of herbivores. In the Great Plains a
dry and cool wooded parkland existed, with a
hardwood forest of oak, aspen, and cottonwood
to the east and a coniferous forest to the
west. In the open areas, sagebrush was dominant.
With glacial retreat, the eastern forest
followed the ice northward into southern
Manitoba and Saskatchewan, while the western
coniferous forest moved upslope into the
Rockies.</p>

<p>During the late Pleistocene, faunal communities
were compressed, and members of such
diverse habitats as alpine tundra and xeric
grasslands were living together in the same
community. A patchy mosaic of Ice Age plants
and animals has also been applied to describe
this time period. With glacial retreat came a
collapse in the Ice Age communities and a reduction
in biotic diversity. More than one-half
of North America's large mammals became
extinct. Less-nutritious Holocene vegetation
communities, which had defensive responses
to grazing and browsing, replaced this mosaic
of highly nutritious late Pleistocene vegetation.
The change was probably too abrupt for the
adaptive abilities of many herbivores. Paleoindian
hunters may have been an additional
cause of the mammals' extinction.</p>

<p>The shift from Pleistocene to Holocene environments
was the most dramatic period of
climatic change in recent earth history. Profound
reorganization of biotic communities
resulted, with a pattern of diverse patchy environments
being replaced by a pattern of zonal
communities&#8211;from "plaids" to "stripes,"
according to Guthrie. The megafaunal species
that survived, such as the bison, were significantly
smaller in size, but they were able to
expand their range to become the predominant
species in the Great Plains.</p>

<p>Increased warmth and generally drier conditions
characterized the early Holocene. Active
stream alluviation occurred throughout
the region, with wetlands and marshes common
in the Southern Plains. The trend toward
increased warmth and decreased precipitation
peaked around 8500 <hi rend="smallcaps">B.P</hi>. The dominance of the
Pacific westerlies and the seasonal peak in solar
radiation were important factors during this
climatic episode, often referred to as the Hypsithermal
or Altithermal. Drought-resistant
grasslands expanded, and lake levels dropped
in a time-transgressive trend that began first in
the Northern Plains and then extended later to
the Central and Southern Plains. For example,
on the prairies of Manitoba thermal maxima
occurred about 7,000 years ago, with summer
temperatures as much as 3.5&#186;F warmer and
annual precipitation about one inch less than
today.</p>

<p>By about 4,500 years ago the onset of modern,
or Neoglacial, conditions began, but
again this was not uniform across the region.
Between 3,000 and 4,000 years ago, the mid-
Holocene prairies of northern Alberta and
Manitoba were replaced by boreal forests. In
the Nebraska Sandhills, increased groundwater,
which changed the mid-Holocene
marshlands to lakes, signaled the beginning of
the Neoglacial in the Central Plains around
3,700 years ago.</p>

<p>While the magnitude of the climatic shift
from the mid-Holocene thermal maxima
to the Neoglacial was nowhere as severe as
the Pleistocene-Holocene shift, significant
changes did take place. In the Colorado Front
Range, expansion of alpine glaciers occurred,
while in the Southern Plains increased moisture
permitted soil formation, and an open
oak woodland became established in central
Texas.</p>

<p>The increased effective moisture of the Late
Holocene, particularly between a.d. 1550 and
1880, appears to have had a positive effect on
bison populations. It has been proposed that
high forage production led to increased population
density, larger herds, and decreased migration.
Plains groups appear to have taken
advantage of this trend, as is evident by large
bison kill sites, such as the Glenrock and Vore
Sites in Wyoming, and abundant evidence of
bison from Central Plains archeological sites.</p>

<p>During the last hundred years the climate
has shifted to a warm-dry regime. How long
this will last is unknown. It is important to
know about Plains paleoenvironments because
they provide an understanding of how Holocene
biotic communities developed and suggest
models for likely future climate change and for
the thoughtful management of ecosystems.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">NATIVE AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.na.006">Archaic Period Sites</ref>; <ref n="egp.na.080">Paleo-Indians</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Kenneth P. Cannon<lb/>
National Park Service<lb/>
Lincoln, Nebraska</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Guthrie, R. Dale. <title level="m">Frozen Fauna of the Mammoth Steppe:
The Story of Blue Babe</title>. Chicago: University of Chicago
Press, 1990.</bibl> <bibl>Porter, Stephen C., ed. <title level="m">The Late Pleistocene</title>,
vol. 1 of <title level="m">Late-Quaternary Environments of the United
States</title>, ed. H. E. Wright, Jr. Minneapolis: University of
Minnesota Press, 1983.</bibl> <bibl>Wright, Herbert E., Jr., ed. <title level="m">The
Holocene</title>, vol. 2 of <title level="m">Late-Quaternary Environments of the
United States</title>. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota
Press, 1983.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>