<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ag.022">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Corn</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>R. L. Nielsen</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ag.022</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Nielsen, R. L.">R. L. Nielsen</author>. <title level="a">"Corn."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">39-40</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-12-10</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">CORN</head>

<head>Corn Produced for Grain in the United States, 1997</head>
<table rows="3" cols="13">
<row><cell role="desc">State</cell><cell role="desc">Harvested acres thousand acres</cell><cell role="desc">Total production thousand bushels</cell></row>
<row><cell role="desc">Nebraska</cell><cell role="data">8,725</cell><cell role="data">1,151,700</cell></row>
<row><cell role="desc">South Dakota</cell><cell role="data">3,400</cell><cell role="data">333,200</cell></row>
<row><cell role="desc">Kansas</cell><cell role="data">2,700</cell><cell role="data">386,1000</cell></row>
<row><cell role="desc">Colorado</cell><cell role="data">1,030</cell><cell role="data">150,380</cell></row>
<row><cell role="desc">Texas</cell><cell role="data">907</cell><cell role="data">167,814</cell></row>
<row><cell role="desc">North Dakota</cell><cell role="data">605</cell><cell role="data">59,895</cell></row>
<row><cell role="desc">Oklahoma</cell><cell role="data">129</cell><cell role="data">20,606</cell></row>
<row><cell role="desc">New Mexico</cell><cell role="data">85</cell><cell role="data">14,875</cell></row>
<row><cell role="desc">Wyoming</cell><cell role="data">57</cell><cell role="data">7,695</cell></row>
<row><cell role="desc">Montana</cell><cell role="data">14</cell><cell role="data">1,890</cell></row>
<row><cell role="desc">Great Plains total</cell><cell role="data">17,651</cell><cell role="data">2,294,155</cell></row>
<row><cell role="desc">U.S. total production</cell><cell role="data">73,720</cell><cell role="data">9,365,574</cell></row>
</table>

<p>Corn is the only major cereal crop whose
origin can be claimed by the Western Hemisphere.
Centuries before Europeans "discovered"
the Americas, corn played a major
role in the Mayan, Aztec, and Incan civilizations
in Central and South America. The earliest
archaeological evidence of corn was
found in Mexico's Valley of Tehuacan and was
dated at about 5000 <hi rend="smallcaps">B.C.</hi></p>

<p>Those who appreciate the importance of
this grassy species to American agriculture
sometimes refer to corn as the King of American
Crops. Native Americans more commonly
used the term maize, "that which sustains
life." The Swedish botanist Karl Linnaeus
gave corn its botanical name, Zea mays L. The
Greek word zeo also means "to live." After
seeing maize for the first time, European settlers
called it "Indian corn" in an attempt to
compare the crop to the small grains grown in
Europe that they called corn. Following corn's
"discovery," the crop quickly spread to Europe,
Africa, and Asia. Today, most of the
world still refers to the crop as maize, but the
United States simply calls it corn.</p>

<p>Corn has been grown in various areas of the
Great Plains for many centuries. At the beginning
of the nineteenth century, for example,
Pawnee Indian women had ten pure varieties
of corn. In today's modern agriculture, corn
continues to play an important role throughout
the ten states that comprise the American
Great Plains. Approximately 24 percent of the
total U.S. corn acreage and production occurs
in the Great Plains, with more than 80 percent
of that accounted for by Kansas, Nebraska,
and South Dakota. Nebraska, itself, has nearly
nine million acres under corn each year and
an annual total production of more than one
billion bushels of the golden grain. Corn production
in the Canadian Great Plains is more
limited because corn is not well adapted to the
cooler and shorter growing seasons there. In
1997 Manitoba produced about 60,000 acres
of corn for grain, with a total production
of about six million bushels. Corn production
in Alberta and Saskatchewan is even less extensive.
Corn production is also limited in
the dry western Plains states of New Mexico,
Wyoming, and Montana.</p>

<p>Corn produced in the Great Plains, like that
of the rest of the U.S. Corn Belt, is used in
many ways. The majority of the crop is used
as a feed grain for livestock and poultry production.
About 20 percent of the grain is exported
to other countries around the world.
The remainder of the corn produced in the
Great Plains is processed into various food
and industrial products such as ethanol fuel,
high fructose syrup, food grade and industrial
starches, and human foodstuffs.</p>

<p>Many of the factors that influence the production
of corn vary dramatically throughout
the Great Plains. Because of the extensive
north-south orientation of the Great Plains,
one of the most variable factors is the length
and warmth of the available growing season.
Corn planting can begin in March in the
warmer areas of the Southern Great Plains,
while significant corn planting efforts do not
typically begin in the Northern Great Plains
until early May because of cooler temperatures.
Harvesting of corn for grain typically
begins as early as late August in Texas and as
late as October in North Dakota. At first
glance, the early harvest times in Texas seem
odd in that much of the available growing season
is not used. However, planting date and
hybrid selection are managed by corn producers
to avoid the occurrence of the critical
corn pollination stage during the hottest,
most stressful times of midsummer. Consequently,
corn pollination in Texas occurs in
mid- to late June rather than the relatively
hotter late July to early August period.</p>

<p>The second major effect of differing growing
season lengths is on the adaptability of
corn hybrid maturities. Producers in the
Southern Great Plains can grow corn hybrids
with a much longer maturity cycle than those
in the Northern Great Plains. Compared to
hybrids that require less time to mature, the
long season hybrids typically have greater
yield potential, are taller and leafier plants,
and have greater tolerance to disease and insect
stress.</p>

<p>Seasonal rainfall varies more from east to
west than from north to south across the
Great Plains, with the majority of the Great
Plains area rainfall patterns generally unable
to supply the twenty to twenty-five inches of
water required to produce a corn crop. Consequently,
irrigation is a very important crop
management technology and tool for corn
production throughout the Great Plains.
More than 50 percent of the harvested acreage
and 65 percent of the total grain production in
the Great Plains is produced under irrigation.
In fact, only the Dakotas do not produce a
major share of their corn under irrigation.
The impact of irrigation on corn grain yields
is dramatic for the whole region (157 versus 75
bushels per acre, irrigated versus dryland),
but especially so for Colorado, Texas, and New
Mexico, where dryland corn grain yields average
less than 30 percent that of irrigated corn.</p>



<closer>
<signed>R. L. Nielsen</signed>
Purdue University</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Hardeman, Nicholas P. <title level="m">Shucks, Shocks, and Hominy
Blocks</title>. Baton Rouge: Louisiana State University Press,
1981.</bibl> <bibl>Sprague, G. F., and J. W. Dudley, eds. <title level="m">Corn and Corn
Improvement</title>. Madison, WI: American Society of Agronomy, Monograph 18: 1988.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>