<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.na.116">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Tonkawas</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Thomas F. Schilz</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.na.116</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Schilz, Thomas F.">Thomas F. Schilz</author>. <title level="a">"Tonkawas."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">606</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-20</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">TONKAWAS</head>

<p>The Tonkawas were a combination of a number
of independent bands. The name "Tonkawa"
translates as "they all stay together."
From at least the eleventh century until their
removal to a reservation in Indian Territory
in 1884, the Tonkawas occupied the pin oak
prairie and grassland that stretched from the
Llano River in central Texas to the Canadian
River in Oklahoma.</p>

<p>The Tonkawas, who numbered several thousand
before contact with Europeans, were led
by a selected tribal chief. Maternal clans were
the basic societal unit, with children becoming
members of the mother's clan and the husband
living with his wife's clan. The Tonkawas subsisted
by hunting bison and other game and by
gathering a wide variety of wild fruits, roots,
and nuts. Unlike most other Plains Indians,
they also ate fish and shellfish. They practiced
agriculture, unsuccessfully, and only when the
elimination of the bison drove them to it. Their
traditional homes were short tipis made of
bison hides. When this resource was no longer
available, in the second half of the nineteenth
century, they lived in tipilike structures made
of brush and grass, and later in flat huts roofed
with brush. The Tonkawa language is thought
to be unrelated to any other Native American
language.</p>

<p>The Tonkawas initially came in contact with
Spanish explorers in the sixteenth century.
They came into permanent association with
European settlers in 1722, when Juan Rodriguez,
the chief of the southern Tonkawas (Ervipiames),
demanded and received a mission,
San Francisco Xavier de Najera, at San Antonio
de Bejar in Texas. Although the Ervipiames
and their allies never settled at San Antonio's
missions in any numbers, the Tonkawas began
to interact with the Spaniards as allies against
the Lipan Apaches and Comanches. But Spain
saw the advantages of Comanche friendship at
the expense of the weaker Tonkawas, and by the
1770s the Tonkawas were left to make a place for
themselves on the borderland between the Comanches
and the Europeans. Under a chief
named El Mocho they aligned themselves with
the Lipans and Bidais. While successfully fending
off Spanish and Comanche attacks, they
moved closer to the forests of East Texas and
absorbed the remnants of the Karankawas, a
coastal tribe.</p>

<p>By 1821, when Stephen F. Austin's colonists
arrived on the Brazos River, the Tonkawas
were in need of powerful allies. They offered
to serve the American settlers as scouts and
fighters. Throughout the years of the Austin
Colony, the Texas Revolution, and into the decade
of Texas's independence, the Tonkawas
served loyally as auxiliaries to the military arm
of Anglo Texas in its battles with Iscanis (a
subtribe of the Wichitas) and Comanches.
Their reward, after the United States had annexed
Texas, was to be removed to a reservation
on the Clear Fork of the Brazos in 1856, a
time when Texans were demanding that all
Indians be exiled from the soil of the state. In
1859 the Tonkawas were removed to Fort Cobb
on the Washita River in Indian Territory, along
with the other tribes of the Texas frontier.</p>

<p>Old enmities died hard, however, as did
old friendships. Tonkawas continued to help
United States and Texas troops fight the Comanches.
With the outbreak of the Civil War,
the Tonkawas sided with the Texans, while
most Indians at Fort Cobb favored the Union.
On October 24, 1862, pro-Union Indians attacked
the Tonkawas, killing half the tribe and
driving the survivors back into Texas, where
Confederate authorities provided them with
food and clothing and enlisted them as scouts
on the frontier.</p>

<p>When the Civil War ended, the relentless
push of Americans westward into Comanche
country once again provided the Tonkawas
with employment. Enlisted by the U.S. Army
as scouts, they were settled at Fort Griffin in
north-central Texas and employed continually
until the Comanche defeat in 1878. Tonkawa
scouts distinguished themselves in every major
action of the post-Civil War era in Texas.
When the Comanches and their allies had
been confined to a reservation, the Tonkawas
expected to be rewarded for their long service
to the United States. Instead Fort Griffin was
abandoned in 1881 and the Tonkawas' funds
were cut off. For three years the tribe survived
mostly on rations, until they were forcibly removed
to lands abandoned by Chief Joseph's
Nez Perces near the present-day town of Tonkawa,
in Kay County, Oklahoma. In 1896 their
reservation was allotted, and their land base
was further reduced. They now hold 399 acres
of land. Their population plummeted to 34 in
1921, then began a slow revival to 43 in 1936
and 186 in 1993.</p>

<p>In recent years Tonkawas have developed an
interest in their past and their role in Texas
settlement. A powwow in Austin and local
gatherings in Oklahoma have served to create
a renewed interest in a people who are among
the original settlers of what is now Texas and
the most loyal of American allies.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Thomas F. Schilz</signed>
San Diego Miramar College</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Carlisle, Jeffery D. "Tonkawa Indians." In <title level="m">The New Handbook
of Texas</title>, edited by Ron Tyler, 6:525-26. Austin: Texas
State Historical Association, 1996.</bibl> <bibl>Smithwick, Noah. <title level="m">The
Evolution of a State, or Recollections of Old Texas Days</title>.
Austin: Gammel Book Co., 1900.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>