<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.na.005">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Arapahos</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Loretta Fowler</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.na.005</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Fowler, Loretta">Loretta Fowler</author>. <title level="a">"Arapahos."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">562-563</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-03</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">ARAPAHOS</head>

<p>Arapahos referred to themselves as Hinanaeina
(<hi rend="italic">hinono'eino</hi>), or "The People." Trappers
and traders in the early nineteenth century
used the Crow name for Arapahos,
<hi rend="italic">Alappaho</hi> (Many Tattoos), and Arapahos began
referring to themselves by that term in
their dealings with Americans. Five dialects of
Arapaho (an Algonquian language) existed in
historical times and correlated with tribal divisions:
Hinanaeina (Arapaho); Hitounena
(Gros Ventre); and three others, the speakers
of which presumably became absorbed by the
other divisions.</p>

<p>Arapahos entered the Northern Plains at
least by the early eighteenth century, probably
from the northeast. The Gros Ventre division
remained in the far Northern Plains, while
Arapahos moved in a southerly direction.
Wealthy in horses, probably since the 1740s,
Arapahos ranged from the headwaters of the
Missouri to the Platte River, and west as far as
the foothills of the Rocky Mountains. By 1806
they allied with Cheyennes, largely to counter
the westward movement of the Sioux (Lakota).
With the Cheyennes, they drove the
Kiowas and Comanches south of the Arkansas
River by 1826 and controlled the region between
the Platte and Arkansas Rivers. In 1835,
diminished by smallpox, they numbered an
estimated 3,600.</p>

<p>Arapahos relied on bison for food, clothing,
and many other necessities. In the 1830s and
1840s they hunted in the Estes Park area of
Colorado (especially the region of the Cache la
Poudre River) and the adjacent Plains to the
east, which they recognized as their exclusive
territory. Men hunted and women dried the
meat, collected and dried roots and berries,
dressed hides, and made tipi covers, clothing,
and containers. The quilled, painted, and, by
the nineteenth century, beaded designs applied
on hide by women represented prayers for the
well being of a relative. After 1857 settlers and
miners moved into the Parks area of presentday
Colorado, driving off the bison, so that the
Arapahos had to hunt more regularly on the
open plains east of the Rockies.</p>

<p>Most of the year, Arapahos lived in bands
that moved together when large camps were
formed or disbanded and affiliated with one
of the several named subdivisions of the Hinanaeina,
but individuals and households
could move from one band to another. Kinship
was reckoned on the basis of bilateral
descent, although other individuals could
be absorbed into kindred by means of "adoption."
Arapahos married outside their group
of kindred and legalized marriage by gift
exchange between the bride's and groom's
families.</p>

<p>The Arapaho origin story focuses on Pipe
Person's creation of the earth from mud below
the surface of an expanse of water. Pipe Person,
through prayer-thought, created all life,
including the first Arapahos. Arapahos henceforth
kept a replica of the Flat Pipe as a symbol
of their covenant with the life force or power
on which Pipe Person drew. Rites centered on
the pipe bundle helped ensure the success of
Arapahos generally and of individuals specifically.
Seven men's and seven women's medicine
bags contained objects and implements
that symbolized forms of power, and these
passed from one custodian to another. Prayerthoughts
could affect events and lives, and the
sincerity of a petitioner's prayer-thought was
validated by sacrifices of property or of the
body by flesh offerings and fasting. In the major
tribal ritual, the Offerings Lodge (also
known as the Sun Dance), a petitioner vowed
to participate (that is, make a sacrifice) in the
ceremony in return for supernatural aid. Individuals
also acquired supernatural aid by
dreaming or fasting for a vision encounter
with a supernatural being. During the early
nineteenth century, many of the men's vision
fasts were on various peaks in Estes Park, Colorado.
Women usually received power in a
dream or from a husband or parent.</p>

<p>A governing council and an age-graded series
of societies, supervised by the elderly
custodians of the medicine bundle, comprised
the tribal government. Initiation into each society was precipitated by a religious vow; the
age mates of the votary went through the ceremony
as a group. Wives were considered to
progress through the men's societies with their
husbands. These men's groups performed political
duties, including keeping order in the
camp and supervising the communal hunts.
The governing council in the nineteenth century
consisted of four leaders representing
four tribal subdivisions, the medicine bundle
custodians, and the leaders of the men's societies.
Beginning in the 1840s "chiefs" served
as intermediaries between the governing council
and federal officials.</p>

<p>The Arapahos prospered from trading bison
robes to Americans in the 1830s, but beginning
in the 1840s, American expansion westward
disturbed the bison herds. The United
States initiated treaty councils, first to prevent
troubles along the immigrant routes and later
to remove Plains peoples from areas where
Americans wanted to settle. In 1851 the Arapahos
signed a peace treaty that guaranteed that
settlers would not trespass on the tribe's lands
in Wyoming and Colorado. Settlers and miners
violated the treaty, with little opposition
from the federal government, which led to
trouble with the Arapahos and Cheyennes. In
1864 Colorado militia massacred a Cheyenne
and Arapaho camp at Sand Creek, provoking a
two-year war and resulting in the separation of
Arapaho bands into politically independent
northern and southern divisions. In 1867 the
Southern Arapahos, led by Little Raven, signed
the Treaty of Medicine Lodge Creek, ending
hostilities. In 1868 the Northern Arapahos,
having fought for several years to hold onto the
bison range in Wyoming and Montana, signed
a treaty under Medicine Man's leadership and
agreed to settle on a reservation. Intermediary
chiefs negotiated with officials during subsequent
months, and in 1869 President Ulysses S.
Grant created by executive order a reservation
for Southern Arapahos and Cheyennes in Indian
Territory (later Oklahoma). In 1878 Northern
Arapahos obtained permission to settle on
the Shoshone reservation in Wyoming.</p>

<p>When they moved to their reservations, the
Southern Arapahos numbered about 1,200
and the Northern Arapahos, 1,000. The Southern
branch continued to hunt bison until 1878,
when game became scarce. During the 1880s
Arapahos on both reservations depended for
subsistence on the supplies issued by the federal
government and disbursed by band leaders,
the most important of whom were Black
Coal and Sharp Nose in Wyoming and Powderface,
Left Hand, and Yellow Bear in Oklahoma.
Leaders also organized communal agricultural
labor on both reservations and freighting and
livestock raising in Oklahoma. The reservation
in Oklahoma was divided into individually
owned allotments of land in 1892, and unallotted
lands were sold to non-Indians. In Wyoming,
allotment occurred in 1901, but the unallotted
lands were in an area undesirable for
farming, and consequently these lands were
never sold. In Oklahoma, the federal government
facilitated the sale of most of the allotments
over the years, while in Wyoming oil was
discovered on the tribally owned unallotted
lands. Since 1940 all Northern Arapahos have
received monthly per capita payments from
mineral royalties and bonuses, which have
helped to alleviate poverty and have kept land
sales to a minimum.</p>

<p>Both the Oklahoma and Wyoming Arapahos
had intermediary chiefs until the third decade
of the twentieth century. These chiefs
worked to defend the treaty rights of their respective
tribes. When the federal government
encouraged the formation of elective, representative,
and constitutional government, Oklahoma
Arapahos instituted a "business committee."
Wyoming Arapahos rejected the idea
of constitutional government, but adopted an
elective, representational "business council."
In both cases, traditional ideals of leadership
became incorporated into the new form of
tribal government. Federal programs that created
jobs, scholarships, housing, and other
kinds of development were introduced, beginning
in the 1960s, and these strengthened the
role of tribal government. In the late 1990s
the population of Arapahos in Oklahoma was
about 4,000, in Wyoming at that time there
were about 4,400 Arapahos&#821;half of whom live
within the boundaries or former boundaries
of the reservation. Enrollment in the Northern
or Southern Arapaho tribes is contingent on
having at least 25 percent Arapaho ancestry;
most have more than 25 percent.</p>

<p>The O'erings Lodge continued in Oklahoma
until 1939, and thereafter Arapahos
took it to Wyoming, where the ceremony continues
today, as does the Sacred Pipe ritual.
The Ghost Dance movement was important
in the 1890s and, in revised form, in the early
twentieth century in both the Oklahoma and
Wyoming communities. Peyote ritual was introduced
to the Southern Arapahos by Plains
Apaches in the 1890s and then transferred to
the Wyoming Arapahos; the Native American
Church continues to be important in both
communities. Mennonite and Baptist missionaries
introduced Christianity in Oklahoma,
and Catholic and Episcopal missionaries
in Wyoming. Generally, the practice of
Native religion and Christianity are not mutually
exclusive. Since the 1970s there has been
an elaboration of "traditional" religious and
social ritual in both the Oklahoma and Wyoming
communities.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">WAR</hi>: <ref n="egp.war.039">Sand Creek Massacre</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Loretta Fowler<lb/>
University of Oklahoma</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Fowler, Loretta. <title level="m">The Arapaho</title>. New York: Chelsea House
Publishers, 1989.</bibl> <bibl>Fowler, Loretta. <title level="m">Arapahoe Politics, 1851– 1978: Symbols in Crises of Authority</title>. Lincoln: University of
Nebraska Press, 1982.</bibl> <bibl>Kroeber, Alfred L. <title level="m">The Arapaho</title>. Bulletin
of the American Museum of Natural History, vol. 18
(New York, 1902–7).</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>