<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.fil.049 SYSTEM "egp.fil.049.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fil.049">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Movie Houses</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Andy Wilkinson</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fil.049</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Wilkinson, Andy">Andy Wilkinson</author>. <title level="a">"Movie Houses."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">274</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-12</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">MOVIE HOUSES</head>

<figure n="egp.fil.049" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Blair Theatre, Belleville, Kansas</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>The first regular cinema opened in Pittsburgh,
Pennsylvania, in 1905. Movie houses began
appearing in the Great Plains shortly thereafter;
for example, the newly incorporated town
of Lubbock, Texas, boasted its first movie
house, the Orpheum, in 1909. By World War I
movie houses were common fixtures in communities
across the Plains.</p>

<p>As in the rest of the nation, movie houses
provided entertainment for Plains folk, that is,
when proprietors could get films. Early newspaper
ads promised nightly shows during the
week and matinees on Saturday, tempered
with the caveat "when available." Nevertheless,
even irregular movie schedules provided
substantially more entertainment than other
sources. Radio would not be widespread on
the Plains for another two decades, television
for another four. Though many small communities
had an opera house, which mostly
hosted musicals and drama and variety shows,
regular performances were difficult to support,
and traveling companies&#8211;tent shows
and circuses&#8211;came to town no more than
once or twice a year.</p>

<p>Besides, the movies provided a different
kind of entertainment, and that difference was
important to the isolated peoples of the Plains.
First, the occasion of seeing a movie was a
social event in and of itself, a time and place
to visit with widely scattered neighbors and
friends. But while the movie house was a great
place to socialize, Plains folk also found there
satisfaction for their staunch independence,
that collective character trait that more than
any other marks this peculiar American tribe.
In the anonymous darkness of the theater, separated
by armrests, with all eyes turned toward
the images flickering on the screen, moviegoers
could escape to a bigger world, a world of
their own choosing. Unlike the traveling shows
and local stage offerings, which catered to narrow
regional tastes and attitudes, motion pictures
were crafted for a wide audience. There
were new and novel sights and new and novel
ideas. In the movie house, the warm smell
of buttered popcorn and the soft mechanical
purr of the projector meant magic. If it was
hard to keep 'em down on the farm after
they'd seen Paree, it was harder still when
Paris, and London and Rome and New York,
could be seen almost anytime without leaving
the county, and for little more than a dime.</p>

<p>But because motion pictures came along at
roughly the same time that settlements were
still appearing on parts of the Plains, movie
houses also had a practical side. Early on,
they provided much-needed facilities for public
use, with local governments, churches,
schools, and civic clubs all relying upon them
for meeting space. Soon they became important
to the local economy, bringing people to
town, then giving them something to do when
they got there. Before long, a nice, modern
movie house became a necessity to chambers
of commerce and other community boosters.
Rounding out the practical side of things,
movie newsreels were an important source for
national and international news until television
made them obsolete.</p>

<p>Movie houses retained their central place in
Great Plains communities, both large and
small, through the Dust Bowl, the Great Depression,
and two world wars. In the cities,
they remain today in roughly the same
numbers. In Lubbock, for instance, the number
of inhabitants per movie screen&#8211;a not-so-
scientific but commonsense yardstick&#8211;has
stayed consistently between 3,000 and 4,000
over the past ninety years.</p>

<p>That said, movie houses themselves have all
but disappeared. The newsreels are gone. And
if the movies themselves still serve Plains peoples,
that service is offered in the sterility of
the modern multiscreen cinema or the isolation
of the television set. In the cities, small
neighborhood theaters have been replaced by
large multiscreen facilities. Outside the cities,
movie theaters of any kind are rare. Too many
people have moved away, and those who remain
rent videotapes and purchase satellite
receivers.</p>

<p>Yet the movie house isn't quite dead. In
Lubbock there's the Cactus; in Claude, Texas,
the Gem, which was featured in the movie
<title>Hud</title>; in Dalhart, Texas, it's the La Rita; and in
McCook, Nebraska, the Fox. In communities
across the Plains, large and small, old theaters
are being renovated and put back to use,
though not for the showing of motion pictures.
Instead, they're providing venues for
plays and concerts and other live performances,
and, once again, bragging rights for
their towns. Even the Royal Theater, the subject
of Larry McMurtry's <title>The Last Picture Show</title>, is being rebuilt as an arts center for the
town of Archer City, Texas. Perhaps there's
some magic still.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Andy Wilkinson<lb/>
Lubbock, Texas</signed>
</closer>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>