<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.na.082">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Pawnees</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>David J. Wishart</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.na.082</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</author>. <title level="a">"Pawnees."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">590-591</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-15</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">PAWNEES</head>

<p>Unlike many Plains Indians, who moved into
the area relatively recently, the Pawnees are
longtime residents of the Great Plains. Linguistic
and archeological evidence indicates
that the Pawnees, specifically the Skiri band,
have roots in central Nebraska extending back
at least as far as the sixteenth century, and
perhaps even further to the Upper Republican
peoples who occupied villages along the Republican
and Loup Rivers from 1100 <hi rend="smallcaps">A.D.</hi>
to 1400 <hi rend="smallcaps">A.D.</hi> This stock was subsequently
reinforced by recurrent migrations of other
Caddoan-speaking bands from the Southern
Great Plains during the seventeenth and eighteenth
centuries. The Pawnees' own traditions
speak of an origin in the southwestern United
States, then a slow migration north, leaving
their relatives, the Wichitas, on the Southern
Plains. Linguistic analysis suggests that this
split occurred in the first few centuries <hi rend="smallcaps">A.D.</hi></p>

<p>By 1800 the Pawnee were a loose confederation
of four bands&#8211;the Skiris (Loups), Chauis
(Grands), Kitkahahkis (Republicans), and
Pitahawiratas (Tappages). Their combined
population, according to Lewis and Clark, was
6,850. The Skiris lived in a large village (twenty
to forty acres in extent) on a terrace of the
Loup River near present-day Palmer, Nebraska;
the Chauis occupied two villages on
the south side of the Platte River near Bellwood
and Linwood; and the Kitkahahkis lived
to the south on the Republican River between
Red Cloud and Guide Rock. By 1811, under
pressure from the Kanzas, the Kitkahahkis
moved north to the Loup. The location of the
Pitahawirata village, if indeed it was separate
from the Chaui sites, is unknown.</p>

<p>Each band was largely independent of the
others, with its own chiefs, priests, and ceremonies.
The Skiris, especially, maintained
an independent stance from the other three
bands. The identity of each band was encapsulated
in their village bundles, the bison hide
packs which contained sacred icons and which
represented the peoples' original charter with
the gods. Every step in the year's cycle of activities
was sanctified by the bundles.</p>

<p>The traditional annual cycle of the Pawnees
began in April when the first thunder from the
south announced that it was time to clear the
fields for cultivation. Corn, beans, squash, and
sunflowers were planted by the women along
the river floodplains. In late June, when the
crops were well established, the Pawnees left
for their summer bison hunt. They returned to
the villages in late August and harvested and
stored their crops. In early November they
again abandoned their villages for the bison
range, where they remained until March,
hunting and camping on the upper reaches of
the Republican, Smokey Hill, Solomon, and
Platte Rivers. The bison hunts not only provided
meat and most of the Indians' raw materials
but also allowed the Pawnees and their
horses (of which there were 6,000 in 1806) to
spread their subsistence base over an extensive
area. This annual cycle was a successful adaptation
to the transitional environment of the
Great Plains, and in most years the Pawnees
produced a food surplus and flourished as the
dominant power in the Central Plains.</p>

<p>In the nineteenth century the traditional
lifestyle of the Pawnees was seriously disrupted
by war and disease. Their population
in 1800 was already only a fraction of the
15,000 or 20,000 people the villages had sustained
in previous years. Smallpox struck in
1798, then again in 1830–31, taking at least half
the population in one winter. After each epidemic,
the Pawnees partly recovered, but after
1831 diseases struck with increased frequency
and the population went on a downward spiral
that was reversed only after 1906.</p>

<p>Also, after 1831 the Pawnee found themselves
caught in a vise, pressed by the Lakotas
from the north and by the expanding American
frontier to the east. From that time until
their departure from Nebraska in 1876, they
lived under the shadow of attack. Hunts and
harvests were disrupted, food supplies became
more precarious, and death rates soared. In
the 1840s, mounting tra.c along the Oregon
Trail led to the depletion of timber and grass,
and the bison were driven west beyond the
forks of the Platte. By 1854, when Nebraska
Territory was opened to settlers, the Pawnees
were a beleaguered people.</p>

<p>Traditionally, the territory occupied and
claimed by the Pawnees reached from the Niobrara
to the Arkansas and Cimarron Rivers.
The southern part of this territory was sold to
the United States in 1833, and subsequent cessions
left the Pawnees with only a small reservation,
later Nance County, Nebraska, on the
Loup River. There, between 1857 and 1876, their
population dropped to fewer than 2,000 people,
and settlers increasingly hemmed in their
lives. In the early 1870s a series of disasters,
including a massacre by the Lakotas in southwestern
Nebraska in 1873 and the destruction
of the crops by drought and grasshoppers, persuaded
the Pawnees to relinquish their reservation
and take up residency near the Wichitas in
Indian Territory.</p>

<p>The migration south and subsequent problems
of adjusting to the new homeland resulted
in further population decline, the nadir being
reached in 1906 when only 650 Pawnees remained.
In 1892 the Pawnees accepted individual
allotments, and the remainder of their
reservation was sold to settlers. The Pawnees
were given $30,000 a year for this land. Many of
their traditions were forgotten, and ceremonies
lapsed. Their culture was resilient, however, and
their rich traditions were preserved in the early
twentieth century by James Murie, a member of
the Skiri band. In 1936 the Pawnees gained tribal
government recognition under the Oklahoma
Indian Welfare Act. Their identity was further
reinforced by lengthy and successful claims-case
litigation before the Indian Claims Commission
from 1946 to 1962. The Pawnees were eventually
awarded $7,316,096 for lands in Nebraska and
Oklahoma that had been taken from them for
an "unconscionably" low payment in the nineteenth
century.</p>

<p>In the late twentieth century the Pawnee
population numbered nearly 2,400, most of
whom lived around the headquarters of the
tribal council in Pawnee, Oklahoma. The tribe
owned 726 acres, and another 19,399 acres was
allotted to individuals. Unemployment stood
at 25 percent. The Pawnees are governed by a
council consisting of a president, vice president,
and five council members.</p>

<closer>
<signed>David J. Wishart</signed>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Blaine, Martha Royce. <title level="m">Pawnee Passage: 1870–1875</title>. Norman:
University of Oklahoma Press, 1990.</bibl> <bibl>Weltfish, Gene.
<title level="m">The Lost Universe: Pawnee Life and Culture</title>. Lincoln: University
of Nebraska Press, 1977.</bibl> <bibl>Wishart, David J. <title level="m">An Unspeakable
Sadness: The Dispossession of the Nebraska Indians</title>.
Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1994.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>