<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.pg.043">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Louisiana Purchase</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Mark R. Ellis</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.pg.043</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Ellis, Mark R.">Mark R. Ellis</author>. <title level="a">"Louisiana Purchase."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">673</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-30</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">LOUISIANA PURCHASE</head>

<p>Purchased in 1803 from France for $15 million
&#8211;about four cents per acre&#8211;the Louisiana
Purchase added much of the Great Plains to
the United States, set the stage for expansion
to the Pacific Ocean, and set in motion sectional
conflicts over slavery that led to the
Civil War.</p>

<p>The territory of Louisiana comprised a significant
region of the interior of North America.
Its borders were the Mississippi River on
the east, the Rocky Mountains on the west, and
the Spanish territories of Texas and New Mexico
on the south, but the northern border was
never clearly defined (although it roughly followed
the forty-ninth parallel). Louisiana Territory&#8211;
under French, Spanish, and American
possession&#8211;was mainly occupied by Native
American peoples until the 1850s. European
settlement was limited to river towns (for example,
New Orleans and St. Louis) and trading
posts along the Mississippi and Missouri
Rivers. Until 1763 France controlled most of
Louisiana Territory, although Spain intruded
on several occasions, including the 1720 Pedro
de Villazur expedition into present-day Nebraska.
France transferred Louisiana to Spain
in 1763 after being defeated in the French and
Indian War (Seven Years War in Europe). By the
early 1790s the fledgling United States, which
was expanding westward toward the Mississippi,
relied on the river and the port of New
Orleans as an outlet for trans-Appalachian produce.
A 1795 treaty with Spain guaranteed
Americans access to New Orleans, but by 1801
that privilege was threatened when Spain gave
Louisiana back to France. Napoleon hoped to
use Louisiana as a base to reestablish its colonial
empire in the Caribbean and possibly in North
America.</p>

<p>Fearing that access to New Orleans might be
blocked by the French presence, President
Thomas Jefferson sought to buy or negotiate
access to a Mississippi port. In January of 1803
James Monroe traveled to Paris with instructions
to offer $2 million for New Orleans and
West Florida. Fortunately for the United States,
their offer came on the heels of French setbacks
in the Caribbean (malaria and yellow fever had
ravaged the French military) and the threat
of war with England. Fearing that Louisiana
would be lost to a British-American alliance,
and in need of money to launch further military
campaigns, Napoleon ordered his minister
to sell all of Louisiana to the American negotiators.
The agreed-upon price, $15 million
($11,250,000 for Louisiana and $3,750,000 for
American civilian claims against France), gave
the United States approximately 828,000 square
miles of territory, nearly doubling the land base
of the nation. The Senate approved the deal on
October 20, 1803.</p>

<p>Exactly what the United States had purchased
remained unclear. When asked by Monroe
about the boundaries, the French foreign minister
responded: "You have made a noble bargain
for yourselves, and I suppose you will make the
most of it." The Lewis and Clark expedition
(1804-6) did just that. The expedition, which
wintered near the mouth of the Columbia River
in 1805-6, pushed the boundaries of Louisiana
beyond the Rocky Mountains to the Pacific
Ocean, giving the United States a claim to Oregon.
The southern boundary was more difficult
to discern, because Spain occupied neighboring
Texas and New Mexico. The Adams-Onis Treaty
of 1819 finally set the southern boundary at the
western bank of the Sabine, Red, and Arkansas
Rivers.</p>

<p>The Louisiana Purchase eventually added
thirteen states to the nation and brought the
Great Plains&#8211;America's future breadbasket&#8211;
into the nation. The purchase also had unforeseen
consequences as it sowed the seeds of sectionalism
over the expansion of slavery.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Mark R. Ellis<lb/>
University of Nebraska at Kearney</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>DeConde, Alexander. <title level="m">This Affair of Louisiana</title>. New York:
Scribner, 1976.</bibl> <bibl>Hermann, Binger. <title level="m">The Louisiana Purchase</title>.
Washington <hi rend="smallcaps">DC</hi>: Government Printing Office, 1898.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>