<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ct.010">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Casper, Wyoming</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Jerry E. Nelson</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ct.010</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Nelson, Jerry E.">Jerry E. Nelson</author>. <title level="a">"Casper, Wyoming."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">161-162</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-22</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">CASPER, WYOMING</head>

<p>Casper sits at several crossroads, literally and
figuratively. From its origins as a trading and
army post at a ford on the North Platte River, it
has grown into a modern city of about 50,000
people. Located at an elevation of about one
mile above sea level, Casper stretches out along
the river and is growing toward the base of
8,000-foot Casper Mountain to the south of
the city.</p>

<p>Casper is at a geological crossroads, sitting
on the Casper Arch, which separates
the Powder River Basin from the Wind River
Basin. This is a low saddle in the Rocky Mountains
that continues to provide a natural topographic
funnel for travelers heading west.
Long before European Americans settled the
area, Native Americans traveled through the
region on their way from the Great Plains
to the mountains and basins of the Middle
Rocky Mountains. The attraction then as now
was the ease of travel provided by the broad
basins and the abundant local resources, especially
water. The first permanent occupation
was a bridge and trading post built by Louis
Guinart in 1859 to provide support and a river
crossing for travelers on the Oregon, California,
Mormon, Pioneer, and Pony Express
Trails and access to the nearby Bridger and
Bozeman Trails. Casper is still a crossroads,
the point of connection for Interstate 25, U.S.
20 and U.S. 26, and Wyoming 220.</p>

<p>Casper is also at a crossroads economically,
struggling with the transition from the boom-and-
bust cycles of the petroleum and minerals
(coal, uranium, trona, bentonite, and clay) industries
to a rapidly developing service and
manufacturing economy. The city is a regional
service center for central Wyoming. The Wyoming
Medical Center provides sophisticated
medical care for the region. Casper College,
a comprehensive community college, and the
University of Wyoming Upper Division Center
combine their resources to provide an everexpanding
number of educational opportunities.
Medical, legal, banking, and recreational
services, along with retail sales and light manufacturing,
are slowly replacing petroleum
and minerals as the economic base. In 1999 the
service sector accounted for almost 30 percent
of total employment, having increased its
share by almost one third over the decade,
while mining employment (including oil and
gas) stood at barely 7 percent of the total and
had declined by almost 10 percent during the
1990s. Oil, gas, and minerals continue to be an
important part of the economic picture, but it
is apparent from the lack of impact on Casper
of the current coal bed methane boom that
Casper can no longer be considered a petroleum
and minerals boomtown.</p>

<p>The culture of Casper is very much like the
culture of many western towns, with one foot
firmly planted in the Old West and one stepping
toward the New West. Wingtips and cowboy
boots mingle together at local watering
holes, tapping in rhythm to both country
western and rock. Nothing illustrates Casper's
position at the cultural and economic crossroads
better than the following juxtaposition.
Casper is now the host city for the College
National Finals Rodeo, which each year in June
fills the town with cowboys and cowgirls from
around the nation. Contrast that Old West picture
with the high technology, New West scene
created by a crowd of locals who recently
gathered on a sage-covered dune just north of
town to witness the test firing of Wickman
Aerospace's latest rocket engine for <hi rend="smallcaps">NASA</hi>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Jerry E. Nelson<lb/>
Casper College</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Casper Zonata Club. <title level="m">Casper Chronicles</title>. Casper <hi rend="smallcaps">WY</hi>: Casper
Zonata Club, 1964.</bibl> <bibl>Mead, Jean. <title level="m">Casper Country: Wyoming's Heartland</title>. Boulder <hi rend="smallcaps">CO</hi>: Pruett Publishing Company,
1987.</bibl>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>