<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.arc.051">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Ukranian Architecture</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>John C. Lehr</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.arc.051</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Lehr, John C.">John C. Lehr</author>. <title level="a">"Ukranian Architecture."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">98-99</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-14</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">UKRANIAN ARCHITECTURE</head>

<p>Ukrainian immigrants, mostly peasants from
eastern Galicia and northern Bukovyna in
western Ukraine, settled large areas of the Canadian
Plains from 1892 to 1914. Almost all
came to North America to seek free 160-acre
homesteads in the "bush country" of the aspen
Parkland Belt in Canada's Prairie Provinces,
but some were also induced to settle in
the Belfield area of southwestern North Dakota
by American land agents. In Canada they
established a series of large, ethnically homogeneous
bloc settlements that stretched northwest
from southeast Manitoba, through central
Saskatchewan, into east-central Alberta.
The Dominion Lands Act of 1872, which governed
the disbursement of homesteads in
Canada, required that all applicants reside
upon their homestead for at least three years
before full title was granted. This made it
impossible for settlers to replicate the villages
they had known in Europe. Nevertheless,
chain migration created loose groupings
of settlers from the same villages or
regions, which encouraged perpetuation of
Old Country cultural traits in the newly settled
territories.</p>

<p>The first shelter built by a Ukrainian pioneer
was often a simple sod-roofed dugout,
called a <hi rend="italic">zemlyanka</hi> or <hi rend="italic">burdei</hi>, patterned on
the temporary shelters used by shepherds
in the Carpathian Mountains of western
Ukraine. These dwellings provided shelter for
the first year or two until a more substantial
house could be built. The first true houses
showed considerable variation in style according
to the builder's region of origin but followed
a general pattern: a south-facing, twoor
three-roomed, single-story log house plastered
and lime washed on the exterior with a
low, overhanging, hip or hipped-gable roof
and a central chimney. This type of house predominated
in Ukrainian rural districts until
the late 1930s. Abandoned examples may still
be seen, and some modernized versions are
still in use.</p>

<p>The aspen parkland provided an array of
building materials similar to those of the western Ukraine. Aspen, poplar, birch, tamarack,
and spruce were all used in place of the hardwoods
of Europe. Slough grass was commonly
used as an acceptable substitute for rye straw
in thatching. Other materials remained unchanged:
clay, fieldstones, chopped straw,
lime, and horse or cow dung.</p>

<p>Log construction was the norm in the homeland
and in North America, although where
Ukrainians settled in timber-scarce areas
wattle-and-daub construction was sometimes
employed. Three methods of log building were
used: horizontally laid logs, post and fill, and
vertical logs. The diameter of available timber
determined the method used. In areas with
mature stands of spruce, logs were squared and
corners dovetailed. Generally, poplar logs were
merely scaled and corners saddle notched.
Where mature timber was more scarce, post
and fill was used: load-bearing vertical logs
were mortised, and short, small-diameter, or
misshapen logs were slotted in as fill. In a few
areas where fire had destroyed all good building
timber, walls were made of small-diameter
logs placed vertically on a wood sill.</p>

<p>Generally, both interior and exterior walls
were plastered with a mix of clay, chopped
straw, and horse or cow dung. The plaster was
anchored to the wall either by pegs driven into
the logs or by a lattice of willow fixed into
place before the application of the mud plaster.
All plaster was invariably coated with a
white lime wash.</p>

<p>High, steeply pitched, thatched, hipped, or
hipped-gable roofs were most common in the
pioneer era. Wood shingles were introduced
in the 1920s. Roofs were then lowered and
changed to the gable form, but the pronounced
eave projection on all sides was
maintained. Settlers from Bukovyna commonly
extended the eave up to three feet at the
front, supporting it with ornate eave brackets
and four vertical posts to create an open
porch.</p>

<p>House dimensions varied but generally
were about twenty-six to thirty feet by twelve
to seventeen feet, with the ratio of the side to
the front about 1:1.8. Space was divided into
the west <hi rend="italic">mala khata</hi> (<hi rend="italic">little house</hi>) and the east
<hi rend="italic">velykha khata</hi> (big house). The front entrance
opened into the <hi rend="italic">mala khata</hi>. In early buildings,
this room, which was the center of daily
activities, housed the large clay stove (<hi rend="italic">pich</hi>)
with a wide sleeping shelf. These stoves were
quickly replaced by lighter and smaller castiron
store-bought stoves. The <hi rend="italic">velykha khata</hi>
was reserved for formal occasions. Icons were
placed along its east wall. A central hallway
was a common feature.</p>

<p>Construction of ancillary farm buildings
followed that of the house, though they were
more likely left without plaster or paint. Usually,
such buildings were arranged in the form
of a square, with the house forming one side.</p>

<p>Acculturation showed in second-generation
buildings, when two-story frame houses were
built that still retained the traditional floor
plan. In some small service centers, commercial
false fronts were grafted onto the gable
ends of traditional log buildings. Decor and
use of space within the house were the two
elements most resistant to acculturation; the
preference for blue and green as decorative
trim colors survived structural and stylistic
changes, as did the use of the east-facing wall
for placement of religious icons and, later,
family photographs.</p>

<p>Churches built by Ukrainian immigrants
during the pioneer era were invariably copies
of the vernacular church styles of the homeland.
Built by settlers from sometimes inexact
recollection, they imbued the new landscape
with a strong Slavic element. On occasion, the
ancient styles of the Carpathian mountain
churches were built, but the Russian Byzantine
style, which was then replacing the older
forms in the homeland, was more common.
Pioneer churches were distinguished by their
separate bell towers, log construction, and adherence
to homeland regional styles. Ornate
pear-shaped <hi rend="italic">banyas</hi> (Byzantine domes) were
sometimes added to early buildings but were
more usually an integral feature of secondgeneration
churches built on a tripartite plan.
Architect-designed churches using balloonframe,
brick, or concrete construction did not
generally appear until the 1930s.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">EUROPEAN AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ea.037">Ukrainians</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>John C. Lehr<lb/>
University of Winnipeg</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Darlington, James W. "The Ukrainian Impress on the Canadian
West." In <title level="m">Canada's Ukrainians: Negotiating an Identity</title>, edited by Lubomyr Luciuk and Stella Hryniuk.
Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 1991: 53-80.</bibl> <bibl>Lehr,
John C. "Ukrainians in Western Canada." In <title level="m">To Build in a New Land</title>, edited by Allen G. Noble. Baltimore <hi rend="smallcaps">MD</hi>: Johns
Hopkins University Press, 1992: 309-30.</bibl> <bibl>Rotoff, Basil, Roman
Yereniuk, and Stella Hryniuk. <title level="m">Monuments to Faith: Ukrainian Churches in Manitoba</title>. Winnipeg: University of
Manitoba Press, 1990.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>