<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.war.036">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Red Cloud (1821-1909)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Robert W. Larson</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.war.036</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Larson, Robert W.">Robert W. Larson</author>. <title level="a">"Red Cloud (1821-1909)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">834</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-28</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">RED CLOUD (1821-1909)</head>
<figure n="egp.war.036" rend="granted" type="noclick">
<figDesc>Red Cloud (South Dakota State Historical Society)</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Lakota Sioux chief Red Cloud, regarded by
many historians as the most influential of the
Native American leaders living in the Great
Plains during the late nineteenth century, was
born on Blue Water Creek in May 1821 in what
is now Garden County, Nebraska. The creek, a
tributary of the North Platte River, was located
in a neutral hunting ground disputed by
the Lakotas and their hated rivals, the Pawnees.
Red Cloud's father, Lone Man, was a
Brul&#233;, one of the seven Lakota, or western
Sioux, tribes that migrated from the woodlands
of Minnesota to the Northern Plains
during the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries.
His mother, Walks-as-She-Thinks, was
an Oglala, another of the seven Lakota tribes.
When Lone Man died of alcoholism, a sad
result of the early commerce with white traders
and trappers, Red Cloud, along with his
brother and sister, went to live with his mother's
people, who were then under the leadership
of an Oglala chief named Smoke.</p>

<p>In 1834, when the Oglalas, led by the domineering
Sioux leader Bull Bear, were drawn
southward to the North Platte River valley by
the commercial possibilities of a trading post,
which later became Fort Laramie, Red Cloud,
a thirteen-year-old member of Smoke's band,
joined this important migration. For more
than two decades, Smoke's people frequently
encamped near Fort Laramie, allowing Red
Cloud to learn more about the ways of the
whites than most tribal leaders in the Great
Plains. Red Cloud also became a great warrior
during these years, killing his first enemy in
combat at the age of sixteen. As a result of his
participation in battles with enemy tribes,
such as the Crows, Pawnees, Utes, and Shoshones,
Red Cloud allegedly earned eighty
coups, a record never matched by any of his
tribal rivals.</p>

<p>Red Cloud became prominent in political
affairs when he got involved in a bitter brawl in
1841 that resulted in Bull Bear's death; in his
autobiography he took personal credit for firing
the fatal shot. He later gained the respect
and fear of whites, with whom he had been on
good terms, when he closed the Bozeman Trail
through Wyoming to prospectors heading
north to the Montana gold fields by engineering
the decisive Fetterman Fight on December
21, 1866. The aftermath of this battle and two
others from the so-called Red Cloud's War was
the Treaty of Fort Laramie in 1868. In this treaty
the Lakotas were assigned an enormous reservation
in Dakota Territory, and their hunting
territory in Wyoming's buffalo-rich Powder
River country was recognized as unceded. The
Lakotas subsequently lost the Black Hills in
1877, partly in retaliation for their victory in
the Battle of the Little Bighorn, and had their
reservation divided and drastically reduced in
size in 1889.</p>

<p>Red Cloud's influence in Lakota affairs,
which was dominant for a quarter of a century,
was diminished as a result of the Ghost Dance,
the chief ceremony of an Indian religious
movement Red Cloud eventually opposed, and
one that ultimately led to the Wounded Knee
Massacre on December 29, 1890. The venerable
leader died on the Pine Ridge Reservation in
South Dakota in 1909 at the age of eighty-eight.</p>

<p>Although Red Cloud has been accused of cruelty
in tribal warfare during his younger years
and of stubbornness in his negotiations with
federal authorities during his older years, his
unwavering political and diplomatic leadership
on behalf of his people cannot be ignored. Indeed,
he demonstrated unusual dedication in
his efforts to maintain those provisions in the
Treaty of Fort Laramie that he insisted should be
honored.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">NATIVE AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.na.107">Sioux</ref>; <ref n="egp.na.118">Treaties</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">RELIGION</hi>: <ref n="egp.rel.023">Ghost Dance</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Robert W. Larson<lb/>
Denver, Colorado</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Larson, Robert W. <title level="m">Red Cloud: Warrior-Statesman of the
Lakota Sioux</title>. Norman: University of Oklahoma Press,
1997.</bibl> <bibl>Paul, R. Eli, ed. <title level="m">Autobiography of Red Cloud: War
Leader of the Oglalas</title>. Helena: Montana Historical Society
Press, 1997.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>