<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.na.004">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Apaches</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Donald C. Cole</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.na.004</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Cole, Donald C.">Donald C. Cole</author>. <title level="a">"Apaches."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">561-562</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-03</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">APACHES</head>

<p>Apaches, along with Navajos, are the southernmost
extension of Athapaskan-language
speakers. Scholars disagree on which Apaches
first lived in the Great Plains. Specialists traditionally
argued for a sixteenth-century Apache
entry into the region, in part because early
Spanish accounts described them in the Plains
of Texas and eastern New Mexico. Scholars
assumed they were recent arrivals. Archeological
work in the 1970s, however, a.rmed an
Apachean presence in the Central Plains in the
fifteenth and sixteenth centuries. Moreover,
the Apaches' own stories place them in the
Plains as early as the ninth century.</p>

<p>On the basis of archeological evidence, Karl
Schlesier postulated four waves of Apachean
migration into the Plains between 50 and 1550
<hi rend="smallcaps">A.D.</hi> The first of these is associated with a
proto-Athapaskan movement into Saskatchewan
and the Northern Great Plains by 50 <hi rend="smallcaps">A.D.</hi>
Their descendants are the Sarcees (Sarsis). A
second movement of people, destined to be
known as southern Athapaskans, arrived in
Montana around 200 <hi rend="smallcaps">A.D.</hi> Schlesier believes
that this wave split into three parts, one of
which remained in place, while the other two
parts continued south into Wyoming and the
Black Hills, respectively. From there they
moved to the Southern Plains, where Spanish
explorers encountered their descendants. A
third wave entered the Plains between 950 and
1225 <hi rend="smallcaps">A.D.</hi> These people became the Navajos
(D&#233;n&#233;) and Chiricahua Apaches (N'de). This
migration is described in traditional stories of
Chiricahua and Mescalero Apache peoples.
Navajo accounts place their arrival in Colorado
and northern New Mexico at about 1100.</p>

<p>A fourth and final wave of Apachean migration,
from 1450 to 1650, brought the ancestors
of the Jicarillas, Lipans, and lastly, the distantly
related Kiowa Apaches (also called
Plains Apaches). These Apaches subsisted by
food gathering, hunting, and horticulture,
augmented by trade with settled farming
communities. Autonomous Apache bands
collected near the Pueblos, where they traded
or raided as conditions warranted.</p>

<p>Spanish entrance into the Southern Plains
in the sixteenth century brought profound
changes to Apache ways of life. Colonization
and forced conversion of Pueblo trading partners
created increased hostility between the
mobile and settled peoples. Acquisition of European
horses and metal weapons presented
new opportunities to raid for additional goods.</p>

<p>Spanish o.cials in New Mexico and Texas
had difficulty identifying Apache tribes by
name and location. Frequent changes in designation
were required to correct mistakes.
By 1700 Apaches in the Plains were identified
as follows: Lipans, occupying central Texas;
Faroans, in the Texas Panhandle; Mescaleros,
in eastern New Mexico; Jicarillas, north and
east of the Mescaleros; Carlanas, located along
the present Colorado&#8211;New Mexico border;
and Cuartelejos, in eastern Colorado and adjacent
western Kansas. Palomas occupied central
Nebraska along the Platte River. Plains
(later also known as Kiowa Apaches) Apaches
were in and around the Black Hills of South
Dakota.</p>

<p>By the mid&#8211;seventeenth century Apaches
had acquired enough horses that their raids
became a major concern for Spanish authorities
in New Mexico. Colonial governors tried
various policies to subjugate them. Military
expeditions against scattered autonomous
bands produced limited results. Spanish alliances
with Pueblos and Comanches were
more productive. After 1700 the Comanches
swept the Apaches off the plains of Texas and
eastern New Mexico. Spanish territorial governors
at times attempted to concentrate
Apaches near Pueblo communities through
dispersal of trade goods, including guns and
alcohol. Some bands accepted Spanish annuities
and settled under Spanish rule. Most
did not. Spain failed to bring Apache bands in
the Plains under control. Mexico fared no better.
Apache raids, along with Comanche inroads,
became the bane of existence in newly
independent Mexico between 1821 and 1846.</p>

<p>In independent Texas (1836–45), policy was
hostile to Indian populations, Apaches included.
Texas, however, focused on war against
Comanches, being less interested in Lipans and
Mescaleros, who were generally far enough west
to be beyond reach. The United States' annexation
of Texas in 1845, and occupation and acquisition
of much of northern Mexico in 1848,
brought immense changes to the Apaches. Gen.
Stephen Watts Kearny pronounced the United
States' policy at Las Vegas, New Mexico, in 1846,
which called for disarming and forcible settlement
of all nomadic raiders. That policy was
pursued for more than thirty years to an eventual
successful conclusion.</p>

<p>From 1849 to 1851 a severe cholera epidemic
along overland trails struck the Apaches. Most
Lipans perished. Survivors, harried by Comanches
and Kiowas, eventually took refuge
with the Mescaleros, who absorbed them.</p>

<p>The United States negotiated treaties with
the Apaches in the 1850s, but most were not
ratified. The U.S. Army carried on a series of
campaigns against specific Apache bands in
the 1850s. By 1861 war with Apaches had become
general. The Jicarillas were fortunate
to find refuge on the immense Maxwell Land
Grant in northern New Mexico. In 1863 the
army was authorized to carry out a war of
extermination against the Apaches. Kit Carson
directed a campaign against the Mescaleros
that resulted in their surrender. They and other
Apache bands were gradually placed, by force
or agreement, on reservations in New Mexico
and Arizona. Apache resistance ended by 1887.</p>

<p>Mescaleros, with surviving Lipans, were established
on a reservation in south-central
New Mexico, where they still remain, numbering
3,511 in 1992. Jicarillas finally were
granted a reservation of their own in northern
New Mexico in 1887, to the west of the Great
Plains. The reservation was increased in size in
1907 and again in 1908. Their population in
1992 was 3,100. Chiricahua Apaches were held
as prisoners of war in Florida and Alabama
until 1893. They were then moved to Fort Sill,
Oklahoma, and placed as prisoners on land
donated by Comanches and Kiowas. In 1913
most of their lands were annexed to Fort Sill.
About two-thirds moved to Mescalero; the
rest stayed at Fort Sill. They are the Fort Sill
Apaches, numbering just over 100. The Plains
Apaches were placed at Fort Sill with Kiowas
and Comanches at the conclusion of hostilities
with those peoples in the 1870s. Most descendants
of the Plains Apaches remain in that
area, where they are officially recognized as
the Apache Tribe of Oklahoma. They have
about 1,600 enrolled tribal members.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Donald C. Cole<lb/>
Bethany College</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Basso, Keith H., and Morris E. Opler, eds. <title level="m">Apachean Culture History and Ethnology</title>. Tucson: University of Arizona
Press, 1971.</bibl> <bibl>Hyde, George E. <title level="m">Indians of the High Plains: From the Prehistoric Period to the Coming of Europeans</title>.
Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1959.</bibl> <bibl>Schlesier, Karl H., ed. <title level="m">Plains Indians,A.D.500–1500: The Archaeological Past of Historic Groups</title>. Norman: University of Oklahoma
Press, 1994.</bibl>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>