<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.arc.001.01 SYSTEM "egp.arc.001.01.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY egp.arc.001.02 SYSTEM "egp.arc.001.02.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY egp.arc.001.03 SYSTEM "egp.arc.001.03.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.arc.001">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Architecture</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>David Murphy</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.arc.001</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Murphy, David">David Murphy</author>. <title level="a">"Architecture."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">61-67</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-12</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">ARCHITECTURE</head>

<p>In what sense can we speak about an architecture
of the Great Plains? Such a narrative
would necessarily derive from essential
characteristics of the whole place&#8211;flora and
fauna, climate and weather, geology, topography,
and horizon&#8211;and would address building
with compelling reference to this ground.
Alternatively, we might speak of architecture
on the Plains, using spatial location as our primary
criterion. Either approach might work,
but this essay will follow the former, first because
the region is defined, in good part, by
properties of the natural place, and second
because architecture, at root, creates cultural
places <hi rend="italic">within</hi> natural place.</p>

<p>Acknowledging natural place as the ground
for architecture changes the perspective on
our view of building. Congruence between
these "two" places can be discerned by thinking
of both in terms of form and structure or,
metaphorically, as mind and body. Though it
is not possible to conclude an entirely homogeneous
interpretation of building from
the diverse constructions on the Plains, this
approach forces us at least to think about architecture
and place in other than humancentered
terms. This perspective reveals an incongruence
between the two aspects of place
that was present from the very beginning of
European American entry to the Plains. This
story is at variance with those we have heard
before.</p>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Ancient Place</head>

<p>Original peoples evolved within an architecture
of place. Because the Plains region includes
many places and peoples, a diverse realization
of architecture occurred. This resulted
in part from materials variability, in part from
prevailing climatic conditions, and in part
from evolving cultural preferences.</p>

<p>A defining characteristic of all prehistoric
architecture in the region was the use of construction
materials taken directly from the
place. Grasses played important roles, particularly
in the tallgrass areas, where they were
utilized for thatching, matting, and underlay
and as wattling for clay-daubed walls. The
most spectacular use was the historic Wichita
lodge of the Southern Plains, though pole-and-
grass huts may also have found early use
in widely scattered Central Plains locations.</p>

<p>Similarly, grassland soils played a role in
most of the more substantial constructions.
Partially excavated interiors were characteristic
of many permanent lodges. Some early
square and rectangular houses utilized wall
systems of closely spaced posts that were wattled
and daubed with clay. Clays were also
used in the southwestern Plains to plaster
floors, make wall bricks, and raise puddled
walls. Highly consolidated soils or sedimentary
rocks were utilized principally along the
High Plains of the western part of the region.
Caves formed by the erosional undercutting
of streams were home to early big-game hunters
along the northwestern Plains from 5,000
to 10,000 years ago. Later cave sites have been
located all across the western margins of the
region. Stone masonry dwellings were built in
the rugged canyon lands and escarpments of
the southwestern Plains. The use of soils culminated
in the earth lodge.</p>

<p>Plains fauna also provided raw materials for
construction. Bison skins were used from historic
times back into the more distant past,
perhaps as many as 5,000 years ago on the
plains of southern Alberta. The historic tipi is
the evolved descendant of a long line of skin
lodges.</p>

<p>The extensive repertoire of walling material
contrasted with a limitation in roof structure.
A scarcity of forested areas limited the location,
size, and duration of permanent settlements.
Temporary campsites and smaller
lodges built of poles with mat, grass, bark, or
skin coverings could utilize woods such as
willow in more widely scattered locations. But
substantial lodges needed large trees for posts,
beams, and rafters; permanent villages were
therefore built near major wooded streams
and rivers.</p>

<p>The formal aspects of this early architecture
are more difficult to determine than its structure.
Evidence gleaned from archaeological
investigation is difficult to interpret, especially
in projecting three-dimensional forms from
two-dimensional remains. Nevertheless, two
distinct patterns, one of circular forms and
the other of rectilinear forms, can be broadly
discerned.</p>

<p>The oldest remains are found along the
western High Plains, where ubiquitous rock
circles mark the base of what were circular
lodges. Rocks were used to secure the covering
of the lodge to the ground or perhaps to stabilize
the poles of the structure. Ancestral in
design to the historic era tipi, these structures
are oldest and most numerous on the Alberta
Plains and become more widely scattered and
presumably later to the south. The more recent
circles mark larger lodges than earlier
ones&#8211;the adoption of the horse by nomadic
peoples increased the size of lodge that could
be transported.</p>

<p>The oldest remains are found along the
western High Plains, where ubiquitous rock
circles mark the base of what were circular
lodges. Rocks were used to secure the covering
of the lodge to the ground or perhaps to stabilize
the poles of the structure. Ancestral in
design to the historic era tipi, these structures
are oldest and most numerous on the Alberta
Plains and become more widely scattered and
presumably later to the south. The more recent
circles mark larger lodges than earlier
ones—the adoption of the horse by nomadic
peoples increased the size of lodge that could
be transported.</p>

<p>Among the oldest of the rectangular-pattern
houses were those constructed at the beginning
of the second millennium of the current
era along the middle Missouri River of contemporary
North and South Dakota. These
semisubterranean houses had floors one or
more meters below the surface, with entrance
through the southerly end of the house via a
long, covered ramp. A slightly raised platform
usually occupied the entrance end and sometimes
extended along the sides. The hearth was
along the long axis. Structurally, these houses
appear to have been gable-roofed buildings,
supported by ridgepoles and side walls built of
closely spaced posts.</p>

<p>Entirely different rectangular houses have
been unearthed in the southwestern Plains.
Dating from nearly the same time, one built in
the upper Washita River drainage contained
a central hearth and two central posts. This
plan is similar to lower Arkansas valley Caddoan
houses of the mid.thirteenth through
mid.fourteenth centuries. Closely spaced
posts around the perimeter indicate wall lines
and narrow, protruding entrance passages.
The roof was likely hipped and thatched,
while walls appear to have been closed with
wattling.</p>

<p>More ubiquitous was a square, four-post
lodge that appeared throughout the Central
and Southern Plains from the tenth through
the fifteenth centuries and that came to be
adopted along the middle Missouri River
somewhat later. Built with considerable variation
in size and detail, this house type appears
to be an enlarged version of the two-post rectangular
house, constructed with a hipped
or pyramidal roof. The nearly square plan
typically had rounded corners with walls of
closely spaced posts that undoubtedly were
wattled and daubed. On the western portions
of the Central Plains they were built on or
near the surface, while to the east they were
semisubterranean.</p>

<p>Initially, square houses were not oriented to
any particular direction, but over time the
four posts came to be set at the semicardinal
points. As the structure was reoriented, the
entrance vestibule was typically built facing
east. The commodious interiors utilized a variety
of features, such as benches and screens,
to divide the space into different compartments.
Square-lodge villages were typically located
on the first or second terraces of rivers
and streams, while the village pattern, regardless
of size, tended to organically follow the
terrain of the terrace. Fortifications were rare
except in the middle Missouri region of the
Northern Plains, and there they protected
only a portion of the extended village.</p>

<p>Perhaps the most distinctive adaptation of
the four-post square house occurred along the
southwest margins of the Plains in the upper
Canadian drainage of what is now the Panhandle
of Texas. Particularly interesting are
villages in the Antelope Creek basin, where
the house was oriented to the cardinal directions
and had a very low, east-facing entrance
passage. The house floor incorporated raised
benches with storage bins. Another raised
platform, either protruding into the house
or occupying a projecting extension of the
west wall, was often found opposite the door.
Hearths were centrally located.</p>

<p>Construction technology further distinguishes
these houses. Walls were built of puddled
clay or clay bricks alternating with horizontal
stone slabs. Occasionally, vertical posts
were used to stabilize the clay walls. Most interesting
was the use of various forms of rock
foundations and footings: single or double
rows of vertical stone slabs set into the
ground, the latter with rubble fill, comprised
the most unusual system.</p>

<figure n="egp.arc.001.01" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Sioux tipis, Fort Buford, Dakota Territory, May 1881</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Village patterns were also distinct. In several,
lodges were built contiguously into large
communal blocks that seem to have been a
function of choice and not of site limitation.
Room configuration was complex. Circular
rooms served as antechambers to one
square house in each block, possibly indicating
some kind of communal function.</p>

<p>Other multichamber complexes were built
farther to the northwest along the upper
reaches of the Canadian and Arkansas drainages
and to the east along Ladder Creek, a
tributary of the Smoky Hill River (in contemporary
New Mexico, Colorado, and Kansas,
respectively). The latter, a pueblo-like construction,
dates to after the Pueblo Revolt of
1620. Known as El Cuartelejo, it was associated
with the Plains Apache.</p>

<p>Even as the house-pattern preference of the
Plains villages coalesced around the four-post
square lodge, a shift toward a circular plan had
already begun. Four-post circular lodges, presumably
walled with wattle and daub like their
square counterparts, were occasionally found
as minority forms within some square-house
villages. Examples from about <hi rend="smallcaps">A.D.</hi> 1000 to
1400 appeared along the Salt Creek drainage
of the Smoky Hill River in what is now western
Kansas and along Muddy Creek in the
South Loup River system of present-day Nebraska.
Other early circular lodges existed to
the south of the High Plains rock-circle clusters
in the rugged Apishapa Canyon of the
upper Arkansas River in present-day southeastern
Colorado. Dating from the latter half
of the thirteenth century, these were singleand
multichamber dwellings constructed of
upright stone slabs. They varied in size from
postless and single-post to four-post structures;
the latter seems to anticipate four-post
circular earth lodges.</p>

<p>The circular earth lodge itself apparently
appeared after 1450 and was common until the
European American invasion. This house type
was adopted by virtually all the semisedentary
communities from the Central Plains northward.
It was like earlier square lodges in the
utilization of the four interior posts, the central
hearth, the extending entrance vestibule,
and the system of roof rafters. Aside from its
plan, major distinctions from its predecessors
occur in the perimeter structural system and
the earthen covering. In structure, vertical wall
members were replaced with a post-and-beam
system, and roof rafters rested on the beam
rather than on a wall plate. Wall members
were leaners that rested against the perimeter
beam. The space beneath these leaners, to the
outside of the posts, was used for a variety of
purposes, including sleeping platforms, storage,
and altars.</p>

<p>Other lodge types of the protohistoric period
adopted the circular form as well. Hunting
camp lodges along the middle Missouri of
Pawnee earth lodge, ca. 1871
the Northern Plains were built with four center
posts whose beams supported leaners that
peaked like a tipi and marked a circle on the
ground. Central Plains Apaches built seasonal
lodges that made the circular motif more explicit.
There the imprint of the leaners was
mirrored in the internal structure, where typically
five and sometimes six interior posts
were set in a circle around the hearth. The
entrance was less an appendage than a protuberance
of the curvilinear form.</p>

<p>On the Southern Plains another circular
lodge emerged that became a Plains house
type of importance equal to the earth lodge.
Known primarily from historic Wichita structures,
the thatched or grass lodge utilized
wall-roof poles set firmly into the ground,
bent across an internal post-and-beam system,
and tied together at the peak. Light horizontal
stringers were tied to these "rafters" to
strengthen the frame and provide support for
bundled grass thatch. Another set of stringers
was applied over the thatch to help secure it to
the frame. Older grass lodges in the Red River
valley along the Texas-Oklahoma border apparently
were built upon a four-post plan. The
evolved Wichita house, however, utilized a circular,
multipost system that retained some of
the significance of the old four-post lodge in
the designation of principal posts for the four
directions.</p>

<figure n="egp.arc.001.02" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Pawnee earth lodge, ca. 1871</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>A similar evolution occurred with the earth
lodge into the historic period, at least among
some tribes. Protohistoric Pawnee villages in
the lower Loup River valley of present-day Nebraska
were composed of four-post circular
lodges, while historic Pawnee lodges utilized
from six to eight or twelve interior posts set in
a circle. This was also the case with historic
Omaha lodges. Thus, while four-post circular
lodges continued to be built on the Northern
Plains, in the Central and Southern Plains
four-post structures gave way to multipost circular
structural systems that reflected the circle
described by the external walls.</p>

<p>While the full meaning of this evolution
cannot be known, some significant patterns
can be discerned. Three principal architectural
forms share the multipost&#8211;or multipole&#8211;
circular configuration. All three utilized
exterior surfaces that were, in essence, angular
projections that began the vaulting over of the
dwelling from the plane of the earth. Neither
wall nor roof in the Western sense, these surfaces
formed a continuous vaulting of the
dwelling that projected upward from a circle
inscribed on the earth. The whole material
body of the Plains was also reflected in these
forms: soil, the geological and biological basis
for the life of the place, was reflected in the
earth lodge; grass, the principal flora of the
Great Plains, was reflected in the thatched
lodge; and bison, the principal faunal life of
this place, was reflected in the skin lodge.</p>

<p>In a real sense, the mind of original Plains
peoples converged with the body of the place
and evolved a climactic Great Plains architecture.
The shapes and cycles of things were
echoed in the evolved architecture. The vast
expanses of the Plains are defined by the circular
horizon, and from the horizon vaults
the still more vast sky. Within this expanse
the rhythmic cycles of the cosmos&#8211;of the
earth, moon, sun, and stars&#8211;are plainly evident.
Here the great circle of the terrestrial
world, the horizon, marked the boundary of
place. Native peoples reflected the shape of the
place in forms that mirrored the place. Cycles
and the place were celebrated in material
form&#8211;from lodges to medicine wheels and
from great camp circles to contemporary
dance arbors.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Disembodiment</head>

<p>Further evolution of Native architecture was
eclipsed by the rapid conquest of the Plains by
European Americans, who defined the place
from a distance. Disembodied, abstract concepts&#8211;
following the Cartesian lead&#8211;took
power and control over the ancient evolved
body of the place, and anthropocentric priorities
began to rift the place to pieces, first in
mind, then in body.</p>

<p>The Great Plains was objectified on desks in
Washington and Ottawa, fueled by concepts of
property and reports from scientific and military
expeditions. New territories were defined
by imaginary lines such as those drawn in abstract
space using the global grid. This grid
became part of the "architectural" transformation
of the Plains; its extension via government
surveys imposed a uniform Cartesian
net over the whole of the "flat" and "empty"
land. Ultimately, the cultural expression of
these lines effected the complete transformation
of place, with property lines determining
the limits of thought.</p>

<p>Three institutions&#8211;the fur trade, the military,
and the railroad&#8211;cleared the way for European
American resettlement and the final
phases of disembodiment. Though the early
architectural presence of these institutions
gave an appearance of being in place due to
their use of local materials, their architectures
quickly evolved into modern facilities of extraction
in keeping with their institutional intent.
Their mature architectural forms rereflected
the power their enterprises had over
the body of the place.</p>

<p>Fur traders, here to strip the Plains of its
fur- and skin-bearing animals, were the first
to make permanent constructions. Early Missouri
River posts were typically built of horizontal
logs cut from the forested valley. Fontenelle's
post at Bellevue (1822), in present-day
Nebraska, consisted of individual buildings
set around a loose, partially fenced courtyard.
Its otherwise benign appearance was belied by
the size of its warehouses. Later constructions
such as those at Fort Union at the mouth of
the Yellowstone (established in 1828) were formally
designed, fully stockaded compounds.
The head trader's house there is an early example
of the elite colonial designs that quickly
made their way onto the Plains.</p>

<p>Other fortified compounds were built, beginning
in the 1830s, as new centers of extraction
were established on the western High
Plains. Wood was not abundant there, so clay
technologies adopted from Hispanic sources
were utilized. From Bent's Fort on the Arkansas
northward to Fort John on the North
Platte, the spread of southwestern construction
techniques was made possible by an
abundance of clays and a liberal use of Latino
labor. Built as variations on the Spanish presidio,
the adobe forts embodied corporate
power with controlled, hierarchical plans that
only looked premodern because of their old
structural systems.</p>

<p>The second wave of corporate technology
was associated with U.S. military campaigns.
Pursuit of the nomadic western tribes for the
security needs of traveling European Americans
led to the initial establishment of numerous
temporary posts. Selective adoption
of premodern techniques facilitated construction
where the preferred materials were rare
or nonexistent: adobe masonry and panel-wall
log construction are just two examples.
Seldom were these valued for permanent installations.
Lumber was imported as soon as
possible, and by the turn of the twentieth century
brick veneers were used extensively to
lend an aura of permanence and substance to
the most important posts.</p>

<p>Unlike the compounds of the fur traders,
military architecture on the Plains was rarely
fortified; industrial weapons technologies obviated
this need. Drawn from Anglo-American
architectural traditions, forts were orderly collections
of individual buildings, hierarchically
arranged and properly attired. Commanding
officers' quarters were patterned after the hierarchical
central-passage houses of eastern merchants.
Though often scaled back to one and a
half stories in height, their symmetrical facades
and front galleries symbolically reinforced
the government's role of establishing
control over the region.</p>

<p>and character of the resettlement. Extensions
into "unsettled" country allowed them to establish
stops, to plat and own towns, and to
control the towns' development. Rail towns
were laid out following a small repertoire of
plans, all focusing on the depot as the central
place. Control of these geometric plats allowed
railroads to shape the character of
towns by deciding which lots were sold for
what purposes and in what order. Business
districts were created in immediate proximity
to the depot, while churches and residential
lots were pushed to the periphery.</p>

<p>The depot was the most intentionally symbolic
structure. Plains railroads adopted standard
plans that allowed for a variety of selections
depending upon the position of the
community within the economic structure of
the corporation. Noteworthy among Plains
designs was the residential depot, which provided
housing for agents in locales that were
not yet developed. The most common of these
had living space on the second floor above
passenger waiting rooms and agent offices.</p>

<p>Standard plans gave way to custom designs
in communities that established themselves as
significant economic entities. Elite designs
created symbolic images for both the community
and the corporation. This became problematic
after World War II, when passenger
service declined or ceased altogether. Corporations
often quickly removed passenger stations,
so that today the sight of a depot is rare
and rarer still in its original location. Given
the depots' prominent siting, their removal
has often left significant gaps in the urban
landscape.</p>

<p>An even greater impact of rail technology
was in the movement of people and goods.
This contribution to the disembodiment of
original place facilitated the commodification
of agriculture, with its widespread replacement
of native flora and fauna. In addition
to stockyards and trackside corrals, the most
permanent and symbolic of the structures of
disembodiment was the grain elevator. The
early stacked-lumber elevators have largely
disappeared except, perhaps, in more remote
regions of the Northern Plains and Prairie
Provinces. Victims of truck transport and corporate
consolidation, the wooden structures
were replaced with larger facilities built of reinforced
concrete. The most substantial of
these are in gateway cities along the fringes of
the region. As the largest and most monumental
constructions in the region, they symbolize
the region's modern role as grain supplier
to the world.</p>

<p>Another architectural result of this activity
was the emergence of sod-wall construction.
Utilized over vast areas of the central and
northern farming Plains, it flourished with increasing
European American settlement in the
1870s and followed wherever the prairies were
broken. Its success as a building technology
relied upon the manufacture of the steel plows
needed to cut the tough prairie-grass roots; its
demise rested upon Anglocentric notions of
"proper" dwelling construction, the proliferation
of industrial building technologies, and
the destruction of the native prairies.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Replacement</head>

<p>The rest of the architectural story is dominated
by the importation of building materials
and abstract architectural ideas. The materials
needed to accommodate Anglo-American
ways of building did not exist in quantity in
the Plains, so the new architectural body
turned its back on the region. The story is one
of replacement.</p>

<p>The existing place didn't feel like a potential
home to European Americans, who had
mostly been a people of the forest, first in Europe
and then in America. On the Plains
everything was strange and seemingly empty;
as one early traveler put it, a single tree would
have been enough to relieve the pain of loneliness
and desolation. That tree would also
have provided the preferred building material
of the newcomer, and so wood, in the form
of imported lumber, became critical to the
replacement.</p>

<p>Though some wood was processed locally
in river towns, regional riparian stands of timber,
following the decimation wreaked by
overland travelers, the army, the railroads, and
the telegraph, were insu.cient to meet anything
but rudimentary local needs. Exogenous
lumber was first supplied by steamboat, and
some precut houses were imported during the
first years of settlement. But it was the completion
of the transcontinental railroads that
started the massive importation of lumber
into the Plains. The resettlement was built
from the body of the upper midwestern and
southern forests, and the trackside lumberyard
became another symbol of European
American resettlement.</p>

<p>Prior to the o.cial opening of the Plains,
the evolution of American wooden building
had begun to standardize around light frame
construction with nail joinery. Locally, however,
framing initially followed diverse patterns.
Heavy braced frames continued to be
built for a time by easterners and some Germans,
but increasingly these were superseded
by modern light wooden frames. Idiosyncratic
hybrid framing was not uncommon, but
eventually the technology settled on more or
less standard balloon and western platform
frames.</p>

<p>The thought behind the replacement was as
out of place as the lumber, and this was reflected
in the forms the replacement took as
well. In the more heavily settled sections of
the region the superimposed spatial grid influenced
the character of the new landscape
from the beginning. Roads, fields, fences,
lanes, farms, schools, churches, and towns all
became subsets of the grid. Terrain and waterways
no longer ordered culture or formed
place; section roads and property lines did.
In the farming countryside checkerboard
fields planted in straight monocultural rows
drilled the modern mechanistic order into the
land itself. The place became changed at ever
deeper levels.</p>

<p>Architectural form followed from the same
mind that overlaid the landscape with the abstract
grid. Though this modern, abstract
mind held sway over the Plains, some communities
initially embraced a wider variety of
attitudes. Architecturally, before the final triumph
of national modernism a more diverse
presence established heterogeneous places
throughout the region.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Diversity</head>

<p>For a time the Great Plains was inhabited by
an international community&#8211;a historically
contingent, multicultural presence of quite
different and sometimes opposing belief systems.
Their initial constructions represented a
wide array of responses to the challenge of
making place. Foreign immigrants often built
in old ways that were familiar and comfortable.
The transference of old forms was restricted
by the extent a material was available
to build in the traditional way. If it was not,
or if one were instead attempting to conform
to emerging national standards, then the old
form was either abandoned for a new one
built of lumber or it was modified to accommodate
the new material.</p>

<p>When we think in regional architectural
terms, we naturally look to the materials that
form the body of the place, and here, due to
notoriety, the sod wall comes first to mind. Its
utilization across a broad expanse of the farming
Plains, irrespective of culture, made the
sod-wall dwelling a true regional vernacular of
the replacement. The nature of the material's
association with disembodiment, however,
precluded its utility beyond the first or second
generation of houses. Constructions of baled
biomass (hay and straw), perhaps the only regional
architectural invention, might have
provided a sustainable counterpart to sod,
though it appeared too late and in areas too
sparsely settled to have had an immediate impact.
Its recent resurgence is another matter.</p>

<p>Less popular than sod but still widespread
were various clay-wall technologies. Unfired
clay found use in brick masonry, puddledclay,
and rammed-earth constructions; its
many iterations were known by diverse terms,
depending upon the culture that utilized the
technique. The clay technologies were primarily
culture-bound, and while they were
preadapted to the Plains environment, their
adoption by others appears to have been only
idiosyncratic. Black Sea Germans, Czechs,
Poles, Ukrainians, and Hispanics were among
the dominant builders in clay.</p>

<p>Diversity was also a theme in the utilization
of other native materials. Variation in the
type, quantity, and quality of stone led vernacular
and elite masons to a remarkable variety
of construction in surprisingly widespread
locales, virtually everywhere su.cient veins of
good-quality rock were found near the surface.
Where quantity and quality supported
commercial quarrying, elite buildings were
constructed. High-quality architectural work
can be found everywhere stone was used, but
probably nowhere in such concentrations as
in the Sioux Quartzite areas of southeastern
South Dakota or the Flint Hills of eastern
Kansas, where sophisticated dressed ashlar
work was common.</p>

<p>Perhaps most surprising for the "treeless"
Plains was the extent of log construction during
the early settlement period. Diversity arose
from the multicultural background of builders
and the mixed flora of the region. Most
of the log-timbering methods known to have
been brought to America, as well as those that
evolved on the continent, were utilized on the
Plains.</p>

<p>Two factors influenced the use of native
material: the first in which the "pioneer" was
forced as a matter of necessity and a second in
which settlers chose native material as a matter
of preference. The former was spatiotemporally
restricted to the ever-shifting line
of resettlement. Few surviving constructions
were built from strict necessity, and most
of what remains derived from cultural preference.
These were built predominantly by Germans,
German Russians, Poles, Czechs, Finns,
Hispanics, and Ukrainians.</p>

<p>Cultural diversity was also reflected in architectural
form, especially among rural folk
and the more conservative immigrants and
during the first, second, and sometimes third
generations of dwelling construction. Usually
the diversity was the result of the direct transplantation
of Old World forms.</p>

<p>Though dwelling types were all within a familiar
western mold, the constructions of
foreign-born settlers were often noticeably
distinct from those of the native-born. Many
early dwellings were built along ancient plans
that accommodated preferred ways of living.
Most of these modest dwellings were characterized
by the presence of principal rooms&#8211;
called halls in the English American tradition&#8211;
and open plans that allowed direct
entry into these rooms, preserving old, intimate
relationships between the house and the
land. The most prominent of the traditional
builders were the Germans, German Russians
(both Black Sea and Volga), Czechs, Poles,
Ukrainians, and Danes. Their old plans were
modified, with rare exception, by the adoption
of American cast-iron stoves for heating
and cooking. The abandonment of old-style
hearths, stoves, and ovens did change the interior
character of dwellings and often necessitated
modifications to traditional foodways.
Some built larger, more modern Old World
dwellings, while others such as the Volga Germans
and Danes chose from American house
types that closely resembled familiar European
forms.</p>

<p>Though some Anglo-Americans initially
built traditional houses (usually a hall-andchamber
house), most erected modernized
plans that abandoned halls in favor of kitchens
and parlors. Other principal features of
this modernization, whatever the kind of
house, included the use of multiple thresholds
and the accommodation of bedrooms and
dining rooms&#8211;all reflective of the increasing
dwelling size and room specialization characteristic
of modern society's movement toward
privacy, individuality, and separation from
the land. Most of the early modern houses
were variations on popular Georgian planning
and formal symmetry. Later settlers
adopted house types derived from rapidly
changing national architectural fashion. The
specific sequences of both the foreign- and
native-born developments varied depending
upon where and when initial settlement took
place.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">National Modernity</head>

<p>In the main, however, the architectural story
of the Great Plains after European American
immigration was about an architecture that
just happened to be built on the Plains. In the
broad sweep it was not substantially different
from that developed anywhere else in the
United States. There is no reason to retell that
story here using local examples. It is, however,
important to at least acknowledge the surge of
national modernity as it played out on the
Plains.</p>

<p>Easterners wasted little time in setting forth
the national parameters within which this
new place was to be defined; lumber was first,
and the architectural pattern book was second.
Mass-produced pattern books made the
transference of formal architectural ideas out
of place possible. Designs no longer needed
to respond to locale; rather, they became abstractions
that could be built on any "site,"
anywhere. Pattern books by eastern and British
architects had already been a means for
expressing and disseminating elite architectural
ideas before initial resettlement began.
Stylish houses could be and were built soon
after the various territories were opened.</p>

<p>By the turn of the twentieth century, books
by architects such as Chicagoan William Radford
were produced for more popular consumption.
Mail-order catalogs were likewise
published by retailers like Sears and Montgomery
Ward, offering not only designs but
also precut materials ready for shipment.
Soon local builders and lumberyards produced
catalogs depicting their own repertoire
of house designs. These were increasingly
built in tracts of similar or identical dwellings.</p>

<p>National and "progressive" trends in farm
building design were also perpetuated through
the state and national agricultural journals
that proliferated from the late nineteenth century.
Following trends established earlier in
architectural publications, they offered advice
on lifestyle as well as technical information on
buildings. Land-grant universities published
technical leaflets with designs for essential
farm and ranch building needs. The impact of
these was substantial, and from around 1900
onward the agricultural landscape became architecturally
more homogenized.</p>

<p>As the demand for architectural and engineering
services increased, especially in the
cities, more architects from the East migrated
west. Some were trained under the apprenticeship
system, while others, both native- and
foreign-born, had also received academic
training. Custom buildings of increasing
structural competence and design sophistication
were soon raised on the Plains, beginning
in the boom years of the 1880s. By the next
century academic training was virtually the
norm. Education was provided by leading
schools in the East, technical universities in
Europe, and the Ecole des Beaux-arts in Paris.
Some Beaux-arts-trained architects such as
Thomas Kimball of Omaha were native sons
who returned home after completing their
schooling to contribute to the development of
the region.</p>

<p>Local apprenticeship systems produced an
extensive lineage of architectural practice that
became the foundation for the licensed practitioners
of the twentieth century. By midcentury
several state land-grant and provincial
universities had established architecture
schools. Some local architectural firms have
become national and even international concerns,
made possible by the ideological trends
of modernity and a globalizing economy.</p>

<p>Great Plains architectural output from the
beginning of the replacement replicated abstract,
national, and modern trends. Essential
influences emanated from eastern cities, then
from Chicago, then from the Pacific Coast,
and finally from avant-garde Europe. Plains
architects creatively adapted national and international
design ideology to local problems,
especially in the cities and for elite clients.
Most moved freely from style to style (a legacy,
first promoted by pattern books, of reductionism
applied to architecture that divorced
the design of a facade from the function and
structure of the building) and have done so in
every era to the present. Architects were often
imported from cities like Chicago, Minneapolis,
Kansas City, St. Louis, and New York for
the most prestigious commissions.</p>

<p>While society's attitudes toward the modern
were national, there was no tendency toward
a national style following European
American entry to the region. The national
classical revivals of the first half of the nineteenth
century were on the wane when resettlement
commenced, and what followed was a
rapid succession of stylistic gyrations. The
first to proliferate on the Plains was the Queen
Anne; it was a style with national extent, but it
lacked national meaning. On the Plains the
ethno-English associations of the style were
vague; its popularity was more related to a
booming economy, ideas of modern "progress,"
and incipient suburbanization&#8211;all concepts
that had national overtones of their
own. Otherwise, architectural style changed
like the prairie winds with the fickle tastes of
consumer capitalism.</p>

<p>Excellent products of these multifarious national
and international trends dot the landscape,
interspersed with delightful local and
popular versions. But anything that might be
suggestive of a distinct architectural character
in the region was more the result of historical
contingency. Boom periods&#8211;via the sheer
quantity of construction&#8211;established an initial
character to rural and urban landscapes
that was distinct from older areas, east or west.
These remain present in most locales that
peaked economically before the current era.
Communities that experienced continued
growth typically replaced the replacements
and now are tending to resemble the "anywhere"
landscapes so emblematic of our time.
In this kind of setting, individual monuments
serve as symbols of place.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Differentiation</head>

<p>Two forms of architectural differentiation appeared
during the first part of the twentieth
century. The first sought explicit ethnocultural
meanings. Designs generated by some
foreign immigrants as they emerged from the
background of settlement and forged a greater
cultural presence on the land created distinctive
local environments. Their architectural
differentiation was more pronounced in a
host environment dominated by revivals intended
in part&#8211;via adoption of very selective
European and American sources&#8211;to create
the solidification of cultural hegemony.
The second was intended to be a resistance to
modernity, an attempt to reground architecture
in nature and place through a revival of
vernacular design, craft tradition, and, if not
indigenous materials, at least the use of natural
materials.</p>

<p>Ethnic architectural emergence by some
groups appears less culture bound than the
result of individual or community tastes and
idiosyncrasies; these groups tended to assimilate
quickly, with a concomitant architectural
melding into the host landscape. Among
them, however, Swedes did participate in an
Academic form (a self-consciously learned
and sophisticated approach to the revisioning
of earlier styles) of what has been dubbed
"National Romanticism" via the Augustana
Synod architect Olof Z. Cervin of Rock Island,
Illinois. His picturesque churches drew inspiration
from national revivals then current
in the Nordic countries. The most explicit of
his work was the yellow brick, stepped-gable
campus of the Bethphage Mission in Kearney
County, Nebraska. Danes also drew inspiration
from the revivals in their homeland,
though in a more provincial mode. This was
evident in picturesque designs for folk schools
such as at Nysted in Nebraska, but a more
ubiquitous if less obvious ethnic presence was
provided especially by Grundtvigian Danish
churches, gymnasia, and other community
buildings whose interiors were richly walled
and ceiled in wood. This harking back to a
distant forested past&#8211;and recalling wooden
seafaring vessels&#8211;represents a distinct architectural
expression on the Plains.</p>

<p>Also provincial but more a part of an Old
World cultural continuum than a revival was
the adoption of simplified baroque designs
for the community buildings of freethinking
Czechs. This "rustic" baroque was part of a
nearly three-century extension of the European
style. The latest Plains example was the
1921 Kollár Hall near Dubois, Nebraska. The
later Orthodox churches of Ukrainian settlers
in the Prairie Provinces were also continuations
of traditions that had been perpetuated
earlier in pioneer church buildings. The free
expressions of Alberta architect Father Philip
Ruh stand out, such as his Ukrainian Catholic
Church of the Immaculate Conception of 1930
at Cooks Creek, Manitoba. In it Ruh retained
the multipart articulated massing of traditional
churches topped with domes (though
not onion domes) but departed from tradition
in his Germanic decorative embellishment.</p>

<p>More Academic in origin and related to
the immigration of trained architects was
the appearance of two German American national
styles. Designs based upon the German
Gothic were unobtrusive in the American
context. Major examples of this <hi rend="italic">Spitzbogenstil</hi>,
or pointed-arch style, were built in German
settlements throughout the region: Sioux Falls
architect Joseph Schwarz's Holy Family Catholic
Church (1903–6) in Mitchell, South Dakota,
and J. P. Guth's St. Johns German Evangelical
Lutheran Church of 1902 near Lyons,
Nebraska, are representative of two common
variations. The second, the Rundbogenstil, or
round-arch style, was more than an ecclesiastical
style. Breweries and other commercial
and public buildings in German-dominated
places were often constructed in this popular
style. Frederick W. Paroth's St. Elizabeth Catholic
Church at Auraria, Colorado (1898), Anton
Dohman's St. Mary's Abbey Church at
Richardton, North Dakota (1905–9), and
Omaha's Anheuser Busch Beer Depot (1887)
are exemplary of a very large repertoire of
such designs.</p>

<p>The impetus toward national styles
throughout Europe in the nineteenth century
grew from emerging nation-state identity, an
issue many immigrants brought with them.
But the impulse applied equally to the dominant
culture in the United States. By the
turn of the twentieth century, a Georgian
Colonial Revival coalesced that had national
overtones among the native-born. Domestically,
the style, reinforced in part by xenophobia,
segued into various English Period
house styles around World War I, then expanded
to include period house choices from
the western Europe of the old immigration.</p>

<p>Multiplicity was the rule for the nondomestic
architecture of the first half of the twentieth
century as well, but it was really a focus on
taste and massive scale associated with the Academic
trend in architecture that characterized
American national romanticism of this
period. Styles were chosen based upon oftenvague
notions of association&#8211;sometimes institutional,
sometimes personal. Thus it could
happen that an Academic skyscraper adorned
in the Gothic Revival&#8211;a sort of "cathedral of
commerce"&#8211;could appear a few blocks from a
new Gothic Revival church, with no apparent
contradiction in meaning. Whatever the associations,
they may never have been known to
the community at large. Such was probably the
case with the appearance of the Romanesque
Revival for many Catholic churches of this period.
Derived from the Italian mode, the style
flowed from Vatican influences within the religious
hierarchy. To outsiders, taste and substance
were probably the primary indicative
aspects of Academic national romanticism.
Though lacking in substance, this taste was
promoted through a series of national expositions,
including the Trans-Mississippi and International
Exposition of 1898 in Omaha.</p>

<p>Another impulse of the trend toward associational
design was a return to American regional
culture. The lack of a prior European
American presence on the Plains, however,
was problematic. There was no regional style
here to revive. One solution to this deficit was
the use of imagination. Coronado's trek into
the Southern Plains provided su.cient impetus
for Omahans Thomas Rogers Kimball and
Archbishop Richard Scannell to conjure the
Spanish Colonial Revival as a style appropriate
to the Central Plains. Kimball's St. Cecilia's
Cathedral in Omaha of 1905.59 initiated an
identity with the American Southwest before
Goodhue's national popularization of the
style at the 1915 Panama-California Exposition
in San Diego. Spanish influences were more
prominent on the Southern Plains, where the
baroque also found expression in a variety
of eclectic designs such as the city hall and
auditorium of 1927 in Wichita Falls, Texas, by
Lang &amp; Witchell in association with Voelcker
&amp; Dixon.</p>

<p>The restrained mission style was more popular,
again particularly on the Southern Plains,
where it was adopted by the Southern Pacific
and Santa Fe Railroads as part of their corporate
identities. The Santa Fe station at Great
Bend, Kansas, is perhaps exemplary. Kansas
City architect Louis Curtiss's more inventive
reprisals of southwestern forms such as his
1907 depot and hotel at Syracuse, Kansas, and
the 1909–11 Lubbock, Texas, depot are probably
high points of this kind of regional identity.
As remote as these associations seem today,
they do appear more grounded, at least in
the South, than the more imaginary associations
drawn directly from the Mediterranean
such as the 1918 Broadmoor Hotel in Colorado
Springs.</p>

<p>The various forms of romanticism held
sway side by side with the California Craftsman
styles that were popularized in the Plains
in the Bungalow movement of the 1910s and
1920s. Craftsman houses were unlike the period
revivals in that they lacked cultural roots
in the American scene. They were similar to
them, however, in a favoring of craftsmanship
and vernacular design as well as a philosophical
intent to reground buildings in nature.
The import of both movements from the East
and West Coasts, however, merely continued
the trend of building out of place. Neither
style's attempts to build with indigenous materials
were very successful. With rare exceptions,
these buildings were little more than
philosophical statements lacking connection
to the Plains.</p>

<p>During this period indigenous materials
were used almost exclusively in recreational
architecture such as the river rock constructions
at the Medicine Park Resort in southwestern
Oklahoma, the earthen shelters of
Emiel Christensen's private retreat, PaWiTo,
along the Platte River in Nebraska, and the
occasional public works project. Exceptions,
however rare, can always be noted. A shortlived
river rock vernacular developed on the
Plains near Medicine Park, Oklahoma, and
here and there distinctive porches appeared
on bungalows throughout the region; those
built with glacial erratics are probably the
most spectacular.</p>

<p>One Chicago influence was related to the
Craftsman style in a general way. It was felt
in the Plains to an extent in Prairie-style adaptations
that borrowed superficial motifs for
application to otherwise derivative Colonial
and catalog forms. The style probably had the
closest theoretical a.nity to what might have
been a Plains architecture but was fully realized
by only a smattering of buildings. This, in
spite of the fact that the Plains boasted examples
of both Frank Lloyd Wright's earlier and
later Prairie houses: the Sutton house of 1905
in McCook, Nebraska, and the Allen house of
1915 in Wichita, Kansas. Fundamental Prairiestyle
forms&#8211;such as low, horizontal, hiproofed
houses&#8211;reappeared after World War II
with the popularization of suburban ranch-style
houses. But these were principally unrelated
to the earlier movement and had their
genesis on the Pacific Coast.</p>

<p>Beyond these halting movements, an impetus
toward regional differentiation simply
never materialized, other than through individual
efforts. The ephemeral Corn Palace at
Mitchell, South Dakota, and the Texas Spring
Palace at Fort Worth are two unconventional
examples. Both were built to celebrate a kind
of cyclical architectural stylishness with their
annually changing facades of modern products
derived from the body of the Plains; at
Mitchell, however, the motifs are applied to a
building designed following Moorish sources.
More permanent regional motifs appear in
places with varying degrees of appropriateness
and success. The cowboys and Indians at the
Frontier Hotel in Cheyenne (1936) and the architectural
inscriptions utilized on the Natrona
County Courthouse in Casper, Wyoming,
are examples. The cowboy and Indian
had appeared earlier as incised sculpture on
the frontispiece of the Panhandle-Plains Historical
Society Museum of 1932 at Canyon,
Texas. Architect E. F. Rittenberry also incorporated
the sculpted head of a longhorn steer
and a gridwork of local cattle brands surrounding
the entrance.</p>

<figure n="egp.arc.001.03" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Nebraska State Capitol</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Perhaps no effort surpassed that of architect
Bertram Goodhue for the Nebraska State Capitol.
It was not regional in style but was an
effort to generate monumental form that was
responsive to the Plains landscape. Though
much about its design and embellishment was
anticipated by the local elite, it came to Goodhue
alone to conceive of the broad horizontal
base and landmark tower in terms that were
modern and more explicitly symbolic of place.
Goodhue's genius needed an equal in local visionary
Hartley Burr Alexander to develop the
thematic elaboration of the building. His plan
for the murals, mosaics, exterior sculpture,
and inscriptions was broadly historical, occasionally
transcendental, and firmly rooted in
the ethnocentric milieu. Themes associated
with place were prominent.</p>

<p>However one might criticize the Canyon
and Lincoln buildings today (or even the one
at Mitchell), they provide occasions for looking
back at place, at least toward cultural
place. All three are expressions of regional
identity that are still locally revered. But the
thinking behind their expression was as fleet
ing as a late summer thunderstorm. Modern
thinking never really looked back at place
again. (I. M. Pei's National Center for Atmospheric
Research at Boulder may be an exception
of a different sort.)</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Hypermodernity</head>

<p>Both the Canyon and Lincoln buildings were
reflective of an emerging modern style. In
spite of its initial theoretical concern with
"space," even European modernism in the
Plains ultimately continued to promote a progressive
and reductive architectural style. This
cause has been taken up with even more seriousness
by so-called postmodern (really
hypermodern) developments, in which now,
quite literally, decorated facades and the seeking
of new forms have again become principal
architectural problems.</p>

<p>Other aspects of modernism's focused reductionism
have different consequences. We
can look to a further loss of the sense of body
in place that might have been anticipated by
one of the region's most noted modernists,
Norman, Oklahoma's Bruce Goff. The philosophical
and psychological split of mind from
body that has informed this essay and that rift
site from place could be exaggerated by Goff's
free expressions, which seem to have been
made possible only by the prior abstract detachment
of site from place. He further pursued
architecture as a container split apart
from the outside, a container in which the
appearance of nature, if it were allowed at all,
would be thoroughly domesticated and constrained
from the inside.</p>

<p>This latter aspect of Goff's production raises
issues concerning a hypermodern extension of
the replacement. Of what we can say is left of
spontaneous Great Plains place (topography
and atmosphere), neither seems destined to
survive our assault. Suburbanization's sprawling
consumption of land increasingly results
in the massive replacement of terrain and topsoil.
Topography is forced into the flat linear
conditions of abstract space and the engineer's
drawing board and then is sometimes mechanically
reintroduced to add "character" to
the new, designed landscape.</p>

<p>Concerning atmosphere, the replacement
further affects human embodiment in place.
The main vehicle for this effort is air conditioning,
a technology that, no matter how desirable
under acute health-related conditions,
conflicts with atmospheric place beyond the
effects of consumption and pollution. Hypermodern
promotion of air conditioning, designed
within a very narrow and absolute
"comfort zone," serves to further human disembodiment
through a more anesthetized
disengagement from place than ever before.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">IMAGES AND ICONS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ii.014">Corn Palace</ref> /
<hi rend="smallcaps">INDUSTRY</hi>: <ref n="egp.ind.022">Fur Trade</ref>, <ref n="egp.ind.036">Lumberyards</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">NATIVE AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.na.080">Paleo-Indians</ref>, <ref n="egp.na.082">Pawnees</ref>, <ref n="egp.na.102">Sacred Geography</ref>, <ref n="egp.na.127">Wichitas</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">WAR</hi>: <ref n="egp.war.017">Frontier Forts</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>David Murphy<lb/>
Nebraska State Historical Society</signed>
</closer>
</div2>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Boddy, Trevor, ed. "Special Issue on Prairie Architecture."
<title level="j">Prairie Forum</title> 5, no. 2 (1980).</bibl> <bibl>Erpestad, David, and David
Wood. <title level="j">Building South Dakota: A Historical Survey of the State's Architecture to 1945</title>. Pierre: South Dakota State Historical
Society Press, 1997.</bibl> <bibl>Henderson, Arn, Frank Parman,
and Dortha Henderson. <title level="j">Architecture in Oklahoma: Landmark and Vernacular</title>. Norman <hi rend="smallcaps">OK</hi>: Point Rivers
Press, 1978.</bibl> <bibl>Henry, Jay C. <hi rend="italic">Architecture in Texas, 1895–1945</hi>.
Austin: University of Texas Press, 1993.</bibl> <bibl>"Historic Places:
The National Register for Nebraska." <title level="j">Nebraska History</title> 70,
no. 1 (1989).</bibl> <bibl>Nabokov, Peter, and Robert Easton. <title level="j">Native American Architecture</title>. New York: Oxford University
Press, 1989: 122–73.</bibl> <bibl>Noel, Thomas J. <title level="j">The Buildings of Colorado</title>.
New York: Oxford University Press, 1997.</bibl> <bibl>Sachs,
David H., and George Ehrlich. <title level="j">Guide to Kansas Architecture</title>.
Lawrence: University Press of Kansas, 1996.</bibl> <bibl>Starr,
Eileen F. <title level="j">Architecture in the Cowboy State, 1849–1940: A Guide</title>. Glendo <hi rend="smallcaps">WY</hi>: High Plains Press, 1992.</bibl> <bibl>Upton, Dell,
ed. <title level="j">America's Architectural Roots: Ethnic Groups That Built America</title>. Building Watchers Series. Washington <hi rend="smallcaps">DC</hi>: Preservation
Press, 1986: 100–165.</bibl>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>