<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.na.127 SYSTEM "egp.na.127.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.na.127">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Wichitas</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Robert L. Brooks</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.na.127</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Brooks, Robert L.">Robert L. Brooks</author>. <title level="a">"Wichitas."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">609-610</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-20</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">WICHITAS</head>

<figure n="egp.na.127" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Wichita Indian grass house</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>When the Spanish explorer Coronado traveled
across the Southern Plains in 1541 in
search of the fabled riches of Quivira, he encountered
large villages of a distinctive tattooed
people along the Great Bend of the Arkansas
River, near present-day Arkansas City,
Kansas. This was the initial European contact
with the Native Americans now recognized as
the Wichita and Affiliated Tribes.</p>

<p>Early historic accounts from Coronado's
<hi rend="italic">entrada</hi> and the later O&#241;ate expedition found
the Wichitas referring to themselves as the
<hi rend="italic">Quicasquiris</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Quirasquiris</hi> (or <hi rend="italic">Ki‘dikir' eis</hi>,
based on interviews conducted with tribal
members in 1949). Close study of Spanish and
French explorers' visits with the Wichitas reveals
a loosely aligned confederacy of a number
of bands. These included the Taovayas,
Tawakonis, Iscanis-Wacos, and the Wichitas
proper. By the eighteenth century the Kitsais,
another tribe related to the Wichita subgroups,
had been assimilated by the Wichitas.</p>

<p>Linguistically, the Wichita language belongs
to the Caddoan language family that also includes
the Pawnee, Kitsai, Caddo, and Arikara
languages. Historically, Wichita is most closely
related to the Northern Caddoan subfamily
languages of Kitsai and Pawnee and is more
distantly related to Caddo of Proto-Caddoan
derivation.</p>

<p>While many Native groups traditionally recognized
as Plains societies (for example, the
Cheyennes) have a relatively recent history in
the Southern Plains, the Wichitas have been
there for 2,000 to 2,500 years. They were among
a diffuse group of people, possibly from Louisiana
or Mississippi, who began a westward
movement some 3,000 years ago. This migration
gradually extended across the Plains, displacing
existing residents. During this expansion,
the newcomers began to develop regional
distinctions in material culture, means of subsistence,
and social, political, and religious organization.
Archeologists now link these regional
expressions to the historic Caddo, Kitsai, Wichita,
Pawnee, and Arikara tribes. Archeological
evidence and historic accounts reveal that the
Wichitas ranged over much of the Southern
Plains, including what is currently northcentral
Texas, Oklahoma, and south-central
Kansas.</p>

<p>Wichita subsistence practices reflected a
dual economy based on farming and hunting.
During the spring and summer they cultivated
sizable plots of corn, beans, and squash and
harvested wild plants such as amaranth and
sunflower. Bison, deer, and small game were
hunted. In the fall and winter the Wichitas
conducted large-scale communal bison hunts.
Greater reliance on hunting by a traditionally
agricultural people was probably connected to
the introduction of the horse in the seventeenth
century.</p>

<p>The Aboriginal material culture of the
Wichitas closely parallels that of other Plains
village societies. A variety of natural products,
such as animal bones and hides, wood, plant
fiber, stone, and clay, were used in the manufacture
of domestic goods, clothing, and ornaments.
Much of the traditional technology
was abandoned by the late nineteenth century
in favor of European American goods. The
most distinctive aspect of the Wichita material
world was their beehive-shaped grass houses.
These houses ranged from fifteen to thirty feet
in diameter and twelve to twenty feet in height.
The dwelling, consisting of fourteen to sixteen
cedar posts with a frame of smaller cedar and
willow poles, was covered with bundles of
coarse grass. Four small poles extended about
three feet from the peak of the house, representing
the four world quarters or gods. Wichita
dwellings were designed to house extended
family units of roughly eight to ten people.
Villages had from thirty to several hundred
such residences. Wichita settlements in the
eighteenth century also typically contained a
palisade or fortification, although not all the
houses of the village would be within this protected
area.</p>

<p>Wichita society has been generally viewed
as highly egalitarian, with male status acquired
through individual achievements in
hunting and warfare. However, there are indications
that some Wichita subgroups, such
as the Tawakonis, had chiefs or rulers with
greater authority; inheritance of these positions
appears likely to have occurred in some
instances. A typical Wichita village would
have a principal chief elected by the head warriors,
a leader responsible for finding new village
locations, shamans or medicine men,
warriors, elders, and "no-count men," who
were servants to the chief, leader, or priests.
Women of the village were responsible for
planting and tending the crops as well as most
of the labor-intensive tasks, such as building
houses, collecting firewood, and hauling water.
Men were principally involved in hunting
and warfare. As was the case in many Native
American farming societies, kinship was matrilinear,
or traced through the woman's side,
and matrilocal, meaning that the husband
moved to the residence of the wife's family
after marriage.</p>

<p>The Wichitas recognized a host of sacred figures.
These were divided into the gods and goddesses
of the earth and sky. Supreme among
these was the god known as <hi rend="italic">Kinnikasus</hi> (Man
Never Known On Earth), who was responsible
for the creation of the universe and its parts.
Other male gods controlled the heavens (with
the exception of the moon goddess), whereas
goddesses&#8212;the goddess of water, for example&#8212;
reigned on earth. The Wichitas also believed
that all animate and inanimate objects possessed
a spirit and that everything could assume more
than its apparent natural characteristics. These
concepts played a significant role in the development
of supernatural powers among the medicine
men. The Wichitas have also been credited
with establishing the calumet ceremony as a
means of initiating truce conditions among
Plains societies.</p>

<p>The arrival of Europeans on the Southern
Plains dramatically transformed Plains tribes.
The presence of the horse and European
goods, weapons, and diseases brought about
drastic changes in demographics, subsistence
economies, and political structures of most
tribes, including the Wichitas. The French and
Spanish also manipulated the tribes, pitting
them against each other in an effort to gain
control of the Southern Plains. In the seventeenth
and eighteenth centuries, the Wichitas
had continuous conflicts with the Apaches
and Comanches to the west and the Osages to
the east. By the mid-eighteenth century, they
had established peace with the Comanches.
Conflicts continued with the Apaches and
Osages. In the 1750s the Osages forced the
Wichitas from the Great Bend of the Arkansas
River to the middle reaches of the Red River.
The Wichitas maintained good relations with
the French but never fully embraced Spanish
authority. They won a major victory over the
Spanish in 1759 when Col. Diego Ortiz Parilla
failed in his attack on a Wichita village on the
Red River.</p>

<p>The Wichitas may have had a total population
of around 10,000 in the 1700s. Subsequently,
introduced diseases and continuing
conflicts with whites and other Indians led to
significant population decline. By the late eighteenth
century their population had dropped
to about 4,000, and by the 1890s only 153 Wichitas
remained.</p>

<p>In 1872 the Wichitas ceded all claims to their
ancestral lands in Texas and Indian Territory to
the United States and were left with a 743,000-
acre reservation in present-day Caddo County,
Oklahoma. However, this agreement was never
ratified, and their title to the land remained in
doubt. In 1901 the reservation was allotted and
greatly reduced by the sale of "surplus lands."</p>

<p>The Wichita and Affiliated Tribes currently
reside adjacent to the Anadarko Agency just
north of Anadarko, Oklahoma. They hold
some 1,260 acres of land in common trust
with the Caddo and Delaware tribes. In 1995
there were 1,798 Wichitas, most of whom lived
in Oklahoma.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Robert L. Brooks</signed>
University of Oklahoma</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Dorsey, George A. <title level="m">The Mythology of the Wichita</title>. Washington
<hi rend="smallcaps">DC</hi>: Carnegie Institution, 1904.</bibl> <bibl>John, Elizabeth
A. H. <title level="m">Storms Brewed in Other Men's Worlds</title>. College Station:
Texas <hi rend="smallcaps">A&amp;M</hi> University Press, 1975.</bibl> <bibl>Newcomb, W. W.
Jr. <title level="m">The Indians of Texas</title>. Austin: University of Texas Press,
1961.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>