<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.tra.022</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Oregon Trail</field>
      <field name="author">Collister, Paul</field>
      <field name="text">

 




OREGON TRAIL


A man shows the width of the Oregon Trail, between 1920 and 1930


The Oregon Trail began as a fur traders' route
across the Great Plains in 1824 with the discovery
of South Pass through the Rocky Mountains.
The pack trains and, later, the wagon
caravans that supplied the mountain rendezvous
started up the trail from Independence
and Westport Landing in the present-day Kansas
City area. They moved northwestward,
tracing the Kansas and Little Blue Rivers to the
Platte, then followed its southern bank westward
across the Plains. Other traffic left Bellevue,
south of present-day Omaha, to follow
the north side of the Platte to the rendezvous.

The fur trade era had shaded into that of the
Pacific Coast migrations by the early 1840s.
The first missionaries and emigrants bound
for California and Oregon accompanied fur
trade caravans, and former mountain men
guided the first emigrant trains. These early
migrants generally came from the Mississippi
River valley, and farm families predominated.
Some 875 settlers traveled the Oregon Trail in
1843, and by 1847 the migration across the Central
Plains had swelled to 4,000–5,000 people.

Emigrants used all manner of conveyances,
though mostly the familiar canvas-topped
wagons. These wagons generally had light
bodies and flat beds caulked for stream crossings.
Oxen pulled the majority of the wagons;
mules and horses hauled the rest. Settlers
formed themselves into trains and, within
trains, into "messes," or a team of travelers
sharing a wagon. Various guides for emigrants,
available at the points of departure,
described in detail what was needed for the
trip.

In the mid-1840s American leaders decided
that this growing migration merited protection.
In 1848 Fort Kearny was founded in the
central Platte River valley, and a year later,
Fort Laramie was remodeled from the fur
trading post, Fort John, near the mouth of the
Laramie River. These two major forts offered
provisions, postal and blacksmith services,
and medical care.

California gold inspired migrations in 1849
and 1850 that dwarfed the earlier migrations.
About 50,000 emigrants went overland to
Oregon and, mainly, California in the latter
year. This new wave featured a greater proportion
of single men and husbands traveling
without families, seeking quick wealth rather
than new homes. These gold seekers generally
came from the upper Mississippi River valley
and were more urban in origin than earlier
travelers. The upriver towns of Weston and St.
Joseph, Missouri, joined the Kansas City area
as major departure points, as did the site of
the first abortive Fort Kearny at present-day
Nebraska City, Nebraska. Farthest north,
Kanesville (Council Bluffs), Iowa, served an
important stream of travel up the north side
of the Platte. After a drop in 1851, heavy traffic
to California resumed in 1852, this time with
more families. Thereafter, migration continued
at a more moderate pace, with something
like 250,000-300,000 people traveling
the trail across the Plains through 1866.

These later migrants followed well-established
routes. Several streams of traffic converged
east of Fort Kearny in the central Platte
River valley. The south-side throng moved
west and crossed the South Platte at three
main crossings to Ash Hollow and the North
Platte valley. The Upper or Old California
Crossing involved a descent into Ash Hollow
down Windlass Hill. Otherwise, travelers entered
Ash Hollow from the east. The road then
lay along the south side of the North Platte
through Robidoux and Mitchell Passes, which
featured trading posts and blacksmith facilities.
From the late 1850s the Later California
Crossing near Julesburg, Colorado, led to a
new route that reached the North Platte at
Courthouse Rock. The south-siders made a
dangerous crossing of the Laramie River at the
fort. Meanwhile, north-siders from Council
Bluffs gathered at the site of present-day Fremont,
Nebraska, then negotiated the dangerous
Loup River crossing. From there they
moved up the north side of the Platte and
North Platte to join the south-siders at Fort
Laramie. By the early 1850s precarious toll
bridges and ferries existed at the Fort Laramie
crossings. From Fort Laramie, travelers hoped
to reach South Pass by around July 4, having
ideally left the Missouri River around April 15.

Naturally, months on the road through a
sometimes harsh land took a toll on travelers,
though emigrant mortality probably did not
much exceed that among the general American
population. Despite apprehensions, few
died at the hands of Plains Indians. Many
more died from accidents: mishaps with firearms,
drownings, and injuries suffered while
driving wagons or handling livestock. Disease,
especially Asiatic cholera, by far killed the
most.

The trail developed new features as emigration
continued. Government mail contracts
stimulated increasingly reliable stagecoach service
from 1850 on. Military contracts launched
large-scale freighting on the trail in 1855. The
Pikes Peak gold rush of 1859 created a thriving
commerce between Colorado and the Nebraska
river towns, which replaced the northwestern
Missouri towns as the dominant outfitting
and departure points. This new traffic
brought about a string of stage stations and
road ranches, which, along with proliferating
bridges and ferries, eliminated much of the
hazard of overland travel.

Abandonment of the Oregon Trail began in
1862. In that year stagecoaches began to follow
the new Overland Trail, moving southwest
from Julesburg, avoiding Indian depredations
beyond Fort Laramie. Emigrant travel followed.
The North Platte valley thus became
largely a military road, except for new civilian
travel bound for the Montana gold fields. In
1866 Union Pacific rails were laid down opposite
Fort Kearny, and the great era of the
Oregon Trail ended.

See also LAW: Overland Trail Constitutions.


Paul Collister
Lincoln, Nebraska




Federal Writers' Project. The Oregon Trail: The Missouri
River to the Pacific Ocean. New York: Hastings House,
1939; reprint, Somerset Publishers, 1972. Mattes, Merrill J.
The Great Platte River Road: The Covered Wagon Mainline
via Fort Kearny to Fort Laramie. Lincoln: Nebraska State
Historical Society, 1969. Unruh, John D., Jr. The Plains
Across: The Overlanders and the Trans-Mississippi West,
1840–60. Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 1979.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>