<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.na.032</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Half-Breed Tract</field>
      <field name="author">Waters, William T.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




HALF-BREED TRACT

The Half-Breed Tract, also known as the Nemaha
Half-Breed Reservation or Reserve, was
established on July 15, 1830, with the signing of
the Treaty of Prairie du Chien in Michigan
Territory. The Half-Breed Tract was established
to provide a homeland for tribal members
of mixed ancestry, at the request of the
signatory Native American nations, the Otoe-
Missourias, Omahas, and Iowas, and on behalf
of the Santees and Yanktons. Article 10 of the
treaty ceded approximately 138,000 acres of
Otoe-Missouria land that extended from the
Missouri River westward between the Great
(Big) Nemaha and Little Nemaha Rivers to
form a triangular tract located in what is now
southeastern Nebraska. This was the first
treaty in which Congress authorized the allotment
of land in severalty to Native Americans.

On September 10, 1860, following thirty
years of controversy regarding the western
boundary of the tract, Lewis Neal became the
first of 389 individuals to receive a patent of
land allotted in severalty. Because there were
too many eligible mixed-blood claimants,
each allottee received only 320 acres instead of
640 acres originally suggested in the Treaty of
Prairie du Chien. By the 1870s most of the land
allotted in the Half-Breed Tract had been
taken over by white settlers, who sometimes
used alcohol to entice mixed-bloods to sell,
or who married mixed-bloods and so gained
entitlement to allotments. The first test of Native
American land severalty in the United
States ended in complete failure in terms of
the original intention of the Treaty of Prairie
du Chien signatories.


William T. Waters
University of Nebraska at Kearney




Chapman, Berlin B. The Otoes and Missourias: A Study of
Indian Removal and the Legal Aftermath. Oklahoma City:
Time Journal Publishing Co., 1965. Johansen, Gregory J.
"To Make Some Provision for Their Half-Breeds, The
Nemaha Half-Breed Reserve, 1830–66." Nebraska History
67 (1986): 8–29.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>