<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ag.015</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Buffalo Ranching</field>
      <field name="author">Hughes, T. R.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BUFFALO RANCHING

Most people are aware of the near extermination
of the Plains buffalo (Bison bison) in the
1870s from a high point population of perhaps
40 million in the mid-1800s. Not so widely
known is the story of the restoration of the
Plains buffalo and the expanding buffalo
ranching scene today.

From an estimated 1,500 animals around
1900, buffalo numbers have expanded to a
current U.S. population of approximately
300,000, with roughly 40 percent located in
the Great Plains region. The 1996 Canadian
Census of Agriculture reported an additional
45,235 bison were being raised on 745 farms
across Canada. Alberta, with 334 farms and
22,782 bison, is by far the leader in production.
Canadian numbers include both the
Plains bison and the indigenous Woods bison
subspecies.

In the United States, government herds,
both state and federal, have remained relatively
constant in number over the past thirty
years. The percentage of buffalo owned and
managed by private individuals has grown
dramatically and now represents approximately
90 percent of the total population. This
change in the percentage of buffalo that are
privately owned has been accompanied by a
shift toward treating the animal as domestic
livestock by many producers.

The National Buffalo Association was
founded in 1966. Its primary goal was to promote
the marketing of buffalo meat and byproducts.
In 1974 the American Bison Association
was founded and took a more aggressive
approach to the raising and marketing of the
animal. In 1995 the two organizations combined
to form the National Bison Association
(NBA). The NBA represents more than 2,000
producers, ranging from many who raise just a
few animals (fifty or less) to several large
ranches each raising thousands of animals.
The large, and many moderate-size, ranches
typically finish animals in feedlots and market
the meat on a large scale to restaurants and the
public. One cooperative in New Rockford,
North Dakota, processes about 10,000 animals
per year.

Producers in the NBA have been increasing
research into the formulation of feeds and
selection of breeding stock to improve the
meat-producing ability of the buffalo. They
do not support the use of hormones and other
such feed additives. The NBA sponsors a Gold
Trophy show and sale annually in Denver in
connection with the National Western Livestock
Show.

Numerous state and regional associations
have sprung up across the country and the
Great Plains to assist in regional production
and marketing. Another philosophy gaining
renewed interest since the 1990s places emphasis
on a more natural approach to the
management, raising, and finishing of buffalo.
The Great Plains Buffalo Association was
formed in 1996 to network grass-fed, grassfinished-
oriented producers.

In 1992, another influential organization
entered onto the buffalo industry scene. That
year Native American tribes formed the Inter-
Tribal Bison Cooperative (ITBC). Now numbering
about fifty tribes nationwide, with
more than half of them in the Great Plains
region, the ITBC's goal is to restore buffalo to
reservation lands. The cooperative also takes a
more spiritual approach to the management
of buffalo. Respect for the animal and the environment
is central to the tribes' care of the
buffalo. With substantial land resources, the
ITBC is becoming an increasingly important
player in the marketing of buffalo products.


T. R. Hughes
Crawford, Nebraska





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>