<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ha.042</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Spanish-Comanche Treaties</field>
      <field name="author">Hämäläinen, Pekka</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SPANISH-COMANCHE TREATIES

In November 1785 several thousand western
Comanches congregated at their favorite wintering
spot at the Big Timbers of the Arkansas
River to discuss important news: after years of
tiring mediation, Juan Bautista de Anza, the
governor of New Mexico, wanted to negotiate
peace with the Kotsoteka, Yamparika, and
Jupe Comanches. Although the eastern Comanche
bands had already entered into an accord
with the Texan Spanish in October, some
western bands remained recalcitrant. The opposition
centered on Toro Blanco, who was
backed by the bands that supported themselves
by raiding New Mexican horse ranches.
To resolve the deadlock, the peace faction assassinated
Toro Blanco and forced his followers
to disperse.

In February 1786 Ecueracapa, a Kotsoteka
chief representing the peace proponents, arrived
in Santa Fe, where he hammered out the
treaty stipulations with Governor Anza. The
Spanish promised the Comanches free access
to New Mexican markets and trade fairs, distribution
of presents to friendly chiefs, and
regulation of the fairs so that the shrewd New
Mexican traders could not cheat their Native
clients. In return, the Comanches agreed to
stop raiding, to unite behind one principal
chief who would negotiate with the Spanish,
and to refrain from trading with foreigners,
particularly Americans. There also would be
a joint Comanche-Spanish war against the
Lipan Apaches, whom both parties wanted to
expunge from New Mexico's eastern border.
The alliance was sealed in an elaborate ceremony
at which Anza distributed lavish gifts,
including presenting Ecueracapa with a Spanish
flag and a saber. The Comanches returned
a New Mexican captive and "buried the war."

This Comanche–New Mexican treaty is one
of the major turning points in the history of the
Southern Plains. It marked a profound change
in Spain's Plains Indian policy by ushering in
the abandonment of the traditional military
approach in favor of a diplomatic-commercial
option. This shift pacified the southwestern
Plains for over a generation: from 1786 to 1821
accommodation and trade rather than violence
defined Comanche.New Mexican relations.
On the other hand, the treaty was a disaster
to the Lipans, who were soon forced
to retreat to the Sangre de Cristo Mountains
by the powerful Comanche-Spanish alliance.
The counterpart of the 1786 Comanche.New
Mexican treaty, the 1785 Comanche-Texan accord,
proved less successful. Comanche-Texas
trade did increase after 1785, but the province's
officials lacked the necessary funds to maintain
a consistent Indian policy. As a result,
Comanche raids in Texas continued throughout
the Spanish era.

See also NATIVE AMERICANS: Comanches.


Pekka Hämäläinen
Texas A&amp;M University




Kavanagh, Thomas W. The Comanches: A History, 1706– 1875. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1999.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>