<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.sr.005</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Basketball</field>
      <field name="author">Shelley, Fred M.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BASKETBALL

The sport of basketball has a long and productive
history in the Great Plains. Plains states
and their universities have contributed many
important players and coaches to this popular
American sport.

Basketball was invented by Dr. James Naismith
in Springfield, Massachusetts, in 1891.
Naismith later moved to Lawrence, Kansas, as
an instructor of physical education at the University
of Kansas and the university's head
basketball coach. Under Naismith and his successors,
Kansas ranks third on the all-time National
Collegiate Athletic Association (NCAA)
victory list. The two universities with more
victories were coached for many years by
Plains natives Adolph Rupp of Halstead, Kansas
(at Kentucky), and Dean Smith of Emporia,
Kansas (at North Carolina).

Several college basketball teams from the
Plains states have won national championships.
Wyoming won in 1943, and Oklahoma
State (then known as Oklahoma A&amp;M) won
titles in 1944 and 1945. The Cowboys were led
by Bob Kurland, who became college basketball's
first dominant big man. The University
of Texas at El Paso (then Texas Western) won
in 1966. The University of Kansas won the title
in 1988.

Several Plains natives have been recognized
as all-Americans for their achievements on the
basketball court. Bob Boozer of Omaha twice
won all-American honors at Kansas State University
in the 1950s. Wichita, Kansas, produced
all-Americans Darnell Valentine of the University
of Kansas (1980) and Antoine Carr
of Wichita State University (1981). Wayman
Tisdale, born in Fort Worth, Texas, and raised
in Tulsa, Oklahoma, became the first freshman
to achieve all-American status at Oklahoma in
1983. He repeated as all-American in 1984 and
1985. Another Sooner, Stacey King of Lawton,
Oklahoma, was an all-American in 1989. Mark
Price of Enid, Oklahoma, became an all-American
for Georgia Tech in the late 1980s.
Bryant "Big Country" Reeves of Gans, Oklahoma,
was an all-American center at Oklahoma
State University in 1995.

Many of these college stars went on to fame
as professional basketball players. In addition,
Bill Sharman from Abilene, Texas, was a member
of the Boston Celtics dynasty, which won
eleven National Basketball Association (NBA)
championships between 1957 and 1969. Sharman
also coached the Los Angeles Lakers to the
nba title in 1971. The NBA's all-time leader in
win percentage for coaches is coach Phil Jackson
(Chicago Bulls/Los Angeles Lakers) of
Williston, North Dakota. Two of the old American
Basketball Association's stars were Zelmo
Beaty of Hillister, Texas, and Ron Boone of
Oklahoma City, Oklahoma.

In addition to organized professional and
college basketball, the Plains states have been
home to several important amateur basketball
teams. Premier among these were the 66ers
of Bartlesville, Oklahoma. Sponsored by the
Phillips Petroleum Company, the 66ers attracted
Kurland and other college stars of the
1940s and 1950s. They won several Amateur
Athletic Union championships, and 66er players
formed the core of U.S. basketball teams
that won gold medals at the Olympic Games
in 1948 and 1952. The 66er players also held
professional positions with Phillips. Kurland
eventually became mayor of Bartlesville, and
several other 66ers rose to high executive positions
with the company.

The Plains states have been a particularly
productive source of women's basketball players
and coaches. The Edmonton Grads were
the best women's basketball team in the world
in the 1920s and 1930s. Jody Conradt of Goldthwaite,
Texas, the longtime coach of the University
of Texas women's basketball team, is
the all-time victories leader among women's
coaches. Conradt was elected to the Basketball
Hall of Fame in 1998. Two Plains natives have
won the Wade Trophy, which is awarded annually
to the outstanding player in women's
college basketball. Kamie Etheridge of Lubbock,
Texas, who won in 1986, played for Conradt
at the University of Texas. Lynette Woodard
of Wichita, Kansas, who won the Wade
Trophy in 1981 while playing for the University
of Kansas, is women's college basketball's all-time
leading scorer. Sheryl Swoopes of Brownfield,
Texas, was the outstanding player in the
women's Final Four in 1993 while leading
Texas Tech to the national championship.


Fred M. Shelley
Southwest Texas State University




Douchant, Mike, ed. The Encyclopedia of College Basketball.
Detroit: Gaines, 1995. Porter, David L., ed. Biographical
Dictionary of American Sports: Basketball and Other
Indoor Sports. Westport CT: Greenwood Press, 1989.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>