<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.rel.008</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Buddhism</field>
      <field name="author">Simmer-Brown, Judith</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BUDDHISM

Buddhism traces its origins to a sixth century
B.C. Indian prince who practiced meditation
until he became realized as the Buddha, or
"enlightened one." During the next two and a
half millennia, Buddhism became a major religious
tradition, thriving in Southeast Asia as
Theravada ("the tradition of the elders"), East
Asia as Mahayana ("the great vehicle"), and
Central Asia as Vajrayana ("the diamond vehicle").
Common practices in these three "vehicles"
are meditation, cultivation of wisdom
and compassion, and the development of
Buddhist communities.

Buddhist adherents now live mainly in
larger towns and cities of the Great Plains in
two general populations (although actual census
figures are not available). First, there are
the Asian American communities of larger
cities such as Omaha, Billings, and Calgary. In
these cities, recently established immigrants
from Asia seek to knit together their ancestral
traditions with Buddhist observance. The
Vietnamese of Oklahoma City have expressed
economic and social confidence with a beautiful
new temple; Thai and Laotian communities
have established impressive Theravada centers
just beyond the Plains borders in Houston,
Dallas, and elsewhere in Texas. Other Asian
communities have multigenerational history
in the Great Plains, and Buddhist temples serve
to join religion, spirituality, and culture in a
single environment. The Buddhist Churches
of America (BCA) was first established around
1900 as the American mission of the Jodo Shinshu,
a popular Pure Land sect from Japan. The
Denver Buddhist Temple has long owned
prime downtown real estate to house not only
its temple, but a community center, subsidized
housing for seniors, and shopping center.

The second category of adherents, widely
distributed throughout the Plains, are "convert"
communities, for whom Buddhism is
not their ancestral tradition. These groups fall
into the three major "vehicles" described
above. The Theravada groups practice vipassana
(insight) meditation with little ritual or
cultural accouterments. Vipassana groups
gather weekly or biweekly for sitting meditation
(zazen) and "dharma talks" given on tape
or by members or visiting teachers. Small centers
based in private homes can be found from
Edmonton and Calgary south to Boulder,
Santa Fe, and Dallas. They communicate
through networking, newsletters, and public
posting.

The primary Mahayana meditation practiced
is Zen, which originated in Japan and China.
Tiny Zen centers dot the Great Plains from
Rapid City to Missoula and from Omaha to
Amarillo, sporting catchy names like "Laughing
Teabowl," "Empty Sky," and "Great Mountain."
Many of these centers are associated with the
Vietnamese Zen master Thich Nhat Hanh, the
monk who played an important role in ending
the U.S.-Vietnam War in his homeland. Others
trace their lineages to the Japanese traditions of
Katagiri Roshi, who established a center in Minneapolis
in the 1960s, or of Maezumi Roshi from
Los Angeles. The Zen centers also stress zazen,
scheduled multiple times each week, as well as
dharma talks and readings from Zen classics.

Vajrayana Buddhism, associated with Tibet,
has centers in Edmonton, Kansas City, and
Dallas, but the greatest concentration of Vajrayana
practice is in Boulder, Colorado, the
home of Naropa University, which in 2000 had
an enrollment of 900. The Buddhist-inspired
accredited university was founded by Chögyam,
Trungpa, a teacher (lama) who escaped from
the Chinese invasion of Tibet in 1959. Vajrayana
communities, centered on authorized teachers,
are characterized by sitting meditation, ritual
practice, tightly knit communities, rigorous
study programs, and dharma talks.

See also ASIAN AMERICANS: Denver Buddhist Temple.


Judith Simmer-Brown
Naropa University




Morreale, Don, ed. The Complete Guide to Buddhist America.
Boston: Shambhala Publications, 1998. Prebish,
Charles S. Luminous Passage: The Practice and Study of
Buddhism in America. Berkeley: University of California
Press, 1999. Seager, Richard Hughes. Buddhism in America.
New York: Columbia University Press, 1999.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>