<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.rel.031</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Lac Ste. Anne Pilgrimage</field>
      <field name="author">Huel, Raymond J. A.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




LAC STE. ANNE PILGRIMAGE

This pilgrimage is the most famous and the
most popular of the Roman Catholic pilgrimages
in western Canada. It is held annually
at Lac Ste. Anne, about forty miles west
of Edmonton, Alberta, in the third week of
July, to coincide with the feast day of Saint
Anne (July 26). Saint Anne, mother of the Virgin
Mary, is also the patron saint of childless
women and miners, as well as the miracle
worker of Canada. The pilgrimage was inaugurated
in 1889 by Joseph Lestanc, a Missionary
Oblate of Mary Immaculate, who, while
visiting the shrine of Saint Anne of Auray in
his native Brittany, felt the need to work ardently
to revive the cult of Saint Anne and to
institute pilgrimages in her honor. Upon Lestanc's
return to Canada, a new chapel was
built at the Lac Ste. Anne Mission, and he
obtained a statue of the saint that had touched
the famous relics at Sainte Anne de Beaupré in
Quebec.

Religious services associated with the pilgrimage
include penitential rites, mass and
Holy Communion, recitation of the rosary,
the blessing of the sick, the stations of the
cross, benediction of the Blessed Sacrament,
and the blessing of the lake. First Nations languages
such as Cree and Blackfoot are used
extensively in these services. Today the annual
pilgrimage attracts thousands of Indians and
Métis from the western provinces and the
Northwest Territories, and it reflects a blend
of traditional Catholic practices implanted
long ago by French-speaking Oblate missionaries
and traditional Native ceremonies and
rituals.


Raymond J. A. Huel
University of Lethbridge




Provincial Archives of Alberta, Fonds Oblat de la province
Alberta-Saskatchewan, Lac Ste Anne, 6, Codex historicus,
Edmonton, Alberta: Provincial Archives of Alberta, 1889–1964.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>