<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.gen.011</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Earhart, Amelia (1897-1937)</field>
      <field name="author">Goldstein, Donald M.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




EARHART, AMELIA (1897-1937)


Amelia Earhart in Denver, Colorado, June 3, 1931


Amelia Earhart was a woman who was ahead
of her time. She was a pioneer aviator, a pacifist,
and a feminist who, although daubed with
grease, was unmistakably a lady. Earhart was
born July 24, 1897, in Atchison, Kansas. On
both sides, her family had been American since
before the Revolution. Her maternal grandfather was a judge who was upright, conventional,
and moderately wealthy. Her paternal
grandfather was a minister, whose saintliness
was matched only by his poverty. The judge's
gentle, lovable daughter married the minister's
brilliant, irresponsible son and the results were
Amelia Earhart and her younger sister, Muriel.
The girls initially enjoyed an idyllic childhood,
spending the school year with their grandparents
in Atchison and the summers with
their parents in Kansas City. However, when
alcoholism caught up with her father it all
came apart, and the family drifted around the
Midwest, living in poor circumstances. Amelia
graduated from high school in Chicago in 1916.

A stint in a Canadian military hospital during
World War I left her a confirmed pacifist
and gave her a first glimpse of aviation activity,
but she did not became involved herself
until a few years later when the family moved
to California. Her first flight was in 1920, and
in 1921 she gained her license from the National
Aeronautics Association. The next year
she set the women's altitude record (14,000
feet).

In 1928, while working as a social worker in
Boston, Amelia had an opportunity that
brought her worldwide recognition. A transatlantic
flight had been arranged, and the
sponsor wanted a woman aboard who not
only could fly but also could represent the
United States with grace and honor. Amelia
was a natural for the position. One of those
who interviewed her was George Palmer Putnam
of the publishing firm G. P. Putnam and
Sons. The success of the flight brought Amelia
headlines. Although she had merely been a
passenger, she was officially the first woman to
fly across the Atlantic.

Taking advantage of her widespread fame,
Putnam (whom Amelia married on February
7, 1931) scheduled Earhart for a full program
of lectures. In addition, she wrote articles and
books to help support her mother and sister.
In her works Amelia stressed two themes: first,
she advocated aviation as a means of transportation
and promoted the unlimited possibilities
for flight in general; and second, as a pioneer
for women's rights, she strove for the
day when women would have the same educational
and career opportunities as men.

Earhart loved the beauty of flight and flew
whenever she could. Although she set several
speed records for women pilots, and in 1931
held the world altitude record for autogyros
at 18,451 feet, her specialty was long-range
routes, which she saw as heralds of regular
commercial routes. On May 20 and 21, 1932,
she made her solo transatlantic flight from
Newfoundland to Ireland. Early in 1935 she
made the first solo nonstop flight from Honolulu
to Oakland; later the same year she established
another record from Mexico City to
New York City.

In 1935 she became a.liated with Purdue
University as an aviation adviser and as a
counselor for women students. Purdue provided
her with a Lockheed Electra as a flying
laboratory. That same year, Amelia decided
that she had one more flight in her system.
She wanted to fly around the world as close to
the equator as possible. Her first attempt,
from east to west, ended in March 1937 when
her plane ground-looped as she was taking off
from Honolulu for Howland Island in the Pacific.
She had to start over again after her aircraft
was repaired. For various reasons she
changed her route to fly from west to east. On
this ill-fated flight, she sent back detailed accounts
of each leg. She appeared to be doing
well, but on the next to the last leg, from New
Guinea to Howland Island, Amelia and her
navigator, Fred Noonan, disappeared on July
2, 1937. On July 17 they were declared lost at
sea.

There the clear stream of Amelia Earhart's
life was lost in a swamp of myth and speculation.
Figuring out what happened to her has
become a sort of cottage industry, with explanations
running from the fairly plausible to
the frankly incredible. The search to find her
plane and body continues, but no one can yet
say with any degree of certainty where and
why Amelia crashed. The real tragedy was the
loss of Amelia Earhart the person: a vivid, likable,
and interesting woman who made an invaluable
contribution to aviation and women's
rights and in the process made herself one
of the best-known and best-liked personalities
of her time.


Donald M. Goldstein
University of Pittsburgh




Goldstein, Donald M., and Katherine V. Dillon. Amelia: Life of the Aviation Legend. Washington DC: Brassey's,
1998. Long, Elgen M., and Maria K. Long. Amelia Earhart: The Mystery Solved. New York: Simon and Schuster, 1999.
Rich, Doris. Amelia Earhart: A Biography. Washington DC:
Smithsonian Institution Press, 1989.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>