<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.wat.027</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Rivers</field>
      <field name="author">Jordan, Paul R.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




RIVERS


Platte River State Park, Nebraska, May 1989



Data for Selected Rivers


Gaging station name Drainage area (square kilometers) Period of discharge analysis Average discharge (cubic meters per second)


Missouri River at St. Joseph, Missouri 1,100,000 1958-96 1,300
Missouri River at Bismarck, North Dakota 480,000 1954-96 650
Missouri River near Culbertson, Montana 240,000 1958-95 300
Platte River at Louisville, Nebraska 220,000 1953-96 200
Yellowstone River near Sidney, Montana 180,000 1967-96 360
Kansas River at DeSoto, Kansas 150,000 1918-97 210
South Saskatchewan River at St. Louis, Saskatchewan 150,000 1980-96 190
Arkansas River at Ralston, Oklahoma 140,000 1977-95 170
North Saskatchewan River at Prince Alberta, Saskatchewan 130,000 1980-96 230
Red River of the North at Emerson, Manitoba 100,000 1912-95 100
Colorado River at Austin, Texas 100,000 1937-96 55
Red River near Gainesville, Texas 80,000 1937-97 94
Pecos River near Girvin, Texas 77,000 1939-96 2
Brazos River near Glen Rose, Texas 67,000 1970-96 34
Canadian River at Purcell, Oklahoma 67,000 1980-95 22
Cheyenne River at Cherry Creek, South Dakota 62,000 1961-94 23




Characteristics of rivers in the Great Plains
reflect the climatic transition from arid environments
in the lee of the Rocky Mountains
eastward to subhumid and humid tallgrass
prairies. There is much less runoff to the rivers
in the western than in the eastern Great Plains;
for example, yearly runoff averages 0.2 inch in
eastern Colorado compared to eight inches in
eastern Kansas.

About one-half of the major Plains rivers
begin in the Rocky Mountains at altitudes of
8,000 to 11,000 feet and receive substantial
flows from mountain snowmelt. After entering
the Great Plains, most of those rivers contribute
some of their flows to extensive irrigation
projects. Rivers originating in the Plains
generally have less flow available in their western
reaches, where water for irrigation is most
needed. The characteristics of the major rivers
are summarized below from north to south in
the Great Plains.

Kis-is-ska-tche-wan, which means "swift
flowing," was the Cree Indian name for the
North and South Saskatchewan Rivers. Rapid
flow and flood conditions are most extreme in
June or July of years when snowmelt in the
mountains coincides with major rainstorms
in the foothills. Dominating water resources
development in Saskatchewan is Lake Diefenbaker,
which was created by Gardiner Dam on
the South Saskatchewan and serves a variety
of purposes, including electricity generation,
irrigation, and recreation.

The Assiniboine River receives flow from
large tributaries, including the Qu'Appelle
and Souris Rivers, before joining the Red
River of the North. A connection with the
South Saskatchewan has existed since the late
1960s when the water level of Lake Diefenbaker
has been high enough for water to be
released to the Qu'Appelle River.

From its origin in western Montana to its
confluence with the Mississippi River, the
Missouri is the longest river in the United
States and has the second largest drainage
area. Early writers described the Missouri as a
muddy and a hungry river, constantly eating
at its banks. A strong current would tear away
an entire strip of forest, blocking the river
with tree trunks that hindered navigation.
Control works have since reduced these characteristics,
but landowners along the banks
where the river is not impounded still become
apprehensive every time the river rises. The
Missouri provides water supplies for Great
Falls, Montana, Omaha, Nebraska, and St.
Joseph and Kansas City, Missouri. It also provides
irrigation water and hydroelectric power
from six reservoirs on the main stem upstream
from Sioux City, Iowa. The reservoirs in North
and South Dakota extend so far along the river
that less than a quarter of the river's length in
those states has not been inundated.

Snowdrifts on the side of Yount's Peak, near
Yellowstone National Park, melt to produce
streams that combine into the Yellowstone
River, which has the upstream half of its drainage
area outside the Great Plains. After making
a journey of more than 671 miles and providing
water supply for the city of Billings, the Yellowstone
joins the Missouri at the Montana–North Dakota boundary.

Although tributaries of the North and South
Platte Rivers are less than ten miles apart in
northern Colorado, the course of the rivers
diverges through Wyoming and Colorado until
they finally flow near each other in Nebraska
and join at the city of North Platte. The Platte
River then flows eastward 310 miles across Nebraska
to join the Missouri River at Plattsmouth.
The Platte and its largest branches provide
irrigation water for vast acreages of crops.
The South Platte and tributaries provide part
of Denver's water supply. Between Lincoln and
Omaha, the Platte provides Lincoln's water
supply and part of Omaha's supply by contributing
induced recharge to wells in the adjoining
alluvium.

The Kansas River has the fifteenth largest
drainage area in the United States; however,
the river bearing that name has a length of
only 185 miles. Topeka, Lawrence, and much
of Johnson County, including the densely
populated suburbs of Kansas City, obtain water
supplies from the Kansas River.

The Arkansas River is the sixth longest in
the United States and has the ninth largest
drainage area. It supplies water for Pueblo,
Aurora, and Colorado Springs, and for extensive
irrigation. In western Kansas during
much of the year it is nearly dry. In eastern
Oklahoma, the Arkansas receives the Canadian
River, which, with tributaries, provides
about half of the water supply for Oklahoma
City.

The headwaters of the Red River are in the
New Mexico part of the level, arid Llano Estacado.
Eastward, the Red River forms much
of the Oklahoma-Texas boundary, and tributaries
provide the Wichita Falls water supply.
Similarly the Brazos and Colorado Rivers begin
on the Llano Estacado, supplying Waco
and Austin near the eastern edge of the Great
Plains.

Developments on several rivers have resulted
in both benefits and unwelcome changes. Well-documented
changes include degradation of
riverbeds downstream from dams and large reductions
in channel width of some rivers.

See also TRANSPORTATION: Water Transportation.


Paul R. Jordan
Lawrence, Kansas




Bartlett, Richard A., ed. Rolling Rivers. New York: McGraw-Hill, 1984.
Department of the Interior, Geological Survey. National Water Summary 1985—Hydrologic Events
and Surface-Water Resources. Reston VA: Water-Supply Paper
2300, 1986. Richards, J. Howard, and Ka Iu Fung, eds.
Atlas of Saskatchewan. Saskatoon: University of Saskatchewan,
1969.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>