<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fil.028</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Harlow, Jean (1911-1937)</field>
      <field name="author">Steen, David</field>
      <field name="text">

 




HARLOW, JEAN (1911-1937)

Jean Harlow circa 1930
     

Jean Harlow, the platinum blond embodiment
of sexual glamour in Hollywood's Golden Age,
was born Harlean Carpenter in Kansas City,
Missouri, on March 3, 1911. An only child doted
upon by her dentist father and domineering
mother, Harlean lived in a lavish Kansas City
home and summered at her grandparents'
twenty-five-room Bonner Springs, Kansas, retreat.
Her parents' divorce in 1922 left Harlean
alone with her mother, so at sixteen she eloped
with wealthy Charles McGrew II and moved to
Beverly Hills, California. Her mother followed,
broke up the marriage, and persuaded
Harlean to find work in films. Assuming her
mother's maiden name, stunning Jean Harlow
achieved instant stardom in Hell's Angels
(1930), an aerial drama financed and directed
by Howard Hughes.

Two years later, Hughes sold Harlow's contract
to Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer, where her
knack for comedy surfaced in Red-Headed Woman and Red Dust (both 1932). Meanwhile,
her two-month marriage to mgm executive
Paul Bern ended with his suicide in their
home. Braving rumors of impotence, bigamy,
and foul play, Harlow not only survived the
scandal but emerged more popular than ever,
becoming one of mgm's most important and
beloved stars in hits like Dinner at Eight (1933), Bombshell (1933), China Seas (1935), and Wife vs. Secretary (1936). Contrary to her provocative screen persona, Harlow was known to
friends and coworkers as "the baby"; at the
height of her stardom, she still lived with her
mother.

Harlow's private life was chaotic and unhappy.
A third marriage to MGM cameraman
Harold Rosson in 1933 lasted eight months,
while a three-year relationship with actor
William Powell was marred by his refusal to
marry. Already an alcoholic, at twenty-six
Harlow succumbed to kidney failure, the result
of an undiagnosed poststreptococcal infection.
Her agonizing death on June 7, 1937,
was widely attributed to her Christian Scientist
mother's refusal to seek medical aid; in
truth, doctors were present, and Harlow died
in a hospital, but at the time no treatment
existed to save her.

Underrated in her own lifetime, Jean Harlow
is now considered a unique and irreplaceable
talent; once notorious, her bleached hair
has become a fashion staple.


David Steen
New York, New York




Steen, David. Bombshell: The Life and Death of Jean Harlow.
New York: Doubleday, 1993.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>