<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.war.031</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Nimitz, Chester (1885-1966)</field>
      <field name="author">Casad, Dede Weldon</field>
      <field name="text">

 




NIMITZ, CHESTER (1885-1966)

"Fleet Admiral Chester W. Nimitz, USN Oil on canvas" (Adrian Lamb, 1960)
     

Chester William Nimitz was born in Fredericksburg,
Texas, on February 24, 1885, to Chester
Bernard, a cattle driver, and Anna (Henke)
Nimitz. Chester's father died before he was
born. He was raised by his mother and his
paternal grandfather, Charles H. Nimitz. The
grandfather, a German immigrant and lover
of the sea, built a steamboat-shaped hotel in
Fredericksburg, the Nimitz Hotel, that still existed
at the beginning of the twenty-first century.
Young Chester listened with wide eyes to
stories of his grandfather's youth in the German
merchant marines.

Nimitz graduated from the U.S. Naval
Academy in Annapolis, Maryland, on January
30, 1905, seventh in a class of 114. For thirty-five
years Nimitz performed his duties in the
U.S. Navy, rising to the rank of admiral. On
December 17, 1941, ten days after the bombing
of Pearl Harbor, Nimitz was appointed commander
in chief of the Pacific Fleet. Admiral
Nimitz quickly rebuilt the fleet into the largest
military armada ever assembled and launched
an offensive, with raids on Wake Island, the
Gilbert Islands, the Marshall Islands, and New
Guinea. He handed the Japanese their first
major setback at Midway Island in June 1942
and continued the offensive in the Pacific until
the Japanese defeat. Along with Gen. Douglas
MacArthur, Nimitz signed the Japanese surrender
agreements.

Chester Nimitz was the first naval officer to
acquire five stars. In response to Nimitz's generosity
in returning to the Japanese their samurai
swords, the Japanese government built a
Garden of Peace behind the Nimitz Hotel in
Fredericksburg as a tribute to his goodwill.
Nimitz died on February 20, 1966, near San
Francisco and was buried in Golden Gate National
Cemetery.


Dade Weldon Casad
Dallas, Texas




Driskill, Frank A., and Dede Weldon Casad. Chester W.
Nimitz: Admiral of the Hills. Austin TX: Eakin Press, 1983.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>