<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.edu.005</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Beadle, William H. H. (1838-1915)</field>
      <field name="author">Jensen, Devon</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BEADLE, WILLIAM H. H. (1838-1915)

William Henry Harrison Beadle was born on
the frontier in Parke County, Indiana, on January
1, 1838. His father wanted him to farm,
but he had dreams of an education. He studied
civil engineering at the University of
Michigan, graduating in 1861. He then enlisted
in the Union army and by the end of the war
had risen to the rank of brigadier general.
Beadle followed this experience with a law degree
from the University of Michigan in 1867
and practiced briefly.

Beadle combined his skills to draft the
school lands provision at the South Dakota
Convention of 1885. The impetus for this
provision came from his appointment by
President Grant in 1869 as surveyor general of
the Dakota Territory, where he met with settlers
face to face and saw state-appropriated
lands being taken by entrepreneurs. General
Beadle was convinced that school lands were a
trust for future generations and should be
sold at their appraised value and never for less
than $10 an acre. State legislators thought this
to be an exaggerated figure, but history soon
proved Beadle to be right. Shortly thereafter,
the Dakota land boom started, and with settlers
immigrating at a rate of several thousand
per year, there was increased demand for
teachers, schools, and school lands. Beadle ensured
that sections 16 and 36 in every township
in the state were set aside as an endowment
for public school purposes. His efforts
have long since been vindicated, with the current
amount realized from the sale of these
lands standing at $125 million. Leasing or
loaning these lands in the future could further
produce some $7.5 million per annum.

Beadle ended his career as president of the
Madison State Normal School (now Dakota
State University) from 1889 to 1906 and as
a professor of history until his retirement in
1912. He died on November 15, 1915, in San
Francisco.


Devon Johnson
University of South Dakota




South Dakota Beadle Club. Permanent School Fund in
South Dakota and the Beadle Club. Aberdeen SD: North
Plains Press, 1976.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>