<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.edu.027</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Morrill Act</field>
      <field name="author">Knoll, Robert E.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MORRILL ACT

The Morrill Act was passed by Congress and
signed into law by President Abraham Lincoln
on July 2, 1862. It authorized the establishment
of land-grant colleges in every state of the
Union and specified that each state be granted
30,000 acres of public land for each member
of Congress and Senate for "the endowment,
support, and maintenance of at least one college
in each state where the leading object
shall be, without excluding other scientific or
classical studies, to teach such branches of
learning as are related to agriculture and the
mechanic arts, as the legislatures of the states
may respectively prescribe, in order to promote
the liberal and practical education of the
industrial classes in the several pursuits and
professions of life." A slightly different version
had been vetoed by President James Buchanan
in 1859, the opposition asserting that the proposed
land grants would be an invasion of the
domestic rights of the states.

Scrip–certificates of possession–were issued
on federal lands in new states when no
public lands in established states were available.
How the land or scrip was to be disposed
of was left to state discretion, but the
grants did not turn out to be the bonanza that
the founders had hoped for. The pressure
for immediate funds glutted the market with
huge blocks of scrip. The concurrent railroad
grants and the inauguration of homesteading
in 1862 depressed land prices, and the unsettled
financial state of the nation in the 1860s
and 1870s further lowered land values. State
officials often seemed to have little appreciation
of the possibilities of the act and used the
grants to secure ready money by quick sale. Established
states–Pennsylvania, Massachusetts,
and Ohio in particular–were inefficient
in disposing of the land, but nine other states
received more than the established minimum
of $1.25 per acre. Western states generally managed
their land above the minimum price. In
Nebraska, for example, no school land was
disposed of for less than $7.00 an acre.

In time, every state and three U.S. territories
established new colleges or combined
the land-grant college with existing institutions.
Twenty separate colleges of agriculture
and mechanic arts were founded, eight in the
Great Plains. They were Colorado Agricultural
and Mechanical College, Fort Collins
(1870); Kansas State Agricultural College,
Manhattan (1863); Montana State College,
Bozeman (1893); New Mexico College of Agriculture
and Mechanic Arts, Las Cruces (1889);
North Dakota Agricultural College, Fargo
(1890); Oklahoma Agricultural and Mechanical
College, Stillwater (1891); South Dakota
State College of Agriculture and Mechanic
Arts, Brookings (1881); and Agricultural and
Mechanical College of Texas, College Station
(1871). Two states in the Great Plains used the
federal grants to found state universities. They
were the University of Nebraska (Lincoln) in
1869 and the University of Wyoming (Laramie)
in 1887.

The importance of the land-grant college to
American society is hard to exaggerate. The
curriculum of American higher education was
broadened to include not just the orthodox
classics and mathematics but also mechanical,
agricultural, and other subjects of assumed
immediate utility. The student body was widened
to include not just the Christian gentlemen
whom Christian colleges traditionally
prepared for public service but all persons
who through ability and ambition might contribute
in a variety of ways to the public welfare.
Through the influence of the land-grant
colleges and state universities, high schools
were established, and their standards were set
across the nation. The colleges stimulated a
spirit of regional pride centered on these local
schools. Women as well as men were invited to
attend by the introduction of courses in home
economics, and coeducation became standard.
Both federally and locally, society was
committed to the support of universities,
whereas earlier universities and colleges had
relied heavily though not exclusively on religious
a.liations. Education was secularized.
Research became a requisite part of higher education
through the model of scientific investigations.
With the Hatch Act of 1887, which
established experiment stations at land-grant
colleges, the federal government assumed
some financial responsibility for both general
and specialized research. The various states
became similarly committed to the support of
both basic and applied research. The Jeffersonian
ideal of an aristocracy of talent was
given a practical means of achievement. The
land-grant college was, and still is, a major
agency for upward mobility in a democratic
world and a lasting and fundamental part of
Great Plains education.


Robert E. Knoll
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Eddy, Edward Danforth, Jr. Colleges for Our Land and
Time: The Land-Grant Idea in American Education. New
York: Harper and Brothers, 1957. Nevins, Allan. The State
Universities and Democracy. Urbana: University of Illinois
Press, 1962. Ross, Earl D. Democracy's Colleges: The Land-
Grant Movement in the Formative States. New York: Arno
Press, 1969.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>