<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ha.017</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Guadalupe Hidalgo, Treaty of</field>
      <field name="author">Adams, Mary E.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




GUADALUPE HIDALGO, TREATY OF

Signed on February 2, 1848, the Treaty of
Guadalupe Hidalgo officially ended the Mexican
American War (1846-48). The treaty required
that Mexico cede 947,570 square miles,
almost half of its territory, in exchange for
peace and $15 million. The United States
gained most of what is now the American
Southwest and parts of the Great Plains, including
New Mexico, Arizona, Utah, Nevada,
California, and parts of Wyoming, Colorado,
and Oklahoma. The treaty also recognized the
annexation of Texas to the United States and
set the boundary between the two nations at
the Rio Grande.

Key factors leading to the war, as well as the
eventual terms of the treaty, included the annexation
of Texas by the United States, an almost
religious belief in American manifest
destiny, and a vulnerable Mexican government.
Unfortunately for Mexico, a succession
of overthrown presidents had followed its
war of independence from Spain, leaving the
unstable nation an easy target for American
expansionism.

Appointed by President James Polk, Nicholas
Trist traveled to Mexico in May 1847 and
began diplomatic relations soon after. He and
three Mexican peace commissioners eventually
signed the treaty at Villa de Guadalupe
Hidalgo, but ratification would be an arduous
process for both countries. While Mexican
o.cials were outraged about lost territory,
Americans were equally disappointed that
they would not receive even more of the defeated
nation.

Aside from land and money, the treaty dealt
with the citizenship and property rights of
those living within the transferred territory:
Mexican citizens could relocate to Mexico,
remain in the territory as Mexican citizens, or
become citizens of the United States. The treaty
promised these new Americans all rights, including
"free enjoyment of liberty and property."
The ratification did not, however, include
Article 10 of the original document,
which had promised to honor Mexican land
grants.


Mary E. Adams
University of Oklahoma




del Castillo, Richard Griswold. The Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo: A Legacy of Conflict. Norman: University of
Oklahoma Press, 1990. Gonzales, Manuel G. Mexicanos: A History of Mexicans in the United States. Bloomington:
Indiana University Press, 1999.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>