<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.law.051</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Vigilantes</field>
      <field name="author">McKanna, Jr., Clare V.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




VIGILANTES

Vigilantes are individuals who take the law
into their own hands. Vigilante movements
have often been viewed in a positive light, and
apologists suggest that vigilance committees
were necessary because duly constituted legal
authorities failed to maintain order and punish
alleged criminals. This assumption has
never been proven or adequately explored.

Vigilantes, often called stranglers, slickers,
white caps, night riders, lynch mobs, and a
variety of other names, usually worked as a
group at night (sometimes hooded) to assure
anonymity, to bolster their courage, to reduce
their personal accountability, and to avoid
prosecution. They formed committees, and in
order to solicit legitimacy for their actions
they issued proclamations that suggested that
they had to act to "preserve" law and order.
Usually vigilantism occurred when a group of
citizens believed that the law either was not
working or was too slow in prosecuting alleged
criminals. Under such conditions local
members of the community took action to
remedy the situation.

San Francisco vigilante movements in 1851
and 1856 were probably the best-known examples
of such extralegal activity. Their methods
included organization of community leaders,
focus on a particular "problem" in society, the
quick apprehension of alleged criminals, and
a "speedy trial" followed by punishment such
as flogging or, more commonly, death by
hanging. Vigilantism spread quickly across the
West. Vigilantes who were little better than
lynch mobs took retribution against anyone
considered to be a threat to Great Plains society.
Although the Canadian Plains seldom
experienced such violent activities, several examples
of vigilante activity took place from
1867 to 1897 in the Kootenay River region
in British Columbia that borders western
Montana.

Walter van Tilburg Clark in The Ox-Bow Incident (1940) correctly perceived that this
distinctly American form of violence appealed
to the local community and that the people
involved in the activity assumed that their actions
were necessary for their community's
welfare. Clark also provided the components
for the lynch mob action: an alleged crime
and criminal, a mob leader, an inflammatory
speech, liberal use of alcohol, a rope, and, finally,
a tree in town or in a nearby cottonwood
grove.

Whether the victim was Sheriff Henry Plummer
in Bannack, Montana, Cattle Kate in Wyoming,
Frank Blackhawk (Standing Rock
Sioux) in Williamsport, North Dakota, William
Brown in Omaha, Nebraska, or some
nameless Indian, Chinese, or Hispanic victim
on a lonely country road, Great Plains vigilantism
or lynch mob action was swift and
usually fatal. Richard Maxwell Brown provides
the following nineteenth-century statistics
for vigilante killings in Great Plains states:
Texas, 140; Montana, 101; Wyoming, 31; Colorado,
23; Nebraska, 21; Kansas, 18; South Dakota,
10; Oklahoma, 2; and North Dakota, 0.
For comparative purposes, California, the
birthplace of western vigilantism, had 109 victims.
However, these statistics are misleading,
since they do not include lynch mob killings.

Some historians claim that vigilantism is
not the same as lynching, but David A. Johnson
suggests that the distinction between organized
vigilance committees and ephemeral
lynch parties is a blurred one. Johnson also
notes that in the 1850s the term mob was seldom
used to describe vigilantism, but a decade
later mob or lynch mob had become the
predominant terms to describe this type of
violence. If one adds lynch mob victims to
vigilante killings, the resulting Great Plains totals
would be Texas, 475; Montana, 122; Oklahoma,
98; Wyoming, 65; Colorado, 41; Nebraska,
38; Kansas, 40; South Dakota, 23; and
North Dakota, 10. Again by comparison, in
California vigilantes and mobs lynched at
least 380 victims.

Regardless of how one chooses to define
"vigilante," it remains a word that stigmatizes
those who took the law into their own hands.
Historically, it has been convenient to modify
what has been called the "shared memory" of a
local community in order to "fit the facts,"
such as in the mysterious hanging of Barrett
Scott, a convicted embezzler, on January 19,
1895, at an abandoned farmhouse in northern
Nebraska and the attempt to avoid detection
by dropping the body in the Niobrara River.
Unfortunately for local taxpayers, Scott was
not given time to return the money. A jury
failed to convict any of the identified vigilantes,
who presumably returned to their community
"vindicated" by their deadly actions.

See also IMAGES AND ICONS: Frontier Violence.


Clare V. McKanna Jr.
San Diego State University




Brown, Richard Maxwell. Strain of Violence: Historical Studies of American Violence and Vigilantism. New York:
Oxford University Press, 1975. Hewitt, James W. "The Fatal
Fall of Barrett Scott: Vigilantes on the Niobrara." Great Plains Quarterly 12 (1992): 107–20. Johnson, David A. "Vigilance
and the Law: The Moral Authority of Popular Justice
in the Far West." American Quarterly 33 (1981): 558–86.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>