<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.tra.027</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Railroad Land Grants</field>
      <field name="author">Grant, Michael J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




RAILROAD LAND GRANTS

Rail lines have played a crucial role in the development
of the Plains. After the Civil War,
rail lines such as the Canadian Pacific Railway,
Union Pacific Railroad, and Northern Pacific
Railway accepted huge gifts of land to subsidize
railroad construction and operations
across the American Plains and Canadian
Prairies. Leaders in both countries contended
that whoever controlled access across this region
would control the Pacific Coast.

The construction of railroads in the Plains
and Prairies differed from that in eastern
North America in that it preceded the settlement
of the land. These lines, rather than the
communities themselves, shaped the architecture,
layout, and placement of towns. In the
United States, federal, state, and local governments
as well as individuals gave railroad
companies gifts of land to build their lines
through the Plains. Railroads received an estimated
185 million acres of land from these
sources. The largest contributor by far was the
federal government, which made the grants
directly to the companies or through state
government intermediaries. Under grants to
the Union Pacific and Central Pacific lines, the
federal government offered twenty square
miles of land for each mile of track laid in
territories and ten square miles of land for
each mile of track laid in states. The land
grants were in alternate sections, next to government
reserved lands, and laid out in a
checkerboard pattern. The government reserved
lands were in escrow and could not be
claimed by homesteaders until the railroads
received their full shares. In Canada, railways
received more than 38 million acres of land.
Most went to the Canadian Pacific line.

During construction and afterward, critics
debated whether the land grant was a reasonable
subsidy or an opportunity to plunder the
landed wealth of the Prairies and Plains. Apologists
for the railroad grants admit that the
legislation appropriating the lands was often
poorly drawn and contradicted land settlement
plans. However, they note that building
and running a railroad was an expensive and
unstable business. Land grants, they write, offered
companies immediate revenues and the
means to meet future capital costs. The rail
lines that bound the Atlantic and Pacific together
certainly would not have been constructed
so early without the subsidies. Especially
in the United States, no other method to
promote railroads in the Plains was politically
possible.

Critics of the railroad land grants in the U.S.
Plains point out that the gifts made railroads
the "proprietors of the West." While they were
in escrow, railroads did not pay taxes. Worse,
they effectively blocked settlement within
the checkerboard patterns. For example, the
Northern Pacific reserved a 120-mile swath of
land between Minnesota and Puget Sound that
was withheld from settlement.

See also EUROPEAN AMERICANS: Land Laws and Settlement.


Michael J. Grant
Lincoln, Nebraska




Gates, Paul W. Fifty Million Acres: Conflicts over Kansas
Land Policy, 1854–1890. Ithaca NY: Cornell University
Press, 1954. Hedges, James B. The Federal Railway Land
Subsidy Policy of Canada. Cambridge: Harvard University
Press, 1934. Mercer, Lloyd J. Railroads and Land Grant
Policy: A Study in Government Intervention. New York:
Academic Press, 1982.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>