<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.016</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Dust Bowl Literature</field>
      <field name="author">Lookingbill, Brad</field>
      <field name="text">

 




DUST BOWL LITERATURE

During the 1930s a number of literary texts
illustrated drought, dusters, and economic
depression through powerful stories and contributed
to aesthetic movements for social realism
and cultural regionalism.

John Steinbeck's 1939 novel, The Grapes of Wrath, inspired the nation with its tale of
a tenant-farm family, the Joads, who lost
their home in eastern Oklahoma and searched
for a more promising land in California. The
novel accentuated human dignity and courage
against a mechanistic, exploitative social system.
In 1937 Frederick Manfred wrote the first
draft of his novel The Golden Bowl, which
was published in 1944. He portrayed a spirited
resistance to fate in the Northern Plains by
focusing on Maury Grant, a wandering protagonist
who returned to the Dust Bowl and
started the cycle of conquest again. After embracing
his fate, he and the Thors, a mythic
family holding onto a dying land, refused to
abandon their homestead.

Set within Kansas during the late nineteenth
century, John Ise's Sod and Stubble: The Story of a Kansas Homestead (1936) recounts a
familial story of remarkable heroism against
drought, grasshoppers, fires, dust storms, and
economic depression. Women homesteaders
in the Dakotas are featured in Edith Kohl's
mixed autobiography and novel, The Land of the Burnt Thigh (1938).

Lawrence Svobida, a western Kansas farmer
turned author, recounted a cautionary tale in
his 1940 autobiography, An Empire of Dust.
Though his wheat farm failed to survive the
dust storms and adverse climate, Svobida
worked incessantly to win a harvest and to
keep the land from blowing away. The story
underscores frustration and pride, but it ends
in failure.

Paul Sears, a botanist at the University of
Oklahoma, authored the most significant ecological
text of the decade. Alarmed by the violent
dust storms raging across the continent,
in Deserts on the March (1935) he explained
how the rapid conquest of North America had
upset the balance of nature. If the nation was
headed down such a slippery slope, Sears argued,
then the assumptions of frontier progress
required reexamination.

Kenneth Porter's prose and poetry, which
lament the failures embodied in a dust cloud
over Kansas, appeared in a number of magazines
in the 1930s. After the Dust Bowl conditions
faded from the landscape, Lois Phillips
Hudson's The Bones of Plenty (1962) and Reapers of the Dust (1964) reinvented empty land,
solid inhabitants, and frontier myths for subsequent
generations. Ann Marie Low's Dust Bowl Diary (1984) recalls the difficulties of
farm life in North Dakota.

Dust bowl literature thus illuminates the
human fight against extreme temperatures,
soil erosion, agricultural maladjustment, and
swirling winds. While the crisis exposed the
nation to a range of anxieties, literature was a
vehicle that could bring the Dust Bowl into
the experiences of readers outside the region.
Limning a powerful landscape in national
memory, Dust Bowl literature invented an enduring
iconography for the Great Plains.

See also FILM: The Grapes of Wrath / MUSIC:
Guthrie, Woody / PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT:
Dust Bowl.


Brad Lookingbill
Columbia College




Lookingbill, Brad. "The Living and the Dead Land: The
Great Plains Environment and the Literature of Depression
America." Heritage of the Great Plains 29 (1996): 38–
48. Quantic, Diane Dufva. The Nature of the Place: A Study of Great Plains Fiction. Lincoln: University of Nebraska
Press, 1995.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>