<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.007</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Campbell, Maria (b. 1940)</field>
      <field name="author">Perreault, Jeanne</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CAMPBELL, MARIA (b. 1940)

Photograph of Maria Campbell


Métis author and activist Maria Campbell is
best known for her remarkable autobiography,
Halfbreed (1973), the first document of its
kind in Canada. In it Campbell describes her
early life in a northern Saskatchewan Métis
trapping community in the 1940s (she was
born at Park Valley in April 1940), the support
of her beloved grandmother Cheechum, and
the gradual destruction of her family and
community by racism, poverty, and alcohol.
Left to care for her seven younger siblings after
her mother's death, Campbell quit school
and married at fifteen. Halfbreed tracks the
young Maria's struggle through alcohol, drug
addiction, and prostitution and, finally, her
healing return to the traditions of her Cree
heritage.

Campbell's collaborative theatrical work,
Jessica, based on Halfbreed, was first performed
in Toronto by Theatre Passe Muraille
in 1981. A description of the troubled process
of the play's creation was later published with
Linda Griffiths under the title The Book of Jessica: A Theatrical Transformation (1989).

Campbell's recent writing has been for children
and includes informational illustrated
works on Plains Indians and Métis heritage.
An illustrated collection of narratives, or "told
to" stories, from old men of northern Saskatchewan
Métis communities, Stories of the Road Allowance People, appeared in 1995.
Campbell has helped establish emergency
shelters for women and community theater
groups, and she has encouraged First Nations
writers. She has been writer in residence at
several universities and in 1999 was teaching
creative writing at the University of Saskatchewan.
Campbell lives on the land homesteaded
by Gabriel Dumont, commander of the Métis
forces in the North-West Rebellion of 1885.


Jeanne Perreault
University of Calgary




Bataille, Gretchen M., and Kathleen Mullen Sands. American Indian Women: Telling Their Lives. Lincoln: University
of Nebraska Press, 1984: 113–26.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>