<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pe.010</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Bison</field>
      <field name="author">Bamforth, Douglas B.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BISON

Bison fight in Grand Teton National Park

    
The North American bison (Bison bison) is
the dominant symbol of the natural world of
the Great Plains. Often referred to as "buffalo,"
the bison is actually the North American
counterpart of a distinct evolutionary lineage
stretching back into the Pliocene. While true
buffalo are found in Africa and southern Asia,
the closest living relative of the North American
bison is the European wisent. Bison first
appear in the fossil record in China and later
spread into North America across the Bering
Land Bridge into modern Alaska, reaching the
Plains during the Middle Pleistocene (730,000
to 128,000 years ago).

The modern male bison stands roughly six
feet tall at the shoulder, is about nine feet
long, and weighs 1,800 to 2,000 pounds. Females
are smaller, averaging about five feet
at the shoulder, seven feet in length, and 700
to 800 pounds. Both sexes have fairly short
horns that curve upward and inward, and
massive heads and forequarters with a large
hump just behind the head, along with relatively
slender hips and hindquarters. The
bison's thick coat insulates it against Plains
winters, and its powerful head and neck allow
it to dig through snow for winter forage. As
individuals, bison (particularly males) are unpredictable
and often aggressive and have
been known to attack humans. However, they
are extremely social and react more predictably
in herds: in particular, bison bunch together
and stampede as a group in response to
even slight provocations. Bison are built to
run, with males clocked at speeds of thirty
miles per hour; a bison can canter far longer
than a horse.

Bison herds on the Plains today live in limited
areas, including national, state, and local
parks and private ranches. Most herds are also
managed, to some degree, through selective
slaughter and provision of winterfeed. Bison,
however, once ranged from northern Mexico to
Canada and from Nevada to the Appalachian
Mountains, and bison numbers and movements
in this vast territory were determined
primarily by the natural distributions and
amount of forage, water, and winter shelter.

For much of the year, females, calves, and
adolescent males tend to form "nursery" herds,
separate from "bull" herds comprised primarily
of adult males. Both nursery and bull
herds form cohesive, hierarchically organized
social units, with social positions determined
by the outcomes of dominance fights in which
pairs of bull bison clash their heads together
and attempt to knock each other off balance.
Although there are few records of bison herd
sizes prior to the nineteenth century, bison
probably dispersed into their smallest social
groups in winter and early spring when food
was least abundant and nutritious. Winter
herds may have been larger in the north as
animals sought out limited sheltered areas to
escape wind and cold. Maximum herd sizes
were probably no larger than 10,000 to 20,000.

In unmanaged modern herds too, late winter
and early spring are hard times, and "winterkill"
resulting from old age, starvation, predation,
and exposure limits population increase.
Calves are born in April and May. Throughout
the Plains, bison aggregate into larger herds
during the summer and early fall, when the
Plains grasses grow best and provide the highest
nutritional yield. Herd sizes particularly
increase in late summer, when nursery and
bull herds combine for the annual rut. During
the rut, fights between males are nearly continuous
because victorious (or dominant)
males have preferential access to females.

Modern bison and their habits resulted
from a long process of evolutionary change.
The earliest North American forms (Bison latifrons)
were much larger than the modern
species and had much longer, straighter, and
sharper horns. Trends toward smaller bodies
with more modern horns were accompanied
by skeletal changes in the head and shoulders
over time, indicating increasing strength and a
greater ability to bear the shock of collisions
in dominance battles. Taken together, these
changes (particularly the shift to a less lethal
horn configuration) imply that dominance
clashes became more common, apparently
because of increasing herd sizes. These trends
reflect changes in the adaptations of the bison,
probably caused by alterations in the Plains
environment. Bison originated as a forest species
and probably lived in small social groups,
with dominance fights rare and, given the lethal
design of their horns, probably often fatal.
The Pleistocene expansion of the Plains
grassland and decreasing forage production
due to increasing aridity within the last 12,000
years probably favored smaller animals living
in larger herds, thereby increasing the frequency
of dominance fights and evolution of
less dangerous fighting apparatus.

Humans have also profoundly influenced
the Plains bison. Native Americans hunted ancient
and modern bison for at least 12,000
years, stalking individual animals or slaughtering
entire herds by driving animals over cliffs
or into corrals or other traps. Within the last
1,000 years, hunter-gatherer groups throughout
the Plains hunted both for their own needs
and to produce a surplus for trade with their
agricultural neighbors.

In the first half of the nineteenth century
the fur trade provided a new market for bison
robes, and hunting increased significantly. After
about 1850, railroad construction, population
expansion, and increased commerce in
bison hides accelerated the rate at which bison
were slaughtered. Bison were also adversely
affected by increasing competition with European
American and Native American horse
and cattle herds for limited winter forage and
by cattle-borne diseases. Ultimately, these
forces reduced an estimated population in the
early nineteenth century of 30 to 50 million
animals to fewer than 1,000 by the 1890s.

Bison populations now total some 70,000,
thanks to efforts by government agencies and
private groups like the National Bison Association
and the InterTribal Bison Cooperative.
Private groups are particularly motivated by
a growing market for bison meat, which is
lower in fat and cholesterol than beef.

See also AGRICULTURE: Buffalo Ranching / NATIVE AMERICANS: Hunting.


Douglas B. Bamforth
University of Colorado




Bamforth, D. B. Ecology and Human Organization on the
Great Plains. New York: Plenum Press, 1988. Flores, Dan.
"Bison Ecology and Bison Diplomacy: The Southern
Plains from 1800 to 1850." Journal of American History 78
(1991): 465-85. Roe, F. G. The North American Buffalo.
Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 1970.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>