<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ha.005</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Bracero Program</field>
      <field name="author">Vigil, Ralph H.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BRACERO PROGRAM

Mexican workers, repatriated during the
Great Depression, were allowed to enter the
United States as temporary contract workers
due to the manpower shortage during World
War II. The August 4, 1942, bilateral agreement
(Public Law 45) between Mexico and the
United States (Mexican Farm Labor Program
Agreement) assured agricultural employers a
steady supply of documented laborers (braceros).
In 1943 railroads were allowed to hire
Mexican workers as section hands. The first
phase of this labor importation ended in 1947.
Approximately 253,000 farmhands were recruited
in these years, and some 80,000 Mexicans
were employed by the rail lines, many of
them in the Great Plains. The number that
o.cially entered the United States diminished
considerably after the war, but the Korean
War and the problems of the ever-increasing
numbers of illegal aliens rationalized demands
by agricultural employers' associations
for legally imported Mexican labor. Formalized
by Public Law 78 as a temporary measure
in 1951 and periodically renewed, the final
phase of this government-sponsored importation
program recruited some 4.6 million braceros
before it was finally ended in 1964.

Critics of the program called it another federal
subsidy to large-scale commercial farm
operators. Since the government paid for the
recruitment and transportation of contract
workers, growers of crops like sugar beets
were spared this expense. The agreement provided
for a regional prevailing wage and adequate
housing, but it was farm employers
rather than the government who ultimately set
wages and the condition of the labor camps.
Mexican workers also acted as "task forces"
where domestic laborers threatened to organize
for higher wages. Not only did the program
adversely affect wages of domestic farmhands,
but it may have contributed to an
increase of undocumented Mexican workers.
On their return to Mexico, legally contracted
workers told others of the higher wages available
in the United States, which motivated
Mexican workers to cross the border illegally.
Further, Public Law 78 did not include provisions
penalizing employers who hired illegal
aliens. In any case, some 3.8 million undocumented
Mexican nationals, pejoratively called
"wetbacks," were rounded up and returned to
Mexico in the 1950s.

Braceros and mojados (undocumented
workers) not only froze or lowered wages for
domestic farmworkers in these years, but undocumented
workers were frequently given legal
status and entered the program. Texas
opted out of the Bracero Program during the
war years and instead decided on an openborder
policy. When the Mexican government
announced it would refuse to send workers to
the state, Texas growers recruited Mexican
workers by using private contractors. Between
1947 and 1950 some 200,000 undocumented
workers, the majority of them in Texas, were
legalized by the federal government and admitted
into the contract labor program. Mexican
Americans in Texas and the Southwest
found it hard to compete for jobs, and many
left to seek work elsewhere. The need for labor
finally persuaded Texas to participate in the
Bracero Program in the 1950s.

The Bracero Program benefited large-scale
growers of crops rather than small farmers.
The braceros themselves formed part of a recent,
massive Mexican migration to the United
States. Mexican immigration, whether legal or
illegal, permanent or temporary, has created
low-wage labor pools, legal peonage, social ostracism,
and a negative stereotyping of Mexican
Americans. Under pressure from organized
labor, the National Farmers Union, and
concerned religious and social reform groups,
Congress finally ended the legal importation of
workers under the Bracero Program, which
seemed to signal that the formerly open southern
border would be harder to cross legally and
illegally.


Ralph H. Vigil
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Craig, Richard B. The Bracero Program: Interest Groups and Foreign Policy. Austin: University of Texas Press, 1971.
Galarza, Ernesto. Merchants of Labor: The Mexican Bracero Story. Santa Barbara CA: McNally and Loftin, 1964.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>