<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fil.022</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Film Companies</field>
      <field name="author">Eisloeffel, Paul J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




FILM COMPANIES

The contribution of the Great Plains to the
heritage of cinema is not limited to the nativeborn
individuals such as Buster Keaton and
Marlon Brando who made names for themselves
in Hollywood. Not only was the Plains
used for "location" filming in mainstream
theatrical releases, newsreels, and documentaries,
but the region was also home to many
motion picture producers, both companies
and individuals.

Motion picture technology was born in the
1890s in North America primarily through the
work of Thomas Edison and his employees.
The key was the invention of flexible photographic
film, created by the Eastman Kodak
Company for use in still cameras. Innovations
abounded in the early years, but soon after the
turn of the twentieth century the 35-mm film
format was well established as a standard in
America (by 1910, motion picture film was
Kodak's best-selling product).

At the same time, motion pictures became
an increasingly popular form of entertainment,
and entrepreneurs were more than willing
to exploit the trend. Public houses (particularly
opera houses) were converted to
accommodate movie projection, and new theaters
were built. Pioneering Colorado filmmaker
Harry Buckwalter described the situation
in 1907: "The picture show business has
developed into a most astonishing industry
throughout the country. Everywhere it is
flourishing. . . . It is the poor man's grand
opera."

In 1915 the Omaha World-Herald, believing
that the movies' influence on the public was
significant, launched a weekly review page. By
1917 there were nearly 600 movie theaters
throughout Nebraska, almost double the
number of just a few years before. Motion picture
projectors could be found in schools,
churches, corporate offices, even in the state
penitentiary and the State Hospital for the Insane.
This scenario was played out in the rest
of the Great Plains as well as throughout the
United States.

All this activity was meant to accommodate
the flood of films being produced both nationally
and locally. In those early years, the
large commercial film studios were located in
New York, New Jersey, Chicago, and Los Angeles,
all quite distant from the Great Plains.
But the lure of the Plains was compelling for
the fledgling motion picture industry, especially
as a setting for that quintessential North
American film genre, the Western. Studios like
Selig Polyscope, American Biograph, Lubin,
Universal, and Famous Players–Lasky all came
to the Plains to take advantage of the broad
landscape and the genuine pioneering qualities
of the locals. Besides bringing Plains scenery
to broad audiences, this cinematic activity
served to encourage local filmmaking efforts.
Photographers, film distributors, and investors
set up independent businesses for the production
of local motion picture projects, particularly
during the 1910s and 1920s. This
phenomenon was certainly not specific to the
Great Plains; homegrown moviemaking was
widespread throughout North America starting
shortly after the turn of the century, fueled
by the rapidly changing technology of motion
picture production and by the great economic
promise of the burgeoning motion picture industry.
But the Great Plains more than kept
abreast of this trend. Notable examples from
the region were the Black Hills Feature Film
Company (Nebraska), the 101 Bison Studio
(Oklahoma), the Rocky Mountain Production
Company (Wyoming), and the Jamieson Film
Company (Texas), as well as independent filmmakers
Harry Buckwalter (Colorado) and
James Freer (Manitoba, Canada). Though
many intended to capitalize on the Western
theme (as did their larger and more famous
counterparts), their productions ultimately
ran the gamut of film genres, from fictional
features, travelogues, and historical reenactments
to industrial training, educational, and
promotional films. In many cases, the people
behind these ventures dreamed of widespread
theatrical distribution, but most often their
products enjoyed only a limited run within a
relatively local geographic area.

In addition to these established production
companies, the Great Plains was also home to
independent itinerant movie producers who
traveled throughout the region and filmed
events, promotions, or short fictional pieces
for a price. Such films were made in countless
venues. They most often resulted in footage of
a county fair or other local celebration or pageant
(known as actuality footage), but some
involved attempts at acting by local residents
playing out roles from a prepackaged script
(these latter productions are called local talent
films).

Capturing the Great Plains on celluloid was
limited to professionals only until 1923, when
the 16-mm home movie film format was introduced
(followed by the 8-mm format in
1932). This put the power of motion picture
production in the hands of hobbyists and resulted
in unique and voluminous film records
of Plains life and culture. After World War II,
the amateur 16-mm format gained professional
status, leading to a flurry of motion picture
production for use in educational, corporate,
and recreational settings and in the new
film delivery medium of television (the first
local TV station within the Great Plains regional
borders was WBAP-TV in Fort Worth,
Texas; it went on the air on September 29,
1948). During this time, the production of
promotional films, public service films, and
educational films abounded, as did the capture
of daily local events for television news
broadcasts. This trend continues today, although
celluloid film has been replaced with
magnetic videotape.

See also AFRICAN AMERICANS: Johnson, Noble; Micheaux, Oscar; Parks, Gordon.


Paul J. Eisloeffel
Nebraska State Historical Society




Horne, G. S. "Interpreting Prairie Cinema." Prairie Forum
22 (1997): 135–51. Jones, William. "Harry Buckwalter: Pioneer
Colorado Filmmaker." Film History 4 (1990): 89–100.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>