<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.mus.023</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Holly, Buddy (1936-1959)</field>
      <field name="author">Hobbs, Wayne</field>
      <field name="text">

 




HOLLY, BUDDY (1936-1959)

Buddy Holly and the Crickets
       

Buddy Holly was born Charles Hardin Holley
on September 7, 1936, in Lubbock, Texas. He
removed the e from his last name in 1956. The
famously bespectacled Holly, along with his
band, the Crickets, was among the most innovative
and influential pioneers of rock and roll
music, an amalgam of white country and
western and black rhythm and blues styles.

The youngest of four children, Holly followed
his mother and siblings in learning to
play a variety of instruments (guitar, violin,
and piano) to accompany country and western
and gospel singing. That early influence
was later modified by exposure to the black
rhythm and blues music he enthusiastically
listened to on late-night radio. Further reinforcement
came from rock and roll trailblazers
Bill Haley and Elvis Presley, for whom
Holly opened concerts in Lubbock in 1955.

Holly was brought to the attention of Decca
Records through the efforts of an agent, Eddie
Crandall, leading in 1956 to commercial recording
sessions in Nashville with country
and western producer Owen Bradley. Bradley's
attempt to force Holly's unique style into
a Nashville mold in releases such as "Blue
Days, Black Nights" met with little success.
Discouraged by the experience, Holly and the
Crickets (drummer Jerry Allison, bassist Larry
Welborn, and guitarist Niki Sullivan) collaborated
in February 1957 with Clovis, New Mexico,
performer, producer, and recording engineer
Norman Petty to record their first hit
record, "That'll Be the Day," in Petty's studio.
The recording, released on Brunswick Records,
reached number one on the American
charts by September; it also topped the British
charts. Other hits followed quickly in 1957:
"Oh Boy!" and "Peggy Sue," released on the
Coral label, rose to the Top 10. The hit records
led to additional recording sessions and national
tours, including the first performance
by a white band at the Apollo Theater in Harlem
and television appearances on American Bandstand and The Ed Sullivan Show.

The year 1958 brought a flurry of recording
sessions with Petty and tours to Hawaii, Australia,
and England. Holly's influence on the
following generations of English rock stars
was massive: Paul McCartney and Keith Richards
later testified to his profound impact on
the nascent Beatles and Rolling Stones in the
BBC documentary The Real Buddy Holly Story.
On August 4, 1958, Holly and Maria Elena
Santiago married. They had no children. In
late 1958 Buddy and Maria moved to Greenwich
Village, following the dissolution of his
managerial arrangement with Petty and the
decision by the Crickets to pursue an independent
future. In New York Holly resumed writing
songs, emphasizing his role as a soloist,
and undertook the promotion of other promising
young artists, including Waylon Jennings.

A midwestern tour led to the fatal crash on
February 3, 1959, of the small plane in which
Holly and two other young performers (the
Big Bopper and Richie Valens) were attempting
to fly from their engagement in Clear Lake,
Iowa, to Fargo, North Dakota. More than 1,100
people gathered for Holly's funeral in Lubbock.
The hits continued after his death, with
the lonesome and defiant "It Doesn't Matter
Anymore" climbing to number one in the
United Kingdom. Holly was a member of the
first group of inductees into the Rock and Roll
Hall of Fame in 1986.

Holly's legacy includes the band format of
two amplified guitars, bass, and drums, the
practice of the artist performing mostly his
original compositions, and even the wearing
of glasses onstage. Techniques developed in
collaboration with Norman Petty–overdubbing,
artificial reverberation, and the use of
piano, celesta, drumming on a cardboard box,
and knee slapping–were later mimicked by
others. Also characteristic of his musical style
are the rhythmic subdivision of a single syllable
(we-e-e-ell, he-he-he-hey), extreme shifts
of vocal register, intense guitar strumming
with consecutive downstrokes, and the pervasive
driving percussion of Jerry Allison.


Wayne Hobbs
Texas Tech University




Amburn, Ellis. Buddy Holly: A Biography. New York:
St. Martin's Press, 1995. Goldrosen, John. Remembering Buddy: The Definitive Biography. New York: Da Capo
Press, 2000. Griggs, Bill. Buddy Holly: Day-by-Day. Lubbock:
Rockin' 50's, 1997–98.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>