<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pd.040</field>
      <field name="titleMain">O'Hare, Kate Richards (1876-1948)</field>
      <field name="author">Miller, Sally M.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




O'HARE, KATE RICHARDS (1876-1948)


Kate Richards O'Hare and family


Born on March 26, 1876, in Ottawa County,
Kansas, Kate Richards O'Hare was one of the
most popular lecturers, journalists, and socialist
reformers of the first decades of the
twentieth century, with her strongest support
coming in the Great Plains and the Southwest.
She was the daughter of Kansas homesteaders
who lost their land in the late 1880s and relocated
to Kansas City, Missouri. Educated in
Kansas, Missouri, and Nebraska, Kate taught
school briefly, then turned to temperance and
missionary work. Disillusioned, she became a
machinist in her father's shop, which introduced
her to the labor movement. In 1901 Kate
enrolled in a socialist program in Girard, Kansas, a hub of socialist activism and the home
of the newspaper Appeal to Reason. She became
an organizer for the newly founded Socialist
Party of America and, with her new
husband, Frank Patrick O'Hare, went on the
road to spread the word of socialism.

For five years the O'Hares and their four
children homesteaded in Oklahoma Territory,
which was then beginning to develop one of
the fastest-growing socialist movements in the
United States. Kate wrote for the regional socialist
press and became the most popular local
speaker at the socialist summer encampments
in the Southwest, which featured nationally
known lecturers and drew thousands of farmers.
In 1909 the O'Hares relocated to Kansas
City, Kansas, where Kate was a candidate for
the U.S. House of Representatives in 1910.
Thereafter, they settled in St. Louis, Missouri,
where she became a staff writer for the National
Rip-Saw, an agrarian socialist monthly,
alongside her close colleague Eugene Debs.

As a socialist, O'Hare advocated peaceful
means to achieve a collectivist system, promoting
electoral activity, mass education,
and reform measures. In the Socialist Party,
she was the voice of the farmers of the Great
Plains, one of the few party leaders who understood
intimately the farmers' struggle with
increasingly overwhelming economic forces.
She introduced an agrarian plank to the party's
platform and tried to expand its definition
of the proletariat to include farmers. Meanwhile,
O'Hare toured constantly on the socialist
lecture circuit, with her spring and summer
itineraries spanning the Dakotas through
Texas and Oklahoma.

During World War I O'Hare upheld the Socialist
Party's opposition to the war. She was
found guilty of violating the Espionage Act for
an antiwar speech she delivered in Bowman,
North Dakota, in 1917 and served fourteen
months of a five-year prison term. Thereafter,
her activities focused on penal reform and labor
education. In 1928 she divorced O'Hare,
and that year married Charles C. Cunningham,
a businessman, and gradually abandoned
her activism, although she continued
to lecture on civic issues until the end of her
life. She died in Benicia, California, on January
10, 1948.


Sally M. Miller
University of the Pacific




Basen, Neil K. "Kate Richards O'Hare: The 'First Lady' of
American Socialism, 1901–1917." Labor History 21 (1980):
165–99. Foner, Philip S., and Sally M. Miller, eds. Kate
Richards O'Hare: Selected Writings and Speeches. Baton
Rouge: Louisiana State University Press, 1982. Miller, Sally
M. From Prairie to Prison: The Life of Social Activist Kate
Richards O'Hare. Columbia: University of Missouri Press,
1993.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>