<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.sr.029</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Hornsby, Rogers (1896-1963)</field>
      <field name="author">Krause, Kent M.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




HORNSBY, ROGERS (1896-1963)

Many baseball experts consider Rogers Hornsby
to be the greatest right-handed hitter in the
game's history. He was born on April 27, 1896,
in Winters, Texas, and later moved to Fort
Worth, where he developed his baseball skills
on city league and high school teams. In 1914
Hornsby joined a Class D minor-league team
in Hugo, Oklahoma. After that franchise
folded, he returned to Texas when a team in
Denison purchased his contract. While playing
for Denison, the infielder impressed a
scout for the St. Louis Cardinals, who then
bought his contract in September 1915.

Over the next decade Hornsby established
himself as one of the most feared hitters in the
major leagues. From 1920 to 1925 he won a
phenomenal six straight batting titles and two
Triple Crowns. Hornsby's .424 batting average
in 1924 is still a modern record. Hornsby was
an aggressive player with a controversial gambling
addiction, and his abrasiveness led to
frequent difficulties with his team's front office.
As a result, St. Louis traded Hornsby following
the 1926 season. He played for five different
teams until his retirement in 1937.

During and following his playing days,
Hornsby managed several teams, including
minor-league franchises in Fort Worth and
Beaumont, Texas. Despite his gruff personality,
Hornsby's baseball accomplishments
made him a hero to thousands of Texans. He
finished his Hall of Fame career with 301 home
runs and a .358 lifetime batting average, the
highest ever for a right-handed hitter. Hornsby
died on January 5, 1963, in Chicago.


Kent M. Krause
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Alexander, Charles C. Rogers Hornsby: A Biography. New
York: Henry Holt and Company, 1995. Dewey, Donald,
and Nicholas Acocella. The Biographical History of Baseball.
New York: Carroll and Graf Publishers, Inc., 1995.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>