<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ea.004</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Cedarvale Communist Community</field>
      <field name="author">Saul, Norman E.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CEDARVALE COMMUNIST COMMUNITY

One of the most unusual foreign settlements
in the Great Plains in the nineteenth century
was a utopian socialist commune established
by Russian exiles on former Osage Indian
lands near Cedarvale in southern Kansas. Its
inspiration goes back to members of the Russian
intelligentsia, led by Alexander Herzen
and Michael Bakunin, and their reception of
the ideas of French socialists such as Fourier
and German romantic philosophers during
the 1830s and 1840s. This generation of thinkers
was followed by one of activists, inspired
especially by Nicholas Chernyshevsky and Peter
Lavrov (the "sons" of Ivan Turgenev's Fathers and Sons), who sought implementation
of basic reforms and socialist ideals based on
the example of Russian peasant collectives.
But this was not easy to accomplish in an autocratic
empire, even during the relatively liberal
reign of Alexander II (1855–81). Some,
therefore, went in search of greater freedom
for experimentation abroad.

One of these was a former army officer and
surveyor of Baltic German background, Vladimir
Geins. Due to American sympathy toward
Russia during the Crimean War and
Russian support of the Union during the Civil
War, literature about the United States was
abundant. Geins and his wife set out for the
"land of social opportunity" in 1868, first settling
in Jersey City, then joining an established
commune in Missouri as Wilhelm and Maria
Frei, which was soon Americanized to William
and Mary Frey. Owing to disputes among
the group and the opening up of Osage land,
the Freys, with a few other American and Russian
followers, moved to Kansas in 1871 to
found the "Progressive Communist Community"
at Cedarvale.

Though small(fifteen members at the
most)and relatively remote, it became well
known for its mixture of Russian atheistic
populists and American Christian socialists,
its adherence to "modern" ideas such as vegetarianism
and, for a few, nudism, and its promotional
and educational efforts. In 1875 Frey
began publishing The Progressive Communist,
a monthly newsletter that circulated to other
communities such as Oneida and Brook
Farm. The Kansas commune was also distinguished
by some of its members, such as
Ukrainian writer Gregory Machtet, Nicholas
Chaikovsky, who played a leading role in the
Russian Revolution in 1917, and Vladimir
Dobroliubov, the brother of Chernyshevsky's
associate.

In 1879 disagreements and financial pressures
came to a head, and the community dissolved.
The Freys lived for a short time at
the New Odessa colony in Oregon, then spent
their remaining years in London, from where
William carried on a widely publicized correspondence
with Leo Tolstoy. Machtet and
Chaikovsky returned to Russia to write of
their experiences and suffer long periods of
forced exile in Siberia.


Norman E. Saul
University of Kansas




Frey, William. Papers. Manuscript Division, New York
Public Library, New York. Saul, Norman E. Concord and Conflict: The United States and Russia, 1867–1914. Lawrence:
University Press of Kansas, 1996. Yarmolinsky,
Avrahm. A Russian's American Dream: A Memoir on William Frey. Lawrence: University Press of Kansas, 1965.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>