<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.mus.032</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Mitchell, Joni (b. 1943)</field>
      <field name="author">Berg, Wesley</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MITCHELL, JONI (b. 1943)

Joni Mitchell with guitar
     

Singer, songwriter, guitarist, and pianist Joni
Mitchell was born Roberta Joan Anderson on
November 7, 1943, in Fort Macleod, Alberta.
She grew up in Saskatoon, Saskatchewan.
Mitchell studied art for a year in Calgary and
then moved to Toronto, where, with her husband,
Chad Mitchell, she began to write songs
and sing in coffeehouses. She moved to Detroit
in 1965 and to New York in 1966 and then
settled in Los Angeles in 1968 with a second
home near Vancouver.

Mitchell made her reputation initially as a
songwriter. Judy Collins recorded Mitchell's
song "Both Sides Now" (1967), and other
Mitchell songs have been recorded by Gordon
Lightfoot, Bob Dylan, and Frank Sinatra.
Seventeen albums over thirty years, with a
Grammy for Clouds (1969), have moved from
the folk styles of her coffeehouse origins
through the jazz influences of the 1970s and
the rock styles of the 1980s to a return to a
simpler folk-based style in the 1990s. Mitchell
has maintained a long, independent career,
and the style of her lyrics and melodies has
been influential. In 1979 she said of her music
that it had a striding quality that was like long
steps across the flat prairies, but she also acknowledged
the increasingly urban influences
of jazz and rock. Her lyrics since the early 1970s
have been autobiographical, dealing with the
pain of love, loneliness, and modern life. Although
she has made her career in the United
States, many of her songs reflect the point of
view of the outsider, a Canadian who can
never fully be a part of life in Los Angeles and
yet can also never return to her small town
Plains roots.


Wesley Berg
University of Alberta




Fetherling, Douglas. Some Day Soon: Essays on Canadian Songwriters. Kingston, Ontario: Quarry Press, 1991. Miller,
Mark. "Joni Mitchell." In Encyclopedia of Music in Canada,
2nd ed., edited by Helmut Kallmann et al. Toronto:
University of Toronto Press, 1992. Mitchell, Joni. The Complete Poems and Lyrics. Toronto: Random House,
1997.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>