<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ha.034</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Ranching Heritage</field>
      <field name="author">Howell, Kenneth W.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




RANCHING HERITAGE

The origins of ranching in the Great Plains
can be traced to those Spanish settlers who
first arrived in the Western Hemisphere. Beginning
as early as 1500, vaqueros, or Spanish
cowboys, were engaged in raising cattle for
commercial purposes in the Caribbean Islands.
During this early period the Spaniards'
tradition of open-range herding and horsemounted
drovers was influenced by African
ranching techniques. African slaves working
as herders introduced the idea of herding the
cattle off the range and into pens at the close
of each day to keep the animals from straying
off the ranch at night. The Africans also contributed
several new words to the Spanish lexicon
that became commonly associated with
the ranching industry. For example, linguists
claim that the word "dogie," a term used to
describe a motherless calf trailing behind a
herd of cattle, originated from the Bombara
language of West Africa. Nevertheless, despite
such African influences, the Spanish tradition
of ranching remained dominant during this
early colonial period.

Following in the wake of Hernán Cortés,
Spaniards first brought cattle from the Caribbean
Islands to the North American mainland
when Gregorio Villalobos arrived in 1520
through the port of the Paunco River near
present-day Tampico, Mexico. Scholars have
substantially documented the early exploits of
Spanish conquistadors against the Indigenous
people of Mexico, but less known is the Natives'
contempt for the Spaniards' cattle that
ravaged their agricultural fields, decimating
valuable subsistence crops. By 1529 the abundance
of livestock in Spanish North America
made it necessary to organize the first ranching
association, or mesta. The mesta required
that all ranchers register their brands with the
authorities located in Mexico City. The cattle
industry quickly became an integral part of
the Mexican colonial economy, especially after
the mid–sixteenth century, when Spanish silver
mines opened in the northern reaches of
Mexico. For those Spaniards living in the
northern mining camps, beef became a significant
part of their diet.

The Spanish tradition of ranching in the
American West began when Don Juan de
Oñate's men herded more than 1,000 head of
cattle across to El Paso del Norte, present-day
El Paso, Texas, in April 1598. Later, Spanish
missions assembled large herds of cattle in
Texas, and by the latter part of the eighteenth
century, more than a million head of cattle
grazed in the open grasslands between the
Nueces and Rio Grande Rivers. It is estimated
that in 1770 the mission La Bahia del Espiritu
Santo, near Goliad, was running approximately
40,000 cattle between the Guadalupe
and San Antonio Rivers.

The famous Texas longhorn breed of cattle
evolved from these early Spanish herds.
Throughout the 1760s and 1770s vaqueros
drove Spanish cattle eastward along trails to
markets located in New Orleans. During the
American Revolution, Spanish cattle from
Texas proved a valuable source of nourishment
for Anglo-American settlers living in the
frontier regions of present-day Kentucky.

Louisiana was the "middle ground" where
Anglos first came into contact with the Hispanic
tradition of cattle ranching. Herding
cattle was already an established profession of
backcountry pioneers in the frontier regions
of the southern British colonies in North
America. However, the cattle industry in the
British colonies differed considerably from
the Hispanic tradition of ranching. Anglo
ranchers constructed pens that were used to
corral their cattle many miles from their established
farms. African or mulatto slaves and
indentured servants were charged with the
care of the animals. Using dogs rather than
riding horses to herd the short-horned British
cattle, the colonial herders acquired the
moniker "cowboys." In their efforts to find
fresh grazing land, the Anglo cattlemen, both
owner and herder, often found themselves in
the vanguard of westward migration.

Shortly after the turn of the nineteenth century,
the backcountry drovers crossed the
Mississippi River. As eastern ranchers moved
farther west, the Anglo tradition of ranching
began to merge with the well-established
practices of the Spanish vaqueros. The newcomers
to the American West learned and
adopted the vaquero traditions of horsemanship
and roping. Spanish influences on the
Anglo cattle culture are clearly evident in the
terminology commonly associated with the
western cattle industry. Words such as "lariat,"
"lasso," "rodeo," "bronc," "corral," "sombrero,"
and "stampede" all have Spanish origins.
While scholars credited Anglos with
spreading the cattle industry northward to the
Great Plains from Texas and Louisiana between
1865 and the 1880s, they also suggest
that the American ranchers could not have
accomplished this feat without first accepting
the Spanish model of ranching. Between 1870
and the late 1880s every American cowboy
who went up the Goodnight-Loving Trail to
Denver, the Western Trail to Dodge City, and
the Chisholm Trail to Abilene used the same
techniques the Spanish vaqueros had introduced
to North America nearly 300 years before
the first railheads emerged on the Central
Plains.

The Spaniards made other contributions to
the ranching heritage of the Great Plains.
In addition to Spanish cattle, the Spaniards
brought horses with them to the New World.
The Spanish horse, like the longhorn, descended
from stock brought into Spain during
the eighth and ninth centuries by the invading
Moors of North Africa. After the Spanish
moved into the Southwest, some of their
horses escaped into the wild, multiplied, and
formed feral herds that eventually populated
the Plains. These wild horses became the
American West's famous mustang. The mustang
horse became one of the most important
components of the Great Plains cattle industry.
Both Spanish vaqueros and American
cowboys praised the endurance and dependability
that the mustangs demonstrated in the
rigid daily routines associated with working
cattle on the open range.

An aspect of the Hispanic ranching heritage
that has received less scholarly attention
than the cattle industry is the Spanish sheepherders.
Sheepherders used the same basic
principles as the cattlemen: they grazed and
watered their sheep on the public domain and
drove their animals along established trails to
reach distant markets.

The Spaniards first introduced sheep into
present-day California, Arizona, New Mexico,
and Texas as part of the Spanish mission establishments.
By 1779 the Hopis were grazing
approximately 30,000 sheep, and one mission
in California was reported to have 100,000
sheep in its herd. The main center of the Spanish
sheep industry, however, was located in
New Mexico. Throughout the late nineteenth
century the sheep population increased dramatically
in the New Mexico Territory. In 1850
there were at least 377,000 sheep raised in the
region and by 1880 there were over 2 million
sheep grazing the New Mexico countryside.
By 1865 herders in New Mexico had moved
their sheep north into the eastern ranges of
Colorado Territory. During the 1880s Texas
became an important center of the sheep industry–
more than 8 million sheep grazed the
Texas range by the middle of the decade. On a
much smaller scale, sheep ranching also developed
in Wyoming, Montana, and the Dakotas.
In these regions there were no large sheep
ranches, but many small commercial enterprises
dotted the Northern Plains. Scholars estimate
that between 1865 and 1900 approximately
15 million sheep were herded along
eastern trails to railheads and feedlots located
in Kansas, Nebraska, and Minnesota.

The ranching heritage of the Great Plains
thus originated with the first Spanish settlers
and continued to develop according to the
trends established by the early Spanish vaqueros.
The most significant contributions of
Hispanic cattlemen involved the introduction
of longhorn cattle to the North American
Plains and the perfection of the techniques
used in moving these rugged animals from
one location to the next. The equestrian skills
learned from the Hispanic vaqueros proved
invaluable to the American cowboys who
drove cattle up the trails from Texas through
the Plains to railheads in Kansas and Nebraska.
The Spanish sheep industry served as
the cornerstone of an alternative model of
ranching that became economically important
to the western regions of the Central
Plains. For these reasons, the Hispanic ranching
culture was vital in establishing the foundation
of a ranching tradition in the Great
Plains.

See also AGRICULTURE: Cattle Ranching.


Kenneth W. Howell
Blinn College




Hine, Robert V., and John Mack Faragher. The American West: A New Interpretive History. New Haven CT: Yale University Press, 2000. Jordan, Terry G. North American Cattle-Ranching Frontiers: Origins, Diffusion, and Differentiation. Albuquerque: University of New Mexico Press, 1993. Webb, Walter P. The Great Plains. Boston: Ginn and Company, 1931.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>