<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ha.021</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Hispano Homeland</field>
      <field name="author">Nostrand, Richard L.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




HISPANO HOMELAND

The term "Hispano" is sometimes used as a
substitute for "Spanish American," a person
who is part of the old and distinctive
New Mexico-centered subculture. In colonial
times Hispanos settled in the Spanish Borderlands
far earlier and became far more numerous
than their subcultural counterparts,
Tejanos and Californios. When the United
States took political control of the Southwest
in the nineteenth century, Hispanos escaped
the onslaught of Mexican immigrants who
engulfed and almost completely absorbed the
Tejanos and Californios. Today, subtle cultural
differences stemming from earlier colonization
and isolation set Hispanos apart from
their Mexican-origin brethren. Also, Hispanos
are far fewer numerically, with 400,000
Hispanos in greater New Mexico compared to
10 million Mexican-origin people elsewhere in
the American Southwest. Significantly, these
Hispanos represent America's only surviving
Spanish colonial subculture.

The creation of a Hispano homeland is the
story of Hispano interaction with four other
peoples. In 1598 Spaniards moved in with the
Pueblo Indians who occupied the upper Rio
Grande basin. The resentful Pueblos staged a
successful revolt that sent the Spaniards south
in 1680. But the Spanish soldier-settlers soon
returned to transform the Pueblo Indian
realm into a Hispano "stronghold" during the
1700s. Meanwhile, nomad Indians, the second
people, stifled Hispano attempts to expand
beyond the Pueblo realm–until about 1790, a
turning point in their pacification. After 1790
Hispano sheepmen seeking new grazing lands
began to spread east into the Great Plains in a
spontaneous village-by-village movement that
lasted until 1890. Territorial expansions into
the Texas and Oklahoma Panhandles happened
quickly in the 1860s and 1870s. Then
Anglo-Americans, the third people, moving
west with their cattle, blunted–indeed drove
back–the Hispano pastores. Anglos, who had
been arriving in Hispano territory since 1821,
continued to come in the twentieth century.
Mexicans, the fourth people, also arrived from
Mexico and the Southwest. By 1900 the Hispano
homeland reached its greatest areal extent
as it stretched over parts of five states and
was the size of Utah. But the arrival of Anglos
and Mexican-origin people especially drove
down the Hispano percentage to only onefifth
of the region's population.

In the process of colonizing greater New
Mexico, Hispanos, acting by themselves, created
a special feeling for their milieu, their
homeland. The highland environment that
they had wrested from the Pueblos required
some adjusting to. Their cultural heritage
brought from Spain and New Spain made
them well prepared to irrigate dryland New
Mexico and to build with adobe brick when
lacking timber. When lowland pastures dried
up in summer, they drove sheep to higher elevations,
a Spanish practice called transhumance.
But adjusting to bitterly cold winter
temperatures required the construction of
livestock shelters in addition to corrals, and
short growing seasons precluded planting
anything but hardy vegetables and deciduous
fruit trees. At the same time, Hispanos created
a distinctive cultural landscape by building
fortified villages for protection from nomadic
Indian attack and by laying out long agricultural
planting lots so that everyone had access
to the irrigation ditch lifeline. Both processes–
adjusting to a highland environment
and stamping that environment with a unique
cultural impress–became central in the Hispanos'
bonding with place. Adding to this
attachment to place came control of land
through land-grant ownership. To this day
Hispanos have an uncommonly strong concept
of homeland among Americans.

But the homeland that Hispanos so deeply
love is by no means uniform. In 1900 three
zones representing degrees of Hispano strength
clearly existed. The inner half of the homeland
constituted a stronghold where Hispanos represented
a minimum of 90 percent of the
population and where they had political clout
but already had lost much economic control.
A broken concentric ring beyond the stronghold
constituted an "inland," suggesting accurately
that Anglos had intruded here to reduce
Hispano numbers to between 50 and
90 percent. Anglos in this area shared political
control with Hispanos and had pretty much
taken over economically. The outer broken
ring, called the "outland," represented areas
to which economic opportunity had pulled
Hispanos from the center. Hispanos had
moved "out" to assume jobs as railroad workers,
miners, ranch hands, shepherds, and laborers.
In the outland, Hispanos owned little
land, had virtually no political say and minimal
social standing, and constituted a minority
population of between 10 and 50 percent.

Since 1900 the three morphological zones
have all but disappeared, but their recent existence
is useful when explaining the Great
Plains segment of the Hispano homeland.
Much of the Hispano homeland that now
overlaps east into the Great Plains is yesterday's
outland. Compared to the long occupation
of their highland stronghold, Hispano
settlement of the high, flat Plains is relatively
recent. They did so either by spreading east in
a lightly settled string of villages founded by
sheepmen, who were later rolled back by Anglo
cattlemen, or by being pulled into the
Plains by Anglo economic opportunity. In
both cases Hispanos came to represent a minority
population that found itself disadvantaged
economically, socially, and politically.
After World War II the problem was compounded
by the arrival of Mexican-origin
people in urban centers like Roswell, Clovis,
Pueblo, and Denver (which in 1980 were all
homeland outliers except Pueblo). Thus, it
seems appropriate to characterize the Hispano
homeland where it overlaps the Great Plains
as an expansion on the periphery of the highland
core.


Richard L. Nostrand
University of Oklahoma




Nostrand, Richard L. The Hispano Homeland. Norman:
University of Oklahoma Press, 1996.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>