<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fol.011</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Farming Lore</field>
      <field name="author">Allen, John C.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




FARMING LORE

The folklore of farming in the Great Plains is a
blend of lore from as far away as Germany and
from as close as the Omaha nation along the
Missouri River of Nebraska. Farming folklore
here is defined as the tales, beliefs, sayings,
proverbs, jokes, and songs that are expressed
in words and have been learned informally.
The lore of the Great Plains is a legacy of migrants
from Europe moving across North
America and of Native American residents
who were already farming, hunting, and passing
on their beliefs through oral history.

Farming lore addresses the trip to the place
where new immigrants could find land of
their own. It is about the myths that developed
around women's madness in the Plains,
and it is about the growing of food and the
dreams that the pioneers had of the future.
The lore of farming is mingled with that of
ranching in the Great Plains. Following the
Civil War, large cattle ranches were established,
and then farmers began arriving. These
tales and songs often placed the role of cowboys
in myth as they worked the Plains from
Texas to Alberta. Often the cowboy tales are
placed in juxtaposition with those of the
farmers who worked the land, providing a
more glamorous antithesis to the life of the
pioneers.

Settlers' songs depicted a living that was
hard and often almost unbearable, as the
words to "The Little Old Shanty" reveal:


I am looking rather seedy now while
holding down my claim,
And the victuals are not always of the
best. . . .
The hinges are of leather and the windows
have no glass,
While the board roof lets the howling
blizzards in.


Against this lament of hardship, the optimism
of the settlers is also recorded and passed
down, as the song continues:


Yet I rather like the novelty of living in this
way,
Though my bill of fare is always rather
tame;
But I'm happy as a clam on the land of
Uncle Sam.


Other songs such as "Starving to Death on
a Government Claim," "But the Mortgage
Worked the Hardest," and "Hard Times" depict
times of severe hardship.

The hardships of the 1870s and 1880s stimulated
the development of the Farmers Alliance.
The Alliance organized to regulate railroads,
to loosen the hold of merchants on the
price of supplies and the marketing system,
and to encourage cooperative stores. Songs
such as "Marching for Freedom," "Dear Prairie
Home," "The Hayseed," "The Pauper's
Cowhides," and "The Patches on My Pants"
illustrate the unrest felt among the Plains
farmers as they were left out of the economic
gains of the cities.

Often the lore of farming and ranching was
depicted in tales. These were set around the
everyday activities of life on a farm. Humor
was a common feature of the tales, as in "A
Threshing Hoax," in which the protagonist
sabotages a competing threshing crew by placing
soap in the boiler so the threshing machine
would not work. This slowed down the
competing crew for a day without causing real
damage to the equipment. Tales of grasshoppers
and other disasters were also passed on,
as in tales of straw being driven through trees
by a tornado. These tales used humor to ease
the burden of living in the Plains.

Children's games were also illustrative of
farming in the Plains. Titles such as "The
Farmer in the Dell," brought from England,
and love games such as "Round and Round
the Valley" showed how mate selection was
envisioned and highlighted the joy of being a
farmer who produces crops of oats, beans,
and barley.

Farming folklore illustrates not only active
farming, mate selection, and dreams and desires,
but also the prophetic, featuring omens,
portents, and signs that farmers and ranchers
in the Great Plains used to guide their activities.
Prophetic sayings feature weather,
marriage and courtship, death and bad luck
signs, and cures. Many focused on the unpredictable
Plains climate, especially the uncertain
rainfall. Sayings such as "If it rains on
Easter Sunday, it will rain on seven Sundays
after" and "If the rooster crows when he goes
to bed, he will get up with a wet head" illustrate
the necessary concern with rain. Mate
selection was also imbedded in sayings, and
the fear of being an unmarried female is the
focus on such sayings as "If a girl sits on a
chair while someone sweeps under it, she will
be an old maid." These prophecies can still be
heard, as Great Plains farmers pass on their
beliefs about weather and other issues that are
beyond their control.

Myths are also part of farming folklore.
One particular myth is that of women going
insane because of the wind, the cold, the animals,
and the loneliness of the vast expanses.
Writers of Plains history have often indicated
that while life in the Plains was difficult for the
men, it was almost unbearable for the women.
Although the myth of insane women settlers
has been shown to be magnified, the impact of
the wind and the austere environment was,
and is, wearing and tiring. In notes left in
courthouses, or in hospitals throughout the
Plains, women cried out for social intercourse
that was often many miles away.

The original Plains farm folklore was not
European American. The Omahas have tales of
agriculture, as illustrated in "Corn Comes to
the Omaha." In this tale the Omaha hunters'
need for food is lamented, and a young man
who goes hunting finds a small bush; the bush
flowers and finally grows to mature maize. At
the end of the first year the maize is shared with
the tribe. Each family receives four kernels of
the maize. The following year messages were
sent to other tribes. It is through this sharing
that corn is believed to have come to the Indigenous
peoples of the Plains.

Farm folklore of the Great Plains focuses on
the difficulties of first getting to the new
homeland, then on settling the land, raising
children, and fighting for a political voice in
the urbanizing society. The lore depicted in
the late 1800s and early 1900s is humorous,
humbling, and angry. Yet, while the lore may
question the wisdom of remaining in this vast
grassland, it also points to the excitement of
the challenge and to possibilities for a better
future.

Although the early settlers have passed away,
and their children and grandchildren have
often moved from the Plains, the lore that expressed
and supported the beliefs, values, and
ways of life of farmers and ranchers is still
heard in coffee shops, around sale barns, and at
other public gatherings, as Plains folk celebrate
the lives they have chosen.

See also IMAGES AND ICONS: 
Mad Pioneer Women.


John C. Allen
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Cannell, Margaret. Signs, Omens and Portents in Nebraska Folklore. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Studies in Language,
Literature, and Criticism, 1933. Welsch, Roger L. A Treasury of Nebraska Pioneer Folklore. Lincoln: University
of Nebraska Press, 1966, 1984.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>