<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.054</field>
      <field name="titleMain">New Deal</field>
      <field name="author">Braeman, John</field>
      <field name="text">

 




NEW DEAL

The New Deal's policies affecting the Great
Plains may be subdivided into national programs
and those aimed explicitly at the region.
But the line is at times blurred. National
programs had a differential impact depending
upon local circumstances.

The absence of large urban centers or industrial
concentrations meant that such New
Deal initiatives as the National Industrial Recovery
Act and the Wagner Labor Relations
Act did not have the same importance in the
Plains as in the Northeast or Great Lakes
states. On the other hand, John Collier's Indian
New Deal had an impact in the Plains
matched only in the Southwest.

Depressed agriculture–intensified in the
Plains by drought from 1930 on–made relief
the region's most pressing want. Whether local
and state governments in the Plains could have
done more to relieve the distress of their citizens
is an open question, given the rise in tax
delinquencies. But the evidence indicates that
lack of will was as much to blame as lack of
resources. Responsibility for taking care of
those requiring public assistance thus fell upon
the Federal Emergency Relief Administration
(FERA), headed by Harry Hopkins. Hopkins
had to wage a continuing battle with local politicians to impose professionalized administration
and gain the demanded matching
spending. The major exception to the laggardness
of the Plains states in social provision was
old-age pensions, because of their relatively
high proportion of elderly.

Of primary long-term importance for the
Plains was the domestic allotment plan incorporated
in the Agricultural Adjustment Act
(AAA) of 1933. The goal was to raise farm
prices to the level of "parity" by inducing
farmers through benefit payments to reduce
acreage. After the Supreme Court held unconstitutional
the processing tax that funded
benefit payments, Congress in 1936 readopted
the plan with a conservationist veneer. Farmers
would be paid out of general revenues to
grow soil-conserving crops instead of soilexhausting
(and surplus) crops, such as wheat
and cotton.

By the end of 1935 the AAA paid out slightly
over $1.1 billion in benefit and rental payments,
with approximately half going to the
ten Plains states. North Dakota, South Dakota,
Nebraska, Texas, and Oklahoma were
the top five states in the percentage of farmer
participation in the program. Prices simultaneously
rose, though still remaining below the
"parity" level. But higher prices were of limited
benefit to those whose crops were ruined
by the drought. Agricultural prosperity did
not return to the Plains until after the return
of higher rainfall levels in the summer of 1938
and the subsequent war in Europe.

Because of the drought, the FERA inaugurated
in 1934 a special program through its
new Division of Rural Rehabilitation to tide
farmers over by loans for the purchase of seed,
fertilizer, livestock, and equipment. The AAA's
emergency cattle purchase program saved
from total ruin the livestock raisers of the
western Plains, whose herds faced decimation
from blowing dust and lack of forage. And the
ranching interests were largely successful in
controlling Department of Interior policies
under the Taylor Grazing Act of 1934. Farm
Credit Administration refinancing of mortgages
was a boon to a section where debt per
farm was among the nation's highest. So was
the rural electrification program pushed
by the Rural Electrification Administration,
given the region's poverty, sparse population,
and distances.

The benefits to the Plains from the New
Deal work relief programs were mixed. The
region lacked the skilled labor and financial
resources for matching funds required for the
capital-intensive projects of the Public Works
Administration. But the large tracts of federally
owned land made the area a favored location
for Civilian Conservation Corps camps,
and the financial boost such camps provided
caused communities to vie for their placement.
As throughout the country, the Works
Progress Administration (WPA)–though giving
many communities otherwise unattainable
new facilities–failed to provide jobs for
all those needing work. And those not taken
on by the WPA, or falling into the special categories
covered by the Social Security Act, fared
poorly when Washington turned back responsibility
for general assistance to the states.

The dust storms that swept over the Plains
from 1934 on were the catalyst for the formulation
of a program to deal with what were regarded
as its long-range problems. There was a
consensus among New Deal planners that the
crux of the difficulty was an exploitative agriculture
ill adapted to the region's climate and
soil. Their 1936 report, The Future of the Great
Plains, called for a multipronged attack to prevent
soil erosion and make the fullest possible
use of available water. But its capstone was a
proposal for a radical restructuring of land
use–a shift from the commercial production
of row crops to livestock pasturage. Undergirding
this proposal was a call for a revolution
in "Attitudes of Mind."

The response of Plains dwellers ranged from
enthusiastic acceptance to hostility. Despite rhetorical
bows to the noble yeoman myth, most
Plains farmers were profit-maximizing capitalists.
Accordingly, fullest exploitation of available
water took highest priority–the more so because
the public at large rather than the beneficiaries
would bear the bulk of the cost of federal
irrigation projects. Despite suspicion about the
ambitions of Hugh Hammond Bennett's Soil
Conservation Service under the Soil Conservation
Act of 1935, the lure of higher outputs
through government-subsidized innovations
such as contour plowing and listing brought at
least partial acceptance. There was, however,
strong resistance to including provision for
mandatory land-use regulations in the states
that were authorizing acts to create soil conservation
districts. Even in the states that did so,
those provisions remained a dead letter.

More ambitious and/or radical proposals
did not find much favor with Congress or–so
far as can be ascertained–with Plains dwellers.
President Franklin D. Roosevelt's pet erosion
solution–building a hundred-mile-wide
shelterbelt of trees from the Texas Panhandle
to Canada–failed to win legislative backing.
Although Roosevelt kept the project going until
1942 with relief funds, the results were a
shadow of his vision. The Resettlement Administration
and Farm Security Administration
continued the fera rehabilitation loan
program, but budget restraints limited what
could be accomplished. The few experiments
at a more collectivist-style agriculture sparked
cries of a communist plot. Even the suggestion
of any large-scale resettlement of population
from the Plains raised angry protests from local
spokesmen. Paradoxically, the New Deal's
success in providing immediate relief undercut
the likelihood of major behavioral and
value changes.

Eight of the top fourteen states in per capita
expenditures by major New Deal agencies from
1933 to 1939 were Plains states, but this largess
brought no long-term political advantage. Roosevelt
carried all the Plains states in 1932 and
again in 1936, while Democrats were swept into
office throughout the region. But many of those
Democrats were Jeffersonian states' righters
(such as Edwin C. Johnson in Colorado), demagogues
(such as "Alfalfa Bill" Murray in Oklahoma),
or political mountebanks (such as
Charles W. Bryan in Nebraska). In Congress,
Roosevelt's leading regional supporters were
progressive Republicans such as George W.
Norris of Nebraska and Bronson Cutting of
New Mexico. No Plains state instituted a "little
New Deal." Even in North Dakota–the most
radically inclined state of the region–Nonpartisan
League–backed Gov. William Langer offered
more bombast than substance.

Plains lawmakers began swinging away
from support for the Roosevelt administration
with the 1937 Supreme Court–packing fight.
The 1938 election showed a similar movement
under way among the public. And in 1940 Roosevelt
himself lost Colorado, Kansas, Nebraska,
and the Dakotas. Crucial in explaining
this rightward shift appears to be the conflict
between New Deal policies and Plains dwellers'
rugged individualist self-image. Financial desperation
led a majority to compromise temporarily
what they saw as their principles—a
compromise that was rationalized by the justification
that people such as themselves were
the backbone of the country and thus uniquely
deserving of governmental solicitude. But extending
that solicitude to the alien and suspect
masses of the cities was another matter; nor
was it required once the agricultural subsidy
programs had become safely institutionalized.

Long-standing rural fears about the threat
of centralized power were raised by Roosevelt's
Court-packing and executive branch reorganization
plans and were reinforced by the
intrusion of federal bureaucrats into the daily
lives of Plains men and women. The New
Deal's growing exploitation of class warfare
rhetoric threatened the myth of classlessness
with which local elites had long buttressed
their own positions. The final blow was Roosevelt's
interventionist foreign policies. Plains
isolationism had diverse roots–the feeling
that American problems should be dealt with
first, suspicions of an international bankers'
conspiracy, ethnic loyalties and resentments–but the result was to solidify the reaction
against the New Deal and its works.

See also AGRICULTURE: Agricultural Adjustment Administration; Farm Security Administration; Taylor Grazing Act.


John Braeman
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Lowitt, Richard. The New Deal and the West. 1984. Norman:
University of Oklahoma Press, 1993. Saloutos, Theodore.
The American Farmer and the New Deal. Ames: Iowa
State University Press, 1982. Schuyler, Michael W. The
Dread of Plenty: Agricultural Relief Activities in the Middle
West, 1933–1939. Manhattan KS: Sunflower University
Press, 1989.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>