<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.tra.028</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Railroads, United States</field>
      <field name="author">Berg, Donald J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




RAILROADS, UNITED STATES

In the last third of the nineteenth century railroads
transformed the Great Plains of North
America from a sparsely populated, primarily
Native American territory to the agricultural
heartland of both the United States and
Canada.

The post–Civil War period saw the first extension
of standard gage tracks across the
American Great Plains with the construction
of the Union Pacific Railroad, a vital component
of the first transcontinental line, completed
in May 1869. At that time the Plains
were perceived as space to cross as expeditiously
as possible, linking the East Coast with
the Pacific Coast. The Plains terrain, gradually
sloping west to east, and the broad, flat river
valleys permitted relatively easy construction
and rapid expansion of the rail network. Although
extractive and exploitative economic
activities had been previously conducted in
the Great Plains (for example, fur trading,
bison hunting, cattle ranching, and mining),
the region was not extensively settled and developed
by European Americans until the latter
third of the nineteenth century, when railroads
made possible the farmers' advance into
the area. While railroads made farming expansion
onto the Plains possible, high freight
rates, caused in part by lack of concern for
farmers' well-being but also by the high cost
of shipping often empty cars to a sparsely
populated region to be filled with agricultural
products, led to protest movements, most notably
the Grange and the Farmers Alliance,
both of which were successful, to a degree, in
achieving government regulation of railroads
by the 1870s and 1880s.

As an instrument of development, railroads
transformed the Great Plains into an integrated
part of both the United States and Canada
by carrying passengers, including inbound
immigrants, and by hauling agricultural products
out and building materials in. After the
Union Pacific, more than a dozen other railroads
laid tracks across the Plains, including
the Southern Pacific and the Northern Pacific.
They began aggressively to articulate their networks
in an effort to capture service territory.
Although their progress was interrupted by
financial panics and other temporary setbacks,
the Great Plains had been laced together with
ribbons of steel by the late nineteenth century.
Later, similar development occurred in Canada. The first line to cross the Canadian Great
Plains was the Canadian Pacific Railway, completed
in 1885. Other railroad companies followed.
Eventually the northern section of the
Plains would have a rail pattern similar to that
of its southern neighbor.

Thus, a railroad landscape, as a feature of a
larger cultural landscape, came into existence.
As the agricultural settlement pattern became
fixed upon the Great Plains railroad companies
continued to build thousands of miles
of secondary and branch lines on both sides of
the international border. The zenith of Plains
railroad development occurred in the early
1920s, when approximately 42,000 miles of
track crisscrossed the region.

Railroads greatly influenced Great Plains
urban patterns. Railroad officials located and
founded the majority of the region's towns
and cities. The distance between the towns
was generally about eight to ten miles, which
was considered a reasonable hauling distance
for farm products, especially small grains. Elevator
capacity of about 30,000 bushels necessitated
a town for every one or two townships.
Consequently, the semihumid eastern Great
Plains developed a fairly dense urban settlement
pattern (too dense, in fact, and many of
the towns eventually failed). The railroads
also platted out the towns, generally in a T
form, with the Main Street perpendicular to
the tracks and the elevator, lumberyard, and
other shipping facilities on the other side.
Areas west of the 100th meridian generally exhibited
a more dispersed pattern, due to their
unsuitability for traditional farming techniques.
Other railroad sites were set up as locomotive
watering and repair points, division
o.ces, and bridging locations on major rivers.
The only European American sites that
preceded railroad towns in the Great Plains
were riverboat ports, fur-trading posts, forts,
mining camps, and prerailroad settlements
within reach of the Missouri River in territorial
Kansas, Nebraska, and Dakota.

After World War II and especially since the
1960s, three themes have characterized railroading
in the Great Plains. The first is abandonment
of unprofitable branch and secondary
lines. Since the 1950s in excess of 8,000
miles of track have been torn up, leaving many
Plains towns without rail service (and bikers
and hikers richly endowed with trails that cut
diagonally across the otherwise right-angled
grid of the Plains landscape). South Dakota,
Kansas, Texas, Nebraska, and Oklahoma have
each lost more than 1,000 miles of track; only
Wyoming has gained, the result of expansion in
the coal-rich Powder River Basin. Second, the
number of rail carriers has declined through
numerous consolidations and mergers. The
Great Plains is crossed by only a handful of Class
A (major carriers) railroads today. A number of
regional and subregional freight lines (short
lines) have emerged from the infrastructures of
the defunct carriers, some of which are successful
financially. State railroad authorities have
purchased trackage in an effort to maintain vital
services such as the delivery of coal to large-scale
electric power generating stations. Third, some
railroads operating in the region have transformed
themselves into long-haul bulk carriers,
with unit coal and grain trains that often consist
of more than 100 railcars. Tonnage has been
increasing as the Class A railroads continue to
haul greater and greater amounts of raw materials
that are either produced in the Great Plains
(in the Wyoming coal fields, for example) or
transported across them. Double tracks support
several high-volume routes that cross the Central
Great Plains, and single track in both the
Northern and Southern Plains is used to capacity.
Also, several Plains rail corridors function as
"dry canals" for the transcontinental movement
of trains hauling only ship container cargoes.

The belief that the Great Plains was a barrier
to be crossed in an east-west direction, coupled
with separate national strategies to connect
East with West, resulted in very little articulation
of the U.S. and Canadian railroad
networks across the international border.
North-south connections were not well developed,
especially on the U.S. side, although
a plan was promoted before World War I to
connect Winnipeg, Manitoba, to Galveston,
Texas, via the eastern Plains. The only major
connection, a Canadian Pacific Railway route,
traces a diagonal line across the Northern
Great Plains from Saskatchewan through Minnesota.
Six passenger corridors traverse the
Plains, operated today by the Amtrak (U.S.)
and Via Rail (Canadian) systems. The passage
is essentially east-west across the region with
only one north-south line on the southeastern
Plains periphery. Relatively little passenger
tra.c is generated at Plains station stops, because
few large cities are located along the respective
routes.

The efficiency and economics of bulk cargo
movement as well as the lesser environmental
impacts of railroads compared to trucks on
roads and highways continue to promote the
use of railroads. A distinctive Great Plains
railroad geography manifests itself across the
region in the general settlement fabric and in
the spectacular coalescence of lines at major
towns. Sounds of diesel locomotive horns and
rushing freight trains moving from horizon to
horizon will continue to reverberate across
the Plains into the foreseeable future.

See also ARCHITECTURE: Railroad Depots /
CITIES AND TOWNS: T-Towns / PROTEST AND
DISSENT: Farmers Alliance; Grange.


Donald J. Berg
South Dakota State University




Hudson, John C. Plains Country Towns. Minneapolis:
University of Minnesota Press, 1985. Kirby, Russell S.
"Nineteenth-Century Patterns of Railroad Development
on the Great Plains." Great Plains Quarterly 3 (1983): 156–70.
Vance, James E., Jr. The North American Railroad: Its
Origin, Evolution, and Geography. Baltimore MD: Johns
Hopkins University Press, 1995.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>