<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.art.022</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Fitzgerald, Lionel Lemoine (1890-1956)</field>
      <field name="author">Murray, Joan</field>
      <field name="text">

 




FITZGERALD, LIONEL LEMOINE (1890-1956)

Lionel LeMoine FitzGerald was a member of
Canada's Group of Seven, joining in 1932. In
1933 he became a founder of the Canadian
Group of Painters. FitzGerald was born in
Winnipeg on March 17, 1890. After study in
Winnipeg and Pittsburgh and at the Art Students
League in New York in 1921 with Boardman
Robinson and Kenneth Hayes Miller,
FitzGerald joined the Winnipeg School of Art
in 1924 and became its principal in 1929. He
held that position until 1947.

FitzGerald's art is distinguished by its precise,
often pointillistic, technique, poetic intensity,
quiet tone, and subtle color. He explored
the light and feeling of space on the
Prairies, often using the area around his home
in St. James, Manitoba, near Winnipeg. Located
there for most of his career (though
stimulated by visits in the 1940s to British Columbia,
where he met Lawren Harris, a fellow
member of the Group of Seven), he sought the
"inner life of things."

In the 1950s FitzGerald turned to abstraction
to express himself, but most critics agree
that he was a typical Prairie artist. Lawren
Harris believed that the brittle clarity of the
atmosphere of the Prairies was reflected in
FitzGerald's landscapes. In the catalog for the
FitzGerald memorial exhibition, Ferdinand
Eckhardt, director of the Winnipeg Art Gallery,
wrote in 1958 that FitzGerald's work was
typical of the Prairie Provinces "not only in
subject matter but also in its simplicity, intensity,
and friendly atmosphere." However, Alan
Jarvis, director of the National Gallery of Canada,
in the same catalog described FitzGerald's
art as classical in a modern sense: "It was
highly personal, sensitive and fastidious." He
also stressed its universal significance. Fitz-
Gerald also painted nudes and still lifes.
Among his well-known works is Doc Snyder's House (1931), now at the National Gallery of
Canada, Ottawa. FitzGerald died in Winnipeg
on August 5, 1956.


Joan Murray
Robert McLaughlin Gallery




L. L. FitzGerald 1890–1956: A Memorial Exhibition. Exhibition
Catalog. Ottawa: National Gallery of Canada, 1958.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>