<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ct.038</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Pierre, South Dakota</field>
      <field name="author">Hogan, Edward Patrick</field>
      <field name="text">

 




PIERRE, SOUTH DAKOTA

Pierre (pronounced "pier") is located in central
South Dakota on the eastern bank of the
Missouri River. Its sister city, Fort Pierre, is
across the river on the western bank. Incorporated
in 1883, Pierre is both the state capital
of South Dakota (since 1889) and the seat
of Hughes County. The boundary dividing
mountain and central time zones follows the
Missouri River, placing Pierre and Fort Pierre
in different time zones.

The area around Pierre was originally a major
fortified center of the Arikara Indians. In
1804 Lewis and Clark held council with three
Teton Sioux chiefs at the mouth of the Teton
(Bad) River near the future site of Pierre. In
1832 the American Fur Company established
Fort Pierre at the site. The fort was a major
trading post for the middle Missouri River region
until 1855, when it was sold to the U.S.
Army. During the Black Hills gold rush (1876–
85) Pierre was a transportation and freighting
outpost for miners and supplies. The city
boomed with the arrival of the railroad in
1880, becoming an important commercial
center for the local farm and ranch economy.
Pierre has continued to grow in population,
increasing from 3,235 in 1890 to 13,876 in 2000.

Today Pierre's economy centers on state and
county government, agriculture (primarily
grains and beef cattle), tourism, and recreation
(fishing and hunting). State government
is the city's most important economic activity.
Products manufactured in Pierre include electrical
and irrigation equipment. Printing is
also a major economic activity.

Located six miles north-northwest of Pierre
is the Oahe Dam, the eighth largest dam in the
world by volume. The dam is a major flood-control
and power production unit on the
Missouri River; the power plant has a total
peaking capacity of 826,000 kilowatts. Behind
the 245-foot-high dam is Lake Oahe. Its waters
stretch 231 miles upstream and cover 374,000
acres of land.

The city is served by the Pierre Regional
Airport, the Dakota, Minnesota, and Eastern
Railroad, and U.S. Highways 14 and 83. Pierre
is home to the Indian Learning Center, a
boarding school for Native Americans in
grades one through eight. The region is also
served by Capital University Center, which
provides access to programs from three state
universities. Major tourism and recreation attractions
in Pierre and the surrounding area
include the Cultural Heritage Center, the
South Dakota Discovery Center and Aquarium,
the state capitol, the Fighting Stallions
Memorial, the Verendrye Museum (in Fort
Pierre), the Oahe Dam and Visitors Center,
the Farm Island State Recreation Area, and the
Fort Pierre National Grassland.


Edward Patrick Hogan
South Dakota State University




Hogan, Edward Patrick, and Erin Hogan Fouberg. The Geography of South Dakota. Sioux Falls SD: Center for
Western Studies, 1998. Schell, Herbert S. The History of South Dakota. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1968.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>