<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.rel.038</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Parham, Charles Fox (1873-1929)</field>
      <field name="author">Synan, Vinson</field>
      <field name="text">

 




PARHAM, CHARLES FOX (1873-1929)

Charles Fox Parham, who was born in Muscatine,
Iowa, on June 4, 1873, is regarded as the
founder and doctrinal father of the worldwide
pentecostal movement. A sickly youth, Parham
nevertheless enrolled in Southwest Kansas
College in 1890, where he became interested
in the Christian ministry. After receiving
a call to preach, he left college before graduating,
and in 1893 accepted the pastorate of a
Methodist church in Linwood, Kansas.

In Linwood, Parham soon became involved
in the holiness movement, which was spreading
in Methodist circles at the time. This
movement stressed instant second-blessing
sanctification as taught by John Wesley. It was
in the Plains that the most radical elements of
the holiness movement took root. By 1895, as
controversy over the second blessing divided
the church, Parham became so enmeshed in
holiness theology that he left the Methodist
Church to follow a career as an independent
holiness evangelist and teacher. He soon began
to emphasize newer doctrines, such as divine
healing and the instant premillennial second
coming of Christ. For the rest of his life, he also
rejected any type of church organization.

In 1898 Parham opened his own "Bethel
Bible School" and healing home in Topeka,
Kansas, where in 1899 he began publication of
a magazine called the Apostolic Faith. It was in
this school that Parham and his students studied
the differing teachings of the holiness
movement relating to the "baptism in the
Holy Spirit" described in Acts 2:4. Through a
student consensus, with some help from Parham,
the student body concluded that speaking
in tongues (glossolalia) was the "Bible evidence"
of such an experience.

On January 1, 1901, a student in the school,
Agnes Ozman, spoke in tongues, electrifying
the school and the Topeka area through sensational
stories in local newspapers. Parham's
teaching that speaking in tongues was the necessary
"Bible evidence" of baptism in the Holy
Spirit became known as the "touch felt round
the world" that, according to J. Roswell Flower
of the Assemblies of God, "made the Twentieth
Century Pentecostal Movement." Parham also
began to teach that glossolalia also constituted
zenolalia (i.e., "missionary tongues"), whereby
missionaries could go to the corners of the
earth and preach miraculously in known human
languages that they had not learned. In a
short time, all Pentecostals except Parham
dropped this belief due to unsuccessful efforts
at preaching in unknown tongues in India and
other places.

By 1906 the pentecostal movement had
spread to Los Angeles through a black preacher,
William Joseph Seymour, who learned pentecostal
theology as Parham's student in another
Bible school in Houston, Texas. From the Azusa
Street Mission led by Seymour, the pentecostal
movement spread rapidly throughout the
world.

In October 1906 Parham visited Azusa
Street and denounced the Los Angeles meetings
as being dominated by "holy rollers and
hypnotists" that featured "darkey camp meeting
stunts." He was thereupon expelled from
Azusa Street by Seymour and his elders. For
the rest of his life, Parham denounced his former
student and the Azusa Street revival as
"spiritual power prostituted." In 1907 Parham
was accused of sodomy in San Antonio during
a local healing crusade. Although he was acquitted
of the charge, his influence as a major
leader in the pentecostal movement was over.
In the last two decades of his life, Parham retired
to his home in Baxter Springs, Kansas,
where several thousand of his followers attended
his annual camp meetings until his
death on January 29, 1929. He is buried in
Baxter Springs.

A century after Parham's movement began in
Topeka, the Pentecostals had grown to be the
second largest family of Christians, with more
than 500 million members in the pentecostal
and charismatic churches and movements that
had spread from Topeka to practically every
nation of the world. Major American denominations
produced by the pentecostal movement
include the Assemblies of God, the Church of
God in Christ, the Pentecostal Holiness Church,
the Church of God (Cleveland, Tennessee), the
United Pentecostal Church, and the Pentecostal
Church of God.


Vinson Synan
Regent University




Burgess, Stanley, Gary McGee, and Patrick Alexander.
Dictionary of Pentecostal and Charismatic Movements.
Grand Rapids MI: Zondervan Publishing House, 1988.
Goff, James R. Fields White unto Harvest: Charles Fox Parham
and the Missionary Origins of Pentecostalism. Fayetteville:
University of Arkansas Press, 1988. Synan, Vinson.
Holiness-Pentecostal Tradition. Grand Rapids MI: William
B. Eerdmans Publishing Co., 1997.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>