<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.048</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Morris, Wright (1910-1998)</field>
      <field name="author">Wydeven, Joseph J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MORRIS, WRIGHT (1910-1998)

Wright Morris, novelist and photographer,
was born in Central City, Nebraska, on January
6, 1910. His mother died when he was six
days old. Morris lived with his father in towns
along the Platte and in Omaha before moving
to Chicago in 1924. In subsequent years, Morris
traveled widely in Mexico and Europe before
settling in Mill Valley, California, where
he died on April 25, 1998.

Of his more than thirty books, Morris is
best known for his photo-texts and the novels
that probe origins, identity, and the significance
of the Plains in shaping human character
and experience. Morris's tone of inquiry is
cogently expressed in the photo-text novel
The Home Place (1948) by protagonist Clyde
Muncy: "There's too much sky out here . . .
too much horizontal, . . . so that the exclamation,
the perpendicular, had to come. Anyone
who was born and raised on the plains knows
that the high false front on the Feed Store, and
the white water tower, are not a question of
vanity. It's a problem of being. Of knowing
you are there." Muncy's nostalgia is tempered
in The World in the Attic (1949) by nausea, an
emotional reaction that warns him against excessive
indulgence in the past. In later novels
Morris examines, with comic compassion, the
consciousness of those who live where "there
is no place to hide"–even, in Ceremony in Lone Tree (1960), from the likes of mass murderer
Charles Starkweather.

In his final novel, Plains Song for Female Voices (1980), Sharon Atkins comes to understand
that complete "escape" from the Plains
is impossible. Morris explores his own umbilical
connections to Nebraska in the photo-text
God's Country and My People (1968) and
his memoir, Will's Boy (1981). At its best, his
words and photographs salvage the post-
Depression era from dissolution by time and
human fallibility.


Joseph J. Wydeven
Bellevue University




Knoll, Robert, ed. Conversations with Wright Morris: Critical Views and Responses. Lincoln: University of Nebraska
Press, 1977. Wydeven, Joseph J. Wright Morris Revisited.
Boston: Twayne, 1998.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>