<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.mus.015</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Etheridge, Melissa (b. 1961)</field>
      <field name="author">Wishart, David J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ETHERIDGE, MELISSA (b. 1961)

Melissa Etheridge
    

Melissa Etheridge, gravelly voice rocker and
gay rights activist, was born in historic Leavenworth,
Kansas, on May 29, 1961. She grew
up listening to a variety of types of music,
from rock to country and blues, on the local
AM stations, and by the age of twelve she was
playing guitar in a band. She lists Keith Richards
of the Rolling Stones as the main influence
on her guitar playing. When she graduated
from high school, she struck out for
Boston and a year at the Berklee College of
Music before landing in Los Angeles in 1982.
By that time she had developed her own style
as a writer and performer of rock songs tinged
with blues.

Etheridge signed with Island Records in
1986 and issued her first album two years later.
It went platinum. In 1992 she won her first
Grammy for "Ain't It Heavy" from the Never Enough album. By 1999 she had put out a total
of seven albums, including 1993's Yes I Am,
which sold more than four million copies and
yielded three Top 10 hits, among them the
Grammy-winning "Come to My Window."
Etheridge has since become a rock celebrity,
performing with her friend and hero, Bruce
Springsteen, on her MTV Unplugged special,
singing "Piece of My Heart" at Janis Joplin's
induction into the Rock and Roll Hall of
Fame, and appearing at Woodstock in 1999.
More than this, however, she has devoted herself
to social activism, especially as a gay rights
advocate. She publicly announced her own
lesbianism in 1993. Etheridge does not shy
away from controversy in her songs or in her
life, but she says (as if with disappointment)
that the only place where her concerts have
drawn right-wing protests is her hometown of
Leavenworth.


David J. Wishart
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Nickson, Chris. The Only One. New York: St. Martin's
Press, 1997.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>