<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ha.022</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Jimenez, Luis (b. 1940)</field>
      <field name="author">Janovy, Karen O.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




JIMENEZ, LUIS (b. 1940)

Luis Alfonso Jimenez Jr., one of the Americas'
most important Hispanic artists, was born on
July 14, 1940, in El Paso, Texas. He received
a bachelor of science degree in art and architecture
from the University of Texas in 1964.
The same year, he attended Ciudad Universitaria,
Mexico. He has been awarded the prestigious
Mid-Career Fellowship Awards at the
American Academy in Rome and the National
Endowment for the Arts, and the American
Institute of Architects Environmental Improvement
Award for Vaquero, his work of
sculpture in Moody Park, Houston, Texas.
Numerous other commissions and exhibitions
are at institutions such as the National
Museum of American Art, Washington DC;
New York's Metropolitan Museum of Art; the
Art Institute of Chicago; the Modern Art Museum
of Fort Worth; the San Antonio Museum
of Arts; and the Sheldon Memorial Art
Gallery, University of Nebraska–Lincoln.

Jimenez's technique in creating monumental
sculptures was learned in the workshop of
his father, a sign painter and neon sign maker.
He is widely known for his large, public, fiberglass
sculptures that are based on a contemporary
language and convey a "Tex-Mex"
flavor, inviting spirited dialogue not only
about their subject matter but also their medium.
He incorporates age-old Chicano and
Mexican icons that can be thought of in a
more popular idiom, and he challenges accepted
notions of the definition of art. His
vigorous, gestural drawings also are full of a
sense of pride in his Latino heritage.


Karen O. Janovy
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Zamudio-Taylor, Victor. "Chicano Art." In Latin American Art in the Twentieth Century, edited by Edward J. Sullivan.
London: Phaidon Press, 1996: 318–21.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>