<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ct.029</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Lawton, Oklahoma</field>
      <field name="author">Crawford, Suzanne Jones</field>
      <field name="text">

 




LAWTON, OKLAHOMA

Situated in southwestern Oklahoma between
the ninety-eighth and ninety-ninth meridians,
roughly nine miles from a small cavalry
post, Lawton resulted from acts of Congress in
1900 and 1901 that eliminated the Kiowa, Comanche,
and Apache Reservation by allotting
every family 160 acres and opening the surplus
land to non-Indian settlement under the
provisions of the homestead and town-site
laws. By March 1901 federal officials had completed
the task of Indian allotment, and on
July 4, 1901, President William McKinley declared
the area ready for settlement.

To avoid the confusion and chaos that had
previously accompanied the establishment of
counties and county seats in Oklahoma Territory,
the secretary of the interior was empowered
to divide the former reservation into
counties and to specify the names and locations
of the county seats. The Interior Department
was also vested with the responsibility
for platting each county seat. In accordance
with Congress's provisions, the sale of commercial
and residential lots in Lawton was to
be done by public auction under the direction
of the Department of the Interior. The bidding
for town lots began on August 6, 1901.
The rapid, orderly sale of town lots spurred
the formation of a local government. On September
28, 1901, Lawton became an incorporated
city with a mayor-council system of government.
In 1911 Lawtonians switched to the
commission plan of government, but in the
1920s city government reverted to the mayor-council
form. Finally in 1972, Lawton voters
adopted the current structure of city manager,
mayor, and city council.

Lawton's initial boomers never imagined
that the nearby fort would have a decided impact
on the future of the new town. They envisioned
that Lawton would become mainly a
commercial hub for the surrounding agriculture
hinterland. However, the designation of
Fort Sill as a field artillery center changed
the outlook of the community. From 1909 onward,
the city's population and economy have
been closely tied to the level of activity of Fort
Sill, and although some economic diversification
has occurred, Fort Sill remained the biggest
employer in the community in 1998.
From 1940 to 1970 the city more than quadrupled
its size, swelling from 18,055 to 74,470.
Much of this growth stemmed from the expansion
of Fort Sill. Subsequent reduction in
military spending has halted Lawton's population
explosion. After 1970 the city's population
increased more slowly, reaching 81,110
in 1998.

Lawton did experience some economic
change during this same period as it developed
new industries. The construction of a
Goodyear tire factory during the 1970s helped
to wean the city from its dependence on Fort
Sill; currently, Goodyear represents the second
largest employer in Lawton. The city also
functions as a regional health-care and higher
education center and continues to act as a retail
hub for surrounding counties in southwestern
Oklahoma. In addition, the adjacent
Wichita Mountain Wildlife Refuge draws
thousands of tourists to the city each year.

See also WAR: Military Bases.


Suzanne Jones Crawford
Cameron University




Crawford, Suzanne Jones. "L. M. Gensman: A Study of
an Early Twentieth Century Western Attorney." Ph.D.
diss., University of Oklahoma, 1980. Stevens, M. David.
Lawton–Ft. Sill: A Pictorial History. Virginia Beach VA:
Donning Company Publishers, 1990.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>