<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.rel.042</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Roberts, Oral (b. 1918)</field>
      <field name="author">Harrell, Jr., David Edwin</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ROBERTS, ORAL (b. 1918)


Prayer Tower at Oral Roberts University


Born on January 24, 1918, in Pontotoc Country,
Oklahoma, Oral Granville Roberts was
one of the chief architects of a pentecostal/
charismatic revival that flourished in the
twentieth century, significantly altering the religious
demography of the world. The son of
Ellis Roberts, an itinerant evangelist in the
Pentecostal Holiness Church, Roberts believed
that he was divinely healed of tuberculosis
while a teenager, and shortly afterward
he was ordained by the Pentecostal Holiness
Church. In 1947 he made a bold decision to
give up his position as pastor of a church in
Enid, Oklahoma, to launch an independent
healing ministry. In the second half of the
twentieth century, Roberts was the most famous
pentecostal evangelist in the world; he
developed fresh methods of fund-raising and
collected hundreds of millions of dollars to
support a diverse assortment of ministries. In
addition to conducting revivals in many nations,
in the 1950s he launched innovative radio
and television ministries. In 1965 Roberts
opened Oral Roberts University in Tulsa. In
1980 Roberts set out to add a hospital and
medical school to the university. While the
university was a successful educational enterprise,
the medical school survived for only
seven years. By the end of the 1980s Roberts
had turned over most of the responsibility for
his ministry and the university to his son,
Richard Roberts.

Roberts's choice of Tulsa as his home base
was a calculated decision. His roots went deep
into the soil of Oklahoma; he was proud that
his maternal great-grandmother had been a
full-blood Cherokee Indian. He imbibed the
Wild West enthusiasm of post–World War II
Tulsa; it was a place, he believed, where "great
ideas can be had and great movements can be
launched." Roberts's presence in Tulsa attracted
other evangelists to the city, making it
a hub of conservative religious activities in the
last half of the twentieth century.

Often ridiculed during his early years as a
"fake healer" and charlatan, Roberts usually
had an uneasy relationship with the press and
with mainstream American religious leaders.
However, in the late 1960s Roberts made a series
of decisions that for a time improved his
public image. In 1968 he stopped holding tent
revivals and discontinued the television programs
that had featured people lining up to be
healed. A few months later, in a risky and expensive
venture, Roberts released a series of
professionally produced television specials
that were aired in prime time. At the same
time, Roberts left the Pentecostal Holiness
Church to become a member of the prestigious
Boston Avenue Methodist Church in
Tulsa. In the 1980s Roberts's public image
once again plummeted. He was criticized by
many Tulsa leaders who opposed the building
of the huge City of Faith Hospital and by the
media because of the extravagant fund-raising
tactics he used to fund his excursion into
medical education. In addition, while no hint
of scandal ever touched Roberts and his wife,
Evelyn, his ministry suffered because of widespread
criticism of televangelists following the
exposes of Jim Bakker and Jimmy Swaggart in
the late 1980s.

Oral Roberts was a pivotal figure in twentieth-century
Protestantism. He pioneered
many of the television techniques that made
possible the rapid expansion of religious television
in the 1970s and 1980s, and he also devised
many of the fund-raising strategies used
by later television ministers. Probably more
important in the long run, in the 1960s Roberts
anticipated the spread of the pentecostal emphasis
on the gifts of the Holy Spirit and divine
healing into mainstream Protestant churches
and the Roman Catholic Church. As early as
the 1950s, Roberts's tent campaigns included
people from many different churches, and in
the 1960s Roberts consciously turned his attention
to ministering to nonpentecostal Christians.
Through his writings and in scores of
conferences at Oral Roberts University, Roberts
encouraged a revising of pentecostal theology
that made it more palatable to mainstream
Christians. By the end of the twentieth century,
Oral Roberts had become a guiding figure
to millions of charismatic Christians around
the world.


David Edwin Harrell, Jr.
Auburn University




Harrell, David Edwin Jr. Oral Roberts: An American Life.
Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1985. Robinson,
Wayne A. Oral: The Warm, Intimate Unauthorized Portrait
of a Man of God. Los Angeles: Acton House, 1976.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>