<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.mus.019</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Guthrie, Woody (1912-1967)</field>
      <field name="author">Lookingbill, Brad</field>
      <field name="text">

 




GUTHRIE, WOODY (1912-1967)

Woody Guthrie, 1943
     

Woodrow Wilson, or Woody, Guthrie was
born in Okemah, Oklahoma, on July 14, 1912.
His formative years exposed him to middleclass
circumstances in a wild and restless
boomtown, although his family life unraveled
by 1927. His father, Charlie, became an alcoholic,
while his mother, Nora, suffered from
Huntington's chorea and was committed to a
mental institution.

Relocating to Pampa, Texas, in 1929, Guthrie
met and married his first wife, Mary Jennings.
While listening to the voices emanating
from the region, he developed his musical talents
and appropriated cowboy songs, gospel
hymns, and hard-luck blues for his repertoire.
Soon he discovered a new life as a rambling
minstrel, playing folksy songs on his guitar at
country dances, rodeos, and carnivals.

In 1937, after experiencing firsthand the blistering
heat and sandstorms of the Dust Bowl,
Guthrie left his family and took to the road. He
arrived in California, where a relative helped
him find work. The boom in country music on
the radio brought ballads to KFVD in Los Angeles,
California, and listeners enjoyed folk
songs that described a distant homeland and
"cornpone" philosophy. While referencing experiences
seemingly long ago and far away,
Guthrie's lyrics summoned an audience's recollections
of hard times in the heartland. From
the beginning of his musical career, he was
dubbed the Dust Bowl Troubadour and the
Okie Balladeer. After a divorce from his first
wife, he married Marjorie Mazia in 1945.

While playing the restless saloon singer,
Guthrie matured into a visionary artist. He
wrote a column for the People's Daily World and
crafted poetry, a novel, and an autobiography.
Composing more than 1,000 songs, he sang of
the Dust Bowl, President Roosevelt's New Deal,
antifascist patriotism, union organization, and
child's play. His titles ranged from "Jesus
Christ" to "Union Maid." His working-class
heroes traveled with him in the classic anthem
"This Land Is Your Land." Over the course of
his journey, he collaborated with Maxine
"Lefty Lou" Crissman, Pete Seeger, Leadbelly,
Burl Ives, Cisco Houston, and Alan Lomax. By
the 1960s, Guthrie had become a legendary
icon for a younger generation of protest musicians,
including Bob Dylan and Joan Baez. His
influence is still seen in the more contemplative
songs of Bruce Springsteen.

Guthrie identified with the "Dust Bowl refugees"
of the Great Plains and, in efect, reinvented
himself. Through the chords of memory
he articulated a collective search among
plain-folk Americans for a better life. While
musing that socialism offered a new hope for
this kind of proletariat, he sang about a primitive
rebel in a nascent state. The wiry balladeer
came to embody the rambling Okie of his
songs. After suffering for fifteen years from
Huntington's chorea, he died in New York on
October 3, 1967.

See also PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT: Dust Bowl / POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT: New Deal.


Brad Lookingbill
Columbia College




Guthrie, Woody. Bound for Glory. New York: E. P. Dutton,
1943. Klein, Joe. Woody Guthrie: A Life. New York: Alfred
A. Knopf, Inc., 1980. Lookingbill, Brad. "Dusty Apocalypse
and Socialist Salvation: A Study of Woody Guthrie's
Dust Bowl Imagery." Chronicles of Oklahoma 72 (1994–
95): 396–413.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>