<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.gen.010</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Diggs, Annie (1848-1916)</field>
      <field name="author">Stone, Joan</field>
      <field name="text">

 




DIGGS, ANNIE (1848-1916)

Annie LePorte Diggs played a prominent role
as a Kansas-based journalist, orator, and political
organizer for women's suffrage, the Farmers
Alliance, the Populist (People's) Party, and
many other causes. The thread that joined all
the causes together was her quest for a more
equitable distribution of wealth and power.

Born in London, Ontario, on February 22,
1848, and raised in New Jersey, Annie moved to
Kansas in 1873. She soon married, bore three
children, and found she needed employment
to supplement the family income. She chose
newspaper work, which threw her among all
classes of people. Although she entered the
political arena via temperance and religion, a
trip to Boston in 1881 convinced her that the
reforms she sought were more economic than
moral. The Boston trip also marked the beginning
of her pattern of leaving Kansas to research
social issues, give speeches, and write
articles for local and national publications,
and then returning to Kansas to organize for
major political campaigns.

From the 1880s to 1912, when Kansas finally
ratified the women's suffrage amendment, Annie
was a leader in the suffrage struggle. For the
Farmers Alliance she wrote and lectured on the
themes of money, transportation, and land,
and pushed for farmers and workers to form a
national third party. Her hard work in the development
of the Populist Party culminated in
her appointment as Kansas State Librarian
(1898-1902), the most important governmental
office assigned to a Kansas woman by that
date. Even after the Populist Party died, she
remained committed to its principle of public
ownership of public utilities and its mission of
bringing justice to the dealings between owners
and workers in the realm of industry. Annie
Diggs died in Detroit on September 7, 1916.


Joan Stone
University of Kansas




Clanton, O. Gene. Kansas Populism. Lawrence: University
Press of Kansas, 1969. Weddle, Connie Andes. "The Platform
and the Pen: The Reform Activities of Annie Diggs."
Master's thesis, Wichita State University, 1979.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>