<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.war.052</field>
      <field name="titleMain">War Chiefs</field>
      <field name="author">Gump, James O.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




WAR CHIEFS

Since superior performance in warfare constituted
a principal measure of leadership potential,
many Native American societies of the
Great Plains during the preconquest era embraced
the concept of a war chief (e.g., toyopki
to the Kiowas; blotahunka among the Oglala
Sioux) and constructed a cultural order that
reinforced a military tradition. For instance,
male warriors belonging to Plains tribes such
as the Arapahos, Blackfoot, Cheyennes, Comanches,
Crows, Kiowas, and Lakotas elevated
their status by winning battle distinctions.
As honors accrued, men embellished
brave deeds through public recitations and
symbolic ornamentation. Assiniboine males
acquired eagle feathers for each martial exploit;
Blackfoot warriors accumulated white
weasel skins; and successful Crow soldiers attached
wolf tails to the heels of their moccasins.
Such recognition did not require the
killing of an enemy or the taking of a scalp. In
fact, in many Plains societies the practice of
counting coup, or touching an enemy with
one's hand or a special stick, outranked killing
as a heroic deed. A Blackfoot warrior, for example,
always dwelt on the number of horses
and guns he captured, not on the quantity of
enemies extinguished. One of the principal
avenues for achieving exalted warrior status
was a.liation with a military society. Sporting
names such as the Dog Soldiers, Fox Soldiers,
and Kit Foxes, war societies extended membership
only to the most promising young
men of the band.

Most Indigenous societies of the Great
Plains practiced some form of hereditary
chieftainship and recognized a head chief. In
theory, the head chief presided over a council
composed of war chiefs, headmen, warriors,
and holy men. In practice, however, charismatic,
self-made war-party leaders often exercised
the most significant authority, especially
in times of crisis. The career of the Oglala
Lakota leader Red Cloud is illustrative. Red
Cloud became a war chief of an Oglala band in
the early 1840s. His power and prestige increased
over the next two decades as a result of
military successes against the Crows, Pawnees,
and Shoshones, as well as his strategic intervention
against whites along the Bozeman
Trail. By the late 1860s the American government
regarded Red Cloud, who still retained
only war chief status among the Oglalas, as the
principal Lakota chief. American officials
sought Red Cloud's influence in negotiating a
peaceful resolution to the warfare raging in the
Northern Plains at the time.

Conflict among the Plains tribes, regardless
of warfare's exalted status, was not a "natural"
condition or simply the result of the "aggressive
instincts" of male warriors. Instead, wars
took place primarily in light of pragmatic
considerations–acquiring horses, expanding
trade, capturing hunting grounds, or defending
compatriots from the incursions of the
U.S. military. In addition, the dynamics of
Plains Indian warfare changed over time in
relation to the shifting cultural landscape. For
example, the acquisition of horses from the
Spanish Southwest during the seventeenth and
eighteenth centuries accelerated the nomadic
lifestyle of bison hunters like the Kiowas, Cheyennes,
and Lakotas, thereby intensifying the
competition for buffalo hunting grounds. In
conjunction with the horse, the procurement of
guns from French, British, and American traders
between the seventeenth and nineteenth
centuries contributed to various military imbalances
in the Great Plains, to the benefit of
groups such as the Blackfoot, Comanches, and
Lakotas. During the late eighteenth and early
nineteenth centuries, the spread of disease
pathogens exacerbated these imbalances. Horticultural
peoples like the Arikaras, Mandans,
and Hidatsas suffered grievously from smallpox
epidemics. On the other hand, migratory hunters
like the Lakotas escaped the wholesale ravages
of disease, enjoyed unprecedented population
growth in the early 1800s, and used their
demographic advantage to dominate much of
the Central and Northern Plains by the mid.
nineteenth century.

By the 1850s, however, the onrush of white
competitors into the trans-Missouri West
posed new military challenges for Native
Americans and forced innovative responses.
The mounting threat gave rise to alliances
among various Plains groups, formed to protect
resources as well as one another from the
white invasion. In the Northern Plains, the
Lakotas, Arapahos, and Cheyennes joined
forces; to the south, the Comanches and Kiowas
built alliances with the Cheyennes and
Arapahos. Emphasis on military accomplishment
within tribes assumed even greater significance
in the nineteenth century, when
white intrusion made martial readiness a prerequisite
to a group's survival. Consequently,
the closing frontier era produced some of the
most notable war chiefs, including Quanah
Parker (Comanche), Satank (Kiowa), and
Crazy Horse (Oglala Lakota).


James O. Gump
University of San Diego




Mishkin, Bernard. Rank and Warfare among the Plains
Indians. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1992.
Secoy, Frank Raymond. Changing Military Patterns of the
Great Plains Indians. Lincoln: University of Nebraska
Press, 1992. Utley, Robert M. The Indian Frontier of the
American West, 1846–1890. Albuquerque: University of
New Mexico Press, 1984.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>