<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.tra.003</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Aviation</field>
      <field name="author">Neufeld, David</field>
      <field name="text">

 




AVIATION


Fuel truck and biplane at Denver (Colorado) Municipal Airport, between 1929 and 1935


The history of air transport in the Great Plains
has been shaped by several factors. The diffuse
population and moderate size of urban centers
in the Great Plains, along with the greater
volume of travel between the larger urban
centers, limited the development of regional
air travel and freight. Nevertheless, the technological
evolution of aircraft, especially the
increasing reliability of engines, range, and
load capacity, gradually made air a viable alternative
to other forms of transport. The evolution
of the necessary supporting infrastructure
of airports, navigation aids, and weather
forecasting also allowed broader public access
to and confidence in the new airlines. Finally,
the interplay of private business interests and
government regulation in both Canada and
the United States played a central part in the
character of the new industry and its role in
the Great Plains.

The high profile of aviation during World
War I and its legacy of trained pilots and
cheap surplus aircraft prompted an immediate
postwar interest in the possibilities of civil
aviation. This was especially so in the Great
Plains because of the great distances and limited
rail connections between urban centers.
However, the restricted utility of ex–
war machines and the lack of even the most
basic support facilities failed to attract capital
investment.

Nevertheless, the barnstorming of the early
1920s did play an important role in capturing
the public's imagination. By the end of the
decade many Plains municipalities were building
airports, anxious to connect with the new
mode of transportation. Federal contributions
in both Canada and the United States were
initially limited to the development of aeronautical
aids in the form of charts and navigation
beacons and airmail subsidies for the air
transport industry. In the American Great
Plains, small interurban airlines were established
on largely north–south routes to act as
feeders to the transcontinental railways. Farther
north, Canadian companies similarly developed
a north–south network, but there the
airlines were more involved in air freight, supporting
the development of a mining industry
beyond the reach of roads and rail.

Regional aviation was largely left to the private
sector. However, national interests in a stable
air transport industry led to a highly regulated
environment. While this included the
creation of a Canadian government national
airline, in both countries it reinforced and institutionalized
a split between large national
carriers that crossed the country and regional
airlines that fed into this larger network.

Civil aviation boomed after World War II,
fostered by the expanded wartime aviation infrastructure,
the availability of trained pilots
and mechanics, and the establishment of a
successful aircraft manufacturing industry
within the region. Public confidence in air
travel also grew, and by the late 1960s air had
surpassed rail in passenger travel. Government
regulation remained a prominent feature
of the industry but was soon to decline in
importance with consequent changes in air
transport structure and character.

The expansion of the highway system
through the 1950s and 1960s, heavily subsidized
by the national government, began to
undermine the utility of the short-haul airlines
that served Great Plains cities. The deregulation
of the airline industry in the late 1970s and
1980s also removed government support for
regional service, and less-profitable service to
many communities was abandoned. The previous
separation between national and regional
carriers dissolved, and smaller companies
operated in a hub-and-spoke system
largely centered on cities outside of the Great
Plains, further eroding levels of service to
many Plains communities.

See also GENDER: Earhart, Amelia.


David Neufeld
Parks Canada




Bilstein, Roger E. Flight in America 1900–1983: From the
Wrights to the Astronauts. Baltimore MD: Johns Hopkins
University Press, 1984. Davies, R. E. G. Airlines of the United
States since 1914. New York: Putnam, 1972. Main, J. R. K.
Voyageurs of the Air: A History of Civil Aviation in Canada,
1858–1967. Ottawa: Canada Department of Transport,
1967.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>