<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pe.019</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Climate</field>
      <field name="author">Leathers, Daniel J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CLIMATE

To a large extent, the climate of the Great
Plains is determined by its geographic position
within North America. The region is affected
by several different air mass types that
possess very different temperature and moisture
properties. Air masses that move south
over the region, from the dry, often snow-covered
interior sections of central Canada,
bring cold, dry air across the Plains. Air
masses that form over the Gulf of Mexico and
the Caribbean often move northward into the
Plains with warm, very moist air. Occasionally,
very warm, dry air will enter the Plains
with air masses that originate in the desert
areas of the southwestern United States and
northern Mexico. Finally, air that originates
over the Pacific Ocean will often move east,
crossing the mountainous region of the western
third of the United States into the Great
Plains. The transport of this air up the windward
side of a mountain barrier and then
down the leeward side results in significant
warming and drying. Depending on the time
of year, one or a combination of these air
masses typically dominate much of the Great
Plains region.

Another major factor in the climate of the
Great Plains is its location near the center of
the continent, a great distance from any large
body of water. For a given input or output of
energy, the temperature of water changes
much more slowly than that of soil surfaces.
Thus the temperature in an area in close proximity
to a large body of water typically experiences
a more consistent climate because of the
moderating effects of the water (such an area
is cooler in the summer and warmer in the
winter). As a result of soil surfaces heating and
cooling rapidly, regions remote from large water
bodies experience large variations in temperature
throughout the course of a year and
over a twenty-four-hour period.

The Great Plains, therefore, has a large range
in both annual and daily temperatures. During
the midwinter months (January and February),
when cold, dry air from central Canada
dominates, temperatures are very cold, with
mean temperatures varying from 40ºF across
the Southern Plains to as low as 10ºF across the
Canadian Prairies. During midsummer (July
and August), when the Plains are dominated
by either warm, moist air from the Gulf of
Mexico or warm, dry air from the Southwest,
mean temperatures increase to approximately
80ºF through the Southern Plains and approximately
66ºF across the Canadian Prairies. This
gives the region a much larger range in annual
temperature than is found elsewhere in North
America. For example, the range in mean
monthly temperature between January and
July in Omaha, Nebraska, is approximately
56ºF, while in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, and
San Francisco, California (each at a similar
latitude), the ranges are 46ºF and 14ºF respectively.
The daily temperature range across the
Plains generally increases to the north and
west, away from the moderating influence of
the Gulf of Mexico. During July, the mean daily
temperature range across the Plains is approximately
30\F, while in the eastern parts of
North America the daily range is 20ºF and
along the Pacific coast only 10ºF.

Precipitation across the Great Plains decreases
dramatically from southeast to northwest.
The main source of atmospheric moisture
is the Gulf of Mexico. Areas near the Gulf,
in the southeastern portion of the Plains, receive
more than forty inches of precipitation
annually. This total decreases to less than fourteen
inches in eastern Montana and parts of
the Canadian Prairies. The annual cycle of
precipitation across the Plains is dominated
by a summer maximum. During the summer
months warm, moist air masses move north
from the Gulf of Mexico. These air masses
normally produce showers and thunderstorms
because of their unstable characteristics.
During the spring cold, dry air masses
from central Canada often interact with the
air from the Gulf to set the stage for the outbreak
of severe thunderstorms that can bring
heavy rainfall, high winds, hail, and tornadoes
to local areas. During the winter snow normally
covers a substantial portion of the
Plains. Annual snowfall averages from less
than one inch across the southern portion of
the region to more than forty inches across
the north. Because of the cold winter temperatures
and the relatively heavy annual
snowfall, snow cover blankets the Northern
Plains throughout much of the winter season.

The year-to-year variability in temperature
and precipitation across the Great Plains is
very large. This variability is especially evident
in the recurrent problem of drought. The very
warm and often dry summer weather that is
characteristic of the Plains leads to high evaporation
and transpiration (water loss from
plants) rates. Soils are often depleted of their
moisture, leading to stressed natural and cultivated
vegetation. A measure of the lack of
available soil moisture for plants, the soil
moisture deficit, has been calculated for the
entire Great Plains region for the period 1895
through 1994. From this it is clear that the
Plains as a whole has undergone recurrent periods
of drought over the last century, especially
during the 1930s (the Dust Bowl years)
and the 1950s. The large annual (within one
year) and interannual (year-to-year) variability
of Great Plains climate makes the region
a natural laboratory for studying the effects of
climate variability on a host of problems associated
with the interaction of humans with
their environment.

See also AGRICULTURE: Agricultural Meteorology / INDUSTRY: Weather Industry / WATER: Drought.


Daniel J. Leathers
University of Delaware




Borchert, John R. "The Climate of the Central North
American Grassland." Annals of the Association of American
Geographers 40 (1950): 1–39. Lawson, Merlin P., and
Charles W. Stockton. "Desert Myth and Climatic Reality."
Annals of the Association of the American Geographers 71
(1981): 527–35. Rosenberg, Norman J. "Climate of the
Great Plains Region of the United States." Great Plains
Quarterly 6 (1986): 22–32.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>