<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fil.019</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Disney, Walt (1901-1966)</field>
      <field name="author">Tibbetts, John C.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




Disney, Walt (1901-1966)

Walt Disney
        

After creating Mickey Mouse in 1928, Walt
Disney proceeded in his cartoons, movies,
television shows, and theme parks to establish
an entertainment empire, dedicated to recreating
American popular culture in Disney's
own image. Walt was essentially a product of
his midwestern upbringing. Born in Chicago
on December 5, 1901, the fourth son of Elias
and Flora Disney, he grew up in two Missouri
towns, rural Marceline and urban Kansas City,
where he acquired the background experience
and moral outlook–Protestant values, indomitable
self-reliance, a sturdy work ethic,
and a distrust of outsiders–that would pervade
all of his work.

Disney began as a cartoonist and animator
from 1921 to 1923 for Kansas City Film Ad and
for his own company, Laugh-O-Gram, producing
animated advertisements for local theaters
and a series of fairy tales for national
distribution. Before he left Kansas City for
good in 1923, he had gathered around him a
circle of friends and associates who would,
either as colleagues or eventual competitors,
follow him to Los Angeles and collectively
change the face of American animation: Ub
Iwerks (thereafter Disney's chief technical supervisor),
theater organist Carl Stalling (who
would later join the Warner Bros. cartoon unit
as its principal composer), Fritz Freleng (later
a cartoon producer for Warner Bros. and for
his own Depatie-Freleng company), and
Hugh Harmon and Rudolph Ising (later the
heads of Harmon-Ising animation, which
originated the Bosco cartoons and the Merrie Melodies series for Warner Bros.).

In important respects, Walt never really left
Kansas City and the Midwest behind. By all
accounts, his early years working on his father's
farm near Marceline, Missouri, were
filled with pain and hardship, dominated by
his abusive father. Yet he transformed and idealized
this miserable experience into a fantasy
of life in a picturesque, turn-of-the-century
small town–with its town square, bandstand,
and quaint shop fronts–that appears in virtually
all the Mickey Mouse cartoons (beginning
with Steamboat Willie in 1928) and in
dozens of live-action feature films and television
shows, including So Dear to My Heart
(1946), Pollyanna (1960), Mary Poppins (1964),
and the Mickey Mouse Club series in the 1950s.
Significantly, it was Marceline's Main Street
that Disney reconstituted into the "Main
Street" of the theme parks in Anaheim, Orlando,
Paris, and Tokyo, the only area through
which every visitor must pass. This obsession
with order and detestation of dirt points up
the midwesterner's ambivalent attitude toward
the soil, the fertile ground from which
both food springs and encroaching weeds
must be cleared away, and it is most graphically
demonstrated in the substantial amount
of screen time (fully one-third of the total
film) devoted to Snow White's instructions to
the Seven Dwarfs about how best to clean up
their cottage. Walt insisted with equal fervor
on tidying and cultivating his own media image
as a plainspoken interpreter of cultural
artifacts like classical music and great works
of literature, diluting and packaging them in
forms accessible to the great American mass
audience. Although he died on December 16,
1966, this process, dubbed the "Disneyfication"
of America, continues. He embodies
the energy that once settled the New World,
plowed it under, paved it over, and pushed its
frontiers ever westward and that now busily
reconfigures it into myth and memory.


John C. Tibbetts
University of Kansas




Schickel, Richard. The Disney Version. New York: Simon
and Schuster, 1968. Shortridge, James R. The Middle West: Its Meaning in American Culture. Lawrence: University
Press of Kansas, 1989. Smoodin, Eric, ed. Disney Discourse: Producing the Magic Kingdom. New York: Frederick Ungar,
1978.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>