<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.art.016</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Dunbier, Augustus (1888-1977)</field>
      <field name="author">Dunbier, Lonnie Pierson</field>
      <field name="text">

 




DUNBIER, AUGUSTUS (1888-1977)

Augustus W. Dunbier, one of Nebraska's most
prominent artists in the early and mid–
twentieth century, was a prolific oil painter
who maintained studios in Omaha from 1916
until his death on September 11, 1977. He was
known for his colorful landscapes, still lifes,
portraits, and figures in an impressionistic
style.

Dunbier was born on a farm in Polk County,
Nebraska, on January 1, 1888. At age sixteen he
moved with his parents to Germany, where
from 1907 to 1914 he was enrolled at the Royal
Academy in Düsseldorf. He later studied at the
Chicago Art Institute. Dunbier returned to
Nebraska just before World War I and opened
his Omaha studio. In 1932 he married Lou
Eckstrom from Newman Grove, Nebraska,
and they had one son, Roger.

In Omaha Dunbier earned a living from the
sale of his paintings, many of them portraits
of prominent persons, and by teaching at
the ymca and later from his home studio at
914 North 49th Avenue. He also conducted
workshops all over Nebraska except in Lincoln,
where he appears to have been unwelcome
because of what was regarded as his
old-fashioned painting style and his vocal disdain
of the university's growing modernist art
collection.

The majority of Dunbier's landscapes, numbering
several thousand, were painted in his
home state, where the artist loved the hills and
trees, lakes and rivers, farm scenes, and city-scapes.
He completed most of these landscapes
outdoors, taking no more than several hours
for each work. In the evenings he frequently
would carve a frame for the painting made that
day, and he often commented that it took him
longer to carve and gild a frame than to paint a
painting. Paintings by Augustus Dunbier are in
the Joslyn Art Museum in Omaha, Nebraska,
the Sheldon Memorial Art Gallery in Lincoln,
and the Museum of Nebraska Art in Kearney,
where a Dunbier retrospective exhibition was
held in 1994.


Lonnie Pierson Dubier
Scottsdale, Arizona




Hooley, Renee. Western Art Digest 14 (1987): 66–71. Robinson,
Natalie U. Southwest Art 18 (1989): 60–64.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>