<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ea.001</field>
      <field name="titleMain">European Americans</field>
      <field name="author">McQuillan, Aidan</field>
      <field name="text">

 




EUROPEAN AMERICANS


Immigrant woman and children in front of Winnipeg Station, Manitoba, ca. 1909


European immigrants and their descendants
created an archipelago of ethnic communities
in the Great Plains largely between 1860 and
1930, although agricultural settlement began
as early as 1811 in the Earl of Selkirk's colony
in the Red River Valley of the North and the
1830s in the German Hill Country of southern
Texas. Even earlier, European explorers and
fur traders had penetrated most parts of the
Great Plains. Within the flood of settlement
spreading out onto the Plains after 1860 were
distinctive streams of immigrants that fed ethnic
communities that would survive as cultural
islands for decades to come. These European
immigrants, like the migrants from the
eastern and central United States and Canada,
encountered an unforgiving physical environment
that demanded changes in their cultures,
distinctive ways of life, and farming
practices. Over time, depending on the volume
and longevity of the migration streams
and on the stability of the communities,
American-born generations preserved some
of their parents' cultures while adopting
North American ways and creating new patterns
of their own. They contributed to the
successful development of new systems of agriculture
on the western grasslands, actively
participated in the political life of Canada and
the United States, and met the challenges
posed by World War I, which became the first
major test of loyalty to their new homeland. In
doing so, they redefined the meaning of what
was required to be American or Canadian


Creating an Archipelago of Communities

Migrations created these distinctive cultural
communities, and a number of other factors
determined whether these communities
waxed or waned. The volume of immigration
to a given destination was important in forming
a significant spatial cluster, and spatial
clustering was another key factor. If the area
had previously been largely unsettled, then
immigrants might be able to realize their goal
of a homogeneous community. Furthermore,
if new settlers shared a common set of values
and goals, and if they had a strong leader, then
the likelihood of the ethnic community's success
also increased. Conversely, if the migration
stream was heterogeneous and heading
for diverse destinations, with little interest
in clustering, then it was less likely that a
successful ethnic community would emerge.
Proximity to a major urban center from which
metropolitan cultural values emanated might
weaken the cultural distinctiveness of an ethnic
community. If the rate of geographic mobility
was high, as it usually was in North
America, then a community's longevity could
be shortened and its cohesiveness weakened.
However, a continuing stream of new immigrants
into the community would counteract
the outflow of settlers, and in those cases a
transfusion model might be used to explain
the continuing vitality of the community.

Streams of European immigration fed the
newly formed communities in the Great
Plains. A general distinction is drawn between
the waves of transatlantic migration before
the economic depression of 1893–96 and those
between 1896 and 1914. The earlier waves carried
large numbers of Germans and Scandinavians,
mostly to the Great Plains of the United
States; the later waves carried immigrants
from central and eastern Europe, mostly to
the Canadian Prairies. Before 1893 the grasslands
in the United States were the strongest
magnet for transatlantic migrants, but by 1890
opportunities had diminished there, so that
after the depression of the 1890s the Canadian
Prairies represented new opportunities not
only for Ukrainians, Poles, Russians, and
Hungarians from Europe but also for settlers
coming northward from the American Plains.
Indeed, the years between 1896 and 1914 saw
considerable longitudinal relocation within
the grasslands as farmers sought new possibilities
in the "Last Best West." New restrictive
immigration policies in both the United States
and Canada in the years after World War I
curtailed further European immigration to
the Great Plains.

Ethnic communities in the Plains were created
in part by immigrants coming directly
from Europe and in part by settlers from
older, well-established communities in the
central Midwest and eastern Prairies. Some
immigrants began farming in established
communities in Illinois, Wisconsin, Iowa,
Minnesota, or Manitoba, where they worked
as farmhands and earned enough cash to purchase
a farm of their own farther west. In
many cases individual families or several families
traveled in hopscotch fashion across the
Midwest before they arrived on the western
fringe of settlement. The successful creation of
new settlements, however, was not the result
of haphazard migration. Communities were
most often the result of careful planning under
the auspices of a church leader, a group of
businessmen, or with the assistance of a railroad
company. Frequently, the stated goal was
a homogeneous community that would provide
economic security (and implicitly, emotional
and spiritual support) for the families
arriving on the frontier. The concept of the
homogeneous ethnic community was supported
by railroad companies, which saw its
advantages for promoting land sales, but it
was an idea that was not always welcomed by
government.

The U.S. government tended to promote
the individual landowner, and it did not assist
in the creation of homogeneous ethnic settlements
in the Great Plains, whereas the Canadian
government adopted a policy of assisting
such settlements, at least in the early years,
by making block land grants to immigrants.
The arrival in the Plains of large numbers of
Mennonites in the early 1870s from southern
Russia highlighted the differences between the
approaches of the two countries. President
Ulysses S. Grant refused to assist in creating
the homogeneous settlements that the Mennonites
desired. Such communities could be
formed by Mennonites homesteading government
lands and by purchasing intervening
railroad lands, but they would have to do it
without government support. The Canadian
government, however, set aside two large
blocks of land in southern Manitoba exclusively
for Mennonite settlement. Within
twenty years, however, the Canadian government
had changed its mind and thereafter discouraged
large block settlements, although it
made a brief exception in the case of Doukhobor
communities after 1900.

Railroads played an important role in the
creation of ethnic-group communities in the
Plains. Not only did they advertise widely in
western and then eastern Europe, but they
also worked energetically with leaders in both
Europe and U.S. midwestern communities
to organize group migrations to the western
grasslands. Thus, Swedes in Chicago and
Galesburg, Illinois, worked with the Union
Pacific in the late 1860s to found Lindsborg,
the initial magnet for the development of a
broad swath of Swedish communities in central
Kansas. Canadian railways and land companies
joined forces to sell lands to German
Catholics migrating from Minnesota in the
first decade of the twentieth century to create
the large St. Peter's colony in central Saskatchewan
and St. Joseph's colony along the
Saskatchewan-Alberta border. The railways
also influenced the location of ethnic communities:
after 1870 railways replaced rivers as the
major routeways along which settlers traveled
to the agricultural frontier, and railways created
towns along the tracks to serve as markets
and supply points for the surrounding agricultural
hinterland.


Settlers from the United States crossing the land


Ethnic communities in the Great Plains
often began with the creation of daughter
colonies, the offspring of communities in the
eastern and central Midwest and Manitoba.
Frequently, church leaders organized the initial
settlement and negotiated with the railroads
for favorable terms of transportation
and land purchase. Through an intricate network
of contacts extending to Europe, pastors
also attracted new immigrants to emerging
settlements. Thus, the populations of young
communities were often comprised of newly
arrived Europeans as well as those who had
lived for several decades in North America. In
the case of the Canadian Prairies there were
fewer daughter colonies, and less east.west
migration, than in the United States. Nevertheless,
in both countries, the new communities
often included families with some previous
farming experience in North America.



Environmental Adaptation

Few European immigrants, regardless of time
spent in North America, had adequate experience
to prepare them for the Plains environment.
Conditions were markedly different
from the central Midwest and vastly different
from their homelands in northern and western
Europe. Only those who came from eastern
and southern Europe, especially from the
Russian steppes, had encountered environments
with similar challenges to farming. The
grasshopper plagues that swept the Plains
states in 1874 and 1876 were only one of the
many natural hazards to induce fear, anxiety,
and discouragement. Prairie fires, violent
thunderstorms, occasional tornadoes, sudden
blizzards, and hailstorms were among the
most disturbing of nature's trials to test the
pioneers' mettle. Perhaps most unsettling of
all was the persistent and subtle problem of
drought. Changes in the amount of moisture
available for crop growth due to differential
rates of evapotranspiration stymied not only
the immigrant but also American farmers in
the Plains. In the Canadian Prairies these
problems were compounded by the short
growing season and the danger of spring and
fall frosts.


Galician woman delivering milk, Manitoba, ca. 1890–1910


The physical landscape created its own psychological
stresses. The very flatness of the
Western Plains created a sense of anomie even
in the most closely knit ethnic communities. A
great dome of sky stretched to the seemingly
endless horizon, accentuating the smallness of
the human scale and the vulnerability of human
endeavors. The human landscape further
unsettled those who were used to the compact,
tightly defined geography of the densely
populated European lowlands. As the grasslands
were domesticated, field boundaries and
roads accentuated a new rectilinear geometry
in the landscape that heightened the sense of
alienation and intensified the differences from
the European homeland. There was no way
that the Old Country patterns of social life
and economic activity could be replicated in
the Great Plains.

Economic forces also bore down heavily on
settlers. The pioneer phase of settlement was
shorter in the Plains than it had been in the
central Midwest: the influence of market pressures
on farming were brought to bear more
rapidly than farther east as railroads increasingly
penetrated the American Plains in the
two decades following the Civil War. In the
Canadian Prairies, both settlement and the
railroads mainly came later, after the 1896 depression,
and European farmers, many with
only limited experience of the pressures of
commercial agriculture, had to adjust rapidly
to the demands of the North American marketplace.
European ways of doing things, including
European patterns of farming, could
not survive for long in the face of an austere
natural environment, changing mortgage
rates, and fluctuations in the market price
of farm produce. New systems of cropping
and livestock farming necessarily had to be
adopted in the Plains.

On first arrival, some European settlers
tried to generate cash with a specialty crop
or activity that would help them get on their
feet until the farm became fully operational.
Swedes grew broomcorn, for example, while
Mennonite communities produced watermelons
and silkworms in the earliest days.
Other specialty crops included sunflowers, tobacco,
and sugar beets. Ukrainians in Canada
gathered ginseng root as a means of earning
cash in the first years. Soon, however, immigrant
communities adopted one or both of the
great cash crops grown in the central Midwest
and carried out onto the Plains—wheat and
corn. Over time the viability of these two major
cash crops would be tested by drought, and
farmers adopted new crops resistant to moisture
shortages (such as alfalfa and sorghum)
or more suited to the short growing season on
the Canadian Prairies (such as fast-maturing
wheat and the hardy grains). Immigrants, especially
those coming from southeastern Europe,
where environmental conditions most
closely approximated conditions in the Plains,
often led the way in developing dryland farming
techniques and other innovative strategies.
Much has been made of the German Russian
Mennonites' role in introducing hard winter
wheat in central Kansas, which led to the
growth of the winter wheat belt in Kansas and
Oklahoma, but of more lasting importance
was their ability to figure out new patterns of
cropping and livestock farming and new dryland
farming techniques, the best approaches
to agriculture for more than fifty years from
North Dakota to Oklahoma. American farmers,
as well as other European immigrants,
soon learned from the German Russians' success.
European immigrants learned to become
flexible, giving up the labor-intensive methods
they brought with them and adopting the
extensive-farming approaches that were better
suited to the Plains. Similarly, on the Canadian
Prairies new strains of fast-maturing
wheat were the key to success in commercial
agriculture among immigrant communities
in the years before and after World War I.

Transfer from one physical environment
to another produced radical changes in the
immigrants' cultures. The majority of Europeans
encountered not only a different physical
environment but also a different economic
system from those they had known
in the Old Country. Fairly rapidly the immigrants
dropped the distinctive crops and
European patterns of farming and adopted
North American cash crops, then took out
mortgages to expand and mechanize their
farm operations and to provide for a new generation
of farmers. In short, they quickly embraced
the North American world of commercial
agriculture and profit maximization,
and in doing so they accepted the culture of
North American consumerism, thereby modifying
their traditional values according to
their new circumstances.



Cultural Transformation

The issue of cultural transformation is one of
the most complex problems faced by scholars
in studying how Europeans became North
Americans. The outward manifestations of
cultural transfer from the European homeland
have been readily identified and have survived
for decades in the landscape of the
Plains. Germans in the Texas Hill Country
built half-timbered and stone houses and lines
of rock fences, Mennonites attempted to duplicate
village patterns of settlement in reconstructing
their communities in Manitoba and
Kansas in the 1870s, Scandinavian communities
had their distinctive smokehouses, and
immigrants from Russia built summer bake
ovens outside the farmhouse to cope with
summer heat. But deep-seated changes in the
cultures of the immigrants–in their mores
and most closely held values–are not so easily
identified, measured, and tracked in the adaptation
to the new milieu.

These mores and values were reflected in
the religious beliefs of the community, with
the church playing a defining role, frequently
circumscribing the behavior of its members.
In German Catholic and Lutheran communities
the churches defined moral behavior
in ways that clearly reflected their European
antecedents. German churches were perhaps
less restrictive and their members more permissive
than in other churches. The Swedish
Lutheran Church has been described as straitlaced
and puritanical in the early years: dancing,
drinking, and card-playing were forbidden,
a clear example of the transfer of mores
directly from Sweden. The most extreme examples
of this transfer can be found among
Anabaptist groups such as the Mennonites.
Church music, dancing, and smoking were
outlawed, although the use of alcohol was permitted.
Over time these patterns changed as
the church relaxed its strictures: German gospel
hymns were allowed by the late 1890s and
social constraints on youthful Mennonite behavior
were also loosened. Some Mennonites
swung toward temperance and against the repeal
of Prohibition in the 1920s as part of
a drift toward Americanization. In general,
however, churches acted as a disciplinary and
conservative force in preserving the core values
of communities well into the twentieth
century.

Immigrants were mostly drawn from the
conservative peasant class in Europe, and
that conservative outlook persisted for generations
in North America. Historian Oscar
Handlin even suggested that immigrants became
more conservative than their relatives
who remained in Europe. That conservatism
was reflected not only in religious practices
but also in social and economic behavior. The
foreign-born were more fiscally conservative,
less keen to borrow than their American-born
neighbors. Such traits, stemming from their
peasant backgrounds, stood them in good
stead in their struggle to establish themselves
in the Plains. Norwegians, who had no experience
making a living in grasslands, survived
because of habits of industry, frugality, and
perseverance, as well as community cohesiveness.
Swedes were also described as patient,
honest, and persistent, as well as hardheaded,
stubborn, contentious, and tightfisted! Germans
were recognized as tidy, careful, and efficient, with a strong interest in maintaining
family continuity on the farm. The degree of
community cooperation varied from community
to community but was strongest among
the Mennonites. All of these traits reflected
the European peasant traditions from which
Plains settlers were drawn.

The transition from European peasant to
North American commercial farmer wrought
fundamental changes in the immigrants' values.
As their financial condition improved
and farmers increasingly developed an expendable
income, their pastors and priests
railed against the inroads of consumerism and
the loss of traditional spiritual values. As pioneer
farmers expanded their operations and
took out mortgages, they were increasingly
drawn into the world of cash crops and profit
maximization. The rise of economic individualism
within immigrant communities meant
a weakening of community cooperation and
communal responsibility, although the sense
of community did not disappear entirely.
Families slowly adopted new goals in this
world of capitalist agriculture, among them a
concern for continuity on the family farm.
The old peasant desire for land, for a farm
they could call their own, survived the transition
to commercial agriculture.

To be sure, elements of their old cultures
survived in the transfer from life in Europe to
life in the Great Plains, but survival was a selective
process. Crops that were environmentally
suitable and for which there was a market
demand continued to be grown. Patterns of
life that could be incorporated within a dispersed
homestead settlement pattern also persisted.
But the distinctive practices of religious
worship and the constraints on individual behavior
slowly changed with time as moral
values and moral responsibility adapted to the
North American social and economic milieu.
Gradually, the values and behavior of a small
bourgeois class living in small Plains towns
became the norm for the upwardly mobile in
rural communities, especially as the second
generation came of age. These adjustments
marked the first stages in the assimilation of
the immigrants.



Assimilation

The term assimilation refers to the process
whereby immigrants entered the mainstream
and became indistinguishable from other
members of American or Canadian society. In
the United States, Frederick Jackson Turner
proposed that the western frontier acted as a
crucible in which immigrants shed their European
heritage and intermarried to create a new
nation of Americans. His "frontier thesis,"
however, was more a statement of ideals than
an observation of reality: he seemed to ignore
the presence of large, clustered ethnic settlements
on the grasslands where assimilation,
insofar as it existed at all, proceeded at glacial
speed. But where the migration streams to
frontier communities were heavily mixed and
where the Europeans demonstrated a weak interest
in clustered settlement, assimilation
could be fairly rapid. Certainly, the adoption
of the English language was necessary in small,
dispersed communities because it gave the
European immigrant access to a wider world
of commerce, politics, and North American
culture.

Biological assimilation presents a more
complex picture than does linguistic assimilation.
Religion represented a major barrier
to intermarriage, particularly between Protestant
and Catholic immigrants and to a much
lesser degree within various branches of the
Protestant faith. Although the rate of exogamy
(marriage across national lines) was moderately
high within groups of Catholic immigrants,
relatively few Catholics married their
predominantly Protestant American neighbors.
But even among Protestant immigrants,
relatively few married Americans–those from
the British Isles led the way, followed by
the various Scandinavian groups; few Slavic
immigrants engaged Americans in marriage.
On the other hand, biological assimilation
was fairly rapid in small communities where
the choices were limited: immigrants were
obliged to find marriage partners among their
American or other European neighbors. For
many immigrant groups, however, exogamy
was generally discouraged; it was even considered
a sin among the Dutch of Montana. After
World War I the rate of biological assimilation
slowly began to increase, but not until well
after World War II did exogamy rates in most
European ethnic groups rise above 50 percent.

By contrast, European immigrants quickly
adopted American material culture. The use
of distinctive architectural styles and materials
in home building soon gave way to the construction
of American houses. Exceptions to
this general rule can be found among Mennonite
and Ukrainian settlers, especially on
the Canadian Prairies. In the American Plains
the Mennonites discarded their Russian-style
houses with thatched roofs, in addition to the
farm tools and implements they had brought
over, within twenty years of their arrival. The
rectangular survey system in both Canada and
the United States was a powerful influence in
molding the European immigrant to North
American ways of economic individualism
and shaping both the structure and operations
of the farm.

The rate of assimilation among immigrant
groups varied according to the community's
size, location, and whether it was rural or urban.
Generally, the pressures as well as the attractions
to join the mainstream were greater
in towns than in rural areas. Much also depended
on the degree to which each group was
perceived to be acceptable by mainstream society.
British immigrants were ranked first.
Scandinavians were also valued and assimilated
readily, and arguments have been advanced
that Swedes assimilated more rapidly
than Norwegians and vice versa. Danes were
thought to be more clannish, and Germans
seemed to remain aloof longer than others.
The Irish had encountered rejection in the
cities of the Atlantic seaboard, but in the Plains
resistance to them was much modified. French
Canadian communities in Kansas and North
Dakota were small, and they too assimilated
fairly quickly. Strongly sectarian groups such
as the Mennonites, Amish, Doukhobors, and
Hutterites consciously resisted assimilation in
varying degrees, and in many cases still do.


Doukhobor village of Vosnesenya, Thunder Hill Colony, Manitoba


The Canadian Prairies presented a different
milieu from that of the American Plains. The
Prairies were opened for agricultural settlement
just after Canadian Confederation in
1867, which recognized that the Dominion had
two founding nations, France and Britain. A
balance was supposed to be maintained between
the two cultures in this keystone region
within Canadian confederation, but it never
was. The French established a small toehold in
Manitoba in the 1870s and 1880s, but it was
English Canadian farmers, particularly from
Ontario, who shaped the social life and the
economy of the Prairies, far out of proportion
to their numbers. Citizens of the Dominion
thought of themselves as British rather than
Canadian in the final decades of the nineteenth century and well into the twentieth
century (a distinctive Canadian identity did
not appear until after World War I and even
then developed slowly). Certainly after 1890,
when the railway network was being built, the
British norm was in the ascendancy in the
Prairie region. British immigrants, of course,
were seen as the most desirable. But the large
German Catholic colonies in Saskatchewan
were peopled by settlers who had come from
Minnesota expressly to resist assimilation, and
they stood apart. New immigrant groups who
arrived after 1896, such as Ukrainians and
Doukhobors, were subjected to vilification in
the local press. They clearly were not wanted
by the local "host society." Indeed, on the Canadian
Prairies one could make the case for
ethnogenesis rather than assimilation among
many European groups.



Ethnogenesis

Ethnogenesis is the process whereby immigrants
transformed themselves, became members
of an ethnic group, and developed a distinctively
new culture and identity. The new
culture was not a replica of their Old World
culture because social, economic, and especially
physical environmental conditions in
North America were so different from what
they left behind. Immigrants often tried to retain
their European language because it fostered
cohesion within the community, defining
their culture and identity. They clung
to their churches, even though churches were
subject to splits and schisms on the frontier.
They married within their own group and
discouraged exogamy. They easily yielded to
change only in matters of material culture
as they adapted to the new conditions and
opportunities. They clustered in fairly homogeneous
settlements because they could maintain
essential services such as churches and
schools and eventually institutions of mutual
assistance. The larger these homogeneous
settlements the easier it was for the
ethnic community to develop "institutional
completeness."

The ability of ethnic groups to create homogeneous
settlements with a substantial "critical
mass" was very important for ethnogenesis.
Germans and Scandinavians, for example,
streaming into the Upper Midwest and then
into the Plains, homesteaded quarter-sections
and later purchased the intervening railroad
lands for themselves and their children,
thereby creating solid ethnic settlements. As
noted above, Mennonite leaders failed to persuade
American federal officials to help them
create exclusively Mennonite settlements. In
Canada they succeeded, and the government
set aside blocks of townships for Mennonite
settlement in the 1870s. But by the turn of
the century Canadian officials had rejected the
notion of block settlements, and so newly arrived
German Catholics from Minnesota settled
in Saskatchewan without government
block grants; instead, they followed the usual
American pattern of combining homesteads
with railroad lands to create homogeneous
communities. Large homogeneous clusters
provided advantages such as ease of communication,
mutual assistance, and a population
large enough to facilitate endogamy.

Survival of the language is often taken as a
marker of the strength of ethnogenesis within
a community. Men adopted English fairly rapidly,
while women, bound to the domestic domain,
retained the mother tongue and passed
it on to the children. Churches also acted as
a bulwark against the assimilative forces of
the public school; pastors were determined to
keep the traditional language alive by using it
in church services and teaching it in Sunday
schools, summer schools, and in after-school
classes. The various branches of the Lutheran
Church in German and Scandinavian communities
were particularly active in preserving
their mother tongues, whereas the Roman
Catholic Church often, though not always, encouraged
the adoption of English as a means
of achieving unity among their nationally diverse
adherents. The major challenge to linguistic
survival came in 1917 as the United
States entered World War I and a new form of
nativism appeared as an anti-German campaign.
Nevertheless, in many communities
sermons continued to be delivered in the old
language until the 1930s.

An ethnic community fostered cooperation
during the pioneer period and facilitated the
development of social and other services in
later years as the community matured. The
first concern of settlers may have been to create
churches and schools, but soon other institutions
appeared that brought stability and
enhanced the security of the community. Colleges
for training teachers were soon established,
ensuring a continuing ethnic presence
in local schools. Local banks organized by successful
immigrants made credit available to
fellow farmers, while general stores and hotels
proudly announced the ethnic origin of the
owner in the hope of attracting customers. In
time hospitals, orphanages, and old folks'
homes were built to cater to community
needs. Musical groups and athletic clubs provided
social opportunities for young people
in the community. Consequently, some ethnic
communities developed an institutional completeness
that reduced needy immigrants' dependence
on external services, thereby reinforcing
their distinctive identity and keeping
them within the ethnic fold.

Churches played a central role in the formation
of a clustered ethnic community, not
only because they provided religious services
and could control the local public school system,
but also because they exercised powerful
social controls and exerted pressures to
conform within the community. Perhaps the
most extreme examples were (and to a degree,
still are) found in Mennonite, Hutterite, and
Doukhobor communities, but the pattern was
also observed among others. The exercise of
such power brought with it hazards, for it
could lead to schism and disunity. In fact, religious
fracturing was occasionally evident on
the frontier and may be understood as yet another
facet of ethnogenesis, as immigrants adjusted
to their new circumstances and subconsciously
began to work out a new identity
for themselves. Most important, however, the
churches fostered a sense of cohesion and preserved
a sense of cultural identity, in addition
to maintaining moral standards of behavior
within ethnic communities in the Great Plains
–just as they had done in the parent communities
of the eastern Midwest.

Leadership was also tremendously important
in the creation and survival of ethnic
communities. Churches, though an important
source, were not the sole source of leadership
candidates within these communities. Teachers,
newspaper editors, and occasionally politicians
emerged as leaders. But lay leaders
rarely challenged the religious leadership. Indeed,
the two categories were not mutually
exclusive–some of the early political leaders
among the Swedes in Kansas were Lutheran
pastors. Newspaper editors created a unique
form of leadership, publishing foreign-language
papers that linked local communities
to a network of ethnic communities across
the Plains and even eastward throughout the
Midwest. These networks were often sustained
by familial ties, especially where daughter colonies
had been created. They kept local readers
informed of events far beyond the local
community and in doing so connected it to a
wide network of communities of their own
kind, whether German, Swedish, Norwegian,
Danish, or Irish, scattered across North America.
The conscious realization that other communities
survived elsewhere in the West and
Midwest was an important factor in ethnogenesis
and in the emergence of ethnic block
voting in regional and national elections.



Political Participation

Newly arrived immigrants usually had little
concern for politics beyond local concerns
such as operating schools, but as their communities
matured they were increasingly
drawn into national political issues. The arcane
debates over monetary issues, for example,
were initially beyond their comprehension,
but local social and cultural issues
engaged their avid attention. Several sectarian
ethnic groups (Hutterites, Doukhobors, and
some Mennonites at first) did not participate
in the political arena: they refused to vote, hold
public office, or engage in public litigation.
Within two decades, however, as Mennonite
isolationism broke down and as they realized
the necessity of protecting their school system,
they were drawn into politics. The issues that
became lightning rods for ethnic political participation
were prohibition, women's suffrage,
and state regulation of parochial schools, although
when the financial crisis of the late
1880s and the depression of the 1890s threatened
foreclosure of their mortgages, many
ethnics abandoned their traditional party affiliations
and supported the Populist wildfire
sweeping the Plains states.

The Republican Party attracted many
foreign-born in the years before and during
the Civil War because of the immigrants' revulsion
to slavery. The Germans in Texas rejected
not only slavery but also secession from
the Union and conscription in the Confederate
army. As the northern Plains states were
settled in the decades after the Civil War
the majority of new immigrants continued
to embrace the Republican Party. Protestant
immigrants joined the Republican Party,
while Catholic immigrants tended to become
Democrats. There were exceptions, however.
Some German Methodists joined the Democratic
Party whereas French Canadians were
mostly Republican. In Canada, British immigrants
tended to be solidly Conservative.
Later immigrants found the Liberal Party
more welcoming.

The decade of the 1890s was a fractious one
in the United States as the economic bubble
burst and depression set in. Many ethnics were
shaken loose from their traditional political
a.liations when mortgage rates escalated and
farm loans were foreclosed. Although many in
ethnic communities were wary of the new radicalism
(some thought it a front for a new
form of nativism), which ran counter to the
fundamental conservatism of the immigrant
property owner, populism did indeed make
inroads. The rockbed republicanism of Swedes
and French Canadians in Kansas, for example,
fractured as they flocked to the Populist cause.
Even Kansas-German farmers abandoned
their loyalty to the Republican Party, although
they drew the line with "Yellin" Mary Lease on
the grounds that a woman's place was in the
home. Populists even found support among
ethnic communities in the cities of the Western
Plains.

Prohibition was another issue that shook
ethnic communities loose from their traditional
allegiances. Here the clash was between
cultures–North American puritanism versus
European immigrant culture. Most foreignborn
thought the idea of prohibition was ridiculous.
But the situation was complex, and a
division occurred largely along religious lines:
Methodists, Evangelicals, and Baptists were in
favor whereas Catholics, German Lutherans,
and Mennonites opposed prohibition. German
Catholics, Bohemian Catholics, German
Lutherans, and Volga Germans were opposed,
while German Methodists and Swedish and
Norwegian Lutherans supported prohibition.
When Kansas went dry in 1889 many Germans
defected to the Democratic Party. In Nebraska
they played a crucial role in defeating prohibition
in 1890. The general German opposition
to prohibition was sustained through the first
two decades of the twentieth century, even
when the United States o.cially adopted the
policy.

The other major cultural clash occurred
over women's right to vote. On this issue Germans
of all denominations were fairly well
united against suffrage. Their stance was
shared by Mennonites and many Scandinavians.
Increasingly, though, Germans stood
out among the ethnic communities as opponents
on the battle lines that marked the clash
between immigrant and American culture. In
part, this was because Germans unified to
make their voice effective in American politics.

In 1901 the German-American Alliance was
founded as a cultural and political organization
determined to preserve German culture,
especially the German language, and to create
a unified voice in the political arena for the
protection of those issues Germans held dear.
Branches were established in various Great
Plains states and were effective in preserving
the German parochial school system, both
Catholic and Lutheran, and in opposing prohibition
and women's suffrage. When World
War I broke out in Europe, they were passionate
in their support for the fatherland and opposed
war loans and the shipment of arms to
the French and British. They declared their
loyalty to the United States but also insisted on
American neutrality in Europe's war. All that
changed when the United States entered the
war in April 1917. World War I was to become
a major watershed not only for Germans but
also for other European ethnic groups in the
Great Plains.

In the United States both major parties attracted
immigrant support, but on the Canadian
Prairies the two major parties were
deeply divided on the question of immigration.
The Conservatives encouraged immigration
from Britain during the 1870s and 1880s
when the Prairies were being opened for settlement. When the Liberals took power in 1896,
a young lawyer from the Prairies, Clifford
Sifton, became minister in charge of immigration
and encouraged opening the doors to
peasant farmers from eastern and central Europe,
especially from the Ukraine. The level of
vitriol in public discourse between the Liberal
Winnipeg Free Press and the Conservative Winnipeg Telegram underscored policy differences
between the two major parties and within the
host society forming on the Prairies. These
divisions did not lessen after 1914, and the two
issues of prohibition and suffrage were intimately
interwoven in Canadian Prairie politics
during the war years.

Support for suffrage and attacks on alcoholism
and prostitution were part of a reform
program launched by Anglo-Canadian
women on the Prairies with the support
of farmer organizations in the years before
World War I. The large number of immigrants,
newly arrived in western Canada, were
not yet ready to join the movement, especially
when suffrage was introduced in 1916. Older
immigrant groups such as the Scandinavians
would be included but not the roughhewn
newcomers. Although young Ukrainian
women began to engage in public discussions
as early as 1912, they were encouraged to emulate
their Anglo-Canadian models but not to
expect the same rights. Furthermore, alcoholism
had been a major scourge in some Ukrainian
communities in Manitoba.and local
legend has it that the anti-Prohibition industry
that funneled supplies across the United
States border in the 1920s and 1930s originated
here. Clearly, in the Anglo-Canadian view, the
morals of these new immigrants would have
to be much improved before full British rights
could be extended to them, long after the war
had ended.



World War I Watershed

The outbreak of war in Europe in 1914 had an
immediate effect on Canadian immigrants,
particularly those of German origin. A strong
anti-German sentiment swept across the
country, including the Prairies, as German-language
schools were ordered to use English
and German-language newspapers were
closed. It was not just German-speaking Canadians
who felt the force of anti-German sentiment.
Those from any part of the Austro-
Hungarian Empire were suspect. Ukrainians,
in particular those with ambitions to establish
a Ukrainian republic and those who were socialists,
were rounded up and put in detention
camps. However, the rights of pacifist groups
such as the Mennonites, Amish, and Hutterites
to refuse military service were upheld.

South of the forty-ninth parallel a policy of
neutrality prevailed until April 1917, when
the United States entered the war. Meanwhile,
those of German ancestry, including the Mennonites,
were far from cowed. The threat of an
attack on the fatherland united Germans in
the United States as never before. They insisted
that the United States should remain
neutral and avoid foreign entanglements. The
German American press attacked the American
media and President Woodrow Wilson for
their apparent tilt toward Britain. German
American communities also raised funds for
the German Red Cross. In the election of 1916
Germans voted Republican, although Mennonites
voted Democratic in the belief that President
Wilson would keep the United States out
of the European war.

The Germans and German-speaking peoples
in the Plains were not alone in lining up
on the German side during the initial years
of the war. Scandinavians generally supported
the German cause, especially Swedes, although
Danes were bitterly divided on the issue. The
Irish in Butte, Montana, also supported the
German side, in large measure because of their
fierce anti-British sentiment.

When the United States entered the war,
loyalty to Germany was incompatible with
loyalty to the United States. A new American
organization, the National Security League
and its offshoot the American Defense League,
raised a voice that spread virulent superpatriotism
and intensified anti-German hysteria.
The superpatriots attacked the use of the German
language in schools as unpatriotic. The
use of German in churches also came under
attack. German was forbidden in the pulpit
in Montana and a Lutheran pastor in Texas
was whipped when he continued to preach
in German. Church congregations varied in
their response to these pressures, but of all
the churches the German Lutherans were most
resilient.

Pacifist groups such as the Mennonites were
doubly vulnerable, not only because of their
use of German in church and school but also
because of their pacifist principles. While
some Mennonite youths from liberal congregations
were willing to perform military service,
there were many who strenuously adhered
to traditional nonviolent principles.
Occasionally violence erupted. The refusal
of conscientious objectors to accept military
service resulted in their vilification, and
their patriotism was called into question. In
North Dakota the Hutterites, who resolutely
refused military service, were in an impossible
position, and many of their young men
were beaten and imprisoned for their pacifist
principles. Many moved north into the Canadian
Prairies. In Kansas some Mennonites
who balked at buying war bonds were threatened
by local mobs, and a few were tarred and
feathered.

Although the United States entered the war
later than Canada, the reaction to "enemy
aliens" in the Plains was more virulent than
on the Prairies. To be sure, the Canadian government
created a register of enemy aliens
that required surrender of firearms, monthly
reporting of their whereabouts, and suppression
of foreign-language journals. But Canada
admitted Hutterite refugees from the Dakotas
despite the opposition of Canadian veterans'
organizations, and Canadian Mennonites
fared better than their American cousins
during the war. As the war continued, however,
Canada also turned up the heat on
enemy aliens in 1917 and 1918. Most discriminatory
of all was the Canadian Wartime Elections
Act of 1917, which deprived naturalized
citizens of enemy origin of the right to vote. In
April 1918 all exemptions to military service
were canceled except those for Mennonites
and Doukhobors. Some zealous local boards
even tried to draft them. Heavy restrictions
were placed on all foreign-language presses in
September 1918, by which time German newspapers
in western Canada had ceased publication.
Pressure on German language and culture
continued to build on both sides of the
border as the war continued.

After the war ended, discriminatory attitudes
toward foreign languages continued,
and many ethnic communities accelerated
their adoption of English. Non-English languages,
including French, were suppressed in
Prairie public schools, and "Canadianization"
became the order of the day. English Canadian
nativism briefly reared its ugly head
on the Prairies and targeted French Canadians
because of the conscription crisis in
Quebec during the war. In the United States
foreign-language instruction declined precipitously
after the war and many parochial
schools adopted English. Although the
German-language press rebounded to an extent
after the war, the number of Germanlanguage
church periodicals and trade journals
dwindled during the 1920s to about onequarter
of their prewar numbers. German
churches in the United States (Catholic and
Lutheran) fell into the hands of leaders committed
to Americanization during the 1920s,
so that foreign-language use in church services
and on tombstones gradually declined.
During this decade the English-language press
and radio made significant inroads into ethnic
homes.

In politics, ethnic communities retained a
distinctive perspective. They could not forget
the discrimination they had experienced during
the war, and the politics of revenge was
practiced, for example, when the German
areas of Nebraska returned huge Republican
majorities after the war. In 1920 especially,
Germans were not so much pro-Harding
as anti-Wilson. But the deepest crisis faced
by German communities was one of regional
leadership. The Burgersbund replaced the old
German-American Alliance in the Midwest,
but the new leadership was weak. Consequently,
the Germans and Mennonites supported
presidential candidate Robert La Follette
and his League for Progressive Political
Action in 1924 and were ineffective in both
major parties. They continued to oppose prohibition
and women's suffrage.

Efforts to organize and unify the ethnic
voice in regional and national elections failed
in the 1930s as assimilation swamped ethnic
identities. The failure of leadership among
Germans permitted the success of Nazi sympathizers
within those communities in the
1930s when Germans in general were anti-
Roosevelt. The onset of World War II, however,
found ethnic communities solidly within
the national camp, and there was no repeat of
the internal conflicts and hostilities that had
marked entry into World War I. So much assimilation
had taken place during the 1920s
and 1930s, and so much suffering had been
endured during the Great Depression, that
ethnic communities blurred the boundaries
that separated their identities from that of the
mainstream host society.

With the possible exception of Ukrainian
communities on the Prairies, where distinctive
religious practices and language retention
remained strong, immigrant communities in
the Plains and Prairies saw a decline in ethnic
solidarity. The use of Swedish and other foreign
languages in Sunday church services, for
example, declined in the early 1930s, and support
for summer-school language instruction
withered during the Depression. Second- and
third-generation farmers of foreign origin
in the Plains and Prairies were faced with
acute problems of farm survival, during
which feelings of community solidarity were
strengthened, especially among sectarian ethnic
groups. But in those difficult years many
had come to think of themselves increasingly
as Americans or Canadians.



Europeans in Urban Centers in the Plains

The vast majority of European immigrants to
the Plains and Prairies lived in rural communities:
they had been drawn to North America
because of the opportunities in farming. Usually,
small service centers emerged in which
American-born merchants and professionals
provided services. But if the town served
a large, ethnically homogeneous community,
then European immigrants would set up a
general store, provide legal, banking, and
other services, publish newspapers, and become
community leaders. Thus, the ethnic
group developed institutional completeness
within these small towns. These good burghers
also "set a tone"–maintained standards
of behavior that became the norm for
their rural cousins. Examples of such towns
might include the Swedes in Lindsborg, Kansas;
Germans in Humboldt, Saskatchewan;
Mennonites in Steinbach, Manitoba; and the
Norwegians in Northwood, North Dakota.
European immigrants in the hundreds of
small service centers scattered across the
Plains played a key role in setting social standards
and in sustaining networks of contact
throughout rural communities.

A few immigrants were drawn to employment
opportunities in small mining communities
in the Plains. Deposits of coal and lead
were exploited in southeastern Kansas in the
1870s and Oklahoma in the 1880s. Italians, who
seldom went into farming, were attracted to
Krebs, Oklahoma, as early as 1875 and dominated
later mining communities in the state
such as McAlester and Coalgate. The Irish
overwhelmed the mining community of Butte,
Montana, to an extraordinary degree: they
owned the mines, supplied the labor, and controlled
the unions and local politics until the
turn of the century when Finns and Italians
began to compete with them in the labor market.
But in general the Irish were not drawn to
mining. Italians and Poles, on the other hand,
were enticed by mining companies from Oklahoma
to the Crowsnest district in Alberta, particularly
after 1896 when immigration from
eastern and southern Europe burgeoned.

The largest urban ethnic communities were
found in the major transportation centers that
served as gateways to the Plains—Kansas City,
Omaha, and Winnipeg. Each ethnic group developed
a niche in the labor market, working
in the warehouse district, in meatpacking
plants, or in small manufacturing enterprises
such as brewing or brickmaking. Newcomers
tended to cluster in the early years of settlement
in these growing cities, but large ethnic
ghettos rarely persisted as they did in eastern
cities. An exception was Winnipeg, where distinctive
Slavic and Jewish settlements emerged
in the "North End." The ethnic and class divisions
in Winnipeg were especially marked as
Germans and Scandinavians blended into the
Anglo-Canadian majority, who also formed
the city's elite. During the famous General
Strike of 1919, however, Jewish and other east
European immigrants joined forces to challenge
the power elite in a rare display of labor
solidarity, despite attempts to denigrate the
strike as anti-British and antidemocratic.



Conclusion

The strategies and concepts that scholars have
used to study the adaptation of European immigrants
to North American society have
changed over the decades. In midcentury,
scholars such as Oscar Handlin focused on the
social transformation of European peasants
and proletariat as they created new homes in
North America. In the last thirty years of
the twentieth century scholarly focus shifted
to the enduring cultures of these European
immigrants. New emphases will no doubt
emerge in the decades to come as the processes
of modernization are brought into the
discussion. One of the most interesting new
concepts to be introduced to ethnic studies is
that of the localization of culture. The concept
offers the possibility of fresh insights into how
Europeans transformed both themselves and
North Americans.

Localization of culture refers to the ability
of immigrants to embed their values deeply in
a locality, not only at the level of the family or
small group but also at the broader community
or county level. If an ethnic group is sufficiently
numerous it may take control of
the local institutions of governance, education,
and politics and infuse them with a distinctive
character, thereby creating a "charter
culture." The charter culture is reflected in the
modes of social control and conformity, the
public morality, the priorities in resource allocations,
and the patterns of checks and balances
in daily life that distinguish one locality
from another. Thus, a myriad of local cultures
is created, which in turn affects the development
and course of mainstream culture and
which ultimately may explain the evolution of
its regional variants.

One of the most distinctive and as yet unexplained
patterns within the Great Plains is the
regional variation in sociopolitical perspectives
that, for want of better terms, we may
label conservative and liberal. In Kansas and
Nebraska one thinks of the Bible Belt and the
political support of fiery radio broadcaster Father
Coughlin and Republican presidential
candidate Alf Landon in the 1930s. It contrasted
sharply with the so-called Red Belt of
the Dakotas and Minnesota, which found expression
in the political views of Henry Wallace
and, later, Eugene McCarthy and George
McGovern. On the Canadian side of the border
there was a Bible Belt in Alberta associated
with the Social Credit Party of Bill Aberhart
and Ernest Manning, which contrasted
sharply with the "social gospel" of Tommy
Douglas and the Cooperative Commonwealth
Federation in Saskatchewan. The links between
these political philosophies and various
branches of Christianity are easy to establish.
The links to ethnic communities, and particularly
to their deeply held values, are not
yet clearly established. But the concept of localization
of culture offers much potential for
exploring those links and for clarifying the
contribution that ethnic communities have
made to regional and mainstream culture and
politics.

Localization of culture is but one of several
perspectives used in studying the making of
new Americans and new Canadians in the
Great Plains. The adjustment of immigrants
to their environment, their assimilation or
ethnogenesis, and their influence on the political,
social, and cultural life of this broad
region all represent other perspectives. But
there can be no doubt that European immigrants
made a distinctive contribution to
Plains life, both in rural and urban communities.
The constant ebb and flow of population,
as farmers and urban workers and their
families left for new frontiers farther west, or
for other opportunities in nascent towns and
cities, resulted in the creation of a network of
family ties, ecclesiastical connections, and institutional
links that strengthened and deepened
the culture and identity of each community.
The evidence remains to this day, for
example, in western Kansas where, due to
rural population decline, German Russians
travel twenty or thirty miles to come together
and maintain churches and social institutions
and so sustain their culture. It may sometimes
seem as if European cultures are fading from
the bright patchwork of ethnic communities
of a century ago, but the reality may also be
that all along they have been forming mainstream
culture as their own.

See also IMAGES AND ICONS: Last Best West /
LAW: Meyer v. Nebraska / 
MEDIA: Immigrant Newspapers / 
POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT: Democratic Party; 
Liberal Party; Populists (People's Party); 
Republican Party / RELIGION: 
Doukhobors; Hutterites; Mennonites / 
TRANSPORTATION: Railroad Land Grants.




Aidan McQuillan
University of Toronto




Conzen, Kathleen N. "Mainstreams and Side Channels:
The Localization of American Cultures." Journal of American Ethnic History 11 (1991): 5–20. Conzen, Michael P.
"Ethnicity on the Land." In The Making of the American
Landscape, edited by Michael P. Conzen. London: Unwin
Hyman, 1990: 221–48. Dawson, Carl A. Group Settlement: Ethnic Communities in Western Canada. Toronto: Mac-
Millan Publishing Company, 1936. Emmons, David M.
The Butte Irish: Class and Ethnicity in an American Mining Town, 1875–1925. Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 1989.
Handlin, Oscar. The Uprooted: The Epic Story of the Great Migrations that Made the American People. New York:
Grosset and Dunlap, 1951. Hudson, John C. "Migration to
an American Frontier." Annals of the Association of American Geographers 66 (1976): 242–65. Lehr, John C., and
D. W. Moodie. "The Polemics of Pioneer Settlement:
Ukrainian Immigration and the Winnipeg Press." Canadian Ethnic Studies 12 (1980): 88–101. Loewen, Royden K.
Family, Church and Market: A Mennonite Community in the New and Old Worlds, 1850–1930. Urbana: University of
Illinois Press, 1993. Luebke, Frederick. Germans in the New World: Essays in the History of Immigration. Urbana: University
of Illinois Press, 1990. McQuillan, D. Aidan. Prevailing over Time: Ethnic Adjustment of the Kansas Prairies, 1875–1923. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1990.
Nugent, Walter T. K. The Tolerant Populists: Kansas Populism and Nativism. Chicago: University of Chicago Press,
1963. Schlichtmann, Hansgeorg. "Ethnic Themes in Geographical
Research on Western Canada." Canadian Ethnic Studies 9 (1977) 9–41. Shortridge, James R. "The Heart of
the Prairie: Culture Areas in the Central and Northern
Great Plains." Great Plains Quarterly 8 (1988): 206–21.
Turner, Frederick Jackson. "The Significance of the Frontier
in American History." Annual Report. American Historical
Association (1893): 199–227.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>