<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.wat.039</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Wetlands</field>
      <field name="author">Hoagland, Kyle D.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




WETLANDS

Although they account for only about 6.4 percent
of the earth's land surface, wetlands are
extremely important ecosystems. Wetlands are
ecotones, or transitional environments between
deeper water systems and terrestrial uplands.
They are characterized by the presence
of water at or near the surface, unique soil
conditions, and hydrophytes (plants suited to
wet conditions). Several formal definitions
have been written during the past twenty years
for regulatory purposes, including the oftencited
U.S. federal definition: "The term wetlands
means those areas that are inundated or
saturated by surface or ground water at a frequency
and duration su.cient to support, and
that under normal circumstances do support,
a prevalence of vegetation typically adapted for
life in saturated soil conditions." Thus, wetlands
include marshes, bogs, swamps, fens, wet
meadows, peatlands, playas, and a number of
other aquatic ecosystems that fall under a variety
of names.

Wetlands can be categorized into five main
types: marine, estuarine, lacustrine, riverine,
and palustrine. The latter three types occur in
abundance throughout the Great Plains. Indeed,
this region includes two of the most important
wetland areas in North America: the
expansive Prairie Potholes region of the Prairie
Provinces and north-central United States,
and the Nebraska Sandhills. Scientists further
group wetlands into subsystems and classes
based upon their seasonal hydrology (e.g., intermittent
or permanent standing water), bottom
substrate material (e.g., rock or soft sediment),
and the predominant plants (fifty-six
subcategories in all). Lacustrine wetlands are
typically associated with ponds and lakes,
forming the shallow areas along the margins,
while riverine wetlands occur along rivers or
streams and are often fed by floodwaters. Palustrine
wetlands include the remaining shallow
water systems that are typically identified
as wetlands, including marshes, swamps, and
bogs.

Wetlands are dynamic systems, exhibiting
major changes in vegetation during the growing
season, as surface and subsurface water
levels change, sometimes dramatically. Consequently,
they provide habitat for a large number
of plants and animals, some adapted
strictly to aquatic existence and others capable
of living in the water for short periods of time
during their life cycle. Many aquatic insects,
for example, require water for their preadult
stages, then emerge as winged adults: dragonflies,
damselflies, midges, and many other insects
are common members of the wetland
community. Aquatic plants, being less mobile,
must have adaptations that allow them to live
underwater or in saturated sediments, adaptations
such as air chambers in their leaves and
stems for gas exchange to roots anchored in
oxygen-depleted muds.

On a per acre basis, wetlands produce more
plant and animal biomass than any other ecosystem
on earth. The vast majority of this production
is hidden to the untrained eye: hydrophytes
in the wetland bottom in the form of
roots, rhizomes, and other storage structures,
and microscopic plants called algae, which are
attached to hydrophytes or bottom mud or
occur free-floating in the water. The propensity
of wetlands to produce plant and animal
biomass is a reflection of their ability to rapidly
take up and cycle basic nutrients such as
phosphorus and nitrogen. Consequently, wetlands
are also now recognized as ideal systems
for treating municipal waste, storm water
runoff, agricultural runoff, and animal waste.
Many wetlands are being constructed each
year for this purpose, and natural and restored
wetlands are also used. Thus, wetlands
have been termed biological filters or the
"kidneys" of the landscape. They serve a variety
of other important functions as well, including
flood control, sediment trapping, erosion
control, and groundwater recharge, in
addition to their recreational benefits for
camping, hunting, canoeing, fishing, and bird
watching.

Perhaps the most significant role of wetlands
is in maintaining biodiversity. It has
been estimated that one-half of the fish, onethird
of the birds, and one-sixth of the mammals
on the U.S. threatened and endangered
species list occur in wetlands. The Prairie Potholes
region, for example, is home to twelve of
the thirty-four species of breeding ducks in
North America. Nevertheless, wetlands continue
to be lost at an alarming rate. Conversions
of wetlands to croplands and urban development
have resulted in a cumulative loss
of 53 percent of all wetlands in the continental
United States. South Dakota and Nebraska
have lost approximately 35 percent of their
wetlands. Federal efforts to preserve and restore
many wetlands have increased in the past
ten years in the Great Plains, but the decline
continues.


Kyle D. Hoagland
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Mitsch, William J., and James G. Gosselink. Wetlands.
New York: Van Nostrand Reinhold Co., 1993. Niering,
William A. Wetlands. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1985.
van der Valk, Arnold G., ed. Northern Prairie Wetlands.
Ames: Iowa State University Press, 1989.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>