<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.067</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Rankin, Jeannette (1880-1973)</field>
      <field name="author">Grieves, Forest L.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




RANKIN, JEANNETTE (1880-1973)


Jeannette Rankin


Jeannette Rankin, the first woman elected to
the U.S. Congress (1916), was born on a ranch
near Missoula, Montana Territory, on June 11,
1880. She was the eldest of seven children of
Olive Pickering Rankin and John Rankin, who
was successful in the ranching and lumbering
business. Her early development and subsequent
career were no doubt influenced by the
relative remoteness of Montana, the freedom
and challenges of frontier life, and the harsh
environmental demands, all of which required
a strong and independent character.

Following graduation from the University
of Montana with a bachelor of science degree
in biology in 1902, she worked for a time as
a country schoolteacher and as a part-time
seamstress. In 1908 she left Montana to study
at the New York School of Philanthropy (now
the Columbia University School of Social
Work), and after a brief stint as a social worker
in Montana and Washington, she entered the
University of Washington in 1909. She became
active in the successful state campaign for
women's suffrage in 1910, which energized her
and helped define her subsequent career, focusing
on suffrage and then incorporating
pacifist issues.

The approval by Montana of female suffrage
in 1914 set the stage for her own campaign for
one of Montana's at-large seats in the U.S.
House of Representatives as a progressive Republican.
Her previous work for suffrage in
Montana gave her contacts, organizational
skills, public speaking ability, and a knowledge
of Montana voters that served her well. In her
campaign she traveled the vastness of the state
by train and automobile (which she drove herself) to speak to groups as disparate as mountain
miners, Plains farmers, and women's
groups. She spoke on street corners, in lumber
camps, union halls, and kitchens. Her brother,
Wellington, who became a highly successful
lawyer and prominent Republican in Montana,
managed her successful campaign.

Jeannette Rankin served two terms in Congress–separated by twenty years–where she
worked hard for reform legislation ranging
from women's issues to various problems of
specific concern to western states. She was defined
as a pacifist when her congressional
terms (1917-19 and 1941-43) coincided with
the outbreak of the two World Wars, and she
was the only member of Congress to vote
against U.S. entry into both of them. Whereas
she received considerable support for her
stance in 1917, she was accorded very little support
in the different atmosphere of 1941. Failing
to win reelection each time, she devoted
her efforts to active involvement in various
pacifist organizations and to world travels.

She returned briefly to public life in 1968, as
part of a women's coalition called the Jeannette
Rankin Brigade, to march on Washington
in protest of the Vietnam War. Even as she
passed the age of ninety, she continued to give
interviews and speeches opposing the Vietnam
War and supporting women's rights. In
1971 the National Organization of Women
named her as the first member of the Susan B.
Anthony Hall of Fame, acclaiming her contribution
to the cause of women's rights. But her
health was deteriorating, and she died in Carmel,
California, on May 18, 1973.

See also GENDER: Suffrage Movement.


Forest L. Grieves
University of Montana




Giles, Kevin S. Flight of the Dove: The Story of Jeannette
Rankin. Beaverton OR: Touchstone Press, 1980. Josephson,
Hannah. Jeannette Rankin: First Lady in Congress–A Biography.
Indianapolis: Bobbs-Merrill Company, Inc., 1974.
Richey, Elinor. Eminent Women of the West: Jeannette
Rankin, Woman of Commitment. Berkeley: Howell-North
Books, 1975.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>