<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.edu.032</field>
      <field name="titleMain">One-Room Schoolhouses</field>
      <field name="author">Wall, Milan</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ONE-ROOM SCHOOLHOUSES


Glenwood School near Hoople, North Dakota, 1899


One-room schoolhouses once were a common
feature in the Great Plains. One teacher, typically
a young, single woman, taught farm children
in grades one through eight in a small
building on the prairie. Often the teacher
had only an eighth-grade education herself.
Still, rural children got a basic education good
enough to produce a literacy rate that was
higher than that in many other parts of the
nation.

Support for rural public schools originated
with the federal Land Ordinance of 1785,
which began the land surveys that laid out
townships and sections across the growing nation.
Every township was to consist of thirtysix
sections containing 640 acres each. Section
16 and later, in 1848, section 36 were set aside
to support schools. By the early 1900s oneroom
schoolhouses dotted the countryside
throughout the Great Plains and the Midwest
to such an extent that the heartland contained
nearly half of the more than 200,000 oneroom
schools nationwide. These schools were
not only the center of learning for the community
but also the center of the community
as a whole. Community meetings, worship
services, weddings, family celebrations, and
funerals were held at the school, often the only
public building in the area.

The first schools were built of readily available
material. On the Plains, that may have
been sod or, in more wooded areas, logs.
Some schools were little more than dugouts.
Eventually, wood frame and even brick became
the common mode of construction. As
they were often poorly insulated, one-room
schools were hard to heat, and ine.cient
wood- or coal-burning stoves were common
fixtures. Teachers had to open the school, start
the fire, and handle all the custodial duties.
Restrooms were outhouses. Water came in by
pail from a neighboring farm until a well was
dug. Still, students learned the basics: reading,
writing, and spelling were the common subjects.
Math, history, geography, and handwriting
usually filled out the curriculum. Students
committed the lessons to memory, then recited
them from the front of the room. By the
end of the eighth grade students had heard the
same lessons many times over.

The decline of rural schools began with
President Theodore Roosevelt's appointment
of the National Commission on Country Life
in 1908. The commission set about to improve
the quality of life–and education–in rural
America. With the advent of better roads and
automated transportation, school consolidation
led to the first wave of elimination of oneroom
schools, often after a bitter debate that
pitted farmers against their cousins in town.

One-room schools struggled through the
Great Depression. In the aftermath of World
War II many one-room schools were eliminated
as mobility became more common,
mechanization increased farm size and reduced
farm numbers, and the migration of
population from rural to urban areas accelerated.
In the state of Kansas, for example, half of
the state's one-room schools were closed between
1945 and 1950.

The rapid elimination of country schools
continued over the next decade. By 1958 some
Great Plains states had all but eliminated them
entirely, while other states still operated hundreds
but not thousands as they once had. By
the mid-1980s fewer than 1,000 one-room
schools could be found throughout the nation,
and more than half of these were located
in three Great Plains states: Montana, Nebraska,
and South Dakota.

Today, many of the few existing one-room
schools are threatened with extinction. Those
that remain, however, have moved past the
basics to include computer literacy as well as
the three R's.


Milan Wall
Heartland Center for Leadership Development




Fuller, Wayne E. One-Room Schools of the Middle West.
Lawrence: University Press of Kansas, 1994. Gulliford, Andrew.
America's Country Schools. Washington DC: Preservation
Press, 1984. U.S. Department of Education. Rural
Education: A Changing Landscape. Washington DC: Government
Printing Office, 1989.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>