<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.art.033</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Houser, Allan (1914-1994)</field>
      <field name="author">Szabo, Joyce M.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




HOUSER, ALLAN (1914-1994)

One of the most influential Native American
artists of the twentieth century, Houser was of
Chiricahua heritage; his grandfather was warchief
Mangus Coloradas, and his granduncle
was Geronimo. Houser was born in Apache,
Oklahoma, on June 30, 1914, and grew up near
Fort Sill. His early life was filled with stories
of Chiricahua resistance. In the 1930s he attended
the Indian School in Santa Fe, working
with Dorothy Dunn in the Studio. The
flat, two-dimensional painting style developed
there was too restrictive for Houser, although
he executed various Studio-style murals, including
some in the Department of the Interior
Building in Washington dc. He studied
muralism with Olaf Nordmark, who suggested
that he turn to sculpture. Beginning in wood,
Houser quickly explored other materials, including
bronze, marble, and steel. He taught at
the Inter-Mountain Boarding School in Utah
between 1951 and 1961 and in Santa Fe at the
new Institute of American Indian Arts from
1962 to 1975. The institute was founded on
principles that Houser held to be deeply important:
that Native American artists should
be encouraged to explore their cultural heritage
as well as to create art in keeping with
their own individual goals and self-expression.
At sixty-one, he officially stopped teaching to
devote his energies to his own art, but he never
stopped helping students.

Numerous awards filled his life, including
a Guggenheim Fellowship (1948) and the
French Palmes d'Académiques (1954) for his
exemplary work as both artist and teacher. He
was inducted into the Oklahoma Hall of Fame
and, in 1992, was the first Native American to
receive the National Medal of Arts. His unceasing
experimentation and creativity were
expressed in subject matter that ranged from
representations of Native figures of the past to
contemporary abstractions without recognizable
imagery. Houser died on August 22, 1994,
in Santa Fe.



Joyce M. Szabo
University of New Mexico




Allan Houser (Ha-o-zous): A Life in Art. Exhibition Catalog.
Santa Fe: Museum of New Mexico, 1991. Perlman,
Barbara H. Allan Houser (Ha-o-zous). Boston: David R.
Godine, 1987. The Studio of Allan Houser. Exhibition Catalog.
Santa Fe: Wheelwright Museum of the American
Indian, 1996.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>