<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ea.014</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Giants in the Earth</field>
      <field name="author">Sjåvik, Jan Ivar</field>
      <field name="text">

 




GIANTS IN THE EARTH

Written by a Norwegian-born professor of
Norwegian at St. Olaf College in Minnesota,
Ole Edvart Rolvaag's novel Giants in the Earth
(1927) tells of the hardships and triumphs of a
group of Norwegian immigrants to the southeastern
Dakota Territory in the 1870s. These
men and women, who had formerly been fishermen
in northern Norway, have to adjust to
the vast expanse of the sea of grass in which
they find themselves as well as to isolation,
loneliness, a harsh climate, and a host culture
that regards their national characteristics as a
nuisance at best and threatening at worst.

The characters respond to their new circumstances
in various ways. Per Hansa, the
male protagonist, exemplifies both the daring
of a skilled fisherman and the thirst for material
advancement of a would-be Yankee. Severely
criticized by the author, Per Hansa finally
loses his life, in large measure as a result
of his hubris. His friend Hans Olsa, in contrast,
has neither Per Hansa's intelligence nor
his daring, but he steadfastly works his land
until struck down by illness. The women characters
in the book are neither as daring nor as
well suited to Plains life as the menfolk. Per
Hansa's wife, Beret, the novel's most memorable
character, suffers from a severe depression,
which Rolvaag suggests has multiple causes:
some of her choices while in Norway, her husband's
decision to move the family to America,
and the loneliness of the Plains. Although
the Norwegian immigrants of Giants in the
Earth are ultimately successful in their quest
for a new and materially better life, the emotional
and spiritual price of their success is
very high indeed.

See also LITERARY TRADITIONS: Rölvaag, O. E.


Jan Ivar Sjåvik
University of Washington




Haugen, Einar. Ole Edvart Rolvaag. Boston: Twayne Publishers,
1983. Paulson, Kristoffer F. "Ole Rolvaag's Giants
in the Earth: The Structure, the Myth, the Tragedy."
Norwegian-American Studies 34 (1995): 201-15. Simonson,
Harold P. Prairies Within: The Tragic Trilogy of Ole
Rolvaag. Seattle: University of Washington Press, 1987.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>