<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.arc.031</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Landscape Architecture</field>
      <field name="author">Sutton, Richard K.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




LANDSCAPE ARCHITECTURE

Landscape architecture is the art and science
of planning, design, and management of both
human-made and natural outdoor environments.
It has strong ties to horticulture, recreation,
architecture, civil engineering, urban
planning, natural resources, social sciences,
humanities, and the arts. Licensure in the profession
is required in all Great Plains states
and provinces except Colorado, North Dakota,
Saskatchewan, and Alberta. Landscape
architecture focuses on the development of
landscapes, though significant emphasis in the
profession also occurs in the preservation and
management of recreational and historical resources.
These factors tend to associate landscape
architecture in the Great Plains with
larger cities and with notable national, state,
provincial, and local parks.

Landscape architecture developed in three
overlapping phases in the Great Plains. The
first period, from about 1860 to 1920, coincided
with initial European American settlement
and involved landscape architects from
outside the region. During the second phase,
from about 1920 to 1970, Plains landscape architects
were often associated with multidisciplinary architecture and engineering
firms. More recently, a third phase has been
characterized by work done by landscape architects
trained in programs in the Great
Plains.

Early projects in the Great Plains were designed
by consultants from eastern cities. In
the late nineteenth century, for example,
the extensive parks and boulevard system in
Omaha was planned by H. W. S. Cleveland
from his Chicago office. During this early period,
landscape architects were also often involved
with the beautification of parks developed
by railroad companies, planning graveyards
in the "rural cemetery" style, and designing
gardens for wealthy patrons. Later, during
the Great Depression, the Work Projects Administration
hired landscape architects to plan
state and municipal parks in the Great Plains.
Mount Rushmore National Memorial and
Wind Cave National Park in South Dakota, for
example, are enhanced with good site design
by landscape architects. The International
Peace Garden, straddling the forty-ninth parallel
between Canada and the United States, is
a particularly special achievement, featuring
gardens of hardy plants in a severe climate. It
was designed by Henry Moore.

Landscape architects have been integral in
improving waterfront areas in Plains cities.
Combining resource conservation and public
recreation goals, landscape architects designed
the Red River Corridor and Winnipeg
River Walk in Manitoba, the Westcan Center
in Regina, Saskatoon, river walks in Calgary
and Edmonton, Alberta, the River Front in
Wichita, Kansas, and the South Platte River
Restoration in Denver, Colorado.

The work of Ernst Herminghaus, who designed
the Nebraska State Capitol grounds
and Pioneers Park in Lincoln, Nebraska, Gerald
Kessler, engineer and landscape architect
with the Kansas City, Missouri, Parks Commission
who planned that city's parks and
boulevard system, and the firm of Hare and
Hare, which coordinated with architect J. C.
Nichols to create the plaza in Kansas City,
Missouri, all deserve special mention. Hare
and Hare was the first significant Great Plains
landscape architecture firm, and its projects
can be found throughout the region, including
plans for Kansas City parks, the University
of Nebraska campus, the Villa Philbrook in
Tulsa, and the Civic Center, capitol sites, and
park system in Oklahoma City.

The first Great Plains university program in
landscape architecture was founded in 1924 at
what is now Kansas State University in Manhattan.
This remained the only Plains program
until the University of Manitoba in
Winnipeg initiated one in 1969. Subsequently,
Texas Tech in Lubbock (1970), the University
of Colorado–Denver (1981), Colorado State
University in Fort Collins (1982), Oklahoma
State University in Stillwater (1983), North
Dakota State University in Fargo (1991), and
the University of Oklahoma in Norman (1995)
have developed accredited programs. Landscape
architecture in the Great Plains is now
homegrown.

See also IMAGES AND ICONS: 
International Peace Garden.


Richard K. Sutton
University of Nebraska-Lincoln





Lee, Janice, David Boutros, Charlotte R. White, and Dean
Wolfenbarger, eds. A Legacy of Design: An Historical Survey of the Kansas City, Missouri Parks and Boulevard System, 1893–1940. Kansas City MO: Kansas City Center for
Design Research, 1995. Tishler, William, ed. Midwestern Landscape Architecture. Urbana: University of Illinois
Press, 2000.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>