<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.med.001</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Media</field>
      <field name="author">Huntzicker, William E.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MEDIA

To receive a television signal at our southeastern
Montana ranch in the early 1960s our family had
to work as a team. My father climbed the old
wind-charger tower on which our antenna was
mounted. I stayed inside to adjust the set, while
my younger sister and brother stood outside the
window to relay messages to Dad on the tower
behind the house. "Hold it," I'd yell. "There. No.
Back just a little the other way. No. Back again
sloooowly." I'd shout my instructions out the
window to my sister, who shouted to my brother
at the corner of the house, and he'd shout up to
Dad. The tower was barely within shouting distance
on a windy day. With the antenna pointed
northeast, we could get stations from Dickinson
and Williston in North Dakota. A slight turn
west of north picked up the signal from Glendive,
Montana. The reward for this effort could
be a Saturday evening watching Richard Boone
as Paladin in Have Gun Will Travel, followed by
James Arness as Marshal Matt Dillon in Gunsmoke.
These network programs were exceptional
because local stations had to earn their
network programs one at a time in those days.
Most of the programs were nonnetwork fare
such as old movies and professional wrestling,
which Dad enjoyed far more than anyone else
in the family. Reception depended upon the
weather.

To get a newspaper, we could drive five miles
to Ismay to pick up the mail, which carried the
previous day's edition of the Miles City Star,
published sixty-five miles away. Otherwise,
we could wait for mail delivery on Tuesdays,
Thursdays, and Saturdays. When we'd pick up
the mail at the Ismay Post Office, Postmaster
Esther Heigh could give an abstract of the day's
news as she handed the paper through the oldfashioned
counter window. Besides the Star,
our subscriptions included the weekly Life
magazine and several farm magazines. The
weekly Fallon County Times was published in
Baker thirty miles away.

We could see a movie at a drive-in twenty
miles away. Radio and phonographs provided
music. In the time we lived there, KFLN began
broadcasting from Baker, carrying agricultural
market reports and country music, as did
KATAL (the "Cattle Call") from Miles City, but a
hill west of our house made reception difficult.
Occasionally, we received stations like KFAB in
Omaha, who in Des Moines, and CKCK in Regina,
but none came in well enough for us to
become devoted listeners. At night, however,
we received several clear-channel stations. As
teenagers we listened to rock station KOMA in
Oklahoma City. Advertisements on that station
promoted events from Oklahoma to Kansas.
In the late 1990s KOMA played the same
music, but the format then was called "golden
oldies." I grew up believing that scratchy radio
reception, snowy television, and late newspapers
were a way of life in the country.


Early Mass Communication

Linking isolated towns and ranches in the
Great Plains with the larger society has always
been a challenge. Early settlers, longing for
news from major population centers they had
left behind, gathered at stage and railroad stations
likely to carry mail and newspapers. Taverns
and cafes increased their appeal by subscribing
to major newspapers. When local
newspapers were established, editors often
supported their publications with commercial
printing. Editors lifted much of their news
from the "exchanges," distant newspapers that
editors traded so they could borrow news
from one another. Editors sought to attract
new settlers and subscribers. Because they had
a stake in the town's success, editors often
boosted the virtues of their towns. Sometimes
town developers even gave them lots to sell as
an additional incentive.

The earliest mass media in the Great Plains,
of course, relied on simple technology. The
Washington handpress, for example, printed
hundreds of small-town newspapers across
the Plains throughout the nineteenth century.
This press differed little from the press Benjamin
Franklin operated in colonial America,
and it allowed one printer to produce the
newspaper alone or with a single assistant, apprentice,
or slave. A variation patented by
Samuel Rust in 1821 moved west in wagons
because innovations, like hollow legs, made it
lighter to move than its cast-iron competitors.
The Ramage press with some wooden components
was introduced to compete with Rust.
Besides the heavy iron press, printers needed
paper, ink, and cases filled with type.

When William N. Byers left Omaha for the
mining country with his Washington handpress
and related equipment in 1859, the press
was so heavy and the streets of Omaha so
muddy that the wagon carrying the press got
bogged down before it got out of town. The
train of wagons sported banners promising a
new newspaper without naming a location,
but the group set out for Fort Laramie. The
wagons covered a mere eight miles on their
first day. Byers had already set the forms for
half of his first run of the Rocky Mountain News, even though he did not know where the
newspaper would be published. Spacers were
inserted to hold room for the place and date
of the first pressrun. When the entourage
stopped, the forms were opened and new type
was inserted to give the date and place of publication.
The outside two pages of the first issue
of the Rocky Mountain News of April 22,
1859, contained some news that was more than
a year old and other items that were not news
at all. Throughout the nineteenth century,
newspapers carried nonnews items such as
fiction, poetry, essays, and morality tales.

Byers started the News in Auraria across
Cherry Creek from Denver City, Colorado,
and it began by appealing to residents of both
towns. Timely news was hard to get because
the nearest post office was more than 100
miles away at Fort Laramie. Without mail or
telegraph service, residents settled for older
news. At least it was newer than word of
mouth around town. Even after newspapers
became established, they often printed the old
news on the outside–the front and back pages
–of a four-page newspaper. These outside
pages could be printed a day or two early and
the inside pages printed later with recent news
and editorial comment.

In promoting their idea of "progress," editors
often attacked the original inhabitants of
the land as "savages" who did not deserve to
own the land. Some western editors, with the
help of eastern "exchanges," exaggerated Indian
atrocities and even faked at least one
massacre. In 1867 the normally respectable
New York Tribune, published by Horace Greeley,
reported on a massacre of eighty people at
the mouth of the Yellowstone River near Fort
Buford. The story even gave details of a small
number of soldiers holding off thousands of
Indians before being overwhelmed. The newspaper
said a colonel shot his wife to save her
from a fate worse than death. When the Tribune
discovered that the story was a fake, it
admitted that it had been duped. Other major
newspapers, however, let the error stand.
Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper once published
a faked story under a picture of "General"
George Armstrong Custer talking to the
surviving members of a homestead family attacked
by Indians. At the end of the story, the
newspaper said the event never happened but
contended that stories like this often did happen
in the West. Especially after each discovery
of gold, newspapers in both the East and
West said Native Americans stood in the way
of national prosperity.



Native American Media

Native American publications in the Great
Plains shared many challenges of small-town
publications. They faced shortages of supplies
and money, carried small subscription lists,
confronted dilemmas related to political sponsorship,
and found national advertising illusive.
Native papers and many Native-owned
broadcast stations continue to receive support
from their tribal councils, and, as a result, they
often face complex political pressures, including
the pressure to satisfy patrons while covering
the news.

Their traditional dilemmas began with the
earliest Native American newspaper, the Cherokee Phoenix, published in both English and
Cherokee in the late 1820s in the original
Cherokee capital at New Echota, Georgia. Editor
Elias Boudinot stood up to the power of
both the tribal council and their white, racist
neighbors. Boudinot waged a courageous
fight against white abuse of Cherokees and reported
on dissension within the tribal council
over Cherokee removal from Georgia to Indian
Territory. The editor got caught in tribal
factionalism, however, and was killed in Indian
Territory in 1839 for signing the treaty
that ceded the Cherokees' original land.

The Reverend Samuel Worcester and printer
John F. Wheeler, both of whom served Georgia
prison time for their work on the Phoenix,
helped the Cherokees start the Cherokee Advocate
in 1844 in the new Cherokee capital of
Tahlequah in Indian Territory, with William P.
Ross, the chief 's nephew, as editor. The Advocate
continued the Phoenix's policies of free
distribution and publication in both Cherokee
and English. The newspaper's objectives were to
spread important news among the Cherokee
people, to advance their general interests,
and to defend Indian rights. Clearly, the
goals reflected a partisan commitment to the
cause of Native peoples, but the newspaper
also reflected factionalism among the Cherokees
and continued, with missionary sponsorship,
to advocate assimilation and defend
human rights within that context. Although
Cherokee law prevented editors from printing
personal and partisan items, political debate
occasionally became intensely personal and
sometimes violent. After the Civil War, the
Cherokee Advocate was published under the
same format until it ceased publication in
1906. The federal government ordered the
Cherokee type preserved in the Smithsonian
Institution and the rest of the equipment sold
in 1911.

The second Native American newspaper,
the Shawnee Sun (Siwinowe Kesibi), began
in 1835 under the editorship of Johnston
Lykins and with the assistance of the Reverend
Jotham Meeker, a missionary who took a
printing press with him to his duties at the
large Baptist mission at Shawnee Mission,
Kansas. The press at Shawnee Mission published
part of the newspaper in the Shawnee
language using the English alphabet. Meeker
translated religious messages and songs and
published Indian material in the Native language.
His press was the first in the area that
is now Kansas. The newspaper was published
monthly or semimonthly until its suspension
in 1839. It resumed publication in 1841 and
apparently lasted until 1844.

By the end of the twentieth century, one of
the three national Native American newspapers
was published in the Great Plains. The
editorial headquarters for Indian Country Today,
formerly the Lakota Times, are located in
Rapid City, South Dakota. Other examples of
Native voices from the Great Plains included
the 2000-watt tribally owned kili, voice of the
Lakota Nation, in Porcupine Butte, South Dakota,
and its sister station, kini, in Rosebud.



Newspaper War in the West

When white settlers arrived in Kansas, they
immediately engaged in a war of words. The
first English-only newspaper in Kansas was the
Kansas Weekly Herald, published in Leavenworth
from 1854 to 1861. The Kansas-Nebraska
Act had created such a rush by competing
groups to settle Kansas that the first issue of
the proslavery Herald was published under a
tree, even before the rest of the town appeared.
Three free-state papers began in Lawrence in
January 1855: the Kansas Herald of Freedom,
the Kansas Free State, and the Kansas Tribune.
More than 100 newspapers were published
during Kansas's territorial period between
1854 and 1861. Like many newspapers, the Tribune
had trouble getting started on a regular
footing. Two-dollar annual subscriptions were
payable in advance, and early issues appeared
sporadically.

After passage of the Kansas-Nebraska Act of
1854 let voters decide whether new states
would be slave or free, war broke out over
which faction would rule Kansas. Every faction
had its newspaper. Local editors risked
their lives in this fight. Missouri bushwhackers
attacked newspaper offices, destroying presses
so they could not be repaired and scattering
type into the street. When slave-state raiders
from Missouri attacked Lawrence in 1856, they
systematically destroyed two newspaper offices
and wrecked the presses. Contemporary
observers said only someone who understood
printing could have done such an effective job
of destroying the presses.



Newspaper Rivalries

Elsewhere in the Great Plains, newspaper rivalries
were also intense. Like the Lawrence
contest over who would be first, two Denver
newspapers raced for the same honor in that
city. William N. Byers and the Rocky Mountain News faced stiff competition in the drive
to control the Denver market. In April 1859
John L. Merrick, who had published the St.
Joseph Gazette in Missouri (probably printed
on a press fished out of the Missouri River
at Independence after anti-Mormon rioters
had sunk it there), moved his newspaper
equipment to Denver City to begin the Cherry Creek Pioneer. Once the editors became aware
of each other, they raced to be first. Byers
won by twenty minutes, and Merrick's Pioneer
folded after the first issue. His primitive press
was capable of printing only seven-by-teninch
sheets one side at a time, putting him at a
severe disadvantage. The victorious News enjoyed
no luxuries. It was published in an attic
room above a saloon whose ceiling had to be
reinforced to prevent bullets fired into the
air from hitting printers at work. Above the
press, a leaky roof allowed rain to drip on the
equipment.

Like that of its short-term competitor, the
Rocky Mountain News's press could also boast
a colorful history. Byers's press may have
printed Nebraska Territory's first newspaper.
The Nebraska Palladium and Platte Valley Advocate
had appeared on November 15, 1854, in
Bellevue and reached a peak of 500 subscribers
before its death the following April. The
press later issued the Bellevue Gazette on October
23, 1856, and ran for about two years,
ending when Byers bought it. From the upstairs
office in Auraria, Byers moved his office
into a new building along Cherry Creek. The
press reached a dramatic end when a fastmoving
Cherry Creek swept away the Rocky Mountain News building, its press, and all its
equipment in the flood of May 19, 1864.

Many western newspapers had short lives.
One of Byers's most persistent early competitors,
Thomas Gibson, tried several times to
start newspapers. He started the Rocky Mountain Gold Reporter and Mountain City Herald
on August 6, 1859, in Mountain City, Colorado,
but soon gave up and returned to Omaha.
Later he managed the Western Mountaineer,
owned by the founders of Golden, Colorado.
The Western Mountaineer began publication
on December 4, 1859, and folded in early 1860.
Gibson returned to Denver to compete with
Byers and started Colorado's first daily newspaper,
the Daily Herald and Rocky Mountain Advertiser, on May 1, 1860. Gibson started a
weekly edition, the Rocky Mountain Herald, on
May 5, 1860.

The Denver Evening Post appeared for the
first time in August 1892, but its editors misjudged
their audience. They supported the
gold standard at a time when their readers
supported William Jennings Bryan and free
silver, and the paper died after its first year.
Determined not to make the same mistake,
two new owners, Frederick G. Bonfils and
Harry Heye Tammen, revived the Evening Post
as a daily in 1894. They reached new heights in
sensationalism and antiauthoritarianism. The
Post's publishers called their red-painted office
the "red room," but local residents took to
calling it the "bucket of blood." Like William
Randolph Hearst in New York, Tammen and
Bonfils exploited sensationalism and identified
with the common folks by attacking politicians.
In one early issue, the Post editors attacked
child labor in department stores: "As
you enter one of them, a little, pale-faced girl
opens the door, standing in the dangerous
drafts, for people are coming and going. This
method of employing child labor at starvation
wages which are all the way from $1 to $1.50 a
week, for which they work from sixty-five to
seventy hours a week, may be fashionable in
Baxter Street, New York, but we desire to serve
notice on these establishments that it will not
go in the great West." A story on the Denver
water company said city residents were drinking
sewage, among other things: "The site of
an old slaughterhouse in Mount Vernon gulch
was visited. Water was running through it
washing the old bones and eventually finding
its way into the city water mains." Editors assumed
that journalism was political, and their
readers believed in the innocent West, in contrast
to a corrupt East, as the reference to New
York indicates.

Like other western newspapers both big and
small, the Post saw itself as an engine of progress.
From its first day, the Post promised to
"devote special and ceaseless attention to the
material interests of the state and to the development
of her vast and varied resources." It
campaigned to "direct its efforts that more
acres of land shall be brought under cultivation"
and to promote trade, mining, and industrial
development. In 2001 the Denver Post
and the Rocky Mountain News entered into a
joint operating agreement. The two papers remain
competitors in one of the few U.S. metropolitan
areas to have competing major
newspapers.



Media Standardization Moves West

Despite their local flavor, small-town western
newspapers often reflected evidence of mass
production. Beginning in the 1870s, syndication
services supplied "patent pages" or "ready
prints"–pages already printed on one side–to
local printers, who then printed on the backs
of the pages. Local newspapers could order
preprinted pages and simply use the other side
of the sheet (two of the newspaper's four
pages) for local news and advertising. Some of
the national syndicates also supplied boilerplate,
preset pages of lead type ready to be
printed. All these services saved time and
money for printers who still set type one letter
at a time while standing at a type case. In the
1880s the Linotype machine allowed a typesetter
to sit at a keyboard and call up letters as
brass forms into which lead was poured one
line at a time, making local news easier to print.
However, the boilerplate and ready-print services
supplied enough material to fill entire
pages or parts of pages, leaving little space to be
filled locally.

The preset syndication services helped some
publishers create "satellite papers" in which
several towns could have virtually the same
newspaper with some minor changes in the
local news columns. Newspapers could then be
printed in nearby towns with the printer inserting
a minimum of local news. Local governments
helped by requiring legal notices,
such as claims for cattle brands and homesteads,
to be published for several consecutive
weeks. With these notices already set for several
weeks, the printer did not have to revise
entire columns from week to week.



Editors and Their Agendas

Newspapers across the Plains worked to overcome
the label of the Great American Desert
applied by early explorers. Town boosters reported
fantasies as well as facts, hoping their
eastern colleagues would reprint articles extolling
the virtues of frontier life. Editors
in homesteader towns dreamed in print of
the day when miraculous farming techniques
would transform gumbo flats into blooming
gardens. Even winter looked good in booster
columns, improving the health and hardiness
of residents. Similarly, boomtown newspapers
predicted a peaceful future for their towns,
while drunken cowboys loped their horses
through the streets, yelling and shooting their
guns into the air. In Denver, for example,
Byers's Rocky Mountain News encouraged
farming as a source of long-term stability, even
while miners celebrated short-term successes.
Newspapers in small homestead towns promoted
dryland farming on the theory that
once the land was plowed the increased moisture
in the air would stimulate rain, hence the
slogan, "rainfall follows the plow."

On the other hand, some editors in towns
dependent upon cattle and mining turned
their backs on reformers. Saloons, gambling,
prostitution, and tolerance of violence often
helped local business for the short term. Editors
often became a saloon's best customers.
The editor wanted to put a good face on town
news, but the saloon, so often a source of conflict,
attracted business. Saloons were dependable
advertisers; in fact, critics said frontier
newspapers contained too many liquor advertisements.
Temperance advocates frequently
wrote letters and, occasionally, became editors,
but they left little evidence that miners
showed any interest in receiving temperance
lectures through the press.

Reports of minor crimes revealed the usual
mix of editorial comment and news. Some
newspapers threatened to help enforce the law
by printing the names of people who persisted
in wild riding through the streets. Editors
often balanced calls for law and order with
comments about the increasing number of
families making their homes within the town.
Frontier editors faced a basic dilemma in deciding
whether to report the seamy side of
town life or to put forth a wholesome image to
attract families. Many editors advocated community
reform without calling attention to
town problems. Editorial campaigns for law
and order frequently supported anonymous
vigilance committees, ironically operating
outside the law to rid the community of undesirables.

Editors in railhead towns at the end of the
Texas to Kansas cattle drives in the 1870s
boosted their towns in the competition to attract
cattle drives. They ignored the indiscretions
of visiting trail hands, who deposited
their wages at saloons. Town delegations occasionally
met the drives on the trail to persuade
drovers to come to their towns. The towns
also fought over railroads; railroads held out
for concessions that could include free land
for rights of way, depots, stockyards, and cash
payments. Editors participated in this process,
defending the promotional expenses to local
readers and extolling the town's virtues to
readers beyond the local trade area. Cow town
editors depended upon the cattle trade because
their towns did, and editors received reliable
revenue from legal notices necessary for
ranchers to establish their ownership of livestock
brands. Editors who at first sided with
cattle drovers on such issues as street violence
and herd laws to protect fenced farms came to
see the future differently as railheads moved
west and waves of immigrants settled in the
country.

Early historians and dime novelists created
stereotypes of frontier editors, especially itinerant
ones. Two such editors, Legh Freeman
and Frederic E. Lockley, have received scholarly
attention. Lockley, who had been a journalist
in Cleveland and New York City, moved
west to cover Indian Territory, Salt Lake City,
and several Kansas towns. During one of his
two stints as a newspaper owner, Lockley
owned the Arkansas City Traveler in the Kansas
border town founded during the Oklahoma
land rush. "I felt myself in a humble way to be a
public teacher; a sound and moral newspaper
press I thought had much to do with our national
life," he wrote at the turn of the century.
But he found that his hours reading exchanges,
condensing news, and writing editorials were
wasted on people who wanted "little local
squibs telling who comes and goes and booming
the town on all occasions."

While involved in land-speculation and
town-promotion schemes, Legh Freeman
tried to live the stereotypical life of a frontier
scout. His Frontier Index, called the "press on
wheels" because of his frequent moves, traveled
from town to town ahead of the Union
Pacific Railroad in Nebraska, Colorado, Wyoming,
Montana, and Utah. Like the mythic
mountain man Jim Bridger, whom Freeman
may have interviewed early in life, the editor
tried to stay ahead of advancing civilization.
Toward the end of Freeman's life, his wife and
family ran the paper while he traveled and sent
home columns.

Humorist Edgar Wilson "Bill" Nye followed
Mark Twain in writing widely reprinted
newspaper columns and popular books and in
touring the lecture circuit. Nye, who edited
the Laramie Boomerang in Wyoming, proposed
a school to train frontier journalists,
with the training including self-defense, first
aid, theology, medicine, and politics (just to
keep up on frontier issues). By the age of
ninety-five, Nye concluded, "The student will
have lost that wild, reckless and impulsive
style so common among younger and less experienced
journalists." At that point the most
pressing question would be whether to invest
in government bonds or real estate in a growing
town. Like many small-town editors, Nye
also worked as postmaster. William Allen
White, editor of the Emporia Gazette in Kansas,
gained national attention in the early
twentieth century for his politics and his articulate
advocacy of the West.

Great Plains newspapers provided other celebrities
as well as national leaders. Canada's
fifth prime minister, Mackenzie Bowell, was
once a compositor on the Calgary Herald. Sir
Clifford Sifton, owner of the Manitoba Free Press, and his editor, John Wesley Dafoe, became
national figures from 1901 through the
late 1920s, while Sifton played a major role as a
national party and provincial leader in defining
Canada's independence from Great Britain.
Dafoe's sixty-year journalism career made
the Free Press a major liberal and progressive
voice in the West. George Creel, who headed
the U.S. propaganda effort during World War
I, had been a Post reporter and police commissioner
in Denver. Willa Cather worked as a
theater and music critic for two newspapers in
Lincoln before moving to Pittsburgh and New
York City journalism. L. Frank Baum wrote
and edited an Aberdeen, South Dakota, newspaper
before he wrote The Wizard of Oz.



Plains Radio

Like newspapers, radio linked the Plains with
the rest of the world. As early as 1917, Plains
residents as far away as Texas occasionally heard
the daily University of Wisconsin weather and
agricultural bulletins broadcast in Morse code
for Wisconsin farmers. Texans got their own
weather and crop reports from the University of
Texas at Austin, where physics professor S. Leroy
Brown built a radio station before World War I.
During the war, however, the federal government
imposed an embargo on radio development
except for military purposes.

Unlicensed pirates continued to broadcast
through the war and after. In 1920 Ashley
Clayton Dixon began broadcasting music by a
pickup orchestra among neighbors from his
new home near Three Mile Trading Post north
of Stevensville, Montana. Dixon and other amateurs
around the nation created an interest in
radio that was exploited by Westinghouse employees,
who began the first commercial radio
station, KDKA in Pittsburgh, in 1920. (The
world's oldest commercial radio station, CFCF
in Montreal, had already gone on the air as
experimental station XWA.) Westinghouse immediately
saw the value of broadcasting to sell
wireless receiving sets while major corporations
fought over patent rights.

University of Nebraska faculty, who had experimented
with voice transmission in 1921,
began offering courses by radio at $12.50 per
student. The cost included textbook, exams,
and two credits for those who passed. By the
spring of 1922 at least nineteen other U.S. academic
institutions had radio stations. The
University of Texas at Austin had two stations,
but they had merged by 1922 into the 500-watt
KUT station, which broadcast from 8 to 10 P.M.
three nights a week. One of the best-equipped
stations in the nation at the time, KUT carried
agricultural and marketing reports, music,
and lectures. It aired a church service on Sundays
and football games in season. In the
mid-1920s the station became KNOW in Austin
and carried no news, sponsored programs, or
commercials. Commercial radio began in
Texas in 1922, and by the end of the year the
state hosted twenty-five stations, including
WBAP and KFLZ in Fort Worth and kgnc in
Amarillo. In 1923 WBAP began a country music
variety show featuring local talent similar
to the style later developed in Nashville as the
Grand Ole Opry.

Before the government allotted frequencies
in 1927 and 1928, many stations tried operating
on the same frequencies. The Kansas City Star operated WDAF and regularly went off the
air at 7 P.M. to allow WHB, also in Kansas City,
to have the frequency–until one evening
when a local politician was scheduled to appear
on WHB to attack the Star. WDAF retained
control over the frequency that evening to
create a weird effect while the man spoke.
Consumers buying radios sometimes hoped
to receive distant stations, so a Chicago newspaper
promoted weekly silent nights–in Kansas
City it was Saturday night–during which
time the local stations would be silent so residents
could listen for distant stations. The silent
nights ended by 1927 with recriminations
and complaints of revenue losses. The idea of
long-distance broadcasting, except for a few
clear-channel frequencies, ended with it.

Many early radio stations were formed to
promote specific businesses that used radio to
sell products. For example, KHD was run by a
marble company in Colorado Springs. In 1923
Dr. John Richard Brinkley began one of the
most unusual radio stations, KFKB ("Kansas
First, Kansas Best" or "Kansas Folks Know
Best") in Milford, to promote his combination
of fundamentalist religion and miracle
cures using goat glands. He also broadcast
other church services, Kansas State College
courses, Masonic lectures, and orchestra concerts.
His broadcasts were so lucrative that he
was able to build a large portion of Milford.
However, the Federal Radio Commission revoked
his license for operating contrary to the
public interest, broadcasting indecent material,
and using point-to-point communication
for commercial purposes, an illegal activity at
the time. The Kansas State Medical Board later
revoked his medical license, challenging his
goat-gland cures.

After being discredited in the United States,
Brinkley persuaded the Mexican government
to license him to broadcast from a powerful
station, in part as revenge to the United States
and Canada for dividing up all the radio frequencies
among themselves. In 1931 his XER
broadcast from 300-foot towers across the Rio
Grande from Del Rio, Texas, and became one
of the first superpower "border radio" stations.
When the Mexican government sought
to prohibit Brinkley's medical broadcasts by
keeping him out of the country, he began a
remote broadcast from a hotel in downtown
Del Rio, with his voice going to the transmitter
in Mexico and back into the U.S. airwaves.

Radio grew rapidly across the continent.
The American public's investment in equipment
grew from $60 million in 1922 to $358
million in 1924. Commercial radio stations in
Canada faced stiff competition for both frequencies
and listeners from the United States
and even from the powerful Mexican border
stations. Like U.S. stations, Canadian stations
argued over frequencies. In Saskatoon three
stations shared the same wavelength in 1925.
Canadian National Railways pioneered radio
for train passengers and, because of the railway's
public ownership, provided a model for
the later British and Canadian Broadcasting
Corporations. The remoteness of Canadian
settlements in the West led to rapid public and
private investment in broadcasting, while
newspapers retained a primarily local focus
through most of the twentieth century. Many
Canadian stations forged agreements with
U.S. stations to carry American programs,
while the Canadian National Railways built
what became the cbc with its strategically located
stations and telephone links. The Canadian
government took control over broadcast
regulation and operation of the public network
only after 1932.

In Regina the Leader newspaper started
CKCK, Saskatchewan's first commercial radio
station, in 1922. Both the newspaper and the
station advised people on how to build their
own receiving sets and warned against unscrupulous
dealers who exaggerated the reception
capabilities of their receivers. Like
their American counterparts, Canadian listeners
received a heavy dose of weather and
agricultural and marketing information. In
the days of distance broadcasting, CKCK's
toughest competitors for listeners included
WLS in Chicago, KOA in Denver, and kfnf in
Hastings, Nebraska.

Although Plains stations began by broadcasting
with local talent, they eventually adopted
standard formats, especially after television
usurped the demand for dramatic and musical
programming. Many national media personalities
such as Johnny Carson and Lawrence
Welk starred on the Plains. Carson, an Iowa
native who was host of NBC television's The Tonight Show for thirty years, started on Nebraska
radio stations, including KFAB and
wow radio and television in Omaha, before
moving to Los Angeles and New York. Welk,
who grew up in Strasburg, North Dakota, began
his broadcasting career on WNAX radio in
Yankton, South Dakota. Chet Huntley, who
played with his first crystal radio set as a child
in Montana, became coanchor with David
Brinkley of NBC's The Huntley-Brinkley Report,
the leading network evening newscast for
much of its fifteen years on the air, beginning
in 1956. Their chief competitor, Walter Cronkite,
who anchored The CBS Evening News 
from 1962 through 1981, spent his early years in
Kansas City, Missouri, and worked as a newspaper
and wire-service reporter in Houston,
Kansas City, Dallas, Austin, and El Paso. His
cbs colleague Eric Sevareid developed an interest
in journalism as a child in Velva, North
Dakota.



The Mass Media Become Concentrated

Despite the myth of individualistic western editors,
the mass media became concentrated in
regional and national chains almost from the
beginning. Montana's notorious copper kings
created a major chain when they bought up
most of the state's daily newspapers in 1900
during their war over the location of the state's
capital. The Anaconda Company controlled
those newspapers until it sold them to the
Iowa-based Lee Enterprises in the 1950s. Although
its major holdings were in the Midwest,
Lee owned newspapers and television
stations across the Plains by the end of the
twentieth century. In Montana Lee continued
to own the daily Billings Gazette, the Montana
Standard of Butte, the Independent Record of Helena, the Missoulian of Missoula, and twelve
weekly shoppers and other specialized publications
in Montana alone. In Nebraska Lee
owned the daily Lincoln Journal-Star, the
weekly Plattsmouth Journal, and KMTV, CBSA.
liated Channel 3 in Omaha. The Lincoln Journal-Star was formed in 1995 when Lee Enterprises
purchased the Lincoln Journal, which
had been owned by the Seacrest family for
generations. The Journal had begun as the Nebraska Commonwealth in Nebraska City in
1867 and moved to Lincoln within a year. The
first Sunday edition appeared in 1871 and became
the State Journal in 1882. A year before
their merger, the Lincoln newspapers claimed
independence from each other through a joint
operating agreement.

Newspapers had spread across the Northern
Plains of both the United States and Canada in
the wake of settlement by the end of the nineteenth
century, well after newspapers had been
established in the Central Plains. While Kansas
newspapers fought the Civil War, European
Americans were yet to settle the Northern
Plains. North Dakota's oldest daily newspaper,
the Bismarck Tribune, was founded in Dakota
Territory by Clement Lounsberry only in 1873.

Some editors made the purpose of their
newspapers clear in their names, like the Calgary Herald, Mining and Ranch Advocate and General Advertiser. Despite the pretentious
name, this paper had humble origins in a tent
beside the Elbow River in 1883. In 1908 William
Southam purchased the Calgary newspaper as
his newspaper empire moved westward from
its base in London, Ontario. Southam purchased
the Edmonton Journal in 1912 and engaged
in a journalism war of sensationalism
with the Bulletin, which had a simple slogan:
"Read the Bible and the Bulletin." The Southam
Corporation grew over the century both in the
number of newspapers and in other industrial
interests, including steel mills, crushed stone,
and carriage manufacturing.

In the mid-1990s, the financially troubled
Southam Corporation merged with Hollinger
International Inc., a newspaper chain controlled
by media mogul Conrad Black, who
had a reputation for operating newspapers as
businesses, holding journalists in contempt,
and advocating tougher libel laws. Hollinger's
far-ranging interests included the Jerusalem Post in Israel, the Chicago Sun-Times in the
United States, the London Daily Telegraph
in England, and the Sydney Morning Herald
in Australia. The merged corporation published
hundreds of nondaily newspapers and
specialized magazines covering diverse topics
such as fishing and trucking. Hollinger has
taken a leading role in online publications in
each nation.

In response to the growing threat from
chains, some smaller newspapers created organizations
such as the Southern Saskatchewan
Press Association. One of its active members
was a newspaper that, like many other Plains
publications, followed the railroads west. The
Courier appeared in Moosomin, Saskatchewan,
soon after the settlers disembarked from
the Canadian Pacific Railway. The newspaper,
now called the World-Spectator, celebrated its
first century in October 1984. As early as 1918
several Saskatoon residents founded Turner's Weekly to be an independent weekly newspaper
with literary aspirations for the general
public. It died in 1920, but one of its founders,
legislator Harris Turner, started the Progressive
in 1923 with the slogan "Reliable News–
Unfettered Opinions–Western Rights." The
publication soon became the Western Producer
weekly newspaper and continued into the
twenty-first century.

The Toronto Sun founded several newspapers
toward the end of the century to compete with
Hollinger and Southam. The Edmonton Sun
opened in 1978 and the Calgary Sun in 1980. In October 1996 the employees purchased the Edmonton Sun and the Calgary Sun from Rogers
Communications Inc., a newspaper chain that
had been founded twenty-five years earlier and
sold to Maclean Hunter and then to Rogers.

The Canadian Broadcasting Corporation
was created, in part, to reach isolated residents
in the West in the 1930s. Like the CBC, U.S.
public broadcasting networks reached into
the Plains with an alternative to American
commercial broadcasting. Because of government
underfunding, the CBC came to rely on
commercial stations to buy its services. Some
U.S. radio stations on the Northern Plains carried
CBC services.

At least one of the world's largest media
companies emerged from the Great Plains.
At the end of the twentieth century, Tele-
Communication, Inc., of Englewood, Colorado,
supplied television to more than 300
markets in North America. Its TCI Cablevision
supplied many Plains cities, including the Colorado
cities of Denver, Grand Junction, Greeley,
Pueblo, and Thornton; the Texas cities of
Abilene, Beaumont, Corpus Christi, Dallas,
Garland, Harlingen, Port Arthur, and Tyler;
and the Wyoming cities of Casper and Cheyenne.
TCI also covered Bellevue, Nebraska;
Billings, Montana; Topeka, Kansas; and Tulsa,
Oklahoma. It owned smaller cable systems
throughout the United States.



The Plains Remain Isolated for Some

Although they were a dying breed, many
small-town newspapers remained local with
local owners. Others joined smaller newspaper
groups, like the Yellowstone Newspapers
of Montana that controlled the daily
Miles City Star and Livingston Enterprise, the
weekly Glendive Ranger-Review, and KATL radio
in Miles City. From 1969 to 1984 David and
Ella Rivenes operated kyus television in Miles
City, one of the smallest stations in the nation.
Miles City had competing KATL ("Cattle") radio
and KYUS ("Cayuse") television, both occasionally
using horses with their logos.

At the beginning of the twenty-first century,
then, no one in Ismay, Montana, climbed
a tower to turn an antenna by hand the way we
did forty years earlier. Like television viewers
around the world, residents of Ismay get as
much television as they can afford. They can
purchase several kinds of disks and then subscribe
to satellite services that provide hundreds
of channels carrying public affairs, old
movies, premium services like HBO and Showtime,
regional network affiliates carrying entertainment
programs and advertising, and
pay-per-view sporting events and movies.
Ranchers and small-town residents no longer
depend upon local stations to acquire network
programming one show at a time. Westerns
like Gunsmoke and Have Gun Will Travel are
still available, but only in reruns on cable
channels or on video. Small-town values prevail,
however, with some folks noticing when a
bachelor neighbor has his disk turned in the
direction of the Playboy channel. Despite a
variety of choices, local news and weather are
hard to find on satellite television, especially
in remote areas. Some ranchers and their families,
however, have chosen not to invest in the
disks and transponders necessary to receive
the new bounty. Some ranchers say their work
takes too much time to warrant investing in
recreational television.

See also CITIES AND TOWNS: Denver, Colorado/ IMAGES AND ICONS: Rainfall Follows the Plow / LITERARY TRADITIONS: Baum, Frank L.; Cather, Willa / MUSIC: Welk, Lawrence/ POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT: Sifton, Clifford / WAR: Bleeding Kansas.



William E. Huntzicker
Bemidji State University




Bennion, Sherilyn Cox. Equal to the Occasion: Women Editors of the Nineteenth-Century West. Reno: University of
Nevada Press, 1990. Carter, L. Edward. The Story of Oklahoma Newspapers. Muskogee: Oklahoma Heritage Association
by Western Heritage Books, 1984. Cloud, Barbara.
The Business of Newspapers on the Western Frontier. Reno:
University of Nevada Press, 1992. Dary, David. Red Blood and Black Ink: Journalism in the Old West. New York: Alfred
A. Knopf, 1998. Huntzicker, William E. "The Frontier
Press 1800–1900." In The Media in America: A History,
edited by William D. Sloan. Northport AL: Vision Press,
2002: 175–98. Karolevitz, Robert F. Newspapering in the Old West. Seattle: Superior Publishing Company, 1965.
Karolevitz, Robert F. With a Shirt Tail Full of Type: The Story of Newspapering in South Dakota. Brookings: South
Dakota Press Association, 1982. Kesterton, W. H. A History of Journalism in Canada. Toronto: McClelland and Stewart
Limited, 1967. Littlefield, Daniel F., Jr., and James W.
Parins. American Indian and Alaska Native Newspapers and Periodicals, 1826–1924. Westport CT: Greenwood
Press, 1984. Lyon, William H., ed. Journalism in the West.
Manhattan KS: Sunflower University Press, 1980. Rankin,
Charles E. "Type and Stereotype: Frederic E. Lockley, Pioneer
Journalist." American Journalist 14 (1997): 182–204.
Schmalz, Wayne. On Air: Radio in Saskatchewan. Regina,
Saskatchewan: Coteau Books, 1990. Schmitt, Jo Ann.
Fighting Editors. San Antonio: Naylor Company, 1958. Vipond,
Mary. Listening In: The First Decade of Canadian Broadcasting, 1922–1923. Montreal: McGill-Queen's University
Press, 1992.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>