<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.med.031</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Native American Radio</field>
      <field name="author">Smith, Bruce L.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




NATIVE AMERICAN RADIO

Logo for National Native News


Radio stations owned and operated by Native
Americans and Native Canadians serve much
of the Great Plains. The delivery systems are
different in the two countries, but the goals
are similar: to help preserve and promote Indigenous
languages and cultures.

Broadcast media were once negative forces
in Indigenous communities because they
bombarded the communities with Western
languages, cultures, and values. The media of
the dominant culture overwhelmed and imperiled
fragile traditional cultures. In recent
years, however, electronic media owned and
operated by Indigenous people have helped to
restore the balance.

The first Native American radio station
went on the air in 1973. A scattered few additional
stations followed during the rest of the
decade, but their development was hampered
by a lack of funds. A change in federal government
policy in the 1980s provided more
resources to equip and operate Native stations,
and their numbers grew steadily. As
of 1999, some forty stations were broadcasting
across the United States, and others were
being planned.

Fourteen of the Native stations serve the
American Great Plains. Each of the stations
operates independently. They are licensed variously
to tribal councils, community colleges,
church groups, and nonprofit corporations.
Half of the stations are located in the Dakotas,
with three in North Dakota and four in South
Dakota. Montana, Wyoming, and Colorado
are each home to one station, and there are
four in New Mexico. One is being planned
for western Minnesota. There are no Native
stations in Nebraska, Oklahoma, Texas, or
Kansas.

Some stations receive programming from
the National Public Radio network, but most
do not because of the expense involved in
being a member of the network. Most do receive
satellite-delivered programming such as
National Native News (a newscast) and Native America Calling (a call-in program) and other
services of the American Indian Radio on Satellite
Network (AIROS). Many non-Native stations
in the region also broadcast some of
these programs. Popular music and public
service programs, including coverage of powwows
and other cultural events, are also featured
on Native stations. Traditional languages
are used extensively on some stations,
while others do little or no Native-language
programming because the languages are seldom
used anymore or there are multiple Indigenous
languages in a listening area, which
limits the use of any single language.

Indigenous stations also serve the Canadian
provinces in the Great Plains. Similar to the
situation in the United States, Indigenous
communities had little control of the media
that reached them until the 1980s, when the
Canadian government began to fund and support
Native-controlled electronic media that
would protect and preserve Indigenous languages
and cultures. Alberta, Saskatchewan,
and Manitoba are each home to sophisticated
radio networks that deliver signals to dozens of
communities in each province. Corporations
in each province provide this service. In Alberta,
CFWE-FM radio, owned and operated by
the Aboriginal Multi-Media Society, reaches
forty-six communities in the province by satellite.
In Saskatchewan, the Missinipi Broadcasting
Corporation provides the service to more
than thirty communities via fm transmitters
or cable. In Manitoba, the Aboriginal fm Network
of Native Communications Inc. reaches
seventy sites. This centralized network system
is different from the American model but is an
efficient means of reaching the large and
sparsely populated regions that are served.


Bruce L. Smith
Southwest Texas State University




Browne, Donald R. Electronic Media and Indigenous Peoples: A Voice of Our Own? Ames: Iowa State University
Press, 1996. Keith, Michael C. Signals in the Air: Native Broadcasting in America. Westport CT: Praeger, 1995.
Smith, Bruce L., and M. L. Cornette. "Electronic Smoke
Signals: Native American Radio in the United States." Cultural Survival Quarterly (spring 1998): 28–31.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>