<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.afam.011</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Brown, "Aunt" Clara (1803-1885)</field>
      <field name="author">Noel, Thomas J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BROWN, "AUNT" CLARA (1803-1885)


"Aunt" Clara Brown, between 1875 and 1880


"Aunt" Clara Brown was born in Tennessee
in 1803 to slave parents, who were sold to
separate owners when she was only three. She
went with her mother to the home of Ambrose
Smith, a farmer in Logan County, Kentucky.
Smith, a kindly man and a devout
Methodist, took Clara and her mother to his
church services.

Clara was eighteen and a tall, strong woman
with warm brown eyes when the Smiths
bought an eighteen-year-old carpenter slave,
Richard. When he and Clara fell in love, they
were encouraged to marry and produce children
to work the Smiths' farm. They were separated
when Clara was sold to George Brown.
Following southern custom, she, like other
mature female slaves, was called "Aunt" and
given the last name of her new owner. The
Browns liked Clara's intelligence and spunk
and helped her buy her freedom. She moved
to St. Louis, where Missouri law protected free
blacks. She later went with the Browns when
they emigrated to Kansas. There she joined a
wagon train headed to Colorado, earning her
way as a cook. She arrived at Denver in June
of 1859.

Denver's first-recorded black woman, Aunt
Clara opened a shop as a laundress, worked
hard, and scraped together $5,000 to go back
to Logan County, Kentucky, to look for her
husband, children, and friends. She returned
to Colorado with one daughter and other relatives
and friends newly freed from bondage.

Aunt Clara moved to Central City and resumed
her laundering work, toiling long
hours and denying herself any luxuries. With
the money she saved she funded the construction
of St. James Methodist Church,
which thrives to this day. She died in her sleep
on October 23, 1885. At her burial at Denver's
Riverside Cemetery, Colorado governor James
B. Grant, Denver mayor John L. Routt, and
other dignitaries praised Aunt Clara as "the
kind old friend whose heart always responded
to the cry of distress, and who, rising from the
humble position of slave to the angelic type of
noble woman, won our sympathy and commanded
our respect."


Thomas J. Noel
University of Colorado at Denver




Bruyn, Kathleen. "Aunt" Clara Brown: Story of a Black
Pioneer. Boulder: Pruett Publishing Co., 1970.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>