<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.024</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Guthrie, A. B., Jr. (1901-1991)</field>
      <field name="author">Bryant, Paul T.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




GUTHRIE, A. B., JR. (1901-1991)

Alfred Bertram Guthrie Jr. is best known for
his cycle of six novels spanning the exploration
and settlement of the West from the days
of the fur trade through the mid–twentieth
century (The Big Sky, 1947; The Way West,
1949; These Thousand Hills, 1956; Arfive, 1971;
Last Valley, 1975; Fair Land, Fair Land, 1982).
He also produced six relatively slight mystery
novels, the screenplays for Shane and The Kentuckian,
a children's book, a volume of poetry,
and short stories. All the fiction, except the
last mystery, are set in the Plains of eastern
Montana and at the edge of the Rocky Mountains.
His autobiography, The Blue Hen's Chick
(1965), reveals the influence of the "Big Sky
Country" on his vision of the westward movement
and the consequences of the closing of
the frontier.

Guthrie was born January 13, 1901, in Bedford,
Indiana, but moved with his family to
Choteau, Montana, six months later. Like his
father, he felt a sense of freedom on the Plains
and in the mountains, and he made the Choteau
area the hub of his fiction. The landscape
is significant in all his fiction, and space is a
persistent theme.

After graduation from the University of
Montana, Guthrie worked at a variety of jobs,
including as a newspaper reporter in Lexington,
Kentucky. In 1944 a Nieman Fellowship
to Harvard gave him the opportunity to
work on The Big Sky. After publication of his
second novel, The Way West, he left newspaper
work and returned to Montana to write
fiction. He died in Choteau on April 26, 1991.


Paul T. Bryant
Radford, Virginia




Bryant, Paul T. "External Characterization in The Big Sky."
Western American Literature 31 (1996): 195–210. Ford,
Thomas W. A. B. Guthrie, Jr. Boston: Twayne, 1981.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>