<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.wat.024</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Report on the Lands of the Arid Region</field>
      <field name="author">Worster, Donald</field>
      <field name="text">

 




REPORT ON THE LANDS OF THE ARID REGION

One of the most famous documents in American
environmental history, the Report on the
Lands of the Arid Region of the United States
(1878) was less than 200 pages long. The authors
were members of the Geographical and
Geological Survey of the Rocky Mountain Region,
under the direction of John Wesley
Powell, intrepid explorer of the Colorado
River and the Grand Canyon. Powell's own
contribution to their report to Congress was
the first two chapters, which were characteristically
bold and visionary.

The nation was moving into a vast region
marked by aridity, Powell warned, and the traditional
system for disposing of the public domain
to private citizens–the 160-acre farming
homestead–was badly adapted to that condition.
Powell relied on data collected by the
Smithsonian showing that beyond the 100th
meridian rainfall was less than twenty inches a
year, on average, which was insu.cient for
most crops. Successful settlement would require
laws that encouraged smaller-scale farms
based on communal irrigation and, more generally,
laws that encouraged a pastoral economy
of sheep and cattle ranches.

Separating the arid from the humid region
was the Great Plains (which Powell called the
Sub-humid Region), stretching over nearly
one-tenth of the country. He predicted that
much agricultural wealth would come out of
this "beautiful prairie country," whose rich
soils seemed ready for the plow. He foresaw,
however, that the Plains would experience
many disastrous droughts, leaving people disappointed
and bankrupt, and he recommended
developing surface irrigation to mitigate
some of this uncertainty.


Donald Worster
University of Kansas




Stegner, Wallace. Beyond the Hundredth Meridian: John
Wesley Powell and the Second Opening of the American
West. Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1954. Worster, Donald.
An Unsettled Country: Changing Landscapes of the American
West. Albuquerque: University of New Mexico, 1994.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>