<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.086</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Warren, Francis (1844-1929)</field>
      <field name="author">Moore, William Howard</field>
      <field name="text">

 




WARREN, FRANCIS (1844-1929)


Francis Warren


U.S. senator Francis Emory Warren used his
seniority and committee assignments to encourage
economic development in the West
and to build an effective Republican political
machine in Wyoming. Born on June 20, 1844,
in Hinsdale, Massachusetts, Warren attended
local schools and won the Congressional
Medal of Honor for his service with a Union
Army regiment during the Civil War. Moving
westward, he arrived in Cheyenne in 1868,
where he clerked in a furniture store. Soon, he
purchased and expanded the enterprise (renaming
it the Warren Mercantile Company)
and established the Warren Land and Livestock
Company and a far-flung set of investments
in banks, railroads, and public utilities.
Possibly the wealthiest individual in Wyoming,
Warren maintained close ties to the
powerful Wyoming Stock Growers Association
and served as president of the National
Wool Growers Association.

Business interests quite naturally attracted
Warren to politics. Appointed territorial governor
in 1885, he sided with business interests
and Chinese workers during the Rock Springs
massacre of 1885. In 1890 Warren was elected
the state's first governor, but he resigned days
later after being chosen U.S. senator. He would
serve more than thirty-seven years in the Senate,
a record unsurpassed until 1964. Warren's
seniority, his energy, his unusual knack for political
organization and patronage, and his
close attention to the state's business interests
brought him extensive influence both in Washington
and in Wyoming.

Warren chose to use that influence primarily
to benefit his state and region. Rejecting
charges of conflict of interest, he worked assiduously
for high tariffs on raw wool, hides,
and beef–-psitions that clearly favored the
sheep and cattle industry. Warren supported
federal leasing policies designed to accommodate
both interests, he opposed policies that
would block fencing on the federal domain,
and he promoted the Carey Act of 1894 and a
host of irrigation and reclamation projects to
advance western interests. He lobbied shamelessly
for the construction of federal buildings
in Wyoming and used his position on the Senate
Military Affairs Committee to enhance
Fort Mackenzie in Sheridan, Wyoming, and
Fort D. A. Russell (later F. E. Warren Air Force
Base) in Cheyenne. As chair of the Senate Appropriations
Committee in the 1920s, Warren
worked for government economy and high
tariffs.

Warren died in Washington dc on November
24, 1929. He was married twice, and a
daughter by his first marriage became the wife
of Gen. John J. Pershing.

See also WAR: Pershing, John J..


William Howard Moore
University of Wyoming




Gould, Lewis L. Wyoming: From Territory to Statehood.
Worland WY: High Plains Publishing Company, 1989. Larson,
Taft Alfred. History of Wyoming. Lincoln: University
of Nebraska Press, 1978. Warren, Francis E. Papers. Ms.
00013. American Heritage Center, University of Wyoming,
Laramie.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>