<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.law.011</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Brown v. The Board of Education of Topeka</field>
      <field name="author">Henderson, Cheryl Brown</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BROWN V. THE BOARD OF EDUCATION OF TOPEKA

Long before Brown v. The Board of Education
of Topeka became part of the national legal
landscape, African American parents were initiating
court cases to challenge segregated
public schools. The first documented school
case took place before the Civil War. In 1849,
in the case of Roberts v. The City of Boston, the
Massachusetts courts denied Benjamin Roberts
and other African American parents the
right to enroll their children in certain Boston
public schools. More than thirty years later,
African American parents in Kansas took up
the cause of gaining equal access to public
schools. The free-state heritage, geographical
location, and composition of its population
positioned Kansas to play a central role in the
major questions of educational freedom and
equality. In 1868 state law allowed but did not
require separate schools. Some schools admitted
children without discrimination, and one
of the first state superintendents of public instruction,
Peter McVicar, vocally opposed segregated
schools.

The arrival of the "Exodusters" from the
South in the 1870s, however, hardened attitudes
toward segregated schools in Kansas.
Migration increased the African American
population from 627 in 1860 to more than
43,000 by 1880. Because of community sentiment,
some schools began to separate children
by race. In 1879 the Kansas legislature
passed a statute specifically allowing first-class
cities (those with populations of 15,000 or
more) to operate separate primary schools.
This law remained in effect into the 1950s.
With the exception of those in Wyandotte
County, secondary schools were not segregated
in Kansas. For a span of nearly seventy
years, from 1881 to 1949, the Kansas Supreme
Court became the venue for the constitutional
question of public schools and segregation.

During that period the following cases were
organized by African American parents across
Kansas: Elijah Tinnon v. The Board of Education
of Ottawa (1881); Knox v. The Board of
Education of Independence (1891); Reynolds v.
The Board of Education of Topeka (1903); Cartwright
v. The Board of Education of Coffeyville
(1906); Rowles v. The Board of Education of
Wichita (1907); Williams v. The Board of Education
of Parsons (1908); Woolridge v. The Board of
Education of Galena (1916); Thurman-Watts v.
The Board of Education of Coffeyville (1924);
Wright v. The Board of Education of Topeka
(1929); Graham v. The Board of Education of
Topeka (1941); and Webb v. School District No.
90, South Park, Johnson County (1949). Individuals or small groups of parents appear to
have acted on their own in the earliest cases. In
later cases state and national strategies of the
National Association for the Advancement of
Colored People (NAACP) were clearly at work.

In response to numerous unsuccessful attempts
to ensure access to equal opportunities
for all children, African American community
leaders and organizations stepped up their
efforts to change public education. In the fall
of 1950 members of the Topeka chapter of the
NAACP agreed to challenge again the separate
but equal doctrine applied to public education
as a result of the 1896 United States Supreme
Court ruling in the case of Plessy v.
Ferguson. Chapter president McKinley Burnett,
secretary Lucinda Todd, and attorneys
Charles Scott, John Scott, and Charles Bledsoe
developed the strategy for this challenge.

The three young attorneys for the Topeka
NAACP were graduates of Washburn University
and Washburn Law School in Topeka. Lucinda
Todd had taught in one of the segregated
African American schools but had
resigned in keeping with the policy that did
not permit married women to teach school.
McKinley Burnett was a longtime community
activist for the rights of African American
people.

From 1948 to 1950 Burnett went before the
Topeka School Board to persuade it to end the
practice of segregated elementary schools
since Kansas law permitted but did not require
segregated public schools. The decision
to challenge segregation in the courts was a
measure of last resort for the NAACP.

The team of Burnett, Todd, Bledsoe, and
the Scotts devised a plan that involved enlisting
the support of fellow NAACP members and
personal friends as plaintiffs in what would be
a class action suit filed against the Board of
Education of Topeka Public Schools. Lucinda
Todd was the first to volunteer on behalf of
her seven-year-old daughter. She was eventually
joined by a group of twelve parents who
agreed to participate on behalf of their children
(nineteen children in all). Individuals in
the Topeka case moved ahead, unaware that at
the same time legal counsel for the NAACP
headquarters in New York was representing
plaintiffs in school cases from Delaware, Virginia,
South Carolina, and Washington DC.

Children of the Topeka plaintiffs had to
travel past and away from nearby schools to
attend the four schools designated for African
Americans. Topeka operated eighteen schools
for white children and only four for African
American children. In the fall of 1950 the thirteen
parents were instructed by the NAACP to
locate the white school closest to their home,
take their child or children there along with a
witness, and attempt enrollment. The parents
were denied the right to enroll their children
in these schools, a result that provided the attorneys
with documentation to file suit. The
NAACP case was filed in federal district court
in February 1951. At that point, Oliver Brown,
the only male among the roster of parents, was
designated as lead plaintiff. With that designation,
the case became known by his name. In
addition to Brown the plaintiff roster included
Darlene Brown (no relation to Oliver), Lena
Carper, Sadie Emmanuel, Marguerite Emmerson,
Shirla Fleming, Zelma Henderson, Shirley
Hodison, Maude Lawton, Alma Lewis,
Iona Richardson, Vivian Scales, and Lucinda
Todd.

Even though their case met with defeat, the
testimony of expert witnesses firmly established
that while educators in African American
schools held more advanced degrees than
their white counterparts, the school buildings
for African American and white children in
Topeka were substantially unequal. These
findings set the stage for a challenge to segregation
per se. Under the leadership of Presiding
Judge Walter Huxman, who had once
served as governor of Kansas, the federal district
court ruled in favor of the Topeka Board
of Education. Attorneys for the NAACP immediately
filed an appeal with the U.S. Supreme
Court.

When the Kansas case reached the Supreme
Court it was combined with the other NAACP
cases from Delaware, South Carolina, Virginia,
and Washington DC. The combined cases became
known by the Kansas case: Oliver L.
Brown v. The Board of Education of Topeka.
These cases were supported by the NAACP and
its executive secretary, Walter White, and were
litigated by the daunting legal team of Charles
Bledsoe, Harold Boulware, Robert Carter,
William T. Coleman, Jack Greenberg, Williams
H. Hastie, George E. C. Hayes, Oliver Hill,
Charles Hamilton Houston, Thurgood Marshall,
James M. Nabrit Jr., Louis Redding,
Frank Reeves, Spotswood Robinson, Charles S.
Scott, John Scott, U. Simpson Tate, and Franklin
Williams.

On May 17, 1954, at 12:52 P.M., the Supreme
Court issued a unanimous decision. The
Court's verdict was based on arguments presented
in the lower courts by social scientists
Louisa Holt and Kenneth Clark. As a consequence
the Court declared that the separation
of children in public schools for no other reason
than race was a violation of the Fourteenth
Amendment and therefore unconstitutional.
In December 1955 the Court directed
the country to implement its decision "with
all deliberate speed." The Court's edict of 1955
became known as Brown II.

To this day, efforts continue in Kansas and
across the country to realize the dream of the
NAACP. In 1979 a group of attorneys was concerned
that a Topeka Public Schools policy
allowing open enrollment would lead to resegregation.
The attorneys believed that with
this type of choice white parents would shift
their children to other schools, creating predominantly
African American and predominantly
white schools, and they petitioned the
federal district court to reopen the original
Brown case to determine if Topeka Public
Schools had in fact ever complied with the
Court's ruling of 1954. Their case became
known as Brown III. The attorneys were Richard
Jones, Joseph Johnson, and Charles Scott
Jr. (son of one of the attorneys in the original
Brown case) in association with Chris Hansen
from the American Civil Liberties Union in
New York. In the late 1980s Topeka Public
Schools were found to be in noncompliance.
On October 28, 1992, after several appeals, the
U.S. Supreme Court denied Topeka Public
Schools' petition to once again hear the Brown
case.

In the absence of another appeal, the Topeka
Board of Education was directed by federal
district court to develop plans for compliance.
In response, three magnet schools
were constructed to replace older buildings
and expand neighborhood boundaries. These
schools are excellent facilities and make every
effort to be racially balanced. In recognition of
the legacy of the 1954 decision, one of these
new schools was named for the Scott family
attorneys. Another was named for one of the
city's leading African American teachers, the
late Mamie Williams.

In 1988, in order to create a living tribute to
the attorneys and plaintiffs in the original
Brown case, the family of the late Oliver L.
Brown and other community members in
Topeka established the Brown Foundation for
Educational Equity, Excellence, and Research.
In 1990 the Brown Foundation sought to create
a permanent place for the interpretation
and commemoration of the landmark Supreme
Court decision. On October 26, 1992,
after two years of work by the Brown Foundation,
President George H. W. Bush signed the
Brown v. The Board of Education National Historic
Site Act to commemorate the landmark
Supreme Court Decision.

See also AFRICAN AMERICANS: Civil Rights; Exodusters; Scott Family / CITIES AND TOWNS: Topeka, Kansas.


Cheryl Brown Henderson
Brown Foundation





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>