<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.law.007</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Billy the Kid (c. 1856-1881)</field>
      <field name="author">Tuska, Jon</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BILLY THE KID (c. 1856-1881)

Portrait photograph of Billy the Kid


Billy the Kid was an outlaw whose legend has
come to overshadow any personal or historical
significance he may have had. It has not been
satisfactorily documented when and where he
was born, although it has been established that
his actual name was Henry McCarty. In 1880 in
Fort Sumner, New Mexico, McCarty (alias
Billy Antrim, Henry Antrim, Kid Antrim, Billy
Bonney, William H. Bonney, and Billy the Kid)
told a federal census taker that he was twentyfive
years old, that both of his parents had been
born in Missouri, and that he too had been
born there. There is no reason to believe he was
lying. It can be documented that in 1866 he was
living in Marion County, Indiana, with his
mother, Catherine McCarty, and his elder
brother, Joseph McCarty. Catherine McCarty
suffered from tuberculosis, and this may have
prompted her to move farther west. In 1873
Billy's mother married William H. Antrim in
Santa Fe, New Mexico. Shortly after his mother's
death in 1874, he took to wandering and
spent two years as a general laborer, cowboy,
and teamster in eastern Arizona.

Only four killings can be documented
against the Kid. The first occurred in 1877 at
Camp Grant, Arizona, when Billy shot and
killed Frank "Windy" Cahill after an argument
turned violent. The Kid was found
guilty of "criminal and unjustifiable" shooting,
but he escaped from custody and returned
to New Mexico. The Kid's other killings
resulted from his involvement in the
Lincoln County War, a deadly feud involving
local merchant and cattle interests. On one
side stood Scottish lawyer Alexander Mc-
Sween and John H. Tunstall, an Englishman
who owned a cattle ranch in Lincoln County.
On the other were James Dolan and Lawrence
Murphy, merchants in the town of Lincoln. In
January 1878 the Kid was working for Tunstall.
When Tunstall was murdered by the Murphy-
Dolan faction, the Kid and other Tunstall-
McSween allies declared themselves "Regulators"
and sought revenge.

For the next year bloody retaliatory warfare
was waged between the two factions. In early
March the Regulators arrested and then killed
Dolan associates Frank Baker and Billy Morton,
reportedly while the pair were trying to
escape. At that point, territorial governor
John Axtell declared the Regulators outlaws;
after that they were hunted. On April 1, 1878,
when Sheriff William Brady and Deputy
George Hindman, both Dolan allies, tried to
ambush McSween, the Regulators fought back
and killed the lawmen. Three days later the
Regulators battled "Buckshot" Roberts, a
heavily armed bounty hunter, at Blazer's Mill.
Roberts and Dick Brewer, a Regulator, were
killed in the gunfight. The decisive battle of
the Lincoln County War was fought during a
five-day shoot-out in Lincoln in July 1878.
Sniping went on for four days, with the Regulators
trapped inside McSween's house. On
the fifth day, after the ineffective U.S. Army
arrived, McSween's home was set on fire, and
the Kid led a rush out of the burning house.
The Kid managed to escape, but McSween and
several others were riddled with bullets.

Along with what was left of the Regulators,
the Kid was outlawed for good. In December
1880 the newly elected sheriff of Lincoln
County, Pat Garrett, and other lawmen captured
the Kid at Stinking Springs. There were
two federal indictments open against the Kid.
The first was for killing Buckshot Roberts, the
second was for the death of a clerk on the
Mescalero reservation. The prosecution decided
that both of these charges would probably
result in acquittal, so it was decided to try
the Kid for the murder of Sheriff Brady. The
Kid was found guilty and sentenced to hang,
but he escaped on April 28, 1881, after killing
two guards. The Kid was shot to death on the
night of July 14, 1881, killed by Pat Garrett during
an ambush at old Fort Sumner.

Hundreds of books, motion pictures, radio
programs, television programs, and even a
ballet have subsequently been inspired by the
legend of Billy the Kid. As a legend, the Kid is
open to a variety of interpretations, principally
as a good man who went bad, as a bad
man who remained bad, as a good man who
was falsely persecuted. Historians, too, have
been guilty of using the Kid's life to prove
some thesis or another about his true nature.
None of this has anything to do, of course,
with the historical Billy the Kid who probably
killed only four men, generally in circumstances
that might be conceived of as selfdefense,
and who was unfortunate enough to
find himself on the losing side in a mercantile
war.

See also WAR: Lincoln County War.


Jon Tuska
Golden West Literary Agency




Fulton, Maurice Garland. History of the Lincoln County War. Tucson: University of Arizona Press, 1968. Tuska,
Jon. Billy the Kid: His Life and Legend. Albuquerque: University
of New Mexico Press, 1997.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>