<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.na.076</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Ojibwas</field>
      <field name="author">McCullough, Martha L.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




OJIBWAS

Within the Great Plains, the Ojibwas reside in
Montana, North Dakota, Manitoba, Saskatchewan,
and Alberta. The name "Ojibwa" is generally
translated as "To Roast Till Puckered
Up," an allusion to the puckered moccasins
worn in the past. In the Great Plains, however,
Ojibwa is more likely to be used as a geographical
designation rather than a self-identifying
term. In fact, no inclusive terms exist to refer
to all the Ojibwa communities in the Great
Plains. Generally, the term "Plains Bungi" (or
Bungee) refers to the Ojibwas residing in Alberta,
Saskatchewan, and western Manitoba.
"Saulteaux" is often used to designate Ojibwas
living in the area near Lake Winnipeg as well as
the region south of the lake and extending to
the international border. Within the United
States, "Chippewas" is frequently used to identify
Ojibwas in North Dakota and Montana. In
addition to these terms, "Metis" is employed
to refer to descendants of French and Ojibwa,
Cree, and/or Chippewa ancestors. The Ojibwas
speak dialects of the Algonquian language
family.

Ojibwas in the eastern portion of their territory
sometimes refer to themselves as Anishinaabes,
which means "The People" or "Original
Man." According to oral traditions, the
Ojibwas once belonged to the three fires of the
Anishinaabes. This triad represented a confederacy
that included not only the Ojibwas
but also the Potawatomis and Ottawas. In
North Dakota, some local Ojibwas also refer to
themselves by the Algonquian word nakkawininiwak,
which means "those who speak differently."
This refers to linguistic differences
between the Ojibwa spoken by the Plains and
Woodland Ojibwas.

The Plains Ojibwas are descended from Algonquian-
speaking Woodland groups located
in Michigan, Wisconsin, Minnesota, and Ontario.
During the late eighteenth century the
expansion of the fur trade and the Iroquois
resulted in the migration of some Ojibwas into
the Great Plains. Many of these migrants settled
in forested areas surrounded by lakes. As
a result, substantial communities developed
near Lake Winnipeg, in the Turtle Mountain
region of North Dakota, and the confluence of
the Red and Red Lake Rivers in Montana.

In these areas the Plains Ojibwas began
hunting bison, elk, deer, and small game. Fur
trapping, fishing, and horse raiding also became
important activities in the region. Like
numerous other Plains populations, the Ojibwas
in the area used bison-hide tipis, the horse
and travois, and hard-soled footwear. Like
their Woodland ancestors, the Plains Ojibwas
continued to use floral designs in their beadwork
and to make fish-skin containers. Other
similarities between the Plains and Woodland
Ojibwas continued in the areas of social organization
and belief systems.

The Plains Ojibwas retained the concept of
nonresidential totemic clans. A number of
these patrilineal clans formed bands. Exogamous
marriages occurred at both the clan and
band level. After marriage, residency was initially
matrilocal, due to the two- to three-year
bride service (labor due to the bride's family)
required of the groom. After that period, the
couple practiced patrilocal residency. Husbands
practiced mother-in-law avoidance.
Joking relationships existed between the wife
and her husband's brothers, as well as between
the husband and his wife's sisters.

Unlike the Woodland Ojibwas, only a few
Plains Ojibwas practiced the Shaking Tent ceremony.
Most Plains Ojibwas instead participated
in the Sun Dance. Throughout the
Ojibwa region, however, belief in Manitou,
Windigo, and Nanibush persisted. Manitou refers
to a neutral power that permeates all matter.
Only through religious training can a person
learn to control this essence. Windigo is a
giant humanlike monster that resides in the
winter forest, and Nanibush refers to a comic
hero that continually breaks taboos. During
the twentieth century the Native American
Church became an important aspect of religious
activities among many Ojibwas in the
United States.

Currently, the Ojibwas occupy five reserves
in Alberta, six in Saskatchewan, two in Manitoba,
two reservations in North Dakota, and
three in Minnesota. Generally, members of
other Native populations also occupy these
reservations and reserves. For example, the
Rocky Boy's Reservation in Montana includes
Plains Ojibwas, Plains Crees, and Metis, and
intermarriage has blurred the lines between
the groups.

In Canada, traditional Ojibwa continues to
be spoken in many households, while within
the United States some adults and fewer children
speak the language. Consequently, a
number of communities in Montana and
North Dakota are establishing bilingual educational
programs.

See also LITERARY TRADITIONS: Erdrich, Louise.


Martha L. McCollough
University of Nebraska-Lincoln



Albers, Patricia C. "Plains Ojibwa." In Handbook of North
American Indians, edited by Raymond J. DeMallie, 13:
652–61. Washington DC: Smithsonian Institution, 2001.
LaCounte, Alysia E. "Ojibwa: Chippewa in Montana." In
Native America in the Twentieth Century: An Encyclopedia,
edited by Mary B. Davis. New York and London: Garland
Publishing, Inc., 1996: 399–401. Murray, Stanley N. "The
Turtle Mountain Chippewa, 1882–1905." North Dakota
History 51 (1984): 14–37.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>