<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ha.035</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Repatriation to Mexico</field>
      <field name="author">Martin, Philip</field>
      <field name="text">

 




REPATRIATION TO MEXICO

Twice in the twentieth century the United
States recruited Mexican workers for seasonal
employment on American farms, and twice
large numbers of Mexicans were repatriated.
The first government-approved recruitment
of Mexican workers occurred on May 23, 1917,
when the Department of Labor permitted
Mexicans to enter the United States to work
for farmers for up to one year. Many Mexicans
had previously left the United States in the
spring of 1917, in part because of rumors that
they would be drafted into the army. To replace
them, as well as to replace American residents
who were drafted, Mexicans were legally
admitted.

Mexicans were eager to emigrate. During
the Mexican Revolution (1913–20), the seven
west-central states of Mexico–Nuevo León,
Tamaulipas, Zacatecas, San Luis Potosí, Guanajuato,
Jalisco, and Michoacán–were a battleground
between the central government in
Mexico City and revolutionaries from Mexican
border states, and the fighting led most
haciendas to reduce their employment. Between
May 1917 and June 1920 some 51,000
Mexicans entered the United States legally under
these exemptions. Eighty percent were
farmworkers, including sugar beet workers in
the Great Plains; others worked on the railroads
and in mines. Housing and meal arrangements
under this program were left to
the discretion of employers. As a result, some
Mexican workers wound up owing money to
farmers at the end of the season. Mexicans
continued to migrate north after 1921, so that
the number of Mexican-born U.S. residents
rose rapidly in the 1920s. However, between
1929 and 1933 an estimated 400,000 Mexicans
were returned–voluntarily and forcibly–to
Mexico, meaning that more Mexicans were repatriated
during these four years than had immigrated
in the 1920s.

In 1942 farmers again won permission to
recruit Mexican workers, and over the next
twenty-two years, some 4.6 million Mexicans
were admitted to the United States to do farmwork,
under what was called the Bracero Program.
At the insistence of Mexico, braceros
were not allowed to be employed legally in
Texas between 1942 and 1947 because of discrimination
there against Mexicans. The Mexican
government also prohibited its citizens
from working in Wyoming after 1963. Both
states eventually regained access to braceros.

There was a major repatriation of Mexicans
during the Bracero Program. In June 1954
the Immigration and Naturalization Service
launched "Operation Wetback" to ensure that
Mexicans employed in the United States had
work authorization. "Operation Wetback" began
in California, moved to Texas, and then
into the Midwest. In coordinated sweeps with
state and local law enforcement authorities,
some 1.1 million persons were returned to
Mexico in 1954, including at least 20,000 from
Chicago, St. Louis, and Kansas City; many
Mexicans living in the Midwest left for Mexico
before they were apprehended. Apprehended
Mexicans were returned to Mexico via Presidio,
Texas, because the Mexican city across
the border, Ojinaga, had rail connections to
the interior of Mexico.

The Bracero Program and "Operation Wetback"
are considered mistakes in U.S. immigration
policy. The Bracero Program set
Mexico-U.S. migration in motion, and "Operation
Wetback" allowed the U.S. government
to violate the rights of legal immigrants and
American citizens in the name of regaining
control of its borders.


Philip Martin
University of California-Davis




Galarza, Ernesto. Merchants of Labor: The Mexican Bracero Story. Charlotte NC: McNally and Loftin, 1964. Garcia,
Juan Ramon. Operation Wetback: The Mass Deportation of Mexican Undocumented Workers in 1954. Westport CT:
Greenwood Press, 1980. Martin, Philip. Promises to Keep: Collective Bargaining in California Agriculture. Ames: Iowa
State University Press, 1996.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>