<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.gen.018</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Hind, Cora (1861-1942)</field>
      <field name="author">Dickin, Janice</field>
      <field name="text">

 




HIND, CORA (1861-1942)


Cora Hind


Ella Cora Hind was a pioneer in breaking gender
barriers and a lifelong advocate for women's rights. She was appointed by J. W. Dafoe
as agricultural editor of the Manitoba Free
Press (later Winnipeg Free Press) in 1901,
twenty years after she was first refused work
there on gender grounds.

Hind was born in Toronto on September 18,
1861. Orphaned in early childhood, she and
her two older brothers grew up on their
grandfather's mixed farm near Orillia, Ontario.
As her grandfather's favorite, Hind
learned about agriculture firsthand. Cora was
raised by her Aunt Alice, who moved to Winnipeg
with Cora in 1882. They lived together
until Alice's death in 1908. During Cora's first
three decades in Winnipeg, Alice was truly her
partner, bringing in an income as a dressmaker,
managing Hind's business in her absence,
and doing research for Cora's freelance
articles.

Cora trained herself to use the new office
innovation, the typewriter, and became a
clerk for a firm of influential lawyers. In 1893
she set up her own office, acting as public secretary
to, among others, a number of farming
organizations. Her big break came in 1898
when she traveled west to report for banking
and business interests on the effects of a late
crop. Her distinguished career in journalism
culminated in a tour around the world (1935.
37) to report on farming, published as Seeing for Myself (1937). Her accurate estimates of
crop yields were legendary on both sides of
the U.S.-Canadian border.

Hind was granted an honorary doctorate
by the University of Manitoba in 1935. When
she died in Winnipeg on October 6, 1942,
trading at the Winnipeg Grain Exchange was
halted for two minutes in her honor.

See also MEDIA: Winnipeg Free Press.


Janice Dickin
University of Calgary




Hacker, Carlotta. E. Cora Hind. Don Mills ON: Fitzhenry
and Whiteside, 1979. Haig, Kenneth M. Brave Harvest: The
Life Story of E. Cora Hind. Toronto: Thomas Allen Ltd.,
1945. Hind, E. Cora. Seeing for Myself: Agricultural Conditions
around the World. Toronto: Macmillan Publishing
Company, 1937.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>