<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.026</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Hogan, Linda (b. 1947)</field>
      <field name="author">Vogel, Mark</field>
      <field name="text">

 




HOGAN, LINDA (b. 1947)

Writer Linda Hogan
  

Contemporary Native American poet, novelist,
and essayist Linda Hogan explores the relationship
of humans to the natural world,
both past and present. She was born in Denver,
Colorado, on July 16, 1947, to a Chickasaw
father and a mother of German descent. Her
father's family in Oklahoma were gifted storytellers,
and this heritage and love for the landscape
inform her belief in the sacredness of
the earth and its inhabitants. A teacher and
political activist, Hogan has taught literature
and creative writing at the Universities of
Minnesota and Colorado. In 1986 she received
an American Book Award for her book of
poems, Seeing through the Sun.

An impassioned political and spiritual
leader, Hogan catalogs the voices of the disenfranchised, particularly those who have suffered
during the settling of the Great Plains.
Her historical novel, Mean Spirit (1990), a finalist
for a Pulitzer Prize in 1991, depicts the
devastating impact of the 1920s Oklahoma oil
boom on an Osage Indian community, especially
its women.

Throughout her work, Hogan argues for a
balancing of spiritual, intellectual, and physical
realms based upon traditional Native beliefs
that link past and present into one coherent
vision. Contrasting the loud and often
violent dominant culture with the voices of
her ancestors, Hogan argues that chaos, violence,
and greed have silenced the wisdom of
the land, yet she seeks to lessen this alienation.
The long "distances" she often evokes are the
space of the Plains as well as the landscape of
lost time and space.

In Hogan's work, women learn from experience
that destruction of parts leads to destruction
of the whole. She documents a history
of extinction and the imposition of a
philosophy without reverence or a sense of the
future. Harshly rewriting the myths of Plains
settlement, she nonetheless holds out hope for
healing and rebirth, seeking new stories and
habits that nurture the creative power of this
region. There is hope, she says, in the land, the
water, and those that listen.


Mark Vogel
Appalachian State University




Hogan, Linda. Dwellings: Reflections on the Natural World.
New York: W. W. Norton, 1995. Scholer, Bo. "A Heart
Made out of Crickets: An Interview with Linda Hogan."
Journal of Ethnic Studies 16 (1988): 107–17.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>