<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.sr.052</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Storm Chasing</field>
      <field name="author">Biddle, Matthew D.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




STORM CHASING

The attempt to intercept supercell thunderstorms
and tornadoes from as close a distance
as possible is known as storm chasing. The
prevalence of flat terrain and a scarcity of trees
combine with a climatology rich in spectacular
and violent weather to make the Great
Plains the optimal arena for storm chasing.
Each spring, people from all corners of the
country and beyond visit "Tornado Alley," an
area of the Great Plains stretching from North
Texas to Nebraska that is the breeding ground
of more tornadoes per area than anywhere in
the world, to storm chase. In addition to meteorological
researchers, amateur weather enthusiasts,
photographers, and videographers
chase storms as a hobby, and emergency management
"storm spotters" and television news
crews chase to provide early warnings to the
public.

Storm chasing was formally begun by a
handful of scientists at the National Severe
Storms Laboratory (NSSL) in Norman, Oklahoma,
in the mid-1970s to obtain ground
truth information in support of the development
of weather radar. Storm chasing is extremely
hazardous, especially when attempted
by those without adequate meteorological
training and experience, but the recent swell
of attention given the endeavor by the media
and the popularity of the Hollywood movie
Twister (1996) have led to its dramatic increase
as a recreational pursuit. Nationally televised
programs regularly take viewers on virtual
chases by following research teams and other
chasers around the Plains each storm season.
Storm-chasing tour companies now take vanloads
of paying storm tourists on weeklong
voyages in search of storms. Customers come
from all backgrounds, and "chase vacations"
in the Great Plains have become popular with
weather enthusiasts from as far away as Europe
and Japan.

Large-scale, research-oriented storm intercept
projects also became more numerous in the
late 1990s as meteorologists sought to improve
warning technologies and understand tornado
genesis. Field intercept projects of note include
the Verification of the Origins of Rotation in
Tornadoes Experiment (VORTEX), an ongoing
multimillion-dollar research project begun in
1994 and headquartered at NSSL. VORTEX utilizes
four to ten vehicles equipped with Mobile
Mesonets, an array of sensors mounted on car
tops that measure and record weather data very
near and around tornadoes. Mobile weather
balloon units, video and photogrammetry
crews, and radar-equipped "hurricane hunter"
aircraft are sometimes used.

Despite their relative frequency on the
Plains, tornadoes are still rare events. Even the
most experienced and schooled chasers face
poor odds of success. Forecasts must be made
hours before a tornado touches down, and it is
common for chases to cover more than 1,000
miles in a day to and from a "target area." An
intercept rate of one tornado witnessed per ten
chases is considered a respectable average. In
spite of these odds, scientific storm chasing has
resulted in the collection of valuable weather
data. The success of such field research operations
coupled with the high profile storm chasing
has gained from media coverage of recent
tornado events such as the 1999 Oklahoma
City outbreak has stirred widespread fascination
with violent weather and made storm
chasing an activity likely to remain part of
Great Plains science and recreation.

See also FOLKWAYS: Tornado Stories / PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT: Tornadoes.


Matthew D. Biddle
University of Oklahoma




Bedard, Richard. In the Shadow of the Tornado. Norman
OK: Gilco Publishing, 1996. Bluestein, Howard. Tornado
Alley: Monster Storms of the Plains. New York: Oxford
University Press, 1999.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>