<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.083</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Tribal Governments, Contemporary</field>
      <field name="author">Haines, Roberta</field>
      <field name="text">

 




TRIBAL GOVERNMENTS, CONTEMPORARY

One of the most interesting questions that can
be asked about contemporary tribal government
is, what is its source of authority and
power? Unlike the federal government or any
state governments, tribal governments in the
United States do not have their foundations
in the U.S. Constitution. Indigenous North
American peoples had sociopolitical organizations
that preceded the federal constitutions of
both Canada and the United States and were
not part of the people or political units that
created these federal systems. Treaties in both
nation-states provide one source for the ongoing
relationships between these nation-states
and the Indigenous governments, but these are
not the only sources. Executive orders, national
legislation, and court cases set further
parameters on the interactions of Indigenous
peoples with dominant states in North America;
however, these are not the sources of tribal
authority.

Current research from several directions in
the United States and Canada concludes that
the most successful tribal development occurs
where traditional structures match the contemporary
ones. This notion is intuitively satisfying,
but it contradicts the historical policy
behind the major pieces of legislation affecting
the structure of tribal government in the
twentieth century. The Indian Reorganization
Act of 1934 (IRA) created a centralized corporate
model for tribal governments, assuming
that traditional systems were inadequate to
the demands of modern society. Similarly, the
Indian Act in Canada (1876) created band
councils. Decision making and development
under these model governments has been uneven
at best.

One successful fusion of traditional and
contemporary governments is the Cheyennes'.
Their prophet, Sweet Medicine, gave the Cheyennes
their code of sacred laws, including organization
of the council of forty-four chiefs
for the ten bands of Cheyennes. The council
consulted with warrior societies before making
its political decisions. While contemporary
Northern Cheyenne government is organized
under the ira, traditional values maintain a
strong influence. Tribal government is represented
at the annual ceremonies, and ceremonial leaders receive tribal grants and, in
some cases, a salary. This has the added benefit
of continuity in the formal network between
the Northern Cheyennes of Montana and the
Southern Cheyennes of Oklahoma. Additionally,
while the ira model centralizes decision
making, the Northern Cheyennes use a referendum
to allow the community a voice on
major decisions.

In a different configuration, the basic political
unit for the nomadic Lakota (Sioux) was
groups of families, or tiyospayes, each governed
by a wicasitancan, or chief. Through the
leaders of fraternal societies the local unit became
part of the band, then part of the larger
Lakota Nation. A signal value for the Lakota
was autonomy, and the critical level of allegiance
was local, to the tiyospaye. Their political
structure was designed to maximize and
encourage this autonomy. In 1889 the United
States forced the Sioux Nation to accept six
separate reservations: Cheyenne River, Crow
Creek, Lower Brulé, Pine Ridge, Rosebud, and
Standing Rock. Those contemporary Lakota
governments, later organized under the ira,
emphasize tribal councils, centralized authorities
with few mechanisms to include the community
or traditional leadership in the decision-
making process. Government decisions
at the Rosebud and Pine Ridge Reservations
have been undermined by local and kinshipbased
allegiances, as would be expected when
the formal governing systems are seen as illegitimate
by many in the community.

The influence of tribal values in tribal political
approaches at the end of the twentieth century
is illustrated in a contemporary interpretation
of Treaty Number 7 as considered from the
position of the Blackfoot Confederacy of southern
Alberta. In the treaty the Blackfeet, Bloods,
and other signatories promise to "maintain
peace and good order." The clause broadly requires
order between and among Indigenous
people and with other Crown subjects at the
time of the treaty (1877) and in the future. Such
an agreement, it is argued, requires or implies
the authority and power to implement the
treaty terms by the Native nations. One avenue
is to participate with the federal and provincial
governments through guaranteed representation
or comanagement.

Despite the amount of influence or interference
from the United States and Canada
and their efforts to transform, and even terminate,
tribal polities, tribal governments persist.
Even Indigenous nations that were forced
to relocate several times, or those whose governments
were repeatedly dissolved by external
forces and whose populations were scattered,
seem to find the most success when they
draw their source of legitimate authority and
power today from historic or traditional
structures.

See also NATIVE AMERICANS: Blackfoot; Cheyennes; Sioux.


Roberta Haines
University of California, Los Angeles




Champagne, Duane. American Indian Societies: Strategies
and Condition of Political and Cultural Survival. Cultural
Survival Report 32. Cambridge MA: Cultural Survival, Inc.,
1989. Cornell, Stephen, and Joseph P. Kalt. What Can Tribes
Do? Strategies and Institutions in American Indian Economic
Development. Los Angeles: American Indian Studies
Center, 1992. Ladner, Kiera L. "Treaty Seven and Guaranteed
Representation: How Treaty Rights Can Evolve into
Parliamentary Seats." Great Plains Quarterly 17 (1997): 85–101.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>