<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.arc.013</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Czech Architecture</field>
      <field name="author">Murphy, David</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CZECH ARCHITECTURE

Ethnic Czechs from the historic provinces of
Bohemia and Moravia brought diverse architectural
traditions to the Great Plains. They
were part of a general emigration that began
after the Peasant Uprising of 1848 and surged
after emigration became legal in 1867. Czechs
on the Plains clustered in large settlements in
southeastern and south-central South Dakota,
north-central and northwestern Kansas, and
all over Nebraska. Later settlements were
established in central and north-central Oklahoma.
The diversity of their architectural tradition
resulted from many factors but primarily
from the dominance of the emigration
by small farmers and cottagers with their varied
provincial cultures.

An ancient preference for log construction
was transferred to the Plains by skilled Czech
carpenters. Log dwellings(rouben)were
characterized by wall beams planked on the
inside and outside faces, then set with full
dovetail notches and chink spaces between the
beams. Interior log partitions were dovetailed
through the exterior walls, and many structures
utilized mortised vertical timbers for
door and window jambs. Several incorporated
the old common rafter roof with tie beams,
while most adopted the simple American rafter
roof secured to the wall plates. Outbuildings
were often built in the same fashion,
though for these other variants also occurred,
such as saddle, V, and full dovetail corner timbering
on unplanked beams.

Some Moravians built earthen walls for
their dwellings(rouben). The most common
technique utilized unfired clay brick, but
puddled clay and rammed earth were not uncommon.
As Czechs adopted light frame construction,
brick, puddled-clay, and lime mortars
were used as nogging between the studs
for stability and thermal mass. Other masonry
construction was utilized by Czechs from both
provinces. Skilled masons commonly employed
rubble, coursed rubble, and occasionally
ashlar work for limestone walls. High
Plains Czechs in Kansas built with sod.

Though considerable provincial variation
in house type existed in the way of room size,
configuration, and nomenclature, the distinctive
Czech tradition is evident as variations on
the quintessential Czech house (Stredocesk), a type common in the heart of Bohemia.
Its tripartite arrangement was comprised of a main room or hall
(tnice), a narrow central entrance chamber
and fire room, and a small storage
chamber (komora). In old times it was
subdivided to provide for a kitchen (cern)(kuchyn) at the back, but on the Plains that
practice was abandoned with the adoption of
American cast-iron stoves. The Pechan house
in Yankton County, South Dakota, is the only
tripartite dwelling known to have subdivided
a kitchen in this manner.

Numerous first-generation houses were
built as single-room dwellings comprised exclusively
of the svetnice; these often became
the basis for an expanded house. Two-room
variations (dvojd) were the most
popular, with both an old type and a new American type
(komora) being built in large
numbers. The latter type simply eliminated
the technologically redundant and moved
the single threshold to the big room. This
dwelling was similar to another ancient type
that included doors into both rooms. Derived
from the house with attached stall, on the
Plains the smaller space of this double-door
type took the role of principal room.

In most Czech lands, houses were oriented
with their narrow gable ends facing the public
street. Typically symmetrical, this gabled facade
continued to be built as the "front"
wall in North America. If decoration was present
at all, it was focused on this gable. On
the Plains, where farms were dispersed rather
than tightly clustered into rural villages, the
front gable was often reoriented to the rear,
where it faced the farmyard. Thresholds were
in the side of the house, also oriented toward
the farmyard or toward a small courtyard if in
an urban setting.

The old practice of attaching farm buildings
to the house and creating single-unit
courtyard farmsteads was abandoned on the
Plains, where land seemed limitless. Following
American practices, farm buildings were built
as detached structures, though often these
were initially modeled along traditional lines;
separate stables, cowsheds, and hay barns
were built instead of the single multifunctional
American barn. The first "barn" in Valley
County, Nebraska, was a traditional threestall
stable with walls raised half a story in
height to accommodate a diminutive hayloft.
Other remnant examples of the old practices
exist, such as the Veselhouse with its attached
cowshed in Knox County, Nebraska,
and the long Merkwan "barn" in Bon Homme
County, South Dakota, with its linearly attached
storeroom, cowshed, and stables.

Early modernized houses retained traditional
characteristics while becoming modestly
enlarged. Most common was the one-and-
one-half-story cross-wing house (uhlov), which provided bedrooms in the loft
and a kitchen, parlor, and chamber (storage
room, often with a bed) on the first floor. Typically,
this house was still built with a single
threshold, now into the kitchen, the new principal
room of the modern dwelling. By the
early twentieth century other houses were
copied from American models, though interiors
often continued to accommodate traditional
living practices by emphasizing kitchens
and dining rooms as principal spaces.
These houses also continued to be built with
facades facing the farmyard.

Also distinctive was the public landscape
created by the ideologically diverse Czechs,
who included freethinkers, Catholics, and
Protestants. Old animosities among these
groups produced separate cemeteries, which
served symbolic, ceremonial, and even nationalistic
functions. A fourth kind, a community
cemetery with a more inclusive intent (Cesko-
Slovansk hrbitov), initiated efforts at ethnic
cohesiveness. Many of the cemeteries, particularly
the national cemeteries of the freethinkers
(Cesko-Nrodni hrbitov), were distinctly
designed and landscaped, while others also exhibited
homeland features such as curbed
and planted graves, cast- and wrought-iron
crosses, and Hussite iconography. Elaborately
crafted iron entrance gates were typical.

While church architecture was primarily
denominationally derived, freethinking and
Sokol (gymnastic society) halls often followed
popular Czech styles. The most distinctive of
these were latter-day American versions of the
provincial baroque style (venkovské barok)
that had become popular in the Czech agricultural
villages after enclosure. The overt nationalistic
associations of these designs on the
Plains were in direct contrast to the Renaissance
Revival of the elite national movement
in Bohemia, where the baroque carried negative
associations with the Counter Reformation.
Many variations on the baroque were
built, from the simple lunette fronts of halls
such as Sladkovsk at Pishelville (1882), to the
modeled facade and doubly curved dormer of
the 1903 Hora hall at Verdigre, both in
Nebraska.

Built following the multifunctional model
of the vernacular opera house (albeit in a distinctly
noncommercial mode), the public
halls of Sokols and Czech fraternal organizations
served a variety of community needs,
including dances, speeches, funerals, gymnastics,
and banquets. Most contained full stage
facilities for the popular Czech national theatrical
performances. These interiors focused
on a proscenium arch with its locally painted
curtains, which usually portrayed Czech landscapes
and symbolic scenes. Few new halls
have been built since the 1880–1920 period,
but most of those extant are still in use.

See also EUROPEAN AMERICANS: Czechs.


David Murphy
Nebraska State Historical Society




Frolec, Václav, and Josef Vaeka. Encyclopedie lidová architektura.
Praha: SNTL—Nakladatelství technické literatury,
and ALFA—Vydavatel'stvo technickej a ekonomickej literatúry,
1983. Murphy, David. "Dramatic Expressions:
Czech Theatre Curtains in Nebraska." Nebraska History 74
(1993): 168–82. Murphy, David. "Jejich Antonie: Czechs,
the Land, Cather, and the Pavelka Farmstead." Great Plains Quarterly 14 (1994): 85–106.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>