<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.032</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Kroetsch, Robert (b. 1927)</field>
      <field name="author">Neuman, Shirley</field>
      <field name="text">

 




KROETSCH, ROBERT (b. 1927)

Robert Kroetsch, novelist, poet, essayist, and
teacher, was born on June 26, 1927, in Heisler,
Alberta. He received degrees in English from
the University of Alberta, Middlebury College,
and the University of Iowa. After teaching at the
State University of New York–Binghamton, he
returned in 1978 to Canada and the University
of Manitoba. He has served as writer in residence
at many universities and is a frequent
and popular teacher of creative writing at
the Banff Centre in Alberta. Kroetsch sets his
writing in and comments directly upon the
Great Plains, particularly, central and southern
Alberta.

Growing up on a farm in central Alberta,
Kroetsch gained an ear for storytelling from
the political speeches of his uncles, the family
histories of his aunts, the pulp fiction favored
by the hired men, and the all-encompassing
cosmology of the Bible. His university training
emphasized the European.North American
literary canon, and Kroetsch himself sought
out the trickster and shaman stories of the Cree
and Blackfoot peoples who had lived in Alberta
for millennia. His fiction combines finely
observed details of the places and people of the
Great Plains with a postmodern sensibility that
disrupts chronology and cause and effect. His
narratives are filled with a virtuosic bawdiness.
For instance, The Studhorse Man (1969), for
which he won the Governor General's Award,
follows the odyssey of trickster and phallic acrobat
Hazard Lepage as he leads his great blue
stallion around post-World War II Alberta in
search of mares in heat. Other novels dealing
with the Great Plains include Words of My Roaring (1966), a parody of the 1935 Alberta
election; Gone Indian (1973); Badlands (1975), a
retelling of the great dinosaur hunts along Alberta's
Red Deer River; and What the Crow Said (1978). Kroetsch has also produced a relatively
small number of short stories and creative
nonfiction essays about the Prairies.

Like his fiction, Kroetsch's poetry accommodates
and parodies world influences as well
as Prairie narratives. In Seed Catalogue (1977)
he asks,


How do you grow a prairie town?
The gopher was the model.
Stand up straight:
telephone poles
grain elevators
church steeples.
Vanish, suddenly: the
gopher was the model.


Later, in The Hornbooks of Rita K (2001), he
writes, more cryptically,


Rita was accustomed to the deceptive
	randomness of
wind and rain and sky, to the violence and
	the blinding
inevitability of prairie sun. She had an
	aversion to
intentional space.


Kroetsch's Alberta (1968) is a memoir of
place that sets up in a nonfictional genre some
of the same themes that appear in his fiction.
His essay collection The Lovely Treachery of Words (1989) both explores the work of other
Prairie writers and sets forth some of the theory
underlying his own work, while the autobiographical
essays in A Likely Story (1995)
further explicate his life and craft. Perhaps
Kroetsch best explained his aims–and his
achievements–in a 1981 interview in which he
said that his fiction and poetry "work out
new relationships" between men and women
as they develop in the new urban centers of
the West. Because the Prairies were wiped out,
"right down to zero," during the Great Depression,
"we started to invent a new concept
of self and a new concept of society. Now
I'm intrigued to watch that developing in the
Prairies."


Frances W. Kaye
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Lecker, Robert. Robert Kroetsch. Boston: Twayne, 1986.
Neuman, Shirley, and Robert Wilson, eds. Labyrinths of Voice: Conversations with Robert Kroetsch. Edmonton:
NeWest Press, 1982. Twigg, Alan. "Robert Kroetsch: Male."
In For Openers: Conversations with 24 Canadian Writers.
Madeira Park, British Columbia: Harbour Publishing,
1981, 107–16.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>