<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pe.025</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Fire Ecology</field>
      <field name="author">Bragg, Thomas B.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




FIRE ECOLOGY

Historically, fire was a ubiquitous component
of the Great Plains environment, interacting
with other components, such as bison whose
grazing patterns resulted in uneven fuel distribution
and therefore in diverse fire effects.
The frequency of historic fires varied throughout
the Great Plains, from every two to three
years in the eastern tallgrass prairies, to three
to four years in the Nebraska Sandhills, six to
twenty-five years in mesic-to-xeric northern
mixed-grass prairies, and five to ten years in
the western shortgrass prairies and desert
grasslands.

Fire effects vary with frequency, season-ofoccurrence,
and location. Generally repeated
fires in any season affect diversity by favoring
grasses over forbs. Dormant-season fires remove
litter and thus may both encourage undesirable
plants, such as smooth brome (Bromus
inermis), sweet clover (Melilotus spp.),
and Kentucky bluegrass (Poa pratensis), and
expose soil to surface erosion. However, dormant-
season fires have less of an effect on
ground-nesting birds and invertebrates. Latespring
fires, the season of most eastern grassland
prescribed burning, favor the dominant,
warm-season species such as big bluestem (Andropogon
gerardii) over cool-season species
like Kentucky bluegrass, but they often have a
major impact on the invertebrate community.
Summer (growing-season) fires, which historically
occurred most frequently but were smallest
in size, reduce plant diversity by favoring
grasses over forbs. These fires are less likely to
affect invertebrates or ground-nesting birds and
are most successful in top-killing woody plants
that invade and degrade unburned prairies.

Individual species, however, do not all respond
similarly to fire. Thus maintaining a
diverse fire regime, interactive with other
ecosystem-level components such as grazing,
is essential to the long-term, ecological diversity
and dynamics of Great Plains grasslands.


Thomas B. Bragg
University of Nebraska at Omaha




Bragg, Thomas B. "Climate, Soils and Fire: The Physical
Environment of North American Grasslands." In The
Changing Prairie, edited by Kathleen H. Keeler and Anthony
Joern. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1995: 49–
81. Bragg, Thomas B., and Lloyd C. Hulbert. "Woody
Plant Invasion of Unburned Kansas Bluestem Prairie."
Journal of Range Management 29 (1976): 19–24.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>