<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ind.018</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Ethanol</field>
      <field name="author">Checkel, M. David</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ETHANOL

Ethyl alcohol (or ethanol, grain alcohol, or
C2H5OH) is a colorless, sweet-smelling substance.
Ethanol production in the form of intoxicating
beverages was one of humankind's
earliest industrial achievements. Beyond being
the key ingredient in alcoholic drinks, ethanol
is a solvent and has a growing role as a
renewable-source fuel for motor vehicles.

Ethanol can be made synthetically by catalytic
reaction of ethylene (from natural gas)
with steam. However, most ethanol is made by
fermentation of plant material. In fermentation,
single-celled yeast organisms consume
simple sugars, excreting ethyl alcohol and carbon
dioxide. Plants are composed of carbohydrates
(compounds containing carbon, hydrogen,
and oxygen), and the simple sugars (called
monosaccharides) are building blocks for
complex carbohydrates like starches, higher
sugars, and cellulose. Fruits tend to be rich in
sugar, and grains are rich in starch, while straw
and wood are dominated by cellulose. Only the
monosaccharide sugars are directly fermentable,
so natural fermentation requires a sugarrich
fruit (like grapes) for significant alcohol
content. To make ethanol from other biomass
sources, higher-order plant structures must be
broken down to monosaccharides. Specialized
enzymes or weak acids are used to break starch
and cellulose into monosaccharides before fermentation.
After fermentation, the resulting
"beer" solution contains a small percentage of
ethanol. Solids are filtered out for use as animal
feed or fuel, and ethanol is separated from the
remaining water by distillation and mole sieve
techniques. Ethanol processes are well established
for grain feed stocks, and research is
improving ethanol yield and energy e.ciency.
New processes and enzymes are being developed
to enable commercial production from
cellulosic materials such as grass, straw, and
wood.

Fuel ethanol is denatured by blending it
with 5 percent gasoline or solvent to render it
undrinkable. The denatured product is then
blended with petroleum-based gasoline as a
high-octane fuel component. American gasoline
contains up to 10 percent ethanol, especially
in winter months and in areas with serious
air pollution. e85 (gasoline with 85
percent ethanol) is used in specially adapted or
"flex-fuel" vehicles. The 15 percent hydrocarbon
content in e85 is tailored to optimize fuel
volatility and inhibit corrosion.

In 2000 American ethanol production was
1.8 billion U.S. gallons with roughly equal
amounts used for fuel and for all other purposes.
About 7 percent was synthetic, and the
rest was the result of fermentation. Of the fermentation
ethanol, 90 percent used corn as a
feedstock, with the dominant production in
Corn Belt states (Illinois, Iowa, Nebraska, and
Minnesota). Overall, the Great Plains states
supplied 23 percent of American fermentation
ethanol. Canadian ethanol production in 2000
was in excess of 160 million U.S. gallons, with
75 percent from Ontario corn and 5 percent
from forest products. The remaining 29 percent
came from wheat, the dominant grain
crop in the Prairie Provinces. Raw grain is
bulky and expensive to transport, so most ethanol
production plants are located in areas of
high grain production or along major transportation
routes. In 2000 there were two ethanol
production plants in the Prairie Provinces–
at Lanigan, Saskatchewan, and Red
Deer, Alberta–and nineteen such plants in the
American Great Plains, with Nebraska, the
leading state, with seven.

Concerns over air pollution, petroleum
supply, and greenhouse gas emissions are leading
to increased production of biologically
based ethanol. Currently, this is raising demand
for grain, a major product of fertile
lands in the Great Plains region. Future growth
of the fuel market and commercialization of
cellulose-based ethanol processes are expected
to create a demand for cellulosic crops such as
switch grass, straw, and poplar wood. These
crops grow well on less fertile lands, so their
production would provide an alternative industry
in Plains areas currently dominated by
livestock.


M. David Checkel
University of Alberta





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>