<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.law.006</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Bean, Judge Roy (c. 1825-1903)</field>
      <field name="author">Ward, Derrick S.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BEAN, JUDGE ROY (c. 1825-1903)

Judge Roy Bean, the legendary "Law West of
the Pecos," operated a combination courthouse-
saloon on the West Texas frontier near
the junction of the Pecos River and the Rio
Grande for more than twenty years. Bean was
one of the most colorful, individualistic, and
controversial personalities on the Great Plains.
In terms of his place in American folklore,
Bean has been compared to Davy Crockett,
Mike Fink, and Paul Bunyan.

Roy Bean was born sometime between 1825
and 1830 in Mason County, Kentucky, to
Francis and Anna Bean. At about the age of
sixteen, Roy is said to have traveled to New
Orleans, where, after alleged complicity in a
major French Quarter brawl, he fled the Crescent
City to avoid possible legal and extralegal
repercussions. Later in his youth Bean reportedly
helped run a saloon–trading post with
his brother Samuel in Chihuahua, Mexico.
There he killed a machete-wielding desperado
who attempted to rob the saloon, and Bean
once again found himself on the run when the
outlaw's friends and relatives vowed revenge.
He wound up in southern California sometime
in 1850.

The accounts of Roy Bean's exploits in California
are deeply imbedded in the state's
folklore and early history. They reflect the romanticism
of Old California and attempt to
portray Bean as a bona fide folk hero, some
kind of King Arthur-meets-Mike Fink figure.
He is said to have fought a duel on horseback
over the affections of the local young ladies of
San Diego. After winning the contest and
being jailed for dueling, Bean escaped, digging
his way out with tools smuggled to him in
tamales prepared by sympathetic local girls.
Next, Roy Bean and his brother Joshua ran the
Headquarters Saloon in San Gabriel, nine
miles outside of Los Angeles, until 1852, when
Joshua was murdered, allegedly by members
of the Joaquin Murrieta gang. After leaving
California in the mid-1850s, Bean married,
had children, plied numerous trades, and became
an embargo runner for the Confederacy
on the Texas border during the Civil War.

The legend of Judge Roy Bean developed
across the desolate regions of southwestern
Texas in 1882, when he was nearly sixty. A
shrewd businessman, Bean capitalized on the
construction of the Southern Pacific Railroad
by establishing a saloon-courthouse at a settlement
called Vinegarroon and later at nearby
Langtry. Contrary to popular belief, Bean
was an authorized justice of the peace with the
full power of the law and often a detachment
of Texas Rangers to enforce his authority. He
was supported by and served the interests of
both the government and the wealthy ranch
owners who sought increased law and order.
Using the 1879 Revised Statutes of Texas as his
legal guide, Judge Roy Bean performed marriages,
held inquests, granted divorces, and
tried horse thieves, drunks, and killers for two
decades.

The true history of Judge Roy Bean is so
intertwined with myth, legend, and folklore
that it is difficult to separate fact from fiction.
Some of the tales are memorable indeed: Bean
fining a corpse $40 for "carrying a concealed
weapon"; the large beer-drinking black bear
that patrolled his courthouse-saloon and slept
at the foot of his bed; his infatuation with the
British actress Lily Langtry. (His saloon the
Jersey Lily was named for her, but he lied
when he wrote her that the town of Langtry,
Texas, was named in her honor.) Judge Roy
Bean died peacefully in his saloon from "excess
of liquor" on March 19, 1903, and was
buried at Del Rio, Texas. For better or worse,
Judge Roy Bean has become an American folk
hero, coming to symbolize the independent,
strong, pragmatic, rugged frontier individual,
able to stand up against the coarser natural
and human elements and prevail.


Derrick S. Ward
Ventura, California




Lloyd, Everett. Law West of the Pecos: The Story of Judge Roy Bean, the Original Manuscript. San Antonio: Naylor
Company, 1936. McDaniel, Ruel. Vinegarroon: The Saga of Judge Roy Bean, the Law West of the Pecos. Kingsport TN:
Southern Publishers, 1936. Sonnichsen, C. L. Roy Bean: Law West of the Pecos. Lincoln: University of Nebraska
Press, 1986.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>