<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pd.021</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Finley, Ira (1886-1981)</field>
      <field name="author">Sellars, Nigel Anthony</field>
      <field name="text">

 




FINLEY, IRA (1886-1981)

Oklahoma socialist and labor leader Ira Monroe
Finley twice served in the state legislature
and began one of the first organizations
for the rights of the unemployed, the Veterans
of Industry of America, during the Great
Depression.

Born in Missouri on December 7, 1886, to
Irish immigrant parents, Finley grew up in
rural Arkansas and Texas. His father had been
a successful farmer in Missouri, but the farm
in Texas failed. After his father's death, Finley
restored the family's fortunes, only to be
ruined by the Panic of 1907.

The twenty-year-old Finley then moved to
Oklahoma, where he engaged in sharecropping
and construction work on the Missouri,
Kansas, and Texas Railroad. After being laid
off the railroad job, Finley became a socialist
and soon involved himself in both the Oklahoma
Socialist Party and the Oklahoma State
Federation of Labor (OSFL). By 1917 he began
organizing Oklahoma locals of the United
Brotherhood of Railroad Maintenance of the
Way Employees. Finley proved so effective that
he received an offer from the union's national
headquarters to serve as a full-time organizer.

Elected to the state legislature in 1922 as a
Democrat and part of the Farmer-Labor Reconstruction
League (FLRL) campaign, Finley
grew disenchanted with the flrl's newly
elected governor, John C. Walton, and voted
to impeach him in November 1923. This was
an act of courage on Finley's part, as the OSFL,
which elected Finley president in June 1923,
had originally organized the flrl and was
dominated by ardent Walton supporters. His
actions cost Finley the OSFL's top post in 1925.

He moved to Oklahoma City in the late
1920s and became prosperous in the road machinery
sales and real estate businesses. But
Finley's interest in politics and public service
never died, and in 1930 he won the state House
seat for Oklahoma City's Capital Hill district.
William H. "Alfalfa Bill" Murray, elected governor
in 1930, soon asked Finley to serve as
director of Oklahoma's relief efforts. Finley
modestly declined, suggesting instead that
Murray select Dr. Charles Evans, former president
of Oklahoma Normal School (now the
University of Central Oklahoma). Murray
agreed, on condition Evans seek Finley's advice
and Finley direct relief efforts in Oklahoma
County. Finley accepted.

During his tenure, Finley came to believe
that a "Share the Work" program to redistribute
wealth, enforced by state or federal
law, was the only effective means to deal with
the Depression. Finley shared this idea with
other county relief directors, and the men established
the Veterans of Industry of America
(VIA) on September 28, 1932.

Finley personally rented the new organization's
offices and paid for them out of his own
pocket. VIA's first efforts involved lobbying for
a state law that would tax businesses that made
their employees work more than thirty hours a
week. Finley also worked to set up local chapters
throughout Oklahoma. By October 1933
VIA claimed 40,000 members, mostly unemployed
workers and displaced farmers, but also
casual workers and even some small businessmen.
Separate locals for blacks existed in eastern
Oklahoma. All the members carried blue
membership cards inscribed with the VIA slogan
written by Finley: "Poverty must be wiped
out. No nation can call itself Christian or civilized
that permits babes, little children and the
aged to suffer for food, clothes and shelter."

VIA became an effective pressure group for
the unemployed in Oklahoma. It proved especially
effective along the Arkansas border,
where small farmers and tenants joined VIA
boycotts of "slave wage" agricultural employers.
VIA members also joined picket lines to
help striking union members and worked to
discourage the unemployed from becoming
strikebreakers.

The Veterans of Industry of America declined
during World War II as defense industries
created new jobs and reduced the number
of unemployed. Finley, however, continued his
involvement with Oklahoma labor and Democratic
Party affairs until his death on May 4,
1981.


Nigel Anthony Sellars
Christopher Newton University




Green, James R. Grass-Roots Socialism: Radical Movements
in the Southwest, 1895–1943. Baton Rouge: Louisiana State
University Press, 1978. McGinnis, Patrick E. Oklahoma's
Depression Radicals: Ira M. Finley and the Veterans of Industry
of America. New York: Peter Lang Publishing, 1991.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>