<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.mus.043</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Teagarden, Jack (1905-1964)</field>
      <field name="author">Anderson, Scott L.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




TEAGARDEN, JACK (1905-1964)

Musician Jack Teagarden
    
    

Weldon Leo "Jack" Teagarden was one of the
most influential jazz trombonists of the early
twentieth century. His playing was among the
first examples of individual style in the genre
of jazz trombone. He was also a fine vocalist.
He has inspired many performers, from jazz
trombonists to the concert trombone soloist
Christian Lindberg.

Teagarden was born in the Texas Panhandle
town of Vernon on August 29, 1905. After his
father died in the 1918 flu epidemic, the family
briefly moved to Chappell, Nebraska, then
headed back south to Oklahoma City. His
family was poor, but there was always music:
Teagarden was playing the piano at the age of
five and the baritone horn by the time he was
seven; by age ten he had taken up the trombone.
He started playing professionally (in
San Antonio) when he was fourteen. His musical
influences were varied, but it is obvious
from his playing that he took a great deal from
black music, especially the blues. Teagarden's
recording career began when he was twentytwo
years old with a session for Johnny Johnson
and his Statler Pennsylvanians. He took
part in the first mixed-race recording session
when he recorded "Knockin' a Jug" with Louis
Armstrong in 1929. Teagarden performed
with many of the other jazz greats of his era,
including Benny Goodman, Red Nichols, Paul
Whiteman, and Eddie Condon. From 1928 to
1933 a great deal of Teagarden's work was as a
musical sideman, including with Ben Pollack's
band, but he also had his own band for a time.
This period produced some of Teagarden's
most distinctive and best-known recordings,
including "Someone Stole Gabriel's Horn"
(1933).

Teagarden led his own band full time from
1939 to 1947, recording (on Decca after 1941)
good music but making no money. After his
band broke up, Teagarden played with the Louis
Armstrong All Stars until 1951, when he formed
his own All Star orchestra and achieved considerable
success playing Dixieland jazz. Teagarden
continued to perform until his death in New
Orleans in 1964. He was inducted into the Jazz
Hall of Fame in 1996.


Scott L. Anderson
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Schuller, Gunther. The Swing Era: The Development of Jazz 1930–1945. New York: Oxford University Press, 1989.
Smith, Jay D., and Len Guttridge. Jack Teagarden: The Story of a Jazz Maverick. New York: Da Capo Press, 1976.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>