<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.mus.018</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Frontier Opera Houses</field>
      <field name="author">Ehlers, D. Layne</field>
      <field name="text">

 




Frontier opera houses (Lodgepole, Nebraska, Opera House, built in 1911, closed in the late 1940s)




FRONTIER OPERA HOUSES

Frontier communities regarded opera houses
as visual symbols of prosperity–ence, promise,
and culture. Though more properly "opera
hall," the name "opera house" suggested refinement
and elegance to local residents, so
it prevailed. The opera house heyday lasted
from about ten years after a town's founding
until approximately 1917. Often on the second
floor of the town's first brick building, opera
houses contained an open space large enough
for a significant portion of the community to
congregate. All contained stages, some had
permanent seating, but most consisted of a
large room that could be arranged in a variety
of configurations depending on need–dances,
political meetings, banquets, basketball games,
concerts, home talent shows, or professional
entertainment.

Opera houses represented all types of vernacular
Main Street architecture from the
early two-part commercial block second-floor
theaters to the one-part community auditorium models favored in the early twentieth
century. These theaters functioned as the
heart of frontier society, gathering places
where folks could celebrate life and escape its
daily rigors. Originally owned and managed
by a civic-spirited merchant, they eventually
passed into public ownership.

The opera house "season" lasted from late
fall to early spring, beginning after the crops
were in and lasting as long as the rutted roads
remained frozen to accommodate evening
travel. Frequent dances provided income for
fire departments, dancing schools, lodges,
bands, commercial clubs, and ball teams.
Home talent performances by cornet bands,
community instrumentalists, choral unions,
local music students, and college or church
choirs always earned high praise from local
newspaper editors.

Several times each season, an opera house
manager contracted for professional entertainment,
often through a lyceum bureau
booking agency. Unable to accommodate the
more pricey offerings of combination companies
booked out of New York, most Plains
communities settled for concerts or other entertainments
by smaller groups such as the
Hallowell Concert Company, complete with
baritone and lady trap-drummer; Round's
Ladies Orchestra; the Schubert Symphony
and Ladies Quartette; the Sue Burgess Concert
Company, featuring contralto, reader, violinist,
and pianist; Blind Boone, a pianist who
drew rowdy crowds; and Mrs. Winters, a melodious
whistler. More exotic musicians included
the Royal Hawaiian Concert Company,
Kulolo's Hawaiians, Vierra's Royal Hawaiians,
Ramos' Spanish Orchestra, Losseff's Russian
Quartet, the Swiss Bell Ringers, and the Chicago
Boys' Choir, which traveled with marambophone,
bagpipes, tambourine, castanets,
and a harp.

Opera houses declined as a performance
venue after 1917 for a variety of reasons related
to twentieth-century technology. Many had
reached the end of their architectural usefulness
and could no longer safely support large
crowds of people; the devastation of the 1903
Iroquois Theatre fire in Chicago, which killed
600 people, made the nation aware of the dangers
of second-floor theaters. Automobiles,
shifts in population, and postwar affluence
meant smaller audiences in small towns. Most
important, motion pictures proved more attractive
to audiences and more cost-effective
to managers than traveling troupes. Plains
towns built no true frontier opera houses after
World War I. Today, small Great Plains towns
use community auditoriums to fill the nonentertainment
functions of the opera house,
while larger cities and television provide the
performance venues.


D. Layne Ehlers
Bacone College




Ehlers, D. Layne. "This Week at the Opera House: Popular
Music Entertainment at Great Plains Opera Houses, 1887–
1917." Great Plains Quarterly 20 (2000): 183–95. Zivanovic,
Judith K., ed. Opera Houses of the Midwest. Manhatten KS:
Mid-America Theatre Conference, 1988.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>