<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.law.053</field>
      <field name="titleMain">White, Byron (1917-2002)</field>
      <field name="author">Hutchinson, Dennis J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




WHITE, BYRON (1917-2002)


University of Colorado football star "The Whizzer" Byron White (right), between 1930 and 1940


Byron Raymond White was born on June 17,
1917, in Fort Collins, Colorado, but grew up in
the nearby sugar beet hamlet of Wellington.
His father ran a lumberyard, and his mother
was a homemaker. Both Byron and his older
brother, Clayton S. (Sam), raised beets and
did odd jobs from an early age to help support
the family. A full-tuition scholarship took Byron
White from this impoverished Plains
background to the University of Colorado,
where he became class president, all-American
in football (second in the 1937 Heisman
Trophy vote), and a Rhodes Scholar. (His
brother had become a Rhodes Scholar four
years earlier.) After a season as the highestpaid
player in the National Football League,
he went to Oxford, but war forced him to
return stateside, where he attended Yale Law
School. Following naval service in the South
Pacific, he returned to Yale, led his class academically,
and then clerked for the chief justice
of the United States.

In 1959 John F. Kennedy, whom White had
met in England and in the navy, enticed him
to help run his impending presidential campaign.
After the election, Kennedy appointed
White deputy attorney general, and White
spent more than a year as the principal administrator
of the Department of Justice, with
special responsibility for staffing and judicial
nominations. He personally went to Alabama
in 1961 to oversee treatment of the Freedom
Riders. When Justice Charles E. Whittaker of
Kansas retired on disability in March 1962,
Kennedy named White to the Court, the only
Colorado native so honored. White spent
three decades on the Court, where he earned a
reputation for brilliance if not eloquence and
for skepticism toward judicial intervention in
social problems unless clearly guided by appropriate
legislation. His best-known opinions
were dissents involving criminal justice
(Miranda v. Arizona), abortion (Roe v. Wade),
and separation of powers (INS v. Chadha).

White retired form the Court in 1993 but
continued to sit on lower federal courts and to
serve the nation in a variety of capacities. He
died in Denver, Colorado, of complications
from pneumonia, on April 15, 2002.


Dennis J. Hutchinson
University of Chicago




Hutchinson, Dennis J. The Man Who Once Was Whizzer White. New York: Free Press, 1998.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>