<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ha.011</field>
      <field name="titleMain">de Baca, Fabiola Cabeza (1898-1933)</field>
      <field name="author">McShane, Becky Jo</field>
      <field name="text">

 




DE BACA, FABIOLA CABEZA (1898-1933)

Fabiola Cabeza de Baca was born on the de
Baca family land grant on the Llano Estacado
in northeastern New Mexico on May 16, 1898.
When she was four years old, de Baca's mother
died and her paternal grandmother, a traditional
Hispana of the patrín (elite) class,
became her primary caregiver. She grew up
speaking Spanish, English, and two Pueblo
dialects–Tewa and Tiwa–fluently.

In 1921 de Baca received a degree in pedagogy
from New Mexico Normal University
and taught in the New Mexico public school
system for several years. In 1929 she received a
degree in home economics from New Mexico
State University in Las Cruces. From 1929 to
1959 she worked as a home demonstration
agent for the New Mexico State Extension Service,
serving the Hispanic and Pueblo villages
of northern New Mexico. There she founded
clubs for women and children, taught nutrition,
and organized marketing of craft products.
In 1939 de Baca married Carlos Gilbert,
an insurance agent.

Throughout her career as a practicing home
economist, de Baca wrote several books and
articles about folkways and culinary traditions
among Hispanos. Her 1939 book Historic Cookery, based on observations in New Mexico
village kitchens, eventually sold more than
100,000 copies. All of her writing furthered her
cause of preserving Hispanic traditions and
correcting American history, which she felt either
neglected New Mexican Hispanos or misrepresented
them.

In 1954 she published We Fed Them Cactus,
her most autobiographical narrative and the
book for which she is best known. The title
refers to an incident that marked the end of an
era for New Mexican Hispanos. Because of
social, economic, and natural conditions–
drought and the influx of American ranchers
and homesteaders in the Plains in the late
nineteenth century–her family was forced to
feed cactus to their cattle. This tragedy calls
attention to the communal bonds of Hispanic
tradition and encourages Hispanos to remember
a better way of life. Ultimately, We Fed Them Cactus imagines an egalitarian society
in which all Hispanos, from empleado (laborer)
to patrín, live in cultural harmony.
Fabiola Cabeza de Baca died in 1993, after
spending her final years in a home for the
elderly in Albuquerque.


Becky Jo McShane
Salt Lake City, Utah




de Baca (Gilbert), Fabiola Cabeza. Historic Cookery. 1939.
Reprint, Las Vegas NM: La Galeria de los Artesanos, 1970.
de Baca, Fabiola Cabeza. We Fed Them Cactus. Albuquerque:
University of New Mexico Press, 1954. Poythress,
Stephanie. "Fabiola Cabeza de Baca Gilbert." In Notable Hispanic American Women, edited by Diane Telgen and
Jim Kamp. Detroit: Gale Research, Inc. 1993: 178–79.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>