<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.047</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Momaday, N. Scott (b. 1934)</field>
      <field name="author">Roemer, Kenneth M.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MOMADAY, N. SCOTT (b. 1934)

N. Scott Momaday


House Made of Dawn (1968), N. Scott Momaday's
Pulitzer Prize–winning novel about a
World War II veteran's experiences at Jemez
Pueblo and in Los Angeles, was a ground-breaking
literary event that attracted widespread
attention to contemporary Native
American writing as well as to much older
written and oral Native American literature.
Since the publication of that novel, Momaday
has written another, The Ancient Child (1989),
and has also gained international recognition
as a poet (The Gourd Dancer, 1976; In the Presence of the Sun: A Gathering of Shields, 1961– 1991, 1992; In the Bear's House, 1999), an autobiographer
and engaging interviewee (The Way to Rainy Mountain, 1969; The Names: A Memoir, 1976; Ancestral Voice, 1989; Conversations with N. Scott Momaday, 1997), an essayist
(The Man Made of Words: Essays, Stories, and Passages, 1997), and a respected artist.

Navarre Scott Momaday was born in Lawton,
Oklahoma, on February 27, 1934. Although
he has lived most of his life away from
his birthplace, southwestern Oklahoma and
other Great Plains landscapes have dominated
much of his best fiction and poetry. In The Ancient Child, some of his most lyric prose
poems capture the majesty and seasonal beauties
of Devil's Tower (Bear Lodge) in Wyoming
and the Wichita Mountains' high meadows
in spring. Several fine poems celebrate
striking aspects of the Plains landscape (the
"prairie fire" of sunrise in "Plainview 3") and
Plains culture (The Gourd Dancer, "Rings of
Bone," and the "Gathering of Shields" prose
poems).

It is in The Way to Rainy Mountain, however,
that Momaday offers his most sustained
and moving testimony to the Great Plains. His
father's people, the Kiowa, undertook a migration
300 years ago that traversed the Great
Plains from the headwaters of the Yellowstone
River to Rainy Mountain in southwestern
Oklahoma and continued in later years with
horseback travels through Texas to Mexico.
For Momaday, the Plains area of southwestern
Oklahoma is "a landscape that is incomparable,"
in part because it grounds and witnesses
a grand paradox for his father's people, "a time
that is gone forever, and the human spirit,
which endures." To capture this landscape in
twenty-four two-page sections, Momaday created
three "angles of vision": storytelling (tribal
narratives and family lore), history-fact, and
personal experience. Together these viewpoints
acknowledge the harshness of the Plains
–blizzards, a summer heat as fierce as "an
anvil's edge," tornadoes powered by a wild
mythical horse–and document the tragedies
of his people: 800 Kiowa horse carcasses rotting
near Fort Sill, thousands of buffalo slaughtered,
many Kiowas killed and taken into captivity.
But in memory, in the present, and in the
sense of sacred play of the three perspectives,
the vitality of the Kiowa Plains endures in a
mountain that "burns and shines" in the "early
sun," in a reverence for the grand wanderings
of great horsemen, and in the joy of seeing a
newborn buffalo that adds life to the returning
buffalo herds. Small wonder that Momaday
can look at the remote knoll that is Rainy
Mountain and see a place "where Creation was
begun."

See also NATIVE AMERICANS: Kiowas.


Kenneth M. Roemer
University of Texas-Arlington




Roemer, Kenneth M., ed. Approaches to Teaching Momaday's "The Way to Rainy Mountain." New York: Modern
Language Association, 1988. Scarberry-Garcia, Susan.
Landmarks of Healing: A Study of "House Made of Dawn."
Albuquerque: University of New Mexico Press, 1990.
Schubnell, Matthias. N. Scott Momaday: The Cultural and Literary Background. Norman: University of Oklahoma
Press, 1985.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>