<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ha.038</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Romero, Casimero (1833-1912)</field>
      <field name="author">Rathjen, Frederick W.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ROMERO, CASIMERO (1833-1912)

Little is known of the early life of Casimero
Romero except that he was of Spanish lineage,
born in 1833 in New Mexico, and that in his
younger years he participated in the comanchero
trade and perhaps was a cibolero as
well. Evidently he prospered, because by the
1870s Romero, then living in Moro County,
was a large-scale sheep rancher. His entrepreneurial
eye turned eastward, however, and led
him to the Texas Panhandle, where he contributed
significantly to the nascent development
of the Southern High Plains.

In November 1876 Romero trailed 3,000
head of sheep to the Canadian River valley to
take advantage of unoccupied, rich, free grasslands.
He built a capacious, sturdy adobe
home and, except for a few staples, produced
or took from the land everything needed to
sustain a good life for his family and workers.
Unwittingly, Romero may have inspired the
first European Americans to migrate into the
Texas Panhandle as residents. Other New
Mexican pastores followed Romero and settled
along the Canadian River, and the town of
Tascosa grew around the Romero plaza.

By the middle 1880s, however, the pastores
found themselves unable to compete with cattle
ranchers who secured land titles which,
backed by barbed wire, enabled them to control
access to grass. The pastores had to find
other livelihoods. While keeping his Tascosa
homestead, Romero turned to a twelve-wagon
freighting business connecting the far-flung
ranchers and the merchants of Tascosa with
their major supply point, Dodge City, Kansas,
thereby contributing in a second way to
Southern High Plains settlement.

Long-haul freighting declined as railroads
crossed the Texas Panhandle and eliminated
the need for Romero's service. Romero experimented
with an irrigated fruit orchard for
a time at Tascosa, but he soon returned to
New Mexico. In 1893 he purchased a sheep
ranch near present-day Bard and lived there
until his death in 1912. He is buried at Endee,
New Mexico.


Frederick W. Rathjen
West Texas A&amp;M University




Carlson, Paul H. Texas Wooleybacks: The Range Sheep and Goat Industry. College Station: Texas A&amp;M University Press,
1982. Romero, José Ynocencio. "Spanish Sheepmen on the
Canadian at Old Tascosa." as told to Ernest R. Archambeau.
Panhandle-Plains Historical Review 19 (1946): 45–72.
Taylor, A. J. "New Mexican Pastores and Priests in the Texas
Panhandle, 1876–1915." Panhandle-Plains Historical Review
56 (1984): 65–79.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>