<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ind.021</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Foreign Investment</field>
      <field name="author">Riefler, Roger</field>
      <field name="text">

 




FOREIGN INVESTMENT

Foreign investment has long been an economic
force in the Great Plains of Canada and
the United States. In the 1870s and early 1880s
English and particularly Scottish syndicates
invested heavily in Plains ranching, only to
lose much of their money when the bottom
dropped out of the business in 1885–86. At the
same time, English investors were buying
huge tracts of land from the railroads in Kansas
and reselling them to settlers for large
profits. North of the forty-ninth parallel, British
investors were even more influential. British
urban real estate firms controlled much of
the early development of Regina, Saskatoon,
Winnipeg, and other cities in the Prairie Provinces,
and British capital also flowed into the
wheat industry and railroad construction.

In the 1990s in the United States as a whole,
foreign investment averaged $33.3 billion a
year. In Canada, during the same period, annual
foreign investment averaged just over $6
billion. In both countries, such investment is
concentrated in coastal states or provinces. For
example, two-thirds of U.K. investment in
Canada (a source that is second only to the
United States) goes to Ontario; Alberta, with 8
percent of total U.K. investment, leads other
Prairie Provinces. In 1995, in the ten states
wholly or partly in the Great Plains of the
United States, there were 509,700 jobs in foreign
affiliates. These jobs accounted for only 4
percent of total private industry employment
in the region, and no state reached the 4.8
percent national average of jobs in foreign affiliates,
though Texas was close. Between 1990
and 1995, however, states in the Great Plains
saw a 6 percent increase in such employment,
outpacing the 4 percent national average. Colorado
led the way, with a 28 percent increase,
rather evenly divided between foreign investment.
generated employment in manufacturing
and nonmanufacturing. Oklahoma experienced
the greatest decrease in this time
period (a 24 percent decline in this type of
employment), probably reflecting problems in
the volatile energy sector.

There are also significant intraregional variations
in sources of foreign investment. The
United States is by far the leading source in the
Prairie Provinces. During the 1990s, for example,
many of the leading U.S. food-processing
firms, including Archer Daniels Midland,
Cargill, and ConAgra, Ltd., made significant
investments in Alberta. South of the forty-ninth
parallel, Canada is the main source of
foreign investment in South Dakota, Montana,
and Kansas. The United Kingdom is an
important source throughout the Plains region,
but especially in Wyoming. Japan is important
too, but proportionately less so than
for the United States as a whole. France and
Germany, on the other hand, have a proportionately
greater presence on the Plains than
they do in the Untied States as a whole.

Foreign investors are drawn to the Great
Plains for a variety of economic and political
reasons, including a desire to expand their foreign
market share, minimize production and
transportation costs, take advantage of the
availability of skilled labor, and profit from
state or province development incentives. The
positive effects for the Plains include increased
competitiveness in the regional economy, the
accumulation of capital and expertise, and, of
course, the provision of jobs. Possible negative
impacts involve overcapacity, especially in
mature industries, and unfair competition
due to foreign subsidies and state and province
development initiatives.


Roger Riefler
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Fahim-Nader, Mahnaz, and William J. Zeile. "Foreign Direct
Investment in the United States." Survey of Current Business 77 (1977): 42–69. Paterson, Donald G. British Direct Investment in Canada, 1890–1914. Toronto: University
of Toronto Press, 1976. Wilkins, Mira. The History of Foreign Investment in the United States to 1914. Cambridge:
Harvard University Press, 1984.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>