<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.015</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Deverell, Rex (b. 1941)</field>
      <field name="author">Kerr, Donald C.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




DEVERELL, REX (b. 1941)

Rex Deverell is a Canadian dramatist noted
for his children's plays, his full-length plays,
and his time as a writer in residence at the
Globe Theatre, Regina, from 1975 to 1990. He
was born July 17, 1941, in Toronto, raised in
Orillia, Ontario, and received a bachelor's
from McMaster University, Hamilton, Ontario,
in 1963, a bachelor of divinity from Mc-
Master in 1966, and a master of sacred theology
from Union Theological Seminary in New
York in 1967. He began writing plays in 1966
and has been a prolific writer ever since, with
more than twenty children's plays, fifteen fulllength
plays, and half a dozen plays commissioned
by various groups. He has participated
in five collective productions and has been an
active playwright for CBC radio.

At the Globe Theatre he began as a children's
playwright and wrote roughly one children's
play a year. His first full-length play,
Boiler Room Suite (1977), became his best
known and most produced. He wrote a number
of Saskatchewan-specific documentaries
like Medicare! (1980), on the introduction of
socialized medicine to Canada and the subsequent
doctors strike, as well as Number 1 Hard
(1978) and Black Powder: Estevan 1931 (1981).
He has also written musicals, including Mandarin Oranges (1985/1990), and plays that explore
religion, including Righteousness (1983),
about Saint Augustine.

Plays produced in a single year, 1985, give a
good cross section of Deverell's work. That
year was the centenary of the North-West Rebellion,
and Deverell composed both a fivehour
radio drama for the cbc, The Riel Commission,
and a play for the Globe, Beyond Batoche. He also wrote a musical, a children's
play, and another radio drama and worked on
a collective show in 1985.


Donald C. Kerr
University of Saskatchewan




Wallace, Robert, and Cynthia Zimmerman, eds. The Works: Conversations with English Canadian Playwrights.
Toronto: Coach House Press, 1982: 127–41.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>