<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fil.017</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Days of Heaven</field>
      <field name="author">Levine, June Perry</field>
      <field name="text">

 




DAYS OF HEAVEN


Days of Heaven


Days of Heaven, written and directed by Terrence
Malick and released in 1978, is perhaps
the most pictorially beautiful depiction of the
Great Plains ever created on film. Set in the
Texas Panhandle at the onset of World War I
but actually filmed in the wheat fields of Alberta,
the film reflects Malick's sensitivity to a
landscape he knows well, having worked on
the wheat harvest as a teenager, following it
from his native Texas north to Canada.

Like his first film, Badlands (1973), which
was based on the Charles Starkweather/Caril
Fugate murder spree across Nebraska in the
late 1950s, Days of Heaven employs voice-over
narration, emphasizes the setting, and centers
on poor and uneducated characters. But Days of Heaven is more generalized and distanced,
almost mythic. This quality is effected by a
number of elements: the plot, based on the
tragic love triangle of Bill, Abby, and "the
Farmer," unfolds episodically but with implacable
inevitability; there is a preponderance of
long shots; dialogue is held to a minimum;
water, fire, and a plague of locusts are important
to the visual presentation; the characters
are often backlit (with the sun behind them,
they are virtually silhouetted) and thus depersonalized;
and much of the shooting was done
at the "magic hour" right after sunset, producing
a clear and lonely light.

Nestor Almendros, the film's internationally
renowned cinematographer, explained that
Days of Heaven was shot in Alberta because it
was a Hutterite area, largely untouched by
modern influences. The Hutterites' wheat was
longer than conventional wheat varieties, their
silos were red, and collectors among them were
in possession of steam tractors and cutters.
This landscape evoked the Plains of the early
twentieth century.

Perhaps because of this pastoralism, some
critics have thought that the film lacks any
political view of the impoverished farmworkers,
but this judgment is debatable. The film's
title sequence is a montage of black-and-white
still photographs of turn-of-the-century urban
poor people taken by Lewis Hine, among
other noted photographers, followed by the
opening sequence of a Chicago steel mill that
shows Bill (Richard Gere) in an argument
with the foreman that leads to his flight by
freight train to the wheat fields. In the fields
we see harvesters' pay docked by the farm
foreman for a "short line" a little while before
the Farmer's accountant tells him that he's becoming
the richest man in the county. The
voice-over of Bill's sister Linda (Linda Manz)
includes lines such as "the rich got it figured
out" and "some got more than they need, others
less." This is not to suggest that Days of Heaven is primarily a progressive political
film; rather, the issue of class is an aspect of
the whole.

If Days of Heaven has a problem it is with
the whole. Its elliptical plot–the love story of
Bill, Abby (Brooke Adams), and the Farmer
(Sam Shepard)–does not sustain the tenor of
the film because the characters lack depth of
development. What is compelling is the cycle
of Plains seasons–the harvest, winter snow,
the emergence of spring shoots–with its eloquently
rendered evocation of the natural
order.


June Perry Levine
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Denby, David. "Museum Piece." New York (September 25,
1978): 138–40. Fox, Terry Curtis. "The Last Rays of Light."
Film Comment (1978): 27–28. Riley, Brooks. "Nestor Almendros
Interviewed." Film Comment (1978): 28–31.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>