<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.044</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Manitoba</field>
      <field name="author">Silver, Jim</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MANITOBA

Manitoba became a Canadian province in
1870. Its origins were intimately connected to
the fate of First Peoples. Aboriginal title to
the lands now constituting much of Manitoba
were extinguished by treaties in the 1870s.
First Peoples, primarily Crees and Ojibwas,
were removed to distant reserves, where they
continued to be ruled in colonial fashion by
Indian agents until well into the twentieth
century. The Red River Métis, people of mixed
Aboriginal and European heritage who had
founded a distinctive culture at the forks of
the Red and Assisiboine Rivers, were similarly
dispossessed. The Métis had fought in the Red
River Resistance of 1869–70 to protect their
rights to the land from a threatened Canadian
takeover. Under the leadership of Louis Riel
they formed a provisional government whose
agents entered into negotiations with Canada,
which led to the establishment of the province
of Manitoba through the Manitoba Act of July
15, 1870. But the rights that the largely Frenchspeaking
Métis believed they had secured in
the Manitoba Act were extinguished throughout
the 1870s and 1880s, leading to their dispossession
and dispersal.

In their wake, settlers of British origin,
many migrating westward from Ontario, arrived
in the 1870s and 1880s to occupy the rich
agricultural land of southern Manitoba. Mennonites
and Icelanders also settled in Manitoba
in the 1870s, but essentially Manitoba
became culturally and economically an extension
of English-speaking Ontario.

In 1896 the great wheat and railway boom
took off, creating the economic foundations
of twentieth-century Manitoba. The boom
was fueled by the massive inflow of eastern
European immigrants, who farmed the lessfertile
and more northerly lands not occupied
by immigrants of British descent, and who
formed the core of the labor force that turned
Winnipeg into a major manufacturing and
distribution center with a hinterland that
stretched to the Pacific Ocean. For a short but
dramatic period, Winnipeg became the "Chicago
of the North."

By 1914 the boom was over. The best prairie
land was occupied, most of the railways were
built, and the insatiable demand for new supplies
and infrastructure was largely filled. The
dynamic for growth was exhausted. The shape
of Manitoba's economy–a wheat and railway
center with significant manufacturing, wholesaling,
and financial strength at the hub of an
east–west economy–was largely determined
for the next fifty years.

A seminal event in shaping Manitoba's politics
soon followed in the form of the 1919 Winnipeg
General Strike. Winnipeg was a city divided:
an aggressive and successful business
class of British origins lived in the comfortable
south end of the city, and a working class disproportionately
comprised of eastern European
immigrants was jammed into the teeming,
poverty-stricken, multilingual North End.
The result was the dramatic, six-week-long
General Strike in 1919. Winnipeg's powerful
business class responded with a nonpartisan
coalition-building strategy intended to ameliorate
the class conflict that, as the General
Strike made clear, was at the heart of Manitoba's
politics. The resulting rurally based
coalition governments were successful in governing
post–General Strike Manitoba from
1922 to 1958.

In 1958 a Conservative government was
elected that finally broke with the fiscally conservative
pattern of the previous forty years.
Premier Duff Roblin adopted a strategy of
public spending to modernize what had become
an economically stagnant province. The
moderately social democratic New Democratic
Party (NDP), elected in 1969, continued
Roblin's "Keynesian welfare state" strategy
and, with the exception of a hiatus from 1977
to 1981, stayed in office from 1969 to 1988.

The Conservatives under Gary Filmon were
reelected in 1988 and served until 1999. Breaking
with the economic pattern of the preceding
thirty years, they have adopted an economic
strategy substantially different from
their ndp and Conservative predecessors.
one consistent with the neoliberal temper of
the times. Their strategy is based on reductions
in taxes and public spending to improve
the business climate and to attract capital
from outside the province, and on increased
exports to the United States consistent with
the Canada-U.S. and the North American
Free Trade Agreements.

As a consequence, Manitoba's economy has
been rotated on its axis from an east–west to a
north–south orientation. The province's historic
role as the hub of a pan-Canadian, east–west economy–the "gateway to the west"–has disappeared, replaced by the attempt to
create a new role as an export platform at the
north end of a midcontinental trade corridor.
Manitoba now seeks to become the "gateway
to the south."

See also INDUSTRY: NAFTA / NATIVE AMERICANS: Métis / PROTEST AND DISSENT: Winnipeg General Strike / WAR: Red River Resistance.


Jim Silver
University of Winnipeg




Friesen, Gerald. The Canadian Prairies: A History. Toronto:
University of Toronto Press, 1984. Morton, William Lewis.
Manitoba: A History. Toronto: University of Toronto Press,
1957. Silver, Jim, and Jeremy Hull, eds. The Political Economy
of Manitoba. Regina: Canadian Plains Research Center,
1990.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>