<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.055</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Ostenso, Martha (1900-1963)</field>
      <field name="author">Harrison, Dick</field>
      <field name="text">

 




OSTENSO, MARTHA (1900-1963)

Author Martha Ostenso (Minnesota State Historical Society)


Martha Ostenso was a Minnesota novelist
often claimed by Canadians because she lived
in Canada for six years and set four of her
novels there. She was born in Norway on September
17, 1900, to Sigurd and Olina Tungeland
Ostenso, who migrated to the Midwest in
1902. After the family moved to Manitoba in
1915, Ostenso taught briefly in the interlake
area north of Winnipeg. She attended the
University of Manitoba for two years before
following her creative writing teacher, Douglas
Durkin, to New York in 1921. Himself a
novelist, Durkin is said to have collaborated
with Ostenso in all her novels, including Wild Geese, which won the Dodd Mead First Novel
Award in 1925. Together they produced a
dozen popular novels under her name over
the next thirty years, including The Young May Moon (1929), The Mandrake Root (1938), and
O River, Remember (1943). They reportedly
earned up to $40,000 annually and kept a
house in Beverly Hills where they socialized
with stars such as Douglas Fairbanks Jr., Mary
Pickford, and Henry Fonda, who starred in a
1941 Hollywood remake of Wild Geese.

Ostenso's best novel, Wild Geese, depicts a
tyrannical Prairie patriarch overthrown by the
suppressed vitality and moral courage of the
women in his family. Hailed as an early contribution
to Prairie realism, the novel draws
much of its power from its romantic characterization.
Ostenso's other novels, set mainly
in the rural Midwest, portray family conflicts
and the darker reaches of romantic love and
often exhibit the author's gift for creating
powerful female characters. Ostenso died in
Seattle on November 24, 1963.


Dick Harrison
Sechelt, British Columbia




Atherton, Stanley S. "Martha Ostenso (1900–63)." In Canadian Writers and Their Works, 4: 210–53, Fiction series,
edited by Robert Lecker, Jack David, and Ellen Quigley.
Toronto: ECW Press, 1991. Baldwin, Charles C. Martha Ostenso: Daughter of the Vikings. New York: Dodd, Mead,
1930.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>