<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.edu.026</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Menninger, Karl (1893-1990)</field>
      <field name="author">Faulkner, Howard J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MENNINGER, KARL (1893-1990)

One of the most distinguished and influential
American psychiatrists of the twentieth century
and cofounder with his father of the Menninger
Clinic (later Foundation), Karl Augustus
Menninger was born July 22, 1893, in
Topeka, Kansas. After graduating from the
University of Wisconsin, Menninger attended
Harvard University, receiving his medical degree
in 1917. Menninger's father, Dr. C. F. Menninger,
had already established his practice in
Topeka, and, influenced by the family arrangement
of the Mayo Clinic, he had planned on
his son joining him in practice. This Karl Menninger
did, but not as his father had foreseen.
While at Harvard, Menninger's chief
influence was Elmer Ernest Southard, a professor
of neuropathology. Southard turned
Menninger's interest toward mental health,
and after his return to Topeka Menninger
steered the direction of the joint practice toward
psychiatry.

In 1920 father and son founded the Menninger
Clinic, thus initiating the younger
Menninger's long and productive career in
Kansas. Five years later, the clinic was complemented
by the Menninger Sanitarium in Topeka,
and in 1926 the Menningers started the
Southard School for children with psychological
problems. In 1941 the clinic and sanitarium,
by then among the most prestigious
in America, were reorganized into the notfor-
profit Menninger Foundation. In 1942
Menninger and his brother William, who had
also joined his father in the enterprise, established
the Topeka Institute for Psychoanalysis.
After World War II, during which Menninger
had been sent to Europe to assess the need
for psychiatric care of military personnel,
Karl Menninger became manager of the nation's
largest Veterans Administration hospital,
Winter Hospital, in Topeka, where students
at the newly founded Menninger School
of Psychiatry trained.

Menninger's approach to psychiatry during
these years became increasingly Freudian. He
underwent analysis in 1930 with Chicago psychoanalyst
Franz Alexander and again in
the early 1940s in New York with Ruth Mack
Brunswick. He not only applied these psychoanalytic
concepts in his clinical practice
but also reflected them in his prolific writing.
In 1930 he published The Human Mind,
which became a best-seller and a Book-of-the-
Month Club selection, the first work by a serious
psychiatrist to achieve such popularity.
In it, he developed a style that would mark
much of his work: the ability to translate abstract
concepts into vivid, concrete cases. His
second book, Man against Himself (1938), a
study of suicide, describes the power of the
death instinct when it is directed inward: the
externally aggressive will to kill combined
with the internal desire to be killed and to die.
In addition to the psychiatric books that Menninger
continued to publish throughout his
life, he also popularized psychiatry in a column
about child rearing that he wrote from
1929 to 1942 in Household magazine and in a
short-lived advice column in the Ladies' Home
Journal (1930–32). In a speech honoring Menninger
at the Smithsonian Institution, Erik
Erikson said that he "translates Freud into
American literature. He is not a popularizer,
but an enlightener."

Menninger was a crusader not only for
Freud and for enlightenment about mental illness
but for social issues as well. Early in his
career his causes were directly related to psychiatry.
He was chair of the first commission
to investigate the role psychiatrists play in legal
proceedings, and in 1946 he chaired an investigatory
panel studying conditions in Kansas
mental hospitals. Later in life he turned his
attention to matters such as capital punishment
(in 1968 he published The Crime of Punishment
), child neglect (in 1966 he founded
The Villages, Inc., a Topeka group home for
homeless children), and the mistreatment of
Native Americans. In 1978, at the age of eighty-five,
he was appointed co–project director of
a federal program to develop programs and
housing for five southwestern Native tribes.

Menninger was married twice. In 1916 he
married Grace Gaines, with whom he had
three children: Julia, Robert, and Martha.
They divorced in 1941. Later that year he married
Jeanetta Lyle, who was to become his collaborator
on many projects, including cowriting his third book, Love against Hate, in 1942.
They adopted a daughter, Rosemary, in 1948.

In 1981 President Jimmy Carter honored
Karl Menninger with the Medal of Freedom
for his long career and invaluable contributions
to American life. Menninger is the only
psychiatrist ever to be so recognized. Menninger
died of abdominal cancer in a Topeka
hospital in July 1990, just four days short of his
ninety-seventh birthday.


Howard J. Faulkner
Washburn University




Faulkner, Howard J., and Virginia D. Pruitt, eds. The Selected
Correspondence of Karl A. Menninger. Columbia:
University of Missouri Press, 1995. Friedman, Lawrence.
Menninger: The Family and the Clinic. Lawrence: University
Press of Kansas, 1992. Hall, Bernard. A Psychiatrist's
World. New York: Viking Press, 1959.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>