<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.med.023</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Huntley, Chet (1911-1974)</field>
      <field name="author">Mayeux, Peter E.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




HUNTLEY, CHET (1911-1974)

Chester Robert Huntley, the national news
broadcaster and commentator, was born on
December 10, 1911, in Cardwell, Montana. His
father, Percy Adams "Pat" Huntley, was a railroad
telegrapher; his mother, Blanche Wadine
Tatham, was a former schoolteacher whose
relatives had crossed the Plains in a covered
wagon. His early life on a northern Montana
ranch near the small town of Saco and in a
succession of railroad towns in southern
Montana greatly influenced his outlook on life
and his reporting style, instilling in him a
work ethic and an independent stance.

Huntley's broadcasting career began early.
His father copied down play-by-play reports
of World Series baseball games as they came
over the wire. Huntley announced the action
out the depot window to the assembled fans.
He graduated from Whitehall High School in
1929 and studied at Montana State College at
Bozeman and the Cornish School of Arts in
Seattle, Washington, before transferring to the
University of Washington at Seattle, where he
received his bachelor's degree in 1934.

While still a student, Chet Huntley worked
at radio stations in Seattle and Spokane before
transferring to kgw in Portland, Oregon. He
then worked in Los Angeles for NBC (1937–
39), CBS (1939–51), and ABC (1951–55). In 1956
he moved to New York City, where he did a
ten-minute radio commentary (Chet Huntley ), a Sunday afternoon television
program, and a Saturday evening news program.
Huntley's reporting style included commentary,
although he was quick to note he was
not interested in advocacy journalism.

Also in 1956 Huntley was teamed with
David Brinkley, NBC's Washington correspondent,
to broadcast the national political conventions.
They worked so well together that
NBC placed them on a fifteen-minute evening
newscast, with Huntley in New York City and
Brinkley in Washington DC. They did their
first program on October 20, 1956. The newscast
expanded to half an hour in 1963. NBC
executives hoped that Huntley's solemn demeanor,
serious tone, and rich voice would
help compete with CBS's Edward R. Murrow.

The Huntley-Brinkley Report was an instant
success. The show's closing signature ("Good
night, Chet. Good night, David. And good
night for NBC News") became familiar to the
20 million viewers they reached at the peak
of their popularity. Their ratings remained
high up to Huntley's departure July 31, 1970.
The partnership helped mold the nightly national
newscast into the principal daily news
source now enjoyed by many Americans. The Huntley-Brinkley Report won every major
news award, including seven Emmy Awards,
four Peabody Awards, and two Overseas Press
Club Awards.

Huntley had left cbs in 1951 because his
bosses were unhappy with his liberal commentary
and because he refused to sign a loyalty
oath. One of his most controversial moves
came on March 29, 1967, when he crossed
picket lines set up by striking members of the
American Federation of Television and Radio
Artists (AFTRA). His coanchor, David Brinkley,
honored the strike. Huntley said at the time he
did not think newsmen belonged in a union
with singers and dancers.

Huntley stayed active in retirement. He
broadcast commentaries, advertised for American
Airlines, and got the company to sponsor a
television series, The American Experience. He
also joined an advertising firm, Levine, Huntley,
Schmidt, Inc. Chet Huntley died March 20,
1974, three days before the opening ceremonies
for his twenty-five-million-dollar recreational
complex called Big Sky near Bozeman.


Peter E. Mayeux
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Chet Huntley Papers (1911–74), Montana State University
Library, Bozeman. Huntley, Chet. The Generous Years: Remembrances of a Frontier Boyhood. New York: Random
House, 1968.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>