<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.asam.014</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Japanese</field>
      <field name="author">Asato, Noriko</field>
      <field name="text">

 




JAPANESE

The first generation of Japanese immigrants,
known as issei, originally came to the Great
Plains as sojourning contract laborers for railroad
or mining companies in the late 1890s
and early 1900s; few other occupations were
open to them. After completing their contracts,
many worked for farmers and meatpackers,
and eventually some became owners
of small businesses and farms. By 1910 Montana,
Wyoming, and Colorado each had a Japanese
population of between 1,500 and 2,500.
The other Great Plains states each had fewer
than 1,000 Japanese. In Canada, most of the
early Japanese immigration was to British Columbia.
In the early 1900s the Canadian Pacific
Railway recruited many Japanese immigrant
workers, especially Okinawans. Just
before World War II there were more than 550
Japanese in Alberta and 40 in Manitoba.

The Oriental Trading Company brought
Japanese railroad gangs to Montana for the
Great Northern Railroad in 1898 and provided
as many as 6,000 workers to eight other railroad
companies in Montana, Idaho, and
North Dakota. Other Japanese workers built
railroads in Colorado, Nebraska, and South
Dakota. Issei were brought to the Great Plains
by labor contractors called keiyaku-nin, who
recruited and transported the laborers to work
sites and negotiated labor conditions with employers.
Contractors also served as foremen,
supervisors, and translators, and they kept a
portion of the workers' wages for their services:
a contractor for the Northern Pacific
Railroad, for example, charged each worker
ten cents out of their $1.10 daily wage. Most
issei were bachelors who lived in boxcars in
despicable conditions, often developing illnesses
from overwork and malnutrition.

Issei first engaged in agriculture as contract
laborers. While European Americans could
obtain land through the Homestead Act or
outright purchase, the majority of Japanese
Americans remained tenants because of the
alien land laws of several states. These prohibited
the acquisition of land for "aliens
ineligible for citizenship''.a racist constitutional
interpretation that until 1952 limited
citizenship to "free white person[s]" and "persons
of African nativity or descent." In the
Great Plains, Japanese Americans mainly grew
sugar beets but gradually diversified by adding
potatoes and beans as they acquired larger
acreages. In the early 1900s the Great Western
Sugar Company in Billings, Montana, and
Scottsbluff, Nebraska, specifically encouraged
Japanese production of sugar beets. In Colorado,
Naoichi Hokazono advanced the sugar
beet venture by cultivating 2,000 acres near
Greeley using Japanese contract laborers. Issei
farmers also made Rocky Ford, Colorado, famous
for quality cantaloupes. Altogether, between
1907 and 1909, issei farmers in Colorado
increased their total farming acreage by 131
percent.

Miners were the other major pioneering
group of issei to first reach the Great Plains. In
1909 there were 300 Japanese miners in Colorado
from a total of 3,555 Japanese Americans
in the state. In Wyoming, Japanese miners,
who worked in at least seven mines, joined the
white labor union. Issei also entered the meatpacking
industry in the Great Plains when labor
contractor Kinji Okajima brought in 120
strikebreakers to an Omaha packinghouse
and another 100 strikebreakers during Kansas
City's 1904 Armour meat packinghouse strike.

Denver became home to the largest Japanese
American community in the Great
Plains. Although Denver's Japanese town survives
in greatly reduced form, its cultural
and religious institutions once served much of
the Great Plains. Denver's Tri-State Buddhist
Church, established in 1916, grew to serve a
600-mile radius, extending into Nebraska and
Wyoming, with fourteen branch churches in
1934. Tamai Towers, a senior citizens' home,
stands in Denver's Sakura Square to honor
Rev. Yoshitaka Tamai, who dedicated his life
to ministering to his dispersed Great Plains
congregation. Farther east, Japanese communities
developed in Nebraska in the cities of
Omaha, Lincoln, North Platte, Scottsbluff,
and Mitchell. Rev. Hiram Hisanori Kano, a
minister of the Episcopal Church in Nebraska
and leader of the Japanese agricultural community,
received an early graduate degree in
agriculture from the University of Nebraska.
A farmer himself, he later established the Japanese
colony of Dutton Ranch in Hebron, Nebraska.
Kano and members of the Nebraska
Japanese Improvement Association achieved a
minor victory when the state's land law was
widened to include aliens, not just those eligible
for citizenship, and leases were extended
from two to five years.

During World War II approximately 120,000
Japanese Americans on the West Coast were
forced to leave their homes and were sent to
temporary detention centers operated by the
army and then to one of ten concentration (a
term now preferred to internment) camps operated
by the War Relocation Authority. Two
of these camps were located in or near the
Great Plains—Heart Mountain near Hunt,
Wyoming, and Amache near Granada, Colorado.
The Japanese Americans and Japanese
Canadians living in the Great Plains were not
forcibly relocated, apart from several issei
leaders, including Reverend Kano. The governors
of the Great Plains states, with the exception
of Colorado's Ralph Carr, may have had
some responsibility for the system of concentration
camps because they opposed settlements
of unguarded Japanese among the general
population in their states. The Justice
Department's Immigration and Naturalization
Service (INS) also operated several smaller
camps for issei, which detained such "security
risks" as community leaders, Japaneselanguage
teachers, and newspaper editors. Several
ins camps were located in the Great Plains,
including those at Bismarck, North Dakota,
and Crystal City, Texas.

Japanese Americans were able to leave the
concentration camps once they secured college
admission, army service, or army clearance.
This led to increased Japanese American
student enrollment at some Great Plains colleges,
particularly in Colorado and Nebraska.
Japanese Americans were also furloughed
temporarily from the camps to work on sugar
beet farms in the surrounding areas. The Canadian
government, as a part of its own forced
relocation, also sent some 3,600 Japanese Canadians
to work in harsh conditions on sugar
beet farms in Alberta and Manitoba. Many
nisei (second-generation Japanese Americans)
from the Great Plains also served in the muchdecorated
442nd Regimental Combat Team.
The sacrifices of soldiers of the 442nd and the
exploits of Nebraska war hero Ben Kuroki are
credited as part of the reason for the amelioration
of anti-Japanese racism.

Although the majority of the removed Japanese
Americans returned to the West Coast,
third- and fourth-generation Japanese Americans
are now part of the fabric of life in the
Great Plains, serving as city council leaders,
editors, professors, and farmers. According to
the 2000 census, 17,120 Japanese citizens and
Japanese Americans live in Texas, 11,571 in Colorado,
2,505 in Oklahoma, 1,935 in Kansas,
1,582 in Nebraska, 1,964 in New Mexico, and
1,906 in other Great Plains states. Canada's
1996 census reveals that 8,280 Japanese and
Japanese Canadians reside in Alberta, 1,670 in
Manitoba, and 415 in Saskatchewan.

See also WAR: World War II.


Noriko Asato
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Daniels, Roger. Asian America: Chinese and Japanese in the United States since 1850. Seattle: University of Washington
Press, 1988. Iwata, Masakasu. Planted in Good Soil: A History of the Issei in United States Agriculture. New York:
Peter Lang, 1992. Takaki, Ronald. Strangers from a Different Shore. New York: Penguin Books, 1989.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>