<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ind.050</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Post, C. W. (1854-1914)</field>
      <field name="author">Vollan, Charles</field>
      <field name="text">

 




POST, C. W. (1854-1914)

Charles William Post was a businessman and
experimenter who invented and marketed several
important breakfast cereals and a coffee
substitute. He was born in Springfield, Illinois,
on October 26, 1854. He attended school in
Illinois, dropping out of Illinois Industrial
University after two years. At age seventeen he
briefly relocated to Independence, Kansas,
where he was a salesman, clerk, and store
owner. After his return to Springfield in 1872,
he focused on selling and manufacturing agricultural
implements as well as inventing his
own cultivator, harrow, plow, and haystacker.

Although he was successful, the strain of
business life proved too much, and Post suffered
a nervous breakdown in 1885. Thereafter,
he moved to Fort Worth, where he worked
to develop two subdivisions. He suffered a second
breakdown in 1891 and moved to Battle
Creek, Michigan, home of John Harvey Kellogg's
health complex. There he partially
adopted Kellogg's beliefs concerning human
health. He started his own sanitarium in 1892,
also in Battle Creek. In 1894 he invented a coffee
substitute called Postum that he insisted
had healthful benefits. He soon recognized the
potential for a strong market in breakfast cereals
and invented Grape-Nuts. He built his
own paper mill in 1899 to construct cartons
for his cereal. Soon he had a cereal empire. In
1908 he invented the popular Post Toasties. As
a result of his activities, Post and Kellogg became
lifelong enemies. Post's empire eventually
became a part of General Foods.

As a successful businessman, Post served as
president of the American Manufacturers Association
and the Citizen's Industrial Association, in which, despite the organization's title,
he worked to defeat unions and the open shop
system. Wealthy enough to pursue his dreams,
in 1906 Post returned to Texas, where he hoped
to establish a model farming community. In
1907 he bought 225,000 acres in Lynn and
Garza Counties, where he established the town
of Post City (now Post), Texas. Although he
platted out the settlement, planted trees, and
built roads and schools, the settlement grew
slowly. Post worked to improve the region's
prospects, going so far as to conduct long and
expensive rainmaking experiments from 1911
to 1914 that failed to produce rain. Post's health
began to fail in his later years, and on May 9,
1914, he apparently committed suicide at his
home in Santa Barbara, California.

See also WATER: Rainmaking.


Charles Vollan
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Major, Nettie Letich. C. W. Post. Washington DC: Judd and
Detweiler, 1963.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>