<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.tra.025</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Portages</field>
      <field name="author">Decker, Jody F.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




PORTAGES

A portage is the carrying of goods or boats
across land between navigable waters and
around obstructions in streams. Portages were
paths originated by game; Native Americans
and subsequently European Americans modified
them when directness, gradient, or footing
dictated. Portages along the extensive inland
waterways of the Prairies and Northern
Plains played a major role in the fur trade,
especially after the Hudson's Bay Company
moved into the western interior of Canada in
1774 in response to competition and American
fur-trading companies began in earnest to exploit
furs in the trans-Missouri West after
1806.

All cargo had to be unloaded from a canoe
or boat to be carried over the portage. To expedite
this process, furs or trade goods were
parceled into ninety-pound packs. A man
could carry two packs for about half a mile,
drop them, then return for two more. With
loading and unloading, a mile-long portage
could take one hour. Most portages around
rapids were a few hundred yards in length,
while height-of-land portages (for example,
the nine-mile Grand portage between the
Hudson Bay and St. Lawrence drainages)
could entail several miles. The cumulative effect
of all portages on a route included substantial
human and economic costs: drowning;
injuries and deaths from lifting, straining, and
exhaustion; snake bites; Indian attacks; and
increased risk of infectious diseases at congestion
points were reported by the traders and
voyageurs. Increased economic costs included
labor and capital equipment costs, opportunity
costs (when men took up space for trade
goods and supplies) or when low water levels
limited supplies and types of vessels used, and
damage to goods from increased handling.
Portages constituted transportation bottlenecks
in a finely tuned economic system that
operated only within the short season of open water.

See also INDUSTRY: Fur Trade.


Jody F. Decker
Wilfrid Laurier University




Decker, Jody F., and Donald B. Freeman. "The Role of
Portages in Shaping the Economic Geography of the
Western Canadian Fur Trade, 1774–1820." In Canada: Geographical
Interpretations. Essays in Honour of John Warkentin,
edited by James R. Gibson. York University–Atkinson
College Geographical Monograph 22 (1993): 31–67. Morse,
Eric W. Fur Trade Canoe Routes of Canada/Then and Now.
Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 1971.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>