<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.asam.019</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Poison Porridge Case</field>
      <field name="author">Leyton-Brown, Ken</field>
      <field name="text">

 




POISON PORRIDGE CASE

In August of 1907 some patrons of a Regina
restaurant fell ill while eating breakfast and
were diagnosed as suffering from arsenic poisoning.
Three later died. Suspicion immediately
fell on Charlie Mack, the Chinese owner
of an older, neighboring restaurant. His business
was known to have suffered because of
competition from the newer establishment,
and he had access to the oatmeal that had
been found to contain arsenic.

The police, however, were unable to locate
him, and public dissatisfaction with their lack
of results finally prompted the police to take
extraordinary measures. In a midnight raid
they rounded up the entire male Chinese population
of Regina and took them to city hall,
apparently believing that they were conspiring
to hide Charlie Mack. The operation was not a
success, though; Charlie Mack was never apprehended.
Moreover, fourteen of those taken
into custody sued the police officers involved
in the raid, the mayor of Regina, and the attorney
general of Saskatchewan, alleging that
they had been falsely arrested and unlawfully
confined. The authorities at first refused to
take the suit seriously, but the complainants
persisted (though the attorney general was
later dropped from the case) and they eventually
won their case. They collected substantial
damages, and the affair cost the chief
of police his job. The most important result,
though, was to deter police from taking
such indiscriminate action against the Chinese
community in the future, and to demonstrate
that the courts of Saskatchewan were
able, and in this case willing, to protect the
rights of all of Saskatchewan's citizens.


Ken Leyton-Brown
University of Regina




Leyton-Brown, Ken. "The 'Poison Porridge' Case: Chinese
and the Administration of Justice in Early Saskatchewan."
Great Plains Quarterly 12 (1992): 99–106.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>