<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pd.059</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Women of All Red Nations</field>
      <field name="author">Thunder Hawk, Madonna</field>
      <field name="text">

 




WOMEN OF ALL RED NATIONS

Women of All Red Nations (WARN) was
founded in 1978 in San Francisco, California,
and to date remains the most prominent activist
Native American women's organization.
warn advocates for Native American treaty
rights and for social, economic, and environmental
justice for Native American peoples.
WARN was created at the height of Indian activism
in the 1970s, when the virtually all-male
national leadership of Indian activist groups
became targeted by federal and state law enforcement
agencies and courts. After the national
American Indian Movement leaders
were prosecuted and imprisoned by the federal
legal system, women were called to the fore of
Native American issues and WARN was born.

From its beginning, warn has sent spokespersons
to international forums concerning
colonialism, land struggles, energy resource
protection, and Indigenous rights recognition.
warn was instrumental in stopping the
uranium mining that was planned for the sacred
Black Hills of South Dakota. The organization
built coalitions with non-Indians
so that uranium mining would never be conducted
in lands sacred to the Lakota, Dakota,
and Nakota people.

WARN also conducted a health study of the
water on the Pine Ridge Reservation in South
Dakota, which found that the groundwater
system was highly radioactive. Since then, federal
funds have been allocated for the construction
of a safe drinking-water system,
called Mni Wiconi, or the Water of Life, for
the greater reservation area. WARN has worked
on numerous issues relating to human health,
specifically the epidemic proportions of Type
II diabetes in Indian Country, as well as the
terrible problems associated with fetal alcohol
syndrome and fetal alcohol effect.

Today, warn continues its advocacy, predominantly
through the efforts of women's
circles in local communities both on and off
reservations. WARN's ongoing community organization
and advocacy on issues affecting
Native Americans at the grassroots level remain
highly focused and effective.


Madonna Thunder Hawk
Eagle Butte, South Dakota





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>