<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ag.031</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Family Farm</field>
      <field name="author">Opie, John</field>
      <field name="text">

 




FAMILY FARM

Americans have long cherished the family
farm as the place where the patriotic virtues
of rugged individualism, hard work, and selfsu.
ciency are practiced best. This institution
was identified as early as the eighteenth century
by Thomas Jefferson and J. Hector St.
John de Crevecoeur and later by Frederick
Jackson Turner who made the family farm the
centerpiece of his "frontier thesis"; by novelists
Hamlin Garland, Willa Cather, and Wallace
Stegner; by modern activists like Wendell
Berry and Wes Jackson; and by agricultural
philosopher Paul B. Thompson. Overall, the
family farm has persisted for more than a
hundred years on the Plains as a decentralized
cottage industry in an increasingly industrialized
world. In Canada, for example, more
than 99 percent of farm businesses are family
operations.

Traditionally on the family farm, household
members owned the land, and everyone,
including women and children, worked the
farm. Its sweat equity and cash flow depended
upon its own resources. The family farm
stood for cherished rural values of conservation,
frugality, responsibility, honesty, dignity
in work, belief in community, concern for
future generations, neighborliness, and selfreliance.
It was institutionalized by the Land
Ordinance of 1785, which privatized the public
domain, and by the classic 160-acre quarter
section provided by the Homestead Act of
1862. The expansion of family farms across the
United States was not significantly modified
until the end of public land sales in 1935. Similarly,
in the Prairie Provinces, the Dominion
Lands Act of 1872 promoted settlement and
family farms with virtually free provisions of
160-acre homesteads.

On the semiarid Great Plains, family farmers
faced great challenges because of the climate
extremes and repeated droughts. During
the Dust Bowl of the 1930s, almost half of U.S.
Plains farms were abandoned. Family farmers
who remained became clients of government
aid, which is a necessary ingredient of survival
even today. Compared to 1950, half the number
of Great Plains farmers worked the same
amount of land in 1980, and the number will
likely be halved again by the end of the first
decade of the twenty-first century. During the
twentieth century, large-scale, centralized, industrial
agriculture gradually replaced family
farms to produce most of the nation's food
and fiber. This put the family farm at risk.
While 94 percent of U.S. farms were still small
family farms in 1998–those with less than
$250,000 gross receipts annually and with a
net cash income of less than $23,000–they
received only 41 percent of all farm receipts.

Family farming might survive into the
future through niche agriculture, based on
low capital investment, intensive labor and
management, and high value crop and livestock
production. Such specialty farming includes
direct marketing of organic foods,
new-generation cooperatives and enlargement
of local farmers' markets, subscription
farming, and farm-to-chef direct marketing,
all outside the industrialized food stream.
Family farming, which still works the majority
of the nation's farm acreage, can also promote
sustainable agriculture and reap significant
environmental benefits by on-site
management of soil, water, and wildlife. Family
farming continues to be a major source of
images, metaphors, myths, and realities about
the intimate bond between humanity and the
wider natural world.

See also EUROPEAN AMERICANS: Land Laws and Settlement / LAW: Anti-Corporate Farming Laws.


John Opie
New Jersey Institute of Technology




Comstock, Gary, ed. Is There a Moral Obligation to Save
the Family Farm? Ames: Iowa State University Press, 1988.
Opie, John. The Law of the Land: Two Hundred Years of
American Farmland Policy. Lincoln: University of Nebraska
Press, 1987. Strange, Marty. Family Farming: A New
Economic Vision. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press,
1988.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>