<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ha.033</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Plan of San Diego</field>
      <field name="author">Sandos, James A.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




Plan of San Diego

From 1915 to 1917 the anarchist-inspired Plan
of San Diego (named after the small town in
South Texas where it was devised) sought to
redress the suffering of some ethnic poor in
America by creating two new, independent republics
from states in the Southwest and the
Great Plains where Hispanics, blacks, Native
Americans, and Japanese could live free from
"capitalist oppression." The plan proposed
liberating first, as a Spanish-speaking homeland,
the lands Mexico had lost to the United
States in 1848, namely Texas, New Mexico, Arizona,
Colorado, and California. Then six
bordering states, Nevada, Utah, Wyoming,
Nebraska, Kansas, and Oklahoma, would be
freed and given to blacks and Indians (Japanese
could live anywhere). These goals would
be achieved by killing all white males over the
age of sixteen and would begin with assaults
against South Texas.

The plan's ideology derived from the Mexican-
origin, Spanish-language anarchist newspaper
Regeneración, which drew 40 percent
of its subscribers from the Great Plains even
though it was published in Los Angeles by Ricardo
and Enrique Flores Magón. Both men
were convicted of violating United States neutrality
statutes, in part by inciting the Plan of
San Diego. Raiding against the United States
from Mexico intensified to the point of contributing
to the war crisis between the two
countries in the summer of 1916. Early in 1917,
when President Woodrow Wilson learned
from the intercepted Zimmermann Telegram
of a German proposal to return to Mexico
lands previously lost to the United States, a
proposal similar to that of the Plan of San
Diego, it played a role in Wilson's decision to
declare war on Germany.

A combination of military and political actions
by the United States and Mexico against
plan insurgents on both sides of the border
defused the movement in 1917. Such success,
however, was little appreciated at the time,
and the legacy of the Plan of San Diego embittered
United States–Mexico relations for seventy
years.


James A. Sandos
University of Redlands




Harris, Charles III, and Louis Sadler. "The Plan of San
Diego and the Mexican War Crisis of 1916: A Re-Examination."
Hispanic American Historical Review 57 (1978):
381–408. Sandos, James A. Rebellion in the Borderlands: Anarchism and the Plan of San Diego, 1904–1923. Norman:
University of Oklahoma Press, 1992.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>