<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.tra.024</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Pony Express</field>
      <field name="author">Lass, William E.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




PONY EXPRESS


Ruins of Three Crossings stage station along the route of the Pony Express, Wyoming, 1870


The Pony Express was a short-lived fast mail
service between St. Joseph, Missouri, and Sacramento,
California. In 1855, responding to
the desires of his California constituents, Senator
William M. Gwin proposed a government-supported
express mail service to Congress.
Failing to secure congressional aid,
Gwin turned to William H. Russell, the lead
partner in the overland freighting firm of Russell,
Majors and Waddell. After persuading his
reluctant partners, Alexander Majors and
William B. Waddell, to undertake the risky
venture, the enterprising Russell rushed to
open Pony Express service.

Preparations were costly. Russell, Majors
and Waddell agents bought about 500 of the
finest horses and hired approximately 200 riders.
Furthermore, they built, outfitted, and
staffãed 182 stations along the 1,966-mile route
that ran by way of Fort Kearny, the Platte River
valley, South Pass, and Salt Lake City. The mail
run was ceremoniously opened on April 3,
1860, when riders were dispatched from both
ends of the trail.

During its eighteen months of operation the
Pony Express carried 34,753 pieces of mail and
traveled 650,000 miles. To minimize weight
and thus increase speed, letters were written on
tissue-thin paper, and the riders were small
men whose average age was nineteen. Riders
on the weekly service ran twenty-four hours a
day year-round. Their fastest time was seven
days, seventeen hours, and in the spring, summer,
and fall they averaged twelve days, two less
than winter. Mail costs were extraordinarily
high–$10 an ounce in the early days of the
service.

 With the completion of the transcontinental
telegraph on October 26, 1861, the Pony
Express ended. Economically, it was a disaster.
The loss of some $200,000 soon propelled
Russell, Majors and Waddell into bankruptcy.
Despite its financial failure, the Pony Express
remains as a major symbol of an often romanticized
American West.


William E. Lass
Mankato State University




Godfrey, Anthony. Historic Resource Study: Pony Express
National Historic Trail. Washington DC: National Park Service,
1994. Smith, Waddell F., ed. The Story of the Pony
Express. San Rafael CA: Pony Express History and Art Gallery,
1960.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>