<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fil.002</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Altman, Robert (b. 1925)</field>
      <field name="author">Tibbetts, john C.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ALTMAN, ROBERT (b. 1925)

One of the prime architects of a renaissance
in American independent filmmaking in the
1970s, Robert Altman has chronicled in his
own idiosyncratic way the vagaries and varieties
of the American experience. He was born
in Kansas City, Missouri, on February 20,
1925. He recalls that his formative youthful
experiences–particularly his frequenting of
the jazz districts around 18th and Vine and the
movie theaters near his Brookside neighborhood
home–provided him with what he calls
his "chips," his "attitudes" toward life and art.

After serving as a B-24 pilot during World
War II, Altman returned to Kansas City, where
he began making industrial films for the Calvin
Company. He made two locally financed
features, The Delinquents (1956) and The James Dean Story (1957), then departed to Los Angeles,
where he began directing for the television
series Alfred Hitchcock Presents, The Rifleman,
and Combat! His breakthrough film was
M*A*S*H in 1970, which he quickly followed
up with several "antigenre" films, McCabe and Mrs. Miller (1971), The Long Goodbye (1973),
Thieves Like Us (1974), and Nashville (1975). He
won the Palme d'Or Award at the Cannes Film
Festival for M*A*S*H and the New York Critics'
Film Circle Award for best director for
Nashville.

Altman returned to his hometown in 1996
to make Kansas City, a portrait of the town's
milieu of jazz, corrupt politics, and rampant
gangsterism in the mid-1930s–a summation
of his thematic preoccupation with loose ends
and failed hopes, served up with his trademark
eccentric, semi-improvisational style
(which he compares to the solo riffs of the jam
sessions he heard as a youth in the Kansas City
clubs). Kansas City may be his most autobiographical
film, drawn as much from his
own memories as from the historical record.
With his characteristic relish for paradox, Altman
admits the film is hardly factual but insists
it is "truthful."


John C. Tibbetts
University of Kansas




Jacobs, Diane. Hollywood Renaissance. New York: A. S.
Barnes and Company, 1977. McGilligan, Patrick. Robert Altman: Jumping off the Cliff. New York: St. Martin's Press,
1989. Tibbetts, John C. "Robert Altman: After Thirty-Five
Years Still the "Action Painter" of American Cinema." Literature/ Film Quarterly 20 (1992): 36-42.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>