<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.084</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Woiwode, Larry (b. 1941)</field>
      <field name="author">Fournier, Denis R.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




WOIWODE, LARRY (b. 1941)

Even though Larry Woiwode moved out of
North Dakota when he was eight and did not
return to live there until 1978, he is imbued
with the "Dakota mystique"–a sense of awe at
the vast land, a need for family and community,
and an awareness of and a faith in God
that helps people there survive. Two of his
novels (Beyond the Bedroom Wall: A Family Album, 1975; Born Brothers, 1988), a number
of his short stories, and some of his poems
focus on North Dakota people and on the
Northern Plains experience. Whether a specific
work is set in North Dakota or not, a
sense of place, of family, and of God permeates
Woiwode's writing, especially in his semi-autobiographical
Beyond the Bedroom Wall.
One reads this novel as if paging through a
family picture album full of places, biographical
vignettes, fragments of memories, and
longer reminiscences that leave the reader curious
about the characters and incidents recorded
in the "snapshots." Parts 1 and 2, set in
rural North Dakota, trace the history of the
family through four generations, until they
move to Illinois.

As of 1998, Woiwode had written three
other novels (What I'm Going to Do, I Think,
1969; Poppa John, 1981; Indian Affairs, 1992),
two volumes of short stories (The Neumiller Stories, 1989; Silent Passengers, 1993), and two
of poetry (Poetry North: Five Poets of North Dakota, 1970; Even Tide, 1977). In addition
to published interviews, Woiwode has short
stories, poems, and nonfiction pieces that
have not yet been collected. Woiwode is a
careful craftsman, a compelling storyteller,
and a stylist with a gift for both lyrical and
precise expression.


Denis R. Fournier
University of Mary




Gardner, John. "The Family of a Man and the Family of
Man." Review of Beyond the Bedroom Wall: A Family Album,
by Larry Woiwode. New York Times Book Review,
September 28, 1975, 1–2. Quantic, Diane Dufva. The Nature of the Place: A Study of Great Plains Fiction. Lincoln:
University of Nebraska Press, 1995.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>