<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.war.010</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Cheyenne Mountain</field>
      <field name="author">Arnold, David C.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CHEYENNE MOUNTAIN

Entrance to U. S. Government's Cheyenne Mountain command center


In a hollowed-out mountain in the Colorado
Rockies, overlooking the Great Plains, is the
command center that would sound the first
alarm of ballistic missile or air attacks against
North America. The North American Aerospace
Defense Command (NORAD), hidden in
Cheyenne Mountain Air Force Station, near
Colorado Springs, Colorado, keeps watch on
aircraft, missiles, and space systems posing a
threat to the United States and Canada. Cheyenne
Mountain is the hub of a communications
system that uses satellites, microwave,
and fiber-optic links, carrying information
from computers around the world to the
NORAD commander in chief and his advisers
in the command center. There, they constantly
assess the aerospace situation on computer
screens that display missile warning and
aerospace surveillance information.

Built between 1961 and 1966, at a total cost
of $142.4 million, the construction required
more than one million pounds of explosives
and removed more than 693,000 tons of granite.
The main excavation consists of three
chambers, each 45 feet wide, 60 feet high, and
588 feet long. Seven thousand tons of steel
were used for the fifteen two- and three-story
buildings inside the mountain. The facility
has built-in utilities and services to make it
fully self-sufficient for up to thirty days in
case of national emergency. The massive blast
doors, each more than three feet thick and
with a swing weight of thirty tons, can be
closed in forty-five seconds. Approximately
200 men and women from the army, navy,
marines, air force, and Canadian forces staff
the operations centers at Cheyenne Mountain.
About 20,000 tourists visit each year.


David C. Arnold
United States Air Force Academy




Air Force Space Command Public Affairs. Cheyenne
Mountain Air Force Base. August 1993.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>