<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.068</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Reform Party</field>
      <field name="author">Harrison, Trevor</field>
      <field name="text">

 




REFORM PARTY

The Reform Party of Canada was founded in
1987 by Preston Manning, son of a former Alberta
premier, as a right-wing populist party
with strong regional support in western Canada,
especially Alberta and British Columbia.
Over the next few years the party steadily
grew, reaching its zenith in the Canadian election
of June 1997, when it won sixty seats (out
of a total of 301), thus making it Her Majesty's
Official Opposition to the victorious Liberal
Party.

The Reform Party's immediate rise stemmed
from disgruntlement on the part of a number
of prominent western conservatives with the
policies of the governing federal Progressive
Conservative Party. Reform's cultural and
ideological roots, however, were much older.
Reform espoused populist notions of direct
democracy (referendums, initiatives, and recall),
brought to the Canadian West in the
early part of the twentieth century by farmers'
parties from the American Midwest. Like
these parties, much of Reform's appeal arose
out of a sense of regional economic and political
alienation. Reform's populism, however,
was also textured by other, later contacts with
the American Great Plains. Particularly influential
were American oil companies and their
personnel from the states of Texas, Oklahoma,
California, and Louisiana who developed Alberta's
oil industry after 1947 and who infused
that province's local political culture with beliefs
supportive of free enterprise, low taxes,
and minimal government. Reform was the vehicle
for this right-populist and moral conservative
tradition in Canada, much as the Republican
Party is in the United States.

At the same time, Reform's appeal can only
be understood in the specific context of social
and political changes that occurred in Canada
after the 1960s, including a series of wrenching
federal-provincial constitutional conflicts.
The Reform Party was particularly opposed to
Canada's official policies of bilingualism and
multiculturalism, continued high levels of immigration,
and "special interest" groups. It
was Reform's staunch opposition to the granting
of special constitutional status to Quebec,
however, that garnered the party its greatest
political support.

Reform failed to win a seat in the 1988 Canadian
election. Between 1990 and 1992, however,
a series of failures to ratify changes to
Canada's constitution threatened a political
crisis. Quebec separatism was on the rise;
public anger and anxiety outside of Quebec
escalated. In this highly charged emotional
context, Reform support rose dramatically.

In the 1993 Canadian election, Reform won
fifty-two seats. All but one of Reform's victories
were in the West: twenty-two seats of twenty-six
in Alberta, twenty-four of thirty in British Columbia,
four in Saskatchewan, and one in Manitoba.
Reform's lone "nonwestern" seat was in
Ontario. The results left Reform as Canada's
third party, behind the governing Liberals and
the separatist Bloc Quebecois, who formed
Canada's Official Opposition party.

After 1993 Reform attempted to broaden its
national appeal. While the party remained fiscally
conservative, it toned down its regionalist
rhetoric and attempted to soften its image as
intolerant of minorities. These efforts brought
mixed results in the election of 1997. Though
the party garnered Official Opposition status,
it seemed more than ever trapped in its western
base. In this context, Manning and others
renewed efforts to unite Canada's right wing
and create a national alternative to the governing
Liberals. In the spring of 2000 Reform
Party members voted to transform the party
into the Canadian Alliance Party. Subsequently,
a new leader was chosen, Stockwell
Day, a former Conservative politician in Alberta.
Later that same year, Day's Alliance
Party won sixty-six seats, repeating Reform's
success in becoming the Official Opposition to
the victorious Liberals. Again, however, the
party's support was largely confined to its
western bastion. Moreover, its success was
short-lived, as Day and the party quickly fell in
the polls amid infighting and widespread perceptions
of ineptitude. Alliance's public humiliation
made many yearn for a resurrection
of its Reform predecessor.


Trevor Harrison
University of Alberta




Flanagan, Tom. Waiting for the Wave: The Reform Party
and Preston Manning. Toronto: Stoddart Publishing Company
Ltd., 1995. Harrison, Trevor. Of Passionate Intensity:
Right-Wing Populism and the Reform Party of Canada.
Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 1995.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>