<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.afam.013</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Christian, Charlie (1916–1942)</field>
      <field name="author">Broadbent, Peter</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CHARLIE CHRISTIAN (1916-1942)

Charles Henry Christian
    

Charles Henry Christian was born to musical
parents in Bonham, Texas, on July 29, 1916.
His father, Clarence James, played trumpet,
and his mother, Willie Mae, played piano.
They are known to have played professionally
in silent-movie theaters. Charlie had two elder
brothers–Edward (born 1906), who was a
fine pianist, and Clarence (born 1911), who
occasionally played string bass and violin.

In 1918 Clarence, Charlie's father, became
blind following an unknown illness. As a direct
result the family moved from Bonham to
live in Oklahoma City. Charlie started first
grade in 1923 at Douglass School but apparently
didn't attend school too often, preferring
to earn money on the streets playing his
ukulele.

He spent the Depression years playing in a
variety of bands and at diverse locations. In
1930 Charlie played at Honey Murphey's Club
with members of his brother Edward's band,
together with members of McKinney's Cotton
Pickers Orchestra, which included Don Redman.
By 1932 Charlie had left school and become
a full-time musician, playing wherever
he could to earn a living but mostly with his
brother Edward's band, which varied between
four and thirteen pieces. T-Bone Walker tells
of coming to Oklahoma City in 1933 with the
Lawson Brooks Band and playing with Charlie
on the streets as a duo. They had a bass and
guitar and would play, sing, and dance together.
When T-Bone had to leave town suddenly,
Charlie took his place in the band. By
1935 Charlie was a regular member of the
Rhymaires Orchestra, which was featured at
the Ritz Ballroom, broadcasting weekly over
local radio. In 1936 Charlie played at the Texas
Centennial celebrations, from which he returned
with the Alphonso Trent Band. During
the winter of 1936–37 Charlie played with the
Trent band in Casper, Wyoming, and at a
lengthy engagement in Deadwood, South Dakota.
From the summer of 1937 on, Charlie
was featured on electric guitar with the Anna
Mae Winburn Orchestra. The band, based in
Omaha, Nebraska, traveled extensively, going
as far afield as Illinois and Minnesota in
1938. Charlie also played a residency with
the Alphonso Trent Sextet in Bismarck, North
Dakota, in the summer of 1938.

Charlie's big break came in July 1939 when,
following a recommendation by Mary Lou
Williams, John Hammond of Columbia Records,
on his way to oversee a Benny Goodman
recording session in Los Angeles, stopped in
Oklahoma City to audition Charlie and his
sextet. A short time later Charlie received
a telegram from Hammond telling him to
come to Los Angeles to play with Benny Goodman.
Fortunately for the world of jazz, Charlie
became a featured member of the Goodman
Sextet, recording regularly and being
heard weekly on radio broadcasts transmitted
throughout the United States. After the reopening
of Minton's Playhouse in October
1940, Charlie was co-opted into the house
band and played almost every evening, following
his work with Goodman, with such
bebop luminaries as Dizzy Gillespie, Thelonious
Monk, and Kenny Clarke.

In July 1941 Charlie was hospitalized with a
recurrence of tuberculosis. He died in Seaview
Sanitarium on Staten Island on March 2, 1942.
With his tragic early death, jazz lost one of its
great innovators, the man who brought the
electric guitar into the forefront of popular
music.


Peter Broadbent
Barry, Vale of Glamorgan, United Kingdom




Broadbent, Peter. Charlie Christian. Blaydon UK: Ashley
Mark, 2002.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>