<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.gen.026</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Native American Gender Roles</field>
      <field name="author">Wishart, David J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




NATIVE AMERICAN GENDER ROLES

Traditionally, Plains Indian gender roles were
well defined, and men's and women's responsibilities
were equally crucial to the functioning,
even the survival, of their societies. Consequently,
both men and women were respected
for doing their jobs well, although this is
not how early European American observers
saw it.

Such observers, coming from societies which
held that women–gentlewomen, that is–
should be cloistered and protected, were
aghast at the workload that Plains Indian
women carried. They witnessed them, from
varying societies and at various times of the
year, clearing fields, planting, hoeing, and harvesting;
digging cache pits and storing food;
erecting and dismantling lodges and tipis; collecting
wild plants and firewood; cooking,
hauling water, and washing dishes; transporting
possessions, generally on foot, on bison
hunts; making household items, including
pottery and clothing; and child rearing. This
workload increased during the first half of
the nineteenth century as the fur trade raised
the demands for dressed skins and robes.
Meanwhile, the European American observers,
often only transitory travelers, saw Indian
men sitting around the village or encampment,
smoking, gambling, perhaps mending
a weapon or caring for a horse. The men
seemed to have all the power; the women
seemed to do all the work.

Visitors who lived with Plains Indians for
more extended periods of time, including
early anthropologists like Alice Fletcher, saw
a much more complex division of labor and
distribution of authority. There is no doubt
that Plains Indian women worked hard, but
they were held in high esteem for the elemental
role they played in supporting village life.
Among the farming Indians of the eastern
Plains at least, women provided most of the
food in most years; even in the bison-hunting
societies of the western Plains they provided
significant amounts of food through collection
of wild plants and berries, and they processed
the meat obtained on the hunt.

While it is true that the women generally
played a subordinate role in ceremonial life
and lacked formal political power (you will
look in vain for a Plains Indian woman's signature
on a treaty with the United States),
they had types of political power that contemporary
American women lacked. In the agricultural
societies–the Pawnees and Omahas
of Nebraska, for example–they owned the
lodge, tipi, and its contents; the fields, seeds,
and implements of production; and they had
the right to trade their surplus crops. On the
bison hunts they often made the decision on
where to camp, and in the lodge the senior
wife (for sororal polygamy was the norm) was
the main decision maker. Women also had the
right to divorce, and since they owned the
lodge, an unkind husband could find himself
homeless, with only his horse and weapons to
his name. Women were also held in high esteem
for their craft work, they played an important
role in healing (especially in problems
associated with childbirth), and they took care
of religious items, a responsibility of the highest
order.

Men's roles were equally misunderstood by
early European American travelers. Men were
responsible for hunting, defensive and aggressive
warfare, manufacturing of weapons, and
nearly all societywide political and religious
operations. Observers who saw Indian men in
their villages saw them "off work," although
often they did help the women in the fields or
in the construction of a lodge. Men's work took
them away from the village, and it was dangerous.
They hunted on increasingly contested
bison ranges and journeyed hundreds of miles
to enemy encampments to steal horses and to
win honors. The reciprocity of the gender roles
is made clear by the hard facts of Indian demography:
in most, if not all, Plains Indian
societies in the mid–nineteenth century there
were far more women than men. Women often
died at an early age, worn down by a life of hard
work and frequent childbearing, but men died
in greater numbers and at earlier ages, victims
of their dangerous occupations. Only in the
late nineteenth century, when wars among the
tribes and with the United States were curtailed,
did the gender ratios equalize. By that
time men and women alike were equally likely
to die from diseases caused by poverty, such as
tuberculosis.

The gender roles devised over generations
by traditional Plains Indian societies persisted
for so long because they worked to keep the
family and the band or tribe intact. In the
last decades of the nineteenth century, the Canadian
and U.S. governments launched a concerted
attack on the traditional roles of Indian
men and women: Indian men were to become
farmers or blacksmiths, and Indian women
were to become housewives, in keeping with
European American concepts of "civilized" divisions
of labor. Indian extended families were
to be fragmented into nuclear families, each
occupying an individual allotment. These imposed
changes were resisted, but Indian men's
traditional roles were fast disappearing, and
as the weight of supporting families fell increasingly
on the women, so did relative
power. This shift has continued to this day.

On Plains reservations and reserves in the
early twenty-first century, women are more
likely than men to have completed high school
and to hold jobs outside the home. They
are often the chief providers for the household,
while Indian men frequently take over
the child care, cooking, and cleaning. Such
changes bring with them benefits, such as
increased authority for women and closer
father-child relationships for men, but they
also bring the stresses of added responsibilities
and altered self-images.


David J. Wishart
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Albers, Patricia, and Beatrice Medicine. The Hidden Half: Studies of Plains Indian Women. Washington DC: University
Press of America, 1983. Billson, Janet Mancini. "Standing
Tradition on Its Head: Role Reversal among Blood
Indian Couples." Great Plains Quarterly 11 (1991): 3–22.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>