<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.mus.004</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Baker, Chet (1929-1988)</field>
      <field name="author">Wilkinson, Jay</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BAKER, CHET (1929-1988)

Chet Baker with trumpet
    

Chet Baker was a jazz trumpeter and extraordinary
musical stylist who helped define the
"cool jazz" era of the 1950s. He was born
in Yale, Oklahoma, on December 23, 1929.
When he was about eleven years old his family
moved to California, where the cool jazz
movement would later thrive. Baker developed
his trumpet-playing ability in the Glendale
High School band and in the army. His philosophy
of jazz was formed in the jazz clubs along
Central Avenue in Los Angeles. In 1951, after
his second discharge from the army, he began
playing with Charlie Parker after winning an
audition that Parker had staged at the Tiffany
Club.

But it was Gerry Mulligan, a popular arranger
and composer during the 1940s, who
launched Baker's career with the Mulligan
quartet in 1952. Theoretically, this unique
quartet, which consisted only of bass, drums,
baritone saxophone, and trumpet but excluded
piano and guitar, should have had a
thin, dead sound, with limited possibility for
creativity. However, due to the players' talent
and vision, the Mulligan quartet was very well
received, and Chet Baker became famous. He
was even named the best trumpeter of 1954 by
Down Beat magazine. Baker was a member of
the Mulligan quartet for only one year. Despite
a drug dependency, he maintained a steady
international solo career from the time he
left the quartet until his mysterious death on
May 13, 1988, when his body was found on the
sidewalk in front of his hotel in Amsterdam.

Chet Baker is remembered for his velvety
tone, his uncanny ability to create beautiful
musical lines during improvisation solos,
and his masterful phrasing. He was also well
known for his smooth, laid-back singing voice.
With his handsome face, rebellious gaze, and
interpretation of songs like "You've Changed"
and "My Funny Valentine," he personified cool
and radiated romance.


Jay Wilkinson
University of Oklahoma




Carr, Roy. A Century of Jazz. New York: Da Capo Press,
1997. Gioia, Ted. West Coast Jazz: Modern Jazz in California, 1945–1960. Berkeley: University of California Press,
1998. Morgenstern, Dan. Jazz People. New York: Da Capo
Press, 1976.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>