<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.edu.029</field>
      <field name="titleMain">National Cowyboy Hall of Fame and Western Heritage Center</field>
      <field name="author">Van Deventer, M. J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




NATIONAL COWYBOY HALL OF FAME AND WESTERN HERITAGE CENTER

There's no better place to learn about the history
and art of the West than the National
Cowboy Hall of Fame and Western Heritage
Center, a sprawling, 80,000 square-foot
museum located atop Persimmon Hill overlooking
old Route 66 in Oklahoma City, Oklahoma.
The center attracts about 350,000 visitors
each year.

The center, founded in 1955, was the dream
of the president of Lee Jeans, Chester A. Reynolds.
A Kansas City, Missouri, entrepreneur,
he had long been concerned about preserving
the country's western heritage. When the museum
o.cially opened in 1965, actor John
Wayne was parade marshal. He served on the
center's board of directors for more than a decade,
and his numerous collections are among
the museum's treasures. Dedicated to the
memory of those who settled the West, the
museum quickly began to acquire, catalog,
and exhibit art, artifacts, and archival material
that pay homage to America's favorite icon,
the American cowboy.

Separating myth from reality has always
been one of the center's major missions. The
reality is found in three major halls of fame,
all within the institution. The Hall of Great
Westerners honors those who have made significant
contributions to the development
of the West. The Hall of Great Western Performers
honors those who have contributed
to the Western genre on stage, screen, and
television. Its inductees are honored each year
during the Academy Awards–style Western
Heritage Awards ceremony. The Rodeo Hall of
Fame honorees, chosen by the Rodeo Historical
Society, are honored each October. The
American Rodeo Gallery displays memorabilia
of these rodeo greats.

Reality and myths mingle in the museum's
western art collection, including works by
such famous artists as Charles M. Russell,
Frederic Remington, Albert Bierstadt, and
William R. Leigh. The work of contemporary
artists is found in the center's Prix de West
Collection, honoring the annual Prix de West
Award winner during the Prix de West Invitational
Exhibition. Held each June, the exhibition
features the work of more than ninety of
the country's most prominent western artists.

Among recent additions to the museum's
showcase of western art and artifacts is the
Arthur and Shifra Silberman Native American
Art Gallery, which presents a narrative from
ledger art to contemporary Indian work. The
American Cowboy Gallery traces cowboy culture
from its vaquero roots to today's cowboy.
The Western Entertainment Gallery highlights
the films of early Western movie stars.
Prosperity Junction, an authentic turn-of-the-century
western town, shows how communities
developed in the Old West. The Children's
Cowboy Corral provides an interactive experience
about western legends.

A constantly changing exhibition schedule
explores aspects of the West from fashion,
cowboy gear, and photography to notables
such as Hopalong Cassidy and Frederic Remington.
Special events round out the museum's
program, including the annual Chuckwagon
Gathering and Children's Festival, a
biannual Cowboy Poetry Festival, a Visions of
the West Gala honoring patrons, and Michael
Martin Murphey's Cowboy Christmas Ball.

What often impresses visitors most is the
sense of monumentality that the museum
now expresses in its massive Canyon Princess,
Welcome Sundown, and End of the Trail sculptures
that are among the first works of art
greeting guests. What often lingers with them
is the memory of viewing the five monumental
western landscape triptychs painted
by Wilson Hurley. These massive paintings,
housed in the Sam Noble Special Events Center,
serve as true "windows to the West" for
museum visitors.

See also IMAGES AND ICONS: Cowboy Culture / 
SPORTS AND RECREATION: Rodeo.

National Cowboy Hall of Fame website.


M. J. Van Deventer
National Cowboy and Western Heritage Museum




Van Deventer, M. J., ed. Visions of the West: A Tribute
to Leadership. Oklahoma City: National Cowboy Hall of
Fame, 1997.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>