<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fol.026</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Insect Lore</field>
      <field name="author">Lockwood, Jeffrey A.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




INSECT LORE

The folklore of the Great Plains touches on
many insects, including buffalo gnats and
Mormon crickets, but no creature so permeates
the culture of this region as the grasshopper–
and the Rocky Mountain locust (Melanoplus
spretus) in particular (a locust is a type of
grasshopper capable of forming immense, migratory
swarms). During periods of favorable
weather, these insects erupted from their "permanent
breeding zones" in the fertile river valleys
and spread over an area of nearly two
million square miles. For half a century, outbreaks
of this locust devastated farms in every
state and province of the Great Plains, and this
species was declared the single greatest impediment
to the settlement of the region.

Glacial deposits containing frozen locusts
in the Rocky Mountains reveal that outbreaks
have occurred for at least 1,000 years, but European
settlers first reported seeing swarms in
1818. Major outbreaks developed in 1855–57
and 1864–67, but the folklore of this locust
was established with the swarms of 1873–78
(1874 was called the "Grasshopper Year" in
Kansas). Laura Ingalls Wilder's description,
from On the Banks of Plum Creek, is classic:
"The cloud was hailing grasshoppers. The
cloud was grasshoppers. Their bodies hid the
sun and made darkness. . . . The rasping whirring
of their wings filled the whole air and
they hit the ground and the house with the
noise of a hailstorm. . . . Laura had to step
on grasshoppers and they smashed squirming
and slimy under her feet."

In fruitless efforts to fight the swarms that
stripped the land of all vegetation, shredded
laundry, and infested larders, people used
smoky fires, burning trenches, and various
contraptions, such as a horse-drawn device to
scoop and smash the insects. Governments offered
bounties for locust eggs ($5 per bushel),
and the eggs were even used as a form of local
currency. Kansas attempted to assemble a
"grasshopper army," requiring every ablebodied
male from age twelve to sixty-five to
fight the locusts. Townspeople reported that
"heavy freight trains were delayed for hours
by their [the locusts'] gathering on the track
in large numbers, the wheels crushing their
bodies and forming an oily, soapy substance,
which caused the wheels to spin around and
around, with no power to go forward." Some
interpreted the swarms as a punishment sent
by Providence. This notion was disputed by a
state entomologist who headed a section of his
report "Not a Divine Visitation."

The catastrophe became the material of tall
tales, like the one about a man who, when
plowing his field, hung his work jacket on a
post, leaving his watch in the pocket. When he
came back to get his jacket, all that was left was
the watch–because the grasshoppers had
eaten his jacket. Another humorous bit of
folklore recounted the man who left his team
in the field while he went to his well for a
drink of water. When he came back the grasshoppers
had eaten up the team and harness
and were playing horseshoes with the iron
shoes the horses had worn.

When the outbreak of the 1870s abated, the
Rocky Mountain locust once again concentrated
in the fertile river valleys. At the same
time, settlers were converging into these regions,
converting them into farmland and effectively
destroying the habitat needed by the
locust during its recession periods. In doing
so, farmers managed to inadvertently drive
their most severe competitor to extinction,
leaving North America without a locust species.
The Rocky Mountain locust lives on only
in folklore; the last living specimen was collected
in 1902.

See also PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT: Grasshoppers.


Jeffrey A. Lockwood
University of Wyoming




Lockwood, Jeffrey A., and Larry D. DeBrey. "A Solution
for the Sudden and Unexplained Extinction of the Rocky
Mountain Locust, Melanoplus spretus (Walsh)." Environmental Entomology 19 (1990): 1194-1205. Welsh, Roger L. A Treasury of Nebraska Pioneer Folklore. Lincoln: University
of Nebraska Press, 1966.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>