<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.gen.028</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Persons Case</field>
      <field name="author">Kaye, Frances W.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




PERSONS CASE

The "Persons Case" was raised by five Alberta
women and resulted in the October 18,
1929, decision by the British Privy Council
that women were legally "persons," not just
in Canada but throughout the whole British
Empire.

The case had its roots back in 1916, when
Emily Murphy took her seat in Edmonton as
the first woman police magistrate in the empire.
A lawyer against whose client she had
ruled claimed that, as a woman, she was not a
"person" in terms of the British North America
Act, Canada's enabling legislation, and
hence was not eligible to serve as a magistrate.
The lawyer did not follow up his objection,
but ten years later Justice Murphy began to be
considered for appointment as Canada's first
woman senator. The British North America
Act allowed qualified "persons" to sit in the
Senate, but an 1876 British court had ruled
that "women are persons in matters of pains
and penalties, but are not persons in matters
of rights and privileges." Murphy joined forces
with four others–Nellie McClung and Louise
McKinney, both suffrage leaders and former
members of the Alberta Legislative Assembly;
Henrietta Muir Edwards, an expert on women's
legal status; and provincial cabinet minister
Irene Parlby–to ask for an interpretation
of the act. When the Supreme Court of Canada
ruled that women were not "persons" in
the senatorial sense, the five women pursued
the case to the British Privy Council, then
Canada's court of last resort, which eventually
admitted that women were "persons."

A statue commemorating the "Famous
Five" was erected in Calgary, Alberta, in 1999.


Frances W. Kaye
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Prentice, Alison, Paula Bourne, Gail Cuthbert Brandt, Beth
Light, Wendy Mitchison, and Naomi Black. Canadian Women: A History. Toronto: Harcourt Brace Canada, 1996.
Savage, Candace. Our Nell: A Scrapbook Biography of Nellie L. McClung. Saskatoon: Western Producer Prairie Books,
1979.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>