<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.tra.010</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Durant, Thomas (1820-1885)</field>
      <field name="author">Gery, Alan H.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




DURANT, THOMAS (1820-1885)

Thomas Clark Durant was born in Lee, Massachusetts,
on February 6, 1820. He graduated
from Albany Medical College in 1840 and
married Heloise Hannah Timbrel in 1847.
They had two children. Durant briefly served
as a professor of medicine at Albany Medical
College but subsequently channeled his energy
into business. A railroad promoter and
contractor, Thomas Durant's importance to
the Great Plains lies in his controlling of route
choice and construction as vice president of
the Union Pacific Railroad.

To encourage what Robert W. Fogel has
called a "premature enterprise," in 1862, 1864,
and 1866 Congress provided incentives and set
standards for a transcontinental railroad. The
Union Pacific was organized to gain the promised
loans and land. Besides his vice presidency
in the Union Pacific, Durant had major
financial interests in the companies he used to
grade and lay the track, companies that were
paid in money and Union Pacific stock.

With ongoing control of the company assured,
the contractors, through Durant, chose
a line that maximized construction profits
with little concern for potential traffic or later
operating costs and profits. In the race with
the Central Pacific for subsidized mileage, the
Union Pacific did not go through the existing
Plains settlement at Denver. The expected expenses
and slow progress of a line pushed
through the rugged mountains to the west
were too great. On the Plains Durant's chosen
route followed the Platte River to Lodgepole
Creek and the relatively easy Gangplank over
the Laramie Range. As Congress intended, the
railroad strengthened Council Bluffs and
Omaha, but it was Durant's direction that
founded new towns westward to Cheyenne
and beyond.

Following charges of defrauding the Union
Pacific Durant was dropped from the company's
directorate in May 1869. In 1870 he sold
almost all of his Union Pacific stock. Much of
his fortune was lost in the panic of 1873. With
his health deteriorating, Durant retired to the
Adirondacks. He died at North Creek, New
York, on October 15, 1885.


Alan H. Grey
Provo, Utah




Dodge, Grenville M. How We Built the Union Pacific Railway.
Washington dc: Government Printing Office, 1910.
Hirshon, Stanley P. Grenville M. Dodge: Soldier, Politician,
Railroad Pioneer. Bloomington: Indiana University Press,
1967.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>