<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.wat.034</field>
      <field name="titleMain">U.S. Army Corps of Engineers</field>
      <field name="author">Hotchkiss, Rollin H.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




U.S. ARMY CORPS OF ENGINEERS

The U.S. Army Corps of Engineers (COE)
dates back to 1779, when Congress formed the
unit for military support purposes. Public
works projects, employing citizens outside the
military to work for the COE, began in 1824
with work to improve navigation on the Ohio
and Mississippi Rivers. The initial and continuing
focus of the Army Corps of Engineers
in the Great Plains is the Missouri River.

The Corps's presence on the Plains began in
1867 when Capt. Charles W. Howell spent
three months on a survey of the Missouri
River from Sioux City, Iowa, to Fort Benton,
Montana. His purpose was to map major
sandbars and snags for those using the Missouri
for military purposes or for transportation
to the Montana goldfields.

Since that first expedition, the objectives of
the COE on the Missouri have been to control
bank erosion, improve navigation, and provide
flood control. All three goals were placed
within reach in the 1950s with the completion
of six dams on the river from Montana to
South Dakota. Financed mostly by the Pick-Sloan
Plan, the dams reduced floods sufficiently
to allow the COE to complete their
work on bank stabilization and to create a
nine-foot-deep navigation channel from the
mouth of the Missouri at St. Louis to Sioux
City. The coe has also constructed smaller
dams on Salt and Papillion Creeks in southeastern
Nebraska and constructed levees along
hundreds of miles of Missouri River tributaries,
including the Big Sioux and Floyd Rivers
of Iowa.

The very nature of the Missouri River has
been changed by coe intervention. What was
once a shallow, swift-flowing river that ranged
in width and was capable of moving tremendous
loads of silt and sand has been transformed
into a relatively narrow, uniform, lowsediment
transportation route. Views of the
river near Plattsmouth, Nebraska, taken from
1934 to 1983, show the dramatic transformations
that have taken place. The strategic
placement of wooden and rock dikes has encouraged
sediment deposition near the stream
banks, leaving flow to be concentrated in the
nine-foot-deep navigational channel, which is
self-scouring and normally does not require
dredging.

The changing nature of society in the Great
Plains is reflected in the current debate over
the prioritized operation of Missouri River
dams. For example, flood protection and navigation
have been important priorities when
deciding on water releases from the dams.
However, because of increased recreational
benefits at the reservoirs and the occurrence
of several endangered species throughout the
river system, there have been calls for expanded
priorities. The revision of the COE's
Master Manual for the operation of the main
stem dams is a subject of ongoing work and
controversy.

The COE is organized into eight divisions
spanning the United States. The Great Plains
is contained within the recently formed Missouri
River Region of the Northwest Division,
comprising the Missouri and Columbia River
basins. The Missouri River Region is composed
of the Kansas City and Omaha Districts.

U.S. Army Corps of Engineers website.


Rollin H. Hotchkiss
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Brey, Debra, Connie Carman, and Kettie Parks, eds. The
Federal Engineer: Damsites to Missile Sites. A History of the
Omaha District of the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers. Washington
DC: Government Printing Office, 1984. Essayons
(Let Us Try): The History of the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers.
Washington DC: Government Printing Office, 1991.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>