<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.wat.006</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Colorado Doctrine</field>
      <field name="author">Josephson, Theron</field>
      <field name="text">

 




COLORADO DOCTRINE

The Colorado Doctrine set the standards under
which a jurisdiction accepts appropriation
water law as the fundamental and exclusive
water law. The Colorado Doctrine is also
known as the doctrine of pure appropriation.
It contrasts with systems under which appropriative
law coexists with other types of water
law.

The doctrine was developed in the late
nineteenth century and is named for the state
in which it originated. Colorado had adopted
appropriation law in its constitution upon
statehood (1876), declaring that rivers in the
state belonged not to the federal government
but to Coloradans, who could appropriate
them. Still, questions remained as to the application
of common law riparian rights in
conjunction with appropriation rights. Up
until that time most decisions regarding appropriation
law mirrored those in California,
where appropriation originated. However, at
the time of Colorado statehood California's
water law system had evolved to also recognize
common law riparian rights, appropriative
water rights, and Spanish pueblo rights.

In 1882 the Colorado Supreme Court settled
Colorado's water law issue in the case of Coffin
v. Left Hand Ditch Company, a water dispute
between agricultural interests in northeastern
Colorado. The court found that the water user
who had established the first use of the water
had the superior right to continue his or her
use despite a riparian claim by an opposing
party. The court concluded that riparian law
did not exist in Colorado and established the
appropriation doctrine as the exclusive water
law of the state. Later, among Plains states,
Wyoming (1896), New Mexico (1900), and
Montana (1921) adopted the Colorado model.


Theron Josephson
Ferris State University




Dunbar, Robert G. Forging New Rights in Western Water.
Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1983. Hutchins, W.
A. Water Rights in the Nineteen Western States. Washington
DC: Government Printing Office, 1974. Trelease, Frank
J., and George A. Gould. Cases and Materials on Water
Law, 4th ed. St. Paul MN: West Publishing Company, 1986.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>