<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.sr.017</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Fishing</field>
      <field name="author">Berger, Tommie</field>
      <field name="text">

 




FISHING

Recreational fishing in the Great Plains is
about as diverse as any angler wants to make it.
Cold-water species such as trout and salmon
can be found in the foothills of the Rocky
Mountains and even out onto the Plains in
cold-water streams and in stocked winter fisheries.
Cool-water species–northern pike,
walleye, smallmouth bass, and yellow perch, to
name a few–abound in the northern part of
the Plains and in some of the deeper artificial
reservoirs. And, of course, warm-water species
abound in the multitude of farm ponds, small
lakes, reservoirs, and stream and river systems
that drain this rich agricultural region. These
species include the catfish, largemouth bass,
crappie, other sunfish species, white bass, the
landlocked striped bass, the relatively new
hybrid wiper and saugeye, and a myriad of
other game and non game fishes.

When it comes to fishing opportunities, anglers
in the Great Plains probably have more
different opportunities than anywhere else in
the United States and Canada. In the northern
part of this region, walleye rank high on the
popularity list, while the southern angler
would likely put the black bass at or near the
top. In the Central Plains, catfish are an important
item on the anglers' list. But specialized
anglers who belong to a striper tournament
circuit, a fly-fishing organization, or a
local bass club, who fish in the yearly carp
derby, or who simply dunk a worm for anything
they can catch are everywhere.

Nationwide in the United States, fishing remains
the number two water-related outdoor
sport, with nearly 45 million participants, according
to a 1997 survey from the National
Sporting Goods Association. Among all indoor
and outdoor sports, fishing is seventh.
Statistics from the 1996 National Survey of
Fishing, Hunting, and Wildlife-Associated
Recreation conducted by the U.S. Fish and
Wildlife Service indicate that recreational fishing
produced $108 billion and created more
than 1.2 million full-time jobs in 1996. In Kansas
in 1996, for example, fishing was worth
$357 million to the state's economy and created
the equivalent of 4,922 full-time jobs. In
Nebraska, the economic benefit of fishing to
the state was even greater, at $427 million and
6,448 jobs. Texas ranks second in the nation,
behind only California, with $6.4 billion in
revenues from fishing and 80,282 associated
jobs (these figures include parts of Texas that
are not part of the Great Plains). Clearly,
throughout the Great Plains fishing is a significant
economic enterprise as well as an integral
part of regional culture.

See also PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT: Fish.


Tommie Berger
Kansas Department of Wildlife and Parks




American Sportsfishing Association. Economic Impact of
Sportsfishing in the United States. Alexandria VA: American
Sportsfishing Association, 1996.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>