<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ct.046</field>
      <field name="titleMain">San Angelo, Texas</field>
      <field name="author">Flemming, Elvis E.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SAN ANGELO, TEXAS


San Angelo, Texas, ca. 1886


The city of San Angelo is located at the confluence
of the North and South Concho Rivers
near where the 100th meridian and the thirtyfirst
line of latitude intersect. This part of
Texas was once the homeland of the Jumano
Indians. The region around this modern-day
city became a center of European activity in
the 1620s, when Spanish missionaries began
ministering to local Indian groups. The permanent
settlement of San Angelo may be
dated to 1867, when the U.S. government established
Fort Concho as part of a series of
forts intended to protect westering settlers. In
1870 a San Antonio entrepreneur named Bart
DeWitt purchased land along the Concho
River (and opposite Fort Concho) with intentions
of founding a town, but the village struggled
in its early years. Initially, it survived by
meeting the numerous needs of military personnel
and their families.

One reason why San Angelo struggled during
its early years was that most local commercial
establishments were located at the nearby
village of Ben Ficklin, the center of a stage
line extending into California. But a devastating
flood in 1882 destroyed that tough little
way station, and six years later the Santa Fe
Railroad connected San Angelo to the outside
world and ensured its growth. The city by the
Conchos flourished.

While Fort Concho had provided much of
the economic stimulus for San Angelo during
its early days, that ended when the federal
government closed the installation in 1889. (In
the 1980s and 1990s city o.cials restored the
fort. It is now a main point of interest for
tourists.) By the late nineteenth century, San
Angelo had become a major center for sheep
and cattle ranching. In the early 1900s farmers
in surrounding areas began growing cotton,
and that enterprise also proved profitable.
Wildcatters struck oil in areas close to the city
in the early 1920s, and the oil industry stimulated
economic growth: banks, department
stores, construction, and real estate activity
boomed. The San Angelo economy early became
diversified, and diversification has been
sustained with the later addition of more than
120 manufacturing plants, modern medical
facilities, and a military presence in the form
of Goodfellow Air Force Base.

Among the notable figures who have played
a hand in shaping the city's destiny is Margaret
A. Shannon, a philanthropist whose large fortune
funded the establishment of the Shannon
Medical Center in 1932; it remains among the
most important medical facilities in West
Texas. After World War II, Houston Harte arrived
in the city to become the editor of the
San Angelo Standard-Times. He became involved
in historic preservation, founded his
own profitable private businesses, and participated
in numerous civic causes. During a
period of almost three decades in the late
twentieth century, Dr. Lloyd D. Vincent transformed
the local junior college into Angelo
State University, which had an enrollment of
6,300 in 2000.

San Angelo's population growth has reflected
its economic development. Between
1920 and 1930, as the oil boom struck, the
city's population more than doubled to 25,309.
The establishment of Goodfellow Air Force
Base in 1950 resulted in another growth spurt,
with the population climbing to 52,093 by
1950. The diverse economy and San Angelo's
attractiveness as a retirement center have kept
the population curve rising–to 73,240 in 1980,
84,474 in 1990, and 88,439 in 2000.


Elvis E. Fleming
Historical Society for Southeast New Mexico




Clemens, Gus. The Concho Country. San Antonio: Mulberry
Books, 1980.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>