<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.033</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Indian Country</field>
      <field name="author">Sutton, Imre</field>
      <field name="text">

 




INDIAN COUNTRY

"Indian Country" refers to a variable geographic
place where Native Americans reside
on trust lands–reserves and reservations. The
term is in use in both Canada and the United
States, but it bears specific legal meaning only
in the latter, where it defines both tribal holdings
and individual land allotments, whether
still in trust or held in fee (absolute ownership).
There is no comparable meaning in
Canada, for Native reserves are administered
only for Indian communities, not for individual
Indians. In both nations the federal government
administers most of these lands and
thereby generally preempts provincial or state
authority over them. Every state and province
in the Great Plains includes Indian Country:
trust lands abound in the northern tier of
states and in the adjacent three provinces–for
example, the Rosebud Reservation in South
Dakota, the Crow Indian Reservation in Montana,
and the Assiniboine Reserve in Saskatchewan.
In the Prairie Provinces there are numerous
very small reserves, many occupied by
brethren of tribes within U.S. borders (e.g.,
the Blackfeet and Crees); in Alberta there are
also a small number of Métis reserves held in
fee simple title. In contrast, reservations on
the Americans side of the border are generally
much larger, although in the states of Kansas,
Nebraska, and Texas, there are only a few small,
scattered reservations. Oklahoma–once Indian
Territory, to which were relocated tribes
from the South, East, and from other parts
of the Plains–does not acknowledge Indian
Country, despite the existence of the Osage Reservation
and so-called former reservations (for
the most part, Indian Territory reservations
were cancelled through allotment).

Because of conflict and litigation over jurisdiction,
other interpretations of Indian Country
would apply extralegal meaning in the
United States. Such interpretations involve
former Aboriginal territory (where, for example,
some tribes may continue to hunt and fish
but not without controversy); adjudicated
claims areas, or lands shown to have historically
belonged to tribes, and all former trust
lands whether within or outside reservations.
State jurisdiction over certain criminal and
civil authority may extend to Indians and
their lands, but not authority over land use.
(Under the Indian Act of 1876 in Canada,
provinces do have some jurisdiction over Indians
on reserves, but rarely over land in reserves,
and provincial zoning authority may
apply only if not contrary to that act and constitutional
revisions of 1982.)

At one time Indian Country was extraterritorial
by treaty and lay beyond local European
American jurisdiction. Such was true of
the Great Plains until settlers and others, seeking
land farther and farther west in both
countries, agitated for the cession of tribal reserves
or reservations. At first, treaties reserved
considerable acreage, as with the Great
Sioux Reservation that once dominated Dakota
Territory and buffered tribes from adjacent
non-Indian communities. Unfortunately,
Congress enabled non-Indian homesteading
within reservations by declaring remaining
acreage "surplus" subsequent to the allotment
of tribal lands to individual Indians. Moreover,
countless non-Indians also acquired
trust lands through sale or inheritance. This
aspect of Indian Country is fundamentally inapplicable
to Canada.

Where entire counties within Indian Country
in some states have become non-Indian in
character, litigation has ensued, leading to the
diminishment of external boundaries of many
allotted reservations. Plains tribes have not escaped
this judicial interpretation. In Rosebud
Sioux Tribe v. Kneip (1977), the Supreme Court
determined that four counties in South Dakota
were disestablished by earlier allotment
laws; consequently, some 2,000 tribal members
and seven recognized communities occupying
trust acreage on the Rosebud Reservation
ended up outside the reservation.
South Dakota does not delineate on official
state maps those counties once part of reservations
that now comprise mostly non-Indian
citizenry. Recent court decisions have continued
to erode the legal meaning of Indian
Country and hence its geographic configuration.
Fee lands owned, utilized, and resided on
by non-Indians constitute a strong demographic
factor disqualifying tribal jurisdiction
over land-use planning and related environmental
management. This interpretation has
led the courts in Devils Lake Sioux Tribe v.
North Dakota PSC to exclude non-Indian
holdings from tribal jurisdiction on the Fort
Totten Reservation (North Dakota); a similar
decision has diminished tribal authority
on the Crow Indian Reservation (Montana).
According to South Dakota v. Bourland, the
alienation of Cheyenne River (South Dakota)
Sioux lands by flood control and other acts
eliminated tribal jurisdiction over non-
Indians on certain lands adjacent to the Missouri
River. In 1998 a similar decision–South
Dakota v. Yankton Sioux Tribe–excluded from
tribal jurisdiction all former trust lands lying
outside diminished reservation borders.

See also NATIVE AMERICANS: Reservations; Reserves.


Imre Sutton
California State University, Fullerton




Getches, David H., Charles F. Wilkinson, and Robert A
Williams Jr. Cases and Materials on Federal Indian Law. St.
Paul: West Publishing Co., 1993. Johnson, Ralph W. "Fragile
Gains: Two Centuries of Canadian and United States
Policy toward Indians." Washington Law Review 66 (1991):
643–718. Sutton, Imre. "Preface to Indian Country: Geography
and Law." American Indian Culture and Research
Journal 15 (1991): 3–35.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>