<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ha.007</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Cervantez, Pedro (1914-1987)</field>
      <field name="author">Grauer, Michael R.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CERVANTEZ, PEDRO (1914-1987)

Born at Wilcox, Arizona, on May 19, 1914, artist
Pedro Lopez Cervantez took his father's last
name–instead of his mother's, as usually dictated
by Hispanic tradition–because he had
been told of an earlier Cervantes who had
been a great man. His mother was a Mexican
Indian whose parents ran a pottery at Durango,
Mexico, before the Mexican Revolution.
Cervantez's father, of Spanish descent,
worked for the Santa Fe Railroad at Texico,
New Mexico. Pedro Cervantez lived most of
his life in Texico and Clovis, New Mexico, and
across the Texas border at Farwell. Most of his
painting focused on life in the Plains of eastern
New Mexico, combining a Regionalist
style with a hybrid surrealism.

Cervantez began painting in oils about
1930. He assisted artist Russell Vernon Hunter
(1900–1955) on Hunter's mural The Last Frontier
(1934), a Public Works of Art Project for
the DeBaca County Courthouse at Fort Sumner,
New Mexico. Allegedly, Cervantez was
disappointed in not receiving any credit for
his work on the mural. Nevertheless, Hunter
continued as his mentor.

Later, Cervantez made easel paintings for
the Works Progress Administration's Federal
Art Project, exhibiting most of his New Deal
productions at the Museum of Fine Arts at
Santa Fe. In 1938 Cervantez's work was included
in the exhibition "Masters of Popular
Painting: Modern Primitives of Europe and
America" at the Museum of Modern Art in
New York. He was one of the first Hispanic
artists in the United States to receive national
attention.

Cervantez enlisted in the U.S. Army in 1940
and was stationed in Italy and Germany during
World War II. Following the war he
worked as a sign painter for the Coca Cola
Bottling Company at Clovis for a number of
years. He never regained his prewar recognition
and never truly returned to easel painting,
about which he felt some bitterness. He
died at Clovis on July 3, 1987, after many years
as a public school custodian. Ironically, some
of his New Deal easel paintings hang at Melrose
(New Mexico) High School. His paintings
were featured in a recent exhibition, "Sin
Nombre: Hispana and Hispano Artists of the
New Deal Era," at the Museum of International
Folk Art in Santa Fe.


Michael R. Grauer
Panhandle-Plains Historical Museum





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>