<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fol.043</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Tornado Stories</field>
      <field name="author">Marshall, Tim</field>
      <field name="text">

 




TORNADO STORIES

The first written accounts of tornadoes in the
Great Plains were from settlements near and
along the Missouri River in Kansas during the
mid-1800s. On October 25, 1844, a tornado
moved northeast from present-day Mission,
Kansas, into Missouri. Many pioneer farms
were damaged or destroyed. A horrific nighttime
tornado struck the Baker home just outside
Stanton, Kansas, on June 8, 1860, killing
all the family. The local townspeople were unaware
of the event until morning, when they
saw pieces of the home scattered across the
hillside. Another nighttime tornado struck
near Galesburg, Kansas, killing three children
and injuring their mother in their home. Tales
spread about the "night phantom that appeared
to be composed of fire."

A small outbreak of tornadoes struck central
Kansas on June 6, 1876. One tornado near
Salina was reported to look like an elephant's
trunk moving side to side for about a half hour.
A man was watching this tornado off to his
north from the doorway of his home when
another tornado approached from the south,
destroying the house and killing him. On August
25, 1877, a tornado destroyed two spans of
the Union Pacific Railroad bridge that crossed
the Missouri River at Omaha. Wrought-iron
bars on the bridge were bent and twisted. Eyewitnesses
saw an immense cloud traveling
down the river lifting water into the funnel. An
injured watchman on the east bank of the river
boated, then swam, to Omaha to warn the next
train leaving town of the destroyed bridge.
One of the first tornadoes reported in South
Dakota occurred on April 17, 1878. The tornado
passed about eleven miles west of Yankton
near Olivet, destroying several homes. A
wagon was reported to have been thrown two
miles. One of the first tornadoes reported in
Texas was on April 15, 1879, near Dallas, injuring
twenty-five people. Fifteen homes were destroyed
and six were damaged by what was
reported to be a "green-rimmed cone-shaped
tornado which rose and fell moving like a
monster wave."

A large tornado outbreak in Kansas, Missouri,
Nebraska, and Iowa occurred on May
29 and 30, 1879. John Park Finley, a young
army cadet, was dispatched from Washington
to conduct a damage survey. Finley recorded
numerous eyewitness accounts, documented
the time of tornado occurrences, and even calculated
the forward speeds of the tornadoes.
He described in graphic detail the "agonies of
death" experienced by some of the tornado
victims: "All of the parties were covered with
mud from head to foot; eyes, mouths, and ears
filled, and clothing torn into shreds. The
mother and two children were left in the rubbish;
the former having her head crushed, and
her long hair, which reached below her waist,
was partly cut and pulled from her head,
twisted into a rope, and found several feet
from her body. That portion of her hair left
upon her head was twisted into little wisps
and mixed with mud." He wrote that "the
bodies of the children, after having been
washed for days, were still covered with specks
of fine dirt and leaves which seemed to be
driven into the flesh."

One of the most famous tornado stories
came from Mr. Will Keller, a farmer near
Greensburg, Kansas, who witnessed the inside
of a tornado from his cellar on June 22, 1928.
He looked up into what appeared to be a hollow
cylinder and saw lightning, "which zigzagged
from side-to-side." Many tornado stories
have involved accounts of plucked poultry,
sulfurous odors, and objects being carried
great distances. Another fascinating account
recalls the tornado that struck the railway station
in Elmont, Kansas, on June 5, 1917. The
ticket window was blown into a nearby field,
where it was found beneath a heavy scale
weight. The glass was not even cracked. On
April 27, 1942, a frame house was blown away
by a tornado that struck Pryor, Oklahoma,
leaving a kerosene lamp, still lighted and burning,
beneath a nearby tree. Such tornado stories
made for good press, and together they
constitute a distinctive folklore.

See also PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT: Tornadoes.


Tim Marshall
Flower Mound, Texas




Flora, Snowden D. Tornadoes of the United States. Norman:
University of Oklahoma Press, 1953. Grazulis, Thomas.
Significant Tornadoes. St. Johnsbury VT: Tornado Project of
Environmental Films, 1993.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>