<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.067</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Rölvaag, O. E. (1876-1931)</field>
      <field name="author">Coleman-Hull, Philip R.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




RÖLVAAG, O. E. (1876-1931)

Photograph of Norwegian author Ole Edvart Rolvaag

    
Born April 22, 1876, to Peder Jakobsen Rölvaag
and Ellerine Pedersdatter Vaag, Ole Edvart
Rölvaag grew up in the Norwegian hamlet of
Rölvaag, a small fishing community on Dønna
Island just below the Arctic Circle. Rölvaag
immigrated to Elk Point, South Dakota, at the
age of twenty and represented this immigrant
experience throughout his fictional work.
Nevertheless, impressions from his early years
remained in his use of Norwegian ballads,
hymns, folklore, and classic literature; his utilization
of sea-going themes and images; and his
blend of the romantic and realistic inspired by
the stunning beauty of Dønna.

In his first published novel, the autobiographical
The Third Life of Per Smevik (1912),
Rölvaag detailed his hardships as a new immigrant
in the West, explored the costs of immigration
to America, and began to reveal his
ideas on cultural integrity, that is, ensuring
cultural identity is not sacrificed in the wake
of the American Dream. He continued these
themes in subsequent works–On Forgotten Paths (1914), Pure Gold (1920), and The Boat of Longing (1921)–before beginning his tour de
force, Giants in the Earth, in 1923 while on
sabbatical from St. Olaf College. First published
in Norway in two parts, the novel revolves
around Per Hansa and his wife, Beret.
Deftly employing Norwegian folklore and
myth, Rölvaag uses Giants to artistically exam
ine the physical, cultural, and psychological
realities of Plains immigrant life while offering
characters who encapsulate more universal
themes. Rolvaag wrote two more novels that
charted the Hansa saga, Peder Victorious (1929)
and Their Father's God (1931). Lacking the epic
grandeur and stylistic brilliance of Giants,
these two novels are more political in nature as
they continue to promote Rölvaag's ideals of
cultural integrity. Having already sketched out
notes for a sequel to these novels, Rolvaag died
of a heart attack on November 5, 1931, in
Northfield, Minnesota.

See also EUROPEAN AMERICANS: Giants in the Earth.


Philip R. Coleman-Hull
Bethany College




Haugen, Einar. Ole Edvart Rölvaag. Boston: Twayne, 1983.
 Jorgenson, Theodore, and Nora Solum. Ole Edvart Rölvaag: A Biography. New York: Harper and Brothers, 1939.
Simonson, Harold P. Prairies Within: The Tragic Trilogy of
Ole Rölvaag. Seattle: University of Washington Press, 1987.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>