<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pe.003</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Amphibians and Reptiles</field>
      <field name="author">Bollinger, Royce E.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




AMPHIBIANS AND REPTILES

Amphibians and reptiles, collectively called
herptiles, are ectothermic or "cold-blooded"
vertebrates. Amphibians include frogs and
toads, salamanders, and caecilians, the latter
not represented in the Great Plains. Reptiles
technically do not constitute a distinct biological
group, but the term is used here in the
vernacular sense to refer to turtles and tortoises,
lizards, snakes, and alligators and crocodiles.
Amphibians and reptiles, except for rattlesnakes,
are not typical icons of the Plains, yet
more than 150 different species occur in some
part of the region. This number represents
about 30 percent of the species occurring in
North America. No herp species is limited to
the Great Plains, but many species reach one of
their distributional limits here. More herps occur
in the southern part of the region.

Only eleven species of salamanders extend
into the Great Plains, mostly along its eastern
periphery. Of these, seven species are restricted
to southeastern Kansas, and only Ambystoma
tigrinum, the tiger salamander, is
found throughout the Great Plains. This salamander
spends much time underground in
burrows and surfaces to feed or reproduce
when environmental conditions are favorable.

There are thirty-two species of frogs and
toads in the Great Plains, including three that
are especially prominent. One species, Spea
bombifrons, the Plains spadefoot, occurs in all
states and provinces of the Great Plains. This
species depends on temporary ponds formed
after spring and summer thunderstorms. Well
known for its rapid tadpole development, it
can breed in roadside ditches. Bufo cognatus,
the Great Plains toad, is abundant and forms
large breeding choruses after thunderstorms.
The shrill call of thousands of these toads
from a "buffalo wallow" can be heard for several
miles. A third species, Rana blairi, the
plains leopard frog, is restricted to the central
grasslands, extending from the Great Plains
into the tallgrass prairie peninsula as far east
as western Indiana. Like other leopard frogs, it
is dependent on permanent ponds and lakes
because its larvae require several months for
metamorphosis.

Of the nineteen species of turtles in the
Great Plains, none occurs in all states and
provinces. The snapping turtle, Chelydra serpentina,
occurring in larger ponds, lakes, or
rivers, is found throughout the Great Plains
except for Alberta. The painted turtle, Chrysemys
picta, is widely distributed across the
Plains except for Texas. This is one of the few
herps of the region whose distribution is more
northern than southern. It frequents permanent
ponds and lakes. Terrapene ornata, the
ornate box turtle, is a common terrestrial species,
especially in sandy soils of the Southern
Plains and as far north as South Dakota. This
species is often associated with mammal burrows,
such as those of prairie dogs, where it
will retreat to overwinter.

The thirty-three species of lizards have a
distinctly southern distribution: all but one
occur in Texas, and none are found entirely
throughout the region. Phrynosoma douglassi,
the short-horned lizard, is the most widespread
species, occurring in all states and provinces
except Manitoba, Kansas, and Oklahoma.
However, this species frequents the
plateaus along the Rocky Mountains rather
than being a true Plains species. The distribution
of Eumeces septentrionalis, the prairie
skink, is remarkably coincident with the tallgrass
prairie from eastern Texas to Manitoba,
although its distribution extends eastward into
Minnesota and Iowa. The Great Plains skink,
Eumeces obsoletus, is distributed from the desert
Southwest into the Southern Plains and as
far north as Nebraska and Wyoming.

Snakes are the most numerous herptiles with
fifty-nine species occurring in some part of the
Plains. Fifty of these species live on the Plains
of Texas. Three species, the plains garter snake
(Thamnophis radix), common garter snake
(Thamnophis sirtalis), and western hognose
snake (Heterodon nasicus), inhabit all states and
provinces of the region. Garter snakes are semiaquatic,
occurring along streams and ponds,
whereas the hognose is common in open, especially
sandy, prairies. The hognose is well known
for its feigning-death behavior when disturbed.
The racer, Coluber constrictor, living throughout
the region except for the Canadian provinces, is
a common species of the open grasslands. The
prairie rattlesnake, Crotalus viridis, is found
throughout the region except for Manitoba. It is
often associated with prairie dog towns and is
much maligned because of its poisonous nature.
The gopher snake, Pituophis catenifer, also
occurs throughout except for Manitoba. This
harmless snake of the open prairies can be more
than six feet long and because of its hissing
behavior gives the appearance of being dangerous.
In fact, perhaps many of the reports of
rattlesnake encounters may actually involve the
gopher snake.

Even though amphibians and reptiles are
frequently inconspicuous to the casual observer,
they are a common and important
component of the fauna of the Great Plains.


Royce E. Bollinger
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Conant, Roger, and Joseph T. Collins. A Field Guide to
Reptiles and Amphibians: Eastern and Central North America.
Boston: Houghton Mifflin Company, 1991. Lynch,
John D. "Annotated Checklist of the Amphibians and
Reptiles of Nebraska." Transactions of the Nebraska Academy
of Sciences 13 (1985): 33–57.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>