<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.rel.028</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Islam</field>
      <field name="author">Ward, Seth</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ISLAM

Islam has more than one billion adherents
who are found in every region of the world,
including the Great Plains. There, as everywhere
else throughout North America, an extraordinarily
diverse Muslim community is
growing dramatically, building places of worship,
schools, and community centers, and
contributing to the broader community.

Islam is a monotheistic faith, recognizing
the oneness of Allah, the same God who
is known, according to Islam, to Abraham,
Moses, Jesus, and others and is worshiped also
by Christians and Jews. According to Islam,
God's word, the Qur'an, was revealed through
Muhammad (ca. 570–632) over a twenty-year
period. Unlike the Bible, which is mostly in
third-person narrative form, the Qur'an is
considered God's direct speech. Recitation of
the Qur'an is a major component of Islamic
ritual and piety.

The mass immigration to North America in
the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries
brought many from traditionally Islamic
countries of the Middle East and North
Africa. Although these were largely Christians
and Jews, some Islamic communities were established,
including one in Cedar Rapids,
Iowa, just outside the Great Plains. Especially
toward the end of this period, there was rising
interest in Islam among African Americans,
including the foundation of various movements
that would coalesce into the Nation of
Islam.

After World War II, and especially after
1980, Islam became established as a major religious
grouping in the Great Plains, at least in
the cities, although the ten largest Muslim
population centers in North America were all
outside the region.

Demographically, many locales have two
main communities–African Americans and
"immigrants"–although the latter now includes
many individuals who were born in
North America, as well as numerous converts.
Both communities may be subdivided.
Islam has grown tremendously among African
Americans. Many youths became Muslims in
prison and retained their new religion after
their release. The Nation of Islam has always
had some authentic Islamic elements, including
the Qur'an, but its racial teachings and its
views about Wallace Fard and Elijah Mohammed
(Fard was deified as Allah) are antithetical
to normative Islam. Since 1975, when Elijah
Mohammed's son W. D. Mohammed broke
with this theology, a sizable portion of African
Americans practice normative Islam and generally
have good ties with the immigrant community.
Within the immigrant community, at
least in the Great Plains, Sunnis and Shiites
form one community, unlike the exclusive situation
found in many traditionally Islamic
countries. Nevertheless, some demographic
scholarship has noted a tendency for mosques
to align along ethnolinguistic lines, the major
groupings being Arab, Persian, South Asian,
and Southeast Asian.

A survey completed in the early 1990s
found mosques, student organizations, or
Muslim organizations in the Denver metropolitan
area, Fort Collins and Greeley, Pueblo
and Colorado Springs, Colorado; Lawrence,
Wichita, Manhattan, and suburban Kansas
City, Kansas; Bozeman and Billings, Montana;
Omaha and Lincoln, Nebraska; Portales, New
Mexico; Fargo, Minot, and Grand Forks,
North Dakota; Stillwater, Tulsa, Oklahoma
City, Edmond, Norman, and Ponca City,
Oklahoma; Brookings, South Dakota; and
Fort Worth and Arlington, Denton, Blanco,
Lubbock, Amarillo, Midland, Odessa, Waco,
and Austin, Texas. In the Canadian Prairie
Provinces, there are Muslim communities in
Regina, Saskatoon, Edmonton, and Winnipeg.
Many of the major mosques or Islamic
Centers serve large university populations.
Some of these communities have established
Islamic day schools that ofer a full general
curriculum that meets all state requirements
but also provides intensive education in Arabic
language, Qur'an, and Islamic religion and
history.

See also PROTEST AND DISSENT: Malcolm X.


Seth Ward
University of Denver




Bagby, Ihsan, ed. Muslim Resource Guide: An Essential
Guide for Media and Government. Fountain Valley CA:
Islamic Resource Institute, 1994. Directory of Masjids and
Muslim Organizations in North America. Fountain Valley
CA: Islamic Resource Institute, 1994. Smith, Jane I. Islam in
America. New York: Columbia University Press, 1999.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>