<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pd.044</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Partridge, Edward A. (1861-1931)</field>
      <field name="author">Knuttila, Murray</field>
      <field name="text">

 




PARTRIDGE, EDWARD A. (1861-1931)

Edward Alexander Partridge was born on
November 5, 1861, in Dalston, Ontario. After
completing school, Partridge earned a teacher's
certificate. He taught in Ontario, but he
was a restless man, content only when building
something. The opening of the Canadian
Prairies beckoned, and in 1883 Partridge and
his brother headed west to homestead near
Sintaluta (now in Saskatchewan), where he resided
until 1927. On arrival at Sintaluta, Partridge
worked as a schoolteacher. He also
fulfilled some of his required homestead residency
by serving in the Yorkton Company Militia
of Canada for three months during the
1885 Riel Rebellion. He fell in love with Mary
Stephens, a young woman from a nearby
town. They married in 1886 and devoted their
lives to building their farm and raising a family
of five.

Partridge quickly developed an analysis of
the Canadian social and economic system that
was premised on the understanding that capitalism
is a class-based system, with inherent
patterns of exploitation, domination, and inequities.
As a result of his and others' difficulties
in marketing grain at competitive
prices, he entered into a lifelong mission to
change the world through collective struggle.
Partridge was present in 1901 when a group of
disgruntled farmers organized one of the first
western Canadian agrarian political action organizations,
the Territorial Grain Growers Association.
Partridge quickly concluded that
political lobbying was limited in its potential
to effect real social change, so in 1908 he campaigned
to form a farmers' grain company,
the Grain Growers Grain Company (GGGC).
Although the GGGC eventually evolved into a
successful cooperative, for Partridge it did not
represent a real solution. As Partridge and
others undertook various campaigns to establish
cooperatives, secure political concessions,
and generally improve the lot of farmers, they
encountered what they considered unfair coverage
in the press. In order to present their
side of the story, they created an agrarian news
journal in 1908. Partridge was the first editor
of the Grain Growers Guide, but as was typical
of his restless spirit, he only lasted one issue
before moving on. His next undertaking was a
campaign to secure public ownership of the
elevator system through the involvement of
provincial governments. Although it never
came to fruition, the "Partridge Plan" did result
in government support for a cooperative
elevator company.

In addition to organizing cooperatives and
grain companies, Prairie farmers attempted to
shape government policies, especially those
relating to tariffs. In 1910 hundreds of farmers
converged on Ottawa in what became known
as the "Siege of Ottawa." Partridge was there.
World War I brought a temporary lull to the
agrarian agitation; however, it also brought
personal tragedy to Partridge and his wife. In
1914 one of their daughters drowned while
swimming near the farm. Then, although Partridge
was a pacifist, their two sons served and
were killed during World War I. Partridge's
health remained a problem, in part because he
had lost a leg in a farm accident in 1908.

Partridge, undoubtedly supported by Mary,
joined the fight for a western political party
after the war. He also became involved in
organizing a new group, the Farmers Union of
Canada, in 1921, and in organizing the Wheat
Pool in Saskatchewan. In 1926 he explicated
his vision of a better world in a book, A War
on Poverty. The vision and spiritual message
of the book reflect the remarkable resilience of
the human spirit; however, he was not able to
recover from one last loss, Mary's death while
she was gardening on the farm. Partridge left
Saskatchewan and ended his own life in Victoria
on August 3, 1931.


Muray Knuttila
University of Regina





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>