<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ea.007</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Danes</field>
      <field name="author">Stølen, Marianne</field>
      <field name="text">

 




DANES

Place-names with a Danish ring, such as Dannevirke,
Nebraska, and Viborg, South Dakota,
testify to the founding of Danish settlements
during the chief migration of Danes to the
Great Plains of the United States from 1860 to
1895. Most of these settlers were dispossessed
farmers taking advantage of the 1862 Homestead Act, which made possible their dream
of landownership. The establishment of railroads
provided additional incentive for emigration,
as large tracts of land owned by the
railroad companies were made available and
transportation was provided. Unlike their
Nordic neighbors, the Danish settlers tended
to scatter widely, with no more than 11 percent
of the total settling in one state. In Kansas, for
example, a number of settlements were the
result of Danes fleeing Prussian rule of their
home province of North Schleswig in the
wake of Denmark's 1864 war with Prussia.
During the first decade of settlement survival
was difficult. Cultivation methods learned at
home were useless on prairie land, where
wheat and corn were the main crops. In Danevang,
Texas, the southernmost Danish settlement
in the Plains, the techniques for growing
cotton had to be learned. One aspect of their
traditional farming system of cooperatives did
transfer, however, and the impact of Danish
dairy cooperatives can still be seen today.

Settlements in North Dakota and the Canadian
provinces of Alberta and Saskatchewan
represent the second migration of the Danes,
many of whom were forced to leave the midwestern
states as a result of rising land prices.
Favorable Canadian homestead legislation
added to the pull of the north. In addition, the
United States' enactment of restrictive immigrant
quotas in 1924 diverted a significant
number of prospective emigrants to Canada.
Settlements in such cities as Omaha and Calgary
reflected the increasing occupational diversity
of the immigrants, from commerce to
the professions, which contributed to wider
settler dispersion.

Nevertheless, by the early twentieth century
immigrants in both rural and urban areas
had established their own churches and folk
schools, many clergy-inspired, as well as fraternal
societies, including the Danish Brotherhood,
social clubs, and newspapers. The Danish Pioneer, the largest Danish newspaper, was
founded in Omaha in 1872 and is still being
published. An 1894 split within the Danish
Lutheran church in North America led to the
formation of two organizations serving the
Danes. One branch was headquartered at
Blair, Nebraska. Its seminary, Trinity College,
also at Blair, evolved into a liberal arts college,
Dana College, which today houses an impressive
archival collection related to Danish immigration
to North America. The Dana Folk
School in Calgary is also associated with the
Blair synod. The other branch, shaped by the
thought of N. F. S. Grundtvig, an influential
Danish pastor and educator, saw as a major
part of its mission the preservation of Danish
language and heritage via the founding of colonies.
Settlements such as Danevang, Texas,
and Dagmar, Montana, and folk schools like
Dalum Folk School in Dalum, Alberta, were
the direct results of its support. Almost all the
folk schools were forced to close in the 1930s
due to the Depression and poor enrollment.

Today's chain of Danish brotherhood and
sisterhood lodges and social clubs, located in
Canada and throughout the United States,
serve to maintain and promote Danish heritage
and culture. So does the Federation of
Danish Associations in Canada. The Danes of
the Great Plains have made major contributions
to American and Canadian life and culture.
Two Danes of exceptional talents were
Niels Hansen, a distinguished pioneering horticulturist
associated with South Dakota State
College, and Gutzon Borghlum, the sculptor
known for his monumental carvings on
Mount Rushmore in North Dakota.

See also ARCHITECTURE: Danish Architecture
/ IMAGES AND ICONS: Mount Rushmore National Memorial.


Marianne Stølen
University of Washington




Bender, H., and B. Flemming Larsen, eds. Danish Emigration to Canada. Aalborg, Denmark: Danes Worldwide Archives,
1991. Hvidt, Kristian. Flight to America: The Social Background of 300,000 Danish Emigrants. New York: Academic
Press, 1975. Nielsen, George R. The Danish Americans.
Boston: Twayne Publishers, 1981.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>