<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.law.034</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Morris, Esther (1814-1902)</field>
      <field name="author">Berry, Lois M.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MORRIS, ESTHER (1814-1902)


Esther Morris


When the commissioners of Sweetwater
County, Wyoming Territory, approved Esther
Morris as a justice of the peace on February 12,
1870, she entered history as the first woman
magistrate in the nation.

Morris was born in Spencer, Tioga County,
New York, on August 8, 1814. Orphaned at an
early age, she learned to support herself and
developed a sense of independence. She lived
for more than twenty years in Peru, Illinois,
where she raised her family. In 1869 she moved
west to the rough-and-tumble gold-mining
town of South Pass City to join her husband
and oldest son, who had moved there the previous
year in search of gold. Five months later,
women in Wyoming Territory were the first in
the nation to be granted suffrage. One of the
few advocates of women's rights in the small
mining town, Morris was encouraged by local
citizens and an influential judge to apply for a
vacant justice of the peace position. She was
appointed on February 17, 1870.

Justice Morris's first case involved the prosecution
of her predecessor, who refused to
turn over the court docket to her as a female
judge. The case was consequently dismissed
without the transfer of the docket, and Morris
purchased a new book in which to record her
cases. Serving less than nine months, she tried
twenty-eight cases, including ten assaults.

Although she chose not to stand for election
at the end of her appointed term, Esther Morris
earned the respect of the predominantly
male, antisuffrage local citizenry. Even though
she was erroneously dubbed the "Mother
of Woman Suffrage" in turn-of-the-century
newspaper and historical reports, she did work
diligently for women's rights, and Judge Morris
rightfully deserves national attention because
of the precedent she set. She died in
Laramie on April 2, 1902. Her statue stands in
front of the Wyoming State Capitol in Cheyenne.

See also GENDER: Suffrage Movement.


Lois M. Berry
University of Wyoming




Dobler, Lavinia. Esther Morris: First Woman Justice of the Peace. Riverton WY: Big Bend Press, 1993. Larson, T. A.
History of Wyoming. Lincoln: University of Nebraska
Press, 1978. Massie, Michael A. "Reform Is Where You
Find It: The Roots of Woman Suffrage in Wyoming." Annals of Wyoming 62 (1990): 2-21.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>