<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ct.032</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Main Street</field>
      <field name="author">Gaber, John</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MAIN STREET


Main Street, Florence, Kansas


Main Street is the heart and soul of all Great
Plains towns and cities, the starting point
from which all towns in this region began.
The combination of community development,
economic growth, and the love-hate relationship
with the automobile makes the
Great Plains Main Street distinctive from
other Main Streets in North America.

Main Street is a planned development that
integrates traffic, commercial markets, and
public open space. The most common characteristic
of Great Plains Main Streets is that they
are part of a grid system of streets. Main Street
is the spine within a series of streets arranged
in a perpendicular pattern. The benefits of a
grid pattern of streets allows for an efficient
flow of traffic and maximizes building access
from the street. Main Streets also share the
following types of land uses: commercial space
for trade and banking; government space for
governance and justice; public open space for
celebrations and festivals; and churches for religious,
educational, and town meetings. All of
these land uses were tightly confined to a few
blocks for several reasons. First, communities
just getting started had limited resources.
Consequently, Main Streets initially developed
within a couple of blocks in order to handle
the most immediate community needs. Second,
most Great Plains Main Streets were developed
at a time when commerce was primarily
regional in focus and did not require
a large amount of space or infrastructure to
support area businesses. Finally, since Main
Streets were not built in an era of modern
telecommunication capabilities, most community
life was handled directly through face-to-
face interactions, which were more easily
accommodated by a densely organized Main
Street where everything was in easy walking
distance.

In addition to meeting local community
needs, Main Streets were also developed to
generate economic resources. The economic
attractiveness of the Main Street design is two-fold.
First, organizing a community around
Main Street provided local buildings with easy
customer access from the street. Buildings that
are easily accessible from the Main Street thoroughfare
generate more revenue and have a
higher real estate market value than buildings
that are located on less traveled arterial routes.
Second, the grid pattern of streets made it
easier for towns to accommodate new growth.
All a town needed to do to grow was to expand
its infrastructure of roads and utilities by
adding another block along Main Street. The
ease of Main Street expansion made real estate
speculation less risky because block sizes were
standardized and new developments were anchored
by the established activity already
on Main Street. In some cities, like Topeka,
Kansas, Main Street grew solely by real estate
development. Plains railroad towns are another
example of towns developing on a Main
Street schema for real estate speculation.

Much of the current demise of Main Streets
came about through the combination of mass
ownership of automobiles and a changing
economy that dictated a new logic in the development
and organization of town space.
Beginning in the 1920s, automobiles became
more prevalent due to their increasing affordability
and dependability. Motorists' demands
for decreasing tra.c congestion and
improving vehicle access to buildings resulted
in reconfiguring Main Streets to accommodate
the car. Main Streets were retrofitted
for this rising mobility through widening the
street, adding traffic signals, and providing
more on-street and off-street parking. By the
end of World War II, the attractiveness of
high-density Main Streets had come to an
end. The advent of mass automobile ownership
required buildings to be more accessible
to cars than to pedestrians. The requirement
of parking spaces forced buildings away from
the street and set them, almost as a backdrop,
behind the parking lot. Also, streets had to be
widened even more, and the stoplights had to
be calibrated to allow for a tolerable flow of
vehicular movement along Main Street and to
prevent unacceptable levels of traffic.

In some Great Plains communities, Main
Streets became economically obsolete because
of their existing dense configuration of buildings
arranged along a narrow high-tra.c corridor.
In such places, Main Streets never grew
beyond their original buildings. The impacts
of telecommunications and the economic
postwar boom in the 1950s and 1960s also created
demand for more decentralized Main
Street space. Commerce from the 1950s to the
early 1970s was no longer dependent on face-to-
face transactions. Decisions could be made
and business deals closed with the interested
parties being physically in two different parts
of the world. In addition, regional economic
systems were becoming more national and international,
requiring larger facilities that
could not be accommodated in the old Main
Street system of spaces. It was becoming less
cost-effective for businesses to be located in
Main Street buildings with high rents, limited
space (especially for storage), and inconvenient
parking.

For other communities, the commercial
decline of their downtown Main Streets was
the result of an overly successful planned and
managed Main Street. In these cases, the grid
pattern of streets with Main Street as the
lynchpin was so successful that it drew people
and economic development out of the Main
Street core to the suburban fringe. Main Street
grew beyond the downtown to become the
arterial spine of suburbanized sections of the
city, accommodating higher traffic densities
and lower building densities such as the suburban
shopping mall. Lincoln, Nebraska, is
one example of a popular Main Street that
expanded out to the suburban fringe, carrying
development away from the original downtown
section.

A revival of the original pedestrian-based
Main Street system has been gaining momentum
since the 1970s. This revival was fueled
by international trends such as rising gasoline
costs, renewed appreciation for historically
significant buildings, antisuburbanization sentiment,
and, more recently, computer and telecommunication
innovations that make businesses
less tied to suburban commercial spaces.
The rekindling of the Main Street spirit has also
been supported by the cooperative efforts of
individual entrepreneurs, local civic groups,
and national organizations like the National
Trust for Historic Preservation. After years of
neglect and countless facade modifications,
old Main Street buildings are now being restored
and maintained according to their
original design. Perkins, Oklahoma, is one example
of a town working to restore historically
significant buildings on its Main Street.
The town's restoration efforts are nicely illustrated
in the 1993 refurbishing of the Baker's
Store Building, built in 1890 on the corner of
Main and Thomas. Through such community
revitalization, Great Plains residents are once
again making Main Street the heart and soul
of their community.

See also ARCHITECTURE: 
Commercial Architecture.


John Gaber
Auburn University




Liebs, Chester. Main Street to Miracle Mile: American Roadside Architecture. Boston: Little, Brown, 1985. Reps,
John. The Forgotten Frontier: Urban Planning in the American West before 1890. Columbia: University of Missouri
Press, 1981.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>