<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.art.014</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Curry, John Steuart (1897-1946)</field>
      <field name="author">Katz, Wendy J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CURRY, JOHN STEUART (1897-1946)

John Steuart Curry and his admirers stressed
his connections with his birthplace, a farm
near Dunavant, Jefferson County, Kansas,
where he was born on November 14, 1847, just
as it was his paintings of rural Kansas that
brought him national fame. However, in a
typical pattern, his career as a regionalist
painter began only when he left Kansas.

After classes from 1916 to 1918 at the Chicago
Art Institute, Curry moved to New York in
1919 and studied with magazine illustrator
Harvey Dunn. His apprenticeship led to a successful
seven-year career illustrating short stories
for periodicals like the Saturday Evening
Post, during which time he moved to Westport,
Connecticut, home to a bohemian artists
colony. There writers like Van Wyck Brooks
introduced him to the regionalist aim of creating
a distinctive and authentic American culture
based on artists who were an organic part
of a community and who represented their
own experience in it. The artist who was responsive
to and shaped by the customs and
traditions of a particular place would naturally
produce an American art that was inseparable
from ordinary people's experience within the
same community.

After a stint in 1926.27 studying the figure
in Vasily Shukayev's studio in Paris, Curry returned
and painted his first regionalist subject,
Baptism in Kansas (1928). It and pictures
like Tornado over Kansas (1929) instantly succeeded
with influential eastern critics and patrons
who admired Kansan traditions and
communities for their differences from the
uniformity and commercialism of modern
mass culture. Gertrude Whitney posed with
Baptism at the opening of the Whitney Museum
of American Art in 1931; by 1934 Curry
was on the cover of Time, anointed with
Grant Wood of Iowa and Thomas Hart Benton
of Missouri as the midwestern leaders of a
new American art movement, distinct from
French modernism and abstraction.

Under the New Deal, the Departments of
Justice and the Interior in Washington DC
hired Curry from 1936 to 1938 to paint mural
cycles on themes like the Oklahoma land rush
and the freeing of the slaves. But Curry's dealers
and friends sought to bolster his regionalist
credentials by bringing him back to the
Midwest, and in 1936 Curry accepted the position
of artist in residence at the University
of Wisconsin's College of Agriculture, where
he fulfilled the requirement to develop regional
art as a force for improving rural culture.
Curry's Ajax (1936–37), which shows a
monumental Hereford bull rising in massive
proportions above a flat landscape, in many
ways fulfilled the goal of regional art: communities
that raised scientifically bred herds of
cattle would have their ideal of beauty celebrated
on their walls.

Curry also sought validation from his home
state of Kansas but with less success, as his
choice of subjects was seen there as closer to
negative provincial stereotyping. In 1937 he
was commissioned to paint murals for the
Kansas State Capitol in Topeka, but his depiction
of Kansas history–including abolitionist
John Brown and soil erosion–met
with such hostility that the murals were never
completed. Curry stayed at the University of
Wisconsin until his death on August 29, 1946,
and his success encouraged the incorporation
of an arts curriculum at other land-grant
universities.


Wendy J. Katz
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Junker, Patricia, ed. John Steuart Curry. New York: Hudson
Hills Press, 1998. Kendall, M. Sue. Rethinking Regionalism: John Steuart Curry and the Kansas Mural Controversy.
Washington DC: Smithsonian Institution Press,
1986. Schmeckebier, Laurence. John Steuart Curry's Pageant of America. New York: American Artists Group, 1943.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>