<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.066</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Railroad Politics</field>
      <field name="author">Kerr, K. Austin</field>
      <field name="text">

 




RAILROAD POLITICS

"Railroad politics" is the term used to summarize
the bargaining among railroads and
their investors, employees, customers, and
public officials. This bargaining has at different
times centered on the location of railroad
lines and supporting facilities, the quality
of service provided by railroad companies, the
wages paid to employees, the profits returned
to investors, and, especially, the charges imposed
on passengers and freight shippers.

Although the first railroads penetrated the
Great Plains of the United States in the 1860s, it
was the 1880s that saw enormous expansion. In
that decade railroad firms laid more miles of
track in the United States than in any comparable
time period anywhere in the world. Similarly,
north of the forty-ninth parallel the decade
of the 1880s saw the completion of the
Canadian Pacific, Canada's first transcontinental
railway. The result in the Great Plains
was a land boom and rapid population growth.
The particular location of the rail lines was
often a matter of political bargaining. Land
speculators, town builders, and municipal officials vied to have railroads come to their favored
location because of the economic vitality
that rail service promised. Fully three-quarters
of the towns incorporated in Alberta were established
by railway companies. Towns that
did not enjoy direct access to the railroad network
either stagnated or died. Locations favored
with railroad junctions, railroad yards
(sidetracks for the storage and sorting of
equipment), terminal facilities, and maintenance
shops were especially likely to boom
economically in the late nineteenth century in
the Plains. Calgary actually bribed the Canadian
Pacific to obtain its maintenance shops
and freight yards.

Railroad companies built too many lines in
the Great Plains for all to be profitable, and
by the depression years of the 1890s several major
carriers were bankrupt but still operating.
Competition for the most profitable long-haul
freight and passenger traffic was intense. Although
improvements in operating efficiencies
had led to lower rates, farmers and merchants
dependent on railroad service often
complained that charges were too high. Some
in the Plains argued for public ownership of
the railroads to ensure their operation in "the
public interest," a policy advocated by the populist
movement. Shippers who complained
about unjust freight rates also turned to state
and federal regulation.

With a return to prosperity in the first years
of the twentieth century, railroads and shippers
continued to bargain for advantage, especially through a system of federal regulation
strengthened by the Hepburn Act of 1906 and
the Mann-Elkins Act of 1910. Railroads sought
permission from regulators to increase rates
so as to improve facilities and operating efficiencies. Employees seeking higher wages and
investors seeking better returns supported the
carriers, while shippers viewed rate increase
requests suspiciously. The political bargaining
among those groups was typically intense,
with elected officials in the Great Plains voicing
support for local merchants and farmers
and expressing hostility toward the carriers.

The intensity of railroad politics gradually
eased as improved highways and long-distance
motor trucks lessened the dependence of shippers
on the railroad serving their local area.
Nevertheless, grain farmers depended on railroads
for taking their products to market
cheaply, and railroads continued to haul large
volumes of other agricultural products and
manufactured goods as well. After the Staggers
Rail Act of 1980 deregulated the carriers, there
were widespread mergers of competing railroads,
as well as the integration of rail and
motor truck freight services. This situation
sometimes led to problems, especially in the
1990s when the Union Pacific Railroad was
unable to manage operations e.ciently after
taking over the Southern Pacific lines, and bitter
complaints again emerged in Texas and
other places in the Great Plains.

See also TRANSPORTATION: Railroads, United States; Railways, Canada.


K. Austin Kerr
Ohio State University




Berk, Gerald. Alternative Tracks: The Constitution of American
Industrial Order, 1865-1917. Baltimore MD: Johns
Hopkins University Press, 1994. Hoogenboom, Ari and
Olive. A History of the ICC: From Panacea to Palliative. New
York: W. W. Norton Co., 1976. Kerr, K. Austin. American
Railroad Politics, 1914-1920: Rates, Wages, and Efficiency.
Pittsburgh: University of Pittsburgh Press, 1968.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>