<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.edu.003</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Adult Education</field>
      <field name="author">Spikes, W. Franklin</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ADULT EDUCATION

Adult education in the Great Plains has a
long and rich history. Unlike many other geographical
regions of the United States, where
learners and providers of adult education programs
enjoy close proximity, the large landmass
and relatively sparse population of the
Great Plains have resulted in the development
of many distinctive educational delivery
systems.

Historically, the critical challenge for adult
education providers in the Great Plains has
been to develop a system of sound educational
options and strategies that allow access to
their resource base and at the same time overcome
the fundamental barrier to participation
that is posed by the substantial distances
that exist between their location and potential
adult students. The work of the Cooperative
Extension Service with regard to community
and leadership development, 4-H, the agricultural
experiment station initiatives, and correspondence
study, an early form of self-paced
learning, are among the most notable examples
of these efforts.

Presently, distance-based learning activities
that are delivered via two-way interactive
video or Web-based coursework to the increasingly
large number of adults in the region
who have access to the Internet are among the
most significant ways in which adult education
degrees as well as personal and professional
development offerings are being provided
to residents of the Great Plains. In
addition, on-site, off-campus college and university
courses and other types of mediated
self-directed instructional activities associated
with the outreach mission of the region's
many land-grant universities as well as the applied
research and development endeavors of
the Cooperative Extension Service, which provides
educational and research services to
agriculturally related interests of the Great
Plains, continue to be among the key means
by which new knowledge is disseminated
throughout the region.

See also AGRICULTURE: 
Agricultural Extension Service.


W. Franklin Spikes
Kansas State University




Knowles, M. S. The Adult Education Movement in the U.S.
Melbourne FL: Krieger, 1983. Merriam, S. B., and P. M.
Cunningham, eds. Handbook of Adult and Continuing Education.
San Francisco: Jossey-Bass, 1989.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>