<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.018</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Direct Democracy</field>
      <field name="author">Smith, Daniel A.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




DIRECT DEMOCRACY

Direct democracy–which includes the plebiscitary
devices of initiative, referendum, and
recall–is the political process whereby citizens
participate directly in the making of public
policy by casting their votes on ballot measures.
The so-called citizen initiative is the
most participatory form of direct democracy.
With the initiative, citizens collect a specified
number of valid signatures in order to place
either a statutory measure or a constitutional
amendment on the ballot for fellow voters to
adopt or reject. In addition to the initiative,
the "popular" referendum allows citizens to
petition their legislatures to place a disputed
legislative action on the ballot for the voters to
reconsider, and the recall enables citizens to
collect signatures to force a retention vote of
an elected official.

The practice of direct democracy grew out
of the doctrines put forth by the Populist (People's)
Party, the single-taxers led by Henry
George, and the Farmers Alliance during the
late nineteenth century. In 1898 the citizens of
South Dakota became the first in the Union to
adopt the use of the three devices at the state
level. The Reverend Robert W. Haire, an activist
in the Knights of Labor, is generally credited
with devising the original South Dakota
scheme. Following the lead of South Dakota,
voters in seven other American states in the
Great Plains region adopted some form of
statewide direct democracy: Montana (1906),
Oklahoma (1907), Colorado (1910), New Mexico
(1911), Nebraska (1912), North Dakota
(1914), and Wyoming (1968). In Canada, more
recently, the Prairie province of Saskatchewan
adopted a nonbinding initiative in 1991. The
citizens of Manitoba embraced the initiative
in 1916, but it was subsequently declared unconstitutional.

In the United States during the 1910s, direct
democracy was highly prized by progressive
reformers as an instrument to return government
back to the people. It was viewed as an
institutional check on the power of unresponsive
state legislatures, which were often seen as
being under the thumb of special interests.
Today, the initiative process is utilized quite
frequently by citizen groups, as well as by special
interests, in the Great Plains states where it
is permitted, but the popular referendum and
the recall election are seldom used.

See also PROTEST AND DISSENT: Haire, Robert.


Daniel A. Smith
University of Denver




Boyer, J. Patrick. Direct Democracy in Canada: The History
and Future of Referendums. Toronto: Dundurn Press, 1992.
Cronin, Thomas E. Direct Democracy: The Politics of Initiative,
Referendum, and Recall. Cambridge: Harvard University
Press, 1989. Munro, William Bennett, ed. The Initiative,
Referendum, and Recall. New York: D. Appleton
and Company, 1912.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>