<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ea.002</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Anglo-Canadians</field>
      <field name="author">Widdis, Randy William</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ANGLO CANADIANS


Canadian-Born by StateGreat Plains, 1850-1930 Census Years

State180018501870188018901900191019201930
North Dakota1,45890610,67823,04528,16621,50715,74312,509
South Dakota9,4937,0446,0104,4623,414
Nebraska4382,6358,62212,1059,0497,3355,7804,410
Kansas5,32412,53611,8748,5387,1885,3524,068
Oklahoma4201,8072,8712,4892,146
Texas1374585972,4722,8662,9493,5344,2004,563
New Mexico1252276817641,023738618
Colorado6074,7499,1429,7979,5817,6425,845
Wyoming3294751,3141,2481,4311,4401,144
1,1722,0889,04013,82613,84214,70011,193



The influence of immigration and ethnicity on
the American and Canadian portions of the
Great Plains has been profound and diverse.
Although European migration to this region
has received considerable attention, little is
known about the experiences of Canadian migrants,
both those crossing the international
border and those moving westward within
their country of birth. This is explained primarily
by the scarcity of data on internal migrants,
although their experience can be reconstructed
through manuscript censuses,
homestead records, and local histories. The
neglect of the Canadian immigrant experience
in the United States is explained in part by the
assumption that Canadians, Anglo-Canadians
specifically, experienced rapid assimilation because
they shared the same language and many
other attributes with the host society. Yet
Anglo-Canadian immigrants invite examination
because they played an important role in
the settlement of the American Great Plains,
particularly in the northern half where they
comprised a significant percentage of the foreign
population during the period of initial
settlement.

North–south intermingling within this region
occurred well before European permanent
settlement, as the American and British
fur-trading systems converged along the upper
Missouri River at the villages of the Mandans
and Hidatsas in what is now west-central
North Dakota. Prior to 1800 several furtrading
posts run by Hudson's Bay and North
West Companies had established operations
in the northern Red River Valley. Anglo-
Ontarians, many of whom had been living in
Manitoba, made their way south to the Pembina
District of Minnesota Territory early in
the nineteenth century, but their numbers
were small. Pembina, located adjacent to the
international border, became the center of
a vast trade territory whose main commerce
was in furs taken from the Northern Plains
and western Canada. Beginning in 1843 oxcarts
operated by Hudson's Bay Company
traveled from Fort Garry and Pembina to St.
Paul carrying furs east and finished products
west. An important player in this trade was
Norman Kittson, originally from Quebec,
who later moved to St. Paul where he and
three other prominent Canadian-born businessmen–
Donald Smith, James J. Hill, and
George Stephen–developed steamboat and
railroad transportation links that would open
up the Northern Plains for settlement. These
developments stirred American capitalists to
look beyond the border and extend their empires
into western Canada, but the trade monopoly
of Fort Benton in Montana and the
grand schemes of St. Paul businessmen were
ended with the building of the Canadian Pacific
Railway.

It has been estimated that from 1861 to 1931
the net migration of Canadians to the United
States totaled over two million, with the greatest
flow occurring in the 1880s. Emigration
from Canada during the latter part of the
nineteenth century was framed by three concurrent
processes: the decomposition of rural
society, a sluggish pace of industrial development
in the midst of a global recession, and
the expansion of urban-industrial opportunities
in nearby border states. While most
Anglo-Canadians located in towns and cities
in states such as Michigan, New York, and
Massachusetts, considerable numbers traveled
farther afield to the Great Plains. Many Canadians
intent on taking up land in Manitoba
following the passage of Canada's Homestead
Act (1872) were attracted by intervening
opportunities in Dakota Territory and
changed their travel plans accordingly. The
well-publicized Dakota land boom of 1879–86
proved especially tantalizing to Canadians. By
1879 Canadians, many of Scottish descent, settling
along the northern part of the Red River
were so numerous that more Canadian than
American money circulated there.

An important factor in the settlement of
Canadian and other immigrant groups in the
Dakota Territory (and also in Kansas) in the
late 1860s and 1870s was the development of a
railroad system that provided a critical link
between farmers and markets. Between 1870
and 1890 more than 120,000 Canadian-born
chose the American Plains over Canada, with
present-day North Dakota being the most important
destination within the region. As a
consequence, more is known about the anglophone
Canadian experience there than in any
other in the American Plains states. Most Canadians
migrating directly to North Dakota
came from three major source regions in Ontario:
the Huron Tract, Glengarry County, and
Bruce and Grey Counties, all areas experiencing
significant population pressure. Many
others from Ontario and other parts of eastern
Canada lived in states such as Michigan
and Illinois before settling in North Dakota.
Those who came to homestead settled primarily
along the Red River and the northern
border, a pattern that still dominated in 1910.
Transplantation of Ontario communities, as
evidenced in the adoption of Canadian placenames,
was made possible by processes of
chain and cluster migration.

Anglo-Canadians in North Dakota as elsewhere
displayed little attachment to group
symbols or institutions. The host society associated
them with their British roots, as did
many of the Canadians themselves. It was generally
easier for Canadians to adapt to an
Anglo-American way of life where Yankee traditions
shaped the banks, businesses, schools,
and politics. In fact, a significant number of
Anglo-Canadians, again primarily from Ontario,
came to North Dakota to take advantage
of the business opportunities accompanying
the opening of a new frontier. Anglo-
Canadians in Grand Forks, for example, mirrored
the American occupational profile more
than any other immigrant group. Yet residential
clustering in farm communities and in the
small towns of the region ensured that members
of this group interacted at both social and
economic levels. As elsewhere in the United
States, kinship and kith connections played
an important role in both location decisions
and adaptation experiences among Anglo-
Canadians. In addition, a high degree of endogamy
existed among this group in North
Dakota, although less so than for the Scandinavians
and Germans.

For many Anglo-Canadians, North Dakota
would only be a temporary stage in their lifelong
migration. Many eventually left the Red
River Valley because of increasing land prices
and mortgage rates and a series of poor crops.
Some of this group tried their luck in the western
part of the state, especially after 1904-5,
when both the Soo and Great Northern Railroads
built lines into the area. But the state's
efforts to settle its western half met with
strong competition from Canada. Given the
poor quality of the generally drier land in
western North Dakota and the lure of cheap
homestead land north of the border, many ex-
Canadians, as well as others from the state and
elsewhere throughout the region, crossed the
boundary into Saskatchewan and Alberta.
The migration focus at the turn of the century
was on the Last Best West, and eastern Canadians
intent on farming shifted their attention
toward the Canadian Prairies.

Little is known about Canadians in other
states, but it is likely that many of the same experiences
were repeated throughout the Great
Plains. Today, the Anglo-Canadian presence is
less visible throughout the region, as U.S. regulations
have restricted the number of immigrants,
and those who do emigrate from
Canada generally choose to locate in urban
regions with a more diverse economic base.
Yet since the Canada.U.S. Free Trade Agreement
and the North American Free Trade
Agreement went into effect in 1989 and 1994,
respectively, the flow of goods between the
two countries has increased even as the movement
of people has slowed considerably. Canada
is the top export market for most of the
states in the Plains, and much of their agricultural,
energy, and transportation needs are in
turn supplied by Canada. Thus, the tradition
of close links between people living on both
sides of the boundary within this international
region continues today, even though
the nature of this relationship has changed.

See also IMAGES AND ICONS: Last Best West /
INDUSTRY: NAFTA.



Randy William Widdis
University of Regina




Hudson, John C. "Migration to an American Frontier."
Annals of the Association of American Geographers 66
(1976): 242–65. Widdis, Randy W. With Scarcely a Ripple: Anglo-Canadian Migration into the United States and Western Canada, 1880–1920. Montreal: McGill-Queen's
University Press, 1998. Wilkins, Robert W., and Wynona
Huchette Wilkins. North Dakota: A Bicentennial History.
New York: W. W. Norton, 1977.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>