<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fil.016</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Dances with Wolves</field>
      <field name="author">Baird, Robert</field>
      <field name="text">

 




DANCES WITH WOLVES

Theatrical Release Poster
     

Kevin Costner's Academy Award-winning
Dances with Wolves (1990) is likely the most
powerful cinematic reminder of the grandeur
of the prairie that once spanned the heart of
the North American continent. Although best
known for its revisionist treatment of Indians
(Lakota Sioux) in the last years of and just after
the Civil War, Dances with Wolves offers many
scenes that help convey the color, breadth, and
vastness of the Great Plains. Dances was shot
on location for five months in South Dakota,
and the centerpiece of the film is an extended
buffalo hunt during which Costner's character,
Lt. John J. Dunbar, kills a wounded buffalo
that threatens a young Sioux and is then informally
initiated into the tribe. For the hunt,
Costner took his actors and crew to a 62,000-
acre ranch northwest of Pierre, South Dakota.
Holding 3,500 head of bison, the ranch offers
visiting hunters the chance to shoot bison at
$1,500 a head.

Exploiting wide-screen cinematography
and an epic format more common to the
1950s and 1960s, Dances is a finely crafted film.
The acting is outstanding in a genre not
known for patient explorations of character;
the cinematography of a reimagined Great
Plains, cavalry blues, Sioux buckskin and face
paint, and horses, wolf, and buffalo blend a
wide-screen lushness with the austerity of a
nature documentary; the editing is expert;
and the gliding camera complements the restrained
performances of all the actors. Many
scenes and moments use little or no dialogue,
encouraging attention to imagery, sound effects,
and a now-alien aural environment.
Early in the film, Dunbar silently brushes his
hand across the waist-high grasses of the
prairie. Later in the film, we see Kicking Bird
(Grahame Greene) repeat the gesture. The
parallelism provides a powerful evocation of
the sublime force of the great prairie on people
of the period. While classic Westerns had
most often been set in valleys over which the
Rockies towered or amidst the other-worldly
landscapes of Monument Valley, Dances with Wolves carefully and quietly evoked the grandeur
of a more subtle geography, where muted
earth tones and the big sky dominate.

In November 1993 ABC broadcast a longer
version of Dances that incorporated footage
left out of the original American theatrical release.
Much of the material, nearly an hour
long, expanded on themes established in the
first film. More environmental destruction is
seen. A white hunting camp on sacred Sioux
grounds is strewn with animal carcasses and
empty whisky bottles. The prior inhabitants
of Fort Sedgewick are shown, isolated on the
Plains and surrounded by Indians, the remainder
of the command reduced to savage
living in cliff-side dugouts–a dark contrast to
Dunbar's successful transition to nature and
Indian ways. A recent treatment of the "vanishing
American" narrative, Dances ends, unsurprisingly,
far above the Plains, with Dunbar
and his bride, Stands with a Fist, ascending
a remote, snow-covered mountain, their tribe
hunted by the army, the prairie no longer a
refuge from accelerating encroachment.


Robert Baird
University of Illinois




Bird, Elizabeth S. Dressing in Feathers: The Construction of the Indian in American Popular Culture. Boulder CO: Westview
Press, 1996. Blake, Michael. Dances with Wolves. New
York: Ballantine, 1988. Rollins, Peter C., and John E.
O'Connor, eds. Hollywood's Indian: The Portrayal of the Native American in Film. Lexington: University Press of
Kentucky, 1998.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>