<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.022</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Grey, Zane (1872-1939)</field>
      <field name="author">Kimball, Arthur G.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




GREY, ZANE (1872-1939)

Zane Grey holds a Koala during a visit to Australia
    

Immensely popular in the 1910s and 1920s as a
writer of Western romances such as Heritage of the Desert (1910) and Riders of the Purple Sage (1912), Zane Grey also wrote sporting and
adventure novels and short stories. He was
born Pearl Zane Grey on January 31, 1872, in
Zanesville, Ohio. He practiced dentistry in
New York City from 1896 to 1904 before traveling
extensively in the West. He died on October
23, 1939, in Altadena, California.

Vintage Grey features a romantic adventure
during which a couple, often two couples, find
true love, marriage, and wealth after overcoming
obstacles in an environment made ambiguous
by conflicting laws. The majestic western
land confronts them: beauty, vastness, physical
challenge, and a renewing spirit. So does outlaw
violence: rustling, gunplay, and threats of
seduction, the latter enhancing the erotic appeal.
They respond with fists and guns. Splendid
horses frequently aid the protagonists. Native
Americans, either as enemies or victims,
often constitute a disturbing presence.

Sometimes locale specific, sometimes not,
Grey's narratives often travel the Great Plains.
In The Trail Driver (1936), Texas Joe Shipman
wins the love of orphan Reddy Bayne on an
1871 cattle drive from Texas to Dodge City.
Tough young Andrew Bonning prevails with
equally tough runaway Martha Ann Dixon in
Wyoming (1953). The earlier U.P. Trail (1918)
celebrates the building of the Union Pacific
Railroad. Several Grey novels involve Texas
Rangers. Wade Holden in Shadow on the Trail
(1946) has to escape them to prove himself. In
Lone Star Ranger (1915) Buck Duane flees from
and then secretly joins the Rangers to clear his
name. The close reader will find intriguing ironies
in Grey; in both Heritage of the Desert and
Lone Star Ranger conflicting and ambiguous
laws call into question their very meaning.


Arthur G. Kimball
Huron International University Tokyo




Kimball, Arthur G. Ace of Hearts: The Westerns of Zane Grey. Fort Worth: Texas Christian University Press, 1993.
Scott, Kenneth W. Zane Grey: Born to the West: A Reference Guide. Boston: G. K. Hall, 1979.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>