<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.gen.032</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Salter, Susanna (1860-1961)</field>
      <field name="author">Leland, Suzanne M.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SALTER, SUSANNA (1860-1961)

Susanna Madora Salter was the first woman to
become mayor in the state of Kansas, and she
was probably the first woman mayor in the
United States. Susanna Madora, or "Dora,"
was born in Ohio on March 2, 1860, and
moved to Kansas with her family when she
was twelve. At age sixteen she enrolled at
Kansas State Agricultural College (later Kansas
State University) in Manhattan; she graduated
in 1879. In September of 1880 Dora met
and married Lewis Salter, son of former lieutenant
governor of Kansas Melville J. Salter.
Susanna's husband ran a hardware store in the
newly established Quaker town of Argonia in
Sumner County, Kansas, where Susanna became
politically active in the Woman's Christian
Temperance Union, founded in 1883.

When Salter was elected mayor in 1887 she
received congratulatory telegrams from all
over the world. She never campaigned for the
position; in fact, by some accounts her name
was placed on the ballot as a joke. Women in
Kansas had just received the right to vote in
municipal elections, and several men in Argonia
were determined to embarrass her by
placing her name on the ballot. To the surprise
of many (herself included), Susanna,
aged twenty-seven, received two-thirds of the
vote. She served for only one uneventful year
and is said to have ceded most of her decisionmaking
power to the men seated on the council.
Even though she was encouraged to run
for an additional term, Susanna refused because
she wished to spend her time with her
eight children.

The Salters took out a claim near Alva,
Oklahoma, in 1893, following the opening of
the Cherokee Strip. After her husband's death
in 1916, Susanna moved her family to Norman,
Oklahoma, where she lived until her
death on March 16, 1961, at age 101.


Suzanne M. Leland
University of North Carolina at Charlotte




Billington, Monroe. "Susanna Madora Salter—First Woman
Mayor." Kansas Historical Quarterly 21 (1954): 173–83.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>