<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.med.012</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Cronkite, Walter Leland (b. 1916)</field>
      <field name="author">James, Doug</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CRONKITE, WALTER LELAND (b. 1916)

Walter Leland Cronkite Jr., the American
journalist whose objectivity and credibility
prompted Time magazine to name him the
most trusted man in America, greatly influenced
the development of national television
news reporting while serving as anchor and
managing editor at CBS News from 1962 to
1981.

Cronkite was born November 4, 1916, in St.
Joseph, Missouri. When his dentist father received
a World War I army commission in
1917, the family moved to Kansas City, Missouri.
In 1928 the family relocated to Houston,
Texas. Cronkite graduated from high school
in 1933 and enrolled as a political science major
at the University of Texas at Austin. Uncertain
about his future vocation, he dropped out
of college in 1935 and worked at a wide variety
of jobs over much of the Midwest. After his
1940 marriage to Betsy Maxwell, Cronkite and
his wife moved to New York City, where he
had been assigned to the United Press foreign
office.

In 1942 Cronkite accepted a position as a
war correspondent based in London, where
he distinguished himself for bravery and professionalism.
Following the surrender of Nazi
Germany in 1945, he was named chief United
Press correspondent at the Nuremberg war
trials. In 1946 he was sent to Moscow for two
years, accompanied by his wife. At Edward R.
Murrow's invitation, Cronkite left United
Press in 1948 to work at radio station kmbd in
Washington DC. In 1951 after joining cbsowned
television station WTOP, his Man of the Week program attracted the attention of CBS
executives. He was chosen to cover the first
televised national political convention in 1952
in Chicago as well as every ensuing convention
while he was with CBS News. Cronkite
was transferred by CBS to New York City in
1953 to host The Twentieth Century, Eyewitness to History, and You Are There.

In 1961 America was introduced to the space
age with Cronkite's televised live launch of
Alan B. Shepard, the first American in space.
Cronkite covered every manned NASA flight
until his retirement. After a 1968 fact-finding
trip to Southeast Asia, Cronkite declared his
opposition to the increasingly unpopular Vietnam
War on a special news program and challenged
the misleading optimism expressed by
governmental officials. His pronouncement
had a powerful impact on American politics,
influencing Lyndon Johnson's decision not to
run for reelection as president.

Cronkite, an outspoken defender of First
Amendment rights, received most of the
credit–or blame–for exposing the multifarious
criminal activities of members of
Richard Nixon's White House staff as they attempted
to cover up the Watergate break-in.
Intense pressure from the public and news
media eventually brought down the entire
Nixon administration.

Cronkite was also responsible for opening
the dialogue between Israeli prime minister
Menachem Begin and Egyptian president Anwar
Sadat, giving President Jimmy Carter the
opportunity to secure an agreement of cooperation
between the two nations in a historic
1979 White House ceremony.

By the time Cronkite retired from cbs in
1981, he had received every major broadcasting
honor as well as the Presidential Medal of
Freedom awarded to him by President Jimmy
Carter.


Doug James
Spring Hill College




James, Doug. Walter Cronkite: His Life and Times. Nashville:
JMP Press, 1991.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>