<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.med.041</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Small-Town Newspapers</field>
      <field name="author">Freeland, Gloria B.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SMALL-TOWN NEWSPAPERS

There are hundreds if not thousands of smalltown
newspapers scattered throughout the
Great Plains, and they play an important role
in the health and vitality of their communities.
In the Canadian Plains, for example,
the Saskatchewan Weekly Newspapers Association
is composed of eighty weekly newspapers
reaching more than 500,000 readers.
The Alberta Weekly Newspapers Association
is about eighty years old and has 102 member
newspapers scattered throughout Alberta and
into the Northwest Territories. Some papers
have a history that goes back to the 1800s; others
are brand new.

Traditionally, the community newspaper
was defined as a nondaily publication serving a
small community. However, as markets, business
models, and technologies have changed
over the years, it is no longer feasible to distinguish
community newspapers based upon
frequency or circulation size. A community
newspaper may be published once a week, several
times a week, or daily. With the emergence
of the Internet, some community newspapers
exist only in cyberspace. Regardless of frequency
or method of distribution, most community
newspapers are committed to providing
local information and related services that
serve and strengthen their communities.

In frontier days, as people moved west, so
too did newspapers, largely because of the
portability and durability of the flatbed press.
A newspaper became one of the earliest marks
of a new Plains community. When a newspaper
arrived in Leavenworth, Kansas Territory,
in 1854, for example, the town consisted
of four tents. Denver's Rocky Mountain News
was first published in 1859 in a saloon attic.
Legh and Frederick Freeman, two former
Confederate telegraph operators, started the
Kearney Herald at Fort Kearny in Nebraska in
1865, then traveled west with the construction
of the Union Pacific, setting up their press at
every new railhead. They first published their
Frontier Index in North Platte and then continued
into Dakota Territory (later Wyoming
Territory).

Evangelists and social activists also pioneered
publishing in the Great Plains. Outspoken
former lawyers, preachers, teachers,
politicians, farmers, miners, and others tried
their hand at journalism. A local editor could
inspire voters and make himself an important
figure in the community. Most editors were
men, but women also participated in the region's
journalism, first as editors' wives and
then leading the papers after their husbands
died. Carry Nation, with her Smasher's Mail,
published in Medicine Lodge, Kansas, in the
first years of the twentieth century, promoted
temperance and prohibition. Woman suffrage
and feminism found early champions in western
newspapers.

Editors were expected to serve the local interests
of their communities by campaigning
for territorial status or statehood, for railroads,
and for or against the abolition of slavery.
Marriages, deaths, births, social events,
prairie fires, lodge meetings, and rumors of
gold and silver strikes were included, along
with stories of local gunfights. One famous
story was the Bismarck Tribune's account of
George Armstrong Custer's defeat at the Battle
of the Little Bighorn in 1876, an account based
on notes retrieved from the body of accompanying
reporter Mark Kellogg.

Papers in the West were known for their
quirky independence. One radical publication
that broke through to a mass audience was
Appeal to Reason, published in Girard, Kansas.
In 1912 it had a circulation of 750,000. Another
small-town newspaper that transcended local
importance was the Emporia Gazette, published
by William Allen White from 1895 to
1944.

Until the late 1800s, little thought was given
to training editors and reporters. For more
than a century, the emphasis was on printing,
and future editors learned to set type under
the apprentice system. But there were some
modest efforts at training. In the 1840s young
Native American students in Indian Territory
were being trained in printing, and as early as
1848 girls at the Park Hill Seminary were producing
a school paper, the Cherokee Rosebud.
Printing in Indian Territory started with the
Cherokee Almanac, which began publishing in
1835 at Tahlequah. Another Native American
newspaper, the Shawnee Sun, began in 1835
at Shawnee Mission in what would become
Kansas. Basic training manuals for journalists
existed in the 1860s, and as early as 1873 Kansas
State College offered printing classes for rural
publishers.

Rural free delivery in 1896 made it possible
for large dailies to reach into rural areas, and
people predicted the end of rural weeklies. Instead,
a special emphasis on local coverage actually
strengthened the small-town papers because
they no longer had to devote space to
world or national events. During World War I
local newspapers promoted war bonds, Red
Cross campaigns, salvage efforts, and recruitment
programs. Personnel problems developed
as printers and editors went off to war,
and many times wives had to fill in. In the
1920s, despite competition for advertising
from radio, many small newspapers, with better
equipment and better business methods,
attained solid footing in their communities.
This did not prevent a large number of failures
during the Great Depression. Newspaper editors
went back to the old system of bartering
because their readers could not afford to buy
the paper and businesses could not afford to
advertise. Still, the Depression was a time of
leadership for many small-town papers. Editorials
called for community efforts to overcome
local problems and promoted optimism.
Papers closed again when World War II
broke out, while others carried on with wives,
sisters, and mothers assuming the responsibilities
of publishing. Newspapers were considered
vital to the war effort because of their
ability to maintain morale on the home front.
When veterans returned home, they flocked
to universities, and interest in journalism careers
rose, in large part because of the experiences
of wartime correspondents.

The years after World War II saw a revolution
in production methods and a change in
the organization of the publishing business
that greatly affected community newspapers.
In the 1950s the change from metal to film
production accelerated, especially at nondaily
newspapers, which could more easily make
the switch since they had fewer machines–
and people–to deal with. Since new production
processes made it easier to start a paper
and suburban expansion increased the need
for more papers, another development, the
newspaper chain, brought change to community
newspaper management. Computers in
the newsroom, the development of digital
cameras, and the convergence of print, audio,
and video on the Internet combined to make
the last few years of the twentieth century an
exciting time for those involved in small-town
newspapers. As with any changes, some newspapers
embraced the new technologies, while
others tried to avoid them.

But the one constant in small-town newspapers
is that they strive to provide people
with local news about their schools, government,
clubs, and activities. They continue to
announce births, deaths, weddings, and anniversaries.
Editors of small-town newspapers
know that if they chronicle people's lives and
the events around them, people will read their
papers.

See also CITIES AND TOWNS: Small Towns / 
PROTEST AND DISSENT: Appeal to Reason; Nation, Carry.


Gloria B. Freeland
Kansas State University




America's Premier Community Newspapers. Arlington VA:
National Newspaper Association, 1998. Karolevitz, Robert
E. From Quill to Computer: The Story of America's Community Newspapers. Freeman SD: Pine Hill Press, 1985.
Sloan, William David, James G. Stovall, and James D.
Startt. The Media in America: A History. Scottsdale AZ:
Publishing Horizons, 1993.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>