<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ha.002</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Adam-Onís Treaty</field>
      <field name="author">Redinger, Matthew A.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ADAM-ONÍS TREATY

The Adams-Onís Treaty of February 12, 1819,
also known as the "Transcontinental Treaty,"
which settled border disputes between the
United States and the Spanish Empire, proved
vital to the nation's security. The catalyst
for the negotiations between U.S. Secretary
of State John Quincy Adams and the Spanish
minister to the United States, Luís de Onís y
Gonzalez, was border raids by Seminoles out
of Spanish Florida. Once negotiations over
Florida commenced, the issue of borders in
the Great Plains and Pacific Northwest came
to the fore.

Central to Spain's willingness to accept
Adams's border demands in the Great Plains
was the secretary of state's eventual willingness
to give up claims on Spanish Texas. After
lengthy negotiations, Adams and Onís established
a Louisiana Purchase boundary line
that followed the Sabine, Red, and Arkansas
Rivers northwest to the forty-second parallel
and then straight west to the Pacific. In accepting
this line, Spain relinquished all claims to
the Pacific Northwest, thereby improving the
chances of the United States gaining control of
the region.

The most significant element of the treaty
was Adams's insistence that the boundary be
extended to the Pacific. Adams's skillful negotiations
opened the way for the United States
to become a transcontinental power. In asserting
for the United States a continental presence,
Adams secured what he believed to be
his most important diplomatic achievement,
and one that marked a new era in U.S. history.


Matthew A. Redinger
Montana State University-Billings




Bemis, Samuel Flagg. John Quincy Adams and the Foundations of American Foreign Policy. New York: Alfred A.
Knopf, Inc., 1949. Brooks, Philip Coolidge. Diplomacy of the Borderlands: The Adams-Onís Treaty of 1819. New York:
Octagon Books, 1970.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>