<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.arc.009</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Cold War Architecture</field>
      <field name="author">Penny, Dori M.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




COLD WAR ARCHITECTURE

The proliferation of tract housing, the popularization
of fallout shelters, and the construction
of missile bases were all a result of
shifts in the American and Canadian outlook
during the cold war. The rise of suburbs and
the construction of large military facilities
during and after World War II changed greatly
the architectural fabric of the Great Plains.
The mass-produced housing of Levittown,
New York, was the model for the construction
of subsequent suburbs, including those in the
Great Plains. William Levitt, the builder, used
methods that had been developed by the military
during World War II for the rapid construction
of installations. Levitt popularized
off-site prefabrication and task specialization
in the construction of postwar housing that
was intended to supply the needs of returning
servicemen.

Ranch-style houses are typical of the 1950s
developments outside the larger cities of the
Great Plains. Most of these homes are one
story, with a low pitched roof and a wide
eave overhang. They also lack the formalized
spaces of earlier eras. This absence of dining
rooms, hallways, and elaborated entryways
made these houses less expensive to build. Picture
and ribbon windows are often present.
An attached or built-in garage is also typical, a
physical manifestation of the importance of
cars in suburban living.

With the deterioration of relations between
the Soviet Union and the United States in
the late 1950s and early 1960s came the threat
of nuclear war and the need for fallout shelters.
In a 1959 publication the Office of Civil
and Defense Mobilization provided plans and
installation instructions for four different
types of fallout shelters: a basement shelter
constructed with concrete blocks, an aboveground
double-wall shelter constructed with
concrete blocks, a prefabricated metal shelter,
and an underground concrete shelter. Advertisements
for houses constructed in the 1950s
and 1960s suggested that shelters could be included
in new home construction at a nominal
cost.

Public and private shelters usually relied on
barrier shielding. This shielding, usually thicknesses
of concrete or earth, was intended
to provide protection by absorbing part of
the radiation generated by a nuclear explosion.
Due to their additional mass, multistory
buildings were believed to provide the most
protection. Based on this idea, shelters were
established in the lower levels of schools and
office buildings.

Active bases and missile sites of the Strategic
Air Command are still present throughout the
Great Plains. Many of the buildings are unassuming
in appearance, with one- or two-story
structures belying the presence of a multilevel
complex below the surface. The initiation of
the intercontinental ballistic missile (ICBM)
program represented both a physical and a
psychological shift in land use in the Great
Plains. F. E. Warren Air Force Base outside of
Cheyenne, Wyoming, was selected as the first
icbm complex in 1957. ICBM complexes were
also constructed at the Mead Ordnance Depot
and at Offutt Air Force Base in Nebraska. Early
complexes, housing Atlas squadrons, included
a launch operations building, three launch
and service buildings, a power plant and
pump house, storage magazines, and a tower,
all enclosed within a security fence. The buildings
are monolithic and industrial in appearance.
The launch operations and launch and
service buildings were constructed of concrete.
The silos are of semihardened concrete,
capable of withstanding overpressures
of twenty-five pounds per square inch. Auxiliary
buildings, such as those found at the entry
to the facility, were generally wood frame clad
with corrugated metal. While the first facilities
emphasized centralized placement, later facilities
utilized plans that separated launch control
centers and missile silos over large areas.

Other ICBM programs included Shark,
Thor, Jupiter, Titan, Minuteman, and Peacekeeper.
The Minuteman B missile was installed
from 1958 to 1962 in 200 silos scattered
across 8,000 square miles. Minuteman B was
replaced by the Minuteman III in 1973. Minuteman
III and Peacekeeper are active programs.
Some abandoned Atlas and Titan facilities
have been remodeled into homes in
several states, including Kansas.

See also IMAGES AND ICONS: Missile Silos / WAR: Cold War.


Dori M. Penny
Larson-Tibesar Associates




Martin, Thomas L., Jr., and Donald C. Latham. Strategy for Survival. Tucson: University of Arizona Press, 1963.
May, Elaine Tyler. Homeward Bound: American Families in the Cold War Era. New York: Basic Books, 1988. Office of
Civil and Defense Mobilization. The Family Fallout Shelter.
Washington DC: Government Printing Office, 1959.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>