<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.war.004</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Arikara Expedition</field>
      <field name="author">Behrens, Joe Lea Wetherilt</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ARIKARA EXPEDITION

Early 1823 proved deadly along the upper Missouri
River after a series of Indian attacks
on fur trappers and trading posts caused staggering
economic losses, especially to the Missouri
Fur Company. In particular, the Arikaras
opposed American attempts to move upriver,
which would eliminate their middleman role
in the fur trade. On June 2 they attacked William
Ashley's trapping party, which was
camped near their villages, close to the confluence
of the Grand and Missouri Rivers, killing
fourteen men. When the survivors limped
into Fort Atkinson (in present-day Nebraska)
on June 18, Col. Henry Leavenworth and Indian
agent Benjamin O'Fallon decided that
American military strength had to be demonstrated.
This would be the first major U.S. expedition
against the Plains Indians.

Leavenworth left Fort Atkinson on June 22
with 230 men of the Sixth U.S. Infantry and
two cannons to punish the Arikaras. Joining
him five days later was trader Joshua Pilcher,
head of the Missouri Fur Company, with sixty
men and a howitzer. Ashley's men added
eighty to the force, and about 700 Lakotas
joined in to fight their enemies, the Arikaras.
As the force neared the villages on August 9,
the Lakotas rode ahead and engaged the Arikaras,
killing ten to fifteen of them. At dawn
on August 10, Leavenworth trained his artillery
on the stockaded Arikara villages, but
they mainly overshot the target. When the
Lakotas deserted the fight to raid the Arikaras'
cornfields, the troops were forced to face an
expected battle alone. Seizing an opportunity
to negotiate with Arikara leaders, Leavenworth
asked them to return Ashley's property
and to promise future good behavior. The
Arikaras were allowed to leave their besieged
villages on the night of August 14. Ashley
seemingly accepted this outcome, but Pilcher
was infuriated.

On August 15 Leavenworth and his troops
headed downriver, followed by Pilcher with
his contingent of trappers. Angry at the dismal
show of force against the Arikaras, Pilcher
set fire to both of their villages. This action
naturally further alienated the Arikaras, who
continued to resist American inroads on the
upper Missouri. Forced to seek a new route to
the trapping grounds, Ashley and his men
forged the overland route into the Central
Rockies through South Pass. The new trail set
the stage for the enormous future pioneer migration
along the Platte Valley and into the
West in the 1840s.

See also INDUSTRY: Fur Trade / NATIVE AMERICANS: Arikaras.


Jo Lea Wetherilt Behrens
University of Nebraska at Omaha




Meyer, Roy Willard. The Village Indians of the Upper Missouri:
The Mandans, Hidatsas, and Arikaras. Lincoln: University
of Nebraska Press, 1977. Morgan, Dale L. Jedediah
Smith and the Opening of the West. Lincoln: University of
Nebraska Press, 1964.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>