<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.art.030</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Henri, Robert (1865-1929)</field>
      <field name="author">Zaruba, Gary</field>
      <field name="text">

 




HENRI, ROBERT (1865-1929)

Robert Henri was a renowned American
painter and teacher in the late nineteenth century
and first quarter of the twentieth century.
He was born Robert Henry Cozad in Cincinnati,
Ohio, on June 24, 1865. His father, John J.
Cozad, a riverboat gambler and land speculator,
settled and developed present-day Cozad,
Nebraska. Robert spent his early years on the
family ranch and attended school in Cozad.
The family hastily left the Plains in 1882 when
Robert's father killed one of his workers in
self-defense.

Robert Henri–the name he adopted because
of fear of repercussions from the Cozad
incident–enrolled in the Pennsylvania Academy
of the Fine Arts in 1886 and studied under
Thomas P. Anshutz. In 1888 he made the first
of a number of visits to Europe when he studied
with Adolphe William Bouguereau at the
Académie Julian in Paris. He found the teaching
in Paris to be stifling, but he was inspired
by the masterpieces in the Louvre and, subsequently,
by the works of Diego Velázquez and
Frans Hals.

Henri taught in Philadelphia, New York,
and Paris. He encouraged his students to seek
the freedom of individual expression and to
break from the European academies' and the
National Academy of Design's conformity to
tradition. Young artists who were influenced
by his teaching include William Glackens,
George Luks, Everett Shinn, and John Sloan,
later members of the Eight, or Ashcan school.
Stuart Davis, George Bellows, and Edward
Hopper were also inspired by his teaching.

Although Henri's reputation was based
mainly on his teaching, he painted many fine
landscapes, cityscapes, and portraits, including
hundreds of portraits of Irish children. He
painted with energetic brushwork, using a
dark palette with sharp contrasts of light and
shade, as seen in Girl in Wedding Gown (1910).
Henri continued to receive honors for his
work right up until his death on July 12, 1929,
in New York.



Gary Zaruba
University of Nebraska at Kearney




Henri, Robert. The Art Spirit. New York: Harper and Row,
1984. Homer, William Innes. Robert Henri and His Circle.
Ithaca NY: Cornell University Press, 1969. Robert Henri.
Exhibition Catalog. Lincoln: Nebraska Art Association,
1971.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>