<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ag.037</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Farm Security Administration</field>
      <field name="author">Lavender, Catherine J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




FARM SECURITY ADMINISTRATION

The Farm Security Administration (FSA) was
created through the Bankhead-Jones Farm
Tenant Act in September of 1937, in order to
deal with the chronic poverty of American independent
farmers and migrant farm laborers.
This act created the fsa out of the Resettlement
Administration, which President
Franklin Roosevelt had launched via an executive
order in the spring of 1935.

The FSA's activities fell into two chief categories:
rationalization of farming in order to
increase its e.ciency and decrease cyclical agricultural
booms and busts and elevation of
public awareness of the problems confronting
farmers, especially in the Dust Bowl–ravaged
Southern Plains. In order to achieve the former
goal, the FSA sponsored fragmentary
land-use reform, provided loans which Farmers
Unions used to build cooperatives, and offered
rehabilitation and settlement camps for
a limited number of migrant farmworkers.
fsa-sponsored photography documented the
struggles of farmers and migrant farm workers,
and included the work of Dorothea Lange,
Walker Evans, Ben Shahn, Roy Striker, and
Marion Post Wolcott. The FSA also sponsored
Pare Lorentz's influential documentary, The Plow That Broke the Plains (1936). In the Great
Plains, the fsa helped launch irrigation projects,
most notably on the Platte River in Nebraska
and the Colorado River in Texas. It also
offered soil conservation assistance and loans
at 3 percent to farmers, while sponsoring continued
research into the causes and outcomes
of the ecological crisis of the Dust Bowl in the
region.

The Farmers Home Administration Act of
1946, signed into law by President Harry S.
Truman, abolished the FSA and created the
Farmers Home Administration (FHA) in its
place.

See also ART: Dust Bowl Photographers / FILM: The Plow That Broke the Plains.


Bradley H. Baltensperger
Michigan Technological University




Baldwin, Sidney. Poverty and Politics: The Rise and Decline of the Farm Security Administration. Chapel Hill: University
of North Carolina Press, 1968. Lowitt, Richard. The New Deal and the West. Bloomington: Indiana University
Press, 1984. Worster, Donald. Dust Bowl: The Southern Plains in the 1930s. New York: Oxford University Press,
1979.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>