<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pd.043</field>
      <field name="titleMain">On-to-Ottawa Trek</field>
      <field name="author">Waiser, Bill</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ON-TO-OTTAWA TREK

In early April 1935 hundreds of dissatisfied,
disillusioned men walked out of federally run
relief camps throughout British Columbia
and descended on Vancouver in a bold attempt to reverse their dead-end lives and
bring about some kind of "work for wages"
program. No one wanted to deal with the
men, least of all Conservative prime minister
R. B. Bennett, who believed that the Communist
Party of Canada had orchestrated the protest.
As the stalemate dragged on week after
numbing week, the men decided to go to Ottawa
and lay their grievances directly before
the government.

An estimated 1,000 On-to-Ottawa trekkers
left Vancouver by freight train in early June
1935. No attempt was made to stop them. Police
and government authorities confidently
assumed that the resolve of the workers on
relief would melt away like the snow in the
interior mountains. But as the freight train
the men were riding gained momentum as it
rumbled down the Albertan foothills into the
Prairies, so too did the trek. The audacity of
the men stirred the imagination of those who
had suffered through five terrible years of
drought and depressed prices. Here were hundreds
of young men headed to Ottawa to
tell the country's political leaders that they
were not doing enough to help ease the hardship
and deprivation of western Canada. The
Bennett government, on the other hand, saw
only an army of single, homeless, unemployed
men who had nothing to lose and might to do
anything.

As the trek continued east from Calgary, the
Canadian government hurriedly made plans
to bring it to an end. Not only had the ranks
of the trekkers swollen to 1,500 because of
a number of new recruits from Alberta, but
hundreds more were expected to join in Winnipeg.
The federal government consequently
announced that the trek would be stopped at
Regina, on the grounds that it was an unlawful
movement.

The On-to-Ottawa Trek, numbering an estimated
2,000 men, reached Regina on June 14.
Over the next two weeks, the two sides tried
unsuccessfully to reach some kind of agreement;
a special meeting between the trek leaders and
the prime minister, for example, quickly degenerated
into a shouting match. With no way out
of Regina, the trekkers decided at the end of
June to return to the west coast. But Ottawa
insisted that the group had to disband on federal
terms–namely, go to a nearby hurriedly erected
holding facility where the men would be processed.
The trek leadership balked at this
proposal–they wanted nothing to do with a
"concentration camp"–and turned to Jimmy
Gardiner's provincial government for assistance
on the afternoon of July 1.

Later that evening, while the provincial cabinet
met to discuss the trek request, the North-West
Mounted Police, with the support of the
Regina city police, decided to execute warrants
for the trek leaders at a public rally at Market
Square. The mounted police could easily have
made the arrests at any time during the day, but
instead, with clubs and tear gas at the ready,
chose to pluck the men from a peaceful fundraising
meeting. The raid quickly degenerated
into a pitched battle between the police and
trekkers and citizens, which spilled over into
the streets of downtown Regina. Order was not
restored until the early hours of the next day,
and only after the police had fired directly into
crowds of rioters. The toll was one dead, a good
number injured, more than 100 arrested, and
thousands of dollars in damage.

In the immediate aftermath of the riot, the
Saskatchewan government launched a public
inquiry. Three hundred and fifty-nine witnesses
provided fifty-three volumes of testimony
and one inescapable conclusion–the
police had provoked the violence by trying to
arrest the trek leaders at a public rally. But in
their two-volume report, the commissioners
assigned the blame for the riot to the trekkers,
while the police were completely exonerated.

The On-to-Ottawa Trek was a testament to
how the Canadian government had so miserably
failed the country's single, homeless, unemployed
population during the Great Depression.
It also underscored how the Canadian government
was prepared to use force in the interests
of "peace, order, and good government."

See also CITIES AND TOWNS: Regina, Saskatchewan
/ POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT: Bennett, Richard B.


Bill Waiser
University of Saskatchewan




Brown, Lorne. When Freedom Was Lost: The Unemployed,
the Agitator, and the State. Montreal: Black Rose Books,
1987. Howard, Victor. "We Were the Salt of the Earth!": A
Narrative of the On-to-Ottawa Trek and the Regina Riot.
Regina: Canadian Plains Research Center, 1985. Saskatchewan
Archives Board.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>