<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.law.018</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Hall, Emmett (1898-1995)</field>
      <field name="author">Gerber, Linda M.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




HALL, EMMETT (1898-1995)

Born at St. Colomban, Quebec, on November
9, 1898, Emmett Matthew Hall moved to
Saskatoon, Saskatchewan, with his family at
age twelve. Later, he studied law at the University
of Saskatchewan (he was a classmate of
John Diefenbaker), graduating at age twentyone.
While Diefenbaker was prime minister,
Hall was elevated to chief justice of Saskatchewan
(1961) and to Canada's Supreme Court,
where he served from 1962 until his retirement
in 1973 at age seventy-five.

This record only partially defines the man,
for Emmett Hall served Canada in a wide range
of roles. By 1962, with Saskatchewan premier
Tommy Douglas, he had developed a comprehensive
plan for publicly supported medical
care. Diefenbaker then asked him to chair
a royal commission on health services, overcome
resistance on the part of the medical
profession, and design a system of universal
health care for all of Canada. Hall's 1964–65
Report of the Royal Commission on Health Services
was implemented in 1967 under Prime
Minister Lester B. Pearson.

While Hall made his mark as the father of
medicare, he also reported on primary and
secondary school education in Ontario (1968),
university organization and structure (1973),
railway arbitration (1973), as well as grain handling
and transportation (1974). Furthermore,
he was a popular and involved chancellor at the
University of Guelph (1971–77) and at the University
of Saskatchewan (1980–86).

At the time of his death on November 12,
1995, at age ninety-six, Emmett Hall was recognized
as an outstanding Canadian. When
he retired from the Supreme Court, he was
appointed a Companion of the Order of Canada
(1974)–the highest honor bestowed by
Canada–for his lifetime of service to the law,
health services, and education. Hall's incomparable
commitment and energy are apparent
in the fact that so many of his contributions in
health care and education came when he was
seventy to eighty-five years old. Modern Canadian
society, in large measure, is shaped by
the vision of this one man.

See also POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT: Diefenbaker, John.


Linda M. Gerber
University of Guelph





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>