<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ind.053</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Small-Town Industrialization</field>
      <field name="author">Darlington, Lisa England, Matthew A.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SMALL-TOWN INDUSTRIALIZATION

Towns and villages with populations of fewer
than 2,500 people are a common feature of the
Great Plains region. Such small towns in the
Plains are home to a diverse collection of
manufacturing industries producing goods
such as animal feeds, toys, antibiotics, potato
chips, computers, plywood, leather handbags,
and plastic pipe. Manufactured goods primarily
are sold in wholesale markets, but a
number of small-town firms in the Great
Plains sell directly to consumers.

Despite the diversity of products manufactured
in small towns in the region, there are
some industries that dominate the landscape,
based on numbers of establishments. Not surprisingly,
a number of these dominant industries
are connected to the agricultural base of
the region. Of the ten manufacturing industries
that account for just over 50 percent of all
manufacturing in small towns at the threedigit
standard industrial classification (SIC)
level, four are agriculturally based: farm machinery
production, meat processing, grain
products, and miscellaneous food products.
The most prevalent industry, however, is not
driven by agriculture but by the need for information.
The printing and publishing of daily
and weekly newspapers account for nearly 13
percent of manufacturing in small towns in the
Great Plains region. The production of farm
equipment and machinery is the second most
common industry in small towns, accounting
for approximately 7 percent of all firms.

Small-town manufacturing firms often produce
more than one product. For example,
since the processes and equipment used for
newspaper and commercial printing are very
similar, and since small towns may not have
enough demand for commercial printing for a
stand-alone operation to be successful, many
small-town newspapers offer commercial
printing services. Farm machinery producers
also commonly produce vehicle and engine
parts, specialized industrial or commercial
machinery, and fabricated metal. Many of
these companion products also are related
to agricultural facilities and processes. Finally,
grain-milling firms may also produce
foods such as pasta and crackers in addition to
marketing certain pesticides, herbicides, and
fertilizers.

The mix of industries does not vary considerably
across towns of different sizes. The
smallest towns, those with populations below
250, however, have a greater proportion of
farm machinery and equipment (often small
machine shops) and lumber products firms
and a lower proportion of printing and publishing
firms when compared to larger towns.
There generally is little variation in the type
of small-town manufacturing activity taking
place across the region. The agricultural base
of the region drives much of the activity.

Small-town industries range in size from
those employing more than 1,000 workers to
home-based businesses employing no paid
workers. Nearly 70 percent of all small-town
manufacturers employ fewer than ten people.
The smallest firms account for nearly three-quarters
of manufacturers in towns with fewer
than 500 residents and for nearly two-thirds
of firms in towns with populations between
2,000 and 2,500.

Employment sizes vary among the most
common industries. The vast majority of
small-town printing and publishing firms (approximately
90 percent) employ fewer than ten
workers. Food-processing firms (including
meat processors and grain mills) tend to be
larger overall, with about 60 percent employing
fewer than ten workers and nearly one-quarter
employing from ten to twenty-four
employees. Just over half of machinery and
equipment producers employ fewer than ten
workers, but nearly a quarter employ up to
200. A small number of firms, mainly food
processors, actually employ workforces greater
in number than the population of the town in
which the firms are located. These firms are
major employers not only in the towns but also
in the areas surrounding them as well.

Relatively few manufacturing industries in
small towns are subsidiaries of national or international
firms. The largest proportion of
this type of subsidiary firm is found in towns
with populations from 500 to 1,499. The majority
of small-town enterprises, however, are
stand-alone profit centers, often sole proprietorships,
or subsidiaries of firms located
within the same state.

See also CITIES AND TOWNS: Small Towns.


Lisa Darlington
Matthew A. England
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Harris Info Source. 1997 Oklahoma Directory of Manufacturers
&amp; Processors. Twinsburg OH: Harris Info Source
Staff, 1997. Nebraska Department of Economic Development.
Nebraska Directory of Manufacturers and Their Products, 1998-1999. Lincoln NE: The Department, 1998.
U.S. Office of Management and Budget. Standard Industrial Classification Manual, 1987. Springfield VA: National
Technical Information Service, 1987.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>