<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.afam.027</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Love, Nat (1854-1921)</field>
      <field name="author">Love, Nat</field>
      <field name="text">

 




LOVE, NAT (1854-1921)


Nat Love (Deadwood Dick), between 1870 and 1890


Also known by his nickname Deadwood Dick,
Nat Love was born a slave in 1854 in Davidson
County, Tennessee. At the age of fifteen he
ventured to the Great Plains where, like many
ex-slaves, he found work in the cattle industry.
For twenty years he worked on cattle ranches
in the Texas Panhandle and Arizona. Love participated
in the great cattle drives of the 1870s,
driving herds to Dodge City, Kansas, and
to mining camps in Montana and the Black
Hills. While in Deadwood, Dakota Territory,
in July 1876, he reportedly earned the nickname
Deadwood Dick after winning a riding,
roping, and shooting competition. Love retired
from the cattle industry in 1890 and went
to work as a porter for the Denver and Rio
Grande Railroad. His last job was as a bank
guard in Los Angeles.

Love is best known for his autobiography,
The Life and Adventures of Nat Love, Better
Known in the Cattle Country as Deadwood
Dick (1907). Unfortunately, the book is highly
exaggerated, and it is difficult to separate truth
from fiction. Inspired by the Western dime
novels of the period, Love describes himself
as the best cowboy, best shooter, and hardest
drinker on the western frontier. The real life of
Nat Love, therefore, is difficult to trace. Nonetheless,
the book is high adventure and includes
colorful western personalities such as
Billy the Kid, Jesse James, and Buffalo Bill
Cody. Love reportedly married a woman
named Alice in 1889 and had one child. He
died in 1921 in Los Angeles, California.



Mark R. Ellis
University of Nebraska at Kearney




Katz, William Loren. The Black West. New York: Doubleday,
1971. Love, Nat. The Life and Adventures of Nat Love,
Better Known in the Cattle Country as Deadwood Dick.
New York: Arno Press, 1968.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>