<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ct.037</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Omaha, Nebraska</field>
      <field name="author">Darlstrom, Harl A.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




OMAHA, NEBRASKA


Omaha, Nebraska, 1900


Omaha was founded in 1854, but its roots date
from 1846, when the westbound Mormons entered
the area. From 1846 to 1848 Winter Quarters,
in modern northern Omaha, was the
Mormon departure point for the Salt Lake valley.
Because Winter Quarters was on Omaha
Indian land, the Mormons were eventually
obliged to make their nearby settlement of
Kanesville, Iowa, their jumping-off point. In
1853 Kanesville was renamed Council Bluffs,
and, although the Mormon preeminence in
the community passed, the town remained a
gateway to the Platte River valley, the easiest
overland route west.

The Kansas-Nebraska Act of 1854 unleashed
the energies of town-site promoters who saw
great futures for communities on the western
bank of the Missouri River. Omaha, Nebraska
Territory, was the product of such promoters
in Council Bluffs. A short distance south of
Omaha was Bellevue, a trading post, Indian
agency, and mission dating from the early
1820s. This settlement's established position
made it a logical site for the territorial capital,
but Governor Francis Burt's death soon after
his arrival in Bellevue aided Omaha's ambitions.
Acting Governor Thomas B. Cuming Jr.
championed Omaha, where he convened the
first territorial legislature in 1855. Despite opposition
from residents south of the Platte,
Omaha remained Nebraska's capital until
statehood in 1867.

The capital was crucial to Omaha's early development;
moreover, proximity to the Platte
valley made the town an outfitting point for
westbound travelers and a center of stagecoach
operations and wagon freighting. The
Rocky Mountain mining boom in 1859 created
close ties between Omaha and Denver. Down
the Missouri, Nebraska City became the territory's
principal wagon-freighting center and
Omaha's key rival. However, in 1863 President
Lincoln designated Iowa's border adjoining
Omaha as the eastern terminus of the Union
Pacific Railroad. The construction of that
line between 1865 and 1869 assured Omaha's
leadership in Nebraska and its regional
importance.

Railroads now tied Council Bluffs to Chicago,
and the completion of the Union Pacific
bridge between Omaha and Council Bluffs in
1872 secured the future of both communities
as rail centers. The construction of other
trans-Missouri lines soon expanded Omaha's
trade sector beyond the service area of the
Union Pacific and augmented Omaha's ties to
the Plains and the West. These links enabled
Omaha to become a smelting center and were
the prelude to the building of the Union
Stockyards in 1884 and South Omaha's rapid
evolution as a packing center.

The 1880s brought the greatest population
increase in Nebraska's history, and Omaha
more than tripled in size. Hard times in the
1890s halted this boom, yet the "Magic City"
of South Omaha, driven by meatpacking,
grew more than threefold. Indeed, the problems
of the nineties encouraged Omaha to
create the Knights of Ak-Sar-Ben (reverse
spelling of Nebraska), a civic group that fostered
closer relations with the city's trade area.
From its founding in 1893, the Commercial
Club (now the Greater Omaha Chamber of
Commerce) promoted business ties between
Omaha and other towns in Nebraska and adjoining
states and took an active interest in
the region's agriculture. Extolling western development,
in 1898 Omaha hosted the Trans-
Mississippi and International Exposition,
which drew some 2.6 million people.

In 1900 Omaha, with a population of
102,555, ranked behind San Francisco, Kansas
City, and Denver as the fourth largest trans-
Missouri city, just ahead of Los Angeles. Despite
its recent origin, South Omaha had a
population of 26,001. The establishment of
the Omaha Grain Exchange in 1903 and growing
wholesale enterprises further emphasized
the city's ties to the Central Plains. Omaha
absorbed South Omaha in 1915, and with
its established economic base, the city grew
gradually.

In 1910 some 53.7 percent of Omaha's residents
and about 64.2 percent of South Omaha's
residents were foreign-born white or had
at least one parent born outside the United
States. Persons of German, Scandinavian,
Czech, Irish, Polish, and Italian background
were numerous. The African American population
increased significantly between 1910
and 1920. South Omaha's anti-Greek riot in
1909 and the lynching of African American
men in 1891 and 1919 in Omaha were the worst
manifestations of ethnic prejudice. As the
civil rights movement grew during the mid–
twentieth century, African Americans sought
an end to employment and housing discrimination.
There were serious episodes of racial
confrontation in 1966, 1968, and 1969. As
the twentieth century closed, the key development
in Omaha's ethnic profile was a growing
Hispanic population.

Preparation for World War II brought the
Glenn L. Martin Bomber Plant to Fort Crook,
adjoining Bellevue. At its peak, the plant employed
14,572 workers, and its closing at war's
end briefly threatened the local economy.
However, the cold war and the establishment
of Strategic Air Command headquarters at
Offutt Air Force Base on the plant's site kept
the Bellevue-Omaha area crucial to American
defense. This major military presence outlasted
the cold war, and Bellevue's growth became
part of the general development of metropolitan
Omaha. From a 1940 population of
1,184, Bellevue grew steadily and has become
Nebraska's third largest city.

By 1955 Omaha was the world's leading livestock
market and meat-processing center, but
between 1967 and 1976 labor costs, outdated
plants, and environmental problems resulted
in a drastic decline in the local packing industry.
Marketing changes contributed to the end
of the Omaha Grain Exchange in 1985 and the
departure of the stockyards in 1999. Yet diversity
continued to mark Omaha's economic development
as service enterprises flourished.
Information technology became a major feature
of the city's livelihood, although at times
Omaha's location has been a challenge to its
growth as a corporate headquarters. In 2000
the metropolitan area had a population of
629,294.

See also AFRICAN AMERICANS: Omaha Race Riot / MEDIA: Omaha World-Herald / WAR: Strategic Air Command.


Harl A. Dalstrom
University of Nebraska at Omaha




Larsen, Lawrence H., and Barbara J. Cottrell. The Gate City: A History of Omaha. Lincoln: University of Nebraska
Press, 1997.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>