<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.sr.051</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Stecher, Joe (1893-1974)</field>
      <field name="author">Ellis, Mark R.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




STECHER, JOE (1893-1974)

Long before Hulk Hogan, "The Rock," or
"Stone Cold" Steve Austin wrestled before national
television audiences, Joe "The Scissors
King" Stecher grappled for world titles with
wrestling stalwarts such as Ed "Strangler"
Lewis, "Masked Marvel" Mort Henderson,
and "Tiger Man" John Pesak. Born to Bohemian
immigrants near Dodge, Nebraska, on
April 4, 1893, Stecher was a three-time world
champion and, at the age of twenty-two, was
the youngest man to ever hold the title.

Stecher was a superb athlete. In high school
he played nearly every sport, excelling at baseball,
swimming, and wrestling. Stecher developed
a powerful physique while working on
the family's 400-acre farm (at the peak of his
career he stood over six feet and weighed 220
pounds). He reportedly perfected his signature
move, the scissor hold, by wrapping his
powerful legs around 100-pound sacks of
grain and squeezing until they burst open.

By his senior year in high school Stecher
was focusing solely on wrestling. In 1912, at the
age of nineteen, Stecher turned professional
and quickly became a sensation after a string
of victories against some of the best wrestlers
in the nation. By 1915 promoters recognized
Stecher's potential to become the next great
champion and organized a championship
bout in Omaha, Nebraska. On July 5, 1915,
before a crowd of 15,000 spectators, he defeated
Charlie Cutler for the world championship.
Over the next few years Stecher traveled
the nation in defense of his title, using his
feared scissors hold on one opponent after another.
In January 1916, for example, he defeated
the "Masked Marvel" Mort Henderson
in New York City. Stecher's first defeat (and
the loss of his title) came on April 4, 1917, at
Omaha to Earl Caddock. Stecher regained his
title from Caddock in 1920 at Madison Square
Garden in what many experts have called one
of the greatest matches ever. His second title
run was short-lived, however, as Ed "Strangler"
Lewis defeated him ten months later.
Stecher continued to battle opponents during
the next five years, and on May 5, 1925, he
defeated Stanislaus Zbyszko to become the
first three-time world champion. "The Scissors
King" defended his final title for another
three years before losing it on February 20,
1928, to "Strangler." Although Stecher continued
to grapple for titles for another six
years, shoulder injuries and age caught up
with him, and he never regained his championship
form.

Stecher retired from wrestling in 1934 at the
age of forty-one. Shortly thereafter, Stecher's
wife left with their children, and the exchampion
suffered a mental breakdown. Mental
problems plagued Stecher for the remainder
of his life; his last thirty years were spent in
an institution in St. Paul, Minnesota. He died
there on March 29, 1974. In 2000 Joe Stecher
was inducted into the International Wrestling
Institute and Museum's Hall of Fame.


Mark R. Ellis
University of Nebraska at Kearney





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>