<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.mus.003</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Axton, Hoyt (1938-1999)</field>
      <field name="author">Markwick, Bill</field>
      <field name="text">

 




AXTON, HOYT (1938-1999)

Hoyt Axton playing guitar
      

Singer, songwriter, guitarist, and actor Hoyt
Axton was born on March 25, 1938, in the
small town of Duncan in southwestern Oklahoma.
He was the son of Mae Boren Axton
(1915–97), who cowrote the 1956 Elvis Presley
hit song "Heartbreak Hotel." A football scholarship
led to Oklahoma University, though he
left in the late 1950s to join the navy.

Axton began writing and performing on his
own in West Coast music clubs during the
burgeoning folk music revival of the late 1950s
and early 1960s. While he built up a loyal following
on the folk club circuit, he remained
relatively unknown until his song "Greenback
Dollar" was recorded by the Kingston Trio in
1962; it led to a recording contract with Horizon
Records and albums such as Balladeer
(1962), Thunder 'n' Lightning (1963), and Saturday's Child (1963).

The popular rock band Steppenwolf recorded
Axton's song "The Pusher" in 1964; it
rose to the top levels of the pop charts and was
eventually included in the sound track of the
1969 film Easy Rider. In the mid-1960s Axton
became interested in acting and performed in
the television series Bonanza, Bionic Woman,
and McCloud. His later motion picture roles
included parts in Black Stallion (1979), E.T.
(1983), and Gremlins (1984). He was also a guest
on many television talk and variety shows.

The rock band Three Dog Night recorded
Axton's "Joy to the World" and "Never Been
to Spain" in 1971 and took him on tour as
an opening act. Concert tours of the United
States, Europe, and Asia followed, along with
the recording of many more albums. His songs
have also been recorded by Waylon Jennings,
Glen Campbell, John Denver, and Ringo Starr.
Hoyt Axton died on October 26, 1999, at his
home in Victor, Montana.


Bill Markwick
Toronto, Ontario




Clarke, Donald. The Penguin Encyclopedia of Popular Music.
London: Viking Books, 1989. Stambler, Irwin, and
Landon Grelun. The Encyclopedia of Folk, Country &amp; Western
Music. New York: St. Martin's Press, 1984.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>