<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.wat.013</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Lake Agassiz</field>
      <field name="author">Pettipas, Leo</field>
      <field name="text">

 




LAKE AGASSIZ

Ten thousand years ago, glacial Lake Agassiz
was the largest body of freshwater in North
America. At its maximum extent, the lake covered
an area of some 135,000 square miles and
had a maximum depth of around 700 feet.
Lake Agassiz was a product of widespread deglaciation
that marked the closure of the last
great Ice Age. By 11,700 years ago, the ice front
had retreated far enough north to permit impoundment
of glacial meltwater–incipient
Lake Agassiz–in the extreme southern end of
the Red River Valley of the North near the
junction of present-day North Dakota, South
Dakota, and Minnesota. As the ice sheet retreated
the lake gradually expanded northward
across the First Steppe (or Manitoba
Plain) and over much of the adjoining Precambrian
Shield. Initially, drainage flowed
southward via the Minnesota and Mississippi
Rivers. The level of the lake rose and fell, and
its margins correspondingly expanded and
contracted, several times in response to a sequence
of ice frontal readvances and retreats
that alternately opened and closed its outlets
into the Lake Superior basin.

Migration made possible by extensive riverine
connections with other drainages to the
south, east, west, and northwest culminated in
a varied fish population in Lake Agassiz. The
lake's huge size, however, precluded human
occupation of a sizeable portion of the northeastern
Plains periphery, while adjacent areas
to the south and west were inhabited by generations
of hunters and gatherers.

The lake began its final phase of drainage
just over 9,000 years ago. Around 1,000 years
later a much-diminished Lake Agassiz discharged
into ancestral Hudson Bay as the last
vestiges of the once-formidable ice dam finally
disintegrated.

See also PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT: Glaciation.


Leo Pettipas
Manitoba Museum of Man and Nature




Teller, James T., and Lee Clayton, eds. Glacial Lake Agassiz.
St. John's, Newfoundland: Geological Association of Canada,
1983. Teller, James T., and Alan E. Kehew. "Introduction
to the Late Glacial History of Large Proglacial Lakes
and Meltwater Runoff along the Laurentide Ice Sheet."
Quaternary Science Reviews 13 (1994): 795-99.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>