<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.041</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Liberal Party</field>
      <field name="author">Bryden, P. E.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




LIBERAL PARTY

The Liberal Party is a usually left-of-center
Canadian political party that has formed the
government at various times at the provincial
level in Alberta, Saskatchewan, and Manitoba,
and it was the governing party of the
whole country for the majority of the twentieth
century.

Manitoba was the first new province to join
the original four in Confederation in 1867,
and it did so in part because of pressure from
a Métis provisional government headed by
Louis Riel and in part to fulfill Ontario's
dreams of western expansion. Its early years
are therefore characterized by a latent sense
of resentment against the central government
and attempts to fashion the province in the
image of Ontario. Manitoba's first Liberal premier,
Thomas Greenway, for example, was an
ardent promoter of Ontario emigration, and
during his administration from 1887 to 1899 he
reshaped the frontier landscape into a mini-Ontario. This included, most importantly,
putting an end to the system of provincially
run Catholic schools that had served the early
francophone and Metis population of Manitoba
and replacing it with a virtual monopoly
for the Protestant school system. The Liberal
Party in Manitoba failed to have much success
after Greenway's government. Liberals fused
with the more left-wing Progressives in 1932
and formed a coalition government first under
John Bracken and then under Stuart Garson in
1943. With the end of the coalition, Douglas
Campbell, an erstwhile Liberal, held the premier's
offoce from 1948 until 1958, but he was
criticized for his conservative policies that
were not in line with traditional Liberal ideals.
Politics in Manitoba tend to be dominated by
either the far left or the right, so the Liberal
party of the center has generally failed to attract
much support.

Political parties were relatively slow to come
to the Great Plains of Canada. Before being
divided into provinces in 1905, the area known
as the Northwest Territories had a territorial
government at Regina that was strictly nonpartisan.
Influenced by such organizations as
the Nonpartisan League in the United States,
territorial officials had refused to divide themselves
into the Liberals and Conservatives that
were the accepted political parties in the rest
of the country. The transition to provincial
status, however, forced political parties upon
the new governments in Alberta and Saskatchewan
and ensured the early preeminence
of the Liberal Party.

In carving provinces out of territories, a
number of structural changes had to be made
that affected the political development of the
two provinces. Two of the key appointments,
made by prime minister of Canada Wilfrid
Laurier, were the positions of lieutenant governor
for the two provinces. These men would
then be responsible for appointing the first
premiers of the provinces prior to the establishment
of the appropriate electoral machinery.
In appointing as lieutenant governors
people with known Liberal Party sympathies,
Laurier effectively ensured that the new governments
of the provinces would also be Liberal.
Thus began the early period of Liberal
dominance in provinces previously committed
to the principles of nonpartisanship.

In Alberta, the Liberal Party remained in
power from 1905 until 1921, when it was replaced
by a group of loosely organized farmers
who were upset with the growing corruption
within the Liberal Party and the government's
inability to deal with the agricultural recession
in the wake of World War I. With a strong
sense of nonpartisanship and close ties to agricultural
associations in the United States, the
United Farmers of Alberta established a government
that was in many ways reminiscent of
the territorial period. Other similar organizations
called United Farmers appeared elsewhere
in the country in the 1920s and formed
the government in a number of provinces. In
Saskatchewan, however, the Liberal Party continued
to hold power through the 1920s, in
part by appointing the chief proponent of the
United Farmer movement, William Motherwell,
as minister of agriculture in the Liberal
government, effectively silencing the opposition
of farmers. The era of Liberal dominance
in Saskatchewan ended briefly in 1929 with the
election of a Conservative government, but
the party returned to power for another decade
in 1934. By 1944, however, the Liberal
Party in Saskatchewan was increasingly regarded
as too conservative, and it was replaced
with North America's first socialist government
under the Cooperative Commonwealth
Federation.

The Liberal Party in Alberta and Saskatchewan
has never matched the success of its period
in office immediately following the provinces'
entry into Confederation. Alberta has
not elected a Liberal government since World
War I, although the party continues to attract
some support and has formed the Official Opposition.
In Saskatchewan, Liberals were again
elected to form the government in 1964, although
the party under Ross Thatcher was regarded
as more conservative in its position
on government intervention in the economy
than is normal for the Liberals.

In addition to being a provincial political
party, the Liberal Party is also a national party,
although there is often no organizational relationship
between Liberals at these two levels of
government. Voters in Alberta and Saskatchewan
were originally strong supporters of the
Liberal Party at the national level, even after
the party was no longer in power at the provincial
level. The west gave solid support to Laurier
at the beginning of the century, continued
to vote for the national Liberals under Mackenzie
King in the 1920s and between 1935 and
1948, and supported the party through the
Louis St. Laurent administration of the 1950s.
This support was rewarded: a number of Liberal
politicians from the region, such as James
Gardiner and Charles Dunning, subsequently
found key positions within the national Liberal
governments of the 1930s, 1940s, and 1950s.
By 1957, however, westerners were disillusioned
with the national Liberal party, finding
it dominated by the people and the needs of
Central Canada and neglecting issues that
would have particular resonance in the Great
Plains. The Liberal agricultural policy was regarded
as especially weak, a problem the party
seems curiously unable to rectify. Thus, the
Liberals have found little support in the Prairie
Provinces since the 1960s, rarely electing more
than one or two politicians from all of Saskatchewan
and Alberta.


P. E. Bryden
Mount Allison University




Smith, David E. Prairie Liberalism: The Liberal Party in
Saskatchewan, 1905–1971. Toronto: University of Toronto
Press, 1975. Smith, David E. The Regional Decline of a
National Party: Liberals on the Prairies. Toronto: University
of Toronto Press, 1981. Thomas, Lewis G. The Liberal
Party in Alberta: A History of Politics in the Province of
Alberta, 1905–1921. Toronto: University of Toronto Press,
1959.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>