<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.057</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Norbeck, Peter (1870-1936)</field>
      <field name="author">Shelley, Fred M.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




NORBECK, PETER (1870-1936)

Peter Norbeck was governor and U.S. senator
from South Dakota and a pivotal figure in
South Dakota politics in the early twentieth
century. Norbeck was born in Clay
County, South Dakota, on August 27, 1870.
He was the son of the Reverend George Norbeck
and Karen Larsen Norbeck, immigrants
from Norway. The Norbecks soon moved to
Charles Mix County, where Peter grew up. After
attending the University of South Dakota,
Norbeck invented an improved method of
drilling wells to extract water from aquifers.
He and his partner, Oscar Nicholson, established
a well-drilling business in Redfield,
South Dakota. The business prospered in the
drought-stricken Great Plains, and Norbeck
became wealthy. He married Lydia Anderson
in 1900, and they raised four children.

Inspired by the progressive Republicanism
of Theodore Roosevelt, Norbeck entered politics.
He was elected to the South Dakota Senate
in 1908 and served three two-year terms.
He was elected lieutenant governor in 1914
and governor in 1916 and 1918. During Norbeck's
governorship, statewide populist parties
were established in several neighboring
states, including the Nonpartisan League of
North Dakota and the Farmer-Labor Party of
Minnesota. Nonpartisan League organizers
tried to establish a similar party in South Dakota,
but Norbeck incorporated many of the
League's policies into his own platform. Norbeck's
popularity among farmers and his progressive
views were instrumental in preventing
the establishment of a third party in South
Dakota, whose Republican Party remained allied
with progressives throughout Norbeck's
lifetime.

In 1920 Norbeck was elected to the U.S.
Senate. He was reelected in 1926 and 1932. As a
senator, Norbeck was especially active in agriculture
and conservation issues. He played an
instrumental role in the establishment of
Mount Rushmore as a national memorial. In
the 1930s Norbeck generally supported New
Deal legislation, but he was distrusted by Republicans
who regarded him as too progressive
and by Democrats who shunned his loyalty
to the Republican Party.

His last years were also overshadowed by
the onset of cancer, which led to his death
in Redfield, South Dakota, on December 20,
1936. Norbeck is recognized as a leader of the
progressive forces of the Northern Plains and
as an instrumental figure in preventing a split
between progressive and conservative Republicans
during the interwar years.

See also IMAGES AND ICONS: Mount Rushmore National Memorial.


Fred M. Shelley
Southwest Texas State University




Fite, Gilbert C., and Peter Norbeck. Prairie Statesman.
Columbia: University of Missouri Press, 1948.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>