<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.art.060</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Weidman, Charles (1901-1975)</field>
      <field name="author">Fusillo, Lisa A.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




WEIDMAN, CHARLES (1901-1975)

Born in Lincoln, Nebraska, on July 22, 1901,
Charles Weidman was a leading figure in
the development of American modern dance.
Weidman's father was a civil engineer who also
served as Lincoln's fire chief, and his mother
was a former roller-skating champion. Influenced,
perhaps, by his father's engineering
background, the young Weidman showed a
strong interest in architecture. But his passion
turned to dance in 1916 after seeing a performance
by the Denishawn Company, the
pioneering American modern dance troupe
founded by Ruth St. Denis and Ted Shawn.
Dance was a field in which Weidman felt he
could use his love of architecture, his sense of
humor, and his newly discovered dance talents
together in the design and creation of dances.

In 1920, after studying dance locally with
Eleanor Frampton, Weidman left Lincoln for
Los Angeles to study at the Denishawn School.
Recognizing Weidman's extraordinary talent
as a mimic, Ted Shawn choreographed solos
for him, putting to use his expressive face
and gestures and his sense of humor. In the
Denishawn Company, Weidman worked with
other young American dance artists who were
beginning to explore their own kinds of movement
and choreography, including Martha
Graham and Doris Humphrey. In 1927 Weidman
and Humphrey left the Denishawn Company
to form their own school in New York.
A year later they presented their first concert.
The Humphrey-Weidman Dance Company
reflected the differences in the two directors'
choreographic styles, with Weidman's
comic and mimetic talent complementing
Humphrey's serious dramatic works. The dual
directorship of a company was unique in
dance and continued for two decades.

Audiences enjoyed Weidman's wit and humor
in works such as The Happy Hypocrite
(1931), in which he used pantomime gestures
to convey the story, then exaggerated the gestures
into dance movements. His work also
had a serious side, shown throughout his career
in dances commenting on human behavior
and social morality. In 1936 he presented
a trio of dances titled Atavisms. Two of the
works were humorous: Bargain Counter, in
which rapacious shoppers stampeded a beleaguered
salesclerk, and Stock Exchange, a satire
of the cutthroat business and personalities of
high finance. The third work, however, Lynchtown,
inspired by an actual incident in Nebraska,
depicted the infectious hatred that
turns individuals into a violent mob. Many
of Weidman's other works also show the influences
of his Nebraska childhood and his
attachment to his family. Autobiographical
dances such as On My Mother's Side (1940)
and And Daddy Was a Fireman (1943) combined
poignant and tender reminiscences in
dance with touching moments of humor. His
past also was the inspiration for one of his
most popular works, Flickers (1941), a piece
poking fun at the Hollywood silent films of his
childhood.

The Charles Weidman Dance Company was
formed in 1945 as Weidman continued to work
on his own after a serious illness forced Doris
Humphrey to stop performing. His humor,
wit, and satire in dance were widely recognized
in the theatrical arena, bringing jobs choreographing
for opera, Broadway musicals, and
dance revues. Weidman's openness to experimentation
and his movement inventiveness
made his choreography and teaching important
influences on the next generation of
dancers and dance teachers. He taught at Bennington
College, the summer gathering place
for the early creators of American modern
dance in the mid-1930s, as well as at other
universities and colleges.

One of Weidman's innovations was the development
of a movement form he called "kinetic
pantomime." He began by discarding
the convention of using pantomime gestures
solely to tell a story or for dramatic effect.
Instead, he based the technique on gestures
that evolved out of movement itself and relied
on movement to connect one gesture to another,
a concept that helped pave the way for
later developments in the field of performance
art. Weidman also pioneered mixed-media
theater when he joined with Mikhail Santaro
in the late 1950s. They later formed the Expression
of Two Arts Theater, experimenting
with performance works that attempted to
make connections between graphic art and
dance.

Throughout his career, Weidman returned
periodically to his native Lincoln, teaching
and giving workshops in performance and
choreography. Continuing to work as a choreographer,
performer, and teacher, he maintained
an active interest in new explorations
in dance until his death in New York City on
July 15, 1975. The Charles Weidman Dance
Foundation in New York is dedicated to the
preservation of his work and his contributions
to dance.


Lisa A. Fusillo
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Cohen, Selma Jean. Doris Humphrey, an Artist First.
Princeton NJ: Princeton Book Company, 1995. Lloyd, Margaret.
The Borzoi Book of Modern Dance. New York: Alfred
A. Knopf, Inc., 1949; reprint, New York: Dance Horizons,
1970.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>