<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pe.017</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Carlsbad Caverns</field>
      <field name="author">Loope, David B.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CARLSBAD CAVERNS


Giant Domes, Carlsbad Caverns National Park, New Mexico, 1933-42


Located in southeastern New Mexico where
the Great Plains meets the block uplifts of the
Basin and Range Province, Carlsbad Caverns
is one of the most spectacular and famous
caves in the world. Carlsbad Caverns was recognized
as a national park in 1930 and as a
World Heritage Site in 1995. Twenty miles of
rooms and passages have been explored and
surveyed, and new discoveries continue to be
made. The Big Room is 375 feet from floor to
ceiling and is adorned with large, but delicate,
stalactites and stalagmites. The cave is home
to about a half million Mexican free-tail bats.
The bat population was estimated at 8.7 million
in the 1930s. ddt use in the United States
and Mexico is the apparent cause for the sharp
decline in their numbers.

The caverns developed in reef and back-reef
limestones that were deposited along the
north margin of a rapidly subsiding marine
basin during Permian times. The large cave
and more than fifty caves nearby lie below a
sparsely vegetated, 4,400-foot-high plateau
that receives less than fifteen inches of rainfall
per year. Most caves form in humid settings
through the dissolution of limestone by carbonic
acid. (Carbonic acid is produced when
carbon dioxide from the root zone mixes with
groundwater.) However, clues such as thick
gypsum (calcium sulfate) deposits within
Carlsbad Caverns indicate that sulfuric, not
carbonic, acid generated this cave. Hydrogen
sulfide gas is abundant in the deeply buried,
petroleum-rich rocks of the basin south of the
cave. When this gas migrated upward, it was
oxidized by groundwater, thereby generating
sulfuric acid. Cavernous pores in the limestone
and gypsum deposits are the resulting
product.

See also INDUSTRY: Tourism / SPORTS AND RECREATION: National Parks.


David B. Loope
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Morehouse, D. F. "Cave development via the sulfuric acid
reaction." National Speliological Society Bulletin 30 (1968):
1–10. Palmer, A. N. "Carlsbad Caverns National Park." In
Geology of the National Parks, edited by Ann Harris and
Ester Tuttle: Dubuque IA: Kendall/Hunt Publishing Company,
1983.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>