<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ind.038</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Meatpacking</field>
      <field name="author">Broadway, Michael J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MEATPACKING

In the last third of the twentieth century the
meatpacking industry became a major force
in the social and economic transformation of
small towns in the Great Plains. From the earliest
days of European American settlement,
cattle were raised on the Plains' extensive pastureland.
The arrival of the railroad allowed
cattle to be shipped to stockyards in Chicago,
Kansas City, Omaha, Winnipeg, Toronto, and
other cities to the east of the Plains. The cattle
would then be purchased by packing companies
and slaughtered in multistoried facilities
located adjacent to the stockyards. A hundred
years later, cattle are still raised on the
Plains, but they are now fattened in feedlots
and sold to nearby packing plants. In 1950 the
states that extend north from Texas to North
Dakota slaughtered 21 percent of U.S. cattle;
by 1997 the corresponding figure was 57 percent.
Most of this growth has been concentrated
in Texas, Kansas, and Nebraska.

The industry's increasing concentration on
the High Plains is attributable to innovations
in cattle feeding and meatpacking. In 1950
U.S.-fed cattle production was 4.4 million
head; by 1997 the equivalent figure was 13.2
million, with nearly 60 percent of this total
being concentrated in Texas, Kansas, and Nebraska.
Center-pivot irrigation was introduced
to the High Plains in the 1960s, allowing
farmers to tap the Ogallala Aquifer and
cultivate feed grains. The availability of feed
and water attracted the feedlot industry.

The industry's shift to small towns near the
Great Plains began in 1961, when Iowa Beef
Packers (now known as IBP Inc.) opened its
first plant in Denison, Iowa. The company has
since grown to become the world's largest red
meat producer. The Denison plant, unlike its
predecessors, did not use gravity to move the
animals through the plant but instead used a
"chain" to move individual cattle along a disassembly
line. Under this system, workers are
stationed along the line and perform the same
operation on each animal as it passes by. The
fact that workers were required to perform the
same task, requiring "less skill" than butchers
in the old plants, was used as a rationale by the
company to avoid the terms of the industrywide
union master contract and lower its labor
costs. By locating the plant close to a source of
cattle, the company lowered its transport costs
and reduced the shrinkage and bruising associated
with shipping cattle long distances.

In 1967 ibp opened a plant in Dakota City,
Nebraska, to produce a new product, boxed
beef. Instead of shipping carcasses to its customers,
IBP removed fat and bone at the plant,
thereby retaining valuable waste materials
such as entrails (to be used for pet food), and
shipped vacuum-packaged portions according
to retail specifications. This innovation allowed
meat wholesalers and supermarkets to
lower their labor costs by eliminating their
need for butchers. The combined effect of
these cost-cutting innovations was to increase
the demand for IBP products, and it responded
by building additional large slaughter-capacity
plants close to feedlots in the High Plains during
the 1970s and 1980s. A plentiful supply of
high-quality water is an important requirement
for these sites, since between 400 and 600
gallons of water are required per head of cattle
slaughtered. This need was met by using the
Ogallala Aquifer.

In response to IBP's cost-cutting innovations,
some competitors demanded wage concessions
or closed plants, while others emulated
IBP's High Plains location strategy. Communities
generally welcomed the packers with financial
incentives such as tax breaks and the
construction of supporting infrastructure.
These changes were particularly evident in
Kansas, which experienced plant closures in
Kansas City and Wichita, while new plants
were constructed in the southwestern portion
of the state in Liberal, Holcomb, Garden City,
and Dodge City.

The construction of large slaughter-capacity
plants and the adoption of the disassembly
line led to increases in both worker productivity
and injury rates. The most common injury
among line workers is carpal tunnel syndrome,
caused by the rapid, repetitive nature
of work on the disassembly line. By the 1980s
meatpacking had become the most hazardous
industry in America. The hazardous working
conditions and low pay contribute to high
employee turnover. Monthly turnover among
line workers in established plants averages between
6 and 8 percent. This means that, in the
case of ibp's Holcomb plant, 5,000 workers
come and go each year.

Most High Plains towns lack surplus labor
to meet the demands of an industry with high
employee turnover, so packers recruit workers
from beyond the local region. In the early
1980s IBP recruited Southeast Asian refugees;
in the 1990s Latinos became the target
of recruitment efforts. The influx of new
immigrants has transformed small packing
towns into multicultural communities and
provided a host of challenges to local social
service providers in the form of housing
shortages, increases in school enrollment and
crime, and demand for social assistance and
special services.

Canada's beefpacking industry has experienced
similar changes. Small, ine.cient urban
plants have closed, while large slaughtercapacity
plants have been constructed in southern
Alberta. The packers have been drawn to
the province by the availability of fed cattle
and water. In 1989 Cargill, the third largest
meatpacker in the United States, constructed a
plant in High River, thirty miles south of Calgary.
Five years later, IBP purchased Lakeside
Packers of Brooks, in southeastern Alberta,
and immediately announced expansion plans
that would result in hiring 2,000 additional
workers. High River has avoided many of the
social problems associated with U.S. packing
plants, as most of its workers live in Calgary
and commute to the plant. In Brooks, immigrant
families and young adult males from
across Canada have moved to the community,
straining local services.

See also AGRICULTURE: Cattle Ranching /
HISPANIC AMERICANS: Meatpackers / WATER:
Ogallala Aquifer.


Michael J. Broadway
Northern Michigan University




Broadway, Michael J. "Following the Leader: ibp and the
Restructuring of Canada's Meatpacking Industry." Culture &amp; Agriculture 18 (1996): 3-8. Skaggs, Jimmy M. Prime Cut: Livestock Raising and Meatpacking in the United States, 1607-1983. College Station: Texas A&amp;M University Press,
1986. Stull, Donald D., Michael J. Broadway, and David
Griffith, eds. Any Way You Cut It: Meat Processing and Small-Town America. Lawrence: University Press of Kansas,
1995.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>