<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pd.058</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Winrod, Gerald (1900-1957)</field>
      <field name="author">Ribuffo, Leo P.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




WINROD, GERALD (1900-1957)

Gerald Burton Winrod was a second-rank
leader in the Protestant fundamentalist movement
during the 1920s and the foremost farright
activist in the Great Plains during the
1930s. Winrod was born on March 7, 1900, in
Wichita, Kansas, where he grew up. In 1925 he
founded the Defenders of the Christian Faith,
and operating from in his hometown of Wichita,
Kansas, he campaigned on the stump, over
the radio, and in his Defender magazine against
Darwinism, liberal theology, and what he
called a national "moral sag." A believer in
Bible prophecy, he found in world events signs
of the rise of the Antichrist and Jesus' imminent
return, but except for a fervent defense of
Prohibition, he initially paid slight attention to
conventional politics.

In 1933 Winrod quickly concluded that the
cosmopolitan New Deal represented both the
"moral sag" in politics and an alien tyranny.
Combining his own premillennial theology
with an anti-Semitic conspiracy theory found
in The Protocols of the Learned Elders of Zion,
the notorious forgery concocted by Russian
royalists at the turn of the twentieth century,
he viewed the Roosevelt administration as
part of a venerable Jewish plot extending back
to the crucifixion of Jesus. By the mid-1930s,
while still trying to convert Jews, he was applauding
Adolf Hitler's suppression of alleged
Jewish subversives. In 1938, temporarily playing
down his anti-Semitism, Winrod ran for
the U.S. Senate from Kansas and finished third
in the Republican primary with 53,149 votes
(21.4 percent).

Winrod's sympathy for Hitler and opposition
to American entry into World War II led
to his indictment for sedition in 1942. The case
ended in a mistrial in 1946, and Winrod resumed
his polemical activities, discerning further
Jewish conspiracies and continued "moral
sag" in the postwar era. A lifelong believer
in faith healing, Winrod distrusted orthodox
medicine and championed spurious cancer
treatments. His refusal to consult a physician
contributed in part to his own death from
pneumonia in Wichita on November 11, 1957.


Leo P. Ribuffo
George Washington University




Ribuffo, Leo P. The Old Christian Right: The Protestant Far
Right from the Great Depression to the Cold War. Philadelphia:
Temple University Press, 1983.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>