<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ind.025</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Grain Processing</field>
      <field name="author">Donnelly, Brendan J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




GRAIN PROCESSING

The Great Plains of the United States and
Canada form one huge production engine for
barley, wheat, and sorghum. Wheat is by far
the dominant cereal grain produced, which
explains why the Great Plains is commonly
referred to as the "Breadbasket of the World."
There are three classes of wheat produced in
the region. Eastern Alberta, Saskatchewan,
southwestern Manitoba, northeastern Montana,
North Dakota, northwestern Minnesota,
and northern South Dakota are the major
production area for hard red spring wheat and
durum wheat. Hard red spring wheat is a
high-protein wheat used as a blending wheat
to upgrade the quality of lower-quality wheats
and is also the source of flour for specialty
breads such as hard rolls. Durum wheat is the
source of semolina, a granular product used in
the production of high-quality pasta products.
The Plains states from South Dakota to
Texas and from Montana to Colorado are the
source of hard red winter wheat, a slightly
lower protein wheat than hard red spring
wheat. The flour from hard red winter wheat
is used primarily in the production of pan
breads.

In 1998 the United States produced an estimated
total of 69.61 million metric tons of
wheat. This included hard red winter wheat,
hard red spring wheat, soft red winter wheat,
soft white wheat, and durum wheat. The
Great Plains states of the United States produced
46.14 million metric tons, or 72 percent
of that total. Total wheat production in Canada
in 1998 was 24.40 million metric tons,
with the Prairie Provinces producing 93 percent
of that total.

The number of flour mills and total milling
capacity in the United States for 1997 were 195
and 1,395,323 hundredweights (cwts), respectively.
Much of the milling of the wheats produced
in the Great Plains is done either within
or relatively close to the grain production
states. Plains states had the following number
of mills and flour production capacity in 1997:
Colorado (4; 22,000 cwts); Kansas (18; 154,640
cwts); Montana (4; 16,880 cwts); Nebraska (5;
26,570 cwts); North Dakota (1; 19,000 cwts);
Oklahoma (4; 31,200 cwts); South Dakota (1;
4,000 cwts); and Texas (8; 64,560 cwts). This
gives a combined total of 45 flour mills and
milling capacity of 338,850 cwts. There is a
similar concentration of durum milling in the
Plains, with North Dakota (4; 19,555 cwts) the
leading state. In all, seven of the twenty-three
durum mills in the country are in North Dakota,
Montana, and Nebraska. The Prairie
Provinces are also an important location for
both flour and semolina production. Close to
30 percent of the flour and 40 percent of the
semolina milling capacity of Canada are in
Alberta, Saskatchewan, and Manitoba.

The three major flour-milling companies in
the U.S. Great Plain states are Archer Daniels
Midland Milling Company, ConAgra Grain
Processing Company, and Cargill Foods Flour
Milling. In the Prairie Provinces the leading
companies are Archer Daniels Midland Milling
Company, CSP Foods, and Robin Hood
Multifoods, Inc. The three major durummilling
companies operating in or close to the
U.S. portion of the Plains states are Archer
Daniels Midland Milling Company, General
Mills, and Harvest States. In the Prairie Provinces,
durum-milling companies include Ellison
Milling Company and Robin Hood Multifoods,
Inc.

Wheat milling and flour extraction have
come a long way from the days of stone grinding.
Today wheat milling is a high-throughput,
automated process that extracts flour
from the wheat in high volume to meet the
needs of the baking industry. An average
bushel of wheat weighs sixty pounds, from
which the miller hopes to "extract" about
forty-five pounds of flour (75 percent) and
fifteen pounds of millfeed (25 percent).

When wheat arrives at the mill by truck,
ship, barge, or rail, samples are taken to ensure
it meets purchase quality specifications
for milling and baking or other end use needs.
Results from inspection and quality testing
determine how the wheat will be handled and
stored. The wheat is blended and stored in
large bins on the basis of the desired end
product. Grain storage is a critical component
of wheat handling to ensure it does not go out
of condition prior to milling.

The first step in the milling process is to
clean the wheat of extraneous material picked
up in the harvesting process. Foreign materials
such as metal, sticks, stones, straw, seeds, and
other grains are removed in steps by a magnetic
separator, vibrating screens, a destoner, a
disc separator, and a scourer. Once the wheat is
cleaned, water is added to it in precise amounts
in a process called tempering. This is done to
toughen the bran and mellow the inner portion
of the wheat kernel (the endosperm), facilitating
separation of the kernel components.
Tempered wheat is stored in bins for twelve to
twenty-four hours, depending on the class of
the wheat. After proper tempering, the wheat
passes through an impact scourer (entoleter)
that breaks apart and removes unsound kernels
and then moves to the grinding bins (large
hoppers that feed the wheat to the grinding
rolls).

Mill rolls are corrugated and paired, and
they counterrotate at different speeds. One
pass between the first break rolls begins the
separation of the bran, endosperm, and germ.
Feeding the tempered wheat to the first break
rolls begins a gradual reduction process
whereby middlings or coarse particles of endosperm
are graded and separated from the
bran by sieves and purifiers. Each size is returned
to appropriate rollers, and the process
is repeated until the desired flour is produced.
The flour is then bleached and enriched with
three B vitamins (thiamin, niacin, and riboflavin),
iron, and folic acid. Family flour for retail
sale is packed in 5-, 10-, or 25-pound bags.
Bakery flour may be packed in 50- or 100-
pound bags or shipped in bulk trucks or railcars.

See also AGRICULTURE: Wheat.


Brendan J. Donnelly
Kansas State University




Grain and Milling Annual. Kansas City MO: Sosland Publishing
Company, 1998. 1998 Crop Quality Report. Washington
DC: U.S. Wheat Associates, Inc., 1998.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>