<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ind.009</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Buffett, Warren (b. 1930)</field>
      <field name="author">Johansen, Thomas</field>
      <field name="text">

 




Buffett, Warren (b. 1930)

Warren Edward Buffett, businessman and investor,
was born August 30, 1930, in Omaha,
Nebraska, to Howard Homan Buffett and
Leila Stahl Buffett. He is the youngest of three
children, with sisters Doris and Roberta. In
1952 he married Susan Thompson. They have
three children, Susan, Howard, and Peter. In
2000 Buffett was the second wealthiest individual
in the United States.

Buffett attended elementary school in
Omaha, then junior high school and high
school in Washington dc while his father
served as a congressman from Nebraska. During
this time, he became interested in business
and pursued a variety of money-making ventures,
including a newspaper route, a pinball
machine business, a Rolls Royce rental business,
and used golf ball sales. He also purchased
forty acres of farmland for $1,200 in
his home state, Nebraska. When he graduated
from high school, Buffett had about $6,000 in
savings.

In 1947 he enrolled in the Wharton School of
Business at the University of Pennsylvania. After
two years, he transferred to the University
of Nebraska-Lincoln and graduated in 1950
with a degree in business. During his senior
year, he read The Intelligent Investor by Benjamin
Graham, a finance professor at Columbia
University in New York. Having tried various
investment strategies, Buffett became
intrigued and enrolled in the graduate program
at Columbia to study under Benjamin
Graham. In 1951 he graduated with a master's
degree and applied for a job at Graham-Newman,
an investment firm. Graham turned him
down, so Buffett returned to Omaha to work
for his father's brokerage firm. In 1954 Graham
offered Buffett a job that he accepted. Two
years later, Graham-Newman closed, and Buffett
again returned to Omaha. At that time,
Buffett started his own investment company,
the Buffett Partnership, with $100 of his own
money and $105,000 contributed by seven limited
partners.

In 1962 Buffett began investing in Berkshire
Hathaway, a textile mill located in New Bedford,
Massachusetts, gaining control of the
firm in 1965. Instead of reinvesting money in
textiles, Buffett used capital to invest in other
companies. Disappointed with opportunities
in the stock market, Buffett ended the partnership
in 1969, suggesting to his partners that
they either cash out, remain invested with
Berkshire Hathaway, or invest in a fund managed
by a classmate from Columbia, William
Ruane. Buffett retained his shares in Berkshire
Hathaway and is currently the chairman and
chief executive officer. Berkshire Hathaway,
no longer a textile company, is a holding company
with investments in Coca-Cola, Gillette,
the Washington Post, Disney, and other wellknown
firms. It also owns the Nebraska Furniture
Mart, Borsheim's jewelry store, See's
Candies, geico insurance, Dairy Queen International,
and several other businesses.

From 1955 to 1969 the partnership earned
an astounding 29.5 percent annual compound
rate of return. Since Buffett gained control of
Berkshire Hathaway, the average annual gain
in net worth is approximately 25 percent compared
to the average percentage gain in the
S&amp;P 500 of approximately 13 percent. His personal
wealth has grown from $9,800 at the
time he left Columbia University to about $30
billion in 2000.

Benjamin Graham, Philip Fisher, and Buffett's
current partner, Charlie Munger, have
influenced Buffett's investment philosophy.
Buffett learned from Graham quantitative
techniques and the importance of margin of
safety, which is the difference between the
market value and the intrinsic value of a business.
Fisher and Munger stress the importance
of business economics and management. Buffett,
who uses aspects of both quantitative and
qualitative techniques, believes that an investor
should understand the business, not worry
about stock market volatility, and should buy
when the market price is significantly less than
the intrinsic value of the business.

Buffett achieves success with hard work,
diligence, dedication, honesty, enthusiasm,
and humility. These characteristics reflect the
spirit and heritage of the Great Plains people.
A native Nebraskan, Warren Edward Buffett
has earned a place in history as one of the
greatest investors of all time.


Thomas Johansen
Fort Hays State University




Hagstrom, Robert G., Jr. The Warren Buffett Way. New
York: John Wiley and Sons, 1995. Kilpatrick, Andrew. Of Permanent Value: The Warren Buffett Story. Birmingham:
AKPE, 1998. Lowenstein, Roger. Buffett: The Making of an American Capitalist. New York: Doubleday, 1995.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>