<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fol.009</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Dobie, J. Frank (1888-1964)</field>
      <field name="author">Logsdon, Guy</field>
      <field name="text">

 




DOBIE, J. FRANK (1888-1964)

James Frank Dobie, the beloved best-known
popularizer of Texas and ranchland folklore,
was born on September 26, 1888, on a small
ranch in Live Oak County, Texas. He grew up
working as a cowboy on his father's ranch and
became a voracious reader. Educated both at
home and in a one-room schoolhouse, he
lived among Hispanic workers and so became
bilingual. As Dobie matured he absorbed the
lore, language, and legends of the land and
people he loved, developing a strong, liberal
philosophy.

Dobie earned a bachelor of arts degree at
Southwestern University in Georgetown,
Texas, and a master of arts degree at Columbia
University in New York City. In 1914, as an
English teacher at the University of Texas,
Austin, he became involved with the Texas
Folklore Society, before enlisting in the army
in 1917. He returned to the University of Texas
in 1921, and later (1923–25) served as head of
the English Department at Oklahoma A&amp;M in
Stillwater.

When Dobie and his wife, Bertha, returned
to Austin after his time in the service, he resumed
teaching English and his well-known
class "Life and Literature of the Southwest."
He served as editor and secretary of the Texas
Folklore Society from 1922 to 1942. Without a
doctorate, he was still promoted to full professor
in 1933, but his honest, outspoken traits
kept him in conflict with his colleagues and
administration. He left the university in 1947.

Academic folklorists criticized Dobie for
rewriting and editing his sources, and he seldom
gave credit to his informants. Nevertheless,
Dobie's books (he wrote more than
twenty in all, including Coronado's Children,
which won a Literary Guild award in 1931),
were the efforts of a natural-born storyteller,
a man who shared with love and reverence
the traditions of his heritage, including those
of Hispanics and African Americans. A true
ranchland Texan, he shared the values of the
southwestern Plains. Dobie was awarded the
Medal of Freedom, the nation's highest civil
honor, on September 14, 1964. Four days later
he died in Austin, Texas.


Guy Logsdon
Tulsa, Oklahoma




Abernethy, Francis Edward, ed. Texas Folklore Society.
Denton: University of North Texas Press, 1992–2000.
Bode, William. A Portrait of Pancho: The Life of a Great Texan. Austin: Pemberton, 1965. Tinkle, Lon. An American Original: The Life of J. Frank Dobie. Boston: Little, Brown
and Co. 1978.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>