<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.arc.029</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Hispanic Architecture</field>
      <field name="author">Wilson, Chris</field>
      <field name="text">

 




HISPANIC ARCHITECTURE

Mexican pioneers first introduced their adobe
building tradition to the Plains in the 1830s.
Later, in the mid-1890s California Mission Revival
style initiated the self-conscious use of
Hispanic imagery for commercial, civic, and
residential purposes. Mexican and Mexican
American workers recruited to the region by
agricultural interests and the railways after
1900 were first provided with rudimentary
housing but in time developed their own distinctive
colonias and barrios. These manifestations
of Hispanic architecture have been
strongest on the southern and western reaches
of the Great Plains but have echoed north at
least into the Dakotas. However, the relation
of the houses built and lived in by Mexican
Americans–the primary Hispanic residents
of the Great Plains–to self-conscious Hispanic
Revival–style buildings has often been
tenuous.

Workmen hired from New Mexico in the
early 1830s constructed Bent's Fort in southeastern
Colorado of adobe, following the
Spanish Mexican presidio plan of an enclosed
quadrangle with rooms one deep on each side
and two towers at opposite corners. Bent's Fort
was the model for six fur-trading forts built
over the next ten years along the South and
North Platte Rivers in northeastern Colorado
and southeastern Wyoming. The U.S. Army
adopted adobe as the most cost-effective material
for its installations on the Central and
Southern Plains from the late 1840s into the
1870s. However, only at Fort Mitchell, in western
Nebraska, did the army also adopt the
quadrangle plan.

Between the mid-1830s and 1900, mestizos
from north-central New Mexico pushed into
southeastern Colorado and the panhandles of
Texas and Oklahoma, while Tejano settlers
moved up the Rio Grande and the Pecos River
onto the Southern Plains in Texas. Both
groups carried the Spanish Mexican vernacular
building tradition of massive load-bearing
walls. These were primarily built of adobe, although
they could also be made of unfinished
stone, vertical posts, or hewn horizontal logs,
all finished with earthen plaster. Log or milled
beams topped by branches or milled decking
and a layer of earth formed the typical flat
roofs. Most houses were two to four rooms,
each with an exterior door and arranged in
single file or L-shaped plans. After 1865 carpenter
Greek Revival detailing and gabled and
hipped roofs of wood or corrugated metal
were added to this owner-built vocabulary.

While most early Plains towns took their
architectural inspiration from Europe and the
East, Spanish Mexican borderlands history
made the romantic evocation of Hispanic
styles plausible, especially on the Southern
Great Plains. The Texas and Colorado state
buildings at the 1893 Chicago World's Fair
evoked this Spanish heritage, and around 1897
the Santa Fe Railway adopted the California
Mission style for its depots and track-side
Harvey House hotels as part of its campaign to
attract tourists from the Midwest.

Most popular from 1900 to 1925, the Mission
style employed buff brick or light stuccoed
walls, red tile roofs, arched porches,
curved and stepping parapets fronting gable
ends, and occasional towers patterned on
Spanish missions. While the Mission-style basics
of stucco and red tile continued after 1920,
mixtilinear parapets became less common,
and a richer vocabulary of cast stone and
glazed terra-cotta ornament based on the baroque
churches of Mexico and Spain provided
the predominant accents for Spanish Colonial
Revival buildings. This Mission-Spanish Colonial
genre was adopted primarily for train
depots, hotels, tourist courts, movie theaters,
sanitariums, veterans hospitals, Catholic
churches, suburban homes, and both public
and mission church schools, especially those
for Mexican or Indian students. Texas Tech
University in Lubbock adopted Spanish Colonial
Revival for its campus in the 1920s.

The related Pueblo Revival style, developed
primarily in New Mexico in the second decade
of the twentieth century, incorporated elements
of the flat-roofed, multistory Pueblo
villages and the carved corbel brackets and
adobe of early Spanish missions. The style was
used for public buildings, hotels, and Indian
schools in the Great Plains. An occasional aficionado
of Santa Fe and Taos might also build
a Pueblo-style suburban home. Although the
projecting log vigas of the Pueblo style and the
simple curved and stepping Mission parapets
occasionally echoed the Mexican American
owner-built vernacular, those commissioning
and designing the great majority of Hispanic
Revival buildings were non-Hispanics.

Even as the Mission style gained popularity
about 1900, workers recruited from Mexico
and the Southwest were provided rudimentary
housing: tents and boxcar houses next to
rail yards and scrap-lumber shacks for migrant
farm laborers. In the 1920s, as laborers
in the sugar beet fields of Colorado, Wyoming,
Nebraska, and the Dakotas sought yearround
residence, the Great Western Sugar
Company responded by developing a series of
workers colonies. Apparently built by the
workers themselves in the off-season, the
housing employed the flat-roofed adobe vernacular
tradition.

In medium-size and large communities,
once workers secured permanent employment
they quickly moved out of company housing
and into working-class districts. Their barrio
communities took names like Guadalupe, Little
Mexico, Argentine, Santa Fe, El Hueso, and
Chihuahua Hill. Workers often rented existing
two-room cottages, shotgun houses, and
modest bungalows. The desire for home
ownership, however, led many extended families
to pool their resources and purchase a
house. Some families built cottages to the rear
from lumber, used railroad ties, rails, and corrugated
sheet metal that might house newly
arrived relatives or be rented to produce extra
income. Some families created enclosed compounds
with packed dirt patios to the rear
and defined their front yards with low chainlink
and wrought-iron fences or concrete
block walls. Barrios are often distinguished by
shrines to the Virgin of Guadalupe, Chicano
murals, and vibrant red, turquoise, and pastel
colors.

Today, many descendants of Mexican American
pioneers and of the first Mexican immigrants
to the Great Plains have entered
integrated, middle-class suburbs, where the
generic Mission style of Taco Bell and scattered
Mediterranean-style houses hint at the
region's Hispanic heritage. In the barrios and
on the fringes of small agricultural communities,
the current generation of Mexican and
Central American immigrants who help support
the restaurants, construction trades, and
food-processing and meat-packing plants still
face chronic problems of substandard and
overcrowded housing.


Chris Wilson
University of New Mexico





Murphy, David. "Building in Clay on the Central Plains."
In Perspectives in Vernacular Architecture III, edited by
Thomas Carter and Bernard L. Herman. Columbia: University
of Missouri Press, 1989: 74–85. Pratt, Boyd C.
"Homesteading the High Plains of New Mexico: An Architectural
Perspective." Panhandle-Plains Historical Review
63 (1990): 1–33. Wilson, Chris. "When a Room Is the
Hall: The Houses of West Las Vegas, New Mexico." In
Images of an American Land: Vernacular Architecture in the Western United States, edited by Thomas Carter. Albuquerque:
University of New Mexico Press, 1997: 113–28.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>