<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.war.043</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Sherman, William Tecumseh (1820-1891)</field>
      <field name="author">Marszalek, John F.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SHERMAN, WILLIAM TECUMSEH (1820-1891)

"William Tecumseh Sherman, 1865"
 

A leading Union general in the Civil War, William
Tecumseh Sherman was also a driving
force in the postwar settlement of the Great
Plains. Sherman was born in Lancaster, Ohio,
on February 8, 1820, and brought up in the
family of Thomas Ewing, a leading politician.
After graduation from the U.S. Military Academy
at West Point, he served in the Second
Seminole War and in the Mexican War. His
success was assured by his leadership and victories
in the Civil War, where he put into practice
his strategy of property destruction as a
means of war, a strategy he would continue
against Plains Indians. From 1866 to 1869 he
commanded the Military Division of the Missouri,
covering the area from the Mississippi
River to the Rocky Mountains (with Texas exexcluded).
In 1869 he became commanding general
of the entire U.S. Army, a position he held
until his retirement in 1884.

Throughout these years, though his responsibilities
were wide-ranging, Sherman focused
much of his attention in the Great Plains.
There, the great transcontinental railroads
were built and the Native Americans struggled
against the ever-increasing encroachment of
the United States. As white settlers poured
into the region, Native Americans tried to
stem the tide, but the U.S. Army, under Sherman's
leadership, thwarted the effort. With
the completion of the first transcontinental
railroad in 1869 and the subsequent building
of other rail lines, Indians could not compete
against increasingly mobile soldiers and the
mass of settlers. Sherman advocated all-out
war aimed at destroying the Indians' subsistence
base. Sherman's view of the struggle was
a complex one. On one hand, he opposed civilian
reformers who proposed a more humanitarian
policy toward the Indians, though
he did serve on the peace commission at the
Medicine Lodge Creek (1867) and Fort Laramie
Treaties (1868), respectively. On the other
hand, he believed that the main cause of war
was American expansion onto tribal lands,
and that it was best, for all concerned, to force
an end to the painful struggle by militarily
controlling the tribes. Through it all, Sherman
insisted that progress and order demanded
that the Indians move aside for the white settlers,
even as he recognized the unjust aspects
of the fight. His love for the region never
wavered, and he regularly left the frustrations
of Washington to tour the Great Plains and
the entire American West, where he found a
peace of mind not available to him elsewhere.
Sherman died in New York City on February
14, 1891.


John F. Marszalek
Mississippi State University




Athearn, Robert G. William Tecumseh Sherman and the
Settlement of the West. 1956. Reprint, Lincoln: University
of Nebraska Press, 1995. Marszalek, John F. Sherman, A
Soldier's Passion for Order. New York: Free Press, 1993;
Vintage, 1994. Sherman Family Papers. Archives of the
University of Notre Dame, South Bend IN.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>