<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fol.012</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Folk Art</field>
      <field name="author">Geist, Troyd</field>
      <field name="text">

 




FOLK ART


Ukrainian Easter eggs made by Angie Chruszch of Belifield, North Dakota


Folk art of the Great Plains is as broad and
seemingly limitless as the landscape itself.
However, the lines of distinction between what
is, and what is not, folk art often blurs, just like
the line between the sky and the land in a Great
Plains horizon. Yet folklorists generally agree
that folk art is a complicated whole comprised
of a number of integrated parts, with some
more prominent than others.

First, a shared sense of identity among the
individuals who comprise a distinctive group
is key. The ties that bind the individual to the
group and are the foundation for tradition
include a shared language, culture, ethnicity,
history, occupation, community, region, and
religion or spirituality. Folk art is rooted in a
tradition. The art often serves as a way to reaffirm the individual's group identity, as well
as to communicate to others who they are,
what they believe, and where they came from.

Second, the process and form of folk art is
influenced heavily by a community sense of
artistic value that changes and adapts from
place to place and through time. That is not
to say there is no room for the artist's individual
creative expression. There is freedom, but
within the boundaries of the community's artistic
standards, based on its shared sense of
tradition. This applies not only to the form of
the art but also to the process by which that
art is created. For example, within a community
of Ukrainian Easter egg artists, the proper
process for the creation of a decorated egg
begins with a prayer to the Virgin Mary to
guide the hands of the artist.

Third, folk art generally passes from one
generation to another informally by way of
example, observation, and word of mouth. It
is usually learned outside of formal educational
settings and institutions. For example, a
German Russian blacksmith who makes decorative
wrought-iron grave crosses may enlist
one of his young sons to help him in the shop.
The son soon learns the proper process and
form for making cemetery crosses simply by
observing and working alongside his father.

Finally, folk art is often part of a larger cultural
context. It plays an active role in the lives
of the community. Ukrainian Easter eggs are
not made just for art's sake. They are taken to
the church on Easter Sunday to be blessed by
the priest. Some Ukrainian traditionalists will
then take one of those eggs and bury it in the
corner of one of their fields, thus ensuring a
bountiful harvest. Similarly, a Native American
ceremonial bag decorated with porcupine
quills is not just a piece of art to be admired; it
also may be used to hold a sacred pipe that is
the focal point of various ceremonies.

Much of the folk art of the Great Plains
stems from tribal or ethnic identity. Plains Native
American and First Nation groups excel in
a wide range of folk arts, from star quilts
used in giveaways, naming ceremonies, and
even funerals, to basketry, beadwork, and porcupine
quillwork used to adorn everything
from moccasins to horse masks and cigarette
lighters.

The Spanish and Mexican influence, which
took root in the Great Plains in the sixteenth
and seventeenth centuries, is still found
through folk arts, such as intricate needlework
and the carving and painting of revered
Santos, or images of Catholic saints, by Hispanic
folk artists. The French influence, which
spread through the fur trade into the Prairie
Provinces in the eighteenth century, can still
be seen in the jigs, reels, and fiddle music
of the Métis people, who are descendants
of French, Irish, and Scottish fur traders and
Native Americans. The farmers and cowboys
who followed in the nineteenth century established
enduring occupational folk arts, such as
wheat weaving, cowboy poetry, and decorative
spur- and saddlemaking.

Subsequent immigration of many eastern
and northern European peoples in the late
nineteenth century brought to the Plains such
folk arts as colorful Polish paper cutting, Norwegian
needlework, Czech Easter eggs decorated
with designs cut from wheat straw,
Greek woodcarving, lively polka music, and
much more. Added to this is the relatively recent
influx of new immigrants: Cambodians
who brought their tradition of story-cloths,
Vietnamese who brought the Dragon Dance,
Armenians from Azerbaijan who brought
copper bas-relief work, and Sudanese and
Congolese who brought adungu music.

Just as ethnic, tribal, or occupational identity
is often at the core of folk art, so too is a
sense of religion or spirituality. It is also important
to remember that both identity and
spirituality are shaped in subtle ways by the
natural environment. Thus, the environment
has an influence in the shaping of folk arts,
especially through time. The natural environment
of the Great Plains is one of vastness and
distant horizons, with a sun that always looms
large. The environment is strong and stark, yet
delicate and colorful. People at first glance
may see the sameness of an immense sky, but
the brilliance of a Plains sunset ends the day.
People notice oceans of grass or wheat, but all
the while there are tiny, colorful crocus flowers
waiting for the watchful eye. The Great
Plains is given to periods of boom and bust, to
cycles of life and death, flood and drought, to
the seasons that are keenly felt, and to renewal.
People incorporate what they see and experience
around them. The natural environment
of the Great Plains gives folk art in this region a
distinctive feel. This can be illustrated through
examples of motifs from nature found in the
folk art of two ethnic and occupational (farming)
groups.

The Ukrainian Easter egg tradition is a pre-Christian art form that was tied to spring fertility
rituals, in recognition of the cycles of
birth, death, and rebirth in nature. Animals,
flowers, birds, and insects are some of the
nature-theme motifs used in this delicate and
colorful tradition, whereby images are applied
to an egg through a batik method of dyeing.
With the advent of Christianity, that spiritual
notion of life after death was readily applied
to the crucifixion of Christ. As Ukrainians
moved to the Great Plains, they brought with
them the Easter egg tradition. Some of the
nature-theme motifs used in the Old Country
continued in the new. Others were discarded
and replaced by motifs more indicative of
the artists' new home. Two motifs that have
continued, and seem to have grown in popularity
in the Plains, reflecting their centrality
in the landscape, are those of wheat, a symbol
of fertility, and the sun, a symbol of God and
rebirth.

The strong, stark German Russian wroughtiron
cemetery crosses also often contain motifs
from nature. These beautiful crosses are eerily
representative of the landscape. Some crosses
are made with a half-circle arcing from one
end of the horizontal bar to the other like a
setting or rising sun on a flat and expansive
horizon. Waving upward from the sun are iron
strands of wheat. These crosses immortalize
silently, yet poetically, the memory of the deceased
with symbols representing shared religious
beliefs of life after death: a prominent
cycle observed in the natural environment that
surrounds these Plains folk.


Troyd Geist
North Dakota Council on the Arts




Dorson, Richard M., ed. Handbook of American Folklore.
Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1983. Geist, Troyd
A. From the Wellspring: Faith, Soil, Tradition. Bismarck:
North Dakota Council on the Arts, 1997. Sherman, William
C., and Playford V. Thorson, eds. North Dakota's Ethnic History. Fargo: The North Dakota Institute for Regional
Studies and North Dakota Humanities Council,
1986.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>