<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.019</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Dole, Bob (b. 1923)</field>
      <field name="author">Loomis, Burdett A.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




DOLE, BOB (b. 1923)

Born on July 22, 1923, in Russell, Kansas, Robert
J. "Bob" Dole rose from county attorney to
become a five-term U.S. senator, chairman of
the Republican Party (1971–72), Republican
nominee for vice president (1976), and threetime
presidential candidate. In 1996 Dole won
the Republican nomination for president but
lost in the general election to incumbent President
Bill Clinton.

Gravely wounded in the last days of World
War II, Dole returned home to Kansas to rehabilitate
his shattered body and to complete
his education. He was elected to the state legislature
in 1951, even before finishing law school
at Topeka's Washburn University. Dole impressed
state Republicans with his prairie conservatism
and capacity for hard work. In 1960,
after eight years as Russell County attorney,
Dole won the Republican nomination for the
U.S. House, where he served for eight years as
a solid representative of western Kansas. In
1968 Republican incumbent Sen. Frank Carlson
stepped down and encouraged Dole to
replace him. After a typically energetic campaign,
Dole won the seat and–save for a narrow
victory over Rep. Bill Roy in 1974–faced
no serious opposition for the remainder of his
tenure on Capitol Hill.

A long-time member of the Agriculture and
Finance Committees, Bob Dole became a national
political figure in the 1970s. He served as
chairman of the Republican National Committee
(RNC) during the 1972 presidential
campaign and was President Gerald Ford's
running mate in 1976. Despite his rnc posi
tion, Dole played no role in the Watergate affair
that brought down Richard Nixon's presidency.
As the vice presidential candidate, Dole
often took the offensive against the Democrats,
thus gaining the reputation as a rough
campaigner.

By the late 1970s Dole had risen through the
Senate's ranks and had won recognition as an
effective legislator whose conservatism was
often tempered with pragmatism. After Republicans
won control of the Senate in 1980,
Dole served first as chairman of the Finance
Committee (1981-84) and then as the Republican
floor leader (majority leader, 1985-86, 1995-96; minority leader, 1987-94). As a
Senate leader Dole demonstrated great talents
and even greater patience in forging majorities
among his Senate colleagues. Nowhere
was this clearer than in his role in "saving"
social security in 1983, as he played a central
role in putting together a package that was
acceptable to Republicans and Democrats in
both houses, as well as to the Reagan White
House. In 1990, after thirty years of trying,
Dole won passage of the Americans with Disabilities
Act, which, with the 1972 food-stamps
initiative, represent two of his most important
substantive legislative legacies.

In 1996 Bob Dole won the Republican presidential
nomination, after which he resigned
from the Senate to concentrate his attention on
the presidential race. He proved incapable of
overcoming a healthy economy and President
Clinton's strong performance on the campaign
trail, and he returned to private life as an attorney
for a prestigious Washington law firm.
Dole remained active in international affairs–
especially on missions to the former Yugoslavia–
and in 1997 President Clinton honored
him with the Presidential Medal of Freedom. In
addition, Elizabeth Dole's continuing prominence
as a Republican presidential hopeful kept
Bob Dole active in national politics beyond his
own period of officeholding and campaigning.


Burdett A. Loomis
University of Kansas




Cramer, Richard Ben. What It Takes. New York: Random
House, 1992. Dole, Bob and Elizabeth. Unlimited Partners.
New York: Simon and Schuster, 1998. Thompson, Jake H.
Bob Dole. New York: Donald Fine, 1994.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>