<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.gen.004</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Berdache</field>
      <field name="author">Roscoe, Will</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BERDACHE

In the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries,
French explorers, traders, and missionaries in
the Mississippi Valley occasionally encountered
Native Americans who could be classified
neither as men nor women. They called
such individuals berdaches, a French term for
younger partners in male homosexual relationships.
In fact, Plains Indian berdaches are
best described as occupying an alternative or
third gender role, in which traits of men and
women are combined with those unique to
berdache status. Male berdaches did women's
work, cross-dressed or combined male and female
clothing, and formed relationships with
non-berdache men.

Plains Indian women often engaged in
hunting and warfare, but a female role equivalent
to that of male berdaches, although
common west of the Rockies, has been documented
in the Plains only among the Cheyennes
(the hetaneman). Even so, some Plains
Indian women became notable warriors and
leaders and behaved much like berdaches. In
the early nineteenth century, Running Eagle of
the Piegans wore male clothing on war parties,
while Woman Chief of the Crows had four
wives.

Male berdaches were known among the
Arapahos (hoxuxunó), Arikaras, Assiniboines
(winktan'), Blackfoot (ake:śkassi), Cheyennes
(he'eman), Comanches, Plains Crees (ayekkwe),
Crows (boté), Gros Ventres, Hidatsas
(miáti), Kansas (minquge), Kiowas, Mandans
(mihdeke), Plains Ojibwas (agokwa),
Omahas (minquga), Osages (mixu'ga), Otoes
(mixo'ge), Pawnees, Poncas (minquga), Potawatomis
(m'nuktokwae), Quapaws, Winnebagos
(shiéngge), and the various Siouan-speaking
tribes (winkte, Lakota; winkta, Dakota). The
two most common reasons cited for individuals
becoming berdaches were childhood preference
for work of the other sex and/or certain
dreams or visions. The Lakotas credited dreams
of Double Woman with influencing men to become
winkte; others credited the Moon. Such
dreams also conveyed valued skills–in particular,
proficiency in women's arts, such as quilling,
tanning, and beading. Among the Dakotas
the saying "fine possessions like a berdache's"
was the highest compliment one could pay a
household.

Berdaches often had distinct religious roles.
A Crow boté selected the central pole used in
constructing Sun Dance lodges. Cheyenne
he'eman directed the tribe's most important
ceremony, the scalp dance. In Hidatsa villages,
miáti were an "organized group" of as many as
fifteen to twenty-five, treated as a "special class
of religious leaders." In several tribes, berdaches
were shamans and healers. Other skills
attributed to berdaches included the ability
to foretell the future and convey luck by bestowing
obscene nicknames (Lakota), make
love magic (Pawnee), and arrange marriages
(Cheyenne). By reputation, many Plains berdaches
were sexually active. George Catlin illustrated
a Sauk and Fox dance in which a
berdache is the central figure surrounded by
"her" male lovers. Dakota warriors sometimes
visited berdaches before joining war parties in
the belief that such encounters augmented
their masculine ferocity. Prominent warriors
and chiefs, including the Omaha American
Horse and the Lakota Crazy Horse, had berdaches
among their wives.

Some observers have explained berdache
roles as niches for males unable to fulfill rigorous
standards of Plains masculinity. But as Dakotas
told anthropologist Ruth Landes, a distinction
was made between men afraid to join
war parties and berdaches, who "had a dream."
In fact, Plains berdaches were active in all aspects
of warfare, from providing assistance on
war parties to leading war ceremonies and entering
battles (and some Dakota berdaches
hunted, even as they maintained tipis that
women envied). When the Hidatsa chief Four
Bears encountered a Lakota winkte, and his
arrow failed to penetrate his robe, the winkte
exclaimed, "You can't kill me for I am holy.
I will strike coups on you with my digging
stick." In 1866 a winkte predicted the success of
Lakota and Cheyenne forces against the Americans
at Fort Phil Kearny. In 1876 the Crow boté
Finds Them and Kills Them killed a Lakota
warrior in the Battle of the Rosebud.

In the reservation period, American missionaries
denounced berdaches, government
agents forced them to do men's work, and
boarding-school teachers punished children
for inappropriate gender behavior. As European
American attitudes toward homosexuality
were adopted in Indian communities, families
often intervened to prevent their own
members from becoming (or behaving like)
berdaches. Nonetheless, traditional berdaches
like Finds Them and Kills Them successfully
resisted efforts to change their lifestyles. In
the 1980s anthropologist Walter Williams
found individuals on Plains reservations still
performing traditional functions of the berdache
role.

In the 1990s the term "two-spirit" was introduced
by Native Americans as an alternative
to berdache, and traditional third gender
roles became the subject of renewed interest
among Natives and non-Natives alike. As Michael
Red Earth, a gay-identified Dakota,
writes, "Once I realized that this respect and
acceptance was a legacy of our traditional Native
past, I was empowered to present my
whole self to the world and reassume the responsibilities
of being a two-spirited person."


Will Roscoe
California Institute of Integral Studies




Jacobs, Sue-Ellen, Wesley Thomas, and Sabine Lang, eds.
Two-Spirit People: Native American Gender Identity, Sexuality, and Spirituality. Urbana: University of Illinois
Press, 1997. Roscoe, Will. Changing Ones: Third and Fourth Genders in Native North America. New York: St.
Martin's Press, 1998. Williams, Walter L. The Spirit and the Flesh: Sexual Diversity in American Indian Culture. Boston:
Beacon Press, 1986.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>