<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.edu.025</field>
      <field name="titleMain">McLaurin v. Oklahoma State Regents</field>
      <field name="author">Smallwood, James M.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MCLAURIN V. OKLAHOMA STATE REGENTS

Working with the National Association for the
Advancement of Colored People (NAACP),
black Oklahomans in the 1940s increasingly
tested laws and state policies that upheld
segregation, including segregated education.
While Oklahoma had a relatively small African
American population (about 8 percent at
the time of statehood in 1907), a majority
of early white Oklahomans had southern
roots and thoroughly embraced the concept
of white supremacy.

The first legislature, meeting in 1907,
had established separate schools for African
Americans and heavy fines for administrators,
teachers, and students who broke the law. In
the state's higher education system the allblack
Langston A&amp;M College, created during
the territorial era, offered African Americans
many programs leading to a bachelor's degree,
but Langston had no graduate programs. Instead,
the state provided out-of-state educational
grants for African American students
who wished to go to graduate school. Approximately
2,000 black Oklahomans received
such grants between 1907 and 1946. However,
such a system was not acceptable to many of
the state's African American students, one of
whom was George McLaurin, an instructor at
Langston who wished to pursue a graduate
degree within the state.

McLaurin became a pioneer in the national
civil rights movement when he, along with
five other African Americans, applied for admission
to the all-white University of Oklahoma's
graduate program in January 1948.
Denied admission, McLaurin applied again in
September. Still denied, he sought a remedy in
federal court, which ordered the university to
admit McLaurin. The ruling, however, did not
specifically void the state's segregation laws.

University president George Lynn Cross,
who did not personally oppose integration,
worked with regents to admit McLaurin while
also obeying the state's segregation laws. However,
the implemented plan was dehumanizing.
The university made arrangements
for McLaurin to take his courses in room
104 in the Carnegie Building. Workers constructed
an alcove (the NAACP's lawyer, Thurgood
Marshall, who, with Robert L. Carter
and Amos T. Hall, argued the case before the
Supreme Court, called it a "broom closet"),
with wooden railings that separated McLaurin
from the rest of the class. He had a separate
entrance and exit to and from the hall. Mc-
Laurin also found that the university had
given him a separate-but-equal men's room, a
separate table in the student union, a separate
table in the campus cafeteria, and a separate
library study table with his name on it. These
arrangements satisfied neither McLaurin nor
the NAACP, whose legal appeal argued that
such on-campus segregation hampered Mc-
Laurin's ability to study, to take part in class
discussions, and to interact further with other
students. On June 5, 1950, the U.S. Supreme
Court agreed and ordered the university to
end the on-campus segregation of McLaurin.

With this victory, McLaurin v. Oklahoma
joined a train of precedents, including Missouri
ex. rel. Gaines v. Canada (1938), Sweatt v.
Painter (a 1950 Texas case), and Sipuel v. Board
of Regents University of Oklahoma (1945),
which integrated the University of Oklahoma
Law School and led to the Supreme Court's
historic Brown v. The Board of Education of
Topeka decision of 1954 and the eventual integration
of schools nationwide.


James M. Smallwood
Oklahoma State University




Fisher, Ada Lois Sipuel. Matter of Black and White: The
Autobiography of Ada Lois Sipuel Fisher. Norman: University
of Oklahoma Press, 1996. Franklin, Jimmie Lewis.
Journey toward Hope: A History of Blacks in Oklahoma.
Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1982. Smallwood,
James. Blacks in Oklahoma. Stillwater: Oklahoma State
University Press, 1981.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>