<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.edu.007</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Boys Town</field>
      <field name="author">Wunder, Susan K.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BOYS TOWN

Founded in Omaha, Nebraska, in 1917, as
a residence for young homeless males, Boys
Town today is a youth care network with multiple
services and locations. It originated with
the work of Father Edward Flanagan, an Irishborn
Catholic priest who aided unemployed
men in Omaha. Flanagan soon turned his attention
to the young boys who arrived at
his Workingmen's Hotel, many of whom
were referred there by local social agencies
and legal authorities. Flanagan was determined
to provide the home he was certain
these boys deserved and required, and his
operation quickly outgrew two consecutive
houses in Omaha. In 1921 he acquired Overlook
Farm on the western outskirts of the city,
where Boys Town grew and stands today as an
incorporated village.

Father Flanagan's often-quoted motto,
"There are no bad boys," was evident in
the development and operation of Boys Town.
The nonsectarian home was open to boys of
all races and religions. There were no fences
surrounding the grounds, the premise being
that only those who wanted to be there should
be. There was no physical punishment for
misdeeds; rather, education and guidance
were the hallmarks of the institution. There
was also hard work, as each resident had regular
chores in addition to studies, participation
in athletic events, and attendance at religious
services. Experience in citizenship was provided
through election of a mayor, council,
and commissioners among the residents.

Father Flanagan sought funds and recognition
for Boys Town through several public enterprises.
A traveling show with the boys,
billed as the "World's Greatest Juvenile Entertainers,"
toured the Great Plains. Flanagan
himself hosted a nationally syndicated radio
program. The Boys Town choir was organized
in the 1930s, performed around the nation,
and made several recordings. The Boys Town
football team also became a respected athletic
power. Great attention came to Boys Town in
1938 with the film Boys Town, starring Spencer
Tracy and Mickey Rooney. Tracy won an
Academy Award as best actor for his portrayal
of Father Flanagan. His Oscar is displayed today
in the Boys Town Hall of History.

Since Flanagan's death in 1948, Boys Town
has continued his basic philosophy. In 1979
it expanded its services to include girls. And
in 2000 seven out of ten residents voted to
change the name to Girls and Boys Town. Today
approximately 500 young people are in
residence at any given time, receiving schooling
and services until they can return to
their families. The original dormitories have
been replaced with seventy-six homestyle residences,
each with six to ten youths living with
a married couple. The campus (now a National
Historic Landmark) covers approximately
900 acres, including a working farm,
Catholic and Protestant chapels, Father Flanagan's
home, middle, high, and vocational
schools, a post office, and meeting facilities.
Also headquartered in Omaha are child care
and training programs and the Boys Town National
Research Hospital, which specializes in
children with communication disorders.

Boys Town's services and programs extend
far beyond its Great Plains origins, with facilities
in thirteen states and Washington DC as
well as a national hotline serving all of North
America. Boys Town administrators estimate
that in one year they provide direct or indirect
care to approximately 1.1 million children.
This influence helps make Boys Town one of
Nebraska's leading tourist attractions, where
visitors are greeted with one of the famous
statues of one boy carrying a smaller one on
his back with the caption, "He ain't heavy,
Father . . . he's m' brother."

Boys Town website.


Susan K. Wunder
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Hickey, Donald R. Nebraska Moments: Glimpses of Nebraska's
Past. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1992:
197–205. Oursler, Fulton, and Will Oursler. Father Flanagan
of Boys Town. Garden City NY: Doubleday, 1949.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>