<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.asam.016</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Kogawa, Joy Nozomi (b. 1935)</field>
      <field name="author">Wishart, David J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




KOGAWA, JOY NOZOMI (b. 1935)

The Japanese Canadian writer and activist Joy
Kogawa is best known for her novel Obasan
(1981), which was based on her own experiences
as a captive in a Canadian internment
camp during World War II. The book won
Books in Canada First Novel Award and Canadian
Authors Association Book of the Year
Award.

Kogawa was born in Vancouver on June 6,
1935, a second-generation Japanese Canadian
(nisei). During World War II she and her family,
together with more than 20,000 other Japanese
Canadians, were shipped to detention
camps in the interior of the country. Kogawa
was sent first to Slocan, British Columbia,
then to Coaldale, Alberta. In Obasan, the
adult Naomi, as an activist seeking justice for
the victims of internment, reconstructs what
had happened to her as a child as she scrutinizes
the records that document this dark period
of Canadian history.

Kogawa studied education at the Universities
of Alberta (1954) and Saskatchewan
(1968) and taught elementary school in Coaldale
for a year. Her first book of poetry, The Splintered Moon, was published in 1967. She
subsequently published three other collections
of poetry. She has written three other
novels since Obasan, two of which also feature
Naomi. Like her main character, Kogawa has
campaigned tirelessly for the rights of Japanese
Canadians, so much so that in a 1988
interview she expressed concern that her writing
would be overwhelmed by her political
commitment. Her most recent novel, The Rain Ascends (1995), moved away from the
previous autobiographical character of her
fiction to tackle an equally charged subject
matter: the abuse of children by clergymen.


David J. Wishart
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Williamson, Janice. Sounding Differences: Conversations with Seventeen Canadian Women Writers. Toronto: University
of Toronto Press, 1993: 148-59.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>