<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.na.061</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Mandans</field>
      <field name="author">Schneider, Mary Jane</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MANDANS

The Siouan-speaking people now called Mandans
referred to themselves as Numangkaki,
or "People of the First Man," a name that reflected
their creation by First Man. Despite
this common name, the people lived in separate,
autonomous villages that were identified
by their locations on the Missouri River and
its tributaries. The two main divisions were
the Nuitadi, "People of the West Side," and
Nuptadi, "People of the East Side." Two other
divisions, the Awigaxa and Istopa, mentioned
by early European and European American
visitors, disappeared under the pressure of
epidemics and American settlement.

In 1797 British explorer David Thompson
found some Mandans still living in villages on
the Missouri while others had settled among
the Hidatsa on the Knife River. Mandan villages
differed from those of the Hidatsas by
the arrangement of the earth lodges around
an open space with a shrine in its center. Like
the Arikaras and Hidatsas, the Mandans combined
bison hunting with corn, beans, squash,
and sunflower agriculture, and this combination
set the seasonal round of spring planting,
summer hunting, fall harvesting, and winter
hunting. While hunting, the tribe lived in tipis
and carried only the most necessary tools and
clothing. At the village, however, the earth
lodge provided plenty of room for storing
items such as pottery and baskets, which the
women made for cooking and harvesting, respectively.
Related women, usually sisters,
would build and occupy a lodge with their
families.

Family relationships were organized on the
basis of matrilineal clans. All the women in a
family and their children were members of
the same clan. A man who married a woman
who was not of his clan moved into her earth
lodge, but his primary loyalty was to his clan.
The clan cared for its members, especially orphans
and the elderly, disciplined its children,
assisted its members in acquiring membership
in military, social, and religious societies, and
helped to purchase sacred bundles that allowed
a man to perform religious ceremonies.
These sacred bundles were earthly manifestations
of the Mandans' origins. Each bundle
contained objects, songs, and instructions for
the sponsor of the ceremony. These ceremonies
ensured the continued success of gardening
and hunting activities that supported
the tribe. The most important ceremony was
the Okipa, a dramatization of the creation of
the Mandan world by Lone Man and the gift
of the animals. Despite their recognition of
common identity, the villages were independent
in their government. Each village selected
two men–one known for his military
abilities and the other for diplomacy–from
the general council of sacred bundle owners to
lead the village. The leaders served only as
long as people accepted their ideas.

The first non-Indians to visit the Mandans
found them to be hospitable to outsiders, and
this established a long tradition of friendship
between the Mandans and European Americans.
In 1837 a devastating smallpox epidemic
killed most of the Mandans and a large number
of Hidatsas, leaving the fewer than 200
survivors vulnerable to attacks from hostile
tribes. As a defensive measure, the Mandans
moved up the Missouri and, with the Hidatsas,
established Like-a-Fishhook Village. This became
a trade and administrative center for the
region, attracting fur traders, government officials, and missionaries. The Arikaras moved to
the village in 1862, completing the association
that eventually became the Three Affiliated
Tribes of the Fort Berthold Indian Reservation.

After forty years, Like-a-Fishhook was overcrowded
and the local resources were exhausted.
Consequently, in the early 1880s, even before
allotment officially began, its inhabitants moved
to new, kinship-based communities along the
Missouri. The Mandans moved to the west side,
where they established the settlements of Charging
Eagle, Red Butte, and Beaver Creek. There
they lived as farmers and ranchers, sending their
children to the community school and attending
church events and traditional ceremonies.
In 1934 the Mandans, Hidatsas, and Arikaras
voted to accept the Indian Reorganization Act
and, under its auspices, established a tribal
council, adopted a constitution, and took the
name Three Affiliated Tribes of Fort Berthold
Reservation.

In 1954 Garrison Dam, part of the Pick-
Sloan Plan, turned the Missouri River into
Lake Sakakawea, causing major changes in
Mandan life. People had to leave the small,
kinship-based, bottomland communities and
move into new houses in new towns. The new
Mandan community of Twin Buttes was built,
but not everyone lived there, and tribal activities
became more difficult to coordinate.
Relatives no longer lived next door to each
other, and the removal of the bridge isolated
this corner of the reservation from New Town,
the new administrative headquarters.

In the years that have passed since the dam
was built, the Mandans have strived to maintain
their language by teaching it in the elementary
school and have revived the Sun
Dance and other ceremonies. Nevertheless,
marriage with outsiders and work opportunities
elsewhere on the reservation continue to
draw young people away. A tenacious core of
Mandan identity survives, however, and their
population, which was only 241 in 1874, has
rebounded to more than 1,200.

See also WATER: Pick-Sloan Plan.


Mary Jane Schneider
University of North Dakota



Bowers, Alfred W. Mandan Social and Ceremonial Organization.
Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1950. Meyer,
Roy W. The Village Indians of the Upper Missouri: The
Mandans, Hidatsas, and Arikaras. Lincoln: University of
Nebraska Press, 1977. Wood, W. Raymond, and Thomas
D. Thiessen. Early Fur Trade on the Northern Plains. Norman:
University of Oklahoma Press, 1985.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>