<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fil.018</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Dennis, Sandy (1937-1992)</field>
      <field name="author">Wishart, David J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




Dennis, Sandy (1937-1992)

Sandra Dale Dennis
     

The actress Sandy Dennis, whose nervous and
fragile screen persona had very little to do
with the real person, was born in Hastings,
Nebraska, on April 17, 1937. Her father was
a postal clerk. At the age of fourteen, after
watching Kim Stanley and Joanne Woodward
in the television production A Lady of Property,
she realized that her calling was acting.
Her talent quickly became evident. She played
leading roles in high school plays and in the
Lincoln Community Theater; at the age of
nineteen she left Nebraska for New York City
and a distinguished career in acting.

Within three months Dennis had won her
first professional role as a thirteen-year-old
in Henrik Ibsen's The Lady from the Sea. She
studied with Lee Strasberg at the Actors Studio
and secured major roles in Broadway plays
in the early 1960s. By 1964 she had collected
two Tonys and a New York Drama Critics Poll
Award.

Dennis's movie breakthrough came in 1967,
when she played Honey, the whimpering wife
of the young faculty member in Who's Afraid of Virginia Woolf. She won an Academy Award
for best supporting actress for her performance.
Other critically acclaimed performances
in comedies and dramas on stage and
screen followed, but her popularity declined
in the 1970s and 1980s, partly because she refused
to glamorize her appearance. Her final
film role was in 1991 in Sean Penn's The Indian Runner, fittingly set in Dennis's home state of
Nebraska.

Dennis was briefly married to her longtime
companion, jazz musician Gerry Mulligan,
from 1975 to 1976. However, a self-described
"solitary person," she seemed to be more comfortable
in the company of cats and dogs than
of people. Sandy Dennis lived the final years of
her life with her mother in Westport, Connecticut,
where she died of ovarian cancer on
March 2, 1992.


David J. Wishart
University of Nebraska-Lincoln





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>