<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pe.055</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Shelterbelts</field>
      <field name="author">Brandle, James R.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SHELTERBELTS

A shelterbelt is an area planted with trees and
shrubs arranged in rows to form a barrier to
reduce surface winds. Planted throughout the
Great Plains, shelterbelts provide wind protection
for homes, farms and ranches, highways,
livestock, crops, and a diversity of habitats
for numerous species of wildlife. This
biodiversity helps maintain various predatorprey
relationships and contributes to biological
control of crop pests.

Shelterbelts were first planted in the region
by early settlers. Many brought tree seeds
and seedlings from the East or gathered seedlings
from local native stands and planted
them around their homes for protection, firewood,
and beauty. During the agricultural expansion
of the early 1900s, much of the native
grassland was plowed and planted to
wheat. As the drought conditions of the 1920s
intensified, many agricultural fields in the
region were abandoned, and wind erosion
escalated.

In 1935, the U.S. Forest Service undertook
the largest tree-planting effort ever conducted,
the Prairie States Forestry Project. During the
next eight years, with labor provided by the
Works Project Administration (WPA), more
than 222 million tree seedlings were planted,
creating in excess of 18,500 miles of shelterbelts.
Most of these shelterbelts were ten to
sixteen rows wide and a mile long. Even under
the dry conditions of the time, most seedlings
survived and for the next thirty to forty years
provided protection to the agricultural lands
of the region.

While many of these original shelterbelts
still exist around farmsteads, most of the
wide-row field shelterbelts have been removed
to make way for center-pivot irrigation systems
or field consolidation. Some have been
replaced with single or double-row field windbreaks.
Today, the Natural Resource Conservation
Service has primary responsibility for
shelterbelts and soil conservation efforts. In
cooperation with state forestry agencies and
local conservation districts, more than 20 million
tree and shrub seedlings are planted annually
throughout the Great Plains, many in
shelterbelts.

Similar efforts occurred in the Prairie Provinces
under the direction of the Prairie Farm
Rehabilitation Administration. Since the beginning
of tree planting efforts in 1892, more
than 500 million seedlings have been distributed
to landowners, and today four to six million
seedlings are distributed to landowners
each year.

Shelterbelts work by reducing wind speed
on the leeward side of the shelterbelt. The
amount of wind speed reduction is determined
by the number and arrangement of
trees and shrubs in the shelterbelt: the denser
the shelterbelt, the greater the reduction. The
size of the protected area depends on the
length and height of the shelterbelt. For example,
a twenty-five-foot tall, moderately dense
shelterbelt will reduce wind speed for a distance
of 250 to 500 feet leeward. In this sheltered
zone, temperature and humidity are increased
slightly and evaporation is reduced.
The goal of any shelterbelt planting is to use
the microclimate created in the sheltered area
to the advantage of the landowner. In winter
the reduced wind speed means a significant
reduction in wind chill temperatures and a 20
to 40 percent reduction in the amount of energy
needed to heat a home. Outdoor activities
are more pleasant in farmyards or livestock
areas when wind protection is available.
Livestock that are protected require less feed
and suffer fewer heath problems. Field shelterbelts
help control wind erosion and increase
production of crops on sheltered fields by an
average of 12 to 15 percent, providing producers
with increased economic returns. Living
snow fences of trees and shrubs planted
along highways reduce snow removal costs
and decrease traffic accidents.


James R. Brandle
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Brandle, James R., D. L. Hintz, and J. W. Sturrock. Windbreak
Technology. Amsterdam: Elsevier Science Publishers
B.V., 1988. Droze, Wilmon H. Trees, Prairies, and People: A
History of Tree Planting in the Plains States. Denton: Texas
Woman's University Press, 1977. Howe, J. A. G. "One Hundred
Years of Prairie Forestry." Prairie Forum 11 (1986):
243–51.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>