<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pe.028</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Geology</field>
      <field name="author">Keeler, Kathleen H. Locklear, James H.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




GEOLOGY


Generalized Chart of Rocks of the Great Plains
Note: Unit names are representative and not complete. Time column is not to scale. Shading represents missing intervals of strata.


Any discussion of the geology of a given physiographic
region should distinguish between
the history of the present landscape and the
older geologic record that, for the most part,
lies buried beneath the area. The oldest rocks
under the Great Plains belong to the Precambrian
era and represent a complex set of
primarily igneous and metamorphic rocks.
They record the construction of the North
American continent as a series of continental
plates which collided with an earlier "North
America" that was 2.1 billion years old and
much farther south than today. These ancient
rocks are exposed at the surface within the
Great Plains in the Black Hills and the Central
Texas and Hartville (eastern Wyoming)
Uplifts.

About one billion years ago, the last amalgamation
of continental material involving
the future Great Plains region was completed,
and erosion prevailed over deposition for the
next half billion years, leaving little in the way
of a rock record in the central part of the continent.
Beginning about 540 million years ago,
the first of many shallow inland seas ushered
in the Paleozoic and later the Mesozoic eras.
Shallow ocean waters covered a significant
part of the interior of North America, including
the region we recognize as the Great
Plains, for most of Paleozoic and Mesozoic
time. Typically between 5,000 and 10,000 feet
of layered sediments, predominantly limestones,
shales, and sandstones representing a
mixture of seafloor, near-shore, and delta environments,
accumulated during the course of
almost 480 million years.

This long period of predominantly shallow
marine deposition was brought to a close some
70 million years ago when a major period of
mountain building (the Laramide Orogeny)
created a belt of mountains stretching from
Alaska to Mexico. This major shift in geologic
processes lasted for more than 20 million
years, as the continental seas retreated, to be
replaced by the first landscapes of the ancestral
Great Plains. Uplift along the eastern margin
of the Rocky Mountains was dramatic, and
deposits of the Cretaceous seas were raised
thousands of feet above sea level. East of the
rising Rockies and the flanking basins, gentle
warping and uplift raised the former seabeds
from one to a few thousand feet. The Black
Hills and the Laramie Range and Hartville Uplift
of eastern Wyoming were formed as highlands
probably late in the Laramide Orogeny.
They reached maximum elevation in the late
Paleocene and early Eocene.

The forces of erosion immediately attacked
all of these new highlands, and the mud, sand,
and gravel produced were transported by
eastward-flowing rivers and deposited in low
basins on the western margin of the newly
created Plains during the Paleocene. The majority
of these deposits were preserved in the
Northern Great Plains, and no sediment or
depositional record has been discovered for
the first 25 million years of the Cenozoic era in
the Central Great Plains except for the Denver
and Raton Basins. Erosion and/or nondeposition
was the order of the day for an even longer
time, some 50 million years, in the Southern
Great Plains. The following discussion will
focus on more specific aspects of the geologic
history of the Southern, Central, and Northern
Great Plains.

The rivers originating in the newly arisen
southern Rocky Mountains flowed eastward
and carved a series of drainages hundreds of
feet deep into the recently uplifted Mesozoic
strata. The record in the Southern Great Plains
for the first 75 percent of the Cenozoic, however,
speaks only of erosion. Only the Raton
Basin contains sedimentary rocks of early
Cenozoic age. The enormous quantity of debris
that was shed off the rising mountains was
transported across the region into the Gulf of
Mexico, forming major deltas along the coastline.
Enough sediment was delivered in the
early Cenozoic to the Gulf that the coastline
was pushed more than 100 miles seaward. Finally,
about 12 million years ago, braided
streams flowing in the valleys began to deposit
sand and gravel, and the construction of the
Southern High Plains was under way. These
valleys did not always completely fill with
stream deposits, and in Texas and eastern New
Mexico they are often capped by windblown
sand and silt, which were also deposited on the
adjacent uplands. Near the end of the Miocene
and into the early Pliocene, sedimentation
rates slowed and extensive calcareous soils
(caliches) developed on a relatively stable land
surface. These calcareous soils form the hard
and durable caprock horizons that cover much
of the Southern High Plains. Geologists have
included these deposits within the Ogallala
Formation or Group. These strata comprise
the majority of sediments in the High Plains
aquifer, the primary source of groundwater in
the Southern and Central Great Plains. The
Quaternary deposits of the Southern High
Plains are primarily windblown sandy silt and
shallow lake sediments.

In the Central Great Plains there is a good
record of early Cenozoic (Paleocene) deposition
only in the Denver Basin and in the Williston
Basin of northwestern South Dakota. The basal
Paleocene rocks (Denver Formation) are up to
1,500 feet thick and consist of fine-grained river
floodplain, swamp, and lake sediments with
scattered coaly beds. These strata are overlain by
coarse sandstones and conglomerates (Dawson
Formation), representing large alluvial fans
deposited by braided rivers that drained the
newly arisen Rocky Mountain Front Range.
The climate was probably tropical to subtropical
throughout most of the Great Plains during
the Paleocene epoch. For the succeeding 20
million years, representing most of the Eocene,
only a sparse rock record is preserved and
erosion or nondeposition was widespread
throughout the Great Plains. A major period
of sedimentation was then initiated in the late
Eocene and continued into the Oligocene.
Over the next eight million years, as much as
1,300 feet of predominantly fine-grained sediment,
the White River Group, was deposited
across much of the Central Great Plains. This
deposit is unique because much of it was deposited
by the wind, and typically more than
80 percent of the fine-grained mineral grains
are shards of volcanic glass or volcanic minerals
derived from huge eruptive centers in the
Great Basin of Nevada and Utah. There are
widespread coarse-grained river deposits in
the lower part of the White River Group, but
the upper half consists primarily of windblown
sandy silt, an ancient dust (loess) deposit
that blanketed and built up the landscapes.
This interval also marks a change from
subtropical to a subhumid (and possibly semiarid)
environment in the Central Great Plains.

The next major set of rocks, the Arikaree
Group, represents about 10 million years of late
Oligocene and early Miocene time and is restricted
to western Nebraska and adjoining
parts of South Dakota and Wyoming. The
basal Arikaree strata were deposited in several
valleys as sandy river sediments. However, the
remainder of the Arikaree is composed primarily
of windblown fine sand and silt. As
much as 40 to 70 percent of these grains have a
volcanic origin, but they appear to be largely
derived from huge volcanic eruptions in Colorado
instead of the Great Basin. At the end of
Arikaree deposition, about 18 million years
ago, the dominant depositional process and
accompanying landscape development underwent
a major shift. The constructional and
widespread windblown deposits of the Arikaree
and White River Groups gave way to
deposition in restricted river valleys that typifies
the Miocene-age Ogallala Group. There
was also a cessation of volcanically derived material
blown into the Great Plains, and from
that time to the present the Rocky Mountains
have been the major source (excluding continental
glacial deposits) of sediment deposited
in the Plains. Ogallala deposition began about
six million years earlier here than in the Southern
Great Plains, and landscape evolution was
more complex, as there are more cycles of valley
cutting and filling preserved in the rock
record. Sediment transported out of the Central
and Northern Great Plains by rivers during
the Miocene was probably delivered to the
ocean via Hudson Bay rather than the Gulf of
Mexico. Observations of ancient soils and
mammal fossils of the Arikaree and Ogallala
Groups suggest that shortgrass prairies first
appeared in the Great Plains in the early Miocene,
about 22 million years ago, and that tallgrass
prairies did not appear until the late
Miocene, about 8 to 10 million years ago.

Ogallala sedimentation ceased across the
Central and Southern Great Plains at about the
same time, some five million years ago at the
end of the Miocene. The region had less local
relief than today and would have presented
remarkable vistas of vast, nearly unbroken
grasslands, sloping gently to the east and
ramping westward up onto the Rockies. Most
of the present physiographic regions of the
Great Plains are a result of erosion in the last
five million years. Widespread uplift to the
west and in the Black Hills caused rivers draining
these highlands to erode the landscape
once again and the Great Plains were carved
up. One of the few remaining examples of the
"climax" Great Plains topography is found in
the "Gangplank" area west of Cheyenne, Wyoming.
Here the Union Pacific Railroad and
Interstate 80 use the gentle slope of the old
Ogallala surface to climb to the summit of the
Laramie Mountains. Renewed uplift of the
Rocky Mountains of northern Colorado and
southeastern Wyoming between 3.5 and 2 million
years ago (Pliocene epoch), perhaps aided
by increased precipitation, delivered coarse
sediment out onto the Great Plains via ancestral
South and North Platte Rivers. Within
Colorado, Wyoming, and western Nebraska,
these deposits were confined to valleys no
larger than those of the present North and
South Platte. In central Nebraska, however, a
complex sheet of sand and gravel, as much as
200 feet thick, was deposited over 20,000
square miles. These deposits, referred to as the
Broadwater and Long Pine Formations, represent
the greatest known volume of coarse material
shed into the Great Plains in the last 34
million years.

The Williston Basin, covering 60,000 square
miles, contains the most extensive and complete
section of Paleocene deposits (Fort Union
Group) in the Great Plains. The Fort Union
Group consists of as much as 1,800 feet of sandstone,
mudstone, and thick coal beds deposited
mainly in delta, swamp, and river environments.
The last of the great interior seas was
slowly retreating toward the northeast and
Hudson Bay while the lower part of the Fort
Union was being deposited. It left behind a
deposit of shale called the Cannonball Formation.
The Eocene primarily marks a time of
erosion. While late Eocene- to Oligocene-age
White River strata were deposited in North
Dakota, to the northwest in Saskatchewan the
equivalent-age Cypress Hills Formation was
deposited. However, it is a coarse-grained river
deposit compared to the windblown White
River strata. There are a few thin and widely
scattered Miocene- and Pliocene-age river deposits
found across the Northern Great Plains.
It has been estimated that up to two kilometers
of sediment were removed by erosion from this
region between 34 and 2 million years ago.
What is left is only a small fraction of the
enormous quantity of material that was moved
out of the region, a situation similar to the
Southern Great Plains.

During the last two million years, the geologic
history of the Central and Northern
Great Plains was dominated by the effects of
continental glaciation. In the Southern Plains,
the record is one of interplay between deposition
by running water, winds, and in lake
basins.


James B. Swinehart
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Baars, D. L. "Basins of the Rocky Mountain Region." In
Sedimentary Cover, North American Craton, U.S., edited
by L. L. Sloss, The Geology of North America, vol. D-2:
109-220. Boulder CO: Geological Society of America, 1988.
Trimble, Donald E. The Geologic Story of the Great Plains.
Geologic Survey Bulletin 1493. Washington DC: Government
Printing Office, 1980.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>