<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.037</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Literary Criticism</field>
      <field name="author">Thacker, Robert</field>
      <field name="text">

 




LITERARY CRITICISM

The predominant critical response to Great
Plains writing has been, to paraphrase Henry
Kreisel, the effect of the landscape upon
the European American imagination. In the
United States, the 1920s saw the publication
of two studies–Dorothy Dondore's The Prairie and the Making of Middle America (1926)
and Lucy Lockwood Hazard's The Frontier in American Literature (1927)–that identified
texts and used them to trace a regional imaginative
history derived from Frederick Jackson
Turner's frontier thesis. Similar work was
done (though with little reference to the frontier
theory) in Canada by Edward McCourt,
whose The Canadian West in Fiction (1949; revised,
1970) laid the basis for the two major
Canadian studies, Laurence Ricou's Vertical Man/Horizontal World (1973) and Dick Harrison's
Unnamed Country (1977). Both are nationalist
studies that largely ignore material
from south of the forty-ninth parallel, and
both argue the primacy of the Prairie landscape
in informing and shaping a distinctly
Canadian point of view, one derived from
imaginative interaction with the land itself
over time.

Written partially as a response to them,
Robert Thacker's The Great Prairie Fact and Literary Imagination (1989) is an analysis of the
European and European American aesthetic
and literary response to the Great Plains landscape
from Cabeza de Vaca during the 1530s to
Sharon Butala during the 1980s. His conclusion,
following Cather in O Pioneers! is that
"the great fact" is "the land itself." Central to all
three post-1970 studies is Wallace Stegner's
Wolf Willow (1962), a volume that has achieved
classic status in Canada owing to its Saskatchewan
setting. Beyond these central studies,
other recent critical works either adopt individual
themes or assert a new critical perspective.
Carol Fairbanks's Prairie Women (1986) is
an instance of the former, as is Steven Olson's
The Prairie in Nineteenth-Century American Poetry (1994). Arnold E. Davidson's Coyote Country (1994) advances a Canadian exceptionalist
argument informed by postmodern
theory in a treatment of a group of writers
succeeding those offered by Ricou, Harrison,
and Thacker. Similarly, and despite an attempt
to treat Canadian writers along with American
ones, Diane Dufva Quantic offers an American
exceptionalist argument in The Nature of the Place (1995). So too does Joni L. Kinsey in Plain Pictures (1996). Kinsey analyzes painted and
photographed images in a way that attests to
the ongoing pull of the Great Plains landscape
upon the imagination.


Robert Thacker
St. Lawrence University




Harrison, Dick. Unnamed Country: The Struggle for a Canadian Prairie Fiction. Edmonton: University of Alberta
Press, 1977. Ricou, Laurence. Vertical Man/Horizontal World: Man and Landscape in Canadian Prairie Fiction.
Vancouver: University of British Columbia Press, 1973.
Thacker, Robert. The Great Prairie Fact and Literary Imagination.
Albuquerque: University of New Mexico Press,
1989.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>