<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fol.005</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Cattle Guards</field>
      <field name="author">Hoy, James F.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CATTLE GUARDS


Cattle guard


A cattle guard is a device of folk technology
(although many today are commercially manufactured)
that allows automotive tra.c to
move freely while hindering the passage of
livestock. Its essential components are a pit,
usually constructed of concrete and a foot or
more deep, placed across a roadway at the
point where it intersects with a fence; a grid of
metal bars, pipe or of railroad rails, fastened
in parallel fashion across the pit and spaced
about three to five inches apart; and a wing on
either side that angles up from the edge of the
grid to the fence. Hoofed livestock, instinctively
wary about insecure footing, are generally
deterred by this barrier. Some ranchers
have created effective cattle guards by placing
fresh cowhides, sheets of tin, or an arrangement
of old tires in a gateway.

The cattle guard had its origin in the Great
Plains, being independently developed in a
number of locations from Texas to North Dakota
in the decade beginning around 1905 in
response to the introduction of a growing
number of automobiles in fenced range country.
The immediate progenitor of the automotive
cattle guard is the railroad cattle guard, an
American innovation dating back at least to
1836. The ultimate progenitor of the cattle
guard is the flat stone stile of Cornwall, England,
where grids of granite bars placed over
pits in public footpaths have been in existence
for more than 2,000 years.

Today, cattle guards are found in all fifty
states and on every continent. The term "cattle
guard" is generally used in the Southern
Plains, while from Nebraska north the terms
"auto gate" or "car gate" are common. In the
Prairie Provinces, a cattle guard usually refers
to the railroad variety, while those on highways
are called "Texas gates."


James F. Hoy
Emporia State University




Hoy, James F. The Cattle Guard: Its History and Lore. Lawrence:
University Press of Kansas, 1982.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>