<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ind.058</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Tourism</field>
      <field name="author">De Bres, Karen J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




TOURISM

As most travelers in the Great Plains are en
route to other places, tourism in the region
tends to focus upon transit tourism rather
than upon destination tourism. And since the
modern "tourist gaze" rarely appreciates the
beauty of the Plains landscape, marketable
tourist attractions tend to be man-made, emphasizing
culture and heritage. The Plains
states contain much of the nation's western
heritage and numerous Native American sites.
All the Plains states now celebrate their Native
American heritages, especially the state of
Oklahoma. Some tourist sites such as Mount
Rushmore National Memorial in South Dakota's
Black Hills and the Little Bighorn Battlefield
National Monument in Montana are
associated with the struggle for ownership
and identity between Native Americans and
the wider American culture. A more traditional
version of the region's settlement history
has been and continues to be celebrated
and marketed as the principal resource of the
Plains tourism industry.

Most of the advertising and state funding
for Plains tourism is focused on the frontier
and early European American settlement period,
which lasted from the 1850s into the beginning
of the twentieth century. In Nebraska
and Kansas, for example, important pioneer
trails such as the Oregon Trail and the Santa
Fe Trail are well marked, and former cattle
towns are often important tourist destinations.
Dodge City, Abilene, and Wichita all
contain replicas of the "Front Streets" of the
1870s. Wichita's replica, which includes several
original buildings, is the most complete and
accurate.

State funding for Plains tourism is often
tied to western heritage promotion. In Kansas,
for example, when the state legislature first
approved $25,000 for tourist promotions in
1953, the funds were specifically set aside to
celebrate the state's "western heritage." This
policy continues, as exemplified by the 1990s
Kansas State Historic Sites Master Plan, which
is organized under the title "Kansas: Where
the West Begins."

Plains tourism is of particular economic
importance to towns and cities located along
major transit routes. Billboards advertising
the attractions of towns, sometimes hundreds
of miles away, attempt to persuade the motorist
to stop and spend the night. From south to
north the major routes are I-10 and I-20 in
Texas, I-35 and I-44 in Oklahoma, I-70 in
Kansas, I-80 in Nebraska, and I-90 in South
Dakota. Cities that particularly benefit from
such motorists include Amarillo, Abilene, Big
Spring, and Odessa, Texas; Tulsa and Oklahoma
City, Oklahoma; Goodland, Colby, Russell,
and Salina, Kansas; North Platte, Kearney,
and Grand Island, Nebraska; and Sioux Falls
and Mitchell, South Dakota. Williston, Grand
Forks, and Minot are also stopover towns in
North Dakota. Given the region's propensity
for sudden snowstorms in the winter and for
tornados and thunderstorms in the summer,
many of these cities also benefit from the presence
of visitors forced to seek shelter unexpectedly.

Other Plains cities that benefit from tourism
are those located on the edge of the region
that often host major conferences. These cities
include Fort Worth, Kansas City, Denver, and
Calgary. In 1998 alone, for example, Calgary
hosted 136 conventions, bringing more than
495,000 visitors to the city.

Two other common features of the Great
Plains attract local tourists rather than a mix
of visitors from within and without the region.
Local tourists especially enjoy the reservoirs
and lakes constructed by the U.S. Army
Corps of Engineers from the 1950s through
the 1970s. They are also the major participants
in the many small-scale festivals and rodeos as
well as the larger state fairs held annually
throughout the region.

Great Plains tourism in Texas focuses on
the Alamo and the nearby River Walk (Paseo
del Rio) in San Antonio. Tourism at the Alamo
is centered almost entirely on a traditional
American interpretation of the wellknown
battle and siege. Less contentious is
Lyndon B. Johnson National Historic Park, located
near Johnson City. The Dallas–Fort
Worth area is home to the Amon G. Carter
Museum, an important repository of American
western art, as well as Six Flags over Texas,
the primary theme park of a major chain. Annual
festivals, rodeos, and celebrations take
place in a number of cities and towns, with the
German towns of New Braunfels (which has
built a water park to attract more tourists) and
Fredericksburg as examples.

In Oklahoma, many of the tourist attractions
feature the state's frontier heritage. Examples
include the National Cowboy Hall of
Fame and Western Heritage Center in Oklahoma
City. Indian City, U.S.A., contains seven
restored Indian villages and is but one example
of a major policy shift in Oklahoma's tourism,
which aims to celebrate rather than downplay
the state's extensive Native American heritage.
Critics still complain of tourist "commodification"
and stereotyping of Native American history.
The Chickasaw National Recreation Area,
the first national park in the state, contains
springs, lakes, and streams. Local festivals include
the American Indian Exposition at Anadarko,
Will Rogers Days at Claremore, and the
Cherokee National Holiday in Tahlequah.

As the boyhood home of a popular American
president, Abilene, Kansas, benefits from
the Eisenhower library, museum, home, and
chapel. Fort Leavenworth and Fort Riley both
have museums dedicated to frontier army life.
The dinosaur museum in Hayes has been
moved from its campus location to a more
convenient and larger site next to Interstate
70. Despite some local opposition, a large
ranch house and its attendant acres of prairie
have been preserved for posterity in Chase
County. Kansas festivals include Wah-Shun-
Gah Days in Council Grove, Dodge City Days
in Dodge City, and Beef Empire Days in Garden
City.

Tourism in Nebraska is also often focused
on its frontier heritage, with the Harold Warp
pioneer village at Minden as one extraordinary
example. As in Kansas, nineteenthcentury
collectors found dinosaur bones in
the state. Some of the fossils not shipped back
east are on display in Royal. Omaha, the state's
largest city, contains, among other tourist attractions,
the Henry Doorly Zoo, the Joslyn
Art Museum, the Durham Western Heritage
Museum, and the renovated Old Market. Nebraska
draws tourists to its spectacular annual
bird migrations, especially those of the sandhill
crane. Annual festivals include the Oregon
Trail Days in Gering and Arbor Day in Nebraska
City.

Most of South Dakota's tourist attractions,
unlike those in other states fully in this region,
are natural rather than cultural features. They
include the Badlands National Park, Wind
Cave National Park, and the Black Hills. The
Black Hills is a tourist destination in its own
right. Mount Rushmore National Memorial
depicts the huge carved granite faces of Presidents
Washington, Jefferson, Lincoln, and
Theodore Roosevelt. As a partial response to
criticism about the use of this site, a monument
to Crazy Horse is being created nearby.
Festivals in South Dakota include Gold Discovery
Days in Custer, the Corn Palace Festival
in Mitchell, and the Sturgis Motorcycle
Rally.

North Dakota's tourist attractions tend to
be located near its major population centers.
Theodore Roosevelt National Park is well
known for its badlands and diverse animal life.
As in most Great Plains states, there are several
restored nineteenth-century forts and Native
American villages, notably those at Lincoln
State Park and at Fargo. Festivals include
Roughriders Days in Dickinson, Norsk Hostfest
in Minot, and Bonanza Days in Wahpeton.

New Mexico, Colorado, Wyoming, and
Montana draw tourists mainly to their western,
mountainous portions, but their eastern
plains also have much to offer to tourists, particularly
if they want to get off the beaten path.
Carlsbad Caverns in southeastern New Mexico
is both a national park and a world heritage
site; its spectacular caves attracted 469,303 visitors
in 2000. Nestled in the lee of the Rocky
Mountains, Colorado Springs has been a tourist
center since the 1870s. North again into eastern
Wyoming, the traveler's eye is struck by Devils
Tower, the volcanic intrusion that abruptly rises
1,267 feet above the Belle Fourche River. A sacred
site to the Kiowas and Comanches, Devils
Tower also attracts rock climbers, 4,000 of
whom made their way to the top in 1998. In
eastern Montana, natural features such as the
badlands of Makoshika State Park and historical
sites such as the restored Fort Union have
much to offer as tourist destinations. One site,
Pompey's Pillar, just east of Billings, bears an
important latter-day graffiti: William Clark's
signature, the only on-site physical evidence of
the Lewis and Clark Expedition.

North of the forty-ninth parallel, the same
generalization holds true: tourists are attracted
to physical settings that, while they may lack
the splendor of the mountains, still present
drama and beauty, to historical sites, and to the
cultural offerings of the cities. The Cypress
Hills Interprovincial Park, for example, standing
600 meters above the plains of southwestern
Saskatchewan, is an alpine environment
of great biotic diversity. Throughout the
Prairie Provinces, the rich multicultural heritage
finds expression in diverse landscapes
and cultural celebrations: at Batoche, in westcentral
Saskatchewan, for example, Metis culture
is reinvigorated each summer with traditional
dancing, fiddling, and jigging. The single
most important tourist destination in the
Prairie Provinces, however, is Calgary, which
in 1998 drew more than 4.2 million people who
spent more than $629 million Canadian.

Tourism may not be what the Great Plains
is known for, yet the attractions are many, and
the economic influence is great. Indeed, in
Nebraska, for example, tourism ranks only
behind agriculture and manufacturing as a
source of state income.

See also EDUCATION: National Cowboy Hall of Fame and Western Heritage Center / PHYSICAL
ENVIRONMENT: Carlsbad Caverns / SPORTS
AND RECREATION: National Parks; Sturgis Motorcycle Rally.


Karen J. De Bres
Kansas State University




De Bres, Karen J. "Cowtowns or Cathedral Precincts? Two
Models for Contemporary Urban Tourism." Area 26
(1994): 57–67. De Bres, Karen J. "Defining Vernacular
Tourism: The View from Kansas." Annals of Tourism Research
4 (1996): 945–54. Jakle, John A. The Tourist: Travel in Twentieth-Century North America. Lincoln: University of
Nebraska Press, 1985.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>