<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.asam.012</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Female Employment Act</field>
      <field name="author">Brown, Ken Layton</field>
      <field name="text">

 




FEMALE EMPLOYMENT ACT

In February of 1912 the Saskatchewan legislature
enacted the Female Employment Act,
which made it illegal for "any Japanese, Chinaman
or other Oriental person" to employ
or offer lodging to any "white woman or girl."
The legislation resulted from, in a general
sense, the adoption in Saskatchewan of pronounced
anti-Chinese ideas, current especially
on the West Coast, and from an almost
pathological fear of miscegenation. However,
the trigger was a seemingly innocuous incident
in Moose Jaw involving a Chinese restaurant
owner who rapped with a broom handle
the ankle of a white woman (and former employee)
who was blocking a doorway in his
establishment. This incident, for which the
restaurateur was convicted of indecent assault,
occurred less than a week before the introduction
and passage of the act.

The owners of two restaurants in Moose
Jaw, with the financial help of other Chinese
businessmen and the active support of their
white female employees, unsuccessfully challenged
the act before the courts, claiming that
it infringed on federal powers. The act's scope
was reduced in 1913 when an amendment confined
the prohibition to Chinese, and again at
the end of World War I when another amendment
allowed the owners of restaurants and
laundries to employ white females if they obtained
a yearly license from the municipal
council.

It was a demeaning experience to apply for
such a license, and by no means guaranteed to
be successful. The effect of the act was to discourage
such businesses, commonly run by
Chinese, from employing white females and
to contribute to the marginalization of the
Chinese in Saskatchewan. Of course the act
also limited employment opportunities for
"white women and girls," and it was this that
ultimately led to the act's repeal in 1969.


Ken Leyton-Brown
University of Regina




Leyton-Brown, Ken. "Discriminatory Legislation in Early
Saskatchewan and the Development of Small Business." In
Proceedings of the Seventh Annual Conference of the International
Council for Small Business–Canada. Regina: icsb-
Canada, 1991: 252–71.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>