<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.052</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Neihardt, John G. (1881-1973)</field>
      <field name="author">Utecht, Lori</field>
      <field name="text">

 




NEIHARDT, JOHN G. (1881-1973)


Black Elk and John G. Neihardt at the Sioux Victory celebration at Pine Ridge, South Dakota, September 1945


John G. Neihardt was born near Sharpsburg,
Illinois, on January 8, 1881. After living for
a time in a sod house in western Kansas and
then in Kansas City, he moved to Wayne, Nebraska,
where he graduated from Nebraska
Normal College at age sixteen and wrote and
published his first book, The Divine Enchantment
(1900), which was based on Vedanta
philosophy.

In 1900 Neihardt moved to Bancroft, Nebraska.
He edited the local newspaper, worked
as a clerk on the Omaha Reservation, and
wrote lyric poetry, short stories, and novels.
Outing Magazine commissioned Neihardt to
record his experiences on a 2,000-mile trip
down the Missouri River in 1908, later published
as The River and I (1910). That same
year, Neihardt married Mona Martinsen, a
sculptor and former student of Rodin. They
had four children: Enid, Sigurd, Hilda, and
Alice.

Neihardt wrote literary columns for a number
of newspapers, including the Minneapolis Journal (1911–21) and the St. Louis Post-Dispatch
(1926–38), producing nearly 3,000 essays and
reviews. In 1912 Neihardt began work on his
five-volume epic Cycle of the West. The Cycle,
completed in 1941, recounts tales of American
explorers and fur traders of the trans-Missouri
country (The Song of Hugh Glass, 1915; The Song of the Three Friends, 1919; and The Song of Jedediah Smith, 1941) and of the Native peoples
dispossessed by those explorers and, later,
settlers (The Song of the Indian Wars, 1925; The Song of the Messiah, 1935). While researching
The Song of the Messiah, Neihardt met an
Oglala Lakota holy man, Black Elk, whose vision
he recorded in Black Elk Speaks (1932).

In 1921 Neihardt was named poet laureate
of Nebraska. From 1949 until 1966 he was poet
in residence and lecturer at the University of
Missouri. He was working on a second volume
of his autobiography when he died on
November 3, 1973, in Lincoln, Nebraska.

See also RELIGION: Black Elk, Nicholas.


Lori Utecht
John G. Neihardt Center




Aly, Lucile T. John G. Neihardt: A Critical Biography. Amsterdam:
Rodopi, 1977. Whitney, Blair. John G. Neihardt.
Boston: G. K. Hall, 1976.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>