<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ha.036</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Richardson, Bill (b. 1947)</field>
      <field name="author">Miller, John J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




RICHARDSON, BILL (b. 1947)

Bill Richardson is one of the most prominent
Hispanic politicians in the United States, serving
in the U.S. House of Representatives for
fourteen years as a New Mexico Democrat
and, during the Clinton administration, as
ambassador to the United Nations (1997.98)
and secretary of energy. He was elected governor
of New Mexico and took office January 1,
2003.

Richardson was born in Pasadena, California,
on November 15, 1947, to an American
father and a Mexican mother. He attended a
Massachusetts boarding school and then Tufts
University, graduating with a bachelor of arts
degree in 1970, after which he was drafted as a
pitcher by the Kansas City Athletics baseball
team (he quit the sport due to an injury).
Richardson arrived in Washington DC as a
low-level aide in Richard Nixon's State Department,
and he later worked on Capitol
Hill. His ambition was to run for public office,
and in 1978 he moved to New Mexico–a place
where he had no roots but where his Hispanic
background and Spanish-speaking abilities
helped him with voters. In 1980 he challenged
Republican congressman Manuel Lujan and
ran a strong race in a losing effort. Two years
later, reapportionment gave New Mexico an
extra House seat, and Richardson was elected
to it, representing the northern tier of the
state.

As a member of Congress, Richardson won
attention for negotiating hostage releases in
Iraq, Kashmir, North Korea, and elsewhere.
This led to his un appointment (where he
briefly became embroiled in the Monica Lewinsky
scandal for holding a job open for her in
late 1997). His promotion to energy secretary
in 1998 came at a troubled time, right before
explosive charges about Chinese espionage at
nuclear labs erupted. Although Richardson
essentially inherited the problem, he came under
sharp attack from Republicans and was
frequently criticized for his role in the Wen
Ho Lee affair. Soaring gas prices in 2000 also
tarnished his reputation. He was talked about
as a possible running mate for Al Gore in
2000, but these two controversies forced him
from serious contention.


John J. Miller
Washington DC





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>