<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.med.028</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Leader-Post (Regina)</field>
      <field name="author">McKenzie, Jim</field>
      <field name="text">

 




Leader-Post (Regina)

The Leader-Post is the only newspaper published
in Regina, Saskatchewan. It is typical of
the monopoly papers operated across Canada
by the nation's biggest chain, the Hollinger
organization, which owns not only the Leader-Post but also the Star-Phoenix in Saskatoon
and the province's two other dailies in Moose
Jaw and Prince Albert.

The L-P, as it is popularly known, was
started by Nicholas Flood Davin, a flamboyant
Irish lawyer, shortly after Regina was
founded in 1882. Davin's small weekly paper,
which he modestly called the Leader, reflected
its owner's feisty personality. Davin, a Conservative,
used the paper to propel himself into
Parliament, then sold out to Walter Scott, a
Liberal. Scott also used the Leader as a political
stepping stone and eventually became
Saskatchewan's first premier.

The Leader prospered and became a daily
when Regina's economy boomed at the beginning
of the twentieth century. After that, the
paper went through several owners. Meanwhile,
a competing paper, the Regina Daily Post, had started up. The Sifton family bought
them both in 1928 and amalgamated them,
enjoying a monopoly for the next seven decades
before selling out to the profit-hungry
Hollinger, which promptly fired a quarter of
the staff to cut costs.

During its peak under the Siftons, the
Leader-Post provided solid coverage of the city
and southern Saskatchewan. It maintained bureaus
in Moose Jaw, Swift Current, Yorkton,
Weyburn, and Estevan as well as Ottawa. During
those good years, from the 1950s to the
1970s, the L-P was the best source of news
between Winnipeg and Calgary.

But over the past quarter-century, competition
from television, declining reader interest,
and a gradual shift in policy toward putting
profit ahead of public service have combined
to reduce the L-P to a shadow of its former
self. It no longer holds a preeminent place in
the journalistic community, and the remaining
newsroom staffers have become so disgruntled
that they recently voted to form a
labor union.

Today's editions of the paper are filled with
wire copy, human-interest features, and other
easy-to-get material. The scaled-down newsroom
staff attends car accidents and news
conferences, but the paper offers little when it
comes to enterprise or investigative reporting.
An independent rival weekly recently failed,
so the L-P has no competition and no incentive
to improve.

News coverage is not the only thing that has
declined. The once-spirited paper has become
timid and bland. Today's editorial page comes
out in favor of responsible citizenship, good
government, and other banalities. The only
thing the Leader-Post regularly gets upset
about is the fate of the Saskatchewan Roughriders
football team, which the sports department
covers in the minutest detail.

The L-P is a big booster of the community,
taking part in promotional events and beating
the drum for good causes. The paper's appearance
is better than its content. Its pages
are well laid out, while reproduction of color
ads and photos is good, thanks to a highquality
press and a modern plant.

See also CITIES AND TOWNS: Regina, Saskatchewan.


Jim McKenzie
University of Regina





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>