<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.mus.006</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Brooks, Garth (b. 1962)</field>
      <field name="author">O'Meilia, Matt</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BROOKS, GARTH (b. 1962)


Garth Brooks, 1987


Country music superstar Troyal Garth Brooks
was born on February 7, 1962, in Tulsa, Oklahoma.
He is the youngest child of Troyal Raymond
and Colleen Carroll Brooks. He has one
older brother, Kelly, and four older half-siblings.
Soon after Brooks's birth, the Brooks
family moved to Yukon, Oklahoma, a small
town outside of Oklahoma City. Country music
was relatively important in Brooks's family
(his mother had a short stint as a singer for
Capitol Records in Nashville in the 1950s), but
his formative years did not indicate that he
was country music royalty in the making.

Growing up, he was more interested in athletics
than music. In grade school and high
school he played baseball, basketball, and
football and ran track. He was influenced by
the popular music of the 1970s: American
singer-songwriter types such as Jim Croce,
James Taylor, Don McLean, and Dan Fogelberg
and "arena-rock" bands such as Bob
Seger and the Silver Bullet Band, Kansas, KISS,
Journey, and Foreigner.

After graduating from Yukon High School
in 1980, Brooks went to Oklahoma State University
(OSU) in Stillwater, Oklahoma, on a
partial track scholarship (javelin throw). Like
most OSU freshmen, Brooks quickly discovered
that music and nightlife were a significant
part of Stillwater culture. Near campus,
on Washington Street, was a three-block row
of restaurants and bars known as the Strip
where local musicians performed nightly for
beer-guzzling students.

Inspired by the variety of music and the
skill of many of the musicians he met, Brooks
began to spend every moment of his free time
practicing the guitar–an instrument he'd
taken up, along with the banjo, in high school
–and singing and writing songs. He eventually
made his musical headquarters at Willie's,
a bar on the Strip that was saloonlike in
style but always hosted an eclectic audience.
Over time, Brooks developed a substantial repertoire
of different styles of music. Between
performing onstage and for the track team,
Brooks managed to earn a degree in advertising,
graduating in 1984.

In June 1987 Brooks and his band, Santa Fe,
moved to Nashville. The band broke up shortly
after the move, due to artistic differences. But
Brooks confidently presented himself to the
Nashville public, eventually catching the eye of
former ASCAP executive Bob Doyle. Doyle became
Brooks's manager and, less than a year
after Brooks had moved to Nashville, landed
his charismatic young charge a contract with
Capitol Records. In 1988 he released his first
album, simply entitled Garth Brooks. Less than
eight years later, he had become the biggest-selling
solo artist of all time, in the process
earning numerous music industry awards and
worldwide popularity.


Matt O'Meilia
Tulsa, Oklahoma




O'Meilia, Matt. Garth Brooks: The Road out of Santa Fe.
Oklahoma: University of Oklahoma Press, 1997.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>