<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.069</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Republican Party</field>
      <field name="author">Shelley, Fred M. Archer, J. Clark</field>
      <field name="text">

 




REPUBLICAN PARTY

The Republican Party has long been a major
political force within the Great Plains, just
as major issues involving the Great Plains
have long posed significant policy concerns
for Republican leaders at various governmental
levels, from local to national. Indeed, the
very origins of the Republican Party can be
traced to mid-nineteenth-century controversies
prompted by settlement and statehood
questions involving the Great Plains.

One of the most troublesome issues accompanying
the westward expansion of the American
frontier was the question of whether slavery
would be permitted or excluded in newly
settled areas. The Missouri Compromise of
1820 admitted Missouri as a slave state and
Maine as a free state, while also prohibiting
slavery from any future states to be formed
from remaining lands of the Louisiana Territory
north of 36º30% north latitude. The uneasy
balance was shattered by the Kansas-Nebraska Act of 1854, which partitioned off
these eventual states from the larger Louisiana
Territory and authorized residents of each of
the two newly organized territories to decide
for themselves whether to allow or disallow
slavery. "Bloody Kansas" conflicts soon broke
out between slaveholders and abolitionists.

Both the Democratic Party and the opposing
Whig Party comprised coalitions that included
advocates of both proslavery and antislavery
positions. In March 1854 antislavery
dissidents from these major parties met in
Ripon, Wisconsin, along with other abolitionists
who were just as outraged by congressional
debate leading to the Kansas-Nebraska
Act, and formed the Republican Party.

The newly formed party became a formidable
political force in the North and West almost
immediately. In the election of 1856 the
young Republican Party captured ninety seats
in the U.S. House of Representatives and
made a very credible run for the White House
by nominating Gen. John C. Frémont, a hero
of the Mexican War, as the party's presidential
candidate. Frémont's total of 1.3 million popular
votes easily bested the 870,000 votes received
by Whig candidate Millard Fillmore,
but it trailed Democratic candidate James
Buchanan's 1.8 million popular votes. Texas,
the only Great Plains state as yet formed, cast
its electoral votes for Buchanan, who won the
Electoral College ballot with 174 votes, compared
with 114 for Fremont, and just 8 for Fillmore.

The Republican juggernaut emerged from
the 1858 off-year elections with 116 out of 238
seats in the U.S. House of Representatives. Republicans
were just shy of an absolute majority
and could easily outvote the eighty-three
Democrats who comprised the next-largest
voting bloc in the lower house of the U.S.
Congress. But while all seats in the U.S. House
are decided at each two-year election cycle,
only one-third of Senate seats are decided at
one time. So Democrats still held a thirty-eight-to twenty-six-seat lead in the U.S. Senate
and could continue to block abolitionist
proposals, at least temporarily.

The impasse led to an electoral showdown
in 1860. As the outcomes of popular contests
for seats in the U.S. House and for seats in
state legislatures, which would in turn choose
new members of the U.S. Senate, began to become
known, it looked likely that Republicans
might gain effective majorities in both houses
of Congress. The presidential contest became
crucial, since a moderate or proslavery president
might be able to effectively veto abolitionist
measures. The Democratic coalition
had fractured into northern and southern
wings, each of which nominated candidates
for the presidency. The rival Constitutional
Union Party, which carried the banner for former
moderate or proslavery Whigs, also nominated
its own presidential candidate. The Republican
presidential nominee was Abraham
Lincoln of Illinois. More than 1.8 million popular
votes were cast for Lincoln, compared
with 1.4 million for Northern Democrat Stephen
A. Douglas, 850,000 for Southern Democrat
John C. Breckinridge, and 591,000 for
Constitutional Union candidate John Bell.
This gave Lincoln a nearly 40 percent plurality
of the popular vote. More importantly, Lincoln's
180 out of 303 electoral votes were more
than the absolute majority needed to settle the
presidential contest.

Bullets soon followed ballots. Secessionist
Southern states broke with the federal Union
to form their own rival Confederate States of
America. The Civil War began on April 12,
1861, when Confederate forces fired on the
Union's Fort Sumter. The stronger Union
eventually prevailed in four years of savage
warfare, but at the cost of nearly 650,000
Union casualties, compared to about 134,000
Confederate casualties. Most of the major battles
were fought on Southern soil, so wartime
destruction and financial losses from the
emancipation of slaves devastated the plantation
economy of the South, including that of
the Plains state of Texas.

Southern secession and the outcome of the
Civil War were of major importance to the
Great Plains. Beforehand, the rivalry over
slavery had compounded many of the practical
difficulties of settling the region. For example,
congressional efforts to authorize the
building of a transcontinental railroad were
stymied on several occasions by Southerners,
who were adamantly opposed to northern
routes, or by Northerners, who were equally
adamantly opposed to southern routes. The
act that finally authorized construction of
the Union Pacific Railroad, from Omaha, Nebraska,
to Sacramento, California, was passed
in 1862, when there were no Southern voices
in the halls of the U.S. Congress. Subsequently,
railroads served as crucial transport
links between Great Plains farms and ranches
and the distant markets for their products.

Another important measure passed by
mainly Republican proponents in the absence of
Southern opposition was the Homestead Act of
1862, which laid the foundation for successive
post–Civil War waves of settlement expansion
across the Great Plains. The Homestead Act encouraged
immigration by providing free government
land to settlers who were willing to live
upon and improve their properties. After the
war, thousands of Union veterans joined
many other settlers from the eastern United
States and many other countries in obtaining
free homestead land throughout the Central
and Northern Plains. The Homestead Act specifically
forbade Confederate veterans who
had taken up arms against the United States
from settling homestead lands. Because Union
veterans tended to be Republicans and Confederate
supporters tended to be Democrats,
this ban reinforced the strongly Republican
character of the Central and Northern Plains.

The Union Pacific Railroad Act, the Homestead
Act, and other related measures endeared
many of those who settled in the Great Plains
in the late nineteenth century to the candidates
of the "Grand Old Party" whose predecessors
had pushed those measures through Congress
at a time of great turmoil and opportunity. All
of the Northern Plains states grew rapidly in
population between 1865 and 1890, and by 1890
all had been admitted to the Union.

With increased population and settlement,
however, came increasing discontent. In the
East and the Great Lakes states, the Republican
movement of the 1850s had been based on
two key principles–abolition of slavery and
support for industrialization. The Civil War
settled the first question, and many Republican
leaders in the 1870s and 1880s were linked
increasingly with large industrial concerns.
However, Great Plains farmers found themselves
more and more at the mercy of easterndominated
railroads, banks, and corporations.
Many became disenchanted with the
conservatism of the Republican Party in the
East. By the 1890s the Populist movement,
which was oriented to the interests of the
small farmer against large corporate interests,
had taken hold and was especially strong in
the Plains. In 1896 William Jennings Bryan
of Nebraska won the presidential nomination
of both the Democrats and the Populists. Although
he carried all of the Plains states except
North Dakota, Bryan was defeated nationally
by Republican William McKinley, and
he lost again in 1900 and 1908.

Despite the fact that Bryan's three defeats
signaled the end of the Populist movement
nationally, populism continued to have considerable
impact on the politics of the Plains
states. Populist-oriented political factions contested
statewide and local elections throughout
the Central and Northern Plains. For example,
the Nonpartisan League emerged as a major
force in North Dakota politics before World
War I, and it remained important until the
1950s. Throughout the twentieth century, politics
in the Central and Northern Plains has
generally been dominated by the Republicans,
with Democrats making occasional inroads. In
the Southern Plains the Democrats were the
dominant party until the 1960s, when Republican
influence began to increase.

This trend is illustrated in the distribution
of governorships across the two parties in the
two regions of the Plains. Republicans held 60
percent of the governorships of the Central
and Northern Plains states (North Dakota,
South Dakota, Nebraska, Kansas, Montana,
Wyoming, and Colorado) between 1900 and
1950, and 55 percent between 1950 and 2000.
In the Southern Plains states of Texas, Oklahoma,
and New Mexico, Republicans held
only 9 percent of the governorships between
1900 and 1950 but 35 percent between 1950 and
2000. Similarly, Republicans held 67 percent
of Central and Northern Plains House seats in
1900, 81 percent in 1950, and 81 percent again
in 2000, while they held no seats in the Southern
Plains in 1900, 6 percent in 1950, and 52
percent in 2000.

The Plains has produced many Republican
leaders who have held national prominence
throughout the past century. Some were
strongly influenced by the progressive sentiments
of the populist movement, while others
have been more conservative. Several Plains
politicians have been nominated by the Republican
Party for national office. Interestingly,
most have had connections to Kansas.
In 1928 Republican Charles Curtis of Kansas
was elected vice president, but he and his running
mate, Herbert Hoover, were defeated in
their reelection bid four years later by Franklin
D. Roosevelt and his running mate, Texan
John Nance Garner. In 1936 the Republicans
nominated Gov. Alfred Landon of Kansas,
who ran unsuccessfully against Roosevelt.
Dwight D. Eisenhower, born in Denison,
Texas, and raised in Abilene, Kansas, was elected
president in 1952 and 1956. Sen. Robert
Dole, who represented Kansas in the Senate
for nearly twenty-eight years, was the unsuccessful
Republican nominee for vice president
in 1976 and for president in 1996. In 2000 two
candidates with Great Plains connections–
though not to Kansas–were nominated and
elected under the Republican Party label.
Thus, the first presidential contest of the
twenty-first century was won by Gov. George
W. Bush of Texas and his vice presidential
running mate, former Wyoming U.S. representative
Richard Cheney, whose birthplace
was Lincoln, Nebraska.

No Plains Republican served as Speaker of
the House of Representatives in the twentieth
century. Two Republicans have served as their
party's leader in the Senate: Kenneth Wherry
of Nebraska was minority leader from 1949 to
1951, while Dole was majority leader from 1985
to 1987 and again from 1995 to 1996 and minority
leader from 1987 to 1995. Many other
Plains Republicans, however, have achieved
notable records in Congress. George Norris of
Nebraska served thirty-six years in the Senate
and was recognized as one of the Senate's leading
progressive Republicans throughout his
career. Among his many legislative achievements
was sponsorship of the bill creating the
Tennessee Valley Authority during the New
Deal era. Peter Norbeck of South Dakota was
a strong supporter of progressive legislation as
governor and senator, and his progressive attitudes
forestalled the creation of an independent
progressive movement in that state. Alan
Simpson of Wyoming was prominent in his
party's leadership in the 1980s and 1990s,
and Henry Bellmon of Oklahoma served two
terms in the Senate and two as governor.
Among the more conservative long-time Republican
members of the Senate were South
Dakota's Karl Mundt and Nebraska's Roman
Hruska and Carl Curtis.


Fred M. Shelley
Southwest Texas State University
J. Clark Archer
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Martis, Kenneth C. The Historical Atlas of Political Parties
in the United States Congress, 1789–1989. New York: Macmillan
Publishing Company, 1989. Shelley, Fred M., J.
Clark Archer, Fiona M. Davidson, and Stanley D. Brunn.
Political Geography of the United States. New York: Guilford
Press, 1996. Witkoski, Michael. "The Republican
Party." In International Encyclopedia of Government and
Politics, edited by Frank N. Magill. Chicago: Salem Press,
1996: 1167–71.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>