<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.art.002</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Adams, Robert (b. 1937)</field>
      <field name="author">Huibregtse, Gary</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ADAMS, ROBERT (b. 1937)

For more than thirty years Robert Adams has
made photographs that describe the beauty of
the land as well as the inexorable impact of
human activity upon it. His earlier photographs,
as seen in the monographs Denver: A Photographic Survey of the Metropolitan Area
(1977) and From the Missouri West (1980), have
been described as bleak and forlorn. They address
the manifestations of unchecked growth:
tract housing, strip malls, storage buildings,
construction sites, and scarred land. Later
work, as found in Perfect Times, Perfect Places
(1988) and Listening to the River (1994), is perhaps
more celebratory of the space and vistas
of the High Plains, with attention given to
the unifying element that graces all his work:
the enduring beauty and revelatory quality of
light.

Born in Orange, New Jersey, on May 8, 1937,
Robert Adams moved with his family to Colorado
in 1952. He lived in the Denver area until
leaving for college in California, where he
eventually earned a doctorate in English.
Adams returned to Colorado in 1962 to accept
a teaching position at Colorado College in
Colorado Springs. Dismayed by the increasing
destruction of familiar territory, he began
photographing as a way to express both
outrage and hope. He was sufficiently encouraged
by the support of John Szarkowski at the
Museum of Modern Art and increasing acceptance
of his work to leave the teaching profession
and devote his energies to his photographic
endeavors. His work has been widely
exhibited and was included in New Topographics: Photographs of a Man-Altered Landscape,
a major exhibition held at the George
Eastman House in 1975. With twenty-two
publications of writing and imagery, Robert
Adams continues to be a major influence in
contemporary photography as well as on our
thinking toward the land we occupy.


Gary Huibregtse
Colorado State University




Adams, Robert. To Make It Home: Photographs of the American West. New York: Aperture, 1989. Adams, Robert.
What We Bought: The New World. Hanover, Germany:
Spectrum-Internationaler Pries für Fotografie der Stiftung
Niedersachsen, 1995. Green, Jonathan. American Photography.
New York: Harry N. Abrams, 1995.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>