<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.law.010</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Brownell, Herbert, Jr. (1904-1996)</field>
      <field name="author">Ellis, Mark R.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BROWNELL, HERBERT, JR. (1904-1996)

Herbert Brownell Jr., attorney general under
President Dwight Eisenhower from 1953–57,
was born on February 20, 1904, in Peru, Nebraska.
Brownell grew up in southeastern Nebraska
and earned a bachelor's degree from
the University of Nebraska in 1924. He left the
Great Plains to attend law school at Yale University.
Graduating in 1927, he was admitted to
the bar in 1928 and immediately began practicing
law in New York City, eventually entering
the prestigious law firm of Lord, Day and
Lord. Brownell also became involved in New
York politics early in his career. At the age
of twenty-eight he was elected to the New
York assembly, representing Manhattan from
1933 to 1937. From 1938 to 1948 he managed
Thomas Dewey's gubernatorial and presidential
campaigns, and he briefly served as the
chairman of the Republican National Committee
(1944–45). During the 1952 presidential
campaign, Brownell worked closely
with Eisenhower, advising him on convention
strategy and the selection of Richard Nixon as
vice president. As a reward, President-elect
Eisenhower nominated Brownell attorney
general.

Brownell's work in the Justice Department
revolved around two themes: anti-Communism
and civil rights. As a staunch anti-Communist,
Brownell resurrected spy cases and accused the
Truman administration of being soft on Communism.
He also protested a stay of execution
for Julius and Ethel Rosenberg, targeted leftwing
organizations, attacked labor unions,
and proposed to Congress an array of anti-
Communist legislation.

At the same time, however, Brownell, more
than any other Eisenhower cabinet member,
worked to further civil rights. It was Brownell's
recommendation, for example, that led to the
appointment of Earl Warren to the Supreme
Court. Brownell also supported the Supreme
Court's decision in Brown v. The Board of Education
of Topeka. Brownell worked hard to
push the Civil Rights Act of 1957 through Congress,
which established a Civil Rights Commission
and created the Civil Rights Division
in the Justice Department. One of his most
important accomplishments was advising Eisenhower
to intervene and forcefully integrate
Central High School in Little Rock, Arkansas.

Brownell resigned as attorney general in
October 1957 and returned to private practice
in New York City. He and his wife, Doris Mc-
Carter, whom he had married on June 16,
1934, in New York City, had four children.
Herbert Brownell died on May 1, 1996.

See also POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT: Eisenhower, Dwight D.


Mark R. Ellis
University of Nebraska at Kearney




Brownell, Herbert, Jr., with John P. Burke. Advising Ike: The Memoirs of Attorney-General Herbert Brownell. Lawrence:
University Press of Kansas, 1993. U.S. Department
of Justice. The Attorney Generals of the United States, 1789-1985. Washington DC: Government Printing Office, 1985.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>