<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.na.095</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Repatriation</field>
      <field name="author">Zimmerman, Larry J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




REPATRIATION

Since the 1970s Native Americans have sought
the repatriation of their ancestors' skeletal remains,
burial goods, and sacred objects from
museums and laboratories. Part of a worldwide
Indigenous movement, Native Americans
contend that these institutions acquired
and retained the remains and objects in violation
of the rights of the dead, the tribe, and
the sacred. In response, some scholars maintain
that the remains provide an important
scientific and educational resource and that
treatment of the materials has been respectful.

The entire repatriation movement may
have started on the fringe of the Great Plains
in 1971. An Ihanktonwan (Yankton Sioux)
woman, Maria Pearson, protested the differential
treatment of Native American remains
buried at the edge of a non-Indian, pioneer
cemetery near Glenwood, Iowa, that
was to be relocated for highway construction.
While the non-Indian remains were immediately
reburied, the Native remains were
taken to the state archeologist's office for
study. A court order, Governor Robert Ray's
intervention, and substantial media coverage
eventually allowed the remains to be reburied.

The case prompted attention by the American
Indian Movement (AIM) and the International
Indian Treaty Council, which took action
against archeologists and their excavations in
several locations. Digs in Minnesota and Iowa
were disrupted by aim members. However,
other pressing matters, such as the takeover at
Alcatraz and Wounded Knee, had turned the
attention of aim elsewhere.

In 1978 the discovery of the massacred remains
of nearly 500 individuals from the prehistoric
Crow Creek Village along the Missouri
River in South Dakota drew international attention
when archeologists and the Army
Corps of Engineers–Omaha District agreed to
rebury the remains after study. After the remains
were reburied in 1981, many archeologists
and human osteologists were critical
of the agreement, contending that new techniques
would have allowed substantially more
information to be gleaned from the remains if
they had been curated for eventual restudy.

In 1982 the International Indian Treaty Council
again turned its attention to repatriation.
One of its members, Jan Hammil, determined
that organizations, with the Smithsonian Institution
as the primary example, should be
pressured to return remains for reburial. She
also pressured the Society for American Archaeology,
the primary organization of professional
archeologists in the United States, not to pass a
resolution against repatriation. This struggle
continued until passage of major federal repatriation
laws in 1989 and 1990.

During this time, several states debated or
enacted laws dealing with repatriation. The
most controversial case in the Plains involved
the Pawnees' efforts to seek the return of skeletons
and grave goods curated in the Nebraska
State Historical Society (NSHS). In 1988 Lawrence
Goodfox Jr. of the Pawnee Tribe of Oklahoma
issued several requests to the NSHS for
the repatriation of remains and burial offerings
long held by the society. NSHS executive
director James Hanson refused to respond to
the tribe's request, and a long, nationally visible
battle ensued. The Pawnees joined forces
with other Nebraska tribes and the Native
American Rights Fund to seek legislative relief
that would force the NSHS to repatriate the
remains. In 1989 the coalition eventually saw
passage in the Nebraska legislature of the Unmarked
Human Burial Sites and Skeletal Remains
Protection Act (LB-340). The law required
Nebraska public museums to return all
tribally identifiable skeletal remains and burial
offerings to tribes that requested them for reburial.

Reburial opponents, led by the NSHS, campaigned
to derail the legislation. Even after
enactment, the NSHS opposed return of remains
from the more distant past, in which
determining tribal affiliation is often difficult.
Eventually, agreements between tribes and the
NSHS allowed the return of many more remains
than had been originally sought.

While the Pawnees' campaign was going on,
the Omahas were working with Harvard University's
Peabody Museum to seek the return of
Umon'hon'ti, their sacred pole. In 1888, under
pressure to abandon their beliefs and accept
Christianity, the Omaha tribe had turned
Umon'hon'ti and other sacred objects, including
the ceremonial war pipes and the sacred
shell, over to ethnographer Alice Fletcher for
safekeeping. Fletcher transferred them to the
Peabody Museum. After an extraordinary
effort on the part of the Omahas to reclaim
their objects, the Peabody returned the pole
in 1989 and has since returned other sacred
objects.

In 1989 the World Archaeological Congress
met at the University of South Dakota for a
forum entitled "Archeological Ethics and the
Treatment of the Dead." Archeologists and Indigenous
people from twenty countries and
twenty-seven Native American nations debated
the repatriation issue, eventually passing
the Vermillion Accord. This accord influenced
the passage of several provincial laws in
Canada and ethics codes for both the World
Archaeological Congress and the Australian
Archaeological Association.

In 1989 and 1990, after lengthy negotiations
between the Native American Rights Fund,
the National Congress of American Indians,
the Society for American Archaeology, and
other interested parties, the U.S. Congress
passed two important federal laws. Targeting
the Smithsonian, the National Museum of the
American Indian Act (Public Law 101-185) required
that the Smithsonian inventory its collection
of skeletal remains so that tribes could
claim them for repatriation. The Smithsonian
has since returned human remains to Plains
tribes, including the Pawnees, Cheyennes, and
Wahpeton Sioux. In 1990 the Native American
Graves Protection and Repatriation Act (Public
Law 101-601) extended the earlier law to all
federal agencies or institutions with any level
of federal involvement. The act requires return
of human remains, grave goods, and
items of cultural patrimony. It also demands
consultation with tribes and requires that a
broader range of information, such as oral
tradition, be considered when documenting
cultural a.liation of remains. After several
years of drafting operative regulations, the law
has generally worked, although details remain
to be worked out. Demonstrations of cultural
affiliation have proved contentious for remains
from the distant past, and another key
issue is the treatment of remains found on
private land.

See also LAW: Native American Rights Fund
/ PROTEST AND DISSENT: American Indian Movement.


Larry J. Zimmerman
University of Iowa



Echo-Hawk, Walter, ed. Special Edition: Repatriation of
American Indian Remains. American Indian Culture and
Research Journal 16 (1992). Echo-Hawk, Walter, and Roger
Echo-Hawk. Battlefields and Burial Grounds: The Indian
Struggle to Protect Ancestral Graves in the United States.
Minneapolis: Lerner Publications Company, 1994. Ridington,
Robin, and Dennis Hastings. Blessing for a Long Time:
The Sacred Pole of the Omaha Tribe. Lincoln: University of
Nebraska Press, 1997.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>