<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ag.003</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Agricultural Adjustment Administration</field>
      <field name="author">Marten, James</field>
      <field name="text">

 




AGRICULTURAL ADJUSTMENT ADMINISTRATION

A decade-long agricultural depression sparked
by plunging crop and livestock prices inspired
President Franklin D. Roosevelt and New Deal
reformers in 1933 to implement the Agricultural
Adjustment Administration, the first
federal program to limit agricultural production.
The dramatic expansion of exports
during World War I–beef exports increased
more than 100 percent, wheat exports more
than doubled, and oats exports soared more
than 2,400 percent–led to record prices and
the cultivation of millions of acres of previously
unused land. With peace and the recovery
of European agriculture, demand and
prices dropped quickly: corn fell from $1.20
per bushel in 1917 to 26 cents in 1921, while
wheat, hogs, and cattle fell to prewar averages.
At the same time, the earning power of the
nation's farmers declined, land prices plummeted,
and thousands of Great Plains banks
failed.

The generally booming national economy
made it easy to ignore the farmers' plight, but
when the stock market crash of 1929 sparked
the Great Depression, the Democratic administration
elected in 1932 turned its attention to
agriculture, passing the Agricultural Adjustment
Act (AAA) during the frantic "100 Days."
The bill drew on earlier attempts to help farmers
achieve parity, a complex formula in which
the prices farmers earned for their products
would fluctuate depending on the prices of
goods they bought, with the years 1909–14
considered "normal." Previous attempts, such
as the McNary-Haugen Bill, had proven politically
untenable, but the mounting crisis in
agriculture forced Roosevelt to take the dramatic
step of involving, for the first time, the
federal government directly in the economic
decisions made by farmers. The aaa initially
paid farmers to reduce production of seven
major commodities–including corn, cotton,
and wheat–and later added eight more, including
cattle. Administered by county extension
agents and farmers committees, the program
was paid for by a tax on processors of
agricultural products.

Farmers welcomed the government checks
that helped them survive the drought and
grasshoppers plaguing the Great Plains in the
1930s; in some areas, 80 to 90 percent of the
population relied on federal relief. Of particular
value to Plains farmers were the massive
livestock-buying programs of the mid-1930s.
Responding to the unprecedented drought
and dust storms of 1934 and 1935, the government
purchased seven million cattle, sending
them to greener pastures or slaughtering and
distributing them to needy families through
other federal agencies. Despite the popularity
of these government payouts, rising food
prices, payments that tended to favor landlords
over tenants, and the failure of the aaa
to raise prices to anything actually approaching
parity limited the overall success of the
program.

The Supreme Court ruled the AAA unconstitutional
in United States v. Butler (1936),
but Congress quickly replaced it with the Soil
Conservation and Domestic Allotment Act
and with a second Agricultural Adjustment
Act in 1938. The AAA and its successors continued
to focus primarily on commercial producers,
sustained the policies of acreage limitation
and price supports in the form of
government loans, and helped convert marginal
croplands to grass and forage for livestock.
This massive government involvement
in the economic lives of Great Plains farmers
is the most prominent legacy of the AAA.

See also POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT: New Deal.


James Marten
Marquette University




Danbom, David B. Born in the Country: A History of Rural
America. Baltimore MD: Johns Hopkins University Press,
1995. Lowitt, Richard. The New Deal and the West. Bloomington:
Indiana University Press, 1984. Perkins, Van L. Crisis
in Agriculture: The Agricultural Adjustment Administration
and the New Deal, 1933. Berkeley: University of
California Press, 1969.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>