<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.asam.001</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Asian Americans</field>
      <field name="author"/>
      <field name="text">

 




ASIAN AMERICANS

In 1870 the first "Chinaman" set foot on the
streets of Denver, Colorado. A local paper described
him as "short, fat, round-faced,
almond-eyed beauty," and added that he "appeared
quite happy to get among civilized people."
Despite this kind of ridicule, the Chinese
of Denver soon became an essential element in
the city's urban economy. They provided domestic
services to a primarily male population
for an affordable price, services that had
not been available before the Chinese arrival.
From that time on, the Asian presence in Denver
and in many other parts of the Great Plains
has been a permanent fixture.

But if one were to open a Denver history
book, or any history book about the Great
Plains for that matter, one would be hardpressed
to find more than one or two pages
written on Asians. This marginalization from
the pages of history is a clear injustice to
a people who have been fundamental to the
development of the region. From the late-nineteenth-century Chinese, who did the
vast majority of the region's laundry, to the
present-day Southeast Asians who have revitalized
city neighborhoods and provided a
workforce for the region's meatpacking industry,
Asians have made and continue to
make vital contributions to the prosperity and
growth of the Great Plains.


Chinese Pioneers

The Chinese were the first Asian immigrant
group to reach the region. Settling originally
in the California goldfields, they began moving
eastward in the 1860s following railroad
construction and mining opportunities. From
California they moved to Nevada, Montana,
Wyoming, and then Colorado. Although the
first Chinese came to the Western Plains to
work on the railroads and in the mines, the
vast majority who followed these pioneers
came to fill the empty economic niche in
laundry work and other domestic services, a
necessity in the rough-and-tumble, predominantly
male frontier towns. By 1880, for example,
Denver had a thriving Chinese community
of 238, of whom more than 80 percent
worked as laundrymen. In other towns such
as Deadwood, South Dakota, Chinese opened
restaurants, general provision stores, and
opium dens. The Plains' Chinese population
gradually began to move farther east, providing
similar urban services along the way. By
1890 there were 224 Chinese in Nebraska, and
by 1920, 261 had settled in Oklahoma.

Chinese also migrated to the Prairie Provinces
of Canada. The majority settled in large
cities such as Edmonton and Calgary, Alberta,
while others settled in smaller urban communities
such as Lethbridge and Medicine Hat,
Alberta. Many were brought in by American
contractors (especially the Minnesota firm of
Langdon and Shepard) to lay the tracks of the
Canadian Pacific Railway in the years 1881 to
1883. Many of the laborers were recruited directly
from the United States, and some returned
to the United States after the contract
ended. After 1883 the Canadian Pacific
Railway recruited directly from Canton and
Hong Kong, as well as from Vancouver. By
1900 Calgary had become home to approximately
eighty Chinese who worked as laborers,
cooks, and domestic servants.

Despite being invaluable to the Great Plains
urban economy, the Chinese were still subject
to discrimination. White workers blamed
Chinese for the slow economy and resented
Chinese competition, particularly in the mining
industry. Politicians stoked this volatile issue
in order to gain the labor vote. As a result,
towns often practiced discriminatory taxation
and passed economic sanctions against the
Chinese.

There were times when these discriminatory
measures did not satisfy a town's populace
and violence ensued. On Sunday, October
31, 1880, for example, a group of several hundred
white males incited an anti-Chinese riot
that resulted in the death of one laundryman
and the destruction of Denver's Hop Alley.
The immediate cause was a bar fight between
two Chinese and two whites, but the underlying
cause was the anti-Chinese agitation of
the local Democratic Party and labor organizations.
A similar incident occurred in Calgary.
On August 2, 1892, a mob of more than
300 destroyed Chinese laundries after learning
that four Chinese who had been quarantined
for smallpox had been released. In both cases,
authorities were exceedingly slow to react.

The best-known and bloodiest action
against the Chinese in, or near, the Great
Plains occurred in September of 1885 in Rock
Springs, Wyoming. A few months earlier, the
Union Pacific Coal Division had brought in
about 300 Chinese to work in the local mines,
an action that infuriated local white workers.
On September 2, two white miners found that
the seam to which they had been assigned was
already being tapped by two Chinese miners.
The enraged miners proceeded to rally other
white miners, and by early afternoon a mob
of 150 moved on Rock Springs' Chinatown,
slaughtering residents at every opportunity.
At day's end, twenty-six Chinese were dead
and fifteen others were wounded. Government
troops eventually restored order and
helped company officials to reinstate Chinese
in the mines. To this day, the Rock Springs
massacre stands as one of the most brutal
manifestations of American opposition to the
Chinese presence.

The Chinese were not always passive in the
face of such oppression. They used the legal
system as a means of resistance and sometimes
even won their cases. In 1882, for example,
local authorities accused Yee Shun of murdering
a fellow Chinese in Las Vegas, New Mexico.
Although the court eventually found Yee
Shun guilty, the defense team achieved a legal
victory of immense proportions for all Chinese
in America. They were able to overturn a
prior ruling prohibiting Chinese from testifying
in court.

Another legal victory for the Chinese occurred
in Regina, Saskatchewan, in 1907. On
the morning of August 8, nine patrons of the
Capital Restaurant became ill after eating porridge. Local authorities soon discovered that
Charlie Mack, the Chinese cook of a competing
restaurant, had poisoned the porridge.
Mack disappeared before he could be arrested,
causing the local authorities to detain the entire
male Chinese population of Regina in
an effort to extract information concerning
his whereabouts. The Chinese, encouraged by
their lawyers, prosecuted the local officials.
They won their case, received a small indemnity,
and had the satisfaction of seeing Regina's
police chief removed from office.

By 1890 the Chinese population in the Great
Plains had peaked. Every state, territory, and
province in the region had Chinese residents.
Soon afterward, however, this population began
to decline, especially in Colorado, Wyoming,
and Montana, the states where the
largest settlements had been concentrated.
The decline followed a national trend that had
begun with the 1882 Chinese Exclusion Act
and continued in the early twentieth century
with the passage of the 1902 Chinese Exclusion
Act, a congressional bill that made permanent
the 1882 act. Because most Chinese in the
United States, including the Great Plains,
were male, and because immigration had been
banned, there was little natural population
growth. Under the circumstances, community
roots never had a chance to take hold, and they
withered quickly after 1902. Similarly, Canada
imposed restrictions on Chinese immigration
in 1903 and 1923. The legislation virtually
halted Chinese immigration until 1947, when
it was repealed.



Japanese: From Farms to Internment

With the decline in the Chinese population,
industrialists and growers needed a new
source of cheap labor. They turned to newly
arrived Japanese immigrants. Between 1880
and 1900, yearly Japanese immigration to the
United States increased from 148 to 24,326. Although
most Japanese settled in Hawaii and
California, a good number moved to the Great
Plains. Like the Chinese before them, the Japanese
followed rail, mining, and agricultural
work to Montana, Wyoming, and Colorado.
By 1910 Japanese migrants also began moving
to Nebraska and Kansas to pursue sugar beet
work and to coastal Texas to cultivate rice.

One immigrant, Naokichi Hokazano, was
particularly instrumental in bringing Japanese
to the Plains. Arriving in Denver in 1898,
Hokazano promptly contracted seventy Japanese
to harvest 1,200 acres of sugar beets that
he owned. Hokazano has been criticized by
Asian American historians for exploiting the
labor of his countrymen by paying them substandard
wages. Nevertheless, he was responsible,
at least in part, for the increase in Japanese
migration from the West Coast to the
Great Plains. By 1909, of the 3,500 Japanese in
Colorado, almost 2,000 were connected to the
sugar beet industry.

Within twenty years, through skill, enterprise,
and hard work, several of these immigrants
became successful landowners and
farmers, a pattern of upward mobility first
seen in California. The Japanese in this economic sector were so successful that many
competing white farmers gave up, leaving the
industry open to further Japanese control.
These pioneers of Colorado agriculture irrigated,
and thus made arable, much of the land
in the northeast corner of the state. Today,
they are honored in the state capitol building,
where Naokichi Hokazano is memorialized in
a stained-glass window.

Japanese also started urban businesses and
organized civic institutions. By 1916 they
owned sixty-seven stores in Denver and had
founded the Japanese Methodist Church and
the Denver Buddhist Church. In Scottsbluff,
hub of Nebraska's sugar beet industry, Japanese
settlers started the Japanese-language
newspaper Neshyu Jibo (Nebraska News) and
founded the Japanese Association of Nebraska.
In Texas, Japanese dominated the nursery
industry.

Like the Chinese before them, Japanese also
settled in the Prairie Provinces of Canada,
moving into southern Alberta shortly after the
turn of the century. They migrated mainly
from British Columbia and the United States.
As in the United States, they worked in the
mines, on railways, and in agriculture and
were quite often recruited by labor supply
companies. In 1907 the Canadian Nippon
Supply Company recruited a large group of
Japanese to work in the mines near Lethbridge,
Alberta. The following year, Nippon
Supply sent 300 more workers to the Lethbridge
mines. Unfair treatment by their employers
and by fellow countrymen working
for labor supply companies prompted Japanese
laborers to organize labor unions soon
after their arrival in the Prairie Provinces. It
was not until the 1920s, however, that Japanese
workers were accepted as equals, with equal
pay, to white workers.

As in the American Great Plains, Japanese
in the Prairie Provinces made their greatest
contribution in agriculture. In 1907 the Canadian
Pacific Railway recruited 370 Japanese
workers through the Nippon Supply Company
to build irrigation ditches. The Raymond
Knight Sugar Company recruited 100
Japanese workers in 1908 and another 105 in
1909. The workers remained wage laborers for
only a few years, however, as they soon began
to lease and, on occasion, buy their own tracts
of land. These successful Japanese pioneers
eventually established permanent communities
with their own newspapers, churches and
temples, and social organizations.

Their success in farming prompted a more
virulent racism. In the early 1920s, following
the example of California, the states of Montana,
Wyoming, Nebraska, and Texas passed
legislation barring Japanese from owning or
leasing land. Colorado was the only Plains
state with a significant Japanese population
that did not pass an alien land law. This was
one reason why more Japanese moved to Colorado
than elsewhere in the Great Plains, and
why Japanese Coloradans were so successful
in agriculture.

The worst act of discrimination perpetrated
against Japanese Americans–an act
that did not bring an o.cial apology from the
United States until August 10, 1988–came
during World War II. On February 19, 1942,
President Franklin Delano Roosevelt signed
Executive Order 9066 allowing for the internment
of all Japanese within a designated
militarized zone. While this zone was located
primarily on the West Coast, "suspected" Japanese
community leaders throughout the nation
were also interned, including those in
the Plains.

Rev. Hiram Hisanori Kano of Nebraska, for
instance, was arrested on the day of the Pearl
Harbor attack. He was held in a Santa Fe, New
Mexico, internment camp until 1944. Kano
and other community leaders were imprisoned
merely on suspicion of disloyalty. Elsewhere
in the Great Plains anti-Japanese hysteria
led to house searches by the FBI, often
carried out in a demeaning and destructive
manner.

The Plains was the site of one of the largest
internment camps in the United States, Granada,
Colorado (also called Amache). Heart
Mountain, Wyoming, another large camp, was
just to the west of the Plains. Several smaller
camps were also located in the region. At one
such camp in Lordsburg, New Mexico, in the
early morning of July 27, 1942, an army guard
shot and killed Hirota Isamura and Toshira
Kobata as they were being delivered for internment.
The guard insisted that Isamura and
Kobata were trying to escape, although several
eyewitness accounts maintained otherwise.
The guard went unpunished.

Meanwhile, as fellow Japanese Americans
were being imprisoned, young nisei (second-generation
Japanese Americans) served in the
American military with distinction. One of
them, Ben Kuroki of Hershey, Nebraska, came
home with a distinguished war record only to
find himself ostracized for being Japanese.
This discrimination led Kuroki to campaign
against the injustices of internment.

The long-overdue apology for internment
came only after a hard-fought redress effort
by Japanese Americans. Bill Hosokawa, a resident
of Denver and himself a veteran of internment,
was particularly instrumental in gaining
this apology. Hosokawa was interned at
Heart Mountain in Wyoming, where he published
the camp newspaper. After his release
Hosokawa became active in the Japanese
American Citizens League (JACL), the organization
primarily responsible for redress.
Hosokawa also became the Denver Post's first
foreign correspondent, and he covered the
Korean War in this capacity. Later in his career
he became the Post's Sunday magazine editor
and then the assistant managing editor. His
career as a journalist made him JACL's selection
to write a history of second-generation
Japanese Americans called Nisei: The Quiet Americans (1969).

Hosokawa and the JACL are at the center of a
five-decade-old controversy that has divided
the Japanese American community. During
the months preceding internment, the JACL
took the stance that cooperation with the government's
internment plans was a necessary
evil that Japanese Americans would have to
endure in order to demonstrate their loyalty.
This stance has not been popular with the
more militant members of the Japanese American
population who argue that it was in essence
a sellout. This controversy continues
to this day and has been fervently taken up
by third-generation Japanese Americans, the
sansei.

Japanese Canadians were also persecuted
during World War II, and again the Great
Plains, securely in the heart of the country,
was the setting for their forced relocation. In
1942, 20,881 Japanese, 75 percent of them Canadian
citizens, were taken from their homes
and moved to detention camps in the interior
of British Columbia and to sugar beet farms in
Manitoba and Alberta. Many of the relocated
Japanese Canadians worked for individual
farmers, but others were gathered into huge
"prisoner of war" camps at Lethbridge and
Medicine Hat. The Canadian government
sold off their assets–farms, homes, fishing
boats–and used the proceeds to finance the
internment. At the end of the war, Japanese
Canadians were given the choice of either returning
to a devastated Japan or moving permanently
to the Prairie Provinces or eastern
Canada. Most chose the latter option.

The discrimination did not end with the
war. In 1946 the Canadian government tried
to deport 10,000 Japanese Canadians, and
only an international outcry prevented this
infamy. Japanese Canadians did not regain
their status as Canadian citizens until 1949.



Late Twentieth-Century Developments

In 1965 the U.S. Congress passed an Immigration
Reform Act. By removing racially based
quotas, promoting family reunification as a
priority, and encouraging the immigration
of professionals, the act opened the way for
a great increase in Asian immigration to the
United States, including the Great Plains. As a
result the Plains has experienced a recent influx
of Filipinos, Koreans, Chinese, and South
Asians (Indians and Pakistanis). Each of these
ethnic groups has thriving communities in
major Plains cities. In 2000 the Denver metropolitan
area, for instance, had an Asian population
of approximately 63,000, Dallas–Fort
Worth had an Asian population of close to
195,480, and Oklahoma City had an Asian
population of almost 18,000. Chinese and
Koreans have played a significant role in reviving
small businesses in urban areas. Filipinos
have mainly entered the professional ranks.
And Indians, in addition to being both shopkeepers
and professionals, have built an occupational
specialty in the small-motel industry.
Chinese and Indians, in particular, are
well represented in higher education and the
high-technology industry.

Similar circumstances have resulted in a
significant increase in Asian numbers in the
Canadian Prairie Provinces. As of 1991 Alberta
was home to 71,635 Chinese, 16,310 Filipinos,
and 54,750 South Asians; Manitoba was home
to 11,145, 22,045, and 24,465, respectively; and
Saskatchewan was home to 7,550, 1,635, and
11,285, respectively. In recent years a large
number of Chinese left Hong Kong in anticipation
of the July 1997 takeover by the People's
Republic of China. Canadian immigration
policy encouraged the immigration of wealthy
Hong Kong investors by granting automatic
residency to any person investing $1 million
in the Canadian economy. Most Asians have
settled in urban areas, particularly Edmonton,
Calgary, and Lethbridge. The presence of the
Nikka Yuko Garden in Lethbridge, one of the
most authentic Japanese gardens in North
America, is visual evidence of the importance
of the Japanese presence in the Prairie
Provinces.

Also in the recent years, the Great Plains
has attracted large numbers of refugees from
Southeast Asia. Subsequent family reunification
has swelled their numbers. Having been
forced to flee their homelands due to war, several
million have made new homes in the
United States and Canada. They migrated in
two waves, one in 1975 and the other starting
in 1979 and continuing to the present. The
first wave consisted primarily of the highly educated
or professionals fleeing from Vietnam
and, in smaller numbers, from Cambodia. By
contrast, the 1979 wave consisted mostly of
farmers and rural dwellers from Vietnam,
Cambodia, and Laos. While U.S. relief agencies
intended to relocate these refugees to all
parts of the nation, the majority have gathered
in only a few states–California, Texas, Washington,
Oregon, and Minnesota. Thus, although
the Plains' Southeast Asian population
is relatively small, it is growing and certainly
an invaluable contributor to the region's social
and economic fabric.

In at least four Plains cities–Denver, Oklahoma
City, Tulsa, and Wichita–Southeast
Asians have formed communities with populations
of more than 1,000. These communities
have started to form civic organizations
that address the multiplicity of adjustment
problems faced by refugees. The Oklahoma
Vietnamese, for instance, formed the Vietnamese
American Association (VAA) in 1978.
To date the VAA has offered English classes and
job training, placement, and upgrading services.
The VAA has been so successful that the
federal government has used it as a model for
its national program.


Asian American population in the U.S. Great Plains as a percentage of total population, by county, in 2000


In Denver, Southeast Asians have also
formed community organizations. Led by a
first-wave refugee, Khan Penn, the Cambodian
community formed the Colorado Cambodian
Community (CCC) in 1976. The CCC
emphasizes the preservation and observation
of cultural traditions and revolves to a large
extent around the Buddhist temple. These
sorts of community activities also serve to
ease the adjustment of Cambodian refugees
although not in as concrete a manner as the
VAA in Oklahoma City.

Southeast Asians have noticeably affected
the demographic makeup of some Plains regions.
For example, more than 100 Laotians
settled in the small town of Tecumseh, Nebraska,
between 1982 and 1992. In the late
1990s they accounted for about 6 percent of
the town's population and more than 17 percent
of its schoolchildren. Refugees often
move to small towns like Tecumseh in order to
escape the more economically competitive environments
of large cities. In many instances
they are also recruited by local industries,
such as Tecumseh's Campbell Soup canning
factory. Garden City, Kansas, has seen similar
changes as more than 1,000 Vietnamese migrated
into the city, mainly to work in local
meatpacking companies.

Southeast Asian numbers in the Plains are
growing at a rapid rate. In Colorado, for instance,
7,210 Vietnamese, 1,320 Cambodians,
1,202 Hmong, and 1,996 Laotians were noted
in the 1990 census. More than 97 percent of
these groups lived in urban areas, particularly
in Denver. Similar situations can be found in
Nebraska although on a smaller scale. More
than 2,600 Southeast Asians lived in the state
in 1990, of whom 1,800 were Vietnamese. The
Vietnamese numbers grew to 6,364 by 2000.
In Colorado, according to the 2000 census,
Vietnamese were the second-largest Asian
ethnic group after Koreans. In Kansas the
Vietnamese population of 11,623 (2000) made
it the single largest Asian ethnic group. In
2000 the total Southeast Asian population in
Kansas numbered more than 15,000. A similar
demographic situation existed in Oklahoma.
There, the Vietnamese numbered 12,566 in
2000, with the total Southeast Asian population
amounting to more than 15,000.

The significant numbers of Southeast
Asians have not only revitalized the meatpacking
industry and other labor-intensive industries
in the Plains but have also reenergized
key segments of urban economies. In Denver,
for instance, the entrepreneurial drive of
Vietnamese refugees invigorated a slumping
Chinatown economy. They opened new restaurants
and groceries, an immigrant entrepreneurial
staple, and they own and operate
beauty parlors, nightclubs, coffee shops, and
jewelry stores, to name only a few enterprises.
Southeast Asians have also contributed significantly
to the success of Denver's high-tech
industry. A large number, if not a majority,
of assembly-line workers in this industry are
Southeast Asian.

Asian Americans have clearly played a significant
if not always acknowledged role in
the history of the American and Canadian
Great Plains. This role dates back to the time
of Chinese railroad construction workers and
miners and Japanese agricultural laborers. Today,
although Asian Americans constitute no
more than 5 percent of the population of any
Great Plains county, Asian Americans are essential
to the regional economy. Southeast
Asians are contributing to the growth of communities
that otherwise might be declining,
and in urban areas such as Denver, Colorado,
and Lethbridge, Alberta, Asian Americans are
contributing to the rejuvenation of the urban
economy. Asian Americans have been,
and will continue to be, integral actors in the
history of the Great Plains.



 

Malcolm Yeung
Evelyn Hu-DeHart
University of Colorado at Boulder



Barth, Gunther. Bitter Strength: A History of the Chinese in the United States, 1850-1870. Cambridge: Harvard University
Press, 1964. Culley, John J. "Trouble at the Lordsburg
Internment Camp." New Mexico Historical Review 60
(1985): 225-48. Daniels, Roger. Concentration Camps, North America: Japanese in the United States and Canada during World War II. Malabar FL: R. E. Krieger Publishing
Co., 1989. Fairbairn, Kenneth J., and Hafiza Khatun. "Residential
Segregation and the Intra-Urban Migration of
South Asians in Edmonton." Canadian Ethnic Studies 21
(1989): 45-64. Ichioka, Yuji. The Issei: The World of the First Generation Japanese, 1885-1924. New York: Free
Press, 1988. Iwaasa, David. "Canadian Japanese in Southern
Alberta: 1905 through 1945." In Two Monographs on Japanese Canadians, edited by Roger Daniels. New York:
Arno Press, 1978. Kano, Hiram Hisanori. A History of the Japanese in Nebraska, edited by Jean and Sheryll
Patterson-Black. Scottsbluff NE: Scottsbluff Public Library,
1984. Muzney, Charles C. The Vietnamese in Oklahoma City: A Study in Ethnic Change. New York: AMS Press,
Inc., 1989. Ralph, Martin G. Boy from Nebraska: The Story of Ben Kuroki. New York: Harper and Brothers Publishers,
1946. Sontag, Deborah. "New Immigrants Test Nation's
Heartland." New York Times, October 18, 1993. Storti,
Craig. Incident at Bitter Creek: The Story of the Rock Springs Chinese Massacre. Ames: Iowa State University
Press, 1991. Takaki, Ronald T. Strangers from a Different Shore: A History of Asian Americans. Boston: Little, Brown,
1989. Wortman, Roy. "Denver's Anti-Chinese Riot, 1880."
Colorado Magazine 42 (1965): 275-91. Wunder, John R.
"Law and the Chinese in Frontier Montana." Montana: The Magazine of Western History 30 (1980): 18-31.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>