<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ag.070</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Swine</field>
      <field name="author">Luce, William G.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SWINE

Great Plains states account for approximately
16 percent of U.S. swine production, with Nebraska,
Oklahoma, and Kansas in the top ten
producing states. Nebraska leads other Plains
states, but Oklahoma has seen the fastest increase
in production in recent years. In Canada,
the Prairie Provinces contribute almost
40 percent to national swine production.

Massive restructuring and technological
changes are taking place in the swine industry
in both countries. Production has moved indoors
to large confinement units with improved management, breeding, and nutrition
practices that have allowed more e.cient production.
This restructuring has resulted in
much larger hog operations but on fewer
farms in the Great Plains.

In the United States, there has been a tremendous
increase in corporate hog farms,
or private farms raising hogs on contract
for swine companies. These changes have
been particularly marked in Texas, Oklahoma,
Kansas, and Colorado. In Oklahoma, swine
companies own approximately 90 percent of
the hog population. By contrast, in Nebraska
most of the swine production is still dominated
by individual farmers, though this is
now changing.

Traditionally, hog production on the Plains
was based in diversified family farms, which
often used home-raised grain, primarily corn
or sorghum grain, for feed. These operations
were usually "farrow-to-finish." The sows
were bred and farrowed and the pigs fed to
market weight, currently 240 to 280 pounds.
Today many of the new swine facilities have
three sites. At one site, sows, usually 600
or more, are bred and farrowed. The pigs
are weaned at two to three weeks of age and
moved to another site called a nursery, where
they live in environmentally controlled housing
and are fed specially prepared starter diets
until they are nine to ten weeks of age and
weigh approximately 50 pounds. The third site
consists of buildings where the pigs are fed out
to market weight. The three-site production
facilities break up the disease cycle and allow
more specialized management and more efficient use of labor.

The future of the swine industry looks
promising in the Great Plains, but it will continue
to consolidate on fewer farms with more
intensive management systems. Corporate or
contract hog production will probably increase,
although the largest independent hog
operations will still be able to compete. Future
expansion will be slowed down or prevented
in some areas by opposition from localities
and environmental groups. Stricter local and
federal environmental regulations are also
being implemented.


William G. Luce
Oklahoma State University




Canadian Pork Council. Statistics Canada, Ottawa, 1997.
U.S. Department of Agriculture. Hog and Pig Report.
Washington DC, 1997.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>