<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.017</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Ellison, Ralph (1911-1994)</field>
      <field name="author">Patton, Venetria K.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ELLISON, RALPH (1911-1994)

Portrait photograph of Ralph Ellison


Ralph Waldo Ellison, best known as the author
of the award-winning novel Invisible Man (1952), was a "Renaissance man": sculptor,
editor, short-story writer, novelist, jazz
trumpeter, and photographer. He was born
March 1, 1914, in Oklahoma City, Oklahoma,
to Lewis Alfred Ellison and Ida Millsap Ellison.
The Ellisons had moved to Oklahoma in
1911 in hopes of finding more opportunities in
an area free of the severe racism of the Deep
South. When Ellison was born, Oklahoma
had only been a state for seven years, and it
retained its frontier spirit.

Oklahoma had a long history of racism, as
evidenced by its maintenance of segregated
schools. Ellison graduated in 1931 from the allblack
Douglas High School, where he received
a rigorous training in music. From 1933 to
1936 Ellison studied music at Tuskegee Institute
in Alabama. He played first trumpet in
the school orchestra as well as serving as the
orchestra's student director.

Ellison decided to spend the summer of
1936 in New York City in order to earn money
for the next academic year. He never returned
to school. While in New York, Ellison met
Langston Hughes and Richard Wright, who
encouraged him to write his first story, "Hymie's
Bull." He then began to write book reviews,
essays, and short stories, and he served
as editor of the Negro Quarterly for a short
time. Ellison's masterwork, Invisible Man, received
many awards, including the National
Book Award in 1953.

Besides his novel, Ellison also published
two essay collections, Shadow and Act (1964)
and Going to the Territory (1987). He began a
second novel from which he released several
sections, but he died April 16, 1994, in New
York City before it was published. Six unpublished
short stories that predate Invisible Man were published posthumously.


Venetria K. Patton
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




O'Meally, Robert G. The Craft of Ralph Ellison. Cambridge:
Harvard University Press, 1980. Reckley, Ralph. "Ellison,
Ralph." In The Oxford Companion to African American Literature, edited by William L. Andrews, Frances Smith
Foster, and Trudier Harris. New York: Oxford University
Press, 1997: 129–31.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>