<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.arc.049</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Tourist Architecture</field>
      <field name="author">West, Carroll Van</field>
      <field name="text">

 




TOURIST ARCHITECTURE

Tourists of the Great Plains have both created
and encountered a distinctive built environment.
In one sense of the term, the first
tourist architecture in the region embraced
the natural landmarks that travelers named
during their overland journeys, places like
Chimney Rock in Nebraska and Register Cliff
in Wyoming, where travelers carved their
names, addresses, and destinations. Later, as
railroads crisscrossed the Plains, company officials
realized that travelers looked for a West
that conformed to preconceived images and
ideas. Rustic-style resort hotels and cabins
were built in vacation destinations, while railroad
depots often reflected a Spanish Colonial
or Pueblo Revival style in their design. For
example, the Northern Pacific Railway depot
in Bismarck, North Dakota, is a striking Spanish
Colonial gateway to the city, even if that
style has no compelling historical associations
with the state.

Yet it was automobile travel that would
create the most distinctive aspects of tourist
architecture in the Great Plains. The first
transcontinental highway, the Lincoln Highway
(later designated U.S. 30), passed through
the heart of the region. Later came famous
roads such as Route 66 and U.S. 40. In their
wake came service stations that initially were
flashy, eye-catching buildings designed to grab
the attention of speeding motorists. The soaring
column of the Tower Station, built in 1936
along Route 66 in Shamrock, Texas, was an
instant landmark. During the 1930s and 1940s,
however, these individualistic designs gave
way to the standardized plans of the major
petroleum companies. Revival designs, especially
reflecting Colonial and Tudor styles, created
an image of homelike comfort and convenience.
After World War II, standardized
designs, like those from Texaco and Standard
Oil, used streamlined building forms, striping,
and glossy enamel wall surfaces to turn
service stations into virtual three-dimensional
corporate billboards. By the 1950s a corporate
stamp marked the roadside landscape, replacing
the unpredictable yet visually exciting designs
of earlier auto travel.

The pattern of evolving design conformity
documented in service stations is also found
in the designs of motels and restaurants, two
additional key buildings of the modern roadscape.
Motels proliferated across the regional
landscape in the late 1940s and 1950s. Some
of these early designs, like the Alamo Court
motels in Texas, reflected both historical
places and revival styles like Spanish Colonial.
But by the 1960s major hotel-motel chains
dominated the market, and their similar standardized
designs varied little, no matter the
location. By the end of the twentieth century,
even the brightly colored signs once associated
with motels, like those of the early Holiday
Inns, were gone, replaced by the large, plastic,
fluorescent-lit signs that now clutter interstate
exits.

The history of restaurant design along the
region's roadsides is a similar story of evolving
architectural conformity. Distinctive roadside
places like Ole's Big Game Tavern in Paxton,
Nebraska, still serve travelers on older federal
highways, but these restaurants are few and far
between compared to the innumerable McDonalds
and Burger Kings lining the main
streets and interstates of the Great Plains.

See also INDUSTRY: Tourism / TRANSPORTATION:
Lincoln Highway; Route 66.


Carroll Van West
Middle Tennessee State University




Hokanson, Drake. The Lincoln Highway: Main Street across America. Iowa City: University of Iowa Press, 1988.
Jakle, John A., and Keith A. Sculle. The Gas Station in America. Baltimore MD: Johns Hopkins University Press,
1994. Jennings, Jan, ed. Roadside America: The Automobile in Design and Culture. Ames: Iowa State University Press,
1990.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>