<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fil.030</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Hopper, Dennis (b. 1936)</field>
      <field name="author">Durst, Karen L.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




HOPPER, DENNIS (b. 1936)

Dennis Hopper
    

Dennis Hopper's childhood (he was born on
May 17, 1936, in Dodge City, Kansas) hardly
foreshadowed the alienated, counterculture
hero he would come to be known as in films of
the 1960s and 1970s. In his early teens a family
relocation to California made possible his
pursuit of a film career. After high school
graduation Hopper was awarded a scholarship
to San Diego's Old Globe Theatre, where
he appeared in a number of Shakespearean
roles.

In the 1950s Warner Bros. cast him in a series
of supporting roles with James Dean (Rebel without a Cause [1955]; Giant [1956]).
Dean's acting style greatly influenced Hopper,
who would later move to New York in order to
study method acting at the Actors Studio. He
also began a new career as a photographer, a
move specifically calculated to teach him the
art of filmmaking and a choice that would
bring him artistic recognition.

In 1969 Hopper directed and costarred in
the acclaimed Easy Rider, filmed from a script
he had coauthored with Peter Fonda. Easy Rider won the prize for best film by a new
director at the Cannes Film Festival. Impressed
by the low-budget, high-grossing film,
Hollywood gave Hopper another chance to
direct. The opportunity was squandered on
The Last Movie (1971), an unsuccessful film
that cost Hopper his studio credibility. He
continued to work in films, including Apocalypse Now (1979), but by 1984 Hopper's history
of substance abuse climaxed with his
commitment to a psychiatric hospital.

Two years later he began another comeback.
In 1986 Hopper won an Academy Award
nomination for his role in Hoosiers and a best
supporting actor award from the National Society
of Film Critics for his malevolent role in
Blue Velvet. A year later he directed Colors, his
first feature film in sixteen years. Hopper continues
to work regularly as a creative artist,
most notably, as a character actor.


Karen L. Durst
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Katz, Ephraim. The Film Encyclopedia. New York: Harper
Collins, 1994. Rodriguez, Elena. Dennis Hopper: A Method to His Madness. New York: St. Martin's Press, 1988.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>