<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.arc.026</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Grain Elevators</field>
      <field name="author">Carney, George O.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




GRAIN ELEVATORS


CO-OP concrete elevator, built in 1935


The grain elevator is a facility that stores dry,
small cereal grains; it handles grain in bulk
rather than in bags or sacks, and it stores, moves,
and processes grain vertically. Vertical handling
and storage are desirable because grain
flows by gravity in tall, narrow bins, and thus
less power and labor are needed. Grain elevators
emerged in the second half of the nineteenth
century in North America when agriculture
shifted from a subsistence-based to a
cash-market economy as wheat farmers of the
Great Plains states and provinces began mass,
long-distance distribution of their produce.

All grain elevators consist of several components.
The workhouse contains the lower
floors, while the headhouse (cupola) consists
of two to five upper stories. The workhouse
name is derived from the fact that much of the
receiving and unloading operations take place
on the work floor of the first story, where the
elevating (lifting) process begins. The headhouse
is so named because the head drive of
the vertical conveyor system is located there.
The workhouse and the headhouse are collectively
referred to as the mainhouse.

The workhouse is the heart of the grain elevator.
It contains a "boot" into which farmers
dump their crop and a vertical belt-andbucket
conveyor that lifts the grain from
the boot to the headhouse, from which it is
spouted to a series of walled bins for bulk storage.
At the bottom of the bins are openings
out of which the grain empties into chutes
connected to waiting transportation such as
trucks and railroad cars.

Grain elevators can be classified according
to arrangement of elevating machinery
and storage bins, construction materials, and
function. There are two classes of arrangement:
self-contained, where the elevating machinery,
distributor, spouting system, and
storage bins are located in the mainhouse; and
the annex, where elevating machinery, distributor,
and spouting system are in the mainhouse,
while storage is in bins connected to
the mainhouse by external spouts and conveyor
systems. In the latter system, grain is
moved from the mainhouse to the annex bins
by an overhead horizontal conveyor belt with
a tripping device that directs it into the designated
bin. Grain is moved from the annex
bins to the mainhouse on a horizontal conveyor
belt below the bins.

The first stage in grain elevator architecture
was the vernacular iron-clad wood type. Constructed
by local farmers and carpenters without
a standardized plan or blueprint, the
structures emphasized function over form.
There are two subtypes based on framing. The
studded type consists of balloon construction,
also used in residential and commercial building.
The cribbed type has walls of two-inchthick
planks, ranging from four to ten inches
wide depending upon the height of the elevator.
These are laid flat, spiked through one
another, and overlapped at the corners. Cladding
of one-by-six-inch lapped boards is used
for both subtypes. Distinctive features of the
iron-clad wood elevator include tie-rods extending
through internal bins that are anchored
to horizontal braces on the exterior
walls and the galvanized iron or tin cladding
applied to the exterior walls. Cladding was
used for weatherproofing as well as to protect
the wood from sparks discharged from coalpowered
locomotives passing nearby.

The design and scale of the iron-clad wood
elevator include a rectangular-shaped workhouse,
forty to sixty feet high and surmounted
by a two- or three-story rectangular full or
partial headhouse approximately fifteen to
twenty feet high. Gable roofs are common for
both workhouse and headhouse. Internal features
include up to as many as twenty cribbed
bins of various capacities for storing and
blending the grain, the boot pit (the central
dump that receives the grain), the wood elevator
leg (the shaft that houses the beltand-
bucket conveyor system), the distributor
wheel that directs movement of grain to various bins, and the wood spouting system that
channels grain to bins or load-out chutes. Depending
upon the size of the structure, total
storage capacity ranges from 10,000 to 50,000
bushels.

From the beginning of commercial agriculture
in the Great Plains, the iron-clad wood
elevator was the primary hub for the grain
storage and shipping industry. Railroads often
provided land (right-of-way) for its construction
as well as grain cars suited for transporting
locally produced grain to distant markets.

Because of the skyrocketing insurance rates
for wood elevators, elevator owners and builders
experimented with other materials, such as
steel and clay tile. Concrete, however, became
the material of choice by 1900 because it eliminated
the twin dangers of weevils and fire and
thus reduced insurance costs. Cylindrical-shaped
concrete structures were an engineering
innovation when introduced to the grain
industry. The slip-form technology used in
their construction produces a tank in one solid
and continuous piece of concrete without
joints and patches. The technique consists of a
concentric double-ring form into which concrete
is poured. As the concrete in the lower
part of the ring sets, the forms are jacked upward,
and more concrete is added. This process
is continued until the desired height is
reached. The walls, six to eight inches thick,
are reinforced with vertical and horizontal
steel rods (I beams).

Grain elevators can be classified into four
types based on function. The first and most
numerous is the country, or local, elevator
sited along railroad tracks in the small towns
of the Great Plains. Because of the large quantities
of grain produced in the surrounding
countryside, farmers need local storage facilities
to handle surplus production before shipping
to domestic or international markets.
Country elevators allow local producers to
hold their grain for a better price, protect
it against waste and spoilage, accommodate
large quantities of grain during a peak harvest
season, and charge lower storage rates than
terminal elevators.

The terminal elevator receives grain via rail
or truck from the country elevators. These
towering bins, up to 150 feet high and arranged
in long, parallel lines, have the capacity
to hold several million bushels of grain. After
receipt of the grain from country elevators,
terminal operators sell huge shipments to
flour manufacturers or store the grain for later
sale to domestic and foreign buyers.

A third type is the processing elevator.
Rather than grain storage, its goal is to process
the grain within or near the facility into a finished
product and series of by-products for
either human or livestock consumption. Processing
elevators consist of two subtypes, the
flour mill and the feed mill. The flour mill
elevator classifies and blends wheat for milling
and is designed to transfer wheat to a nearby
flour mill, where the milling process is completed.
The storage tank arrangement of a
flour mill elevator is comprised of a variety of
bin sizes to hold different grades of wheat
used for producing different types of flour.
The turning-over process is important in a
flour mill elevator in order to retain wellconditioned
wheat during prolonged periods
of storage. Therefore, flour mill elevators require
a complex network of vertical and horizontal
conveyors to withdraw wheat from any
bin and send it to another. Flour mill elevators
also feature specialized equipment concerned
with testing and cleaning raw grain such as
laboratories, dampers, washers, and driers.

The feed mill elevator normally handles, in
addition to wheat, a variety of grains, including
corn, oats, and soybeans. Because of
this, the feed mill elevator's internal storage
must be arranged to provide bins of varying
sizes to accommodate different types of grain.
Feed mill elevators require different types of
space, chutes, and auxiliary buildings such as
load-out chutes and docks for both sacked
and bulk feed, packing rooms, and warehouses
for sacked-feed storage. Moreover,
formula-feed mixing plants are connected to
the elevator if this process is not completed
within. Finally, feed mill elevators also contain
specialized equipment, including corn shellers,
cob crushers, roller mills, aspirators, sacking
spouts, and batch mixers, which blend
mineral supplements and other grains according
to customer formulas.

There are two noticeable differences between
grain elevators in the Canadian Prairie
Provinces and those elsewhere in the Great
Plains. First, wood elevators remain more numerous
in the Canadian provinces, although
this is expected to change as they are replaced
by the concrete version. Second, the exterior
of Canadian wood elevators is usually painted.
Colors vary according to company ownership;
however, red, silver, white, and brown are the
most common.

Whether wood, tile, or concrete, the grain
elevator continues to dominate the visual
landscape of the Great Plains, where it has
played a significant role in the economic life of
small towns for more than 100 years.


George O. Carney
Oklahoma State University





Carney, George O. "Grain Elevators in the United States
and Canada: Functional or Symbolic?" Material Culture
27 (1995): 1–24. Clark, Charles S., ed. Grain Elevators of North America. Chicago: Grain and Feed Journals Consolidated,
1942. Riley, Robert B. "Grain Elevators: Symbols of
Time, Place, and Honest Building." American Institute of Architects Journal 66 (1977): 50–55.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>