<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.na.050</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Indian Territory</field>
      <field name="author">Bays, Brad A.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




INDIAN TERRITORY

Map of Oklahoma and Indian Territories


All of Oklahoma was referred to as "Indian
Territory" until 1890, when Congress partitioned
Oklahoma Territory and made "Indian
Territory" the formal name for the Five Civilized
Tribes' domain. Indian Territory's relevance
to the Great Plains thus spans from the
1820s, when the United States cleared title
through treaty cessions by the Quapaws (1818)
and Osages (1825) and designated the area as
"Indian Country," to the Oklahoma land runs,
beginning in 1889.

The area had long been permanently or seasonally
occupied by Great Plains peoples, notably
the Wichitas, Kiowas, and Plains Apaches.
Comanche, Cheyenne, Arapaho, and
Pawnee bison hunters also knew it well in the
1820s, as did hunters from the east, including
bands of Cherokees, who came to the Arkansas
and Red River areas decades before their
nation was forcibly relocated there. The treaties
that forced the Five Tribes to remove from
their eastern homelands in the 1830s gave
them roughly equivalent areas in Indian Territory,
overlapping the eastern margin of the
Great Plains.

The Five Tribes' three ribbons of Great
Plains land included the Cherokee Outlet in
the north, a strip between this and the Canadian
River shared by the Creek and Seminole
Nations, and a wide expanse between the Canadian
and North Fork of the Red River owned
by the Choctaws and Chickasaws (Texas began
west of the North Fork). The Five Tribes' settlements
clung to the safe, humid, accessible, alluvial
valleys to the east, which left the Kiowas
and Comanches to command their western
lands.

Beginning in the 1850s western Indian Territory
became a dumping ground for dispossessed
Plains Indians. When the Chickasaws
and Choctaws separated in 1855, they leased
the western third of their domain to the
United States to resettle Texas Indians. After
the Civil War the Five Tribes were forced to
cede their western lands to make room for
new reservations. The eastern third of the
Cherokee, Creek, and Seminole holdings was
parceled among a diverse set of Native American
refugees, creating a cluster of small,
poverty-stricken reservations. The western
lands of the Seminoles, Choctaws, and Chickasaws
became reservations for the Cheyennes
and Arapahos, Comanches, and Kiowas and
Apaches, following their brutal suppression
by the army in the 1860s and 1870s, which also
coincided with the era of the cattle drives
through the area.

By the 1880s reservation farming was largely
unsuccessful, since the most rational land
use for land-rich, capital-poor Indians was to
lease land to white cattlemen. For quite different
reasons, farmers and humanitarian reformers
agreed that the communal land tenure
on reservations had to end. In 1887 Congress
passed the General Allotment (Dawes) Act,
which required tribal members to select 160
acres of land for their own use, although title
would be held for a period of years by the
government. The acreage that remained was
then opened to white settlement. The reservations
of western Indian Territory were allotted
in the late 1880s and early 1890s. This was immediately
followed by land runs and lotteries
that brought tens of thousands of white families
to the region.

See also POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT: Oklahoma.


Brad A. Bays
Oklahoma State University




Debo, Angie. And Still the Waters Run: The Betrayal of the
Five Civilized Tribes. Princeton NJ: Princeton University
Press, 1940. Gibson, Arrell Morgan. Oklahoma: A History
of Five Centuries. Norman: University of Oklahoma Press,
1981. Morris, John W., Charles R. Goins, and Edwin C.
McReynolds. Historical Atlas of Oklahoma. Norman: University
of Oklahoma Press, 1986.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>