<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ind.052</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Potash Corporation of Saskatchewan</field>
      <field name="author">Blake, Raymond B.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




POTASH CORPORATION OF SASKATCHEWAN

The Potash Corporation of Saskatchewan,
headquartered at Saskatoon and operating six
mines in Saskatchewan, one in New Brunswick,
and, until its sale in 2000, one in Moab,
Utah, is the world's largest fertilizer enterprise.
In 1999 the corporation's production of
potash stood at 6.4 million metric tons, or 15
percent of the world's output. Potash is a generic
term for several types of potassium salts
or nutrients essential for modern agricultural
fertilizers.

It is estimated that the Potash Corporation
of Saskatchewan has 60 percent of the world's
excess potash capacity and enough reserves for
1,000 years of production. Potash was first discovered
in southern Saskatchewan in 1943, but
the first potash mine was not established until
1958, when the Potash Company of America
began production of the extensive deposits.
Technical difficulties delayed large-scale exploitation
until the late 1960s, but by 1971 ten
potash mines were in operation in Saskatchewan,
a province where there had always been a
debate over how best to develop its natural
resources.

Allan Blakeney's election as premier of
Saskatchewan in 1971 marked the beginning of
a long-running feud between the government
and the potash producers over an existing
prorating plan to control production and
price. In 1974 the government instituted a new
tax on producers, and in early 1975 it announced
plans to create the Potash Corporation
of Saskatchewan and nationalize some or
all of the province's potash industry. In October
1976 the government purchased its first
producing mine, and within two years it controlled
40 percent of the province's capacity.

The defeat of Premier Blakeney and his
New Democratic Party in 1982 marked a dramatic
political and ideological shift in the
province. Premier Grant Devine and the Progressive
Conservatives assumed office with a
profound faith in the primacy of the market,
as did many governments throughout the
western democracies at the time. They placed
little value on state-run enterprises and proceeded
to privatize the Potash Corporation of
Saskatchewan through a public share offering.
Ironically, it was a New Democratic Party government,
led by Roy Romanow, that completed
the sale of the Potash Corporation
shares that the province had retained after the
initial public offering.

See also POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT: New Democratic Party.


Raymond B. Blake
University of Regina





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>