<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.mus.024</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Jennings, Waylon (1937-2002)</field>
      <field name="author">Vollan, Charles</field>
      <field name="text">

 




JENNINGS, WAYLON (1937-2002)

Waylon Jennings playing guitar
    

Among the leaders of the outlaw movement
that revitalized country music in the 1970s,
Waylon Jennings was born on June 15, 1937, in
Littlefield, Texas. He formed his own band at
the age of twelve and worked as a radio DJ two
years later. He dropped out of high school in
the tenth grade to pursue his career. In 1954
Jennings moved to Lubbock, Texas, where he
met Buddy Holly the following year. His influences
included Hank Williams, Ernest Tubb,
Webb Price, B. B. King, and Bobbie "Blue"
Bland as well as his early mentor, Buddy Holly.

From 1958 to 1959 Jennings played bass for
Buddy Holly, who produced Jennings's first
album and taught him that there should be no
barriers between the audience and the performer.
Jennings gave his seat to the Big Bopper
on the fatal flight that also took the lives of
Holly and Richie Valens in February 1959. Following
this close call, Jennings returned to
Lubbock to regroup before moving to Phoenix,
where he started his band, the Waylors,
and began to build a diverse audience.

Jennings moved to Nashville in 1965, signing
with RCA. Like Willie Nelson before him,
Jennings found himself an outcast in Nashville
and perhaps a little more "country" than the
industry itself. Although he scored several Top
5 hits, including "Only Daddy That'll Walk the
Line" and "Walk on out of My Mind," he
found success elusive until he began to produce
his own records and use his own musicians.
In 1969 he married fellow singer Jessi
Colter.

By the 1970s Jennings had a series of hit
albums, including the first platinum-selling
solo country album, Ol' Waylon, in 1977. He
was long associated with fellow outlaws Willie
Nelson, Johnny Cash, and Kris Kristofferson,
with whom he recorded as the Highwaymen
in the late 1980s. His teaming with Willie Nelson
produced two notable albums, Waylon and Willie (1978), which produced the crossover
hit "Mammas, Don't Let Your Babies
Grow up to Be Cowboys," and WWII (1982),
which went gold.

In addition to his musical work, Jennings
acted in films such as Outlaw Justice (with Kris
Kristofferson, Willie Nelson, and Travis Tritt,
1999) and the made-for-television Stagecoach
(1986) as well as providing the narration for
the television show The Dukes of Hazzard. He
wrote his autobiography, Waylon (1996), and
even produced a children's album, Cowboys,
Sisters, Rascals &amp; Dirt (1993). His work was well
received, with Jennings winning numerous
awards from the Country Music Association:
male vocalist of the year (1975), vocal duo of
the year with Willie Nelson (1976), album of
the year (Wanted: The Outlaws, 1976), and single
of the year ("Good Hearted Woman,"
1976). He was inducted into the Country Music
Hall of Fame in 2001.

Jennings spoke and wrote openly about his
troubles with alcohol and drugs. After earning
his GED in 1989, he also promoted the equivalency
program and worked to encourage
children to stay in school.

Despite less than enthusiastic acceptance
from the country music industry, Jennings
nonetheless attained legendary status due to
his outlaw reputation and ability to appeal
to rock audiences. Indeed, his popularity is
broader and deeper than that of most modern
country music stars, despite the lack of airplay
that his songs now receive.

Jennings died on February 13, 2002, in Chandler,
Arizona, of complications from diabetes.


Charles Vollan
University of Nebraska-Lincoln





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>