<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.005</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Bellmon, Henry (b. 1921)</field>
      <field name="author">Shelley, Fred M.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BELLMON, HENRY (b. 1921)

Henry Bellmon, governor and U.S. senator
from Oklahoma, was the pivotal figure in creating
Oklahoma's modern two-party politics.
Bellmon was born on September 3, 1921, on a
farm near Billings, Noble County, Oklahoma.
He graduated from Oklahoma A&amp;M University
(now Oklahoma State University) in 1942 and
served with distinction in the U.S. Marine
Corps during World War II. After the war
ended, he returned to the family farm and
became active in local politics. He was elected
to the Oklahoma legislature in 1946 but was
defeated for reelection in 1948.

In 1947 Bellmon married Shirley Osborn,
and for the next fifteen years he concentrated
on farming and raising his three daughters. In
1960 he was elected as chair of the Oklahoma
Republican Party and in that capacity worked
to make the party competitive at the state and
local level. Two years later he announced his
candidacy for governor of Oklahoma. He defeated
Democrat Bill Atkinson, and in doing so
became the first Republican governor of Oklahoma
and the first Republican to be governor
of any southern state since Reconstruction.

Bellmon was ineligible to succeed himself as
governor and left office in 1967. The following
year, he ran for the U.S. Senate and defeated
incumbent Democrat Mike Monroney. Despite
his close association with President Richard
Nixon, Bellmon was reelected over Democrat
Ed Edmondson in 1974 by a narrow margin.
During his two terms in the Senate, Bellmon
rose to become ranking minority member of the
Senate Budget Committee. He voted a generally
conservative line but angered doctrinaire conservatives
with his support for the Panama Canal
treaty and school integration.

Bellmon declined to run for a third term in
1980 and returned to Oklahoma. He served as
a member of the faculty at the University of
Oklahoma before running for a second term
as governor in 1986. By winning the election,
Bellmon became Oklahoma's first Republican
to win a second term as governor. During his
second term Bellmon presided over the centennial
of the Oklahoma Land Run of 1889. He
continued to steer a moderate course and implemented
important budgetary and educational
reforms. Bellmon retired after completing
his term in 1991, but he remained active in
local and state political activity. Henry Bellmon
will be remembered as the architect of
modern two-party politics in Oklahoma and
as a governor and senator of independence
and integrity.


Fred M. Shelley
Southwest Texas State University




Bellmon, Henry. The Life and Times of Henry Bellmon.
Tulsa OK: Charter Oak Press. 1992.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>