<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.gen.002</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Albert v. Albert</field>
      <field name="author">Scherer, Mark R.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ALBERT V. ALBERT

In Albert v. Albert (1885) the Supreme Court of
Montana held that a single incident of physical
abuse by a husband against his wife could
be deemed to constitute "extreme cruelty" so
as to justify the granting of a divorce. The
decision arose out of a petition for divorce
filed in the Second District Court of Deer
Lodge County by Kate Albert against her husband,
Charles. Mrs. Albert claimed that she
had been repeatedly beaten and whipped by
Charles, and that the abuse she had incurred
constituted extreme cruelty within the meaning
of the applicable common law standards
prescribing su.cient cause for the granting of
a divorce. Mr. Albert defended his actions by
claiming that he had beaten his wife on only
one occasion and that he had been justified in
doing so because Kate had publicly accused
him of adultery.

In its charge to the jury, the trial court sided
with Mr. Albert's view of the legal standards
applicable to the situation, instructing the
jury that even if they found that Mr. Albert
had in fact struck his wife on more than one
occasion, those actions did not necessarily establish
the charge of extreme cruelty. The
court further instructed the jury that if they
found from the evidence that Mrs. Albert had
"provoked" her husband to strike her, then
Mr. Albert could be excused for treating her in
a harsher manner than would have otherwise
been justified. Based upon those instructions,
the jury concluded that Mrs. Albert had not
established her claim of extreme cruelty and
denied the requested divorce decree.

On appeal by Mrs. Albert, the Montana Supreme
Court reversed the trial court's judgment.
In a decision that represented a significant
departure from prevailing judicial
interpretations of traditional gender roles and
marital relations, the court held that even a
single act of physical violence by a husband
against a wife constituted sufficient proof of
extreme cruelty to justify a divorce decree. The
court further held that mere words uttered by a
wife against her husband could never provide
an excuse for a husband's violent response.

For the next twenty years the Montana Supreme
Court's enunciation of this "single incident"
standard for extreme cruelty provided
the foundation for additional judicial tinkering
with traditional legal interpretations of the
marital relationship. Some legal historians, for
example, point to the Albert decision as illustrative
of the leading role played by western
and Great Plains legal institutions in the evolution
of new patterns of judicial recognition
for the emerging "cult of true womanhood"
and "companionate marriage ideal" of the
Victorian period. In 1906, however, the Montana
Supreme Court stepped back from the
progressivism embodied in Albert and reversed
itself on the single incident standard. In
Ryan v. Ryan the court held that Albert had
been superseded by legislation which provided
that only mistreatment resulting in
"grievous bodily injury" to a wife could give
rise to an action for divorce. In response to
Ryan, the Montana legislature amended the
relevant statute again so as to provide that
even the threat of grievous bodily harm would
su.ce to state a claim of extreme cruelty.
Thus, Albert v. Albert remains a leading example
of the evolving progressivism of Great
Plains legal institutions in the reshaping of
gender roles and marital dynamics in the late
nineteenth and early twentieth centuries.


Mark R. Scherer
University of Nebraska at Omaha




Albert v. Albert, 5 Mont. 577, 6 P. 23 (1885). Petrik, Paula. No Step Backward: Women and Family on the Rocky Mountain Mining Frontier, Helena, Montana, 1865–1900. Helena:
Montana Historical Society Press, 1987.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>