<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.tra.033</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Russell, Majors and Waddell</field>
      <field name="author">Ward, Derrick S.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




RUSSELL, MAJORS AND WEDDELL

The freighting and staging firm of Russell,
Majors and Waddell, formed in 1854 to supply
military posts in the American West and
Southwest, played a significant role in the history
of transportation in the Great Plains.
Among the firm's achievements was the creation
of the legendary Pony Express.

The founding of Russell, Majors and Waddell
was rooted in the U.S. Army's need for an
efficient means of transporting military supplies
between a new depot in Santa Fe and six
new army posts in New Mexico Territory, all
established at the end of the Mexican War in
1848. In 1854 the War Department decided the
best way to efficiently supply these and other
posts would be to award two-year contracts to
private freighting companies. The quartermaster
awarded the first of these contracts to
the firm of Russell, Majors and Waddell, a
partnership of William H. Russell, Alexander
Majors, and William B. Waddell, headquartered
in Leavenworth, Kansas. They also transported
civilian freight on a large scale.

The company’s dealings with the government,
rewarding at the start, eventually cost
them financially. This downward financial
spiral began in 1857, a busy year during which
the firm moved nearly five million pounds of
supplies to army depots and military posts
across Kansas, New Mexico, and Utah. At the
outbreak of the 1857 Mormon War, the quartermaster
at Fort Leavenworth requested that
Russell, Majors and Waddell move some 2.5
million pounds of freight to Salt Lake City, a
load far exceeding the firm’s contractual obligations
for the year. Rather than jeopardize its
position as chief army contractor in the West
by refusing the excess freight, Russell, Majors
and Waddell borrowed to fulfill the request
and incurred heavy losses waiting for future
reimbursement from the government. A series
of transactions in 1858 put the company in
debt, and the decision to launch the Central
Overland California and Pikes Peak Express, a
staging and express concern, further eroded
the firm's finances.

In 1860, despite growing financial trouble,
Russell created the firm's most enduring legacy
by convincing his two reluctant partners
to support the establishment of the Pony Express
as a means of publicizing the superiority
of the central route over the lengthier
southern route then employed in the trans-Mississippi
West by the Overland Mail Company.
That same year, Russell found that he
could no longer honor his financial obligations.
He became entangled in the most serious
financial scandal of the period, a scheme
involving high-level Interior and War Department
officials. Indicted in the scandal, Russell's
involvement effectively destroyed the financial
standing of all three partners, and
Russell, Majors and Waddell went out of business
in 1862.


Derrick S. Ward
Ventura, California




Settle, Raymond W., and Mary Lund Settle. War Drums
and Wagon Wheels: The Story of Russell, Majors, and Waddell.
Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1966.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>