<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ct.028</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Kansas City, Kansas and Missouri</field>
      <field name="author">De Bres, Karen J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




KANSAS CITY, KANSAS AND MISSOURI

Kansas City owes its fortunes to its geography,
since it is located precisely where the Missouri
River stops flowing to the south and begins to
stretch out eastward. In 1833 this fortunate situation
was enhanced when J. C. McCoy found
a rock ledge that could serve as a natural boat
landing. McCoy connected the landing by trail
to his new settlement at Westport, creating
one of the best jumping-off points for western
land routes. The present-day Kansas City,
Missouri, city center was incorporated in 1850.
At around the same time settlement was beginning
along the river bottoms in Wyandotte
County just across the border in the state of
Kansas. So from the 1850s on there were two
Kansas Cities, divided by the Missouri-Kansas
state line, and both grew from a consolidation
of villages rather than from a single unit.

The construction of the Hannibal Bridge
across the Missouri River in 1869 (the first
railroad bridge to span the river) allowed
Kansas City to develop quickly as a grain- and
meat-processing center. The meatpacking industry
began on the Kansas side of the river, as
did the Santa Fe Railroad shops and yards, and
this area became the home of several important
ethnic populations, notably, Slavic, Hispanic,
and African American. The African
American population was increased by the arrival
of the "Exodusters" from the South in the
1870s. African Americans established newspapers,
churches, and a university in Kansas
City, Kansas, during the late nineteenth century,
but it was their twentieth-century contributions
in both Kansas Cities that have been
the most long lasting. From 1908 to 1955 Kansas
City, Missouri, was home to the Kansas
City Monarchs, one of the best teams in the
Negro baseball league. Beginning in the 1920s
Kansas City developed its own style of jazz,
which was so popular that at one time there
were more than fifty jazz clubs, located mainly
between Twelfth and Eighteenth Streets on the
Missouri side of the river. Kansas City barbeque
is another mainly African American
contribution.

Kansas City, Missouri, had also established
itself as the "Gateway to the Southwest," with
important rail connections and the industries
that profited from them. Between 1880 and
1890 the population doubled, and in the next
two decades ambitious plans for a network
of boulevards and parks were established and
eventually implemented. Suburbanization began
in the 1920s with the creation of large residential
districts mainly to the south of the
downtown area. J. C. Nichols was the most
successful real estate developer of this period.
He created the Country Club Plaza, the first
shopping center in the nation. The plaza has
several notable features: it was designed in the
1920s with free parking lots placed around its
periphery, and it was originally the home of a
number of branch stores from the downtown
area, serving as a model for retail suburbanization
across the United States.

Prosperity ended with the Depression, but
while the population stagnated, Kansas City,
Missouri, benefited from a number of federal
building initiatives, including a new post office
(1933), a municipal auditorium (1935),
and a new federal courts building (1933). It
also profited from planned expansion. Unlike
many older cities such as St. Louis that are
hemmed in by surrounding counties, Kansas
City, Missouri, was able to expand in an extraordinary
fashion during the second half of
the twentieth century, increasing in size from
60 square miles in 1940 to 130 square miles in
1960 and 316 square miles in 2001. The population
of Kansas City, Missouri, stood at 435,000
in 2000.

During the Depression, Kansas City, Kansas,
benefited mainly from a large levee development
project. During World War II many
firms produced munitions, engines, and the
landing craft for the Normandy invasion, and
after the war the city's industrial base began
to diversify even more. Kansas City's industries
now include Hallmark Cards, H &amp; R
Block, Kansas City Southern Industries, Ford
Motor Company, and General Motors. The
famous Kansas City stockyards are now virtually
closed.

Kansas City, Kansas, has a population of
143,000, leaving Wichita as the largest city in
Kansas. But if the explosive suburban growth
seen in Johnson County, Kansas, in the 1980s
and 1990s was added to the population of
Kansas City, Kansas, it would be Kansas's
largest city. Johnson County and Wyandotte
County display the sharpest divide in social
geography in Kansas. Wyandotte County's
population is long established and mainly
blue collar, with a large minority component.
By contrast, Johnson County's population
consists mainly of affluent, recently arrived,
middle-class white residents.

Following the nationwide trend of the 1980s
and 1990s, the urban school systems in both
Kansas Cities now have a majority of African
American and Hispanic students. But the two
cities present other distinct contrasts. Kansas
City, Missouri, known as the "City of Fountains,"
is currently undergoing urban revitalization
in many of its downtown neighborhoods,
notably at Westport and near the
Plaza. In the late 1990s Union Station was remodeled
into a science museum with funds
supplied by both city and county taxpayers.
Kansas City, Kansas, has not been able to attract
as many new residents or new businesses
as its neighbor, but it maintains its distinct
social heritage and several of its historic ethnic
neighborhoods, notably, Strawberry Hill. The
entire metropolitan area now contains fifteen
counties, thirty-five communities in two
states, and nearly two million people.

See also AFRICAN AMERICANS: Baseball, Interracial / ARCHITECTURE: Country Club Plaza / INDUSTRY: Hallmark Cards, Inc. / MUSIC: Kansas City Jazz.


Karen J. De Bres
Kansas State University




De Bres, K. "Kansas City Urban Sites: Historical and Modern."
Papers and Proceedings of the Applied Geography Conference
19 (1996): 299–305. Shortridge, J. "New Introduction."
In The WPAGuide to 1930s Kansas, Lawrence:
University Press of Kansas, 1984.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>