<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.edu.035</field>
      <field name="titleMain">School Consolidation and Reorganization</field>
      <field name="author">Bryant, Miles T.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SCHOOL CONSOLIDATION AND REORGANIZATION

School districts proliferated during the settling
of the Great Plains. As the region became
sprinkled with small communities and rural
settlements, school districts were formed.
Geographic distance, the platting of agricultural
land in large sections, and a widely dispersed
population all combined to make the
rural school the only viable way to deliver education
to the children of an expanding agricultural
population. The increase in school
districts was also accelerated by state policies.
Later, as the region's population declined, the
number of schools followed suit. In the period
of decline, population decreases and waves of
consolidation efforts have worked to reduce
the number of school districts.

Up to the time of the Dust Bowl and the
Great Depression, the region sustained large
numbers of school districts. In the peak year
of 1924 there were 56,121 school districts in
Great Plains states, with Kansas alone having
9,326. The Canadian Prairie Provinces showed
a similar pattern: by the 1930s Saskatchewan
reported 4,000 school districts and Manitoba
1,700. Significant population declines followed
the droughts and economic crisis that
struck the Great Plains in the thirties. By the
end of the 1960s the states and provinces of the
Great Plains had closed many of their school
districts. In the U.S. portion of the region, by
1968 only 4,822 school districts remained.

The school districts that sprang up in the
Great Plains were filled with thousands of
one-teacher country schools. By 1931, of the
143,391 one-teacher schools in existence in the
United States, more than 41,000 were located
in the rural parts of the Great Plains, with
Kansas leading the numbers with 6,983 and
Nebraska close behind with 6,136. State policies
encouraged the formation of school districts.
In Kansas a county superintendent
could create school districts as long as there
were fifteen persons of school age in the new
district. In South Dakota residents could petition
a county board for a new school as long
as there were seven children living within
three miles of the proposed school. In Colorado
a majority of local voters could create a
district. State educational policy was compatible
with the economic development policies
of the settlement era, policies that sought to
populate the Great Plains region.

In the 1920s and 1930s states began exercising
their constitutional authority to organize
school districts differently. In some states
the boundaries of the town or community became
coterminous with the boundaries of the
school district. Some states created county
boards with the authority to consolidate
schools in their jurisdictions. Outside the
Plains, the state of Washington set up a commission
to oversee consolidation plans in the
1940s. In the Great Plains region, Colorado,
North Dakota, and Kansas followed suit. Beliefs
about what constituted an adequate educational
program drove these efforts. Small
schools simply could not provide the range of
curricula that educational experts had determined
should be offered.

Beginning in the early thirties, as dirt roads
gave way to paved streets and automobiles facilitated
travel to district commercial centers,
school districts began to disappear on the
prairie and in very small communities. This
disappearance was hastened by successive
waves of consolidation efforts. The first reorganization
period was characterized by a
national initiative to reduce the number of
rural country schools. Small elementary districts,
with their classic one-room schoolhouses,
were combined with larger K-12 districts.
By 1970 only 1,572 one-teacher schools
remained in the Great Plains states, and Kansas,
the leader in such schools in 1931, had
none. A second wave of consolidation efforts
began in the 1960s with what was called the
Great Plains School District Organization
Project. Funded by federal dollars under Title
V of the Elementary and Secondary Education
Act of 1965, this project set out to provide both
an educational argument and an economic
case for consolidating school districts into
larger administrative units. This consolidation
effort met with stiff resistance and generated
heated debate, and the Great Plains
District Organization Project did not immediately
lead to large numbers of school district
closures. But school districts have since declined
in number as pressure to consolidate
has continued unabated from state agencies
and educational experts. In the 1980s and
1990s the successful reorganization of school
districts was carried out by state legislatures as
almost all of the states and Canadian provinces
forced the realignment of school district
boundaries.

Throughout this period there has been resistance.
Representatives of rural communities
and small towns have argued that a
school district is an essential part of their economic
and cultural well-being. Supporters
of consolidation efforts typically argue that
economies of scale as well as adequate educational
programming demand consolidation
into larger administrative units. No definitive
research has established that one particular
organizational scheme of education works
better than another. The forces that now buffet
rural schools are mainly economic. Dependent
more and more upon state sources of
funding, since a sparse population no longer
supports a property tax base to provide for
rural education, rural schools have an uncertain
future in the Great Plains.


Miles T. Bryant
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Dawson, Howard. "Trends in School District Reorganization."
Phi Delta Kappan 32 (1951): 302–7. Phillips, Charles.
"District Reorganization in Canada." Phi Delta Kappan 32
(1951): 308–12. Purdy, Ralph. The Great Plains School District
Reorganization Project. Lincoln: Nebraska Department
of Education, 1968.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>