<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.gen.039</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Victorian Women Travelers</field>
      <field name="author">Morin, Karen M.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




VICTORIAN WOMEN TRAVELERS

"Victorian women travelers" generally refers
to professional European and American travel
writers, tourists, wives of colonial administrators, and other (mostly) elite women
who wrote narratives about their experiences
abroad in the nineteenth century. From a "liberal"
feminist perspective in Anglo-European
scholarship, travel presented one means toward
female liberation for middle- and upper-class
Victorian women. Many studies from the
1970s onward have demonstrated the ways in
which women's gendered identities were negotiated
differently "at home" versus "away," thus
showing women's self-development through
travel. The more recent "poststructural" turn
in studies of Victorian travel writing has focused
attention on women's diverse and fragmented
identities as they narrated their travel
experiences. In this framework, emphasis is
placed on women's sense of themselves as
women in new locations, but only as they
worked through their ties to nation, class,
whiteness, and colonial and imperial power
structures. Much recent work has examined
Victorian women travelers' not-so-innocent
participation in European empire building, especially
in terms of women travelers' ambivalent
relationships with Indigenous peoples in
Asia, Africa, and the Americas.

In the North American context, attention
has been drawn to Victorian women's narratives
of travels throughout the American and
Canadian West, portions of which describe
the Great Plains. (This was stimulated at least
in part by western historians' long-standing
interest in women settlers' relationships with
the land.) Coinciding with advances in transportation
technology, particularly in the
steamship and railroad, the American and Canadian
West was opened for wide-scale tourism
and travel by the middle or upper classes
in the later Victorian period (1870s in the
United States, a decade later in Canada). Oftentimes,
foreign visitors from Europe came
to the United States and Canada as part of a
world tour, and they, as well as east-coast
North Americans, took "grand tours" of the
continent when the transcontinental railroad
lines were completed. For many travelers, the
Great Plains was a place en route to the welladvertised
scenic attractions of points farther
west, such as Yosemite or Vancouver, rather
than a destination in its own right. Thus,
while many Victorian women travelers commented
on the scenery, people, and economic
development of the Great Plains in their travelogues,
they did so without ever leaving the
trains during the portions of their journeys
through the region.

There are many exceptions, though. The
Englishwoman Lady Rose Pender, for instance,
traveled with her husband to inspect
the family's investments in Wyoming ranching,
and they participated in a cattle roundup
in the Niobrara River valley–camping out
and "roughing it" for the first time in her life.
Pender thoroughly enjoyed this "wild rough
life"–the clear air, the stirring scenery, and
her feeling of physical well-being and "utter
freedom." Mrs. Cecil Hall's 1884 narrative describes
her three-month visit to her emigrant
brother's farm in Manitoba. Again, what these
and other Victorian travelers wrote about the
Great Plains depended to a large extent on
their routes and destinations. Women's travels
through the Plains often followed the transects
of the railroads; thus, for instance, those
riding the Union Pacific Railroad wrote about
Kansas City, Omaha, and Cheyenne, as well as
the farms, settlements, train depots, and open
country in between. Since it took up to several
days to travel from Chicago to Denver by
train, oftentimes the women wrote about the
(in)adequacy of the train compartments
themselves or described their primarily visual
(and often bored) experience of passing landscapes.
Many travelers expounded at length
on the situation of Native Americans, especially
Native women, who they sometimes encountered
at train depots. British Victorian
women travelers' rhetoric about Native peoples
often resembled that of Indian reformers
of the period.


Karen M. Morin
Bucknell University




Hall, Mrs. Cecil. A Lady's Life on a Farm in Manitoba.
London: W. H. Allen, 1884. Hardy, Lady Duffus. Through Cities and Prairie Lands: Sketches of an American Tour.
Chicago: Belford, Clarke and Co., 1882. Pender, Rose. A Lady's Experiences in the Wild West in 1883. Lincoln: University
of Nebraska Press, 1978.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>