<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ind.056</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Swather</field>
      <field name="author">Foulke, Steven V.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SWATHER

A swather, also known as a windrower, is a self-propelled
agricultural implement that harvests
all types of hay. The introduction of the
swather radically altered harvesting techniques
in the Great Plains (particularly in South Dakota,
North Dakota, northern Nebraska, and
southeastern Colorado, where haying is prevalent)
and throughout the world. The machine
was refined and marketed by an agricultural
implement manufacturer in central Kansas
whose considerable economic clout resulted
directly from the popularity of the swather.

In the nineteenth and early twentieth centuries
hay was grown widely on mixed farming
operations. It was a profitable crop because it
was consumed as feed by horses and mules in
cities and rural areas. However, its harvest was
time-consuming. A different implement was
necessary for each step in the process: mowing
the hay, collecting the mowed crop into narrow,
elongated piles (windrows) in order to
dry it, and–to facilitate drying–"raking" or
turning over the windrows. Dry hay is critical
to preventing molding once the crop is baled
and stored. If the hay is stored when damp, the
resulting decomposition can eventually generate
enough heat to cause the hay to catch fire.

Hay-harvesting methods were destined to
change drastically when Lyle Yost, a Mennonite
entrepreneur from Hesston, Kansas,
helped form the Hesston Manufacturing
Company in 1949. The firm acquired the production
rights from a machine-shop owner in
Iowa to a device that single-handedly accomplished
all the tasks of hay harvesting. Yost's
company introduced the "swather" (later renamed
the "windrower") in the mid-1950s. In
addition to mowing, windrowing, and being
self-propelled, the swather has an innovation
that enables hay to dry faster and more thoroughly.
As the crop is mowed, the stalks are
crushed (known as conditioning), allowing
the plant's moisture to evaporate more quickly
once the hay is stacked in windrows. Ideally,
conditioning hay eliminates the need for raking
and protects the protein-rich tips and
leaves of harvested plants. Today's windrowers
are larger and more sophisticated than earlier
models, and their central role in haying remains
undiminished.

Based largely on the popularity of the
swather, Yost's fledgling company eventually
employed well over 1,000 people and became
an international force in the implement industry.
In 1966 the company was renamed
Hesston Corporation. In the late 1980s the
business underwent major financial restructuring,
but it continues to manufacture agricultural
implements as Hay and Forage, Inc.
Hesston Corporation and its home community,
Hesston, became synonymous with hay
harvesting. The town of Hesston was transformed
from a small farming hamlet into a
prosperous suburban-like community by the
company's success. Hesston high school sports
teams are known as the Swathers, which says
much about the influence of Yost, his company,
and his hay harvester.

See also AGRICULTURE: Hay.


Steven V. Foulke
Perry, Kansas




Jones, Billy M. Factory on the Plains: Lyle Yost and the Hesston Corporation. Wichita KS: Center for Entrepreneurship,
Wichita State University, 1987.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>