<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fol.027</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Lomax, John A. (1867-1948)</field>
      <field name="author">Porterfield, Nolan</field>
      <field name="text">

 




LOMAX, JOHN A. (1867-1948)

John A. Lomax

    
Although best known as the folk-song collector
who found Huddie "Leadbelly" Ledbetter
in a Louisiana prison, John A. Lomax's pioneering
role in cultural preservation was established
more than thirty years earlier with the
publication of Cowboy Songs and Other Frontier Ballads (1910). Born in Holmes County,
Mississippi, on September 23, 1867, he was
scarcely two when his family moved to Texas,
and he always considered himself a native
Texan. The social and cultural heritage of the
Lone Star State was to have a pervasive influence
on his life's work.

In his youth Lomax attended a small frontier
"college" in Granbury, Texas, and later
taught school for a time. In 1895, when he was
twenty-eight, he entered the University of
Texas as a freshman and eventually earned two
degrees there (bachelor of arts, 1897; master of
arts, 1906). He also attended the University of
Chicago (1985, 1903) and, ultimately, Harvard
University (master of arts, 1907), where he
studied comparative literature and balladry
under such luminaries as Barrett Wendell and
George Lyman Kittredge. From 1897 to 1903 he
served as registrar of the University of Texas,
and at intervals beginning in 1903 he taught
English at the Agricultural and Mechanical
College of Texas (later Texas A&amp;M University).

In 1907, supported by Kittredge and Wendell,
Lomax began what proved to be one of
the first serious, systematic efforts to collect
American folk songs. Traveling through the
Central Plains and Southwest, sometimes on
horseback, he gathered and recorded such
now-famous classics as "Home on the Range,"
"Git Along Little Dogies," and "The Old Chisholm
Trail," published three years later, with
109 others, as Cowboy Songs and Other Frontier Ballads.

Lomax returned to the University of Texas
in 1910. His association with the university
shaped both his personal and professional life
for many years, although he left or was forced
out of positions there no fewer than three
times between 1903 and 1925, when he moved
to Dallas to accept a job as vice president of
the Republic National Bank. At that point his
song-collecting activity, which had dwindled
over the years, seemed finished.

When the Depression struck, Lomax was in
his sixties, in ill health, and mourning the
death of his wife. In 1932 his sons, John Jr.
and Alan, persuaded him to resume his folksong
lecture tours and fieldwork. Together
they mapped out a six-month lecture-and-collecting
tour that took them across the nation,
restored both Lomax's health and bank
account, and set the pattern for the next ten
years of his life. From this work came American Ballads and Folk Songs (1934) and Our Singing Country (1941), which preserved in print
such national treasures as "Casey Jones," "Rye
Whiskey," "Amazing Grace," "Cotton-Eyed
Joe," "Jack o' Diamonds," and many others.

In 1933 Lomax was named curator of the
Archive of American Folksong at the Library
of Congress. With support from that institution,
he and his son Alan made field recording
trips throughout the 1930s, pioneering the
use of instantaneous disk recording for that
purpose and eventually depositing in the archive
recordings of more than 4,000 folk
songs. Along the way he found time to conduct
notorious verbal duels with his critics
and detractors, to promote Leadbelly, and
to publish seven more books, including his
autobiography.

In early 1948 Lomax traveled to Greenville,
Mississippi, near his birthplace, for a celebration
in his honor. Before the ceremony could
begin, he suffered a massive heart attack and
died two days later, on January 26, 1948.

See also MUSIC: Cowboy Music.


Nolan Porterfield
Bowling Green, Kentucky




Lomax Family Papers. Center for American History, University
of Texas at Austin. Lomax, John, and Alan Lomax.
Cowboy Songs and Other Frontier Ballads. New York: Collier
Books, 1986. Porterfield, Nolan. Last Cavalier: The Life and Times of John A. Lomax. Urbana: University of Illinois
Press, 1996.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>