<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.rel.037</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Okipa</field>
      <field name="author">Tischauser, Leslie V.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




OKIPA

The Okipa was the most powerful religious
ceremony of the Mandan people of North Dakota.
The four-day ceremony was performed
every year during the summer. It retold the
history of the creation of the Earth and all
living things. The main characters are the
Okipa Maker, or Lone Man, who created the
Mandan and gave them their rituals; Hoita, or
Speckled Eagle, who created the animals; and
Oxinhede, the Foolish One, who did not believe
in the power of Okipa and was cast out of
the village at the end. These three dancers are
joined by others impersonating buffalo, bald
eagles, holy women, swans, snakes, grizzly
bears, night, day, wolves, coyotes, meadowlarks,
and antelopes. They are supported by
drummers playing sacred turtle drums.

The dancers performed inside the Okipa
lodge, which was filled by men fasting, praying,
and seeking visions. Sacred bundles, containing
objects such as buffalo hair, a stuffed
raven, a porcupine headdress, buffalo teeth,
and a warbonnet of raven and swan feathers,
were also presented. These objects represented
key elements in the history of the people.
The younger men generally underwent torture
to demonstrate their bravery. Long wooden
skewers were pushed through cuts in the skin
on their backs or chests, and they were hung by
ropes from beams. Their bodies were weighted
down with buffalo skulls hung from other
skewers thrust into their thighs and calves. The
torment was extreme, but crying out was a sign
of cowardice, and those best able to stand the
pain became Mandan leaders. Women were
not allowed inside the lodge, although some
would sit on the roof, where they would fast.

The purpose of the ceremony was to rea.
rm the bond between the people and the
natural world and to unify the Mandans
through a ritual of suffering and bloodshed.
The Okipa had been performed for hundreds
of years when the artist George Catlin witnessed
the ceremony in 1832. The Okipa was
probably last held on Fort Berthold Reservation
in 1889 or 1890, after which it was suppressed
by the United States.

See also NATIVE AMERICANS: Mandans.


Leslie V. Tischauser
Prairie State College




Bowers, Alfred. Mandan Social and Ceremonial Organization.
Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1950. McHugh,
Tom. The Time of the Buffalo. Lincoln: University of Nebraska
Press, 1972. Meyer, Roy W. The Village Indians of
the Upper Missouri: The Mandan, Hidatsas, and Arikaras.
Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1977.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>