<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.004</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Birdsell, Sandra (b. 1942)</field>
      <field name="author">Reimer, Douglas</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BIRDSELL, SANDRA (b. 1942)

Sandra Birdsell, who was born in the small
town of Hamiota, Manitoba, on April 22, 1942,
is the author of two novels, three volumes of
short fiction, one collection of short stories,
and a children's book. She has also written
scripts for television. Her Agassiz Stories was
chosen by Macleans as one of the ten best
books of 1987, and her short story "Falling in
Love" received the National Magazine Award
in 1984.

Most of her adult fiction, essentially realist
in style, is set in the fictional southern Manitoba
town of Agassiz. Her stories typically concern
the encounter of young women either
with men who don't deserve them or with unimaginative
old people (grandparents, neighbors,
accidental acquaintances) who have
grown weary of life. Birdsell writes a marvelous
short story: "Night Travelers," "Ladies of the
House," and "The Two-Headed Calf" all share
that irresistibility common to excellent writing.
"Night Travelers," for instance, tells of
a mixed Mennonite-Metis marriage that has
gone wrong. Various members of the family
gradually come to know of the wife's infidelity.
Birdsell's novels excel at introducing conflicts
that the reader longs to see resolved. Middleaged,
eccentric Minnie Pullman starts off The Missing Child (1989) with a vision she has while
floating naked down the Red River at night
that the world is about to experience a second
Noah's flood. Young Amy, early in The Chrome Suite (1995), is marked for life by a ruffian's
kick in the stomach. She manages to blame
all the subsequent sufferings and disappointments
in her life on this youthful tragedy and
the chronic pain beneath her ribs. Birdsell's
The Town that Floated Away (1997) charms
us with the adventures of an irrepressible orphan,
Virginia Potts, who faces an ethical dilemma
she almost does not solve. Like much of
her adult fiction, this story makes use of the
theme or symbol of a catastrophic, worldchanging
flood.


Douglas Reimer
University of Manitoba





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>