<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.asam.023</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Wong, Fee Lee (Wing Tsue) (ca. 1846-1921)</field>
      <field name="author">Webb, Rena</field>
      <field name="text">

 




WONG, FEE LEE (WING TSUE) (ca. 1846-1921)


Wong Family


Between 1848 and 1900 some 200,000 Cantonese
were brought to the United States by
labor contractors. Put to work at menial jobs
in mining camps and on railroad construction
crews, they moved eastward from California
in the wake of new gold strikes. Some of them,
including Fee Lee Wong, found their way to
the Black Hills of Dakota Territory during the
1875–76 gold rush.

Hundreds of gold-hungry prospectors hastily
erected rough cabins and tents along
Whitewood and Deadwood Creeks in narrow
Deadwood Gulch. By the late 1800s the north
end of the mining camp's main street was a
noisy, bustling Chinese village where Fee Lee
Wong, better known as Wing Tsue, established
his thriving business. His shop at 566 Main
Street stocked a wide selection of Chinese
foods and herbs, novelties, silk, tea, porcelain,
and other luxury import gifts. Wing Tsue's
name was listed in the 1880 census along with
212 other Chinese, most of them young men in
their twenties and thirties. Actual numbers
were probably much higher.

Although most of Deadwood's Chinese returned
home or moved on to larger cities as
the gold rush waned, Wing Tsue remained for
forty years, becoming a prominent and respected
businessman. When he brought his
wife, Hal Shek Wong, from China, he announced
she would be pleased to receive wives
of his white business friends in their home on
New Year's Day. In her book Old Deadwood Days, Estelline Bennett described the luxuriously
appointed Wong home and said Mrs.
Wing Tsue herself was "the loveliest bit of exquisite
china I ever saw."

The Wong children, two sons and four
daughters, attended Deadwood's public
schools and Sunday schools. Records of
Mount Moriah Cemetery show the burial of
an eleven-month-old child of Wing Tsue on
January 30, 1895, and the removal of the body
in 1904. Another daughter, born in 1900, died
in 1902.

According to a family biography compiled
by his grandson, Wing Tsue took his family
back to China in 1902, then had difficulty reentering
the United States two years later. Intervention
by a U.S. congressman allowed
him to return to Deadwood. The First National
Bank of Deadwood bought the Wing
Tsue building for $1,055 in 1915 when the Chinese
merchant defaulted on the loan. The
family left Deadwood for the final time in
1919, after Wing Tsue suffered a stroke at a
meeting of the Society of Black Hills Pioneers.
He died in Canton, China, in 1921 at the age of
seventy-five.

See also IMAGES AND ICONS: Deadwood, South Dakota.


Rena Webb
Rapid City, South Dakota




Bennett, Estelline. Old Deadwood Days. New York: J. H.
Sears, 1928. Fielder, Mildred. The Chinese in the Black Hills. Deadwood SD: Centennial Distributors, 1982.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>