<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.war.015</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Crook, George (1828-1890)</field>
      <field name="author">Porter, Joseph C.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CROOK, GEORGE (1828-1890)


Gen. George Crook


George Crook was born on September 8, 1828,
near Taylorsville, Ohio, to Elizabeth Matthews
and Thomas Crook, farmers. He graduated
from the U.S. Military Academy at West Point
in 1852 and served in California and Oregon
fighting Indians until 1861. After serving in the
Civil War as colonel of the Thirty-sixth Ohio
Volunteer Infantry, Crook returned to the Pacific
Northwest.

In 1871 the army ordered Lieutenant Colonel
Crook to Arizona to quell the Apaches.
After a successful campaign, Crook was promoted
to brigadier general in 1873. In 1875 he
assumed command of the Military Department
of the Platte in Omaha, Nebraska.

In December 1875 the government ordered
the army to force Lakotas and Northern Cheyennes
from the Powder River country to Indian
reservations in Nebraska. On June 17,
1876, Crook's Wyoming Column with 1,300
fighting men (including 175 Crow and 86 Shoshone
warriors) fought approximately 1,500
Lakotas and Cheyennes led by Crazy Horse in
the fierce six-hour Battle of the Rosebud, Montana,
where Crazy Horse stopped Crook's advance.
Crook and other officers campaigned
throughout 1876 and early 1877, destroying Indian
villages and disrupting their hunting.
Crazy Horse and other nontreaty Lakotas and
Cheyennes were compelled to surrender during
the spring of 1877.

Crook, who believed that Americans were to
blame for the Indian wars, consistently advocated
Indian rights. In 1878 the government
ordered Crook to arrest members of the Ponca
Tribe who had returned to their Nebraska
homeland from Indian Territory. Crook, seeing
the injustice in this, convinced others to
initiate a lawsuit to stay his orders. In the resulting
case, Standing Bear v. Crook, Judge
Elmer Dundy ruled for the first time in American
history that "an Indian is a person within
the laws of the United States."

In 1882 Crook returned to Arizona, where he
achieved his finest military accomplishment.
In 1883 he led nearly 200 Western Apache
scouts and about fifty soldiers into the Chiricahuas'
sanctuaries in the Sierra Madre of
Mexico. After one skirmish, Crook negotiated
the Chiricahuas' peaceful return to their Arizona
reservation. Crook's superior officer, Gen.
Philip Sheridan, publicly criticized Crook's
Apache policy, and relations between the two
deteriorated to the point that in 1886 Crook
asked to be relieved of his command in Arizona.
Crook returned to the Department of the Platte
until 1888, when he became a major general and
was assigned to command the Division of the
Missouri, headquartered in Chicago. Crook
died there on March 21, 1890. He was survived
by his wife, Mary.

See also NATIVE AMERICANS: Standing Bear / PROTEST AND DISSENT: Trial of Standing Bear.


Joseph C. Porter
University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill




Greene, Jerome A. "George Crook." In Soldiers West: Biographies
from the Military Frontier, edited by Paul Hutton.
Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1987: 115–36.
Schmitt, Martin F., ed. General George Crook: His Autobiography.
Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1960.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>