<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fil.010</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Chaney, Lon (1883-1930)</field>
      <field name="author">Mirsalis, Jon C.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CHANEY, LON (1883-1930)


Lon Chaney


Famous star of silent motion pictures, Lon
(Leonidas) Chaney was dubbed "The Man of
a Thousand Faces" for his elaborate makeups.
He was born to deaf-mute parents in Colorado
Springs on April 1, 1883. His acting career
began in 1902 with comic operas for the Colorado
Springs Opera House. After touring with
several musical comedy troupes, he joined
Fischer's Follies of Los Angeles in 1912. Chaney
began to do bit parts for the Universal Film
Manufacturing Company in 1912, and he used
novel makeups in films as early as The Sea Urchin (1913), in which he played a hunchback.
His breakthrough role was as a con man
pretending to be crippled in The Miracle Man
(1919).

In 1923 Chaney starred in The Hunchback of Notre Dame, and his incredible makeup and
performance as Quasimodo vaulted him to
fame. He achieved superstardom in The Phantom of the Opera (1925), arguably the most
famous of all silent films. The remainder of his
career included many macabre roles at mgm,
often teamed with director Tod Browning, including
The Unholy Three (1925), The Unknown (1925), London after Midnight (1927), and West of Zanzibar (1928). Some of his best performances, however, came in his nonmakeup roles: as a tough drill sergeant in Tell It to the Marines (1927) and as a detective in While the City Sleeps (1928). Chaney appeared in only one sound film, a remake of The Unholy Three (1930), before dying of lung cancer
on August 26, 1930. He appeared in approximately
160 films. His only child, Creighton,
appeared in numerous horror films, billed as
Lon Chaney Jr.


Jon C. Mirsalis
Emerald Hills, California




Blake, Michael F. Lon Chaney: The Man behind the Thousand Faces. New York: Vestal Press, 1990.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>