<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.na.053</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Jumanos</field>
      <field name="author">Hickerson, Nancy Parrott</field>
      <field name="text">

 




JUMANOS

Jumano is the standard ethnonym applied by
scholars to a Native American people who, between
the sixteenth and eighteenth centuries,
were variously identified as Jumano, Humana,
Xuman, Sumana, and Chouman. Modern interest
began in 1890, when Adolph Bandelier
observed that the Jumanos, evidently an important
Indian nation during the early days of
Spanish exploration north of Mexico, had virtually
disappeared from the historical record
by 1700. Scholars have since ranged far and
wide in pursuit of the identity and the fate of
the Jumanos: Frederick W. Hodge believed
them to be Caddoans, ancestors of the Wichitas;
Carl Sauer favored a Uto-Aztecan affiliation,
linking them to the Tarahumaras and
other Mexican Indians; Jack D. Forbes argued
that they were early Apacheans. In 1940
France V. Scholes and H. P. Mera proposed that
"Jumano" was simply a generic term that
Spanish colonists had used to designate all Indians
who painted or tattooed their faces with
horizontal lines; in view of the diversity of
opinion, it is not surprising that this suggestion
found wide acceptance. Recently,
Nancy P. Hickerson has reopened the discussion,
citing inferential evidence that the Jumanos'
language (never recorded) was actually
Tanoan, closely related to that of their trading
partners in the eastern Pueblos of New Mexico.

Bandelier's data provided no clues to Jumano
prehistory, nor did he speculate about
their linguistic or cultural links with other
tribes. During the intervening century, archival
and archeological research has revealed a
fuller–if still incomplete–picture of their adaptation
and possible origins. The Jumanos
ranged from south of the Rio Grande to the
Southern Plains. Within this territory they
were essentially nomadic, although there were
permanent enclaves at La Junta de los Rios
(near present-day Ojinaga, Chihuahua), in
the Tompiro Pueblos of New Mexico, and perhaps
elsewhere. Their eastward movements
were timed to coincide with seasonal rains
and prime bison hunting in the Plains; the
return trip brought the Jumano bands back to
spend the winter at or near the communities
of their trading partners. There, meat, hides,
and other trophies of the hunt were traded
for agricultural produce. Such a relationship
of reciprocity between related farmers and
hunter-gatherers has many parallels and often
develops as an adaptation to changing ecological
conditions.

The historical importance of the Jumanos
rests primarily on their role as intertribal and
interregional traders. This role undoubtedly
developed as a consequence of their pattern of
seasonal migration. The Southern Plains was a
hunting area shared by many Native American
groups–Caddoan, Tonkawan, Coahuiltecan,
and others. The Jumanos established a close
relationship with the Caddos and their neighbors
(the "Tejas" alliance) and became active
agents in trade between these tribes and those
along the Rio Grande. Their routes followed
and linked several river systems, including the
Pecos, Canadian, Brazos, and Colorado of
Texas.

The Jumanos' trade sphere expanded when
they adopted an equestrian way of life, and it
changed in character as they began to deal in
horses. Records of French explorer La Salle's
visits to the Ceni (Caddos) reveal the impact
of the Jumano trade, which provided the Caddo
elite with Spanish clothing, swords, religious
artifacts, and many horses; on the return
trip, hides and peltries were carried for
sale in New Spain. At this time the Jumano
traders were, in effect, serving as Spanish surrogates
in promoting friendly relations between
the "Nations of the North" (the Caddoan
confederacies) and the Spanish Crown.

Even as their interregional trade reached its
height, the Jumanos' territorial base was increasingly
under attack. Apaches and Jumanos
were in contention, both for hunting grounds
and for trade access along the Rio Grande. In
1540 Coronado's expedition witnessed the enmity
between Querechos (Apaches) and Teyas
(probably Jumanos). By 1600 the Apaches had
taken control of the trade at Pecos Pueblo, and
they dominated a wide area east of that site. In
the Tompiro region, farther south, the Jumano
population was augmented by refugees from
the war in the Plains. When the Tompiros also
came under attack, around 1660, the Jumanos
abandoned New Mexico for good; thereafter,
La Junta de los Rios was their only foothold on
the Rio Grande. The Jumanos' trade continued
from La Junta following a route along the
lower Pecos and Colorado Rivers. This route
was broken around 1690, when Apache bands
pushed eastward to the upper Colorado and
the Brazos. Thereafter, the Jumanos had no
intact territorial base, and their activities
as traders came to an end. Remnant groups
around La Junta evidently joined forces with
their conquerors after 1700, when Apache occupancy
extended southward along the Rio
Grande below El Paso.

Throughout the seventeenth century there
were several occasions in which Jumano leaders
acted as spokesmen for their own and allied
tribes, seeking Spanish assistance in defending
their territories and trade routes. In
1682 the Jumano chief Juan Sabeata addressed
such an appeal to New Mexican authorities at
El Paso and escorted a party of soldiers and
Franciscan friars to meet with representatives
of more than thirty Indian nations on the upper
Colorado of Texas. When this effort failed,
a remarkable transregional economic and political
alliance came to an end, and the Jumanos
effectively vanished from the history of
the Southern Plains.


Nancy Parrott Hickerson
Texas Tech University



Hickerson, Nancy P. The Jumanos: Hunters and Traders of
the South Plains. Austin: University of Texas Press, 1994.
Kelley, J. Charles. "Juan Sabeata and Diffusion in Aboriginal
Texas." American Anthropologist 57 (1955): 981-95.
Scholes, France V., and H. P. Mera. "Some Aspects of the
Jumano Problem." Contributions to American Anthropology
and History 6 (1940): 269-99.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>