<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fol.013</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Folk Belief</field>
      <field name="author">Bado-Fralick, Nikki</field>
      <field name="text">

 




FOLK BELIEF

People often use "folk belief" to refer to superstitions,
old wives' tales, and unorthodox
religious and medical practices. This view of
folk belief reinforces a perception of already
marginalized people as more exotic and backward
than previously imagined. Folk beliefs
are better seen as providing insights into how
people live their lives and what they think of as
important. Understood in this way, folk beliefs
and practices provide valuable clues into
how people construct their worlds and bring
meaning to their experiences.

The folk beliefs of the Great Plains reflect
the many groups contained within its vast
boundaries. Indigenous peoples, European
pioneer settlers, and more recent arrivals such
as the Hmong (Laotians) all contribute to the
rich cultural heritage of folklife in the Plains.
Along with traditional beliefs and practices,
each group creates new forms of folk belief
through exposure to unfamiliar terrain, conditions,
and other groups. Folk beliefs thus
reflect a dynamic process of tradition making,
with plenty of room for individual variations
and stylistic differences along with crosscultural
sharing within the region.

Folk belief takes on a regional flavor through
the response of people to their immediate natural
world. For instance, weather signs and
omens form a vital part of folk belief within the
Plains. Examples include "Rain follows the
plow," "Heavy fur on animals means a severe
winter," and "A tornado never hits the junction
of two rivers." Sometimes weather signs
are put in the form of rhymes: "Sunset red and
morning gray sends the traveler on his way /
Sunset gray and morning red keeps the traveler
to his bed."

The world encountered by early settlers in
the Great Plains was filled with wondrous and
formidable creatures, many of which figure
prominently in folk belief. One of the more
unpleasant aspects of Plains life was the abundance
of snakes. Snakes slithered by the hundreds
in massive dens, crawled easily through
the sod walls of Plains homes, and startled
unwary humans and horses alike. A few examples
of snake lore include stories about fabled
"hoop snakes" and "joint snakes" and beliefs
such as "Black snakes will suck cows."

Because of its deadly bite, rattlesnakes hold
a special place in Plains snake lore. Kill a garter
snake, and you'll get rain. But kill a rattler
and get a BIG rain. Watch out for its mate,
however, because "everyone knows a rattler's
mate will come lookin' for it." A rattler's fangs
naturally have special powers: "Be careful
about killing a rattler with a lariat. Its fangs
might get caught in the rope and bite you
when you coil it." If this happens, be sure to
apply plenty of "fresh, warm cow dung" to
cure it. Ironically, rattlers also serve a medicinal
function among Plains folk. To cure a
headache, just place a rattlesnake's rattle in
your hatband.

Of course, if that doesn't cure your headache,
you might try a red bandana, wearing
earrings, or finding a person born in October
to rub your temples. Folk remedies and
charms for good health are abundant throughout
the Plains. "Unlucky enough to get a sty?
Rub a wedding ring on your eye." Or say this
helpful charm: "Sty, sty, come off my eye, and
go to the next passerby." Of course, if that
passerby gives you a black eye, a silver knife is
sure to draw the soreness out! Transference
also works well with warts. Should you get
warts from playing with a toad, simply sell
them to another person or rub them with a
penny and give the penny away.

Many folk beliefs and practices deal with
luck. Find a "four-leaf clover" or a "red ear of
corn" for good. Spill salt and throw some over
your left shoulder to avoid bad. Bad luck at
cards? "Get up and walk around your chair
three times or sit on a handkerchief." Animals
bring luck–crickets and rabbit's feet for good
and crows bad. Some animals bring both
kinds of luck: "If a black cat crosses your path,
it's bad," but "If a black cat comes to stay at
your house, it's good." Just don't kill it, whatever
you do–that's bad. Death, the ultimate
bad luck, comes by many signs: birds flying
into the house, dogs howling at night, rain
in an open grave, and pictures falling from
the wall.

Folk beliefs and practices reveal the challenges
faced daily by Plains folk. They underscore
such things as the importance of good
weather for survival, provide ways of dealing
with the unexpected, and help cope with
the often-precarious conditions of life in the
Great Plains.


Nikki Bado-Fralick
Iowa State University




Hoy, Jim. "Rattlesnakes." In Plains Folk: A Commonplace of the Great Plains, edited by Jim Hoy and Tom Isern.
Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1987: 3–4. Sackett,
S. J., and William E. Koch, eds. Kansas Folklore. Lincoln:
University of Nebraska Press, 1961. Welsch, Roger L.
A Treasury of Nebraska Pioneer Folklore. Lincoln: University
of Nebraska Press, 1966, 1984.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>