<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.rel.003</field>
      <field name="titleMain">ASSEMBLIES OF GOD</field>
      <field name="author">Brown, Gene</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ASSEMBLIES OF GOD

The Assemblies of God, headquartered in
Springfield, Missouri, was founded in April
1914, when 300 ministers and delegates assembled in Hot Springs, Arkansas, and sought a
way to accredit ministers, commission and
support missionaries, select a common biblical
name, and establish a Bible training school.
The convention lasted ten days and was characterized
by passionate preaching, heated debate,
fervent prayer, and an unusual unity that
produced an agreement to form a "cooperative"
fellowship of churches that would not
be an organization but an "organism" empowered
and directed by the Holy Spirit. The
result of this meeting was called the General
Council of the Assemblies of God.

After Hot Springs, successful evangelistic
campaigns were conducted in brush arbors,
tents, town halls, and any other place where
people could gather and seek God. Meetings
were characterized by shouting, unusual physical
manifestations, and testimonies of divine
healing. Preaching was centered on four cardinal
doctrines that included salvation by grace
through faith, divine healing as part of Christ's
atonement, the baptism in the Holy Spirit initially
evidenced by speaking in tongues, and
the imminent return of Jesus Christ to earth.
Early Assemblies of God ministers called it the
full gospel, and it swept through the High
Plains like a prairie fire.

By 1922 the Assemblies of God had established
regional district councils in North
Texas, West Texas, Oklahoma, Kansas, Nebraska,
South Dakota, and North Dakota, all
part of annual district councils that supervised
a growing number of churches. By 1925
the Pentecostal Assemblies of Canada had
formed its own organization and begun a prolonged
period of growth that is still expanding
under the leadership of its present general superintendent,
James McKnight.

The Assemblies of God has flourished
among the independent and highly individualistic
communities of the Great Plains. Two of
the largest districts of the Assemblies of God
are in the Great Plains. In all, more than 1,700
churches and 190,000 members throughout
the Plains make up 10 percent of its total
church membership. Outstanding leaders in
the Assemblies of God, such as Bert Webb,
Bartlett Petersen, Stanley Berg, G. Raymond
Carlson, A. G. Ward, A. H. Argue, E. R. Foster,
Hugh Cadwalder, A. A. Wilson, and the present
general treasurer of the Assemblies of God,
James K. Bridges, have all labored in Great
Plains districts.


Gene Brown
Waxahachie, Texas




Burgess, Stanley M., and Gary B. McGee, eds. "Pentecostal
Assemblies of Canada." In Dictionary of Pentecostal and
Charismatic Movements. Grand Rapids MI: Zondervan
Publishing House, 1988: 695–99. Carlson, G. Raymond.
"When Pentecost Came to the Upper Midwest." Assemblies
of God Heritage 4 (1984): 3–7. Menzies, William W.
Anointed to Serve. Springfield MO: Gospel Publishing
House, 1971.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>