<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.gen.006</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Calamity Jane (1856-1903)</field>
      <field name="author">McLaird, James D.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CALAMITY JANE (1856-1903)


Calamity Jane


Martha Canary (Calamity Jane), the famous
frontierswoman, was born in 1856 in the vicinity
of Princeton, Missouri, the eldest daughter
of Robert and Charlotte Canary. In 1864 the
Canary family joined the gold rush to Montana.
Martha's parents died in the West a few
years later, and Martha was reported alone in
the 1869 census of Piedmont, Wyoming. She
evidently became a prostitute, traveling between
the bustling new Union Pacific Railroad
towns and Wyoming's military posts. At some
point she gained her famous nickname, "Calamity
Jane," probably based on her propensity
for raising a ruckus or because of her calamitous
origins. The first published notice
of Martha bearing her famous nickname appeared
in 1875, when in the capacity of camp
follower she accompanied the "Jenney expedition"
from Fort Laramie to the Black Hills of
Dakota Territory.

Martha's local notoriety increased in 1876
when, again as camp follower, she accompanied
Gen. George Crook's command against
the Sioux; for the remainder of her life, Martha
claimed to have scouted for Crook. Shortly
afterward she joined James Butler "Wild Bill"
Hickok's wagon train headed for the Black
Hills. Though their acquaintance lasted only a
few weeks before Hickok was murdered in
Deadwood on August 2, 1876, the names of
Calamity Jane and Wild Bill Hickok would be
joined in folklore.

Martha gained national prominence in 1877
after Horatio N. Maguire penned a colorful
account of her in his promotional booklet The Black Hills and American Wonderland. His description
was appropriated by dime-novelist
Edward Wheeler for his new "Deadwood
Dick" series, instantly transforming "Calamity
Jane" into a nationally known heroine.

Her life was less glamorous than the dimenovel
descriptions allowed. She worked as a
dance-hall girl, waitress, and laundress, living
with a series of male companions she identified
as husbands. Following early experiences,
she migrated to newly constructed railroad
towns, mining camps, and military posts. She
followed the Northern Pacific Railroad as it
built westward through Montana in the early
1880s, then migrated to the Wyoming region
as railroad extensions were built into interior
regions. For several years she was the companion
of William Steers, a physically abusive railroad
brakeman. They were legally married
several months after the birth of their daughter,
Jessie, in 1887.

In 1895 Calamity Jane made a celebrated return
to Deadwood, selling photographs of
herself in frontier costume. Publicity led to a
contract to tour eastern cities with Kohl and
Middleton's dime museums in 1896. Her
somewhat fictionalized autobiography, Life and Adventures of Calamity Jane, By Herself,
was published during this tour for sale to audiences.
Afterward Martha returned to Montana,
making a subsistence living from sales
of her autobiography and photographs and
from performing menial labor. A generous
woman, she attended people in illness and
shared her meager proceeds; an alcoholic, she
never held lasting jobs nor accumulated property
or wealth.

Exhibiting increasing signs of serious illness,
Martha once again received national
publicity in 1901 when author Josephine Brake
offered her the opportunity to live with her in
New York. Upon her arrival there, Calamity
Jane was exhibited with Colonel Frederic T.
Cummins's "Indian Congress" at the Pan-
American Exposition in Buffalo. Unhappy
and feeling used, Martha returned to Montana,
where her drunken celebrations made
her less and less welcome. In December 1902
she departed for the Black Hills, where she
died in Terry, near Deadwood, on August 1,
1903. She was buried in the vicinity of Hickok.

See also IMAGES AND ICONS: 
Deadwood, South Dakota; Hickok, Wild Bill.


James D. McLaird
Dakota Wesleyan University




Etulain, Richard W. "Calamity Jane: Independent Woman
of the Wild West." In By Grit and Grace: Eleven Women Who Shaped the American West, edited by Glenda Riley
and Richard W. Etulain. Golden CO: Fulcrum Publishing,
1997: 72–92. Jennewein, J. Leonard. Calamity Jane of the Western Trails. Huron SD: Dakota Books, 1953. Sollid,
Roberta Beed. Calamity Jane: A Study in Historical Criticism.
Helena: Montana Historical Society, 1995.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>