<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ct.001</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Cities and Towns</field>
      <field name="author">Conzen, Michael P.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CITIES AND TOWNS


Cities of the Great Plains


Cities were crucial to the European colonization
of the Great Plains, yet when measured
against the power of the protean natural environment,
cities would play little direct role
in defining the perceived human character of
the region. Therein lies the paradox of urbanism
in this vast territory of America, and
its explanation is profoundly geographical.
The primacy of cities for the region's actual
development rests on two themes: the fundamental
importance of urban markets in
the American East and overseas in stimulating
the huge demand for agricultural and mineral
products that the Great Plains could satisfy,
and the urban-based management of the very
colonization system employed to settle people
on the Plains. Furthermore, railroads, those
avid servants of cities, brought settlers to
the region and simultaneously provided them
with an instant network of new urban sites to
coordinate the supply of economic and social
services the region required. On the other
hand, the geographical logic of those supply
lines placed the largest cities at the very rim of
the region, if not wholly outside it, and so the
Great Plains has evolved virtually as the hole
in the urban "doughnut" of America. Consequently,
the urban culture of the Great Plains
is overwhelmingly a small-town culture in
which attitudes and outlook are much closer
to those of the rural vastnesses of their immediate
trade areas than to the tempo and timbre
of the big-city urban web that surrounds them
on practically all sides. Only on the Canadian
Prairies–unlike the American Great Plains,
surrounded on all sides by terrain ill suited
for the building of cities–is the hole-in-thedoughnut
simile less appropriate.


Great Plains Towns in a Continental Context

Towns and cities in the American and Canadian
Great Plains are among the youngest urban
foundations on the continent. Few cities
can trace their urban existence further back
than 1860, and many towns in the region were
founded as recently as the early decades of
the twentieth century. Amarillo and Lubbock,
Texas, Wichita, Kansas, and Regina and Saskatoon,
Saskatchewan, the only sizable cities
centrally on the Plains, were founded in 1887,
1890, 1873, 1882, and 1883, respectively. Associated
with the youth of the region's urban
places is the low level of urbanization overall.
In the four states that are wholly contained
within the region (North and South Dakota,
Nebraska, and Kansas), only 49.5 percent of
the population at the end of the twentieth century
lived in metropolitan areas, as opposed to
79.8 percent nationally, and only five urban
areas in these four states exceeded 100,000
residents. It requires no further statistics to
establish that the Great Plains is a region in
which large cities are only marginally important,
but those geographically peripheral cities
loom large socially and economically within
the actual urban pattern of the region.

The other overarching characteristic of
Great Plains urbanism is the enduring asymmetry of its spatial structure and national
connections. The Plains was settled from the
East, and its towns and cities have historically
looked east for markets, sources of supply, and
general inspiration. The immediate ties of
commerce and urban culture on the Plains
are to the large metropolises of the Middle
West and, more distantly, the northeastern
seaboard. Minneapolis, to take the most pronounced
case, has long enjoyed an extraordinary
westward reach in its economic dominance
of the Northern Plains, making not
only all of North and South Dakota tributary
to its businesses and banking services but also
the entire state of Montana. Not only Billings,
at the western edge of the Plains, but Butte
and Missoula in the mountains have stronger
business ties to Minneapolis than to Seattle,
only a third of the distance away. Similarly,
within the Plains states, urban trade areas
have long been hugely skewed to the west: in
South Dakota, Mitchell newspapers in the
1920s were read as far west as Philip, which is
three times closer to Rapid City than to
Mitchell. In the Canadian Prairies, because of
the triangular shape of the region, such
skewedness tends to be to the northwest or
north of the key urban centers.

The long distances between towns and the
low population densities within so much of
the region dictate that its towns and cities
fulfill only a restricted range of economic and
social functions, and customers seeking advanced
services such as high-tech medical attention,
wider consumer choice, and major
sporting events often need to travel to the
large cities on the region's margins to obtain
them. Since the development of hub-andspoke
service in the deregulated airline industry,
residents south of the forty-ninth parallel
have had to endure decidedly poor and remote
air service. For the same reasons, manufacturing
is an insignificant component of
most towns and cities of the region, except for
oil and gas processing in the Canadian provincial
centers of Calgary and Edmonton. Industrial
activity, if it is based on exports at all, is
generally extremely small-scale or devoted to
repair rather than fabrication. As such, urban
life tends to be replicative rather than innovative
and best developed in the gateway cities
on its margin. These, then, are some of the
abiding features of urban life in the Great
Plains seen within a wider context.



Periods of Urban Life

Notwithstanding the comparative recency of
towns and cities as historical artifacts in the
Great Plains, their appearance on the physical
landscape and in the social fabric of the region
should be seen as the product of a fairly complex
phasing in time and space. It is reasonable
to recognize four broad phases in that emergence:
town life in places established during
the river and droving regime (1850s–1870s);
town life during the phase of railroad colonization
(1870s–1910s); urban life during the
period of early-twentieth-century modernity
(1910s–1950s); and, latterly, the era of urban
polarization and retreat (1950s–present).
Plainly, such historical distinctions are but a
convenience for general understanding. The
key processes attached to each phase can be
found in adjacent phases, particularly when
one considers geography: developments had a
way of spreading from east to west over time,
though very unevenly, and the retreat of urban
life appears to be progressing, with similar unevenness,
from west to east. It is revealing
nonetheless to consider these four phases as
distinct periods of social experience in the
Great Plains, because each has left its own
characteristic marks on the landscape and
echoes within the composite outlook of the
region's population.

Urban origins in the Great Plains predate
the railroad. This may seem obvious, but it
deserves emphasis because the greatest flows
of population into the region occurred during
the railroad period and thus shaped the "majority"
experience that became handed down
as lore through the generations. Before the
1850s, urbanism in the Great Plains was represented
largely by the wealth the fur trade
bestowed on St. Louis, Winnipeg, and Edmonton.
As the tide of European American
settlement pushed up the Missouri River and
territories were organized across the Plains
proper, river towns appeared on the west bank
of the Missouri in Kansas and Nebraska during
the 1850s. Thus, a narrow zone on the eastern
margins of the Plains urbanized under a
steamboat regime (essentially, a potamic or
water-based colonization system), supplying
both military forts planted deep on the frontier
as well as the overland freighting trade,
cattle droving, and the first tentative farm settlements.
Towns were laid out with grandiose
plats from Wyandott to Leavenworth, Atchison,
Bellevue, Nebraska City, Omaha, and
Florence. The river-port system was extended
upriver into Dakota Territory, with Yankton
and Vermillion founded around 1858, as well
as along the lower reaches of the Kansas River.

These river towns owed their morphology
and social character largely to their eastern
predecessors on the Mississippi and Ohio
Rivers, but they represented also the western
limit of this type of urban function as
transshipment points between waterways and
wagon trails. The utility of great rivers as localizing
arteries of commerce and population
dispersion, so fundamental to America as far
west as Missouri, fell foul of the shallow river
conditions and uncertain water levels of the
Great Plains. Settlement would have stalled
had the railroads not caught up with potamic
colonization on the middle Missouri River
during the late 1860s. Nevertheless, the river
towns of the Plains add depth to the urban
record of the region and echo an early a.liation
with water routes that would soon be lost.

Railroads could cross dry terrain with virtual
impunity, and they spearheaded an unprecedented
wave of urban and rural settlement
across the Great Plains from the 1870s
well into the twentieth century. This is the
great era of town construction from scratch.
This second and dramatic phase of Plains urbanization
witnessed a standardization and
corporatization of town founding, inasmuch
as railroad companies developed something
of a science in planting towns at suitable distances
along their lines in hopes of generating
maximum tra.c and perfected the art of
controlling the supply of key urban equipment
such as grain elevators, stockyards, coal
and lumberyards, banks, and hotels, many financed
and owned by businessmen in midwestern
centers such as Minneapolis and Chicago.
In the Canadian Prairies the pattern was
slightly different, owing to the direct role
of the national government in developing the
railroads. However, there was no lack of uniformity
in the planning and look of Prairie
towns north of the forty-ninth parallel.

During this period, regional differences
in the density and location of urbanization
across the Great Plains became quite evident.
At first, the drive to complete several trans-continental
railroad trunk lines produced
lonely linear corridors of towns at several latitudes
across the Plains. Then, as the continental
wheat belt bifurcated into two zones
and surged northwestward into the Dakotas
and Canadian Prairies and southwestward
into Kansas, dense networks of rails and shipping
towns arose in their midst. But try as
they might, settlers could not establish a firm
foothold in certain areas, and the West River
country of North and South Dakota and the
Sandhills of Nebraska would stand out as inimical
to town development. Farther west,
north, and south, the rangelands that stretch
from Montana to Texas and the southern portion
of the Canadian Prairies, which the Palliser
expedition described as an extension
of the Great American Desert, also proved
hostile to more than minimal railroad service,
and, consequently, they saw infrequent town
foundations.

However, all this became framed by the
heady growth of the gateway cities, those
"hinge" nodes that sort the tra.c between the
Great Plains and their neighboring regions.
The trunk railroad pattern ensured that eventually
towns like Calgary and Edmonton, Billings,
Cheyenne, and Denver would prosper
along the western border, while Winnipeg,
Fargo, Omaha, Kansas City, Wichita, Oklahoma
City, and Fort Worth would rise on the
eastern margin.

During the opening two decades of the
twentieth century railroads overpenetrated
the productive portions of the Great Plains, a
miscalculation that the first droughts of the
period would dramatize. This is the last time
new towns would be added to the region's network.
The period lasting roughly from 1910
to 1950 can be distinguished and lent some
coherence by its mixed signals of progress
and retardation. While the limits were being
tested, both by the last pioneering generation
on the farms and by the overconfident and
often overextended railroads, the era also witnessed
the seepage of modernity into the entire
region. Automobiles, electricity, radio, the
movies, modern hospitals, and college education
spread their influence across the Plains,
simultaneously bringing hope of a better life
from the outside as well as reinforcing how
relatively backward many areas on the Plains
were by comparison with more settled areas.

In the same period that agricultural science
was assisting in diffusing better farming methods
applicable to the dry Plains and strong
demand and bumper crops produced occasional
good economic times, other forces were
conspiring to sort out the town system of the
Great Plains in an ominous way. The mailorder
business, for one, undercut the commerce
of local store merchants. The "viability"
of farm trade centers across the region
became the worrisome watchword of the new
rural sociologists, and the first patterns of differential
growth between small towns and
larger centers became clear. The diffusion of
the automobile decreased physical isolation
but simultaneously increased the geographical
consolidation of retailing and other services in
fewer, larger places.

After the Second World War, patterns of
small-town decline across the Great Plains intensified,
and they have continued unabated
to the present. Broad changes in the continental
organization of farming, wholesaling,
and retailing have produced in this region,
as elsewhere, fewer and larger farms, mechanized
production requiring less labor, and a
steady migration of farm and small-town people to the cities within and beyond the region.
Family cars and trucks only permit the heavier
concentration of services in a sparser network
of towns spaced at ever greater driving distances
away.

This fourth period of urban life in the Great
Plains has produced, then, an intractable implosion
of the region's urban pattern. Generations
of investment in town buildings, streets,
plantings, special facilities (most forlornly, the
schools) lie bleaching under the open prairie
skies in numberless towns too small to hold
their populations. By the end of the twentieth
century, very few towns under 15,000 inhabitants
showed any ability to grow, and only
cities at the geographical margins or with specific
and solid functions such as in government,
education, or health seem able to keep
pace with national norms. The result is a
scramble among the region's cities to chase
growth for its own sake, competing within the
national urban system for business investments
at the risk of their tax base, while midsize
cities soak up the small-town migrants
discouraged by job losses and limited economic
and social horizons in the small towns
of their birth. The region is urbanizing at
an unprecedented rate (given the ratio of
city dwellers to rural residents) while losing
the vast majority of its once-urban places. No
other region in North America is undergoing
quite this transformation. Since midcentury
the Plains has been experiencing the "hollowest"
era of its urban history, but it may also be
qualitatively the best.



The Origins of Individual Urban Places

It is a commonplace to characterize urban life
in the Great Plains almost exclusively on the
basis of its small towns and to speak of the
huge sameness among them as if they differed
no more from each other than one generic
strip mall from the next. The first tendency
likely derives from the fringe position of most
of the region's bona fide large cities. Denver is,
after all, no more the metropolis of the High
Plains portion of eastern Colorado than it is
the capital of mountainous western Colorado.
Kansas City also serves two regions of different
economy and culture. The region's large
cities seem more simply members of the national
urban system, more preoccupied with
global positioning than with representing the
interests of their nearby Plains hinterlands, so
the "Plains country town" does sterling duty
as the "default" urban symbol for the region.
But even if this is so, the standard image is
misleadingly simplistic. Not all Plains cities
and towns were platted by railroad tycoons,
milked for their income, and cast to the winds
when no longer useful.

A few Plains urban locations can trace their
essential locations to early trading posts in the
fur trade and forts guarding western trails, and
to this day their proximity to water and to
suitable crossing points for wheeled tra.c explains
more fully their specific siting than any
subsequent feature. Winnipeg, Manitoba; Edmonton,
Alberta; Pierre, South Dakota; Fort
Benton, Montana; and Leavenworth, Kansas,
serve as ready examples. To these can be added
a number of river towns sited as suitable places
for emigrant provisioning and agricultural
trade such as Atchison, Lawrence, and Topeka,
Kansas. This type is distinguished by huge
urban plats designed for speculative land sales
and boosterism, and it prefigured those of
the railroad era. But even before the railroad
arived, spreading agricultural settlement
stimulated the creation of "inland towns"
(i.e., located away from navigable rivers), vast
numbers of which failed to survive, but a
goodly number that did, such as Bottineau
and Cando, North Dakota, invariably did so
by attracting a railroad.


Union Pacific Railroad depot (built 1886), looking west, Cheyenne, Wyoming


The railroads greatly augmented the frequency
and density of speculative railroad
towns on the Plains. Some independent townsite
promoters thought it was sufficient to announce
the mere existence of town plats on
their land, but this rarely su.ced to attract
settlers and generally dissuaded railroads.
Promotion was most successful when undertaken
by the railroads themselves, for they
controlled both local land sales and connection
with the wider world. The key to understanding
the relation of speculative towns to
the railroad is the alignment of railroad tracks
within the plats; by definition, a railroad town
is one wholly oriented to the axis of the rails,
with its linear "railroad reserve." All other
plan patterns denote some more complicated
history of town and railroad.

Two other types of town origin loom large
in the Great Plains. Towns founded as county
seats declare this fact through the designation
of a public square reserved for the county
courthouse. Many actual county-seat towns
lack such features because they were founded
without such ambition, and numerous country
towns contain such squares even though
political history was not to bless them with
the hoped-for prize. Presence and absence of
such prominent elements in the built form of
Plains towns echo the history of such aspirations
and the geographical pattern of their
outcome. In most cases, the primacy of commerce
relegated the courthouse square to a
peripheral position within the town plan.

Last among the key types of town origins
are mining and oil towns. Here the striking
features are the often-chaotic patterns produced
by boom conditions, especially when
aided by restricted sites, such as in the Black
Hills of South Dakota. Awkward topography
and rapid, unplanned growth have given
places like Deadwood and Lead quite singular
curving and terraced townscapes. Often, mining
settlements were strictly company towns,
though such origins did not always guarantee
regular plans and coherent development.

Despite the diversity of urban origins, however,
their initial distinctions have often barely
endured, if at all. Subsequent development has
had a way of generalizing if not standardizing
the layout and built form as well as the social
composition and community dynamics of
many Plains towns. This has produced a high
degree of geographical homogeneity among
them, regardless of function or size, and has
encouraged the emergence of a strong urban
stereotype of the small town on the Plains.



Urban Roles and Town-Country Relations

This stereotype of the Plains small town transcends
population size, although a town's size
clearly betrays the accumulation of functions
that it performs within the region's urban network.
The largest cities on the Plains are the
entrepôt towns, "gateway" cities that not
only act as bulking and processing centers for
crops and livestock raised on the Plains for
onward shipment to distant markets in the
East but also handle through traffic. One cannot
stand on the street bridges that pass over
the railroad yards in Cheyenne, Wyoming,
and Fargo, North Dakota, and fail to appreciate
that the Great Plains is a vast transit region,
a geographical obstacle to freight passing
across the continent from end to end.
Such traffic is almost irrelevant to the region,
except that its maintenance provides some local
jobs. But these gateway cities are more
than entrepots: they are also hubs for people
and goods originating and terminating somewhere
not too far away on the Plains; most
strikingly, now they are portals for air travel.

The purpose of towns and cities on the
Plains has always been primarily to organize
the export of crops, livestock, and minerals
from the region. This necessitates a mostly
dispersed rural population to produce the
materials and supply centers to provide the
essentials of life to that dispersed population.
Hence, "shipping" is the key function of all
such places, regardless of scale. Location on
the transportation arteries of this system has
always been the essence of their success, first
and last via the railroad system, from the first
boisterous frontier cow towns to the prosaic
farm or ranch towns of today.

The smallest shipping points represent
towns–one can hardly call them that–with a
couple of grain elevators, a repair garage perhaps,
and a hundred or so residents. Farther
up the size scale are towns that can still boast a
grocery store, gas station, maybe a bank, and
some other businesses and support a population
of several hundred. Beyond this, there is
one standard function that boosts such towns
into another league: a few hundred towns
have county-seat status. Serving as centers of
county government provides work for a small
host of professionals, including engineers,
lawyers, accountants, politicians, and office
workers whose combined income supports a
thousand residents or more and a correspondingly
wider range of stores and other social
services. Often, county towns contain courthouses
with eye-catching classical or modern
architecture: the higher the Plains (i.e., the
more westerly the location), the lower the pretension.
With just these three lower rungs of
the Great Plains urban hierarchy, we have accounted
for the vast majority of urban places
in the whole region.


County courthouse and surrounding business district, Weatherford, Texas


Between the small service centers and the
gateway cities, the hierarchy supports a few
medium-size cities that derive their importance
from special functions. These are the
state capitals, college towns, and mineral
towns that dot the region with a casual regularity.
Only five capitals of the ten states with
territory in the Great Plains are situated well
within the Plains proper. Colleges, particularly
public institutions, share with other state facilities
such as prisons and medical centers the
historical function of ensuring the permanent
decentralization of state expenditures. Only
the mineral towns, whether mining gold or
pumping oil, obey geology and cluster where
the deposits have been found, in the Black
Hills of South Dakota or the gas and oil fields
of the Permian Basin. The size and facilities of
all these places with special functions create a
different local culture, sometimes more cosmopolitan,
sometimes even more tenuous
than that of farm and ranch urbanism. Midland,
Texas, for example, headquarters of Permian
Basin oil power, was obliged to promote
itself as a retirement town and convention center
due to the decline of oil prices after 1986
and the subsequent contraction of the industry.
The future of Lead, South Dakota, is even
more precarious, following the announcement
in 2000 that its renowned Homestake
Gold Mine was phasing out operations.

What is strikingly absent from the Plains,
however, is large-scale urban manufacturing.
Early city boosters may have hoped for the
expansion of the national manufacturing belt
into the region, but its remoteness from the
majority of the nation's urban demand guaranteed
that it would never really develop
heavy industry. Pueblo, Colorado, has had a
steel industry since the 1880s, but this is an
exception (and even there employment has
fallen from more than 9,000 in the 1950s to
fewer than 700 in 2000). Manufacturing logic
has always placed most final-stage processing
and fabrication close to the markets rather
than the raw materials. While meatpacking
decentralized westward onto the Plains during
the twentieth century, attracting especially
Latino workers, it does not pack the economic
punch of car plants or steelmaking.



People Attracted to Great Plains Towns

Plains towns, like their surrounding rural
areas, acquired their early populations from
three distinct sources: Indigenous peoples,
native-born migrants from the East and Midwest
moving farther west, and foreign-born
immigrants arriving especially from northern
and eastern Europe. Long-established ethnic
groups have contributed significant populations
to local towns in areas where they
have been well represented, such as Native
Americans in eastern Montana, North and
South Dakota, and Oklahoma, Hispanics in
northeastern New Mexico, West Texas, and
southeastern Colorado, and African Americans
in eastern Oklahoma. American migrants
from states to the east have maintained
broad though somewhat mixed zones of latitudinal
movement, so that settlers of eastern
and central Canada, New England, and upper
Midwest heritage were more likely to settle on
the Northern Plains, those of "North Midland"
origin on the Central Plains, and those
from the South on the Southern Plains. Into
this mixture, Europeans came in large numbers,
filling up the open frontier especially in
the Prairie Provinces and the Dakotas but also
localities farther south, often in response to
vigorous promotional efforts.

The "latitudinal" transfer of population to
the Canadian Prairies a century ago from Ontario
and points east was even more pronounced
than south of the border precisely
because of the linear structure of Canada's human
geography. This was especially so for
the English-speaking Canadian and British
migrants, who, because of advantages of language
and petty capital, could often form a
wide and deep small business class that populated
the towns of all sizes across the region.
Nevertheless, this western border was non-ideological
and porous, and many settlers
of British, Canadian, American, and continental
European stock drifted easily back and
forth between American Plains and Canadian
Prairies.

Over time, there have been subtle shifts in
the social composition of Plains towns. Early
on, Canadian and American migrants often
made up the bulk of the small merchant class
because they brought trading experience and
some capital to the frontier towns. Slowly,
as young country people moved to town, the
business class broadened its ethnic complexion,
while retired farmers from strongly ethnic
country communities added further to the social
diversity of the towns. Suggestive is the
proportion of businessmen of Norwegian to
Anglo stock in three North Dakota counties
with strong Norwegian representation, judged
by the ethnicity of advertisers in county atlases
in the early twentieth century. The Grand
Forks County atlas of 1909 contains the names
of ninety Anglo businessmen to fifty-three of
Norwegian stock, and the McHenry County
atlas of 1910 shows forty-seven of Anglo background
and thirty of Norwegian stock. By
1929, however, the Bottineau County atlas was
listing only thirty-eight Anglo businessmen to
seventy-six of Norwegian extraction. Crude
though these comparisons are, they lend some
credence to the notion that Plains towns gradually
extended participation to the would-be
entrepreneurs of their hinterlands. Such opportunities
often provided staging points for
family members to migrate farther up the regional
and national urban ladder.



Three Plains Urban Archetypes

The comparative diversity of urban roles performed
by towns on the Plains might suggest
any number of "typical" towns for the region.
The dominating image of the "plains country
town," on the other hand, works hard against
that. What follows is an attempt to recognize at
least a trinity of typical Plains towns, the better
to capture some of the diversity already noted
while concentrating on characteristics readily
apparent to anyone with an attentive eye. Although
they are selective, these types–the
gateway city, the plains country town, and the
ethnic town–exist clearly in the landscape.


THE GATEWAY CITY

It is virtually impossible to approach the
Great Plains from either east or west by train
today (using what is left of the fabled passenger
rail network of bygone days) without
passing through one of the region's gateway
cities. Even using superhighways, one enters
the region by skirting the edges of one or
another of these great entrepôts. They have
preserved, indeed enhanced, their historic regional
roles while adding new ones pertinent
to the information age. What do these gateway
cities look like, how are they laid out, and
what are their distinctive features?

However much the central skyline of the
gateway city center resembles that of all other
self-respecting American downtowns, with its
tall office buildings and hotels, its ring of
parking lots, and the awkward architectural
remains of a once-thriving shopping district,
what typifies the gateway city is the scale and
land-use dominance of freight-handling facilities
and warehouse districts. Most gateway
centers have modernized their transportation
zones, placing them recurrently on or near the
urban fringe to gain the space for the vast
operations needed. These outlying districts
are impressive enough, but the long history of
transfer functions can be found even closer to
hand, in the near-central railroad depots and
brick warehouse districts that still lurk near
the old downtown, now often transformed
into funky entertainment districts for tourists
and locals alike. Many such districts have
lost numerous structures, victims of bulldozer
redevelopment before old brick became fashionable.
But the remaining warehouse quarters
of cities such as Omaha, Denver, Fort
Worth, Fargo, Cheyenne, and Billings, to
name a few, stand as testimony to the specialized
role these places have long played in
the national system of cities.

The wholesale warehouse districts have always
been tied to the railroads, and even today,
with the importance of truck shipments
and intermodal transport, that link survives
intact. Winnipeg boasts a great array of railroad
yards and transfer facilities, far more extensive
than in most other cities of its population
size.

Gateway cities that collect the produce of
the corn and wheat belts also sport impressive
stands of grain elevators, not just the two or
three silos of the country shipping point but
huge regiments of cylindrical concrete towers,
taller than any office block in town, that
march across and blot out the horizon, as in
Atchison, Kansas, and Enid, Oklahoma. Gateway
towns opposite ranching areas used to
boast massive stockyards, such as at Fort
Worth and Omaha, but they are now victims
of a westward decentralization of slaughtering.
Even here, however, the cultural heritage
of such facilities lives on in the urban folk
life of such places, sustained by the nostalgia
of country and western music or perhaps a
famed steakhouse.

Not only the physical equipment of railroad
and truck transshipment distinguishes these
cities but also their historical occupational
profiles and still distinctive business and political
cultures, with hotels catering to visitors
to the cities' wheat exchanges and stockmen's
clubs, where deals still get made. In a world of
corporate globalism, more of the action is taking
place elsewhere, but the original purposes
of these gateway cities have yet to be wholly
eclipsed. Many have begun to market their
special character for tourists, even at the risk
of bowdlerization. But theatrics apart, what
remains undisputable about the Plains gateway
city is its long involvement in transport,
transfer, and storage and its geographical
function as the eye of the needle through
which all the produce of the Plains is threaded
on its way to distant processing and divided
profit. The Plains gateway cities are large
enough each to have a peculiar morphology,
but, at base, the essential features are common
to all of their class.



THE PLAINS COUNTRY TOWN


Bradshaw, Nebraska, 1889


The scale of the Plains country town is personal.
It is, in its archetypal form, small
enough to be walked through from end to end
in a few minutes. It is also virtually predictable
in its contents and layout. Whether a "parallel"
town, a "T-town" (referring to the axes of railroad
reserve and commercial core), or a fusion
of the two patterns, the Plains country town
is like some outsize combination of a child's
erector set, wooden play blocks, and model
train layout. Invariably stamped on the prairie
as if with a cookie cutter by a railroad department
or a speculative land company and
named after the railroad's owner or other such
chance association, the town pays almost total
obeisance to the railroad tracks.

The genre can be encapsulated in its essentials
by the case of Bradshaw, Nebraska, in
1889. Founded in 1879 by the Burlington and
Missouri River Railroad Company, the town
site had a population of 150 residents the very
next year. Created to serve the farmers of western
York County, about fifty-five miles west of
Lincoln, Bradshaw in 1889 offered three grain
elevators along the tracks, together with the
train depot and a small stockyard. Railway
Street ran like a cordon along the railroad reserve,
from which sprang Lincoln Street, the
business thoroughfare–all one and a half
blocks of it. There was a lumberyard, a hotel, a
bank, two liveries, thirty business buildings,
three churches, a school, and eighty-nine residences.
Strikingly, while the business district
was compact, reflecting the importance for
merchants of proximity to the railroad and
other businesses, the town's residential space
was loose. After only ten years of life and with
112 empty building lots still available in the
"Original Town," landowners felt it essential
to plat four "additions," more than doubling
the lotted area of the town. Forty-one residences
lolled over this additional territory,
their owners quite unable to contemplate settling
on the still vacant land of the Original
Town.

Such was the planning and early development
history of Bradshaw. Vary the orientation
by which the tracks pass through the locality,
shift the street alignments accordingly
so that they meet at some angle, but no matter
what adjustments are made, this is the physical
blueprint for tens of thousands of "towns"
planted upon the soil of the Great Plains. As
speculations, their future was subject to the
fortunes of remote markets, railroad politics,
and sometimes chicanery, and thousands
failed almost before they had started. Importantly,
though, here was a model plan, infinitely
expandable should the town succeed,
simple, orderly, but allowing for the disorder
of individual choice, and a perfect mechanism
for transferring the risks of urban growth to
the shoulders of optimistic settlers while relieving
them of a sizable chunk of their initial
capital. Town boosting had long become a
high art in American life by the time the Plains
were settled, and its exquisite delineation on
the ground can be found right here. Bradshaw
in 1889, even in its elegant simplicity, was a
cipher for all the utilitarian philosophy of urbanism
that played itself out like a hapless tide
across the Great Plains.



THE ETHNIC TOWN

The ethnic town or, more often, village is
the third recurrent urban archetype of the
Great Plains. Consistent with the small scale
of most "urban" places on the Plains, many
small urban centers have emerged and even
survived as de facto ethnic towns, representative
of the high concentration of ethnic settlement
in the surrounding countryside, sometimes
even remaining virtually exclusive to
one group. The larger cities have developed
their varied neighborhoods of immigrant
complexion, from Calgary to Kansas City, but
these seem little different from those of big
cities all over the nation. It is precisely on the
Plains proper, where the relative recency of
concentrated ethnic settlement has preserved
a sharper ethnic imprint on the landscape
than in most older sections of the two countries,
that one can find still viable, if not always
vibrant, ethnic towns. Their comparative isolation
favored slower national integration,
and some groups have resisted assimilation
through various habits and attitudes, hence
the survival to this day of numerous small but
stubbornly distinctive and self-conscious ethnic
enclaves throughout the Great Plains.

The Canadian Prairies and the Northern
Plains of the United States stand out in this
respect, given their availability for settlement
during the last great tides of agrarian immigration
from central, eastern, and northern
Europe around the turn of the twentieth century.
From the Ukrainian, German, Scandinavian,
and French Canadian tracts around
Edmonton to the Doukhobor districts north
of Saskatoon and the French Canadian and
Mennonite settlements in the southern and
western hinterlands of Winnipeg, small urban
centers with names like Wostok, St. Alphonse,
and Halbstadt dot the western Canadian landscape.
In their churches and ethnic business
names, if not always in other features, they
display their ethnic affiliation, indeed, their
urban purpose. Farther south, the pattern is
repeated from North Dakota to central Kansas
and even in Oklahoma and Texas. Few travelers
can fail to observe the Native American
characteristics of towns serving Indian populations
in Oklahoma such as Okmulgee, where
the old Creek Council House graces the courthouse
square, or Tahlequah, where street signs
are bilingual. Likewise, the cultural character
of the Volga German communities of Ellis
County, Kansas, finds expression in the unexpected
and strikingly tall Catholic church
steeples of Pfeifer, Liebenthal, St. Catharine,
and, most dramatically, the "Cathedral of the
Plains" at Victoria (Herzog).


Nicodemus, Kansas


Nicodemus, Kansas, stands as a celebrated
all-black town settled by "Exodusters" in 1877.
Founded as a speculative town site to attract
blacks from the South, it was paired as a business
enterprise with Hill City, a town twelve
miles to the west in Graham County intended
for white settlers. Twelve years later, the Union
Pacific Railroad bypassed Nicodemus and
connected Hill City, which consequently became
the county seat. Thereafter, Nicodemus
stagnated, losing most of its businesses to
nearby Bogue and to Hill City. Notable are
Nicodemus's long but narrow town lots, which
measure 25 by 160 feet. The modal urban lot
width in the Great Plains is closer to 50 feet.
While Hill City also has 25-foot-wide lots, the
early town plan there included city blocks reserved
for a school and a courthouse, amenities
lacking in the Nicodemus plan, the purest
expression of monetized land. While Nicodemus
never filled up the plat, it hung on as
a social center for the surrounding African
American farming community and in 1976
was designated a national historic landmark
for its significance in interpreting the nation's
cultural heritage. To this day, Emancipation
Day is celebrated on the informal "town
square."




City Building and Urban Culture

The progress of American urbanism in the
Great Plains is measured for the most part
in the diffusion of amenities, technical accomplishments,
and stylistic fashions over
time from the largest trendsetting metropolises
of the nation–New York, Chicago, St.
Louis, and their ilk–to the gateway cities and
medium-size centers of the region. It is hardly
to be expected that great new urban innovations
would emanate from the modest cities of
the Plains. Nevertheless, Plains urbanism was
developed in the late nineteenth century by
the most routinized and relentless booster
program up to that period. Because the Great
Plains was so vast and seemingly so underdeveloped,
boosting was particularly required
in order to steer capital into the region and
attract settlers.

In some ways, Plains urban centers were
designed and built with "cutting-edge" concepts
on a tabula rasa. Even today, commercial
districts and residential sections reflect the
new norms of building technology, design,
and furnishings current during the period
from the 1890s through the 1920s. Since the
first wooden merchant structures lasted at
least a few years, most of the more substantial
buildings that replaced them came in the
twentieth century. Where high-rise business
structures were built, they sported the new
wide, Chicago-style windows that let in light
rather than the narrow, New York–influenced
vertical windows long popular in the East.
Residences featured the latest in standard
manufactured design, and Plains towns must
account for a disproportionate national share
of the mail-order homes shipped by Sears,
Roebuck and Company and its competitors.

Occasionally, Plains cities claimed national
attention for some avant-garde creation,
which is best illustrated in the case of two
state capitols. By 1918 Nebraska's capitol
was deemed insu.cient, and, following a national
competition won by Bertram Grosvenor
Goodhue, in 1922 construction began on
the present mini-dome-capped skyscraper edifice,
with Art Deco decoration produced by
local artists. North Dakota followed in 1931,
when fire destroyed the existing traditional
capitol, opting for a spartan, slablike office
high-rise building designed by a consortium
of local and Chicago architects. Such choices
reflect the ethos of modernity that was permeating
the Plains in the early twentieth century
and a certain rejection of unnecessary frills in
favor of functionalism. By and large, however,
such banner projects found few echoes in the
private sector, and on the residential front,
most urban neighborhoods, of whatever social
class, have tended to exude a comfortable,
traditional normality of external appearance
while displaying internal modernity in proportion
to economic capacity. Much of this
stems from the relative homogeneity of income
in Plains towns, where the extremes of
urban wealth generated by high industrialism
have generally been absent or muted. Only the
banker's house, the doctor's house, and the
funeral home stand out as conspicuous ornaments
in many a Plains country town. And
only rarely does a public building seek to astound,
as the Corn Palace in Mitchell, South
Dakota, in a folksy way surely does.

In public infrastructure, Plains cities have
performed close to the national average for
their size. A late start in city building for most
towns meant that the thresholds of population
needed to capitalize services such as electric
power plants, street railways, telephones, and
modern hospitals kept these places from being
precocious centers of innovation. But in terms
of their own development, many such services
came sooner in the experience of residents
than they had in older cities. Street railways are
a good indicator: while Plains cities were not
innovators in this realm, they adopted the
technology with eagerness. Street railways
came early in the individual history of Plains
towns because their fast initial growth promised
the patronage needed to sustain the railways.
Installations were so numerous in towns
below 5,000 population, however, that many
failed and caused the towns to wait a number
of years before reinstallation was successful. In
other respects, urban centers on the Plains
generally attempted to participate in urbanistic
novelties in proportion to their size and
enterprise. Most cities of any size, for example,
display some of the boulevards and curving
drives so fashionable in the trendsetting metropolises
of the East and Far West, even if on a
modest or token scale.



Generalizations

Risking dispute through inevitable selectivity,
several generalizations about urbanism in the
Great Plains might be proposed here. First,
the past is still young in Plains towns and
cities, and it is not very important while economic
growth is apparent. The past becomes
more important when growth subsides and
economic stress increases, because it offers a
validation of prior accomplishments and a
means to recapitalize the built environment
through historic preservation and tourist edification.
Some of the striking public sculpture
to be found in some Plains towns featuring
heroic ox teams plowing the prairies
(in Fargo, North Dakota) or cowboys herding
steers (Billings, Montana, and Dodge City,
Kansas) now seeks to develop this urban
theme.

Second, in county seats on the Plains, government
functions are generally secondary to
commercial ones, so it is very rare, in contrast
to such places in older sections of the nation,
to find the courthouse square the central focus
of the town; rather, it is the railroad and its
shipping facilities that define the town and
attract the business district, leaving the civil
government precinct well off to the side in the
town plat.

Third, the size and variety of urban equipment
in the Great Plains is inversely proportional
to altitude. Generally, the farther west
towns are located, the more limited are the
size, number, and architectural pretension of
their business buildings and government installations.
In western North Dakota, for example,
some county courthouses in exterior
appearance are almost indistinguishable from
neighboring real estate agencies and grocery
stores. In the western Canadian north–south
corridor from Edmonton to Lethbridge, however,
many quite pretentious public buildings
stand in contrast to this rule.

Fourth, the formal urban threshold is set
comparatively low in the Great Plains, and for
historical reasons. Incorporation laws in several
Plains states, for example, permit places
to be regarded as "cities" at population levels
far below the national norm. Kansas provides
the most extreme case, allowing settlements of
as small as 300 inhabitants to incorporate as
cities. Elsewhere in the modern world, such
places would be considered mere hamlets or
villages. Indeed, even in Kansas they are usually
that, despite their legal status.

Fifth, many rim cities and state and provincial
capitals are prominent in service functions
such as health facilities, insurance companies,
and educational campuses, drawing
from sometimes-enormous tributary areas.
Billings, Montana, offers hospital facilities
that would scarcely be found in cities of comparable
size in, say, Illinois, because distances
on the Plains are so large and such cities few
and far between. Conversely, and sixth, transshipment
and wholesale activities are more
significant than manufacturing. This imbalance
suggests the extent to which Plains urban
centers are more dependent on the outside
world than those in denser settled regions, a
characteristic once shared with the traditional
South but no longer.

Seventh, all cities and towns actually on the
Plains are close to the countryside, in a mental
sense, through their intimate economic ties
and the remoteness of sophisticated urban distractions.
A broadly engendered "small-town
mentalité" exists even in the larger centers, reinforced
by migration patterns from the rural
areas and knowledge of their rural constituencies'
demands for cultural inspiration.

Lastly, Great Plains urbanism is a kind of
derivative and dependent urbanism. There is
comparatively little that was, or is, original,
self-sustaining, or generative about urban
life in the Great Plains. In terms of the two
nation-states across which the Great Plains extend,
their urban landscapes reflect classically
those of internal colonization. Nevertheless,
they represent an extraordinary production of
urban life across a vast land.

See also AFRICAN AMERICANS: Exodusters /
ARCHITECTURE: Grain Elevators; 
Nebraska State Capitol; 
Public Buildings; Warehouse Districts / 
EUROPEAN AMERICANS: Settlement Patterns, Canada; 
Settlement Patterns, United States / 
IMAGES AND ICONS: Corn Palace; 
Deadwood, South Dakota / PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT:
Palliser's Triangle / TRANSPORTATION:
Railroads, United States; Railways, Canada.



Michael P. Conzen
University of Chicago





Artibise, Alan F., ed. Town and City: Aspects of Western Canadian Urban Development. Regina: University of Regina,
Canadian Plains Research Center, 1981. Bennett,
John W., and Seena B. Kohl. Settling the Canadian-American West, 1890–1915: Pioneer Adaptation and Community Building: An Anthropological History. Lincoln:
University of Nebraska Press, 1995. Hamilton, Kenneth
Marvin. Black Towns and Profit: Promotion and Development in the Trans-Appalachian West, 1877–1915. Urbana:
University of Illinois Press, 1991. Haywood, C. Robert. Victorian West: Class and Culture in Kansas Cattle Towns.
Lawrence: University Press of Kansas, 1991. Hudson, John
C. Plains Country Towns. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota
Press, 1985. Melnyk, Bryan P. Calgary Builds: The Emergence of an Urban Landscape, 1905–1914. Calgary: Alberta
Culture, Canadian Plains Research Centre, 1985.
Mothershead, Harmon. "River Town Rivalry for the Overland
Trade." Overland Journal 7 (1989): 14–23. Nelson,
Paula M. After the West Was Won: Homesteaders and Townbuilders in Western South Dakota, 1900–1917. Iowa
City: University of Iowa Press, 1986. Reps, John W. Cities of the American West: A History of Frontier Urban Planning.
Princeton NJ: Princeton University Press, 1979. Schellenberg,
James A. Conflict between Communities: American County Seat Wars. New York: Paragon House, 1987. Stock,
Catherine McNicol. Main Street in Crisis: The Great Depression and the Old Middle Class on the Northern Plains.
Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1992.
Tauxe, Caroline S. Farms, Mines, and Main Streets: Uneven Development in a Dakota County. Philadelphia: Temple
University Press, 1993. Toms, Donald D. The Flavor of Lead: An Ethnic History. Lead SD: Lead Historic Preservation
Commission, 1992. West, Carroll Van. Capitalism on the Frontier: Billings and the Yellowstone Valley in the Nineteenth Century. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press,
1993. Wetherell, Donald G., and Irene R. A. Kmet. Town Life: Main Street and the Evolution of Small Town Alberta.
Edmonton: University of Alberta Press, 1995.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>