<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ct.052</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Tulsa, Oklahoma</field>
      <field name="author">DeSpain, S. Matthew</field>
      <field name="text">

 




TULSA, OKLAHOMA

Tulsa, located on the Arkansas River where it
bends to flow south, is Oklahoma's second
largest municipality and the principal urban
center for the state's northeastern region. In
2000 the population of Tulsa proper was almost
400,000 and of the greater metropolitan
area 803,000.

The Lochapokas, a band of Creek Indians
who endured their own "trail of tears" to Indian
Territory in 1836, first settled the area and
named their settlement Tallasi. Unable to pronounce
Creek properly, whites called the settlement
Tulsi or Tulsa. The community remained
isolated and experienced little growth
until after the Civil War, when Reconstruction
agreements and land allotments forced upon
the Creeks by the federal government opened
the area to white settlement. In 1882 the Frisco
Railroad made Tulsa a terminus, and the town
became the hub for the region's cattle industry.

It was a series of oil discoveries in northeastern
Oklahoma between 1901 and 1907 (the
largest being the Cushing field) that really
transformed Tulsa by bringing a flood of laborers,
speculators, and financiers. The city's
population surged from 7,298 in 1907 to 72,000
in 1920. As the epicenter for the midcontinent
field, Tulsa was labeled the "Oil Capital of the
World." Companies like John D. Rockefeller's
Prairie and Gas Company, the Texas Company
(now Texaco), and Gulf Oil operated out of
Tulsa. Pipelines reached out, carrying crude
to Port Arthur, Texas, Whiting, Indiana, and
Baton Rouge, Louisiana. By 1927 Tulsa was
headquarters of 1,500 oil-based companies.
Those who profited most from oil built extravagant
homes. One such subdivision, Maple
Ridge, became a national historic site.

Besides the prosperity and progress of the
1920s, Tulsans created and experienced one of
the nation's worst acts of terror against African
Americans. On June 1, 1921, deputized and
armed white mobs invaded and shot, robbed,
and burned their way through Greenwood,
the city's northern African American section.
Planes dropped turpentine bombs, and machine
gunners shot fleeing residents. Thirty-five
city blocks were razed. At least thirty-nine
and probably many more black Tulsans were
murdered. Not a single individual was brought
to justice. A state investigation in 2000 recommended
reparations to survivors and their
descendants. Racism persisted as Tulsa became
a hotbed of Ku Klux Klan activity during
the 1920s.

The collapse of the petroleum industry in
1930 accentuated the Great Depression's effect
on the city. But, as with many western cities,
World War II defense industries rescued Tulsa,
stimulated and diversified its economy, and
transformed its demography. Tulsa became
a leading manufacturer of military aircraft
and home to companies like Douglas Aircraft.
Tulsa was also a training center for British,
Canadian, and American pilots at the Spartan
Aircraft Company and School. Cold war defense
spending and a prospering aeronautical
industry confirmed the city's renewed
prosperity, making Tulsa the regional center
of aviation production (with companies like
North American and McDonnell-Douglass)
and commercial services (American Airlines).
Prosperity also led to Tulsa being labeled
"America's Most Beautiful City" in 1957.

During the 1960s and 1970s Tulsa, like other
American cities, became the victim of suburban
sprawl, with new suburbs clustered
around new commercial centers. The suburbanization
resulted largely from white flight
to the south and east. The result created many
Tulsas: North Tulsa was predominantly African
American, West Tulsa stayed working
class, East Tulsa grew with the expanding middle
class, and South Tulsa remained predominantly
upper class. The federal government
also made Tulsa one of ten urban centers selected
for the program to relocate Native
Americans during the 1950s and 1960s; Tulsa
now has the highest per capita Native American
population of any metropolis. Tulsa continues
to attract immigrants from a variety of
ethnicities. Recent grassroots and municipal-level
efforts have begun to unite the various
Tulsas.

Today, numerous industries and information-
based services unrelated to oil, agriculture,
or aviation are located in Tulsa. In
addition to its economic, political, and educational
prominence, Tulsa is also a major cultural
center. It is home to two world-class art
museums, the Philbrook Museum of Art and
the Thomas Gilcrease Museum, which boasts
one of the world's largest and most prestigious
collections of western and Native American
art and artifacts. Tulsa is the smallest American
metropolis to support professional fulltime
ballet and opera companies as well as
a symphony orchestra. Professional hockey,
baseball, and soccer teams make Tulsa their
home. In the 1970s the 'Tulsa sound" of J. J.
Cale and Leon Russell greatly influenced rock
music, and the musical scene remains important
today. Music and cultural festivals include
Oktoberfest, Reggaefest, the Juneteenth Blues
and Jazz Festival, the Greenwood Jazz Festival,
and the Tulsa University Powwow. Because of
the high quality and diversity of life there,
Tulsa has been labeled an all-American city.

See also AFRICAN AMERICANS: Tulsa Race Riot / ART: Gilcrease, Thomas / INDUSTRY: Petroleum, United States.


S. Matthew DeSpain
University of Oklahoma




Debo, Angie. Tulsa: From Creek Town to Oil Capital. Norman:
University of Oklahoma Press, 1943. Ellswourth,
Scott. Death in a Promised Land: The Tulsa Race Riot of 1921. Baton Rouge: Louisiana State University Press, 1982.
Goble, Danney. Tulsa!: Biography of the American City.
Tulsa OK: Council Oak Books, 1997.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>