<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.mus.009</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Cochran, Eddie (1938-1960)</field>
      <field name="author">Wishart, David J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




COCHRAN, EDDIE (1938-1960)

Musician Eddie Cochran 
     

Eddie Cochran, the pioneering rock and roll
songwriter, singer, and guitarist with the
James Dean good looks, was a product of a
Plains background, even though his place of
birth remains disputed. Some rock references
maintain that he was born in Oklahoma City;
others have him coming into the world in Albert
Lea, Minnesota. The date, October 3,
1938, is not in dispute, nor is the fact that his
parents moved from Oklahoma City to Albert
Lea at some point during the 1930s. Cochran
himself claimed Oklahoma City as his hometown,
and the country and western music that
his parents absorbed in Oklahoma was a formative
influence on the young musician.

By the time the family moved on to California
in 1953, Eddie Cochran had become an
accomplished guitarist. He started his career as
backup guitarist to hillbilly singer Hank Cochran
(not related), but his big break came when
he teamed up with songwriter Jerry Capehart
and obtained a recording contract with Liberty.
The hits started coming in 1957, and he
soared into prominence in 1958 with "Summertime
Blues," that raucous outburst of teenage
frustration and rebelliousness. More hits
followed, including "C'mon Everybody" and
"Somethin' Else," and Cochran seemed positioned
to move up alongside Elvis Presley as a
superstar when, in 1960, he embarked on a
tour of Britain with his friend Gene Vincent.
The tour was a great success; both artists were
already superstars in Britain. Cochran played
his last concert at the Bristol Hippodrome on
April 16. The following day, Easter Sunday,
on the way to Heathrow Airport, their car
crashed into a lamppost, killing Cochran and
badly injuring Vincent.

Eddie Cochran, despite his early death, had
a lasting impact on rock music. Many artists,
including the Sex Pistols and, most famously,
the Who, have recorded his songs. He was inducted
into the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame in
1987.


David J. Wishart
University of Nebraska-Lincoln





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>