<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.sr.011</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Crosby, Bob (1897-1947)</field>
      <field name="author">Rattenbury, Richard C.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CROSBY, BOB (1897-1947)

Among the best and most colorful steer ropers
and all-around hands in early rodeo, Bob
Crosby was born on February 27, 1897, in
Midland, Texas. Raised around Kenna, New
Mexico, he developed into a seasoned cowhand
prior to becoming a rodeo contestant in
1923 at New York's Yankee Stadium.

Known as "Wild Horse Bob" on the circuit,
Crosby always competed aggressively. In 1925,
1927, and again in 1928 he captured the combined
all-around titles at both Pendleton and
Cheyenne, thus retiring the coveted Roosevelt
Trophy. This remarkable feat–amassing the
most cumulative points among the broncriding,
steer-roping, bulldogging, and wild
horse-racing events–amounted to three
world championships in the era before official
titles were declared.

Bob Crosby specialized in the roping events.
He won the calf-roping title at Madison Square
Garden three times and the steer-roping title
twice at Cheyenne and four times at Pendleton.
In the late 1930s and 1940s, while operating
his Cross B Ranch near Roswell, New Mexico,
Cosby took part in a series of celebrated,
matched steer ropings against Carl Arnold and
the Weir brothers. He is remembered for his
lucky black hat, his string of great roping
horses, and his tenacity in competing and winning
even with serious injuries.

Once declared the "King of the Cowboys"
by Life magazine, Wild Horse Bob Crosby
died in a Jeep accident near his New Mexico
ranch on October 20, 1947. He was inducted
into the National Cowboy and Western Heritage
Museum's Rodeo Hall of Fame in 1966.


Richard C. Rattenbury
National Cowboy and Western Heritage Museum




Bob Crosby, Biographical File, National Cowboy and
Western Heritage Museum Archives, Oklahoma City. Porter,
Willard H. Who's Who in Rodeo. Oklahoma City: Powder
River Book Company, 1982. Westermeier, Clifford P.
Man, Beast, Dust: The Story of Rodeo. Lincoln: University
of Nebraska Press, 1987.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>