<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.060</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Nye, Gerald (1892-1971)</field>
      <field name="author">Pedeliski, Theodore B.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




NYE, GERALD (1892-1971)

Sen. Gerald P. Nye of North Dakota gained
prominence as one of the most outspoken of
Great Plains isolationists in the pre–World
War II period. Born in Wisconsin on December
19, 1892, Nye moved to North Dakota in
1916 and became a small-town newspaper
publisher. In 1924 he was an unsuccessful independent
candidate for Congress. When Sen.
Edwin F. Ladd of North Dakota died in 1926,
Nye emerged as the dark horse interim appointment
of Gov. Arthur G. Sorlie. He won
his first election on a platform of "North Dakota
for North Dakotans." In his first term he
voiced typical populist conspiracy themes of
the exploitation of farmers and little people by
big business and banks. In the early 1930s he
supported Father Charles Coughlin and his
goal to control the evils of capitalism and Dr.
Francis Townsend's plan to give every person
over sixty a pension of $200 a month. He initially
supported the National Recovery Administration
but then felt it had been completely
co-opted by industry.

In 1933 Nye gained national prominence by
heading an investigation of the munitions industry
in which he cast the industry as profiteers
and warmongers. The late 1930s saw
Nye's isolationist views come to fruition in the
Neutrality Acts of 1936 and 1937. After war
broke out in Europe in 1939, Nye worked with
the America First Committee and protested
any efforts to aid Britain or defend our freedoms
on the high seas. He even sought to investigate
the movie industry, especially Jewish
film producers, alleging bias in demonizing
Germany. Pearl Harbor undercut Nye's support.
He mellowed his views to offer support
for the war, but in 1944 he was defeated. His
defeat was less over the war issue than such
local issues such as his divorce and hasty reremarriage,
his Chevy Chase lifestyle, and his
failure to bring home the bacon to the home
folks. He died in Washington DC on July 18,
1971.


Theodore B. Pedeliski
University of North Dakota




Cole, Wayne. Senator Gerald P. Nye and American Foreign
Relations. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press,
1962.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>