<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ha.015</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Gonzales, Corky (b. 1928)</field>
      <field name="author">Ingen, Linda Van</field>
      <field name="text">

 




GONZALES, CORKY (b. 1928)


Corky Gonzales (under banner) speaks at war protest in front of the capitol, Denver, Colorado, 1970.


Rodolfo "Corky" Gonzales is best known for
his contribution to the Chicano movement.
Born in Denver, Colorado, on June 18, 1928,
Gonzales became one the most dynamic and
influential leaders of the Mexican American
struggle for self-determination and cultural
pride in the 1960s and 1970s.

The son of a migrant father from Chihuahua,
Mexico, Gonzales grew up in a Denver
barrio amid poverty, discrimination, and hard
work. His mother died when he was two years
old, leaving Gonzales, the youngest child, in
the care of his father and seven siblings. Nicknamed
"Corky" at a young age by one of his
older brothers, Gonzales spent much of his
youth working alongside family members in
the sugar beet and potato fields of northern
and southern Colorado.

Gonzales attended numerous public schools
in the Denver area. In 1944, at age sixteen, he
graduated from Denver's Manual High School.
Gonzales completed one term at the University
of Denver but found the costs of further attendance
prohibitive. Nevertheless, he pursued
knowledge, learning not only from his experiences
and the many people he met but also
from reading the likes of Federico García
Lorca, Pablo Neruda, John Steinbeck, and Ernest
Hemingway. Gonzales's intellectual and
creative capacity is evident in his many writings—
hundreds of speeches, letters, and editorials,
two plays, and many poems. His widely
read poem, "I Am Joaquín," first published in
1967, has become one of the major pieces of
Chicano literature. Revealing the cultural and
spiritual conflicts in the Chicano identity, the
poem inspired Chicano pride and activism.

Gonzales developed a strong, charismatic
presence early in life. He drew crowds as an
amateur boxer and became one of the best
fighters of the time. He won the National Amateur
Athletic Union Bantamweight Championship
in 1947, and until 1955 fought professionally
in featherweight divisions, with
seventy-five wins, nine losses, and one draw.
In 1988 Gonzales was inducted into the Colorado
Sports Hall of Fame, the first Latino to be
so honored.

Gonzales's first foray into politics centered
around the Democratic Party. He campaigned
for Quigg Newton for Denver mayor in 1947,
and as a district captain in Denver County he
organized Latino support for the Democratic
Party in the 1950s. In 1960 he led the Colorado
"Viva Kennedy" campaign. Gonzales himself
ran unsuccessfully for office, including a bid
for Denver City Council in 1955, the Colorado
House of Representatives in 1964, and mayor
of Denver in 1967. In 1965 he was appointed
director of Denver's War on Poverty.

Increasingly frustrated by partisan wrangling,
Gonzales publicly resigned from the
Democratic Party in 1967. He had begun to
shift his focus to the Crusade for Justice, which
he and other community activists founded in
1966. A grassroots, human-rights cultural center
located in Denver, the Crusade for Justice
became an important site for Chicano activism.
Gonzales represented the organization
throughout the nation, as he gave speeches,
conducted forums, and otherwise inspired
and organized Chicanos to action. Under his
leadership, the Crusade for Justice hosted
three annual National Chicano Youth Liberation
conferences. More than 1,500 Chicano
youths attended the first conference in 1969.
They produced goals for the Chicano movement
and introduced the concept of Aztlán in
the document Espiritual de Aztlán. Gonzales
purposely focused on the younger generation
of Mexican Americans, finding them receptive
to his major themes of Chicano nationalism,
self-determination, and cultural and historical
pride.

In 1970 Gonzales formed the Colorado La
Raza Unida Party, a third-party political organization
dedicated to the goals of the Chicano
movement. At the party's first national convention
in El Paso, Texas, in 1972, Gonzales
vied unsuccessfully against Texas La Raza
leader José Angel Gutiérrez for the national
chairmanship. At issue in the campaign was
Gonzales's emphasis on ethnic nationalism
against Gutiérrez's political pragmatism.

While becoming a significant public leader
of the Chicano movement, Gonzales remained
dedicated to his family in Colorado. In 2001 he
celebrated more than fifty years of marriage to
his wife, Geri Romero de Gonzales, with his
eight children, eighteen grandchildren, and
many great-grandchildren. Although slowed
by a serious automobile accident in 1988 and
heart surgery in 1989, Gonzales remains active
and is working on his autobiography.


Linda Van Ingen
University of Nebraska at Kearney




Gonzales, Rodolfo "Corky." Message to Aztlán: Selected Writings of Rodolfo "Corky" Gonzales. Houston: Arte Público
Press, 2001. Marín, Christine. A Spokesman of the Mexican American Movement: Rodolfo "Corky" Gonzales and the Fight for Chicano Liberation, 1966–1972. San Francisco:
R and E Research Associates, 1977. Vigil, Ernesto V.
The Crusade for Justice: Chicano Militancy and the Government's War on Dissent. Madison: University of Wisconsin
Press, 1999.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>