<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ind.045</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Petro-Canada</field>
      <field name="author">Ferguson, Barry</field>
      <field name="text">

 




PETRO-CANADA

Petro-Canada is an integrated petroleum corporation
based in Calgary, Alberta. It combines
"upstream" oil and gas exploration and
refining with a "downstream" national chain
of service stations. Petro-Canada is the second
largest petroleum company in Canada and the
largest Canadian-owned operation.

Petro-Canada, founded in 1975 as a petroleum
exploration company, was owned by the
federal government. During the 1970s and
early 1980s, the world was preoccupied by the
issues of oil and gas scarcity and cost, and
Canada was divided by debates about the effects
of foreign ownership as well as by federal-provincial
disputes over petroleum taxation
and export regulations. As a result, and unlike
many "crown corporations" created by federal
and provincial governments in strategic industries
in twentieth-century Canada, Petro-
Canada was less a conventional state enterprise
than an instrument of specific national policy
in two key ways. First, Petro-Canada was capitalized
by the federal treasury through direct
cash transfers rather than by bond issues. The
company acquired a number of Canadian subsidiaries
of international oil firms, including
Atlantic Richfield in 1976, Pacific Petroleum
in 1979, Petrofina in 1981, and British Petroleum
in 1983. Second, when the government of
Canada created a new National Energy Programme
(NEP) in 1980, a statist reaction to the
energy crisis, the nep granted Petro-Canada
the federal share of oil and gas prospects on all
federal crown land, including Arctic and Atlantic
offshore prospects as well as a share of
Syncrude Canada's northern Alberta bituminous
sands synthetic oil.

The federal election of 1984 saw a change of
government and national energy policy. The
new policies of fiscal restraint, free trade, and
privatization reoriented Petro-Canada to a
more conventional petroleum company. In
1991 it issued common shares, creating private
ownership in about 20 percent of the company.
In 1995 a larger issue of shares reduced the
federal government stake to below 20 percent.
The company acquired other firms, including
Gulf Canada's service stations in 1985 and the
Amerada Hess holdings in 1995. Petro-Canada
is the operator of the large Hibernia oil field,
which became the first producing field in the
Atlantic offshore in 1997, and is currently developing
other offshore fields as well as a new
bituminous sands project.


Barry Ferguson
University of Manitoba




Fossum, John E. Oil, the State, and Federalism: The Rise and Demise of Petro-Canada as a Statist Impulse. Toronto:
University of Toronto Press, 1997. Foster, Peter. Self-Serve: How Petro-Canada Pumped Canada Dry. Toronto: Macfarlane,
Walter and Ross, 1992. Petro-Canada, Annual Reports,
1976–2000.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>