<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.078</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Webb, Walter Prescott (1888-1963)</field>
      <field name="author">Reinhartz, Dennis</field>
      <field name="text">

 




WEBB, WALTER PRESCOTT (1888-1963)

Photograph of Walter Prescott Webb

    
A child of the Great Plains, Walter Prescott
Webb was one of the preeminent historians of
the region and of the American western frontier.
He was born on April 3, 1888, in Panola
County, East Texas, on the southern fringe of
the Great Plains and grew to manhood in the
farmland of the Stephens-Eastland Counties
area of West Texas. After graduating from high
school and before going on to the University
of Texas at Austin for his higher education in
1909, Webb taught in several of the local country
schools. At the University of Texas he completed
his bachelor's degree in history in 1915
and became a member of the history faculty in
1918. He became a particularly close friend of
the western writer J. Frank Dobie and the
Texas naturalist Roy Bedichek while at the
University of Texas.

Webb earned his master's degree from the
University of Texas in 1920, writing his thesis
on the Texas Rangers. In 1922, at the age of
thirty-four, Webb took a leave of absence from
his faculty duties to pursue a doctorate in history
at the University of Chicago, but he failed
to complete the degree and returned to Austin
a year later. Webb finally received his doctorate
from Texas in 1932, having submitted the
previously published The Great Plains (1931)
as his dissertation. For his many scholarly
achievements (he wrote or edited more than
twenty books), the University of Chicago presented
him with an honorary doctorate of
laws in 1958. Among his accomplishments
were the books The Texas Rangers (1935), Divided We Stand (1937), and The Great Frontier
(1952). Webb was a Harkness Lecturer at London
University in 1938, the Harmsworth Professor
of American History at Oxford University
in 1942–43, president of the Mississippi
Valley Historical Association (Organization of
American Historians) in 1954–55, and president
of the American Historical Association
in 1958.

Webb married Jane Oliphant on September
16, 1916; they had one daughter, Mildred Alice,
born on July 30, 1918. Almost two years after
Jane's death, Webb married Terrell Maverick,
the widow of San Antonio mayor and New
Deal congressman Maury Maverick, on December
14, 1961. Webb died in an automobile
accident near Austin on March 8, 1963.

Webb drew much of his love and understanding
of the Great Plains from his own life
and the writings of historians of the American
frontier, especially Frederick Jackson Turner.
In The Great Frontier, Webb even went so far
as to expand Turner's ideas on the lure of the
frontier into a global arena. But clearly Webb's
major work was The Great Plains. It is a pioneering
work not only in regional and frontier
history but also in environmental history
and historical geography. Webb argued that
the frontier of settlement halted at the eastern
edge of the Great Plains (he called it a "cultural
fault line") because European American
institutions and settlers were not prepared for
a semiarid environment with few trees and
less water. In Webb's view, settlement proceeded
only after technological advancements
such as the six-gun, windmill, and barbed
wire allowed farmers and ranchers to master
the environment. But Webb realized that
aridity would continue to be a major regional
problem, and because of this he questioned
whether large populations could be sustained
indefinitely in the Great Plains. Webb also
noted the powerful impact of the Plains environment
on those who came to settle there
and the effect of the region on the rest of the
country. Historically and methodologically,
Walter Prescott Webb showed how to understand
the Great Plains, and more than any
other scholar he defined the Plains as a North
American region.

See also FOLKWAYS: Dobie, J. Frank.


Dennis Reinhartz
University of Texas at Arlington




Furman, Necah S. Walter Prescott Webb: His Life and His Impact. Albuquerque: University of New Mexico Press,
1976. Owens, William A. Three Friends: Roy Bedichek, J. Frank Dobie, Walter Prescott Webb. Austin: University of
Texas Press, 1967.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>