<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pe.012</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Black-Tailed Prairie Dog</field>
      <field name="author">Hygnstrom, Scott E. VerCauteren, Kurt C.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BLACK-TAILED PRAIRIE DOGS

"A BLack-Tailed Prairie Dog photographed at Wichita Mountain Wildlife Refuge. Note that it has an ear tag" (Leonardo Weiss)


The black-tailed prairie dog (Cynomys ludovicianus)
is a medium-sized burrowing rodent
that lives in colonies or towns. About five billion
prairie dogs inhabited the Great Plains in
the early 1900s. The largest prairie dog colony
on record, in Texas, measured 100 miles wide
by 250 miles long.

Black-tailed prairie dogs are social animals
and have twelve distinct calls and various postures
that they use to communicate with others.
They warn each other of danger with a
short series of barks and signal all is clear with
a spectacular jump-yip call. Each family group
defends an area of about one acre. When two
prairie dogs meet, they often touch their teeth
together. This "kiss" is used to distinguish a
family member from a stranger.

Black-tailed prairie dogs are active year-round.
During the day, they feed on grasses,
clip tall plants, and maintain their burrows.
The vegetation in a colony is shorter and consists
of different species than the surrounding
grasslands, resulting in unique islands of habitat.
More than 200 species of wildlife have
been observed in the vicinity of prairie dog
towns. Species that are closely associated with
prairie dogs include the mountain plover, ferruginous
hawk, burrowing owl, and the endangered
black-footed ferret. Songbirds and
small mammals frequent towns in search of
food and shelter. Prairie dog burrows provide
homes for deer mice, cottontail rabbits,
and prairie rattlesnakes. Prairie dogs also
are food for several predators, including the
golden eagle, badger, coyote, and swift fox.

Historically, bison grazed on prairie dog
towns. Humans replaced the bison with cattle
and much of the prairie with crop fields. Since
1900, populations of prairie dogs have been
reduced significantly in some areas and eliminated
in others, largely due to cultivation of
prairie soils, efforts to poison prairie dogs,
and residential development. The black-tailed
prairie dog was recently proposed for listing as
a threatened species under the federal Endangered
Species Act. The listing of the black-tailed
prairie dog was determined to be "warranted
but precluded," and their status is now
reviewed annually. Several federal and state
agencies, Native American tribes, conservation
organizations, and individuals are developing
plans and programs to ensure the
long-term viability of prairie dog populations
and minimize the impacts of prairie dogs on
private landowners. Prairie dogs provide recreation
for nature observers, photographers,
and the sporting public. With proper management,
populations can be maintained at levels
that ensure the natural heritage and biodiversity
of the Great Plains.


Scott E. Hygnstrom
University of Nebraska-Lincoln
Kurt C. VerCauteren
USDA/APHIS/Wildlife Services




Hoogland, John, L. The Black-tailed Prairie Dog—Social
Life of a Burrowing Mammal. Chicago: University of Chicago
Press, 1995. Hygnstrom, Scott E., and Dallas R. Virchow.
"Prairie Dogs." In Prevention and Control of Wildlife
Damage, edited by Scott E. Hygnstrom, Robert M. Timm,
and Gary E. Larson. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Cooperative
Extension, 1994: 1385–96.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>