<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fil.067</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Zanuck, Darryl F. (1902-1979)</field>
      <field name="author">Custen, George F.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ZANUCK, DARRYL F. (1902-1979)

Darryl F. Zanuck and Oscar for "Gentlemen's Agreement"
    

Darryl Francis Zanuck was born on September
5, 1902, in Wahoo, Nebraska. His father,
Frank Zanuck, and his mother, Louise Torpin
Zanuck, were an unhappy couple. After the
death of an older brother in an accident Darryl
became an only child, and when his parents
divorced he lived with his mother, dividing the
year between Glendale, California, and Oakdale,
Nebraska, the home of his maternal
grandparents. Though this cannot be verified,
Zanuck claimed to have first thought of working
in film at the age of seven or eight, when he
was hired as a movie extra. Restless and energetic,
the diminutive young man lied about his
age and at fifteen enlisted in the army. Private
Zanuck saw action on the French and Belgian
fronts during World War I, and this wartime
experience left a strong imprint on his life,
later recalled in a number of films, most notably,
The Longest Day (1962).

After his discharge he worked in a series
of unsatisfying jobs. With only an eighthgrade
education, he nevertheless persisted as a
writer. He finally succeeded in placing some of
his short silent scenarios at Universal and the
FBO Company (a forerunner of RKO). Often
generously borrowing from other film or stage
sources, the young writer, barely nineteen,
wrote quickly, drawing his inspiration from
tabloids and pulp fiction. Hired in 1924 by
growth-oriented Warner Bros., his big break
came when his wildly successful scenarios
made Rin Tin Tin the studio's biggest draw.

Soon an almost atavistic energy and an intuitive
grasp of all aspects of filmmaking, absorbed
at the studio, caused Zanuck to outgrow
his screenwriting limitations (he was notoriously
weak with dialogue), and with a
string of hits credited to his three screen
names, he rose quickly to become Warner's
head of production before he was thirty. As
production chief he practically invented the
genres of the gangster film, the biopic, and the
backstage musical. He used his love of tabloid
and pulp to turn the American cinema (which
was reaching for a new direction with the advent
of sound) away from the British-derived
gentility of rival producers Irving Thalberg
and David Selznick and toward a distinctive
but contradictory American world of urban
crime and small-town nostalgia. Before he left
the studio in a dispute with its difficult owners
he had signed a number of memorable stars
(James Cagney, Edward G. Robinson, and
Barbara Stanwyck among them) and produced
a number of legendary films such as
The Jazz Singer (1927), The Public Enemy
(1931), and Forty-Second Street (1933).

In 1933 Zanuck joined forces with mogul
Joseph Schenck to found Twentieth Century
Pictures. Two years and more than a dozen hit
films later, Zanuck merged his company with
Fox Films to form Twentieth Century Fox.
From 1935 to 1956, under the title vice president
in charge of production, he ruled the
studio uninterrupted (except for military service
in World War II) and virtually unquestioned.
He supervised every detail of every
film, creating careers for Tyrone Power, Sonja
Henie, Marilyn Monroe, and Betty Grable,
and he took several established figures (notably,
Shirley Temple and Alice Faye) to new
heights of popularity. His studio program was
divided between controversial prestige films
like The Grapes of Wrath (1940) and The Snake Pit (1948) and escapist musicals and films of
small-town nostalgia. Although Zanuck almost
never returned to Nebraska, the imprint
of small-town Plains life was always a strong
presence in his vision of the cinema. During
the studio era, more than a quarter of his studio's
films were set in small towns at the turn
of the century, giving moviegoers a highly
nostalgic, almost regressive vision of a United
States that was becoming increasingly urban
and populated by non-wasp immigrants.

Leaving Fox in 1956, Zanuck became an independent
producer, operating largely out of
Paris. But after five failed productions, it appeared
as if Zanuck, the recipient of a record
three Thalberg Awards and three Oscars for
best picture (How Green Was My Valley, 1941;
Gentleman's Agreement, 1947; and All about Eve, 1950), had lost his touch. He surprised
everyone and made a stunning comeback with
his blockbuster version of the D day operation
The Longest Day. In 1962, with his old studio
nearly destroyed by poor management and
the costly fiasco of Cleopatra (1963), Zanuck
ousted the head of the corporation, Spyros
Skouras. While he operated from the New
York office, he placed his twenty-eight-yearold
son, Richard, in charge of the studio. With
hits like The Sound of Music (1965) and The Planet of the Apes (1967) series, it appeared as
if Zanuck could go on forever. But a changed
set of power relations in the motion picture
business and a string of costly box office
bombs made in an attempt to imitate The Sound of Music resulted in Zanuck's summary
dismissal in 1971.

Impaired by Alzheimer's disease, Zanuck
was taken back by his estranged wife, Virginia,
whom he had left in 1956, and he died quietly
out of the limelight on December 22, 1979. At
his funeral Orson Welles recalled him as the
most gifted Hollywood producer of all, one
whose greatest assets were his personal loyalty
and his strength in story construction. Few
people were able to see past his outlandish
mogul behavior (oversized cigars, swinging
a polo mallet, an endless string of malapropisms)
to observe that Zanuck was one of
the industry's most creative and courageous
giants. Even though he left the world of the
Plains at a young age, of all the old-time producers
his voice was the most genuinely American
from the inside, a perspective that suffuses
almost every film he made. He brought to the
American cinema a populist's sense of fair play,
a no-nonsense patriotism, a love of simple stories,
and a dose of social criticism.


George F. Custen
City University of New York, College of Staten Island, and Graduate Center of the City University




Custen, George F. Twentieth Century's Fox: Darryl F. Zanuck and the Culture of Hollywood. New York: Basic
Books, 1997.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>