<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pe.004</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Armadillos</field>
      <field name="author">Meinzer, Wyman</field>
      <field name="text">

 




AMARILLOS


Amarillo


The nine-banded armadillo, Dasypus novemcinctus,
is a member of the order Xenarthra,
which includes slow-moving and highly specialized
creatures such as sloths and anteaters.
Historically a creature of South America, the
coastal prairies, and extreme south Texas, the
armadillo extended its range during the twentieth
century into the Plains region of Texas,
Oklahoma, Kansas, and southern Nebraska.
Since 1981 the armadillo has been the official
state mascot of Texas.

With long claws on all of its toes, the armadillo
is a proficient digger. Other physical aspects
include a bony carapace protecting the
entire dorsal area of the body and nine bands
between the rump and shoulders allowing
flexibility in body movement. The head, protected
by a bony plate, can be withdrawn into
the shell when perceived or real danger is near.
Overall body coloration is a grayish brown.
About 90 percent of the armadillo's diet consists
of insects and various species of invertebrates
such as crayfish and millipedes.

Population densities within its range vary
widely and are dictated by soil types and
favorable habitat. Densities tend to be high
where loose sandy soil exists along streambeds
and in woodlands and lower in areas where
tighter clay-based soils predominate. The denning
habit of the armadillo is novel in that a
single animal may excavate and occupy several
dens within its range. These lairs are located
along stream banks, beneath boulders, and
around tree trunks. Armadillos do not hibernate,
but they do stay underground for extended
periods in freezing weather.

The armadillo's reproduction system involves
delayed implantation. Breeding occurs
in late July, but the fertilized ovum remains in
the uterus for about fourteen weeks without
development. By November, normal development
resumes and the young are born four
months later as identical quadruplets of the
same sex.


Wyman Meinzer
Benjamin, Texas




Davis, William B., and David J. Schmidly. The Mammals of
Texas. Austin: Texas Parks and Wildlife Press, 1994. Smith,
Larry L., and R. W. Doughty. The Amazing Armadillo.
Austin: University of Texas Press, 1984.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>