<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ea.006</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Czechs</field>
      <field name="author">Garver, Bruce M.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CZECHS

Czechs were among the largest groups of continental
European immigrants to settle on the
American Great Plains from 1865 through
1914. Of the more than 620,000 Americans
who reported Czech to be their mother tongue
in the 1920 census, 22.8 percent, or 141,782,
lived in the six Great Plains states from Texas
through North Dakota. Ten years earlier,
125,140 citizens in the same states constituted
23.6 percent of all Czech Americans nationwide.
Of the latter group, 72.8 percent resided
in Nebraska and Texas and the remaining 27.2
percent in Oklahoma, Kansas, and the Dakotas.
An additional 5,308 Czech Americans in
1910 lived in the states of New Mexico, Colorado,
Wyoming, and Montana. Of these residents,
a majority had settled on the High
Plains. Within the above ten states, at least
90 percent of all Czech Americans resided
east of the 100th meridian and primarily
in eastern and southeastern Nebraska, eastcentral
Texas, central Oklahoma, northcentral
Kansas, southeastern South Dakota,
and eastern North Dakota. Almost all of these
citizens lived on farms or in small towns. In
this enormous ten-state area, the only city
with a large Czech American population was
Omaha, which ranked fourth nationally in
this regard after Chicago, Cleveland, and New
York City. From the 1870s to the 1950s Omaha
was second only to Chicago as an American
Czech-language publishing center and home
to the Hospodár, the largest Czech-language
agricultural periodical in the world.

By contrast, few Czechs migrated to the Canadian
Plains, or to Canada as a whole, before
U.S. immigration quotas in 1921 and 1924
made Canada a more attractive destination.
The 1921 census put the national Czech population
at only 8,840. Yet Czechs were present in
the Canadian Plains as early as the 1880s: Kolin
in Saskatchewan was probably the first settlement.
By the early twentieth century Winnipeg
had a significant Czech population.
Most of these early settlers were farmers,
miners, and artisans. Among the Czechs who
migrated to the Prairie Provinces in the 1920s
were sugar beet farmers who settled around
Lethbridge, Alberta.

Like many European immigrants of the period
1865 through 1914, most Czechs departed
from regions characterized by "agricultural
overpopulation." The typical Czech immigrant
couple left a farm of ten to fifty acres
in size that was not large enough to support
a family. Other landless Czech immigrants
seldom had capital and usually sought employment
in large industrial cities, notably
Chicago, where one in four Czech Americans
resided by 1920. In the trans-Missouri
West, Bohemian Czechs predominated in Nebraska,
South Dakota, Kansas, and Oklahoma,
whereas Moravian Czechs were more
numerous in Texas and North Dakota.

Czech immigrants were divided not only by
social class, occupation, and regional origin
but also by religious differences. At least half
of all Czech immigrants up to 1914 were "freethinkers"
(svobodomyslné Cesi) who chose
not to affiliate with any organized religion and
who established fraternal and benevolent associations
to advance many of the same goals
as those promoted by churches: fellowship,
community solidarity, and civic service. Outstanding
among these associations were the
Sokol, dating from 1862 in Bohemia and 1864
in the United States, and the various benevolent
associations, including the CSPS (Ceskoslovanský podporuici spolek or Czecho-Slavic
Benevolent Society) and its trans-Mississippi
offshoots and rivals, the ZCBJ (Západni ceská
bratrská jednota or Western Bohemian Fraternal
Association), founded in Omaha in 1897,
and the SPJST (Slovanská podporuici jednota
státu Texasu or Slavonic Benevolent Order of
the State of Texas), founded in 1898 and affectionately
referred to as the "Special People
Jesus Sent to Texas." The founding of the ZCBJ
by trans-Mississippi members of the CSPS reflected
their desire to admit women to membership
on the same terms as men and to obtain
lower insurance premiums for western
lodge members, who tended to be younger
and have longer life expectancies than eastern
industrial workers.

Nearly half of all Czech immigrants were
practicing Catholics, who established Czechspeaking
parishes in almost all urban and
rural areas with sizable Czech populations.
Protestants numbered no more than 5 percent
of the Czech American population and organized
independent congregations only in
Texas. In the other Great Plains states, fledgling
Czech Protestant congregations developed
with the support of mainline Protestant
denominations, notably the Presbyterians. After
several decades of acculturation, tens of
thousands of Czech freethinkers and their descendants
joined liberal Protestant denominations
or returned to their ancestral Catholic
faith. Czech-speaking Jews usually a.liated
with local synagogues and other Jewish organizations,
and some, like the Rosewater and
Brandeis families in Omaha, rose to positions
of political and commercial leadership.

Similar social, occupational, and religious
divisions were evident among the tens of thousands
of Czech immigrants who came to the
United States immediately after World War I
and before the immigration quotas. The most
recent waves of Czech immigrants–in 1938–
39, 1948, and 1968–fled Nazi or Communist
oppression and included a larger percentage
of professional and managerial people. These
waves flowed heavily into the largest American
and Canadian metropolitan areas.

Three times–after 1914, 1939, and 1948–
Czech Americans, regardless of occupation
or religious outlook, made common cause
with a majority of Slovak Americans. Their
first joint effort supported the Czechoslovak
National Council abroad during World War I
in its successful effort to establish an independent
Czechoslovak republic. In early September
1914 Czech Americans in Omaha conducted
the first public subscription of funds
to support Czech interests against the Austro-
Hungarian government. The Czech National
Bazaar of Freedom (Ceský národní bazar
swobody) in Omaha in September 1918 was the
largest of many American fundraisers for the
Czechoslovak independence movement led by
T. G. Masaryk.

After Nazi Germany's occupation of Bohemia
and Moravia on March 15, 1939, Americans
of Czech and Slovak ancestry, including
Roman Hruska from Nebraska, met at the
University of Chicago to help former Czechoslovak
president Edvard Bene¡s organize a
Czechoslovak government in exile and work
for the restoration of Czechoslovak independence.
Similarly, during the cold war, many
Czech American and Slovak American organizations
welcomed immigrants who had fled
from Czechoslovakia after the Czechoslovak
communist coup of February 1948. These organizations
also helped expose Czechoslovak
communism's ongoing corruption, mendacity,
and disregard for human rights. The restoration
of democracy and a market economy to
the Czech Republic and Slovakia after November
1989 facilitated an intensification of
personal and institutional contacts between
Americans of Czech ancestry and the citizens
of the Czech Republic.

See also ARCHITECTURE: Czech Architecture.


Bruce M. Garver
University of Nebraska-Omaha




Garver, Bruce. "Czech-American Freethinkers on the
Great Plains, 1871–1914." In Ethnicity in the Great Plains,
edited by Frederick Luebke. Lincoln: University of Nebraska
Press, 1980: 147–69. Gellner, John, and John
Smerek. The Czechs and Slovaks in Canada. Toronto: University
of Toronto Press, 1968. Jerabek, Esther. Czechs and Slovaks in North America: A Bibliography. New York:
Czechoslovak Society of Arts and Sciences in America and
Czechoslovak National Council of America, 1976.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>