<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pd.012</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Brown, John (1800-1859)</field>
      <field name="author">Winkle, Kenneth J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BROWN, JOHN (1800-1859)

John Brown, an abolitionist extremist, heightened
sectional tensions and fomented violence
before the Civil War by leading the "Pottawatomie
Massacre" in Kansas in 1856 and
the raid against the federal arsenal at Harpers
Ferry, Virginia, in 1859. Brown was born in
West Torrington, Connecticut, on May 9,
1800, and moved with his family to Hudson,
Ohio, at age five. A tanner by trade, Brown
married twice and reared twenty children.

Brown inherited from his father a religious
antipathy toward slavery that was reinforced
by the religious ferment of the Second Great
Awakening. He adopted a strict Calvinist belief
in predestination, divine election, and human
depravity that prompted him to consider
slavery a sin, which he was chosen by God to
help eradicate. During the 1830s, when abolitionists
such as William Lloyd Garrison increasingly
appealed to religious conscience,
Brown developed an uncompromising hostility
toward slavery and joined the radical abolitionist
movement that demanded immediate
emancipation. While living in Springfield,
Ohio, Brown attacked slavery with heightening
militancy, aiding runaway slaves, associating
with the African American abolitionist
Frederick Douglass, writing antislavery essays,
and citing the Bible in defense of violent resistance.
During the 1840s he developed a reputation
for proposing impractical schemes for
fomenting rebellion in the South, including
guerrilla warfare.

When passage of the Kansas-Nebraska Act
in 1854 led to armed resistance in Kansas,
Brown settled near Osawatomie with five of
his sons and their families. He joined the Free
State guerrilla movement and commanded a
company of twenty men known as the Liberty
Guards. Enraged by the sack of Lawrence, a
Free State stronghold, Brown led a raid on
May 24, 1856, against a settlement at Pottawatomie
Creek, killing five southern settlers. For
the next four months, a veritable civil war
raged in the territory, claiming 200 lives and
earning the label "Bleeding Kansas." After a
proslavery counterattack against Osawatomie
in August, Brown fled Kansas.

Hailed as a hero among northern abolitionists
and excoriated as a lunatic among southern
defenders of slavery, Brown accepted support
from a group of abolitionists dubbed the
"Secret Six." He spent the next three years lecturing,
raising funds, aiding runaway slaves,
writing, and organizing his raid against Harpers
Ferry. On October 16, 1859, Brown seized
the federal arsenal at Harpers Ferry with a
force of eighteen men, including five free African
Americans, in hopes of igniting a widespread
slave revolt. By the time federal troops
recaptured the arsenal two days later, Brown's
followers had killed four men and suffered ten
casualties, including two of Brown's sons.
Brown's impassioned self-defense as he and six
followers underwent trial, conviction, and execution
made him a martyr among abolitionists
and a popular antislavery crusader throughout
the North. His execution, on December 2, 1859,
became a political issue, inflamed sectional tensions,
and inspired the Civil War hymn that
began with the line "John Brown's body lies a
mould'ring in the grave."


Kenneth J. Winkle
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Oates, Stephen B. To Purge This Land with Blood: A Biography
of John Brown. New York: Harper and Row, 1970.
Rawley, James A. Race and Politics: "Bleeding Kansas" and
the Coming of the Civil War. Philadelphia: Lippincott,
1969.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>