<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ag.030</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Fairs</field>
      <field name="author">Ambler, Cathy</field>
      <field name="text">

 




FAIRS


Hog exhibit, Shawnee County, Kansas, 1918


As carnivals ready rides to serve eager customers,
youths finish grooming livestock for
judging, and community groups tidy fundraising
booths, excitement builds as communities
anticipate the opening day of their annual
fair. The constancy of fair activity from
early settlement through today attests to their
importance as economic, social, and cultural
events, as well as their ability to adapt to the
changing needs of Plains residents.

Early agricultural fairs were significant
events in fledgling Great Plains communities.
As settlement spread, town boosters competed
to attract as many new immigrants to an
area as possible. Started and funded mainly
by merchants and stockbreeders, fairs became
impressive showcases for the production capabilities
of an area's fertile soil. Piles of lush
apples–the bigger the better–visually guaranteed
a region's potential and proclaimed
that success was only a matter of hard work.
Every local, state, and regional promoter tried
to make their fair exhibits the most enticing,
since boosters knew the economic benefits of
promoting a fair "open to the world."

Though organized mainly by merchants,
early agricultural societies needed farmers to
enter their crops and animals for display and
judging, and farmers attended fairs to socialize
and see the bounty of new consumer products.
Horse racing, carnivals, and sideshows
provided something for everyone and increased
gate receipts. When confronted with
bad weather or cycles of drought and depression,
which kept attendance down, fairs struggled
to maintain financial stability.

Among unusual fairs on the Plains were the
Indian International Fairs in Muskogee, Indian
Territory (now Oklahoma), which began
in 1874, and the Trans-Mississippi and International
Exposition in Omaha, Nebraska, in
1898, which included an Indian Congress. The
congress took on a Wild West show atmosphere
with sham battles staged to increase
gate receipts.

Fairs changed significantly between 1900
and 1950. During the two world wars, agricultural
production was critical in both the
United States and Canada, and Great Plains
communities celebrated agricultural successes
at their fairs. Instead of the promotional
events of earlier days, fairs became more educational,
highlighting agricultural production,
education, and pride of place. To aid
fairs financially, many states legislated tax support,
and in Canada, provincial governments
and towns provided assistance grants.

Since World War II fairs have met the
changing needs of Great Plains residents. As
the number of farmers declined and the size of
farms increased, fair organizations adjusted.
Agriculture is still featured, with shining new
implements on display and awards for crops
and animals, but fairs now serve mixed purposes
for more diverse communities. Contemporary
fairs often celebrate a cultural heritage
tied to the pioneer image of the Great
Plains featuring cowpokes, rodeos, and saddle
club events. Famous country-western stars attract
fairgoers from large urban areas and
rural settings alike.

Despite changes in organization, emphasis,
and funding, Great Plains fairs have endured.
From the Texas State Fair to the Calgary Exhibition
and Stampede, fairs remain community
celebrations where agricultural products
of the region are displayed, and where friends
and neighbors socialize, gossip about town
events, see the sights, encounter new experiences,
and refresh some awareness of who
they are and where they live.


Cathy Ambler
Kansas State Historical Society




Ambler, Cathy. "The Look of the Fair: Kansas County
Fairscapes, 1854–1994." Ph.D. diss., University of Kansas,
1996. MacEwan, Grant. Agriculture on Parade: The Story
of Fairs and Exhibitions of Western Canada. Toronto:
Thomas Nelson and Sons, 1950. Neely, Wayne C. The Agricultural
Fair. New York: Columbia University Press, 1935.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>