<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.wat.005</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Cheyenne Bottoms</field>
      <field name="author">Zimmerman, John L.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CHEYENNE BOTTOMS

Cheyenne Bottoms is a 41,000-acre elliptical
basin, formed during the late Pleistocene,
north of the great bend on the Arkansas River
in Barton County, Kansas. This depression,
surrounded by agricultural land and mixedgrass
prairie, contains the largest remnant
wetland in Kansas and is an important stopover
site for tens of thousands of migratory
waterfowl and shorebirds, as well as a nesting
haven for herons, ducks, rails, gulls, and terns.
It has been estimated that more than 90 percent
of the continental populations of several
shorebird species east of the Rocky Mountains
stop at the bottoms during their spring migration
from the Southern Hemisphere to the
Arctic. No other location in the Great Plains
attracts even 10 percent of the number of
shorebirds during migration.

The site has been designated as a Wetland of
International Importance by the Ramsar Convention
and is listed as a Hemispheric Reserve
by the Western Hemisphere Shorebird Preserve
Network. Since 1949, half of the area has
been managed by the Kansas Department of
Wildlife and Parks, which uses diverted surface
water to provide habitat for migrant
and breeding waterbirds. However, increasing
competition for limited surface flows and continued
withdrawal of groundwater for irrigation
has threatened the state's ability to maintain
this wetland. The conflict went to court
and was resolved, ensuring that the bottoms
will receive at least some of its allotted water.
During the past decade, an additional 6,500
acres of prime wetland within the basin have
been preserved by The Nature Conservancy.

See also PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT: Bird Migrations.


John L. Zimmerman
Kansas State University




Gilpin, John. Prairie Promises: History of the Bow River
Irrigation District. Vauxhall, Alberta: Bow River Irrigation
District, 1976. Kirk, D. W. The Bow River Irrigation Project:
The History and Development of the Bow River Irrigation
Project up to and Including Its Purchase by the Government
of Canada in 1950. Regina, Saskatchewan: Prairie Farm
Rehabilitation Administration, 1955.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>