<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.rel.009</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Canadian Wesleyan Methodism</field>
      <field name="author">Waugh, Earle H.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CANADIAN WESLEYAN METHODISM

Whereas Methodism in Upper and Lower Canada
had been subjected to the strong imprint of
American Methodism and subsequently drew
many of its leading lights from Loyalist stock,
the missions to the western Canadian Plains
were initially dominated by strong English connections.
Missionaries, headed by James Evans
(1801-1846), came to the Plains under the initiative
of the Wesleyan Missionary Society and the
jurisdiction of the Hudson's Bay Company in
London. Evans established his base at Norway
House, on the northern tip of Lake Winnipeg,
and from there he and his coworkers branched
out westward across the vast territories toward
the Rocky Mountains. Robert Terrill Rundle
(1811-1896) made his headquarters at Fort Edmonton
in 1840 and traveled widely among the
Crees and the Blackfoot. Both Rundle and Evans
were particularly skilled in the Cree language,
the latter fashioning a syllabics system that became
the basis of the first published hymnary in
western Canada. While Rundle was an effective
itinerant preacher, his only permanent legacy
was a community at Pigeon Lake, Alberta.
Greater success was accorded Henry Bird Stein
hauer (c.1820–1884), an Ojibwa from Ontario,
who joined another Methodist missionary, William
Mason (c. 1813–1893), in Manitoba. After
ordination, Steinhauer went to Alberta and
founded the mission at Whitefish Lake, where
he stayed for the remainder of his life.

The last decades of the century, however,
were marked by the pressures of mass immigration
of Europeans to the Prairies, a process
accelerated by the Hudson's Bay Company's
ceding of the West to the British government
in 1869. Thereafter, Methodist influence expanded
in the new towns and cities. For example,
George Young (1821–1890) of the Canadian
Conference established Grace Church in
Winnipeg in 1871. Mission programs from
churches in eastern Canada swung into play to
care for the influx. With this movement, the
Methodist tradition shifted away from proselytizing
to transforming the vast immigrant
crowd into "good" Canadians, and away from
condemnation of sin to criticism of the social
order. Educational institutions sprouted up,
such as Wesley College (1877) in Winnipeg
and Alberta College (1903) in Edmonton. By
the time Methodists joined with Presbyterians
in 1925 to form the United Church of Canada,
Methodist agitation for social order, public
morality, community focus, and sensitivity to
lay concerns had already forged a solid position
in Prairie consciousness, an influence
that continues to this day.


Earle H. Waugh
University of Alberta




Emery, George. The Methodist Church on the Prairies,
1896–1914. Montreal: McGill-Queen's University Press,
2001. French, G. S., and J. W. Grant. "Canada." In Encyclopedia
of World Methodism, edited by N. B. Harmon. Nashville:
United Methodist Publishing House, 1974: 385–401.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>