<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.048</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Monroney, Mike (1902-1980)</field>
      <field name="author">Creel, Von Russell</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MONRONEY, MIKE (1902-1980)

Almer Stillwell "Mike" Monroney was born in
Oklahoma City on March 2, 1902. He graduated
from the University of Oklahoma in 1924
with a degree in journalism and a Phi Beta
Kappa key. He worked first as a journalist for
the Oklahoma News, then in 1929 took over
management of his father's business, the oldest
furniture company in Oklahoma. In 1932
Monroney married Mary Ellen Mellon.

Monroney's first venture into politics as a
candidate came in 1937 when he ran unsuccessfully
in a special election for congressman
from Oklahoma's Fifth District. Running
again in 1938, Democrat Monroney won the
seat. Monroney's twelve years of service in the
U.S. House of Representatives spanned the
end of the New Deal and World War II, and
the beginning of the cold war and the Korean
War. Monroney was a strong supporter of
wartime wage and price controls and public
housing. His most lasting contribution, however,
was the Legislative Reorganization Act of
1946, the first and only major overhaul of congressional
machinery in the twentieth century.

In 1950 Monroney was elected to the U.S.
Senate, where he authored the legislation establishing
the Federal Aviation Administration.
He also authored the bill establishing the
International Development Association to
make low-interest loans to underdeveloped
nations. He was reelected in 1956 and 1962.

Monroney came to the Senate during the
height of Sen. Joseph McCarthy's controversial
hearings on subversive activities, and he
played a major role in the censuring of the
Wisconsin senator. On more than one occasion,
Monroney and McCarthy clashed on the
Senate floor. A strong supporter of Adlai Stevenson's
presidential bids, Monroney came
close to being named to the ticket with Stevenson
in 1952. In 1960 he headed the effort to
draft Stevenson for a third presidential nomination.
Monroney was defeated in 1968 in his
bid for a fourth term. He died on February 13,
1980.


Von Russell Creel
Oklahoma City University




Creel, Von Russell, and Bob Burke. Mike Monroney: Oklahoma
Liberal. Oklahoma City: University of Central Oklahoma
and Oklahoma Heritage Association, 1997. Fried,
Richard. Men against McCarthy. New York: Columbia
University Press, 1976.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>