<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.art.003</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Allen, Terry (b. 1943)</field>
      <field name="author">Neal, Mo</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ALLEN, TERRY (b. 1943)

Terry Allen, whose genres include musical and
visual arts, theater, film scripts, radio, and various
collaborations, may be a Renaissance
man in the sense of being a revivalist. His
works have roamed topics as diverse as a
hitchhiking Jesus, political terrorists, West
Texas hookers, wrecks of art trucks, and a
twelve-year body of work, Youth in Asia, on
the Vietnam War.

Shortly after his birth on May 7, 1943, in
Wichita, Kansas, Terry Allen's family moved
to Lubbock, Texas. In the 1950s the Allen family's
dance hall featured blues, country, and
early rock 'n' roll and played a major role in
shaping the teenage Allen as well as in desegregating
Lubbock culture. Leaving Lubbock
for Los Angeles, Allen earned a B.F.A. at
Chouinard Art Institute in 1966. He continued
creating visual arts while teaching at Chouinard
and, through the 1970s, at California
State University in Fresno. Allen now lives in
Santa Fe, New Mexico.

His recording career took off with the 1975
LP Juarez, which included in its packaging
six original lithographs. Allen has also produced
albums, collaborating with Jo Harvey
Allen, David Byrne, Joe Ely, Jimmie Dale
Gilmore, Butch Hancock, Wayne Hancock,
and others. His most recent album (1999) is
titled Salivation.

Throughout his career Allen has blended
the visual and audio, forming works of irony
and humor. He utilizes many mediums, from
printmaking and painting to installation and
public sculptural commissions. Corporate Head, for example, completed in 1991 for Citicorp
Center in Los Angeles, realistically shows
an attaché case carrying a bronze businessman
whose head is imbedded in a stone pier
on the ground floor. The George Bush Intercontinental
Airport in Houston houses Allen's
3,600-square-foot sculpture installation
Countree Music, which includes a music collaboration
with Joe Ely and David Byrne. On
the floor, continents surround Houston as the
center of the world. A bronze-cast thirty-foot
oak tree rises from the center, and from each
continent an indigenous instrument plays as
people walk over.

Since 1966 Allen's art has been included in
more than 50 one-person exhibitions and 150
group shows, including the São Paulo Biennial,
and the Whitney Biennial. His awards
include a Residency Fellowship from the Wexner
Center for the Arts in 1992, a Guggenheim
Fellowship in 1986, a Bessie Award in 1986,
and National Endowment for the Arts Fellowships
in 1970, 1978, and 1985.


Mo Neal
University of Nebraska-Lincoln





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>