<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.tra.032</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Route 66</field>
      <field name="author">Henriksson, Markku</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ROUTE 66

Route 66 is one of the most famous highways
in the world. It runs some 2,200 miles from
Chicago to Los Angeles through eight states,
cutting across the Great Plains through fourteen
miles of southeastern Kansas, then on to
Tulsa, Oklahoma City, Amarillo, Albuquerque,
and points west. It was originally part of
the U.S. highway system established in 1926. It
was fully paved by 1938 but was later replaced
by the present interstate system. Recently,
some remaining segments have been designated
as Historic Route 66, and in 1999 Congress
passed and President Bill Clinton signed
into law the National Route 66 Preservation
Bill that will preserve and restore historic
properties along the route. Throughout most
of its existence as a highway, Route 66 was not
very important at either terminus, but it was
crucial for communication and transportation
in the Southern Plains and the Southwest.
The route linked hundreds of rural communities,
locally carried farmers' products, and,
as one of the few diagonal long-distance highways,
was a major trucking artery.

The route earned real fame with John Steinbeck's
novel The Grapes of Wrath (1939), in
which the Joad family and other Okies fled the
Great Depression from Oklahoma to California
on Route 66. Steinbeck called 66 the
"mother road," and some 400,000 people
traveled west on it during the 1930s. The 1940
film by John Ford based on Steinbeck’s novel
further embedded the shield-shaped road sign
of Route 66 into the American imagination.
Later Route 66 movies include Easy Rider
(1969) and Bagdad Cafe (1987). The highway
was also featured in the 1960s television series
Route 66, starring Martin Milner and George
Maharis.

Folksinger Woody Guthrie wrote several
songs in which Route 66 was mentioned as the
"Main Street" of the Dust Bowl refugees. The
most famous of the many Route 66 songs is
"(Get Your Kicks on) Route 66," written by
Bobby Troup and recorded by Nat King Cole
in 1946. Perhaps more than anything else, this
song has made Route 66 an American icon.
Several museums and Web sites and a Route
66 magazine commemorate the highway's
glory days, and the National Historic Route 66
Federation works to preserve both the route
and its memory.

See also FILM: The Grapes of Wrath / MUSIC: Guthrie, Woody.


Markku Henriksson
Unviersity of Helsinki




Snyder, Tom. Route 66 Traveler's Guide and Roadside Companion.
New York: St. Martin's Griffin, 1995. Wallis, Michael.
Route 66: The Mother Road. New York: St. Martin's
Press, 1990. Witzel, Michael Karl. Route 66 Remembered.
Osceola WI: Motorbooks International, 1966.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>