<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pd.017</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Doctors' Strike</field>
      <field name="author">Ostry, Aleck</field>
      <field name="text">

 




DOCTORS' STRIKE

In 1944 the first social democratic government
in North America was elected in the province
of Saskatchewan. The new government of Premier
Tommy Douglas intended to introduce
plans to insure both medical and hospital services
immediately following the election; however,
because of financial limitations, it decided
instead to establish a provincewide system
of hospital insurance. The Saskatchewan
Hospital Insurance Plan, established in 1947
and funded mainly from provincial tax revenue,
provided free inpatient hospital care for
all residents of the province.

In 1957 the federal government introduced
its Canada-wide universal hospital insurance
plan, based on the Saskatchewan model. The
financial restrictions on the Saskatchewan
government, which had delayed the implementation
of Medical Care Insurance, were
then significantly reduced as money was injected
by the federal government into the Saskatchewan
government's hospital insurance
plan. The Saskatchewan government was, by
the end of the 1950s, in a good financial position
and, with this federal support, able
to turn its attention to developing a Medical
Care Insurance plan.

While most doctors in Saskatchewan were
in favor of the Hospital Insurance Plan, they
were strongly opposed to a Medical Care Insurance
plan because they felt it was an infringement
on the financial and professional
relationship between themselves and their patients.
The plan did not place doctors on salary
but did control the fees they could charge
for consultations and surgeries, which doctors
felt would limit their ability to earn income
in the future. The Saskatchewan doctors' resistance
to the plan, although couched in the
language of concern for the plan's impact on
patients' well-being, was largely predicated on
its impact on physicians' incomes.

Accordingly, on July 1, 1962, the date the Medical
Care Insurance Plan was to go into effect,
more than 90 percent of the province's doctors
withdrew their services. This strike, although
relatively short–it only lasted twenty-three
days–was very bitter. The government used the
threat of bringing doctors in from the British
National Health Service as strikebreakers. At the
same time, they asked a physician-mediator and
peer of the British realm, Lord Taylor, to help
settle the dispute. After tireless negotiations, begun
on July 16, Taylor brought the two sides
together, and the strike was settled on July 23.

Like the pioneering Saskatchewan Hospital
Insurance Plan, the Saskatchewan government's
Medical Service Plan of 1962 was the
first universal, publicly funded insurance
scheme to pay for doctors' services in North
America. And again, as in the case of the Hospital
Insurance Plan, this plan for insuring
physicians' services was the model the federal
government turned to when it introduced nationwide
medical care insurance in 1967.

The 1962 Doctors' Strike was an important
point in Canadian medical history. If the doctors
had won the strike, it is not clear whether
the universal, nationwide, publicly funded
system of medicare, as it exists in Canada today,
would have been established.

See also POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT: Douglas, Tommy.


Aleck Ostry
University of British Columbia





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>