<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ct.026</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Great Falls, Montana</field>
      <field name="author">Furdell, William J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




GREAT FALLS, MONTANA

Great Falls, Montana, is situated at the upper
end of a series of cataracts that begin at Black
Eagle Falls and extend a dozen miles downstream
to the largest drop in the Missouri
River (given the name Big Falls by Meriwether
Lewis), the site of present-day Ryan Dam. Nez
Percé and Flathead Indians regularly defied
the Blackfoot and entered the Plains from
west of the mountains in search of bison,
which were abundant in the vicinity of the site
of the present city. Another attraction was the
shallows situated just upstream from presentday
downtown Great Falls, in those days the
only practical place to cross the Missouri for
forty miles in either direction.

In the heart of Blackfoot country and off
the track for road freighters, who gave a wide
berth to the deep cuts and coulees formed by
the Missouri's feeder streams, the site of the
future city remained virtually devoid of permanent
occupation by Native Americans and
settlers alike until Paris Gibson, a wool merchant
and pioneer sheep rancher, founded the
town in 1884. He had read the Lewis and Clark
journals and came to see the falls for himself.
Impressed with their beauty and their industrial
potential, he convinced his friend, railroad
magnate James Hill, to invest in the town
site and urged him to extend his railroad
through the new city on its way to the Pacific.
Hill made the investment, but to Gibson's chagrin
Hill subsequently chose a more northerly
route for his transcontinental railroad (the
Great Northern) so that the main line bypassed
the town. Nonetheless, Gibson proceeded
to supervise the symmetrical platting
of streets and avenues, laid out on north-
south and east-west axes with fourteen lots to
the block, each lot precisely 50 by 150 feet.
Gibson saw to the inclusion of parks and insisted
on planting trees in abundance along
the town's streets and avenues. Great Falls was
a planned town–a businessman's town, different
in style and character from mining
camps and cattle towns that had sprung up of
their own volition. This difference was noted
by another of Gibson's friends, the famed
cowboy artist Charlie Russell, who lauded
Gibson for his work in founding the city.

Great Falls served from the first as a trade
center for area farmers and ranchers, and Gibson
and his partners saw to the building of
dams to harness waterpower within a decade
of the city's founding. Silver smelting emerged
early on, and despite the repeal of the Sherman
Silver Purchase Act in 1893 and other
subsequent setbacks in the crusade to put silver
at the center of the country's monetary
system, the smelting industry survived and expanded,
with copper becoming the predominant
product during an era of industrial expansion.
The 506-foot "Big Stack" dominated
the city's skyline from the time of its completion
in 1908. The smelter closed in 1980, and
demolition of the landmark stack two years
later marked the end of an era during which
the smelter had been the single greatest source
of industrial jobs for generations of Great
Falls residents.

With the loss of the smelter and the effects
of repeated drought years during the 1980s,
Great Falls faced difficult times. However,
other foundations of the local economy remained
in place. One such was Malmstrom
Air Force Base, established during World War
II as the East Base to serve as a ferrying point
for lend-lease aircraft headed for the Russian
front via Alaska and Siberia. During the cold
war era it continued as a missile base. From
the first the military's presence had a significant
social as well as economic impact. It
brought to Great Falls significant numbers of
people from many parts of the country, resulting
in an increased population and a more
diverse social and cultural milieu.

Other institutions also continued to bolster
the local economy. National chains added to
the number of large retail discount stores in
Great Falls during the 1980s and 1990s, serving
customers drawn from throughout the northern
and central parts of Montana. Major medical and educational facilities have remained
in place, and the state university system has
steadily increased its presence in the city. During
the late 1990s two new interpretive centers
were built, one dedicated to the Lewis and
Clark Expedition and the other to the Native
American pishkun, or bison kill site, located
not far from town. These joined the C. M.
Russell Museum to attract increasing numbers
of tourists to the city.

A number of factors combined to stem the
initial steep declines following the closing of
the smelter and the years of drought and agricultural
depression. Great Falls entered the
new millennium in a modest growth mode,
with its most recent population at 56,690,
drawing the city virtually even with where it
stood in 1980 before the smelter closed.

See also TRANSPORTATION: Hill, James.


William J. Furdell
University of Great Falls




Frohlicher, S. V. Stone Age to Space Age in 100 Years: Cascade County History and Gazetteer. Great Falls MT: Cascade
County Historical Society, 1981. Furdell, William J.
"The Great Falls Home Front during World War II." Montana:
The Magazine of Western History 48 (1998): 63–73.
Furdell, William J., and Elizabeth L. Furdell. Great Falls: A Pictorial History. Virginia Beach VA: Donning Company
Publishers, 1984.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>