<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ct.012</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Cheyenne, Wyoming</field>
      <field name="author">Elliott, Mark Johns, Jim</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CHEYENNE, WYOMING


A stereograph of Cheyenne, Wyoming, 1869


Cheyenne, the capital city of Wyoming, is located
in Laramie County on the semiarid
High Plains at an elevation of 6,100 feet. In
2000 the city's population was 53,000. The
Union Pacific Railroad gave birth to Cheyenne
during the summer of 1867 when its chief engineer,
Maj. Gen. Grenville M. Dodge, selected
and surveyed the site as a supply depot.
The city was named for the Cheyenne Indians,
who ranged in the area and had engaged in
hostilities with Dodge. The name Cheyenne is
probably a Lakota term meaning "people of
different speech" or "red talkers." The town
literally sprang into existence, engulfed by
numerous barkeeps, gamblers, merchants,
and prostitutes who inhabited the "Hell on
Wheels" communities that traveled with the
construction gangs of the railroad. By November
13, 1867, when the first train arrived,
Cheyenne's population had grown rapidly to
4,000. At first, the city was part of the Dakota
Territory, but in 1869 Cheyenne was selected
as the territorial capital of the newly established
Wyoming Territory. A few miles northwest
of the city the army built Fort D. A. Russell
and Camp Carlin, a major quartermaster
supply depot.

In 1875, with the discovery of gold in the
Black Hills, Cheyenne became an outfitting
center for miners and stage passengers on their
journey to the mines. The railroad was also
essential in the development of the prosperous
Wyoming livestock industry, and Cheyenne
became the center of the territory's cattle
boom. Wealthy ranchers built luxurious
homes in a neighborhood dubbed Millionaires'
Row and mingled at the elegant Cheyenne
Club. Because of its rapid birth and ability
to recover from periodic economic slumps,
Cheyenne was called the "Magic City of the
Plains." As the city matured during the territorial
period (1869–90), it also developed a
reputation as a social and cultural center. The
city was notable for its opera house, the Atlas
Theater, the Cheyenne Club, the Inter-Ocean
Hotel, numerous retail businesses, and more
than forty lavish mansions. The success and
wealth of the city attracted western legends
such as Wild Bill Hickok, Calamity Jane, Buffalo
Bill Cody, Tom Horn, and Wyatt Earp,
who rode shotgun on the Cheyenne–Black
Hills stage.

Historically, government has been an important
economic base of Cheyenne, especially
after the creation of the state of Wyoming
in 1890. Among the city's prominent
politicians and judges have been Joseph M.
Carey, U.S. attorney for the territory of Wyoming,
justice of the Wyoming Supreme Court,
territorial delegate to Congress, U.S. senator,
and Wyoming governor; Willis Van Devanter,
who held the positions of chief of the territorial
court and federal court justice and was
appointed to the U.S. Supreme Court in 1910;
and Francis E. Warren, a rival to Joseph Carey
who was perhaps Cheyenne's most distinguished
citizen. He served as territorial governor,
first governor of the state of Wyoming,
and U.S. senator for thirty-seven years.

Transportation has always been an important
economic and cultural stimulus for Cheyenne.
For years Cheyenne was a repair terminal
and passenger depot for the Union
Pacific. As the railroad's impact on the community
subsided, Cheyenne benefited from its
location along the Lincoln Highway, the nation's
first coast-to-coast automobile thoroughfare,
and today the city has the advantage
of being at the junction of Interstates 80 and
25. Its economic base still includes agriculture,
cattle, sheep, and the railroad, but its major
economic benefits derive from the presence
of federal and state governments and
Warren Air Force Base. Cheyenne's most important
tourist attraction is the Frontier Days
rodeo, popularly known as the "Daddy of 'Em
All." Regarded as one of the largest and oldest
continuous rodeos in the country, Frontier
Days held its first Wild West celebration on
September 23, 1897.

See also POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT: 
Warren, Francis / SPORTS AND RECREATION: Rodeo / TRANSPORTATION: Dodge, Grenville.


Mark Elliott
Jim Johns
Laramie County Community College




Adams, Judith. Cheyenne: City of Blue Sky. Northridge CA:
Windsor Publications, 1988. Carley, Maurice, William Dubois,
and Katherine Halverson. Cheyenne: The Magic City of the Plains. Cheyenne WY: Cheyenne Centennial Committee,
1967. Field, Sharon Lass, ed. History of Cheyenne, Wyoming. Dallas: Curtis Media Corporation, 1989.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>