<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.arc.005</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Black Sea German Architecture</field>
      <field name="author">Koop, Michael H.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BLACK SEA GERMAN ARCHITECTURE

Black Sea German immigrants who moved
from southern Russia to the Northern Great
Plains in the late nineteenth and early twentieth
centuries carried a blend of German and
Russian culture that distinguishes them from
neighboring ethnic groups. One component
of this culture is a basic vernacular architecture
that was executed in a variety of ways by
individual builders.

These buildings are not the ephemeral sod
structures commonly associated with Great
Plains settlement; rather, skillful builders used
a range of materials from clay and rammed
earth to stone and balloon-frame construction.
Fundamental to all the buildings except
frame is a basic clay mixture that serves as a
load-bearing material in walls, as a mortar,
and as filler between floor joists. Puddled clay
is a freehand method of construction that utilizes
no wooden forms to erect load-bearing
walls. Instead, clay is piled directly on the
foundation up to a height of about thirteen to
eighteen inches. Stones are often combined
with the clay in regular courses near the exterior
surface of walls to serve as filler. Batsa is
the term used to describe sun-dried bricks
made of puddled clay. They are shaped by
pressing the clay into wooden molds to form
bricks ranging in length from ten to eighteen
inches. Rammed-earth walls are formed by
piling puddled clay between vertical wooden
forms and compressing the clay with a handheld
ramming device. Masonry construction
employs puddled clay as mortar in loadbearing
walls of either coursed rubble or fieldstone.
Traditional balloon-frame construction
is also used, in some cases with batsa bricks
placed between the studs of the exterior wall
to serve as insulation.

Black Sea German houses represent an unusual
synthesis of German, Russian Ukrainian,
and other western European architectural
features. Their domestic architecture
developed through an integration of specific
morphological prototypes expressed in the
form, scale, function, and materials of each
building. A typical house is distinguished by
its one-story height with a loft and an attached
vestibule (vorhausl) on the long side leading
into the kitchen. The rather narrow, rectangular
shape is covered with a gable roof. A
smaller two- or three-room dwelling is known
as a semelanka, while larger house-barn combinations,
which provide living quarters for
people and animals under a single roof, are
called kolonistenhaus.

Rooms are subdivided by partitions made
of wood, puddled clay, and batsa, creating
houses two or three bays wide and one or two
rooms deep. A central kitchen is typically
flanked to the left by a parlor or living room
(stube) and sometimes by a storage or sleeping
room on the right. Some dwellings have a
black kitchen (schwarze kuche), a small, centrally
located, six-foot-square room that functions
as a separate space for preparing and
cooking food. Abutting the black kitchen and
heating the parlor and rear bedroom (kammer)
is a large clay oven (bachofen), which is
distinctively Black Sea German. The spatial arrangement
of the black kitchen and bachofen
is not uncommon in many regions in western
Europe; the form was subsequently transplanted
through the Black Sea region to several
settlement areas in the Northern Plains.

See also EUROPEAN AMERICANS: German Russians.


Michael H. Koop
Minnesota Historical Society




Koop, Michael H. "An Analysis of German-Russian
Houses in South Dakota Based on Their Origin, Form and
Materials." Master's thesis, University of Wisconsin–
Madison, 1989. Schnurr, J. Heimatbuch der Deutschen aus Russland. Stuttgart: Landsmannschaft der Deutschen aus Russland, 1967–68. Sherman, William C. "Prairie Architecture
of the Russian-German Settlers." In Russian-German Settlements in the United States, edited by Richard
Sallet. Fargo: North Dakota Institute for Regional Studies,
1974: 185–95.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>