<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.med.043</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Star-Phoenix (Saskatoon)</field>
      <field name="author">McKenzie, Jim</field>
      <field name="text">

 




STAR-PHOENIX (Saskatoon)

The Star-Phoenix is the only daily newspaper
published in Saskatoon, Saskatchewan. With a
circulation of about 65,000, it is the largest
and best newspaper in the province. But in
recent years, Star-Phoenix news executives
have struggled to maintain the high quality of
coverage the paper has traditionally offered its
readers.

This fight to uphold newsroom standards
has been particularly difficult since 1996, when
the Star-Phoenix was purchased by the Hollinger
organization. Hollinger, controlled by
press baron Conrad Black, is Canada's largest
newspaper chain. The Siftons, who operated
the paper for seventy years through four generations,
always looked after their employees. It
was a tradition stretching back to the Great
Depression, when the Star-Phoenix kept everyone
on the job despite tough economic times.

Hollinger promised that nothing would
change and that it would maintain the paper's
editorial quality. But once the sale was finalized,
the profit-hungry Hollinger's first move
was to fire one-quarter of the newspaper's
staff, including twenty-four people in the editorial
department. This mass firing, coupled
with a similar move at the Leader-Post in Regina,
sent shock waves through newsrooms
across the nation. That day, March 2, 1996,
which has become known as "Black Saturday,"
has gone down as one of the cruelest and
darkest days in Canadian journalistic history.

The S-P, as it is popularly called, also came
to national attention in 1978, when the Supreme
Court of Canada upheld a lower-court
judgment against the paper in a libel case. The
S-P had published a letter to the editor from
two law students who accused a Saskatoon alderman
named Morris Chernesky of displaying
"racist resistance" for opposing the location
of an alcoholic rehabilitation center for
Indians in a white area. The Supreme Court
awarded Chernesky $25,000 and ruled that the
newspaper could not use the defense of "fair
comment" because the opinions expressed in
the letter were not those of the newspaper it
self. This ruling prompted several provincial
governments to change their libel laws to ensure
that newspapers could publish letters
from readers who held opinions not necessarily
agreeing with those of the paper.

The Star-Phoenix has grown up with the
city it serves. It began life as the Phenix in
1902. The paper, initially printed on a Washington
handpress by Westley and Edward
Norman, was renamed the Phoenix in 1905. It
became a daily a year later. A second paper,
the Capital, was started in 1906 and renamed
the Star six years later. The Star and the Phoenix
were merged in 1928, when both papers
were purchased by the Sifton family.

Editorially, the Star-Phoenix has frequently
shown itself to be sharper and quicker off the
mark than the Leader-Post, its sister paper in
Regina. The S-P puts more emphasis on original
reporting, and its columnists are more inclined
to take controversial stands. This difference
is due in part to the fact that while Regina,
the provincial capital, is dominated by a civilservice
mentality, Saskatoon has a more business-
oriented and progressive outlook.

See also CITIES AND TOWNS: Saskatoon, Saskatchewan.


Jim McKenzie
University of Regina





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>