<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.037</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Kassebaum, Nancy (b. 1932)</field>
      <field name="author">Cigler, Allan J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




KASSEBAUM, NANCY (b. 1932)

Nancy Landon Kassebaum, daughter of the
1936 Republican presidential nominee Alf
Landon, was born in Topeka, Kansas, on July
29, 1932. She was first elected to the U.S. Senate
from Kansas in 1978 and served two additional
terms before retiring in 1996. She had little
experience in public office prior to her election,
mainly having served only on the school
board in the small town of Maize, Kansas, between
1973 and 1975. She capitalized on her
prominent family name to win the 1978 Republican
primary and then won a relatively
close race against a better-known Democratic
opponent in the general election. She quickly
became a popular figure in the state and won
reelection in both 1984 and 1990 by a three-toone
margin.

Senator Kassebaum developed a reputation
in the Senate as a conservative on domestic
economic issues and a moderate on social issues.
She was an aggressive advocate for devolution,
the transferring of power from the
government in Washington to the states. She
deviated from many Senate Republicans by
supporting international family planning
abroad and pro-choice policies domestically,
angering a number of Christian Right Republicans
in her home state.

With a master's degree in international relations
from the University of Michigan (1956),
Senator Kassebaum was an active member of
the Senate Foreign Relations Committee. She
was a staunch supporter of economic sanctions
against South Africa during the Reagan
years. She unsuccessfully challenged the Bush
administration to cut off food credit guarantees
to Iraq prior to the Gulf War, money that
was later revealed to be used for that nation's
military buildup.

After her retirement from the U.S. Senate,
Kassebaum married former Republican Senate
minority leader Howard Baker. She currently
resides in Tennessee and has been disengaged
from Kansas politics since her retirement.


Allan J. Cigler
University of Kansas





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>