<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.025</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Ferguson, James and Miriam (1871-1944; 1875-1961)</field>
      <field name="author">Shelley, Fred M.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




FERGUSON, JAMES AND MIRIAM (1871-1944; 1875-1961)

James and Miriam "Ma" Ferguson were dominant
political figures in Texas between World
Wars I and II. James Edward Ferguson was
born on a farm near Salado, Bell County,
Texas, on August 31, 1871, and was educated in
local public schools. He studied law at night
and was admitted to the bar in 1897. He and
Miriam Wallace, a Bell County native born on
June 13, 1875, were married in 1899. With
strong support from progressive and anti-Prohibition forces, "Farmer Jim" was elected
governor of Texas in 1914. He was reelected in
1916 but the following year was impeached on
grounds of misusing public funds and removed
from office. The conviction forbade
Ferguson to hold "any office of honor, trust,
or profit" in Texas. In order to keep Ferguson's
name in the public spotlight, the Fergusons
began to publish a weekly political newspaper,
the Ferguson Forum.

Ferguson's impeachment decree did not apply
to federal offices, and in 1922 Ferguson ran
for the U.S. Senate as an opponent of Prohibition
and the Ku Klux Klan. He was supported
by many rural Populist voters and by enemies
of the Klan, but lost to Klan member Earle
Mayfield. Arguing that his impeachment was
invalid, Ferguson attempted to run for governor
in the 1924 Democratic primary. After the
party leadership refused to place his name on
the ballot, his wife ran in his stead.

Ma Ferguson ran for governor of Texas five
times, winning twice. In the 1924 election, Ma
opposed the Klan and campaigned on the slogan
"two governors for the price of one," making
clear that her husband, often called "Pa,"
would make major decisions. She was elected
and so became the first woman to be elected
governor of any state. She lost to Dan Moody
two years later and lost again in 1930, but was
elected for a second two-year term in 1932. She
ran one final time in 1940 but lost to W. Lee
"Pappy" O'Daniel.

Jim Ferguson died on September 21, 1944,
and with his death the era of Ferguson leadership
of Texas's rural populists and anti-Klan
activists ended. Miriam Ferguson lived quietly
in retirement until her death on June 25, 1961.
The Fergusons are buried side by side in Austin's
State Cemetery.


Fred M. Shelley
Southwest Texas State University




Brown, Norman D. Hood, Bonnet, and Little Brown Jug: Texas Politics, 1921-1928. College Station: Texas A&amp;M University
Press, 1984. Key, V. O., Jr. Southern Politics. New
York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1949.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>