<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.042</field>
      <field name="titleMain">May, Karl (1842-1912)</field>
      <field name="author">McCain, Meredith</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MAY, KARL (1842-1912)


Karl May dressed as "Old Shatterhand"


Among the most popular German writers of
all times, Karl Friedrich May was born February
25, 1842, in Ernstthal, Saxony, the fifth
child of fourteen to impoverished weavers. After
a difficult youth, May lost the opportunity
to become a teacher when he was accused of
the theft of a watch and had to serve a jail
term. More serious charges of impersonation
and fraud later sent him back to prison for a
total of eight years.

When May was released at age thirty-two,
he was determined to become a writer. By the
time of his death on March 30, 1912, in Radebeul
outside Dresden, May was wealthy and
famous, and his place was firmly established
in German history. His enormous success (he
wrote some eighty books) rests on the gripping
first-person narration of travel stories
(translated into more than thirty languages),
many set in the American West and six specifically
on the Llano Estacado. In May's "Western"
stories, the narrator, Old Shatterhand, a
German frontiersman, forms a blood-brother
bond with a noble, handsome, and intelligent
Mescalero Apache chief, Winnetou, a character
who may well be the most beloved figure in
all of German literature. As described in The Spirit of the Llano Estacado (1887–88), these
friends ride through dangerous, arid terrain
and violently shifting weather patterns portrayed
in vivid detail. In response to his fans'
clamor, May had cards produced showing him
dressed in trapper's clothing and signed "Dr.
Karl May, known as ‘Old Shatterhand.'"

Revelations in the press concerning May's
prison record and the fact that he had never
been to the United States when he wrote his
famous stories assaulted him mercilessly in
the last years of his life. The question of May's
sources–writers who had actually been in
America, such as the Germans Charles Sealsfield,
Friedrich Gerstäcker, Balduin Möllhausen,
and the Irishman Mayne Reid, who spent
time on the Llano Estacado–remains a major
issue.

See also PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT: Llano Estacado.


Meredith McClain
Texas Tech University




Frayling, Christopher. Spaghetti Westerns: Cowboys and Europeans from Karl May to Sergio Leone. London: Routledge
and Kegan Paul, 1981. Sammons, Jeffrey L. Ideology, Mimesis, Fantasy: Charles Sealsfield, Friedrich Gerstacker, Karl May, and Other German Novelists of America. Chapel
Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1998.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>