<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ind.011</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Center Pivots</field>
      <field name="author">Schwieger, Dennis</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CENTER PIVOTS

Irrigation equipment in the Great Plains most
often refers to center-pivot equipment. A
center-pivot irrigation installation consists of
a fixed, four-legged pivot structure with a long
pipeline to which sprinklers are attached for
dispersing water. The pipeline rotates around
the central pivot in a straight radial-arm fashion,
riding on wheeled tower structures and
creating a large irrigated circle pattern on
planted crops.

The industry originated in the Great Plains.
Frank Zybach, a dryland wheat farmer in Colorado,
developed the first system in 1948. The
first prototype, made of steel and aluminum,
was propelled by piston-driven actuators
powered by water pressure from the pivot system
water supply. In 1954 Robert Daugherty of
Valley Manufacturing acquired the marketing
rights to the patent and continued development
of the concept over the next ten years,
perfecting it into a strong, durable design and
establishing an entire industry.

In the thirty years after World War II, more
than sixty companies in the United States
manufactured center-pivot irrigation systems.
Today there are four major suppliers, all located
in Nebraska: Valmont (in Valley and Mc-
Cook, with plants in South Africa, Spain, and
the United Arab Emirates), Lindsay (headquarters
in Omaha and plants in Lindsay, Nebraska,
and France), Reinke (in Deshler), and
T-L (in Hastings). These four companies supply
85 percent of the global demand for center
pivots and virtually all of the North American
market requirement. All four companies go to
market through networks of exclusive dealers
and distributors. Center pivots are now used in
more than 100 countries around the globe.

Major developments in center pivots have
included the transition from water power to
electric and oil-hydraulic power, the adoption
of durable coatings for the pipes and structure,
and the invention of special spans mounted at
the end of the pivot arm to cover the corners in
square and irregularly shaped fields. Linear
move machines are built from the same components
but are not fixed to a central pivot.
Linear move machines, introduced in the
1970s, proceed in a straight line to cover rectangular
fields. Special water application devices
for the low-energy precision application
of water were introduced in the 1980s. In the
1990s computerized controls were added, along
with integration of controls with soil moisture
monitoring and weather monitoring capability.

Mechanized pivot irrigation equipment has
advantages over other methods of irrigation
because of the uniform application of water to
large fields, low energy consumption, relatively
low cost, and the savings in labor required
for irrigation. The average life of a center
pivot is more than twenty-five years of
annual usage, resulting in a very low total life-time
cost of ownership. Its ability to operate
over undulating ground gives the additional
advantage of not requiring costly land leveling,
as is the case with other forms of irrigation.
Chemicals can also be applied to the crop
through aqueous solution with the irrigation
water or by separate spray manifolds mounted
on the pipeline structure. Water runoff can be
virtually eliminated by the precise application
of only the amount of water that can be absorbed
by the soil. There is a growing market
for mechanized irrigation equipment to dispense
wastewater through pivots to irrigate
field crops such as alfalfa hay. Large industrial
consumers of water such as food processors,
paper producers, and municipalities can benefit
from the reuse of the water through pivots in
such productive ways.

Crops produced under center pivots include
fruit tree orchards, commercial turf,
high-value vegetables, cotton, and all major
commodity grain crops.

See also WATER: Irrigation.


Dennis Schwieger
Valmont Irrigation





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>