<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pd.046</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Reed, Myron (1836-1899)</field>
      <field name="author">Denton, James A.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




REED, MYRON (1836-1899)


Myron Reed, between 1886 and 1901


Myron Winslow Reed, Civil War veteran, celebrated
preacher, and the West's foremost
Christian Socialist, demanded justice for Native
Americans, women's suffrage, and assistance
for the poor without mandating any
moral criteria. Reed was born in Windsor
County, Vermont, on July 24, 1836, and graduated
from Chicago Theological Seminary in
1868. He conducted ministries in New Orleans,
Milwaukee, and Indianapolis before moving to
Denver to pastor the First Congregational
Church (1884-94). A Democratic candidate
for Congress in 1886 and a cofounder of Denver's
Associated Charities Organization in
1887, Reed felt he would be more effective as a
voice for the Populists, laborers, and ordinary
folk: he declared that he would speak his mind
to all who would listen, and no rich man would
own him.

In response to the problems imposed on the
West by industrialism, Reed offered Christian
Socialism. After the 1886 Haymarket Affair in
Chicago, which resulted in deaths of protesting
workers and police, the Rocky Mountain News
published Reed's observations that the nation's
newspapers had condemned a version of socialism,
but not true socialism. He emphasized
a Christian Socialism based on cooperation,
not cutthroat competition, and which advocated
a new society fashioned by persuasion,
not violence. In "The Evolution of the Tramp,"
four sermons published by the News (1886),
Reed declared that jobless tramps were victims
of industrialism. The tramp, he argued, acted
as a warning to society that the social system
had failed. Known for his epigrams, Reed said,
"It is not a comfortable world while a single
soul goes without."

Reed supported the Knights of Labor and
the worker's right to organize and bargain collectively.
During the 1894 Cripple Creek miners'
strike, he publicly backed the strikers. This
action resulted in his resignation from his pastorate
and the subsequent organization of
the independent Broadway Temple, which
charged no pew rent. Here Reed preached to a
full auditorium, emphasizing workers' rights
and Christian Socialism. As president of
the Brotherhood of the Cooperative Commonwealth,
he planned to organize a socialist
colony in Colorado, but illness stopped him.

"The people's voice" died on January 30,
1899. More than 6,000 people from all walks
of life tried to crowd into the Broadway Temple
for his funeral. These mourners confirmed
his influence and popularity for all social
classes.


James A. Denton
University of Colorado at Boulder




Denton, James A. Rocky Mountain Radical: Myron W.
Reed, Christian Socialist. Albuquerque: University of New
Mexico Press, 1997. Reed, Myron W. Temple Talks. Indianapolis:
Bowen-Merrill Company, 1898. Szasz, Ferenc
Morton. The Protestant Clergy in the Great Plains and
Mountain West, 1865–1915. Albuquerque: University of
New Mexico Press, 1988.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>