<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.war.024</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Lincoln County War</field>
      <field name="author">Wilson, John P.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




LINCOLN COUNTY WAR


William H. Bonney (Billy the Kid), ca. 1879


When lawyer Alexander McSween and a young
Englishman, John H. Tunstall, began competing
with local merchants Lawrence G. Murphy
and James Dolan in the tiny community of
Lincoln, New Mexico, in the late 1870s, the
result was the Lincoln County War. From February
18, 1878, to February 18, 1879, the rivals
fought for economic supremacy, first through
the legal system and then with bullets, until law
and order finally collapsed.

Tunstall's murder by a sheriff's posse in February
1878 prompted his supporters, now
styled "the Regulators," to regroup around
McSween. On April 1, Regulators shot Sheriff
William Brady and his deputy on Lincoln's
main, and only, street. George W. Peppin replaced
Brady as sheriff. In the following weeks,
McSween and his partisans skirmished with
Peppin's posses. McSween led his Regulators
back into Lincoln on July 14, and for five days
the town was rocked with gunfire. Pleas for
help from a frightened resident brought Lt.
Col. N. A. M. Dudley and his men from nearby
Fort Stanton, but Dudley only stood by as
Sheriff Peppin and his men besieged McSween's
house. McSween died in a hail of gunfire,
as a young outlaw going under the name of
William Bonney, or simply "the Kid," led a
desperate escape from the burning building.

As a result of the violence, President Rutherford
Hayes dismissed territorial governor
Samuel Axell and appointed Lew Wallace, a
former general (and later, author of Ben Hur),
in his place. The U.S. Army was brought in to
help civilian law officers, and the violence
died away gradually. Governor Wallace's amnesty
permitted most of the outlaws to go free;
only William Bonney was convicted for the
murder of Sheriff Brady. Bonney, by then
known as "Billy the Kid," rode away from Lincoln
branded forever with a reputation as an
outlaw.

See also IMAGES AND ICONS: Frontier Violence / LAW: Billy the Kid.


John P. Wilson
Las Cruces, New Mexico




Nolan, Frederick. The Lincoln County War: A Documentary
History. Norman: University of Oklahoma Press,
1992. Utley, Robert. High Noon in Lincoln: Violence on the
Western Frontier. Albuquerque: University of New Mexico
Press, 1987.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>