<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.med.033</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Neuharth, Allen (b. 1924)</field>
      <field name="author">Arvidson, Cheryl</field>
      <field name="text">

 




NEUHARTH, ALLEN (b. 1924)

Allen H. Neuharth, the founder of USA Today,
is a self-made multimillionaire who has never
forgotten his South Dakota roots. Neuharth's
pioneering use of a lighter, brighter style,
coupled with a heavy reliance on color and
graphics, changed the face of the American
newspaper. He also is the founder of the Freedom
Forum, a nonprofit, nonpartisan media
foundation dedicated to free speech and free
press for people around the world.

Born on March 22, 1924, in Eureka, South
Dakota, Neuharth watched his mother, Christina,
struggle to make ends meet and raise two
young children after his father, Daniel, died
when Neuharth was a toddler. Neuharth later
would describe his mother as the first victim
of discrimination he knew; her plight, and
that of the state's Native American population,
had a profound impact on him.

After Daniel Neuharth's death, the family
moved to Alpena so Christina could be near
her family. It was there that young Al got his
first taste of newspapering, as a delivery boy
and later in the composing room of the weekly
Alpena Journal. He graduated from Alpena
High School and enlisted in the army, serving
with General George Patton as a combat infantryman
in World War II. He received the
Bronze Star.

Following the war, Neuharth took advantage
of the GI Bill to attend the University of
South Dakota in Vermillion, where he majored
in journalism and served as the editor of
the college paper, the Volante. After graduating,
Neuharth and a friend founded a statewide
tabloid called SoDak Sports that lasted
only two years before folding. Neuharth attributes
that early failure with giving him the
courage to take chances and achieve success
later in life.

After a series of reporting, editing, and
management jobs at newspapers around the
country, Neuharth joined Gannett in 1963
and ultimately became president, chairman,
and chief executive officer of the company. It
was at Gannett that Neuharth founded USA
Today and became a vocal advocate for the
hiring, training, and promotion of women
and minorities.

Neuharth makes frequent trips back to his
native state, including an annual visit to the
University of South Dakota campus for the
presentation of the Allen H. Neuharth Award
for Excellence in Journalism to a prominent
print or broadcast journalist. A two-milliondollar
gift from the Freedom Forum in 2000
enabled renovation of a building that was
named for Neuharth and houses the Department
of Contemporary Media and Journalism,
the student newspaper, TV and radio facilities,
the Freedom Forum Neuharth Center,
and all other media operations on the campus.
Through the Freedom Forum, Neuharth also
has been instrumental in establishing professional
development and recruitment programs
for Native American journalists and in
providing support for the Crazy Horse Monument
in the Black Hills.

Neuharth has two grown children from his
first marriage. He and his current wife, Dr.
Rachel Fornes, reside in Cocoa Beach, Florida,
with their six adopted children.


Cheryl Arvidson
Freedom Forum Newsroom




Boye, Will. "The Most Notable Ambassadors of Diversity
2001." Proud (winter 2001): 13–23. Neuharth, Allen H.
Confessions of an S.O.B. New York: Doubleday, 1989.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>