<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.na.062</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Mankiller, Wilma (b. 1945)</field>
      <field name="author">Justice, Daniel Heath</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MANKILLER, WILMA (b. 1945)

Wilma Mankiller at a speaking engagement


The first woman to lead the Cherokee Nation
of Oklahoma, and the tribe's most influential
principal chief since John Ross of the nineteenth
century, Wilma Mankiller's dedication
to her people and their future defines her life
of public service and social activism. Among
Cherokees and other Native American peoples,
Mankiller remains a staunch advocate of
Native civil, spiritual, and sovereignty rights,
economic independence, women's rights, and
education and health reform, all while successfully
fighting her own battles with emotional
tragedy and personal illness.

Wilma Pearl Mankiller was born at Tahlequah,
Oklahoma, on November 18, 1945, to
Irene, of Dutch-Irish heritage, and Charlie, a
full-blood Cherokee. Material poverty marked
her life on the family's allotment tract, known
as Mankiller Flats. This poverty would serve as
the impetus for her family's move to San Francisco,
California, in 1956 as part of the federal
government's relocation policies under the
auspices of the Bureau of Indian Affairs (BIA).
When the bia's promises of financial security
proved false, the family turned to the San Francisco
Indian Center for cultural and emotional
support. Mankiller and her father developed a
particularly strong relationship with the center,
and she credits her interests in politics to
watching Charlie work as an advocate for the
Indian community of San Francisco.

In 1963 Mankiller married Hector Hugo
Olaya de Bardi, whom she had met while a
student at San Francisco State College, and by
1966 she was the mother of two daughters,
Felicia and Gina. Her growing activism for
Indian rights was heightened by the Indian
occupation of Alcatraz Island; while her siblings
joined the protesters on the island itself,
Mankiller spent much of her time in fundraising
activities for the movement. In 1974,
due to fundamental differences in political
and personal philosophies, Mankiller and her
husband divorced, and in 1977 she returned to
Mankiller Flats with her daughters.

Mankiller's work with the Cherokee Nation,
as an economic stimulus coordinator,
began shortly after her arrival but was interrupted
by a near-fatal car accident in 1979,
in which her best friend, Sherry Morris,
was killed when her vehicle struck Mankiller's
car head-on while passing on a blind curve.
Mankiller's recovery was compounded by the
emotional trauma of Morris's death and the
onset of myasthenia gravis, a type of muscular
dystrophy in which the immune system
attacks skeletal muscles. With help from
Cherokee medicine people, surgery, and drug
therapy, Mankiller fully recovered and in
1980 continued her work with the Cherokee
Nation.

By 1983, after directing a highly successful
community revitalization program, Mankiller
had developed a strong reputation as an efficient organizer and dedicated advocate of
Cherokee people, particularly the poor of the
nation. Ross Swimmer, then principal chief,
asked her to be his running mate as deputy
chief. Swimmer and Mankiller narrowly won
the election. In 1985 Swimmer resigned to
head the bia in Washington dc, and Mankiller
became the first woman principal chief of the
Cherokee Nation. She was reelected in a runoff
in 1987, and in 1991, a year after repeated
hospitalizations and a kidney transplant, she
won her second election with 82 percent of
the vote.

The move toward tribal revitalization
marked Mankiller's tenure as principal chief,
during which she focused on Cherokee selfreliance,
independence, and pride. She championed
a variety of economic, political, educational,
and cultural projects, including
Cherokee language and literacy classes, rural
development and housing construction, health
care initiatives, and land claims settlement.
Due to continued ill health, including a second
kidney operation and treatment for lymphatic
cancer, Mankiller declined in 1995 to run for a
third term, but she has since remained active in
Cherokee affairs and international Indigenous
and women's rights. She and her husband,
Charlie Soap, a bilingual full-blood Cherokee,
are often seen at multitribal cultural and political
events; at powwows, Charlie is a noted
Plains-style dancer.

Some of the honors Mankiller has received
include induction into the International
Women's Forum Hall of Fame, the National
Women's Hall of Fame, and the Oklahoma
Women's Hall of Fame. She is the recipient of
the National Racial Justice award, Ms. magazine's
Woman of the Year award, and the Oklahoma
Federation of Women's American Indian
Woman of the Year award, and she was
named in the Marquis Who's Who as one of
the fifty great Americans. In 1998 Mankiller
received the Medal of Freedom, the top civilian
honor given by the U.S. government, from
President Bill Clinton in honor of her work
for the rights of women and Native peoples
throughout the world.


Daniel Heath Justice
University of Toronto



Mankiller, Wilma, and Michael Wallis. Mankiller: A Chief
and Her People. New York: St. Martin's Press, 1993.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>