<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.031</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Kreisel, Henry (1922–1991)</field>
      <field name="author">Neuman, Shirley</field>
      <field name="text">

 




KREISEL, HENRY (1922–1991)

Born in Vienna on June 5, 1922, Jewish novelist,
literary critic, and academic Henry Kreisel
escaped to England after the German annexation
of Austria in 1938. Along with other
German-speaking Jews and political refugees,
he was apprehended as an "enemy alien" in
May 1940 and sent to an internment camp
in New Brunswick, Canada. He described his
camp experience as fortunate in that it liberated
him from his factory job and, in the debates among the many intellectuals interned
with him, proved to be an excellent "university."
While interned, he decided to become
a writer in English, taking as his inspiration
Joseph Conrad. Released in November 1941,
he studied at Harbord Collegiate and the University
of Toronto and went on to a career at
the University of Alberta as professor of English
and vice-president. He died on April 22,
1991.

Kreisel conceived of his fiction as seeing Europe
(particularly, the Holocaust) through
Canadian eyes and Canada (particularly, its
political security and naïveté) through immigrant
eyes. In his novels The Rich Man (1948)
and The Betrayal (1964) and in the short stories
collected in The Almost Meeting (1981),
most of which are set during the months immediately
preceding the Holocaust or the
months and years immediately following it, he
explores themes of emotional loss and survival,
human dilemmas and weakness leading
to moral paralysis and betrayal, and human
forgiveness.

Kreisel became a strong and perceptive
voice defining Prairie fiction in "The Broken
Globe" (1965), his story of a Ukrainian immigrant
farmer's passionate attachment to his
land, and in the essay "The Prairie: A State of
Mind" (1968). This essay surveys earlier fiction
about the Canadian Prairies, beginning
by noting its frequent analogies between the
Prairie landscape and the sea in terms of the
vacancy, stillness, and wind of both. Arguing
that the physical fact of the Prairie landscape
produces a state of mind in which men feel
compelled to conquer the land while also feeling
diminished and spiritually imprisoned in
its vastness, he suggests that this landscape is
productive of a puritanism subject to occasional
eruptions of violence. This essay was
one of the first to note that European settlers'
writings about the Prairies suppressed the history
and presence of Native peoples.

Henry Kreisel played an active role in the
development of Canadian literature curricula
in the university and was a founding member
(1977) of NeWest Press, which defined its publishing
mandate in terms of Prairie regionalism.


Shirley Neuman
University of British Columbia




Brenner, Rachel Feldhay. "Henry Kreisel—European Experience
of Canadian Reality: A State of Mind." World Literature Written in English 28 (1988): 269–87. Henry
Kreisel Papers, Mss., Collection of the Library of the University
of Manitoba, Winnipeg. Neuman, Shirley, ed. Another Country: Writings by and about Henry Kreisel. Edmonton:
NeWest Press, 1985.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>