<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.law.004</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Anti-Corporate Farming Laws</field>
      <field name="author">Thompson, Nancy L.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ANTI-CORPORATE FARMING LAWS

Corporate farming has long been considered
by some to be an economic, environmental,
and social threat to family farmers. Advocates
of diversified, family-owned and -operated
farms point to fifty years of research that indicates
that corporate agriculture leads to
negative conditions in rural communities, including
population decline, lower per capita
income, fewer community services, and environmental
pollution. During the 1930s, one
response to the growth of large corporate
farms in the Great Plains was the adoption of
laws prohibiting corporations from owning
farmland or participating in farming activities.
The first such law was adopted in Kansas
in 1931, followed shortly thereafter by one enacted
in North Dakota in 1932.

In the 1970s other anti.corporate farming
laws were adopted in Iowa, Minnesota, Missouri,
Oklahoma, South Dakota, and Wisconsin.
When Kansas and North Dakota enacted
amendments to their anti-corporate farming
statutes in 1981, the laws in all eight states became
similar in content and form. Beginning
in the mid-1970s, several attempts were made
in the Nebraska legislature to pass an anti-
corporate farming statute, but the efforts
failed. As a result, a citizen petition was begun,
and in November 1982 Nebraska became the
first state to have its anti-corporate farming
law placed in the constitution by citizens
rather than adopted through statute by a legislature.
In 1998 the citizens of South Dakota
also amended their constitution through the
petition process with an anti-corporate farming
law patterned after Nebraska's.

While the anti-corporate farming laws in all
nine states contain similar language and a variety
of exemptions allowing certain corporations
to engage in farming or to own farmland,
the laws also differ considerably. For instance,
the definition of a family farm corporation,
whether the law allows so-called authorized
farm corporations, and whether the law prohibits
the ownership of livestock as well as
farmland are all key issues in interpreting these
laws. For instance, in Iowa there are few restrictions
on who may qualify as a family farm
corporation other than a requirement that 60
percent of the corporation's income must
come from farming. But in Nebraska and
South Dakota, one of the family members
must either reside on the farm or be actively
engaged in the day-to-day labor and management
of the farm in order to qualify for an
exemption.

Debate over the effectiveness and wisdom
of anti-corporate farming laws has intensified
in recent years as agriculture has become
more specialized and concentrated, especially
in livestock production. Opponents
of anti-corporate farming laws claim the laws
limit competition. Proponents of strong anti.
corporate farming laws, however, argue that
the tax advantages and limited liability available
to corporations give them an unfair advantage
over individual farmers. Family farm
advocates contrast the growth of large, corporately
owned operations in states without
anti-corporate farming laws with the relative
health of family farming in states such as Nebraska
that have tough restrictions on corporate
farms.

Controversy over anti–corporate farming
laws is expected to persist as the structure of
agriculture continues to impact the well-being
of rural communities throughout the Great
Plains.

See also AGRICULTURE: Corporate Farming.


Nancy L. Thompson
South Sioux City, Nebraska




Pedersen, Donald B., and Keith G. Meyer. Agricultural Law in a Nutshell. St. Paul MN: West Publishing, 1995.
Stayton, Brian F. "A Legislative Experiment in Rural Culture:
The Anti-Corporate Farming Statutes." UMKC Law Review 59 (1991): 679-93. Thompson, Nancy L. Raising Hogs in Nebraska Legally: A Farmer's Guide to Pork Production under Initiative 300. Walthill NE: Center for Rural
Affairs, 1998.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>