<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.afam.016</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Douglas, Aaron (1899–1979)</field>
      <field name="author">Kirschke, Amy</field>
      <field name="text">

 




DOUGLAS, AARON (1899–1979)

Self-portrait of the artist Aaron Douglas
      

Aaron Douglas was the leading visual artist
of the Harlem Renaissance. Born on May 26,
1899, Douglas attended high school in his
hometown of Topeka, Kansas, and received
his art training at the University of Nebraska,
graduating with a bachelor of fine arts degree
in 1922. Douglas had arrived at Nebraska
without his high school records, ten days into
the term. Still, he was warmly welcomed, and
he considered his years at Nebraska one of
the more positive times in his life. Douglas
worked as an art teacher at Lincoln High
School from 1923 to 1925, then moved to
Harlem.

Within weeks of his arrival in Harlem,
Douglas was recruited by the NAACP's W. E. B.
Du Bois, editor of The Crisis, and Charles S.
Johnson, director of the Urban League and
editor of Opportunity, to contribute illustrations
to their journals. Douglas quickly became
one of the leading artists in the New
Negro movement, or Harlem Renaissance.
Within this largely literary movement, Douglas
was specifically hired to create a visual message
for a public that had grown dramatically
as black migration to the North increased during
World War I. The Crisis had a national
readership, and any illustration Douglas made
would be seen in libraries, schools, and homes
across the country. Douglas tried to reach this
new black middle-class public–a public that
was difficult to define and locate–by creating
a new, positive, African-influenced black image
for his audience.

He wanted to change the way blacks were
depicted in art, and to bring the language of
African art first to Harlem and then to the
whole country. Douglas's growth and experimentation
can be traced in his magazine illustrations,
which were some of his most forceful
and interesting works. Through them he
evolved his artistic language, a distinctive language
immersed in African art. His illustrations,
blending art deco, cubism, and West
African sculpture, are clean and bold, often
showing a few simple figures or illustrating a
basic idea. In his first year in Harlem he won
three prizes for his work.

Douglas's Harlem years were filled with
commissions for illustrating books and painting
murals, most notably his 1934 Aspects of
Negro Life, which was commissioned by the
Public Works Administration for the Countee
Cullen Branch of the New York Public Library.
Douglas left Harlem in 1937, and in 1939 became
the founding member of the Art Department
at Fisk University. He chaired that
department for almost three decades. Douglas
died in Nashville on February 2, 1979.



Amy Kirschke
Vanderbilt University




Kirschke, Amy H. Aaron Douglas: Art, Race and the Harlem
Renaissance. Oxford: University Press of Mississippi,
1995.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>