<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.032</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Indian Agents</field>
      <field name="author">Wishart, David J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




INDIAN AGENTS

Cartoon commentary on Indian Agents (Library of Congress)


In both Canada and the United States, Indian
agents were responsible for implementing
federal Indian policy. They were the government's
representatives on reservations and reserves
and, as such, they wielded great power
over Native peoples, even to the extent of
usurping their traditional political authority,
suppressing religious practices, and transforming
social roles.

In the United States, Indian policy was
transmitted from a commissioner of Indian
Affairs (operating, after 1849, from the Office
of Indian Affairs in Washington DC) through
regional superintendents, to agents, who were
responsible for a single tribe or a group of
tribes. The agents, in turn, supervised teachers,
blacksmiths, farmers, and other agency
employees. In the early nineteenth century in
the U.S. Great Plains, agents like John Dougherty,
who was in charge of the Upper Missouri
Agency from 1827 to 1837, were roving ambassadors
who strived to maintain peace and to
obtain Indian lands. In the second half of the
nineteenth century agents took up residence
on their designated reservations and promoted
the government's assimilation policy.

In Canada, a separate Department of Indian
Affairs was not established until 1880, following
the Indian Act of 1876. Federal policy
(the federal government was confirmed in its
authority over First Nations in the Constitution
Act of 1867) was formulated in Ottawa, in
the "Inside Service" of the Department of Indian
Affairs. From there it passed through regional
superintendencies (there were three
such districts–headquartered at Battleford,
Qu'Appelle, and Calgary–in the Prairie Provinces
in 1897) to agents on the numerous reserves
that were established after the treaties of
the 1870s.

In the early nineteenth century, in the
United States, Plains Indian agents were often
traders who moved into the Indian service
when the fur trade collapsed. Later, their
origins were more diverse, but in both Canada
and the United States they tended to come
from eastern states and provinces, and they
were often unsuited for the job. Political patronage
played a major role in appointments.
In the late 1860s Quakers and other religious
denominations were put in charge of many of
the agencies in the U.S. Great Plains in an
effort to introduce some honesty into the service;
a similar transition occurred in the Prairie
Provinces in the 1870s. Military officers
were also appointed as agents on some U.S.
Plains reservations in the late 1860s and 1870s.

Some agents did their jobs honorably amid
the terrible living conditions that prevailed on
the reservations and reserves. They were convinced
that the only way the Native peoples
could survive was by becoming individualized
Christian farmers who made a living on their
own pieces of private property. Many others
were corrupt, taking advantage of the remoteness
of their situations by skimming their
charges' annuities or by colluding with settlers
to steal Indian lands. Because of dismissals for
corruption or ineptitude and resignations
caused by the hardships of living in such isolated,
desperate situations, agent turnover was
high. At the Blackfoot Agency in Montana, for
example, ten agents came and went in the thirteen
years from 1863 to 1876; to the south at
the Crow Agency, eight agents served in the
nine years from 1869 to 1878. Such frenetic
change did not inspire confidence in federal
policy.

In the late nineteenth century and early
twentieth century, agents imposed the assimilation
policy with increasing force. After 1881
on the Canadian reserves, agents were given
the powers of justices of the peace and encouraged
to use them to control the Indians' behavior,
including restricting them to the reserves
by enforcing antivagrancy laws. South
of the international boundary, agents threatened
to withhold the Indians' annuities if they
did not put their children in schools or work
in the fields. In both countries, agents increasingly
took over the political decision
making that had previously resided with tribal
councils.

In the United States, the post of Indian agent
was abolished in 1908 by commissioner of Indian
Affairs Francis Leupp. Thereafter, doctors
and teachers, officially called superintendents,
took over the agents' duties. Leupp believed
that they would be more successful in promoting
assimilation. On Canadian reserves, agents
remained the federal government's representatives,
with comprehensive powers to regulate
the Indians' lives, until the 1960s. Thereafter,
agents were gradually removed from the reserves.
The position no longer exists in the
Department of Indian Affairs.

See also NATIVE AMERICANS: Reservations; Reserves.


David J. Wishart
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Abbott, Frederick H. The Administration of Indian Affairs
in Canada. Washington DC: Board of Indian Commissioners,
1915. Hill, Edward E. The Office of Indian Affairs,
1824-1880: Historical Sketches. New York: Clearwater Publishing
Co., 1974. Report of the Royal Commission on Aboriginal
Peoples. Ottawa: rcap, 1996.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>