<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.edu.022</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Libby, Orin (1864-1952)</field>
      <field name="author">Iseminger, Gordon L.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




LIBBY, ORIN (1864-1952)

Orin Grant Libby was born on June 9, 1864,
on a farm near Hammond, Wisconsin. After
receiving his diploma from River Falls State
Normal School in 1886, he taught in Wisconsin
high schools until 1890. Entering the
University of Wisconsin as a junior, he was
awarded a bachelor of letters degree in 1892.
He remained in Madison and was among the
first graduate students of the historian Frederick
Jackson Turner. Libby's doctoral dissertation,
entitled "The Geographical Distribution
of the Vote of the Thirteen States on the Federal
Constitution 1787–8," may be the most
important single contribution ever made to
the interpretation of the movement for the
federal Constitution.

After receiving his doctorate in 1895, Libby
remained at Wisconsin for seven years as an
instructor, teaching history and pursuing his
interests in birds and bird migration. In 1902
he accepted the position of professor and
chair of history at the University of North Dakota
in Grand Forks, a position he held until
he retired in 1945 at the age of eighty-one.

Realizing on his arrival that the young state's
history was still in the making, Libby turned
to researching the history of North Dakota,
thereby earning the title the "Father of North
Dakota History." He reorganized the State Historical
Society, served as its secretary for more
than forty years, and, until his retirement, edited
the society's journals, the Collections and
the North Dakota Historical Quarterly. He created
the State Museum, the State Historical
Library, and the State Park System. In 1907
Libby helped organize the Mississippi Valley
Historical Association, and in 1903 he organized
the North Dakota Audubon Society.

Libby spent thirty-five years researching the
visit in 1738 of Pierre Gaultier de Varennes,
sieur de La Vérendrye, and his sons to the Missouri
River in what is now North Dakota.
A recognized authority on North Dakota's Native
Americans, Libby cleared the Arikara
scouts who had served under Lt. Col. George
Armstrong Custer at the Battle of the Little
Bighorn of the charge that they had acted
cowardly and had been responsible for the defeat
of Maj. Marcus Reno's men. In 1912 Libby
interviewed the nine surviving scouts and
published his findings in The Arikara Narrative
of the Campaign against the Hostile Dakotas,
June, 1876. Recently reissued to favorable
reviews, Libby's account cannot be
disregarded in any serious study of the Battle
of the Little Bighorn.

Throughout his life, Libby recorded the
memories of the state's early inhabitants, their
relatives, and their descendants; excavated for
artifacts and remains of historic sites; photographed
log cabins, sod houses, and dugouts;
collected letters, photographs, diaries,
Indian legends, newspapers, and documents;
and encouraged the writing of lodge, church,
community, and county histories. Little of
North Dakota's history escaped his interest
and efforts.

Orin Grant Libby died on March 29, 1952, at
the age of eighty-seven. He was survived
by wife, Eva Cory Libby, daughter, Margaret,
son, Charles, and four grandchildren. He was
buried in Memorial Park Cemetery in Grand
Forks.

See also WAR: 
Little Bighorn, Battle of the.


Gordon L. Iseminger
University of North Dakota




Libby, Orin Grant. "The Geographical Distribution of the
Vote of the Thirteen States on the Federal Constitution
1787–8." Bulletin of the University of Wisconsin (1894): 1–
116. Libby, Orin G., ed. The Arikara Narrative of Custer's
Campaign and the Battle of the Little Bighorn. Norman:
University of Oklahoma Press, 1998.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>