<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.035</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Laurence, Margaret (1926-1987)</field>
      <field name="author">Xiques, Donez</field>
      <field name="text">

 




LAURENCE, MARGARET (1926-1987)

Margaret Laurence was born Jean Margaret
Wemyss on July 18, 1926, in Neepawa, Manitoba,
a small Prairie town 130 miles northwest
of Winnipeg. Although both her parents died
before she was nine, she remained in Neepawa,
where she was raised during the Depression
years by her aunt Margaret Simpson
Wemyss, who had become her stepmother.

Laurence attended United College, Winnipeg,
where she was profoundly influenced by
the tenets of the Social Gospel. In 1947 she
married John Fergus "Jack" Laurence, an Albertan
and veteran of World War II. While he
completed his engineering studies, Laurence
worked as a journalist in Winnipeg, first for
the Westerner and then for the Winnipeg Citizen,
a cooperatively owned Socialist daily.
Those newspaper pieces contain her reflections
on life and culture in the bustling city of
Winnipeg. While living there, Laurence became
friends with Adele Wiseman, who would
later receive a Governor General's Award for
her novel The Sacrifice. The friendship between
Wiseman and Laurence endured and
produced a remarkable correspondence, now
published.

Beginning in 1950 Laurence and her husband
spent seven years in Africa, where Jack
worked on engineering projects in the British
Somaliland Protectorate (Somalia) and in the
Gold Coast (Ghana). While in Africa, Laurence
completed her first book, A Tree for Poverty
(1954), a collaborative effort that involved
a Polish linguist and Somali interpreters. This
remarkable achievement was the first English
translation of Somali oral literature.

Returning to Canada in 1957 with her husband
and their two young children, Laurence
embarked on what was to become her bestknown
fiction: a series of related novels and a
collection of short stories, A Bird in the House
(1970), which deal with a small fictional Prairie
town named Manawaka. It was not so
much one particular Prairie town, Laurence
remarked, but rather an amalgam of many
Prairie towns. In 1962 the Laurences separated.
Margaret and the children moved to
England. The couple divorced in 1969.

Margaret Laurence wrote fifteen books, including
several works for children, and a travel
memoir, The Prophet's Camel Bell (1963). In
her Manawaka fiction, with its forthright portrayal
of memorable women, characters struggle
against stultifying and hypocritical elements
in a small Prairie town. Their lives are a
paradigm of any individual's struggle with inner
forces that must be confronted if one is to
live a full life.

In The Stone Angel (1964), Hagar Shipley,
a ninety-year-old proud Prairie woman of
Scots-Irish descent and Presbyterian background,
recalls her life and contemplates the
approach of death without self-pity or sentimentality.
Laurence's last and most structurally
complex novel, The Diviners (1974),
encompasses not only the contemporary story
of Morag Gunn as wife, mother, and writer
but also stories of Scots ancestors, Canadian
pioneers, and Métis. The Diviners also examines
the nature of memory and explores the
ways in which the present and past shape each
other.

After Laurence returned permanently to
Canada in 1974, she became active in establishing
the Writers' Union of Canada and continued
to offer encouragement to fellow writers
while working for nuclear disarmament
and world peace. Although Margaret Laurence
settled in Lakefield, Ontario, she remained
a Prairie person who believed that her
girlhood in Neepawa continued to shape her
vision of life. Margaret Laurence's collection
Heart of a Stranger (1976) contains several essays
describing the lasting impact of the Prairie
years on her personal growth and on her
view of the world. She died in Lakefield, Ontario,
on January 5, 1987.


Donez Xiques
Brooklyn College, City University of New York




King, James. The Life of Margaret Laurence. Toronto: Alfred
A. Knopf Canada, 1997. Morley, Patricia. Margaret Laurence: The Long Journey Home. Montreal: McGill-
Queen's University Press, 1991. Thomas, Clara. The Manawaka World of Margaret Laurence. Toronto: McClelland
and Stewart, 1975.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>