<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.gen.043</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Women in the Fur Trade</field>
      <field name="author">Radke, Andrea G.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




WOMEN IN THE FUR TRADE

Women played an integral part in the North
American fur trade from its inception. Yet the
role of women, especially Native American
women, has often been ignored in fur trade
history. Contrary to the notion that the fur
trade was a male-dominated activity, it actually
depended upon the participation and labor
of Native women for its very survival and
economic success. Native women acted as essential
producers in the fur trade of the Canadian
and American Plains.

European women have appeared very little
in fur trade lore. A few French wives may have
ventured west with their trapper husbands,
and some Hudson's Bay Company officials
brought their wives from Europe. White
women Narcissa Whitman and Eliza Spaulding
acted as observers of the American fur
trade when they accompanied a caravan across
the Plains and attended the 1836 rendezvous.
Two years later, four other white women, Mary
Gray, Mary Richardson Walker, Myra Fairbanks
Eells, and Sarah Gilbert White Smith,
also attended the rendezvous with their missionary
husbands. Their detailed journal descriptions
of fur trade activities are an important
part of the historical record.

Native women were the primary female
participants in the fur trade. Plains Indian
women married French Canadian, British,
American, and Indian employees of the fur
companies. As wives and daughters, Native
women acted in such important fur trade
roles as producers, translators, traders, and
guides. Marriage between white men and Indian
women encouraged political, social, and
economic alliances within the fur trade systems.
Marriage à la façon du pays, or "according
to the custom of the country," served as a
unifying bond between European American
and Canadian fur traders and Native tribes,
with many traders paying a "bride price" for
the daughters of important tribal leaders. For
example, in 1814 the St. Louis trader Manuel
Lisa married Mitain, daughter of an Omaha
chief, and secured an alliance that kept the
Omahas tied to the United States during the
War of 1812 with Britain and also kept their
furs flowing to Lisa's post. In spite of cultural
differences and the economic motivations,
many mixed marriages were stable, loving,
and long-lasting. White traders also married
the Métis, or mixed-blood, daughters of
white-Indian marriages, as a means of improving
their status in the fur trade community.
However, with the arrival of more European
wives in the mid-1800s, Métis wives and
children suffered increased discrimination.

Indian and Métis women were instrumental
to fur trade success. Whether at forts or in
settled communities, at the rendezvous or on
hunts, women were participants in fur operations.
They actively promoted and benefited
from the trade of woolen blankets, cloth, glass
beads, steel knives, awls, needles, and pans. In
turn, they contributed to the trade's success
through varied support roles and especially
through the production of furs. Women were,
in fact, the primary producers of the fur trade:
they trapped the smaller marten for its fur,
and they made the moccasins, snowshoes, canoes,
and other equipment necessary for
travel on winter hunts. For food they hunted
small animals, fished, and made pemmican.
Most importantly, Native women prepared, or
dressed, the bison robes and the beaver and
otter pelts for their ultimate use as hats and
clothing. Crow women in particular were renowned
for production of fine hides and
moccasins. Native women may have traded
their dressed skins and furs, too, though it has
been argued that their status actually decreased
with the fur trade, as market negotiations
were taken over by Native American
men. Certainly, women's workload went up
with fur trade demands: tanning a robe was a
three-day job, and Indian women aimed at
tanning up to thirty-five over a winter season.

Native women also served as important
guides and translators to expeditions, most famously,
Sacagawea. The lesser-known Thanadelthur,
a Chipewyan woman, guided and
interpreted for an early expedition of the
Hudson's Bay Company. Without fame or salaries,
Native women actively contributed to
the success of the North American fur trade.

See also INDUSTRY: Hudson's Bay Company / NATIVE AMERICANS: Métis.


Andrea G. Radke
Brigham Young University




Brown, Jennifer, Strangers in Blood: Fur Trade Company Families in Indian Country. Vancouver: University of British
Columbia Press, 1980. Faragher, John Mack, "The
Custom of the Country: Cross-Cultural Marriage in the
Far Western Fur Trade." In Western Women: Their Land, Their Lives, edited by Lillian Schlissel, Vicki L. Ruiz, and
Janice Monk. Albuquerque: University of New Mexico
Press, 1988: 199–225. Van Kirk, Sylvia. Many Tender Ties: Women in Fur-Trade Society, 1670–1870. Norman: University
of Oklahoma Press, 1980.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>