<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pe.008</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Bird Migrations</field>
      <field name="author">Richert, Amy L. Church, Kevin E.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BIRD MIGRATIONS

Bird migrations are regular two-way movements
of birds that have evolved to assure
more space and food for raising offspring as
well as increased overwinter survival. Internal
rhythms, often related to the reproductive
cycle, are triggered by photoperiod (changing
amount of daylight), prompting the migration.
Weather conditions usually influence
date of departure and pace of advancement
toward a destination. The result is one of the
Great Plains's most spectacular natural events,
as millions of birds move northward to breeding
grounds and southward to wintering sites
over large expanses of grasslands, wetlands,
and grain fields.

The endangered whooping crane (Grus
americana) is probably the most renowned
Plains migrant. All of the world's naturally occurring
whoopers (about 170 individuals) migrate
between Arkansas National Wildlife Refuge,
along the Texas coast, and Wood Buffalo
National Park, along the borders of Alberta,
Saskatchewan, and the Northwest Territories,
using a pathway that covers the north to south
extent of the Plains region. Most migrant
waterfowl common to the Plains, such as the
lesser snow goose (Chen caerulescens), white-fronted
goose (Anser albifrons), northern pintail
(Anas acuta), and mallard (A. platyrhynchos),
follow the Central Flyway, a locational
characterization of seasonal waterfowl movements
used for international management of
migratory game birds. The flight strategies of
other Plains migrants, such as raptors (burrowing
owl [Speotyto cunicularia] and ferruginous
hawk [Buteo regalis]), shorebirds
(upland sandpiper [Bartramia longicauda],
long-billed curlew [Numenius americanus],
and red-necked phalarope [Libipes lobatus]),
and songbirds (Harris's sparrow [Zonotricha
querula] and clay-colored sparrow [Spizella
pallida]), are more temporally and spatially
diverse.

Bald eagles (Haliaeetus leucocephalus) are the
first migrators during early spring. The next
arrivals are sandhill cranes (Grus canadensis),
ducks, and geese. During later spring, shorebirds
are followed by songbirds. Some migrant
songbirds, such as the dickcissel (Spiza americana),
arrive on breeding grounds in the
Northern Plains while individuals of the same
species have already completed their nesting in
the Southern Plains and started their migration
to wintering grounds. Arctic nesters such as the
Harris's sparrow move to the Central Plains for
the entire winter, whereas the snow bunting
(Plectrophenax nivalis) moves in and out of the
Central Plains in response to severe weather.

Many Plains migrants use different routes
during spring and fall, possibly to optimize
feeding opportunities or avoid harsh winds.
For example, the American golden plover
(Pluvialis dominica) breeds from the northern
coast of Alaska to the eastern shores of northern
Canada, flies southward along the Atlantic
coast to its wintering area in southern South
America, then forms a migration loop as it
returns to its breeding grounds by flying over
the Great Plains.

Distances that birds migrate vary within
and among species. Individuals that nest in
the southernmost part of the lark bunting's
(Calamospiza melanocorys) breeding range
migrate shorter distances to wintering locations
(less than fifty miles) than those in the
northern part of the breeding grounds (hundreds
of miles). Blue-winged teal (Anas discors)
that nest close to the Arctic Circle and
winter in Argentina move a distance of about
7,000 miles. Long-distance fliers rely on a variety
of cues for navigation, such as the position
of celestial bodies, the magnetic field of
the earth, and landscape features. For example,
shorebirds and cranes closely follow paths
that lie over a series of basin wetlands that
extend from the Texas coast to the Northwest
Territories.

Long-distance migrants may fly without
stopping. Others may spend a few hours, days,
or even weeks at a particular location for rest
and refueling. Birds that fly long distances before
stopping rely on fat reserves for energy or
winds associated with weather systems. Shorebirds
are especially known for moving great
distances in short time periods. The American
golden plover for example, can move 4,000
miles in less than three days with the help of
winds in the direction of flight. Most Great
Plains migrants are not equipped to make
such marathon flights. Instead, they make regular
refueling and drinking stops.

Locations where migrants land for short duration
are referred to as stopover sites. Solitary
birds or family groups usually use these sites.
Examples are the seasonally flooded fields and
shallow wetlands used by whooping cranes for
feeding and resting. Habitats used by migrating
birds for longer time periods to replenish
energy for farther movement or gain weight
for reproduction are sometimes referred to as
staging areas. Large groups of Plains migrants
are often associated with wetland-related staging
areas, many of which are protected as state
or national conservation areas, such as Bosque
del Apache, New Mexico, Cheyenne Bottoms
Wildlife Management Area, Kansas, J. Clark
Salyer National Wildlife Refuge, North Dakota,
and Delta Marsh, Manitoba, Canada. Arguably
the best location in the world for viewing
bird migrations is the Central Platte River
Valley and Rainwater Basin of south-central
Nebraska, which attracts up to three million
geese, fifty-two species of waterbirds, and
the world's largest concentration of cranes
(500,000) in spring.

Since 1900, habitat alterations, such as channel
flow reduction, wetland drainage, and conversion
of grassland to cropland, have rendered
migrant species more susceptible to diseases
and natural disasters such as drought. Traditionally,
conservation efforts for Plains species
emphasized breeding and wintering locations.
Current studies emphasize understanding habitat
requirements during migration and how to
most effectively protect migrant species.

See also SPORTS AND RECREATION: National Wildlife Refuges / WATER: Cheyenne Bottoms;
Platte River Whooping Crane Maintenance Trust.


Amy L. Richert
University of Nebraska-Lincoln
Kevin E. Church
Nebraska Game and Parks Commission




Alerstam, Thomas. Bird Migration. New York: Cambridge
University Press, 1990. Farrand, John, Jr., ed. The Audubon
Society Master Guide to Birding. New York: Alfred A.
Knopf, 1983.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>