<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ind.037</field>
      <field name="titleMain">McKenzie, Kenneth (1797-1861)</field>
      <field name="author">Wishart, David J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MCKENZIE, KENNETH (1797-1861)

Kenneth McKenzie was, as fur trade historian
Hiram Martin Chittenden put it, "the ablest
trader the American Fur Company ever possessed."
From his headquarters at Fort Union
(which he was instrumental in establishing in
1829) he ruled the fur trade of the upper Missouri
in its halcyon days. He pioneered the
company's expansion into Blackfeet country
with the establishment of Fort McKenzie in
1834; he was, with Pierre Chouteau Jr., the innovator
of steamboat navigation on the upper
Missouri, which revolutionized the transportation
system; and he can even be credited with
building what was perhaps the first whiskey
still in the Great Plains, an imaginative but
illegal and short-lived effort to evade the government's laws against importation of alcohol
into Indian Country. McKenzie was like a king
at Fort Union: dressed in a fine uniform, he
lived in a residence with the rare luxury of glass
windows and earned a reputation both as a
martinet who brooked no insubordination
and as a gracious host who presided over the
best table of food and wine in the West.

McKenzie was born in Rosshire, Scotland,
on April 15, 1797. He settled in St. Louis in 1822
after serving his apprenticeship in the fur
trade with the North West Company. Within a
year he was running the Columbia Fur Company,
which controlled the trade on the upper
Missouri until it was bought out by the American
Fur Company in 1827. In the course of the
following six years, as head of the Upper Missouri
Outfit of the American Fur Company,
McKenzie secured the company's virtual monopoly
over the fur trade on the Northern
Great Plains. By 1834 almost 2,000 packs of
bison robes a year were being collected at Fort
Union as well as large quantities of beaver, fox,
and muskrat skins.

McKenzie retired from the fur trade in 1834,
in part because of the furor over his whiskey
scheme. In St. Louis he subsequently operated
wholesale grocery and liquor businesses and
invested in land and railroads. Kenneth Mc-
Kenzie, "King of the Missouri," died on April
26, 1861. He was survived by his wife, Mary
Marshall (whom he married in 1842), and
four children in St. Louis as well as by his
family from a previous marriage to an Indian
woman at Fort Union.


David J. Wishart
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Chittenden, Hiram Martin. The American Fur Trade of the Far West. New York: F. R. Harper, 1903. Mattison, Ray H.
"Kenneth McKenzie." In The Mountain Men and the Fur Trade of the Far West, edited by LeRoy R. Hafen, 2: 217–24.
Glendale CA: Arthur H. Clark Company, 1965.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>