<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.war.021</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Hazen, William (1830-1887)</field>
      <field name="author">Kroeker, Marvin E.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




HAZEN, WILLIAM (1830-1887)

William B. Hazen was a frontier army officer
with eighteen years of service in the Great
Plains. Born September 27, 1830, in Hartfort,
Vermont, he grew up in Ohio, graduated from
the U.S. Military Academy at West Point,
fought Indians in Oregon, and was seriously
wounded in a skirmish with Comanches in
Texas in 1859. He served with distinction in the
Civil War.

As commander of the Southern Military
District at Fort Cobb, Indian Territory, in
1868–69, Hazen helped implement the reservation
system in the Southern Plains. During
the Washita campaign in 1868, he prevented
Gen. Philip Sheridan and Lt. Col. George Custer
from attacking his Kiowa charges, which
created an animosity that lasted throughout
their careers. In 1869 he helped select the site
for Fort Sill in Indian Territory. That same
year, he was named commander of the Sixth
Infantry, a commission he held until 1880.

Hazen's assignments took him into every
Great Plains state and territory. Always controversial,
he opposed the railroads and land
speculators by publishing articles warning
prospective settlers that the arid lands of the
High Plains were not worth "one penny an
acre" for agricultural purposes. He also opposed
Sheridan's plan to wipe out the buffalo
herds as a means of subjugating the Indians,
and in 1872 he exposed corruption of post traders
at Fort Sill, which resulted in the impeachment
and resignation of Secretary of War William
Belknap. In retaliation, Belknap and
Sheridan collaborated to exile Hazen to Fort
Buford, Dakota Territory, the army's Siberia.

After his friend James Garfield was elected
president in 1880, Hazen gained appointment
as brigadier general and chief signal officer. In
1871 he married Mildred McLean, a member
of a prominent newspaper family. He died in
Washington DC on January 16, 1887.


Marvin E. Kroeker
Ada, Oklahoma




Kroeker, Marvin E. Great Plains Command: William B.
Hazen in the Frontier West. Norman: University of Oklahoma
Press, 1976.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>