<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.war.047</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Summit Springs, Battle of</field>
      <field name="author">Monnett, John H.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SUMMIT SPRINGS, BATTLE OF

The Battle of Summit Springs, on July 11, 1869,
was one of the most decisive engagements
fought between the U.S. military and the
Southern Plains Indians. In retribution for
raids on Kansas settlements in 1868 and 1869,
Brig. Gen. C. C. Augur, commander of the
Department of the Platte, organized the "Republican
River Expedition." His orders to expedition
leader Maj. Eugene A. Carr were to
clear Indians from the Republican River country
with eight companies of the Fifth Cavalry
and 150 Pawnee scouts under Maj. Frank
North. The command was also to rescue two
white prisoners, Maria Weichell and Susanna
Alderice.

The campaign, which began from Fort McPherson,
Nebraska, was directed against the
famed Dog Soldier warrior society of the
Southern Cheyennes led by Tall Bull. After
eluding the soldiers, Tall Bull stopped on the
south side of the swollen South Platte River in
Logan County, Colorado. On July 11, under
the cover of fog, the command advanced on
the village of eighty-five lodges. Carr divided
his troops into two attack wings and launched
the assault about 3:00 p.m. The Pawnee scouts
reached the village first, taking the Dog Soldiers
by surprise. Guided by Two Crows,
women and children took refuge in a nearby
ravine. Tall Bull died defending his people, as
did the highly regarded Wolf With Plenty of
Hair, allegedly the last Dog Soldier to "stake
himself out" with a symbolic "dog rope" in
warfare. Carr officially reported one trooper
wounded, fifty-two Indians killed, and seventeen
women and children captured. Susanna
Alderice was killed in the attack, and Maria
Weichell was severely wounded.

Summit Springs ended conflict with Native
Americans in the Colorado Plains. According
to George Bent, who later related the history
of the Cheyenne people, the Dog Solders were
never again an important factor.


John H. Monnett
Metropolitan State College of Denver




Grinnell, George B. Two Great Scouts and Their Pawnee
Battalion: The Experiences of Frank J. North and Luther H.
North. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1973. Monnett,
John H. The Battle of Beecher Island and the Indian
War of 1867–1869. Niwot: University Press of Colorado,
1992.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>