<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.tra.013</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Good Roads Movement</field>
      <field name="author">Hugill, Peter J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




GOOD ROADS MOVEMENT

There have been three major road-building
movements in the United States. The first
good roads movement was for water-bound
macadam roads funded by state and local government
bonds. This extended from roughly
1880 to 1921 and was confined to the northeastern
states and California. The second
movement, from 1921 to 1956, saw massive federal
funding using taxes raised from gasoline
sales to build a nationwide network of bituminous
macadam and concrete two-lane roads.
This movement had a tremendous effect in
the Great Plains. The third movement, which
extended nationwide federal funding to high-speed
interstate highways, began in 1956 and is
essentially now completed.

The first good roads movement had two
periods. From 1880 to 1900, farmers granges,
the U.S. Post Office, and the organization of
bicyclists known by the charming name of the
League of American Wheelmen agitated for
farm-to-market roads. These were constructed
of graded rock bound together with water on
the principles laid down in the late eighteenth
century by Scottish engineer John Loudon
McAdam. Macadam roads lowered the costs of
getting farm produce to local railheads, allowed
rural free delivery, and made bicycle
tourism possible. After 1900 automobilists
proved an even more powerful lobby than bicyclists.
The first automobiles, imported and
expensive, were purchased by wealthy easterners
who soon influenced road development,
diverting it from farm-to-market roads. As
early as 1910, the suburban, intercity, and touring
networks of highways funded in states such
as Massachusetts and New York were clearly
being shaped by elite automobile owners.

During the mid-1910s, automobiles severely
damaged the water-bound macadam roads.
Trucks, also coming into wide use by the midteens,
added to the problem because of their
much greater weight and power. A surface was
needed that could resist the torque of wheels
turned by internal combustion engines. California,
which came late to the first good roads
movement, proved that concrete and bituminous
macadam highways held up far better
than the early water-bound macadam, although
they were considerably more expensive.

With federal funding the second good
roads movement extended to the entire country
between 1921 and 1956 the lessons learned
during the first. A 1914 map showed that none
of the Plains states had any improved highways.
In 1921 federal funding of the good
roads program provided jobs for World War I
veterans returning to rural areas. This movement
had a huge and enduring impact on mobility
in the Great Plains, especially when
combined with the rapid appearance of ever-cheaper
automobiles and professional engineering
of the road network. Henry Ford was
mass-producing his Model T by 1913, prices
had fallen below $300 by the early 1920s, and
there was a dealer in most county seats in the
country by the late 1920s. In 1919 Thomas H.
Macdonald, a Colorado native, left his position
as chief engineer of the Iowa Highway
Commission to become chief of the U.S. Bureau
of Public Roads. The bureau embodied
the best Progressive Era politics: centralized
standards set by professional engineers and
experts but localized decision making with regard
to the resulting network.

Macdonald's management of public spending
during the 1920s and the Great Depression
heavily favored rural, less-populated states
and renewed the first movement's emphasis
on farm-to-market roads. In 1924 Colorado,
Kansas, Nebraska, North Dakota, South Dakota,
Montana, and Wyoming only had 12
percent of the country's improved roads by
mileage, but by 1939 they had 21 percent. Yet in
1938 these states had only 6.5 percent of the
country's registered motor vehicles and generated
only 5.5 percent of the fuel tax receipts,
which were the major source of funding for
good roads. By 1939 these seven states had decent
statewide networks of two-lane hardsurfaced
roads, thanks to the good roads
movement.


Peter J. Hugill
Texas A&amp;M University




Hugill, Peter J. "Good Roads and the Automobile in the
United States 1880–1929." Geographical Review 72 (1982):
327–49. Seely, Bruce. Building the American Highway System:
Engineers as Policy Makers. Philadelphia: Temple University
Press, 1987. Wixom, Charles W. ARBA Pictorial History
of Roadbuilding. Washington DC: American Road
Builders Association, 1975.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>