<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.020</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Douglas, Tommy (1904-1986)</field>
      <field name="author">Brown, F. Laurie</field>
      <field name="text">

 




DOUGLAS, TOMMY (1904-1986)


Tommy Douglas


Thomas Clement Douglas was born in Falkirk,
Scotland, on October 20, 1904. His family
moved to Winnipeg, Manitoba, in 1919,
where he witnessed the Winnipeg General
Strike. After being ordained a Baptist minister
in 1930, Douglas moved to Weyburn, Saskatchewan.
Motivated by the widespread suffering
he saw during the Depression, he decided
to pursue a course of political activism.

In 1935 Douglas was elected to the House of
Commons as a member of the socialist Cooperative
Commonwealth Federation (CCF). In
1944 he resigned from the House of Commons
to lead the Saskatchewan CCF, which swept
to power to become the first socialist government
in North America. Douglas was premier
of Saskatchewan for the next seventeen years.

Tommy Douglas was the most beloved premier
in Saskatchewan history. He was a spellbinding
orator with a ready wit, whose views
were informed by the Social Gospel, the notion
that people should create heaven on earth
by helping others. He was opposed to doctrinaire
socialism aimed at overthrowing capitalism;
instead, he favored state regulation so
that the "little guy" could compete against
vested interests. He preached a liberal democratic
philosophy based on individual rights,
but more than others of his day, he also supported
the collective rights of First Nations.

The Douglas government, though not without
its failures, introduced reforms of seminal
importance. It was the first in Canada to adopt
a provincial Bill of Rights. Its social welfare
legislation, based on human dignity, was the
most enlightened of its day. It was the first
provincial government to address the problems
of Aboriginal peoples. And, over the objections
of doctors, it created a provincial
health care system that became a model for the
rest of Canada.

In 1962 Douglas returned to the House of
Commons in Ottawa to lead the New Democratic
Party (NDP), the successor to the federal
CCF. He surrendered the leadership of the NDP
in 1971 and retired from Parliament eight years
later. Tommy Douglas died in Ottawa on February
24, 1986.


F. Laurie Brown
University of Kansas




Barron, F. Laurie. Walking in Indian Moccasins: The Native
Policies of Tommy Douglas and the CCF. Vancouver: University
of British Columbia Press, 1997. McLeod, Thomas H.,
and Ian McLead. Tommy Douglas: The Road to Jerusalem.
Edmonton: Hurtig Publishers, 1987. Thomas, Lewis H., ed.
The Making of a Socialist: The Recollections of T. C. Douglas.
Edmonton: University of Alberta Press, 1982.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>