<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.076</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Sorensen, Ted (b. 1928)</field>
      <field name="author">Medhurst, Martin J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SORENSEN, TED (b. 1928)

Theodore Sorensen was born on May 8, 1928,
in a sod house in Lincoln, Nebraska. He was
one of five children born to Christian Abraham
Sorensen and Annis Chaikin Sorensen.
His father was active in Republican Party politics,
rising to become the state attorney general
of Nebraska. His mother, an outspoken feminist
and pacifist of Russian Jewish heritage,
gave her family name to each of her five children
as their middle name. The Sorensen
household was a regular meeting place for progressive
Republicans, and Ted absorbed most
of his early ideas from the lively debates that
were a regular part of his family life. He attended
the public schools in Lincoln, graduating
from Lincoln High School in 1945. Sorenson
graduated from the University of Nebraska
in 1949, entered the University of Nebraska
College of Law, where he eventually became
editor in chief of the Nebraska Law Review. He
graduated first in his class in 1951.

Seeking a larger venue for his talents, Sorensen
moved to Washington dc, where he took a
position as a staff attorney for the Federal Security
Agency (1951-52), worked as a staff
member for the Joint Committee on Railroad
Retirement (1952), and ultimately joined the
staff of newly elected Sen. John F. Kennedy
(1953-61). Sorensen quickly became Senator
Kennedy's chief policy adviser and speechwriter.
He did the background research for
Kennedy's Pulitzer Prize.winning book, Profiles
in Courage, and wrote Kennedy's speech
that electrified the 1956 Democratic National
Convention. Sorensen worked tirelessly to
help John Kennedy secure the 1960 democratic
presidential nomination, serving as both the
campaign's chief policy adviser and speechwriter.
Upon his assumption of the presidential
office in 1961, John F. Kennedy appointed
Sorensen as special counsel to the president, a
title created specifically for him. He remained
the chief policy adviser and speechwriter for
President Kennedy. Sorensen retained this title
throughout the Kennedy administration and
into the early months of the Lyndon Johnson
administration. In 1965 Sorensen published his
book Kennedy, which became a national bestseller.
Two years later, with Robert Kennedy
then a U.S. senator from New York, Sorensen
became chairman of the New York State Democratic
Committee's advisory council, and he
served as a delegate to the 1968 Democratic
National Convention, a convention at which
he had hoped to help Robert F. Kennedy wrest
the nomination away from Hubert H. Humphrey
and Eugene McCarthy. But an assassin's
bullet ended the Kennedy quest in June 1968,
just weeks before the convention. Sorensen
tried to pick up the pieces of the Kennedy
organization and offered himself as the Democratic
candidate for the U.S. Senate from New
York in 1970. Following his defeat, he returned
to the New York law firm of Paul, Weiss, Rifkind,
Wharton and Garrison, where he remained
in 2000.

Throughout the 1980s and 1990s Sorensen
devoted himself to numerous causes, serving as
a director of the Twentieth-Century Fund, as a
member of the Council on Foreign Relations
and the National Democratic Institute for International
Affairs, and as a trustee of the New
York Academy of Medicine, among many
other positions. Over the years he has been
awarded honorary degrees from the University
of Canterbury, Alfred University, Temple University,
Fairfield University, and the University
of Nebraska. He is the author or editor of seven
books, most recently Why I Am a Democrat
(1996). He is a member of the bar of the U.S.
Supreme Court, the District of Columbia, and
the states of New York and Nebraska.


Martin J. Medhurst
Texas A&amp;M University




Sorensen, Theodore. Papers. John F. Kennedy Presidential
Library, Boston. Sorensen, Theodore C. Why I Am a Democrat.
New York: Henry Holt and Company, 1996.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>