<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ea.026</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Mallet Brothers</field>
      <field name="author">Blakeslee, Donald J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MALLET BROTHERS

Pierre and Paul Mallet were French Canadians
who led the first successful European expedition
across the Great Plains to Santa Fe. Born
in Montreal to Pierre Mallet and Madelaine
Tuvée DuFresne, the brothers were frontiersmen
who moved to Illinois in about 1734. In
1739 they led a group of seven other men up
the Missouri River in search of Santa Fe. Confused
about the geography of the Great Plains,
they traveled all the way to present-day South
Dakota before friendly Arikaras and Skidi
Pawnees put them on the right road. They
returned downriver to an Omaha village in
what is now northeastern Nebraska, where
they purchased horses for their overland trip.
Using existing trails, and with the help of a
Native American guide for part of the journey,
they traveled first to the Pawnee villages in
central Nebraska, then south through Kansas
and western Oklahoma to Santa Fe.

In spite of the fact that they lost most of
their trade goods while crossing the Kansas
River, the Mallets and their companions were
welcomed in Santa Fe, where they spent the
winter. In 1740 they returned to Louisiana
rather than Illinois, carrying letters from the
lieutenant governor of New Mexico and from
a priest, both of whom encouraged trade between
the French and Spanish colonies. Jean-
Baptiste LeMoyne de Bienville, the governor
of French Louisiana, prepared a summary of
the Mallet journal, which is fortunate because
the journal was later lost, and so the summary
is the primary source of information about
the route taken by the Mallets.

French colonial o.cials were very interested
in trade with the Spanish and in the remote
possibility of conquering the Spanish
silver mines that lay somewhere south of
Santa Fe. Within three months of the arrival
of the Mallets in New Orleans, a new expedition
led by Fabry de la Bruyere set out up the
Arkansas and Canadian Rivers. Bruyere's expedition
did not get past eastern Oklahoma,
however, and the Mallet brothers appear to
have fought continually with him over how
best to proceed. Eventually, Fabry turned back
while the Mallets pressed on, only to lose their
trade goods this time in the Canadian River,
whereupon they too turned back. French attempts
to penetrate to New Mexico then languished
for a decade. In 1750, however, the
new governor of Louisiana, the Marquis de
Vaudreuil, sent Pierre Mallet west for a third
time. On the way Comanches robbed him of
his trade goods and most of his official documents.
On his arrival in Santa Fe, he was arrested
as an illegal intruder and sent to jail in
Mexico City, where he disappears from the
documentary record. Paul Mallet remained
behind in Louisiana, where the last documentary
record of his life has him living with a
wife and three daughters at the Arkansas Post.

Although none of the three expeditions led
by the Mallet brothers was economically successful,
their endeavors are recorded in several
place-names, including the Canadian
River and the Bayou Mallet and Bois Mallet,
both in Louisiana.


Donald J. Blakeslee
Wichita State University




Blakeslee, Donald J. Along Ancient Trails: The Mallet Expedition of 1739. Niwot: University Press of Colorado, 1995.
Folmer, Henri. "The Mallet Expedition of 1739 through
Nebraska, Kansas, and Colorado to Santa Fe." Colorado Magazine 16 (1939): 163–73.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>