<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pd.037</field>
      <field name="titleMain">National Congress of American Indians</field>
      <field name="author">Ellis, Mark R.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




NATIONAL CONGRESS OF AMERICAN INDIANS

Logo for the National Congress of American Indians


The National Congress of American Indians
(NCAI) is the oldest pan-Indian organization
in the United States. Its mission is to "inform
the public and the federal government on
tribal self-government, treaty rights, and a
broad range of federal policy issues affecting
tribal governments." The NCAI provides legal
aid to protect Indian civil rights and serves as
a watchdog in protection of treaty rights.

Organized in Denver, Colorado, in 1944 by
well-educated Native American leaders such as
D'Arcy McNickle (Flathead), Archie Phinney
(Nez Perce), and Charles E. Heacock (Sioux),
the NCAI battled against the federal government's
policies of termination of tribal status
and relocation. The NCAI also scored an important
victory in helping create the Indian
Claims Commission. By the 1960s, with the
threat of termination fading, the NCAI focused
on issues such as poverty and public health.
However, during the 1960s the NCAI lost its
position as the sole voice for Native Americans.
More radical groups, such as the American
Indian Movement and the National Indian
Youth Council, diverged from the moderate
policies of the NCAI by taking a more militant
stand. During the 1980s and 1990s the ncai
continued to work to protect Native American
cultural rights and the repatriation of Indian
artifacts and remains.

The NCAI has grown from an original membership
of fifty tribes in 1944 to more than 250
member tribes in 2001. The NCAI functions as
a legislative body, with tribes electing delegates
to represent them at a national convention.
With its headquarters in Washington, D.C.,
the NCAI continues to operate as a lobbying
agent on behalf of all Native American peoples.
Issues concerning the NCAI in 2001 included
environmental protection and natural
resources management, enhancement of Indian
health, and the protection of Indian cultural
resources and religious freedom.


Mark R. Ellis
University of Nebraska at Kearney




Cowger, Thomas W. The National Congress of American
Indians: The Founding Years. Lincoln: University of Nebraska
Press, 1999.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>