<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ag.064</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Sugar Beets</field>
      <field name="author">Jacobsen, Barry</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SUGAR BEETS


Sugar beets, Huntley Irrigation Project, Montana, 1906


Sugar beet (Beta vulgaris) is one of the world's
two sources of sucrose. Sugar beets are grown
in almost all temperate areas of the world and
are produced in North America from southern
Canada to Mexico at elevations ranging
from sea level to near 7,000 feet. In the United
States, sugar beets are produced in fourteen
states on more than 1.46 million acres, yielding
annual output of more than 3.8 million
tons of sucrose. Farm gate value (the value of
the product when it leaves the farm and before
value-added processing, wholesaling, and retailing)
to producers is more than $1.1 billion.
Sugar beets are grown under dryland
conditions in Michigan, Ohio, Minnesota,
and eastern North Dakota, and under irrigation
in western North Dakota, Montana,
Wyoming, New Mexico, Colorado, Nebraska,
Idaho, Oregon, Washington, and California.

Sugar beet production in the Great Plains
region accounts for more than 64 percent of
the United States total. The crop has been an
important part of the farm economy in eastern
Colorado and western Nebraska since
1890. Commercial production in the Red
River Valley of the North began in 1925. The
Minnesota–North Dakota production area
that includes the Red River Valley of the North
now has nearly 46 percent (667,000 acres) of
U.S. acreage; other Great Plains states contribute
another 17 percent of the nation's production.
Production areas involving western Nebraska
and adjacent Colorado and Wyoming
annually plant approximately 150,000 acres,
and the production areas in the Yellowstone,
Missouri, and Bighorn valleys of Montana,
Wyoming, and western North Dakota plant
approximately 120,000 acres. In 1998 the only
sugar beet factory in Texas was closed due to
chronically high disease losses. Sugar beet
production in Canada is centered in Taber,
Alberta, and has recently been targeted for expansion
by the minister of agriculture.

The sugar beet is a biennial, cross-pollinated
plant whose growth is favored by medium-
to light-textured soils with a 6.0–7.5 pH
and warm bright days and cool nights. Sugar
beets require significant nitrogen–150 to 200
pounds per acre–for maximum production.
Nitrogen levels must be carefully monitored
since excess nitrogen at harvest will reduce
both sugar content and quality. Sugar content
in roots can be as high as 22 percent, but commercial
production generally ranges from 12 to
20 percent. Two major innovations were critical
to the modern culture of this crop: the
discovery of cytoplasmic male sterility in the
1940s by Dr. W. F. Owens allowed the production
of high yielding hybrids, and the discovery
of monogerm seed in 1948 by Drs. V. F.
and Helen Savitsky eliminated the need for
hand thinning. Since the late 1960s all sugar
beet crops in the United States are planted
with monogerm, hybrid seed. Harvesting has
been done entirely by machines since the early
1950s.

All sugar beets are grown under contract
with sugar companies or grower cooperatives.
Typically, a minimum of 25,000 to 30,000 contracted
acres are needed to support a sugar
processing plant. In the Great Plains region
seeding generally starts in March and is finished
in early May. After harvest, beets are
stored in piles until they are processed during
a 60- to 200-day processing period. Sugar
beets are almost always grown in rotations of
two to three or more years. Shorter rotations
lead to depressed yields because of fungal and
virus diseases, the sugar beet cyst nematode
(Heterodera schacctii), insects, and weeds.
Historically the most important diseases are
Cercospora leaf spot, curly top virus, rhizomania
(beet necrotic yellow vein virus),
powdery mildew, Rhizoctonia crown and root
rot, and Aphanomyces black root. Insect pests
include sugar beet root maggot, sugar beet
root aphid, armyworms, cutworms, aphids,
and leafhoppers. Weed management is critical
to high yields of this important Plains crop.

See also HISPANIC AMERICANS: Betabeleros / INDUSTRY: Sugar Beet Processing.


Barry Jacobsen
Montana State University




Cooke, D. A., and R. K. Scott, eds. The Sugar Beet Crop.
London: Chapman and Hall, 1993. Whitney, E. D., and J.
E. Duffus, eds. Compendium of Beet Diseases and Insects.
St. Paul: APS Press, 1986.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>