<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ha.019</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Herrera, Juan José (ca. 1840s-1902?)</field>
      <field name="author">Philips, John Nieto</field>
      <field name="text">

 




HERRERA, JUAN JOSÉ (ca. 1840s-1902?)

In the late 1880s Juan José Herrera rose to
prominence in San Miguel County, New Mexico,
as district organizer for the Knights of
Labor, or Los Caballeros del Trabajo. Known as
El Capitan by his followers, Herrera's efforts
to organize labor and vigilante groups earned
him great respect among poor and dispossessed
neomexicanos (Spanish-speaking New
Mexicans), as well as disdain among many
Anglo-American settlers, local officials, and
landed neomexicanos. From April 1889 and
into 1891, he reportedly led the Gorras Blancas
(White Caps) in an armed campaign against
Anglo-Americans and neomexicanos who
had presumably encroached on community
lands. Although he and several of his followers
were arrested for vigilante activities in 1889,
none was convicted. Herrera denied association
with the Gorras Blancas.

Two years later Herrera was elected probate
judge of San Miguel County. His varied background
prepared him for popular organizing.
A captain in the Union army, Herrera departed
from New Mexico in 1866, leaving his
wife, Luisa Pinard, and became an Indian
agent, traveling among various western states.
By the time he finally resettled in New Mexico
in 1887, he had learned to speak several Native
languages or dialects, as well as French. His
command of English, his growing knowledge
of the law, and his political instinct served him
well in his brief organizing career. According
to his descendants, Herrera, who was born
sometime in the 1840s, died in relative obscurity
in Utah in or about 1902.


John Nieto-Philips
New Mexico State University




Arellano, Anselmo. "The People's Movement: Las Gorras
Blancas." In The Contested Homeland: A Chicano History of New Mexico, edited by Erlinda Gonzales-Berry and
David R. Maciel. Albuquerque: University of New Mexico
Press, 2000: 59–82. Larson, Robert W. "The White Caps of
New Mexico: A Study of Ethnic Militancy in the Southwest."
Pacific Historical Review 44 (1975): 171–85. Rosenbaum,
Robert J. Mexicano Resistance in the Southwest: "The Sacred Right of Self-Preservation." Austin: University
of Texas Press, 1981.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>