<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.law.043</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Pound, Roscoe (1870-1964)</field>
      <field name="author">Ellis, Mark R.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




POUND, ROSCOE (1870-1964)

Roscoe Pound was a botanist, lawyer, educator,
law professor, writer, and legal theorist. A
leading American legal scholar of the twentieth
century, Pound had a significant impact
on American legal culture.

Pound was born in Lincoln, Nebraska, on
October 27, 1870. Education was important to
the Pound family. Roscoe's mother educated
her children at home, infusing in them her love
of literature and botany. Pound went on to the
University of Nebraska, where he graduated
with a degree in botany in 1888. Influenced by
his father, Stephen, a prominent Nebraska lawyer
and judge, Pound entered Harvard Law
School but returned to Nebraska after one
year. He continued his study of law–in a law
office rather than law school–and in 1890 was
admitted to the Nebraska bar. Even while practicing
law, however, Pound's interest in botany
continued, and in 1897 he earned a doctorate in
that subject from the University of Nebraska.
Pound taught botany at the university, served
as the director of Nebraska's botanical survey,
and identified a rare lichen, which was given
the scientific name roscoepoundia.

Between 1890 and 1906 Pound was active in
Nebraska's legal community. In addition to
practicing law, he played a key role in the 1900
organization of the Nebraska State Bar Association,
drafting the association's constitution
and serving as its secretary for six years. In
1901 Pound was appointed a commissioner
(temporary appellate judge) to the Nebraska
Supreme Court. Finally, in 1903 the University
of Nebraska appointed him dean of the law
school, a position he held for several years.

Pound drew national attention in 1906
when he addressed the American Bar Association
in St. Paul, Minnesota. In this speech
Pound outlined his theory of "sociological jurisprudence,"
arguing that the law was not
static but that judges should consider the social
and economic consequences of their decisions.
Impressed by the young legal scholar,
Northwestern University hired him as a law
professor. After serving two years there and
another at the University of Chicago, Pound
took a position at Harvard Law School and
went on to become its dean from 1916 to 1936.

Although Pound left the Great Plains in
1907, he continued to have a significant impact
on Nebraska's legal community. The University
of Nebraska Law School appointed its
deans largely based on Pound's recommendations.
Pound also periodically returned to the
Plains to deliver addresses at the annual meetings
of the Nebraska State Bar Association.

Over the course of a multifaceted career,
Pound wrote on a wide variety of topics, including
botany, criminal law, prison reform,
and the organization of courts. The 1959 publication
of Jurisprudence, a five-volume work,
capped a legal career that spanned more than
seventy years. Pound died on July 1, 1964, in
Cambridge, Massachusetts.

See also EDUCATION: Pound, Louise.


Mark R. Ellis
University of Nebraska at Kearney





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>