<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.law.008</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Bonnie and Clyde</field>
      <field name="author">Phillips, John Neal</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BONNIE AND CLYDE


Bonnie and Clyde on a road between Dallas and Marshall, Texas, shortly after the car pictured was stolen, 1933


Bonnie Parker and Clyde Barrow came of age
during the Great Depression and ultimately
led authorities on a deadly twenty-seven-and-a-
half-month spree of robbery, abduction,
and murder between 1932 and 1934. They represented
a new breed of bandit: youths, predators
really, traversing mostly rural parts of an
America not too far removed from the preindustrial
Old West but employing the technology
of their age such as automatic weapons
and automobiles.

Their robberies, though involving banks
from time to time, consisted largely of petty
thefts, often from grocery stores and filling
stations. As thieves they held no notoriety, but
as dangerously slippery fugitives, Bonnie and
Clyde were something quite apart. Indeed, the
inevitability that Clyde Barrow would open
fire when cornered and probably succeed in
shooting his way out of almost any situation,
taking Bonnie with him, was the stuff upon
which the legend of Bonnie and Clyde was
based. The fact that they were young and by all
accounts deeply in love added fuel to the legend.
It has also contributed to the ongoing
tendency to romanticize their deeds and misdeeds,
which is unfortunate. There was nothing
romantic about their lives–not for Bonnie
and Clyde and certainly not for their
victims.

By the time they died in a bloody hail of
gunfire on May 23, 1934, Bonnie and Clyde
were linked to the deaths of nine lawmen and
four or five civilians, depending on the source.
Of these, Clyde Barrow probably killed five,
perhaps six. The rest were gunned down by
accomplices like Joe Palmer, Henry Methvin,
and Clyde's brother Buck. Interestingly, Bonnie
Parker, despite her image, rarely handled
weapons. In fact, there is no hard evidence
that she ever shot anyone, except herself once,
in the foot, while clowning around with one
of Clyde's guns.

Bonnie Parker was born on the Plains on
October 1, 1910, in the West Texas town of
Rowena. Clyde Barrow was born on March 24,
1909, on the fringe of the Great Plains in Telico,
Texas, forty miles south of Dallas. There is
some debate among family members as to
whether he was born in 1909, as is usually
cited, or in 1910, as recorded in the family
Bible. Nevertheless, by 1922 both families were
living in West Dallas, at the time an unincorporated
slum of dirt streets and shotgun
shacks located just across the Trinity River
from downtown Dallas. It was there, at the
home of a mutual friend, that Bonnie and
Clyde first met. The year was 1930.

Two weeks later, Barrow, already quite involved
in crime, was arrested and subsequently
sentenced to fourteen years in the
Texas penitentiary for burglary and auto theft.
In 1932, because of prison overcrowding, he
was issued a conditional pardon and released.
He quickly rejoined Bonnie and for a time
tried to go straight, working at a Dallas glass
and mirror company while she waited tables
at a cafe near the county courthouse.

Barrow's status as an ex-convict from West
Dallas made him the inevitable target of random
police roundups and incessant questioning.
In March 1932 he was fired from his job
because of the bad image he had acquired
from being visited so frequently by the police.
At that point, Barrow left town and took to
crime with a vengeance, swearing he would
never be taken alive. Initially, Bonnie accompanied
Clyde only sporadically, but by mid-
August 1932 she was with him almost constantly,
vowing to die with him.

Although many of their more notorious
crimes and gun battles took place beyond
the Great Plains, Bonnie and Clyde were no
strangers to that part of the country, ranging
throughout the region from Mexico to Canada.
On August 14, 1932, Bonnie and Clyde,
along with a friend named Raymond Hamilton,
abducted a New Mexico deputy sheriff
and drove him all the way to the Texas Hill
Country. The lawman had pulled up to the
Carlsbad home of Bonnie's aunt to take a
closer look at what he correctly identified as a
stolen car. Suddenly, he found himself staring
down the bore of a shotgun and being loaded
into the very car he was trying to investigate.
Twelve hours later, the deputy was given a few
dollars and released fifteen miles from San
Antonio.

On June 10, 1933, Bonnie and Clyde and
another cohort named W. D. Jones were involved
in a grinding one-car wreck near the
Texas Panhandle town of Wellington. Barrow
and Jones were thrown free and miraculously
escaped injury, but Bonnie was briefly trapped
in the car and severely burned. When two lawmen
arrived, Clyde and Jones abducted them
both and transported them, along with the
injured Bonnie, to Erick, Oklahoma, using the
officers' own car. Bonnie survived her burns,
but subsequently she could neither walk nor
stand without some form of support.

Bonnie and Clyde frequently prowled Kansas,
which, according to former gang member
Ralph Fults, was the best bank-robbing state
in the Union because of its numerous straight
roads, each intersecting every mile or so with
another road, creating a network of escape
routes virtually impossible to seal off. Clyde
Barrow robbed his first bank in Kansas along
with Fults and Hamilton.

In September 1933 Barrow and another pair
of accomplices tried to hijack a car from a
group of people playing croquet in Meade,
Kansas. A woman in the group attacked the
outlaws with her mallet, clubbing and capturing
one of Barrow's companions. Barrow and
the third man managed to escape on foot. On
April 29, 1934, Bonnie and Clyde stole a brand
new Ford V-8 Deluxe from the driveway of
Jesse and Ruth Warren in Topeka, Kansas. The
car only had a few hundred miles on the
odometer, but when it turned up a little more
than three weeks later on a narrow dirt road
eight miles south of Gibsland, Louisiana, it
had been driven more than 6,000 miles, and
Bonnie and Clyde were slumped in the front
seat, bloodied and filled with bullet holes.
They had finally fulfilled their vows, dying together,
violently and in a car, a car stolen on
the Great Plains.


John Neal Phillips
Dallas, Texas




Dallas Police Department, File #6048, Clyde Champion
Barrow, Texas/Dallas Archives Division, Dallas Public Library.
Phillips, John Neal. Running with Bonnie and Clyde: The Ten Fast Years of Ralph Fults. Norman: University of
Oklahoma Press, 1996.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>