<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.na.002</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Allotment</field>
      <field name="author">Greenwald, Emily</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ALLOTMENT

Allotment in severalty is the process of dividing
collectively occupied lands into individually
owned parcels. European Americans applied
the concept to Native Americans many
times, beginning in the colonial era and culminating
in the passage of the 1887 General Allotment
(Dawes) Act. It began as a strategy for
rewarding cooperative Native leaders with
large parcels of land. Later, the government
used allotments to appease Indian peoples who
opposed being removed from their homelands.
When Native Americans were removed from
the southeastern United States in the 1830s,
treaties granted allotments of land to families
who wished to stay, while dictating the terms of
removal to the Southern Plains for all others.
Many people who took allotments under these
treaties lost them to fraud perpetrated by land
speculators.

As the reservation policy emerged in the
1850s, the United States began inserting allotment
provisions into land cession treaties.
The treaties divided reservation lands into individual
parcels at the president's discretion,
but this use of allotment served no clear policy
objective. In the late 1860s the government reinvented
allotment in severalty as an assimilation
strategy. Reformers believed that individualized
landownership (private property)
would help transform Native Americans into
farmers, thereby integrating them into the
American economy. Development-oriented
westerners supported the idea, hoping that allotment
would free up "surplus" lands for settlement,
mining, ranching, and forestry. The
uneasy alliance of these two powerful interest
groups helped win passage of the General Allotment
(Dawes) Act in 1887, after eight years
of congressional debate. Similarly, in the Prairie
Provinces in the 1870s and 1880s, newly
created reserves for First Nations were allotted
into individual and family parcels as part of
the assimilation program.

During the debate over severalty legislation
in the United States, Native Americans voiced
their opinions on the topic. Some, like the
Omahas, lobbied for their own allotment acts
to secure title to their homelands. Others,
like the Five Tribes of Indian Territory, petitioned
to be excluded from the Dawes Act,
arguing that they were already su.ciently
"Americanized."

The Dawes Act mandated the division of
reservations into individually owned allotments
of land, using a base size of 160 acres
for adult males and smaller amounts for other
tribal members. Typically, though, allotment
sizes were determined on a reservation-by-reservation
basis, and often all members of the
tribe received the same acreage. Unallotted
"surplus" land could be purchased by the federal
government and sold to non-Indians.
The allotments themselves were to remain in
trust (protected against sale and untaxed) for
twenty-five years, but Congress eroded this
protection in the 1890s and early 1900s.

The president determined which reservations
would be allotted, and pressure from development
interests usually drove his selections.
Tribes in the Plains were singled out
more frequently than those in other regions
because ranchers and farmers wanted access
to their lands. Plains tribes were also disproportionately
targeted by competency commissions
that decided which allottees were "competent"
to handle their own business affairs.
"Competent" individuals were compelled to
take outright title to their allotments, dissolving
the trust status and leaving the land vulnerable
to sale.

The Indian Reorganization Act of 1934 officially
ended the allotment policy. But many
tribes continue to deal with the complex geographic,
legal, and economic legacy of the legislation,
which turned their reservations into
patchworks of tribal lands, allotments, and
non-Indian lands.

See also LAW: Dawes Act.


Emily Greenwald
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Carlson, Leonard A. Indians, Bureaucrats, and Land: The Dawes Act and the Decline of Indian Farming. Westport CT:
Greenwood Press, 1981. McDonnell, Janet A. The Dispossession of the American Indian, 1887–1934. Bloomington:
Indiana University Press, 1991. Otis, D. S. The Dawes Act and the Allotment of Indian Lands. Norman: University of
Oklahoma Press, 1973.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>