<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.sr.055</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Tibbs, Casey (1929-1990)</field>
      <field name="author">Duffy, John Michael</field>
      <field name="text">

 




TIBBS, CASEY (1929-1990)

Casey Tibbs
 

The Great Plains is the home of the open
range cattle kingdom, Wild West shows, and
an enduring ranching industry, so it is not
surprising that the region has produced some
of the greatest rodeo champions ever. One of
these was Casey Tibbs. Tibbs was born at Mission
Ridge, South Dakota, on March 5, 1929,
and grew up as a traditional ranch hand,
working horses out of his family's log house at
the mouth of the Cheyenne River. When he
began hitching-to contests in the 1940s, the
slightly built Tibbs’s uncanny "rhythm riding"
drew the derision of older, more powerful
riders. They could not argue with his success,
however, and by decade's end Tibbs was the
youngest world champion in history. As his
collection of tack and buckles grew in the
1950s, Tibbs became a darling of the postwar
decade alongside major-league baseball stars.
His striking good looks, purple luxury sedans,
and silk shirts became legendary both in and
out of rodeo circles.

By the time of his retirement in 1959, Tibbs
had won eighteen world championships (nine
Professional Rodeo Cowboys Association and
nine International Rodeo Association). His
list of championships was matched only by
his flamboyant personality. Tibbs had a knack
for capturing and in some cases creating
the limelight. In 1951 Life magazine featured
the photogenic South Dakota cowboy on
its cover, the only cowboy ever to earn that
distinction, and set the stage for Tibbs's post-rodeo
careers in acting and overseas Wild
West shows. Tibbs died on January 28, 1990, in
Ramona, California.


John Michael Duffy
Mission, South Dakota




Fredriksson, Kristine. American Rodeo. College Station:
Texas A&amp;M University, 1985. Porter, Willard H. Who's
Who in Rodeosssss. Oklahoma City: Powder River Book Company,
1982.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>