<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ha.030</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Otero, Miguel Antonio (1829-1882)</field>
      <field name="author">Ellis, Mark R.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




OTERO, MIGUEL ANTONIO (1829-1882)

Businessman, banker, politician, and railroad
promoter, Miguel Antonio Otero was born in
Valenica, New Mexico (then a province of the
Mexican Republic), on June 21, 1829. Otero
was educated in private schools in Missouri,
attended St. Louis University, and graduated
from Pingree College in Fishkill, New York.
He taught briefly at Pingree before returning
to Missouri, where he studied law under Governor
Trusten Polk. After being admitted to
the bar in 1851, Otero returned to New Mexico
(by then a U.S. territory) to practice law. He
quickly became involved in territorial politics:
he served in the territorial legislature, briefly
held the position of territorial district attorney,
and was elected New Mexico's delegate
to Congress in 1855 (he held that position until
1861). While serving in Congress Otero married
Mary Josephine Blackwood of Charleston,
South Carolina; the Oteros had four children
(son Miguel Antonio Jr. was New Mexico
Territory's first Hispanic American governor).

Otero focused on a variety of business ventures
after leaving Congress. In 1867 he opened
a mercantile business in Westport Landing,
Missouri, and as the railroad moved west
across Kansas he relocated to Leavenworth,
Fort Harker, and Hays City. Otero also became
active in railroad promotion. He worked for
the Atchison, Topeka, and Santa Fe Railroad
during the 1870s and he helped organize the
New Mexico and Southern Pacific Railroad,
which built through New Mexico. At Raton
Pass in December 1878, Otero drove the ceremonial
spike into the first rail laid in New
Mexico. By the late 1870s Otero was living in
Las Vegas, New Mexico, and was engaged in
mining, banking, health resorts, and a telephone
company. He founded and was the first
president of the San Miguel National Bank.
Otero died of pneumonia at age fifty-two on
May 30, 1882, in Las Vegas.


Mark R. Ellis
University of Nebraska at Kearney




Otero, Miguel Antonio Jr. Otero: An Autobiographical Trilogy.
New York: Arno Press, 1974. Vigil, Maurilio E. "Miguel
Antonio Otero." In Los Patrones: Profiles of Hispanic Political Leaders in New Mexico History, edited by Maurilio E.
Vigil. Washington DC: University Press of America, 1980:
45–48.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>