<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.med.049</field>
      <field name="titleMain">White, William Allen (1868-1944)</field>
      <field name="author">Agran, Edward Gale</field>
      <field name="text">

 




WHITE, WILLIAM ALLEN (1868-1944)


William Allen White at his Gazette desk, ca. 1909


William Allen White, a dean of American
journalism and social commentary through
the first half of the twentieth century, was
born in Emporia, Kansas, on February 10,
1868. Few at the start of the twenty-first century
recall White beyond textbook references
to his scathing editorial rebuke of Populism in
1896 entitled "What's the Matter with Kansas?"
White was then a conservative Republican and the upstart publisher of the Emporia Gazette, which he had purchased in 1895. His
editorial was picked up by the national party,
which spread the word widely. White soon
shifted from conservative to progressive politics.
He became an intimate ally of Theodore
Roosevelt and a national progressive spokesperson,
and he remained in the liberal limelight
for half a century.

White was a masterful wordsmith: his Gazette
editorials were regularly picked up by
newspapers, and his commentary and syndicated
reporting were published in leading
newspapers and magazines such as McClure's
and the Saturday Evening Post. White wrote
biographies of Calvin Coolidge (1925 and 1938)
and Woodrow Wilson (1924) as well as fiction
–his short stories and novels, published into
the early 1920s, packed hefty social and political
charges. A Certain Rich Man (1909) was the
most successful, eventually selling close to
300,000 copies. White gained more fame and
respect for two editorials written in the early
twenties: "Mary White," which eulogized the
tragic death of his spirited daughter in 1921,
and "To an Anxious Friend," which won a
Pulitzer Prize for its defense of free speech in
1922. Collections of his editorials in the Emporia Gazette were widely read and greatly influenced
the next generation of journalists.

White always retained an active interest in
politics. He joined Roosevelt in the 1912 Bull
Moose revolt; he defended liberal Republican
policies through the 1920s; he generally supported
New Deal initiatives in the 1930s; and,
while a staunch Republican, he prominently
allied himself with Franklin Roosevelt to overcome
isolationist sentiment in 1940–41 and
chaired the Committee to Defend America by
Aiding the Allies.

White died in Emporia on January 29, 1944.
He had remained a citizen of that town, but he
traveled widely, and he was acknowledged as a
national folk hero. White was a strong proponent
of small-town values; he advocated the
impression of those values upon an urbanindustrial
America he enthusiastically embraced.
His Emporia home is now a historic
landmark.


Edward Gale Agran
Wilmington College




Johnson, Walter. William Allen White's America. New
York: Henry Holt and Company, 1947. Johnson, Walter,
and Alberta Pantle. "A Bibliography of the Published
Works of William Allen White." Kansas Historical Quarterly
15 (1947): 22–41. White, William Allen. The Autobiography of William Allen White. New York: Macmillan
Publishing Company, 1946.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>