<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.038</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Little Magazines</field>
      <field name="author">Randolph, Ladette</field>
      <field name="text">

 




LITTLE MAGAZINES

If the job of little magazines is to shape literary
taste, the Great Plains states have helped shape
such taste for the better part of a century.
Some of the oldest and most venerable of the
country's literary magazines are published in
the Great Plains: Prairie Schooner has been
published continuously at the University of
Nebraska since 1926, and North Dakota Quarterly,
which started in 1910 at Grand Forks as
Quarterly Review, ceased publication from
1933 to 1955 and then began publication again
under its new name. More recent nationally
recognized university-based journals include
South Dakota Review (Vermillion, 1963), Nebraska
Review (Omaha, 1972), Cimarron Review
(Stillwater, Oklahoma, 1967), Denver Quarterly (1966), Colorado Review (Fort Collins,
1956), Writers' Forum (Colorado Springs,
1974), The Texas Review (Huntsville, 1980) and
Puerto del Sol (Las Cruces, New Mexico, 1960).

Historically, critics have charged that university-
sponsored magazines do not find truly
new literary work because their institutions
are interested primarily in establishing orthodox
reputations, while the little magazine
ought to be interested in the unorthodox. In
any case, the Great Plains also hosts a number
of literary journals independent of academia.
The Bloomsbury Review has been a highly successful
Denver independent since 1980. The
magazine's large subscriber base (65,000) and
loyal advertisers keep it solvent. Robert Greer,
founder and editor of Denver's High Plains Literary Review since 1986, is a medical doctor
who teaches in the University of Colorado's
medical school and writes medical thrillers. He
started the magazine to showcase work he felt
was not being published in other journals. Volunteers,
including editor Polly Swafford, are
the reason Potpourri (Prairie Village, Kansas,
1989) claims it has been able to continue to
publish. However, independent publishers
also have problems with censorship, as Michael
Hathaway, editor of the Chiron Review
(St. John, Kansas, 1982), discovered when he
had to search for a new printer after the newspaper
that printed the quarterly took offense at
accepted material.

The Canadian independents, most notably
Prairie Fire (Winnipeg, 1978) and Grain (Regina,
1973), are primarily funded by three
sources: provincial writers guilds, the Canada
Council for the Arts, and local arts councils,
while Prairie Journal (Calgary, 1983) is supported
by a trust.

Both university-sponsored and independent
literary magazines located in the Great
Plains have played a significant role in the formation
of contemporary literary taste. The
tradition promises to remain strong in the
twenty-first century.


Ladette Randolph
University of Nebraska Press




Anderson, Elliott, and Mary Kinzie, eds. The Little Magazine in America: A Modern Documentary History. Yonkers
NY: Pushcart Press, 1978. Council of Literary Magazines
and Presses. Directory of Literary Magazines 1997–98.
Wakefield RI: Asphodel Press, 1997.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>