<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ea.032</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Settlement Patterns, Canada</field>
      <field name="author">Thompson, John Herd</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SETTLEMENT PATTERNS, CANADA

The two-year-old Dominion of Canada purchased
that part of the Great Plains that extended
north of the forty-ninth parallel from
the Hudson's Bay Company in 1869. Peopling
this region with farm families, connecting it to
Central Canada with a railroad, and exploiting
the region's resources were the goals of the
"National Policy," Canada's western development
strategy. Migrants from Europe, the
United States, and from Maritime and Central
Canada reshaped this expanse into the Prairie
Provinces: Manitoba (1870), Saskatchewan
(1905), and Alberta (1905).

Ironically, given Canada's determination to
differentiate the Canadian West from the
American West, Canadian settlement and development
policy copied basic U.S. models.
The Dominion Lands Act of 1872, like the U.S.
Homestead Act, gave would-be farmers 160
acres if they "proved up": planted crops, built
a shack, and survived on the homestead for
three years. As in the United States, the routes
the railways chose shaped the broad patterns
of settlement in the Canadian Plains. Also as
in the United States, Canada subsidized privately
owned railways. The Canadian Pacific
Railway, completed in 1885, received generous
gifts of public land and public money. By
1915 the Canadian Pacific had been joined by
two new transcontinentals, the Grand Trunk
Pacific and the Canadian Northern Railway,
supported by government guarantees of their
corporate bonds. Soon bankrupt, the new
railways were nationalized between 1917 and
1923 as Canadian National Railways.

Until the late 1890s European settlement of
Canada's Prairie West proceeded slowly. Most
settlers who moved west came from the eastern
provinces, a majority of them from Ontario.
For complex reasons, one of which was
English Canadian hostility, only small numbers
of French Canadians migrated west. The
region had only 31,000 farms in 1891, and
the total non–First Nations population had
grown only to 251,000, compared to the combined
population of Montana and North Dakota
of 334,000 in 1890. Most embarrassing
was that the U.S. census showed that a tenth
of these North Dakotans and Montanans had
migrated south from Canada.

Slower population growth made the Canadian
government more generous toward block
settlement by ethnic groups than was its U.S.
counterpart. Two communities of Mennonites
were attracted to Manitoba in 1874 with promises of freedom from military service, subsidized
ocean passage, and grants of twentyfive
townships on the east and west sides of the
Red River. The U.S. government refused to allow
village settlement on homestead lands, but
the Canadian government agreed to a "hamlet
clause": Mennonite families could live in a village
away from the land they farmed and earn
title without fulfilling the usual residence requirements.

Like the Mennonites, other minorities were
pushed to the Canadian Prairie West by conditions
in their homelands and pulled by the
liberality of the Canadian government. In 1877
Icelanders settled a block grant on the west
shore of Lake Winnipeg. Mormons moved
north from Utah to evade a U.S. antipolygamy
law; their capital and experience enabled them
to buy and irrigate railway lands in southern
Alberta, and Canada took no action against
polygamy. Attracted by assurances that they
could preserve their cultural distinctiveness,
Jewish homesteaders abandoned North Dakota
to create six agricultural colonies in
Manitoba and Saskatchewan, and 1,700 Hutterites
left South Dakota for Manitoba and
Alberta.

After 1900 a surging export-oriented wheat
economy initiated massive migration to what
Canadian immigration pamphlets called the
"Last Best West." Regional population leaped
to almost two million in 1921, and from 5 percent
to 22 percent of Canada's total population.
Prairie prosperity persuaded emigrants
from the eastern provinces to migrate west
within Canada rather than to depart for the
United States. But four out of ten in the region
in 1921 came from outside Canada: from the
British Isles, every country in Europe (Canadians
did not think of Britain as part of Europe),
or the United States. Canadian immigration
policy was unrestrictive, with one
massive exception: immigration laws kept low
the numbers of people of color–Chinese, Japanese,
and South Asian.

The newcomers came as individuals or in
families, but no longer did they come as whole
villages. Canada's magnanimity toward other
ethnic groups was motivated by desperation;
when the Canadian West became more attractive
to migrants, policies became less generous
and less flexible. The 7,400 Russian Doukhobors
who settled in north-central Saskatchewan
in 1899 were denied the privilege of proving
up their lands collectively and had their
homestead entries universally canceled in
1907. Informal block settlement continued;
however, Department of the Interior officials encouraged Ukrainian migrants from the
Austro-Hungarian Empire to choose homesteads
in the parkland belt, which fringed the
prairies to the north, close to countrymen
with whom they shared a language. Their established
Ukrainian neighbors would help
impoverished newcomers through their first
winter without any cost to the government,
and their segregation averted friction with
English-speaking Canadians.

Ukrainian homesteaders also became seasonal
workers for the railways and resource
industries. Although Canada officially sought
farmers from Europe, after 1906 more European
immigrants were actually unskilled
workers destined for the same sort of work
than they were homesteaders or farm workers.
Half or more of those who came were not
"immigrants" at all, but sojourners who
sought work in North America intending to
return to Europe. A durable ethnic pecking
order evolved in the region: English-speaking
Canadians, Britons, and Americans nearest
the top, Swedes, Norwegians, and Protestant
Germans (until World War I) next, and the
laborers and peasant homesteaders from eastern
Europe at the bottom.

This ethnically diverse population set the
Prairie Provinces apart from the rest of Canada,
and to a lesser extent from adjacent states
of the United States. English-speaking westerners
wanted to force European immigrants
to speak English and to conform to British
Canadian values, but the sheer numbers of
immigrants limited their capacity to do so.
The ethnic segregation of both the countryside
and the cities of the Prairie Provinces also
worked against the assimilation of European
immigrants. There were striking differences in
the rural and urban populations of particular
ethnic groups. More than half of British Isles
immigrants lived in cities and towns, but twothirds
of those from the United States were
farmers and three-quarters of Ukrainians
lived in the countryside.

In the rural Prairie Provinces, ethnic background,
time of settlement, available capital,
and differing local environments created different
agricultural patterns. A handful were
large-scale farmers like American immigrant
Charles S. Noble, who cultivated 30,000 acres
of southern Alberta in 1917, when the average
farm was less than 300 acres. Much more numerous
were the near-peasant families like the
Ukrainian settlers of southeastern Manitoba
or northeastern Alberta, who hewed homesteads
from the aspen parkland belt, where
they found the wood and water that they
needed for almost self-sufficient agriculture.
Between these extremes were the families in
the parkland belt and the river valleys who
attempted diversified farming on mixed farms
like the ones that they had grown up on in
Ontario or the United States. Finally, in the
dry plains closest to the Canada-U.S. boundary
were the grain growers. For most farm
families the goal was economic independence
in order to sustain and reproduce the family.
Settlers did not set out alone into the unknown,
but traveled west with family and
friends. The rural society that migrants fashioned
in the Canadian Prairie West before
1920 retained elements of traditional rural societies
alongside elements of modern industrial
society. Settlers within the region shared
the settlement experience, cooperated with
their neighbors to harvest and to thresh, and
took part in the same community activities.

A recession in 1912. 13 interrupted immigration
to the Prairie Provinces. World War I,
which for Canada began in August 1914, stimulated
the economy but made migration
across the Atlantic impossible and discouraged
American immigration. War also made
the relationship between immigrant minorities
and the English-speaking majority more
difficult. English-speaking westerners saw the
war as a patriotic duty to the British Empire
and a struggle for democratic principles, but
their conduct was most undemocratic. Manitoba
in 1916 and Saskatchewan in 1918 abolished
the educational rights of linguistic minorities
and made public schools unilingual;
French was treated as a "foreign" language
and was eliminated along with German and
Ukrainian. English-speaking westerners also
enthusiastically supported the wartime internment
of Ukrainian immigrants, who posed absolutely
no threat, and welcomed the disenfranchisement
of naturalized "enemy aliens"
in the federal election of 1917.

Over nativist opposition, the flow of immigrants
resumed in the mid-1920s. The sources
of the flow shifted. Many fewer migrants came
from Britain and very few from the United
States, and a majority came from central
and eastern Europe. Shut out of the United
States by the quota system introduced in 1924,
Poles, Ukrainians, Mennonites, Czechs, German
Russians, and Hungarians chose the Canadian
West. The federal government allowed
the Canadian Pacific and the Canadian National
Railway to recruit immigrants in Europe
to do pick-and-shovel work in the resource
industries, to work the grain harvest,
and to start small farms on quarter-sections in
the parkland belt, purchased on time from the
railway companies.

Ethnic diversity made the Prairie West polyglot,
but it could not make it pluralistic. In
Saskatchewan the Ku Klux Klan flourished
briefly by connecting nativism and anti-
Catholicism. English-speaking westerners attempted
to force the newcomers into the mold
of Anglo-conformity. But immigrant ethnic
identities persisted, not as static transplantations
from the Old Country but as identities
relocated to and reconstructed within western
Canada. Ethnic minorities acculturated to English
as necessary but spoke their mother
tongue at home: the census reported that in
Saskatchewan 70 percent of Germans and
more than 90 percent of Ukrainians continued
to do so in 1941. They married endogamously
in ethnic churches, belonged to ethnic fraternal
societies, and maintained distinctive residential
and occupational patterns. The minority
ethnic identities measured by these
demographic characteristics persisted in the
Canadian Prairie West longer than they did in
Plains states for several structural reasons, including
primarily rural residence in Canada,
formal and informal block settlement, and the
longer continuation of wide-open immigration.
Eventually, immigrant communities negotiated
their own relationship with Canada
and with the dominant British Canadian culture.
In the Prairie West, immigrant communities
themselves invented the Canadian
"multicultural mosaic" three decades before
governments discovered and sanctioned it.

Without New Deal programs to entice or
compel small-scale farm families off the land,
the economic crisis of the 1930s did not produce
an exodus from the Prairie Provinces as it
did in the Great Plains states. Some farm families
in the Dust Bowl areas stuck it out through
drought and depression; others made new
farms in the northern reaches of the parkland
belt or in Alberta's Peace River country. Not
until World War II, which began for Canada in
1939, did military service and jobs in wartime
industries initiate the migration of hundreds
of thousands of young women and men out of
the countryside, and often out of the region.
This rural depopulation has continued; in 1996
the three Prairie Provinces had only 132,000
farms as compared to 301,000 in 1936, when the
total number of farms reached its peak.

The proportion of immigrants to Canada
who chose the Prairie West as their destination
fell from more than one in two before
1930 to about one in seven after 1950. The total
population of the Prairie West fell from 21 percent
of Canada's population in 1941 to 16 percent
in 1971, where it has remained. The
largest numbers of immigrants who chose the
Prairie Provinces in recent decades have come
from South, Southeast, or East Asia; 7 percent
of Alberta's population traced its origins to
these parts of the world in 1996. The collapse
of the former Soviet Union and of Yugoslavia
also brought small migrations to the Prairie
Provinces from longer-established ethnic
groups. Whatever their origins, recent immigrants
settled overwhelmingly in the large
cities–Calgary, Edmonton, or Winnipeg.

Changes in immigration patterns, migration
from country to city, and internal migration
within the region have profoundly transformed
the three Prairie Provinces. Manitoba
and especially Saskatchewan experience continued
out-migration to Alberta, to the cities
of Edmonton and Calgary in particular. The
2001 census showed that Alberta has more
than half of the regional population of more
than five million. It also showed that, although
the Prairie Provinces contain 80 percent
of Canada's agricultural land, the number
of farm families continues to diminish as a
once rural region becomes ever more urban.

See also: ASIAN AMERICANS: Asian Canadians / IMAGES AND ICONS: Canadian Mosaic; Last Best West / TRANSPORTATION: Railways, Canada.


John Herd Thompson
Duke University




The Canada Yearbook. Ottawa: Statistics Canada, 1867–
2000. Kerr, Donald, and Deryck W. Holdsworth. Historical Atlas of Canada. Vol. 3, Addressing the Twentieth Century 1891–1961. Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 1990.
Lehr, John C., and Yossi Katz. "Crown, Corporation and
Church: The Role of Institutions in the Stability of Pioneer
Settlements in the Canadian West, 1870–1914." Journal of Historical Geography 21 (1995): 413–29.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>