<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.035</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Kansas</field>
      <field name="author">Cigler, Allan J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




KANSAS

The nation's thirty-fourth state was admitted
to the Union on January 29, 1861, after a brief
but contentious history. Prior to the Louisiana
Purchase in 1803, what is now Kansas was occupied
by Native Americans, including the
Kaws, Osages, and Wichitas. A number of Europeans,
including Spanish explorer Francisco
Vásquez de Coronado, had visited the area
from 1541 on. Congress initially attached the
northern portion of the Louisiana Purchase,
to which Kansas was a part, to Indiana Territory.
This area became part of Missouri Territory
in 1812. After the Missouri Compromise
of 1820, which provided for the admission of
Missouri to the Union as a slave state, the area
of Kansas was considered to be part of "Indian
Country" and outside U.S. jurisdiction.

The 1854 Kansas-Nebraska Act was the prelude
for the American settlement of Kansas.
The act superseded the Missouri Compromise,
giving settlers the right to determine
whether Kansas should be a free or slave territory.
An influx of proslavery advocates from
southern states and abolitionists from New
England ensued, resulting in bloodshed. The
fiery abolitionist John Brown was active in the
territory, leading his followers in a massacre of
proslavery Missouri settlers at Pottawatomie
Creek in Franklin County on May 24, 1856.
Later, in 1863, William Quantrill led his proslavery
guerrilla forces in raiding and burning
a number of Kansas farms and towns (including
Lawrence) whose citizens opposed slavery.

Proslavery Democrats controlled the first
territorial government and dominated in the
early years. But by October 1859, after numerous
attempts to draft a constitution, a
document reflecting the views of Republican
free-state forces was approved by a margin of
nearly two to one. Statehood was delayed by
national partisan divisions, which led Democratic
senators from the South to oppose the
addition of a Republican state prior to the
1860 presidential election. It was not until January
21, 1861, after a number of southern senators
had left Washington in anticipation of the
secession of their states, that Kansas received
the necessary votes for admission; the Kansas
statehood bill was signed by President James
Buchanan eight days later.

Since the granting of statehood, Kansas has
remained one of the most Republican of all
states in national politics. The state's political
culture has been characterized as "moralistic,"
and Kansans played prominent leadership
roles in a variety of movements such as populism,
progressivism, and prohibition. Republican
Dwight D. Eisenhower, from Abilene,
served as the thirty-fourth president of the
United States from 1953 to 1961. Two other
Kansans have run (unsuccessfully) for president
on the Republican ticket in this century:
Gov. Alf Landon in 1936 and former U.S. Senate
majority leader Bob Dole in 1996. Kansas's
partisan tendencies survived even the powerful
political forces that brought about the critical
realignments of the 1890s and 1930s. While
the agricultural depressions underlying the
Populist Revolt and the New Deal enabled
third parties and Democrats to gain occasional
short-run advantage, there were few
permanent voter shifts within the electorate,
and the state in each instance quickly returned
to its Republican predilections. Kansas rarely
deviates from the Republican Party in its presidential
voting, and it stands as the only state
not to have elected at least one Democratic
senator since the 1930s. Republicans hold a
45 to 30 percent registration advantage over
Democrats, with 25 percent of registrants
choosing to be independents. In 1998 a Republican
was governor (elected by a three-toone
margin), Republicans had strong majorities
in both houses of the Kansas legislature,
and three of the state's four congressmen were
Republican.

The Republican dominance has always
been a reflection of the state's socioeconomic
population mix. Kansas has lacked the
economic-cultural-racial diversity that often
characterizes two-party competition in other
states. Traditionally Democratic minority
groups enjoy only a modest presence in the
state. Of nearly 2.7 million residents in 2000,
only 5.7 percent were African American, 7 percent
Hispanic, 1.7 percent Asian, and less than
1 percent Native American. Despite an estimated
80,000 members of organized labor,
most a.liated with the afl-cio, right-towork
laws have impeded the development of a
strong union movement that traditionally offers
support to the Democratic Party.

Kansas has an image as a rural, agricultural
state, but urbanization has taken place at a
rapid pace, particularly in the suburbs adjacent
to Kansas City and near Wichita. The
number of farms has dwindled while the average
size has increased, and the proportion of
rural residents in the state is now less than
30 percent. While the rural-based agriculture
and oil and gas industries still are important,
wholesale and retail trade are now the largest
components of the state's economy.

Kansas politics in recent decades has been
dominated by divisions within the Republican
Party between its rural and suburban wings on
such issues as the redistribution of aid from
wealthy suburban school districts to the poorer
rural school districts. In the late 1980s and the
1990s, abortion policy led to major internal divisions
in the Republican Party organization between
Christian Right elements and social moderates.
Republican factionalism has enabled
conservative Democrats to win the governorship
on a number of occasions.


Allan J. Cigler
University of Kansas




Cigler, Allan J., and Burdette A. Loomis. "Kansas: Two-
Party Competition in a One-Party State." In Party Realignment
and State Politics, edited by Maureen Moakley. Columbus:
Ohio State University Press, 1992: 163–78. Drury,
James W. The Government of Kansas. Topeka: University
of Kansas, Capitol Complex Center, 1997. Frederickson,
H. George, ed. Public Policy and the Two States of Kansas.
Lawrence: University Press of Kansas, 1994.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>