<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.war.026</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Long, Stephen H. (1784-1864)</field>
      <field name="author">Nichols, Roger L.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




LONG, STEPHEN H. (1784-1864)

Stephen Harriman Long, army engineer and
explorer, helped foster the idea that the Great
Plains was the Great American Desert. Son of
Moses and Lucy Long, he was born on December
10, 1784, at Hopkinton, New Hampshire.
In 1809 he graduated from Dartmouth
College, and for the next five years he taught
school and worked as a surveyor. Near the end
of the War of 1812, Long became a second lieutenant
in the Army Corps of Engineers. He
remained an army officer for nearly fifty years.

Long hoped to become the next important
western explorer after Lewis and Clark, and in
1818 he received orders to organize and lead a
scientific expedition west. That year he designed
a steamboat, the Western Engineer, to
carry the scientists up the Missouri River, but it
proved unable to navigate that river successfully.
In 1820 Long led a small party of scientists
and soldiers west to the Rocky Mountains.
They examined the land, streams, animals,
plants, and minerals along the way. At the
Rockies they turned south, searching for the
headwaters of the Red River without success.
After nearly starving in the Plains, they returned
to Fort Smith, Arkansas, late in the
summer.

The explorers brought back specimens of
plants and animals, as well as new geographic
information about the Central Plains. Their
report and maps clearly labeled the region as
desert. When taken with similar comments
from Zebulon Pike, Long's descriptions persuaded
many that the Plains was unfit for agriculture.
After this, his duties shifted to planning
railroads and clearing obstructions out
of some of America's larger rivers. His army
career ended in 1863, and he died the next year
at Alton, Illinois, on September 4.

See also IMAGES AND ICONS: Great American Desert.


Roger L. Nichols
University of Arizona




Nichols, Roger L., and Patrick L. Haley. Stephen Long and
American Frontier Exploration. Newark: University of Delaware
Press, 1980.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>