<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.wat.003</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Bow River Irrigation Project</field>
      <field name="author">Regehr, Ted D.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BOW RIVER IRRIGATION PROJECT

The Bow River Irrigation Project developed
the waters of the Bow River for irrigation purposes
in the semiarid districts of south-central
Alberta. It was not the first irrigation project
in western Canada, but eventually it became
one of the largest. The project serves an area of
530,000 acres of land lying between the cities
of Medicine Hat, Calgary, and Lethbridge in
southern Alberta and has brought approximately
210,000 acres under irrigation.

The Bow River Irrigation Project traces its
origins to the Grand Forks Cattle Company,
which was incorporated in 1903. That company
was a successful ranching operation, but
in 1906 its operations were taken over by the
Robins Irrigation Company, which applied to
the federal government of Canada for authority
to purchase 151,180 acres of land as well as
for water rights to develop irrigation works
for 95,143 acres of that land. Di.culties in
raising the required capital resulted in a reorganization
under which the Southern Alberta
Land Company acquired the assets of the former
Grand Forks Cattle Company and of the
Robins Irrigation Company.

The Southern Alberta Land Company began
construction of water diversion works in
1909, but failure or legal inability to sell irrigation
lands before it had completed construction
of all the irrigation works, coupled with a
major accident at one of its headgates and a
severe tightening of the financial markets in
London just before the outbreak of World
War I, forced the Southern Alberta Land
Company into receivership in June 1914. Difficult
and legally contentious negotiations resulted
in acquisition of the assets and obligations
of the Southern Alberta Land Company
by the Canada Land and Irrigation Company
in 1917.

Water for irrigation purposes was first delivered
by the Canada Land and Irrigation Company
in 1920, but severely depressed prices for
wheat in 1922–23, and even more disastrous
drought and commodity price declines after
1929, made it impossible for the company to
meet its financial obligations. Its operations
were taken over in 1935 by the Prairie Farm
Rehabilitation Administration (PFRA), which
continues to operate the huge irrigation works
today.

The Bow River Irrigation Project brought
the benefits of irrigation to more than 200,000
acres of arid and semiarid prairie. Irrigation
has dramatically increased the productive capacity
of vast tracts of prairie lands, but, at
least in dry years, those irrigation projects
have exhausted the available water supplies.
They now threaten the ecology of the entire
Bow River drainage basin.

See also AGRICULTURE: Prairie Farm Rehabilitation Administration.


Ted D. Regehr
University of Saskatchewan and University of Calgary




Gilpin, John. Prairie Promises: History of the Bow River
Irrigation District. Vauxhall, Alberta: Bow River Irrigation
District, 1976. Kirk, D. W. The Bow River Irrigation Project:
The History and Development of the Bow River Irrigation
Project up to and Including Its Purchase by the Government
of Canada in 1950. Regina, Saskatchewan: Prairie Farm
Rehabilitation Administration, 1955.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>