<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.wat.018</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Ogallala Aquifer</field>
      <field name="author">Diffendal, Jr., R. F.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




OGALLALA AQUIFER


Ogallala Aquifer


The Ogallala, or High Plains, Aquifer is a porous
body of complex sediments and sedimentary
rock formations that conducts groundwater
and yields significant quantities of water
to wells and springs. The principal sediments
and rocks of the aquifer range in age from 33
million years old to sediments being deposited
today, but the majority is less than 12 million
years old. Much of the aquifer is composed of
the Ogallala Group or Formation. The dominant
sediments in the Ogallala and the other
hydrogeologic units in the aquifer are riverand
wind-deposited sands.

The aquifer underlies about 174,000 square
miles of the High Plains. The water-saturated
part of the aquifer varies in thickness and is
more than 1,000 feet thick in places. Both the
thickest and the most extensive areas are in Nebraska.
The water from the aquifer is being
pumped by nearly 200,000 irrigation wells,
most of them installed since the 1940s. Installation
rates have varied, with the highest rates
generally occurring during dry years. In places,
particularly in the southern region, pumping
has lowered water levels as much as 200 feet.

Across the Great Plains, many rivers, smaller
streams, and springs periodically go dry; consequently
water from wells is a more reliable
source. Since the late nineteenth century, the
U.S. government has recognized the importance
of finding sources of underground water
to meet the needs of settlers in the Great Plains.
Robert Hay (1895), N. H. Darton (1898, 1899),
and Willard Johnson (1901, 1902) of the U.S.
Geological Survey (USGS) conducted surveys
of the region that helped to locate adequate
supplies. Several types of surface sediments
that accumulated during the Quaternary period
(the last 1.6 million years of geologic history)
were recognized in their reports. The
Ogallala Formation of late Tertiary age was
described first by Darton in some detail from
study of the unit in western Nebraska. Darton
also identified Tertiary sediment and rock layers
older than the Ogallala, called the Arikaree
Formation, Gering Formation, and the still
older Brule Clay in parts of western Nebraska.

Later geologists have recognized that the
Ogallala in Nebraska can be subdivided into
formations and have raised the Ogallala to a
higher level called a group. The Gering Formation
has been included in the Arikaree. The
name Brule Clay has been changed to Brule
Formation, and several widespread subdivisions
of the Brule strata have been recognized.
The distributions of the Brule, Arikaree, Ogallala,
and the Broadwater Formations, all of
which were deposited in the middle to late
Tertiary period (an interval from 33 million to
1.6 million years ago), have been mapped in
Nebraska and adjacent Great Plains states.
Only the Ogallala is known from Kansas south.
Most of these deposits yield water to wells and
springs and are thus parts of an aquifer system,
which has been called both the Ogallala Aquifer
and the High Plains Aquifer.

Water is present in interconnected openings
or pore spaces passing through the formations
or between sediment grains of the formations.
If the openings are large enough to allow the
water to move through them, the formations
are said to be permeable. Most of the water in
the High Plains Aquifer moves through the
narrow, interconnected pore spaces between
grains of gravel and/or sand (here gravel is any
sediment grain larger than two millimeters in
intermediate diameter; sand, 2–0.0625 mm;
silt and clay have smaller intermediate diameters).
Larger fractures and openings enlarged
by water erosion have been observed in the
several units of the aquifer but are only locally
important. Rocks beneath the High Plains
Aquifer are generally impermeable and thus
act as a seal that prevents water from moving
into them.

The origins and natures of the various units
di&#129;ãer. The upper parts of the Brule Formation
are primarily composed of volcanic dust and
ash, carried by winds from erupting volcanoes
in the west to the northern High Plains and
deposited as blankets over the region. After
the Brule was deposited, rivers draining across
the developing High Plains eroded valleys into
the formation. The deeper parts of the valleys
were filled with river deposits, consisting
largely of reworked volcanic debris of the Gering
Formation. Most of the remainder of the
Arikaree Group is wind-deposited volcanic
ash that fills the parts of the ancient valleys
above the Gering. The Ogallala Group is a
complex and heterogeneous mass of sediment
mostly composed of river alluvium derived
from erosion of the southern Rocky Mountains.
During deposition of the Ogallala and
the younger Broadwater Formation, rivers repeatedly
eroded valleys and then filled these
valleys. Minor finer-grained lake sediments,
volcanic ash deposits, and lime-cemented soil
horizons occur throughout the Ogallala sequence. Wind-deposited sands are common
in the Ogallala in the Southern High Plains.
Quaternary river alluvium, wind deposits,
lake beds, and volcanic ash layers cover much
of the High Plains and fill parts of valleys cutting
across the High Plains.

The USGS estimates that in 1980 the aquifer
contained about 3.25 billion acre-feet of drainable
water (an acre-foot is the volume of a oneacre
area one foot thick or 43,560 cubic feet). If
impounded on the surface, this volume of water
would cover the High Plains region to an
average depth of about thirty feet. Most of the
water in the aquifer comes from precipitation
on the High Plains. With the increase of irrigated
agriculture, water levels have dropped in
places where the groundwater from the aquifer
was pumped out faster than water from precipitation
moved through the sediments and
rocks to replace it. In other areas, water levels
have risen where precipitation has allowed water
to infiltrate the aquifer at rates greater than
those at which water was pumped out, or where
reservoirs and canals have lost water to the aquifer
at rates greater than the withdrawal.

See also PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT: Geology.


R. F. Diffendal Jr.
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Darton, N. H. "Geology and Water Resources of Nebraska
West of the One Hundred and Third Meridian." U.S. Geological
Survey 19th Annual Report, Part 4 (1899): 719–85.
Dugan, J. T., and Sharpe, J. B. "Water-level Changes in the
High Plains Aquifer—Predevelopment to 1994." U.S. Geological
Survey Water-Resources Investigations Report 95–4208
(1996). Johnson, W. D. "The High Plains and Their
Utilization." U.S. Geological Survey 22nd Annual Report,
Part 4 (1902): 631–69.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>