<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.sr.020</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Football, Six-Man</field>
      <field name="author">Maslowski, Peter Wunder, John R.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




FOOTBALL, SIX-MAN

Invented in 1934 by Stephen Epler, a Chester,
Nebraska, teacher who wanted students at
small high schools to experience playing football,
six-man football is a special Plains phenomenon.
After envisioning a modified version
of traditional football, Epler spent the
summer of 1934 at the University of Nebraska
developing his ideas in a project for a summer
graduate education course. The first game was
played in Hebron, Nebraska, on September 26,
1934, before more than 1,000 fans. In the only
six-man game that year, players from Chester
and nearby Hardy lined up against boys from
Alexandria and Belvidere high schools, resulting
in a 19 to 19 tie. The next year uniforms and
equipment were purchased for several six-man
teams, and enough schools decided to take on
this new Plains sport to form a league.

At its height in 1951, six-man football was
played in 2,463 schools in forty-eight states.
Plains states claimed five of the top ten, with
Nebraska second at 167, Texas third at 163,
North Dakota sixth at 120, Montana eighth at
85, and South Dakota ninth at 83 schools. In
1997 only 158 schools in seven states (six of
them Plains states) fielded six-man football
teams: Texas (90), Nebraska (21), Colorado
(17), Montana (14), New Mexico (12), Kansas
(2), and California (2). With increasing pressure
on smaller schools to consolidate, fewer
and fewer six-man football teams will be organized.
For example, after the 1997 season Nebraska
lost seven teams, leaving only fourteen;
1998 marked the last year for the sport in
a high school tournament, because future
school consolidations will reduce the number
below a critical mass necessary for a legitimate
play-off system.

Six-man football is different in several ways
from eleven- and eight-man football. Perhaps
the most colorful rule–one that has resulted
in at least two distinctive Plains phrases–is
that if an opponent achieves a lead of fortyfive
points or more in the second half, the
game is called. In Texas, this is the slaughter
rule, and so "to be slaughtered" takes on a new
meaning. In Nebraska small towns, local expressions
include "to be forty-fived," which
is a phrase residents hope will never be said
about their team. Other noteworthy differences
in this high-scoring game include a first
down requiring advancing the ball fifteen
rather than ten yards; the six-man field being
80 (not 100) yards long; all players being eligible
for a pass, which can make even the center
a "skill" position; and the quarterback having
to lateral the ball in order for the offense to
advance the ball (since 1998 the quarterback is
also able to make a handoff). Scoring is also
distinctive. Because preventing a kick from
being blocked is very difficult, a successful
field goal counts four points in six-man football,
and a kick after a touchdown counts two
points, while an extra point scored by a pass
or run is only one point. Since size, speed,
agility, and finesse are as important for successful
six-man football players as they are for
eleven- and eight-man team members, these
teams have produced players who have gone
on to star in college football programs and
even professional leagues.

In 1993 a Wall Street Journal reporter visited
several small towns in West Texas and described
a Friday night six-man football game
in Amherst, a Last Picture Show kind of town.
At the time the reporter thought that the
game's popularity was making a comeback,
but that observation seemed premature in the
late 1990s. Much more accurate was his notion
that six-man football boosts the spirit of small
Plains communities.

See also EDUCATION: School Consolidation and Reorganization.


Peter Maslowski
University of Nebraska-Lincoln
John R. Wunder
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Ingersoll, Bruce. "You Might Call This Football Lite, but It
Keeps a Ritual Alive." Wall Street Journal, December 3,
1993. Secter, Bob. "A Revival of Six-Man Football." Los
Angeles Times, October 23, 1991.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>