<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.gen.029</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Quilting Circles</field>
      <field name="author">Ronning, Kari</field>
      <field name="text">

 




QUILTING CIRCLES

Quilting has long been a means of connecting
women in the Great Plains. As material objects,
quilts connected European American
settlers with their past homes. As process,
making quilts gave women an acceptable outlet
for their creative powers while fulfilling
their household duties. Sharing the labor of
quilting, through formal and informal quilting
circles, relieved the isolation of women's
lives. Especially in the early years of settlement,
communal quilting activities were inclusive;
as the entire quilt had to be quilted in
one day, it would have been counterproductive
as well as impolitic to leave any neighbor
out. It seems likely that European immigrants
assimilated the Anglo-American quilt traditions
through such gatherings.

Although most quilts were made for domestic
use, women also joined to make quilts for
public purposes: helping the needy or honoring
community leaders through presentation
quilts inscribed with the names of the makers.
Women's church societies raised money by
quilting: a Ladies Aid in Harvard, Nebraska,
for example, earned more than $1,400 in seven
years through quilting and socials.

Women living in towns who shared an interest–
temperance, suffrage, self-improvement,
or quilting–found it easier to form organizations
than did rural women. A "young
ladies crazy patchwork society" in 1884 in Red
Cloud, Nebraska, is an early instance of a specifically
quilt-related group. When quiltmaking
regained popularity in the 1910s and 1920s,
better transportation enabled rural women to
come together more often. While women still
made quilts as individuals, in the 1920s and
1930s they also turned to friends and neighbors
who met in many informal clubs, with
names like the Willing Workers, the Helping
Hands, or the Friendship Club. The hostess at
each meeting would "furnish work" for members,
who often made the quilt blocks as well
as helped to quilt the finished top.

Despite standardizing influences such as
quilts pictured in national women's magazines,
patterns published by regional media
such as the Kansas City Star, and kits and patterns
distributed through national companies,
distinctive styles evolved in some communities.
Emporia, Kansas, became a center for
some of the finest appliqué quiltmaking of the
twentieth century. Some of the Mennonite
communities scattered throughout the Great
Plains have become known for a style of
whole-cloth quilts; auctions of their quilts
benefit relief and mission work. Another unusual
style, based on the Lone Star design, has
evolved among Native Americans on reservations
in the Dakotas.

Quiltmaking declined again during World
War II, as transportation and materials again
became scarce. Still, church sewing societies in
rural areas kept the skills, patterns, and traditions
alive until the late 1960s, when interest in
the past and in handmade things led to a revival
of interest that has lasted since that time.
Quilt guilds began to form on the local level in
the early 1970s and spread to state and national
levels. These guilds develop the individual
quilter, add to the body of knowledge of
quilting, and continue the philanthropic work
of the early quilting circles in the Plains.

See also FOLKWAYS: Quilting.


Kari Running
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Brackman, Barbara, Jennie A. Chinn, Gayle R. Davis, Terry
Thompson, Sara Reimer Farley, and Nancy Hornback.
Kansas Quilts and Quilters. Lawrence: University Press of
Kansas, 1993. Crews, Patricia Cox, and Ronald Naugle,
eds. Nebraska Quilts and Quiltmakers. Lincoln: University
of Nebraska Press, 1991. Pulford, Florence. Morning Star Quilts: A Presentation of the Work and Lives of Northern Plains Indian Women. Los Altos CA: Leone Publications,
1989.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>