<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.med.022</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Hall, Monte (b. 1923)</field>
      <field name="author">Wishart, David J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




HALL, MONTE (b. 1923)

Monte Hall, television celebrity and noted philanthropist,
was born in Winnipeg on August
25, 1923, and brought up in the close-knit Jewish
community there. His maternal grandfather
migrated from the village of Poveltch in
the Ukraine, stepping off the train in Winnipeg
in 1901. Within a few years he had built a successful
fruit and vegetable business. Hall traces
his strong Jewish roots to lessons learned in his
grandfather's home and to the example of his
mother, a leading figure among Canadian
Jewry. He believes that his Jewish upbringing
in his grandfather's home–a home filled with
four generations of relatives–gave him the
sense of humor that prepared him for his
show-business career.

While a student at the University of Manitoba
in the early 1940s, Hall acted in musical
and dramatic productions and served as a
host of Canadian army shows. After graduation
with a bachelor of science degree in 1945,
he moved to Toronto and continued his career
as an actor, emcee, and sportscaster. In New
York from 1955 to 1960 he was emcee of NBC's
radio show Monitor. Hall's big break came in
Hollywood in 1963, when he and coproducer
Stefan Hatos put together Let's Make a Deal,
the game show where contestants from the
audience dressed in outrageous costumes to
get Hall's attention and offered items they had
brought with them in exchange for valuable
or nonsense prizes hidden in boxes behind a
curtain. With Hall as the amiable host, Let's Make a Deal ran from 1963 to 1968 on NBC,
from 1968 to 1976 on ABC, and briefly again on
NBC in 1990-91.

Hall has also devoted his time to myriad
charitable and philanthropic endeavors. He
was recognized for this work in 1988, when he
was made an Officer of the Order of Canada,
the country's most prestigious award. Honorary
degrees at the Universities of Manitoba
(1987) and Haifa (1989) and at the Hahneman
College of Medicine (1988) as well as induction
into the National Broadcasters Hall of
Fame (1995) also attest to Monte Hall's lifetime
achievements.


David J. Wishart
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Hall, Monte. "My Canadian Jewish Childhood." Western States Jewish History 26 (1994): 101–11.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>