<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.mus.046</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Trudell, John (b. 1946)</field>
      <field name="author">Reinhardt, Akim D.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




TRUDELL, JOHN (b. 1946)

Group portrait with John Trudell, on left. (newtopiamagazine.files.wordpress.com)
     

A Santee Dakota, John Trudell was born in
Omaha, Nebraska, on February 15, 1946, and
raised on the Santee Sioux Reservation. Initially,
he achieved national notoriety for his
political activism on behalf of Native Americans.
He was a leader of the Indians of All
Tribes' occupation of Alcatraz in 1969, and in
that capacity he hosted a radio program in
1970, Radio Free Alcatraz, that was broadcast
in Berkeley, Los Angeles, and New York City.
From 1973 to 1979 he served as the national
chairman of the American Indian Movement
(AIM). After the fire-bombing death of his
wife, mother-in-law, and three daughters at
their home on the Duck Valley Reservation in
Nevada on February 11, 1979, Trudell began
moving away from direct political action and
devoted more of his time to artistic and intellectual
endeavors.

In 1981 he wrote his first book, Living in Reality.
In 1985 he formed the Graffiti Band with
Jesse Ed Davis, a prolific studio guitarist from
Oklahoma City who was of Seminole and Kiowa
descent. Together they wedded Trudell's poetry,
which ranged from political and social commentary
to love poems, with Davis's unique
musical style. They released AKA Graffiti Man
and Heart Jump Bouquet before Davis's death in
1988. AKA was subsequently rereleased on a major
label (Rykodisk) in 1992 and was executively
produced by Jackson Browne. It featured the
original tapes of Davis and Trudell, which were
remastered and fleshed out with additional
musicians. Guest appearances were made by
Browne and Kris Kristofferson. AKA received
high critical acclaim (Bob Dylan called it the
best album of the year) and was followed by
Johnny Damas and Me (1995).

Trudell has also acted in several feature
films, including Thunderheart (1992), On Deadly Ground (1994), and Smoke Signals
(1998). In 1994 he published his second book,
Stickman.

See also PROTEST AND DISSENT: American Indian Movement.


Akim D. Reinhardt
Towson University





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>