<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.mus.025</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Kansas City Jazz</field>
      <field name="author">Ineck, Tom</field>
      <field name="text">

 




KANSAS CITY JAZZ

Like its counterparts in other urban cultural
hotbeds, Kansas City jazz emerged in the early
decades of the twentieth century with a distinctive
sense of place. The unique Kansas City
brand of jazz drew on the orchestral ragtime,
boogie-woogie, and rural blues of the region;
was based largely on repetitive phrases, or
riffs; and was performed by big bands. In that
respect, it owes little to the more familiar jazz
style of New Orleans, which was distinguished
by its small group interplay, or polyphony. By
contrast, Kansas City jazz is known for its
powerful rhythmic drive and the dominance
of reed instruments, especially the saxophone.

Kansas City's prominence as a jazz center in
the 1920s and 1930s can be attributed in part to
geography. A hub for itinerant territory bands
that performed throughout the Great Plains
and Southwest, Kansas City attracted a talented
cross section of musicians. They came
from Oklahoma City and Tulsa, from Dallas
and San Antonio, from Omaha and Wichita,
often stopping in Kansas City for a respite
from the road, to hire new band members
from the growing stable of players, or to sample
the burgeoning nightlife. From disparate
musical backgrounds they conceived and gave
birth to a new, exhilarating style of jazz.

The long reign of mayor and political boss
Tom Pendergast also made it possible for jazz
to flourish in Prohibition Era Kansas City.
From about 1925 until his indictment in 1938
for income tax fraud, Pendergast virtually controlled
the city, awarding construction contracts
to friends and relatives and subtly encouraging
vice as bootleggers, gangsters, and
corrupt politicians exploited the lucrative network
of speakeasies and all-night cabarets.
Pendergast's permissive political policies unwittingly
nurtured Kansas City jazz. During
the peak years, the city boasted several hundred
nightclubs, ballrooms, and other venues
offering live music–a profitable training
ground for musicians to learn their trade and
develop the individual sound that is the hallmark
of jazz.

Dozens of the most popular clubs–including
the Sunset Club, the Subway Club, the
Boulevard Lounge, the Cherry Blossom, the
Lone Star, the Panama, Lucille's Paradise Band
Box, Elks' Rest, and the Old Kentucky Bar-
B-Que–were clustered in a district bordered
by Twelfth Street on the north and Eighteenth
Street on the south. Outside the district but
still within easy walking distance were the
Amos and Andy, Greenleaf Gardens, and the
Hey Hay Club. Most famous of all was the
Reno Club, where the Count Basie Orchestra
got its start.

Kansas City jazz evolved as performance
opportunities proliferated in theaters, dance
halls, and, most importantly, intimate afterhours
clubs. Because many of the early practitioners
of Kansas City jazz were traveling musicians
staying in town only briefly, the musical
arrangements remained simple enough for
all to learn quickly, often during informal jam
sessions. These so-called head arrangements,
many of which incorporated standard threechord
blues patterns, were rehearsed and
committed to memory, allowing more freedom
for instrumental soloists.

Kansas City's all-night jam sessions are legendary.
In some clubs a rhythm section was
installed, and guest musicians were encouraged
to sit in. In other venues the sessions
would begin after the regular evening's entertainment
had ended and continue until the
last players were ready for bed or breakfast,
which was served at many local diners catering
to the city's nocturnal revelers. Competitive
jam sessions, or cutting contests, among
musicians were so prolific that a hierarchy
evolved. Only the most skilled musicians were
allowed to take the stage at the Sunset, the
Subway, and the Reno, while other clubs were
reserved for beginners.

The earliest and most important exemplar of
the Kansas City jazz style was Bennie Moten's
Kansas City Orchestra, which employed many
of the best musicians and made some of the
music's most memorable recordings such as
the standards "Moten Swing" and "Prince of
Wails." Other significant bands in the early history
of Kansas City jazz were Walter Page's Blue
Devils, George E. Lee's Novelty Singing Orchestra,
the Alphonso Trent Orchestra, and
Troy Floyd's Shadowland Orchestra.

After Moten's sudden death in 1935, several
members of the band formed the nucleus of a
smaller ensemble led by pianist Bill Basie. It
was later expanded to become the Count Basie
Orchestra. Until his death in 1984, Basie was
the most prominent and most publicized ambassador
of the Kansas City jazz style, repeatedly
touring the world to popular acclaim.

Other Kansas City bands of note were led
by Andy Kirk, Harlan Leonard, and Jay Mc-
Shann, best known for giving a young alto
saxophonist named Charlie Parker his first big
break. During a stint with McShann from
1940 to 1942, Parker toured and made his first
recordings, although he is better known for
later pioneering the bebop style after his move
to New York City.

In the competitive, superheated climate of
the Kansas City jam sessions, the powerful
sound of the tenor saxophone emerged as the
dominant instrument. Among the great tenor
players who participated in these storied sessions
were Lester Young, Coleman Hawkins,
Ben Webster, Herschel Evans, Chu Berry,
Budd Johnson, and Buddy Tate. Also contributing
to the driving swing sound associated
with Kansas City jazz were the walking bass
technique, the time-keeping function of the
rhythm guitar, and the use of the hi-hat for
greater rhythmic emphasis. All of these were
exemplified by early members of the Basie
rhythm section–bassist Walter Page, guitarist
Freddie Green, and drummer Jo Jones.

The Kansas City sound was largely instrumental,
but it also drew on the blues vocal
tradition of the Deep South and Southwest.
The blues shouter added variety to the concert
repertoire and became a fixture of Kansas City
jazz bands. Among the best were Joe Turner,
Jimmy Rushing, and Walter Brown. Similarly,
boogie-woogie piano players like McShann
and Pete Johnson had a role in developing the
Kansas City jazz style but with a sound closely
related to the blues. Pianist Mary Lou Williams
had a more sophisticated jazz keyboard style
and also distinguished herself as a composer.

As the era of "Pendergast prosperity" ended
in the early 1940s, so did many employment
opportunities for musicians. The popular,
dance-friendly Kansas City swing style would
eventually be incorporated into mainstream
jazz, where its irresistible rhythms can still be
heard.

See also CITIES AND TOWNS: Kansas City, Kansas and Missouri.


Tom Ineck
Nebraska Humanities Council




Driggs, Frank. "The Real Kansas City Jazz." Liner notes
for the CD.  The Real Kansas City Jazz of the '20s, '30s, '40s,
Columbia Records 64855 (March 1996). Robinson, J. Bradford.
The New Grove Dictionary of Jazz, S.V."Kansas City
jazz." New York: St. Martin's Press, 1988. Russell, Ross. Jazz Style in Kansas City and the Southwest. Berkeley: University
of California Press, 1971.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>