<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.arc.010</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Commercial Architecture</field>
      <field name="author">Longstreth, Richard</field>
      <field name="text">

 




COMMERCIAL ARCHITECTURE

Buildings designed specifically for commercial
and related business functions appeared
early and figured prominently in the settlement
of the Great Plains. Stores, banks, office
blocks, restaurants and bars, and hotels were
all well-defined types by the mid.nineteenth
century, when the region was opened to European
American settlement. While many new
settlers took up agriculture and lived dispersed
on the land, others came to pursue
trades and professions and were actively engaged
in town building. In many parts of the
Great Plains the competition among nascent
communities was intense. Many boosters harbored
visions of their towns becoming metropolises
in the span of a generation, just as
had occurred to midwestern centers such as
Chicago and St. Louis.

Virtually from the inception of settlement,
a principal business street began to emerge
in Great Plains towns. This first-generation
growth was impermanent in both intent and
appearance. Buildings were generally of woodframe
construction and were utilitarian in
character, with little or no embellishment.
They were also modest in size, occupying only
a portion of their lots and seldom exceeding
one or two stories. Like the businesses they
held, these buildings were initial ventures; it
was presumed they would be replaced later by
more substantial quarters.

The overplatting of towns in the Great
Plains led to many instances where communities
fell far short of original expectations.
At the same time, hundreds of places did advance
to the second generation of growth,
which entailed permanent commercial buildings
erected approximately two to four decades
after initial settlement. The new buildings
were generally of substantial masonry
wall construction. They consumed the full
width and much of the depth of their lots and
boasted ornamental fronts, often with cast- or
stamped-iron details. The majority of these
buildings were two stories tall; some, especially
those housing hotels, theaters, and fraternal
organizations, were three or four stories.
Only in the largest cities such as Omaha
were greater heights reached before the turn
of the twentieth century.

Second-generation buildings were tightly
clustered for purposes of convenience but also
out of a collective desire to make the community
appear impressive. As in towns farther
east, these commercial centers rose as symbols
of attainment and potential for their communities.
Individual design and group arrangement
emulated established urban models;
only the character of overall development–
the wide main street, the low density of surrounding
residential areas, the expansiveness
of open space beyond–distinguished Plains
towns from older cities to the east. Aspirations
of metropolitan stature began to dissipate by
the early twentieth century, as the industry
needed to sustain large concentrations of people
failed to materialize.

The region supported few true cities; in numerous
cases town centers did not expand significantly
during the decades that followed.
Instead, commercial development was a process
of small, incremental changes to the existing
fabric, many of them in response to functional
demands. The growth of retailing, for
example, led to the construction of new department
stores and, by the 1920s, the remodeling
of others to accommodate emerging
national chains such as Montgomery Ward
and J. C. Penney. With the rapid rise of electrification
and telephone networks, utility
companies often erected fancy new quarters.
In the late nineteenth century many towns
of 2,000 people or more had at least one theater,
often called an opera house. Many opera
houses were later supplanted by movie theaters,
with exotic fronts and interior spaces.
The hotel was often the largest, best-appointed
building in town. Between 1900 and 1950 and
especially during the 1920s, with the proliferation
of automobile travel, imposing multistory
hotels were erected with elaborate public
rooms. The automobile also led to the creation
of new building types, including sales
and service facilities, filling stations, and tourist
courts.

Until the 1960s most downtowns retained
the business functions that served their communities
and the rural areas beyond. But even
by the 1920s small-scale business dispersal was
evident in the larger towns. Many of these facilities
were modest, purveying routine goods
in residential neighborhoods. Clusters of more
than two or three commercial buildings were
rare except in cities or in districts catering to
large numbers of college students. While most
filling and service stations were concentrated
in the center, growing numbers were dispersed,
primarily along main routes through
the community. These arteries also attracted
tourist courts, which generally were sited near
the periphery.

Substantial changes occurred to the appearance,
configuration, and siting of commercial
buildings during the second half of
the twentieth century. Designs sporting the
abstract vocabularies of modernism, rare
in the region before World War II, had become
ubiquitous for buildings of all types by
the 1950s. Many commercial establishments
already standing were given new veneers,
often covering the entire facade. Spiraling demand
for space to accommodate motorists led
to the demolition of existing buildings for
parking lots. Banks erected conspicuous new
quarters on the edge of downtown in what
had been residential blocks. Business development
away from the center grew. By the 1960s
shopping centers had emerged to challenge
the downtown's hegemony, and the continued
development of such places has led to the decay
or a much narrower focus of commercial
functions in the core. Commercial centers in
many small towns have been rendered redundant
by improved highway access to regional
facilities in larger communities. As
pronounced as such shifts have been, they embody
national characteristics no less than
did the commercial center of the nineteenth
century.

See also CITIES AND TOWNS: Main Street; 
Small Towns.


Richard Longstreth
George Washington University




Hudson, John C. Plains Country Towns. Minneapolis:
University of Minnesota Press, 1985. Larson, Paul Clifford,
ed. The Spirit of H. H. Richardson on the Midland Prairies: Regional Transformations of an Architectural Style. Ames:
Iowa State University Press, 1988. Longstreth, Richard. The Buildings of Main Street: A Guide to American Commercial Architecture. Washington DC: Preservation Press, 1987.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>