<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.arc.053</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Volga Warehouse Districts</field>
      <field name="author">Haecker, George A.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




WAREHOUSE DISTRICTS


"Jobbers' Canyon," looking south along Ninth Street from Farnam Street, Omaha, Nebraska


In the last half of the nineteenth century, as
settlement moved westward, an intriguing
building type called the warehouse, or jobbers,
district developed in "gateway cities"
in the Great Plains. These districts marked
the establishment of an urban presence in the
Great Plains. Where they remain today, they
are among the strongest and richest of central
business neighborhoods.

At their peak in the 1860s, there were over
sixty such districts in the Great Plains and
Midwest. This number had declined to twenty
by 1930, and today only a handful remain with
their original integrity intact. Plains cities notable
for the development of these districts include,
from north to south, Winnipeg, Manitoba;
Sioux City, Iowa; Omaha and Lincoln,
Nebraska; and St. Joseph and Kansas City,
Missouri.

A number of factors in the transport of
goods and services came together to create the
need for and configuration of these districts.
Where there was a break in a method of transport
(e.g., from cart to water or water to
horse), a settlement usually occurred. When
there was a break in the ownership of the
goods transported, a commercial area developed.
Thus in the Great Plains a number of
gateway cities developed where these changes
in transport and ownership occurred.

Farming and settlement development in the
Great Plains created a large demand for goods.
Originally, these were stockpiled in East Coast
warehouses and shipped via wagon and river
to various western settlements and outposts.
With the development of the railroad and the
telegraph in the 1850s and 1860s, it was possible
to do the "jobbing" of goods from the
Midwest rather than from East Coast locations.
Merchants communicated their orders
by wire. The goods could then be shipped e.-
ciently by rail to gateway points, where they
were stored for sale and then transshipped to
smaller wholesalers and retailers scattered
throughout the region. This situation created
a demand for large storage buildings and was
the economic force that produced a warehouse
district. This commercial engine roared
from the 1850s to the crash of 1893, then revived
around 1900 and continued through the
1920s. Then, because of trucking and transportation
changes, the need for large jobbing
areas and their distinctive buildings slowly
disappeared.

The architectural style of the warehouse
buildings varied from austere brick boxes that
were relatively unadorned to rich examples of
Renaissance Revival and Richardsonian Romanesque.
A typical district, like Omaha's,
was a mix of building styles. The architectural
strength of these areas lay not so much in the
individual buildings as in the collective character
of the districts they formed. In general,
they were laid out on a grid pattern, filling
whole blocks from curb to curb and ranging
up to eight or nine stories high. This
height, combined with their street-level activity
around office areas, loading docks, and
traffic, created a strong urban character. In
many cases, these buildings provided the most
identifiable "city element" of their communities
as well as the richest architecture.

The need for large floor areas and the strict
functional requirements dictated some unique
structural solutions. Also, encouraged in part
by the tremendous amount of rebuilding required
after the Chicago fire of 1871, many innovative
engineering and construction solutions
developed that spread throughout the
Midwest and Great Plains. The Chicago architectural
firms of Burnham and Root and Adler
and Sullivan were early leaders in these engineering
and architectural advancements.

The structure of a typical warehouse included
exterior brick bearing walls with heavy
timber columns and joists with wood flooring.
Heavy timber, with large cross sections of
wood, proved to be more fire resistant than
cast iron, which would warp and sag at temperatures
at which wood was still noncombustible.
Toward the end of the warehouse era
a new structural system developed in reinforced
concrete. Pioneered by Deere and Company
of Moline, Illinois, and their in-house
architect, Oscar Eckerman, this system consisted
of brick bearing walls with reinforced
columns and flat concrete slabs. The flat-slab
technology eliminated the height requirement
of beams and joists and developed the most
efficient floor areas for high-volume storage.
This system was also virtually fireproof, and,
concurrently, many innovative fire safety details
were developed, such as fireproof exit
stairs and stand pipes for water distribution.

The functional requirements that produced
the warehouse districts declined from the
1920s on. The districts slowly fell into disuse
until the early 1970s, when they were rediscovered
for a variety of retail, commercial,
and housing activities. Today, warehouse districts
are enjoying a rebirth, and where they
remain they still represent some of the best
architecture and urban character of Great
Plains cities.

See also CITIES AND TOWNS: River Towns.


George A. Haecker
Bahr Vermeer and Haecker Architects




Eaton, Leonard K. Gateway Cities and Other Essays. Ames:
Iowa State University Press, 1989.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>