<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.afam.005</field>
      <field name="titleMain">African Canadians</field>
      <field name="author">Sehpard, R. Bruce</field>
      <field name="text">

 




AFRICAN CANADIANS

Between 1905 and 1912 some 1,500 African
Americans migrated to the Plains region of
Canada. They came from Oklahoma, although
a few families were from Kansas and Texas.
They settled in small, rural communities in
the Canadian provinces of Saskatchewan and
Alberta.

The first black farmers began arriving in
1905. They appear to have been lured north by
reports of good agricultural land being available.
During the late nineteenth and early
twentieth centuries, the federal government of
Canada launched an extensive campaign in
the U.S. Midwest and Great Plains to attract
experienced farmers. Advertisements flooded
regional newspapers, pamphlets were widely
distributed, and Canadian exhibits were regular
features at state and local agricultural fairs.
The Canadian advertising did not mention
race as a factor in determining who would be
allowed to settle in the northern dominion.

The trickle of black farmers into western
Canada increased substantially when Oklahoma
became a state in 1907. The Oklahoma
Democratic Party campaigned for delegates to
the Constitutional Convention, and later the
first state legislature, on a "Jim Crow" segregation
platform. Their racist appeals were
effective and, once elected, the Democrats
moved quickly to implement a range of racial
segregation measures. Black Oklahomans
reacted to these developments by organizing,
petitioning, boycotting, protesting,
and launching court challenges. Their tactics
were no more successful in the new state than
they had been elsewhere in the South. This led
some of them to leave Oklahoma, and one of
their destinations was the much-promoted
lands available in western Canada.

The movement north was renewed in 1910
when Oklahoma Democrats moved to disenfranchise
African Americans. Black Americans
had traditionally voted for Lincoln's
party, the Republicans. Their votes, when
combined with a sizable white Republican minority
in Oklahoma, always presented a challenge
to the Democrats' political hold on the
state. Three years after they segregated African
Americans in public services, the Democrats
eliminated the black voter from the state's political
scene.

White western Canadians shared many of
their American neighbors' racial attitudes,
though they rarely expressed them as violently.
They reacted overwhelmingly against
the black migration and successfully petitioned
their federal government to stop African
Americans from coming north. At first
the Canadian federal authorities tried to discourage
blacks by not sending information
to prospective African American settlers and
by delaying their entry at the border. These
methods were only partially effective, and
eventually the Immigration Branch of the Canadian
Department of the Interior sent two
agents to Oklahoma to try to stop black settlers
from leaving for Canada. One of these
agents was particularly effective, probably because
he was himself black, and by late 1911 the
African American migration from Oklahoma
was ending. Still concerned about possible
migration, the Canadian federal cabinet approved
an order barring blacks from entering
Canada. When the work of the agents in
Oklahoma proved to be successful, the order
was quietly repealed.

African Americans who managed to get
through Canada's immigration barriers appear
to have avoided heavily settled areas on
the Canadian Plains, possibly in an effort
to minimize contact with whites. The areas
where they chose to settle were remote, even
by the standards of the settlement era. Black
farmers headed to the alternating bush and
meadowlands that form the northern boundary
of the Canadian Great Plains. The principal
settlement in Saskatchewan was along the
North Saskatchewan River, north of the town
of Maidstone. In Alberta, African Americans
fanned out from Edmonton, forming an arc
of settlements at Breton, Lobstick Lake, Wildwood,
and Amber Valley.

African American families in western Canada
went to work immediately, transforming
the bush and meadowlands into productive
farms. It was hard work, and they had to learn
new ways of farming. Black pioneers had
farmed cotton and tobacco in Oklahoma but
now had to make a transition to raising grain
and livestock.

Their hard work eventually paid dividends,
and within a decade of initial settlement most
black farmers were well established. Within
those years they also began to create the institutions
that gave substance to their Canadian
communities. One particularly important
social institution was the school, because
a large number of children had come north
and were soon joined by brothers and sisters
born in Canada. African Americans soon
learned that they were not completely isolated
from white society, and that racially mixed
schools were as delicate an issue for whites
living north of the forty-ninth parallel as for
those south of it. Black children were barred
from one Alberta school, while another African
American community in Alberta organized
its own separate school. In Saskatchewan
black children were segregated in their
own school for several years.

As with so many rural areas across the
Great Plains, African American communities
began losing their young people to the economic 
lure of the cities. Yet racial prejudice
was also common in the cities of the Canadian
Plains during the early twentieth century, and
the new African Canadians found that they
were limited to jobs in construction, cartage
and hauling, and meatpacking. African Canadians
also found that railroading was one of
the few industries open to them, and blacks
from western Canada (like their counterparts
in the United States) found steady employment
as porters, although the more lucrative
and prestigious position of conductor was
closed to them for decades. These African Canadian
railroad families gradually relocated
across the country, and today the descendants
of western Canada's black pioneers are found
in railroad centers such as Vancouver, Calgary,
Winnipeg, Toronto, and Montreal.

While they faced persistent racial prejudice,
black pioneers and their offspring quickly
identified with their new country. Perhaps
there was no better indicator of that allegiance
than the readiness with which young African
Canadians volunteered for the Canadian
armed forces during World Wars I and II.
Black Canadians served their country with
distinction during both conflicts.

African Americans who migrated to Saskatchewan
and Alberta were seeking a refuge
from the racism they had experienced in the
United States. They headed north to a region
that must have seemed both different and
tragically familiar. They learned new ways of
farming and how to deal with a different government.
Unfortunately, they also encountered
another variety of the racism they had
fled. Their African Canadian descendants
have taken up the struggle for equality and
respect, and are calling upon a historical
legacy to help them in that struggle.


R. Bruce Shepard
University of Saskatchewan




Painter, Nell Irvin. Exodusters: Black Migration to Kansas
after Reconstruction. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1976.
Shepard, R. Bruce. Deemed Unsuitable. Toronto: Umbrella
Press, 1997. Winks, Robin. The Blacks in Canada: A
History. New Haven CT: Yale University Press, 1971.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>