<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.082</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Wilder, Laura Ingalls (1867-1957)</field>
      <field name="author">Romines, Ann</field>
      <field name="text">

 




WILDER, LAURA INGALLS (1867-1957)


Laura Ingalls Wilder, 1918


Laura Ingalls Wilder was born in a log cabin
near Pepin, Wisconsin, on February 7, 1867.
She subsequently lived in Kansas, Minnesota,
Iowa, and South Dakota before settling in her
final home in Mansfield, Missouri, in 1894.
She died there on February 10, 1957.

The Little House series, Laura Ingalls Wilder's
eight-volume set of autobiographical
novels for children (1932–43), is arguably the
most influential twentieth-century narrative
of female childhood and adolescence on the
western frontier. On their publication during
the Great Depression, these books were almost
immediately canonized as children's
"classics," and they have shaped generations of
children's and adults' beliefs about European
American settlers' lives on the nineteenth-century
Great Plains.

Wilder was a sixty-five-year-old Missouri
farm woman with a long working life as housekeeper,
poultry woman, teacher, and journalist
behind her when the first Little House book
was published in 1932. Her (unacknowledged)
collaborator and adviser was her daughter,
nationally known writer Rose Wilder Lane.
Much of the power of the Little House series
comes from the immediacy of its autobiographical
protagonist: it places a spirited girl at
the center of the cultural controversies of the
1870s and 1880s Great Plains. In the first book,
Little House in the Big Woods (1932), Laura
Ingalls is four, experiencing the satisfying
rhythms of settled farm life with her young
parents and sisters. In Little House on the Prairie
(1935), Pa tires of the Wisconsin farm's predictabilities
and persuades his dubious wife to
move to Kansas "Indian country," where they
settle illegally on Indian lands. Laura is intensely
curious about their Native American
neighbors, whom Ma fears and hates and Pa
(sometimes) admires and emulates. She discovers
a passion for the Great Plains country of
waving grasses and no visible boundaries.
When, after laboriously constructing a little
log house, the Ingallses are ordered off their
claim by the U.S. government, they backtrack
to Minnesota and, in On the Banks of Plum Creek (1937), settle on a farm near an established
town. Church and school offer cultural
advantages, and Laura's domestic education intensifies.
But the Ingallses are beset by drought,
grasshoppers, and illness, and by the next book
(By the Shores of Silver Lake, 1939) are glad
to leave for a new western homestead in Dakota
Territory. In this and the three following
books, adolescent Laura learns the boundaries
of women's and men's work in a frontier town,
surviving blizzards in The Long Winter (1940)
and, in Little Town on the Prairie (1941), seeking
adult occupations that engage her energy and
agency. The series ends, in These Happy Golden Years (1943), with the interwoven stories of
Laura's first adult professional success as a
schoolteacher and her courtship and marriage
to a young homesteader, Almanzo Wilder.

The Little House series engages important
issues of European American settler culture in
the Great Plains: the competition of Ma's settled
domesticity and Pa's westering wanderlust;
the broached and botched possibilities of
intercultural contacts between frontier Americans
of different races and ethnicities; the
gendered alternatives of work, consumption,
and courtship offered to female children and
adolescents in Plains towns. Recently, critics,
historians, and biographers have debated
whether Wilder's series confirms or questions
the Turnerian account of the settling of the
American West, have scrutinized constructions
of gender and domestic culture in the
series, and have argued about the extent and
importance of Rose Wilder Lane's collaboration.
Meanwhile, the Little House series has
continued to spawn cultural spin-offs that attest
to the persistent freshness and importance
of this canonical Great Plains narrative.


Ann Romines
George Washington University




Romines, Ann. Constructing the Little House: Gender, Culture, and Laura Ingalls Wilder. Amherst: University of
Massachusetts Press, 1997. Wilder, Laura Ingalls, and Rose
Wilder Lane. A Little House Sampler, edited by William T.
Anderson. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1988.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>