<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.wat.016</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Northwest Irrigation Act</field>
      <field name="author">Regehr, Ted D.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




NORTHWEST IRRIGATION ACT

The Northwest Irrigation Act, amending and
consolidating the Northwest Irrigation Acts of
1894 and 1895, was passed by the Canadian
federal government in 1898. It defined and
provided for the regulation and control of water
rights in the territories that became the
provinces of Saskatchewan and Alberta in
1905. Drought conditions in the 1880s and
1890s, together with the arrival of Mormon
settlers familiar with irrigation techniques
and increased interest in irrigation by the Canadian
Pacific Railway, had made it necessary
for the federal government to regulate the orderly
use of the water resources of the semiarid
Southern Canadian Prairies.

The Northwest Irrigation Act unequivocally
revoked or rescinded common law riparian
rights, declaring that the water in all streams,
lakes, ponds, springs, or other sources belongs
to the Crown. It then defined the conditions
under which federal officials could grant water
rights or concessions to companies or individuals
for a variety of uses. Those applying for
water rights for irrigation purposes had to define
the quantity of water required, the specific
lands to be irrigated, and the irrigation works
to be constructed. Successful applicants were
given indisputable title to the water granted
them under their licenses, provided that they
used it only in accordance with the terms and
conditions of their application. The licensees
also enjoyed rights of expropriation of land
needed for the development of approved
works. But failure to develop the works, or
misuse of the water, could result in the revocation
of the rights granted. Decisions of government
officials regarding revocations were final
and without right of appeal to the courts.

Creation of the new provinces of Alberta
and Saskatchewan in 1905 necessitated passage
of a new federal irrigation act that granted the
new provinces some very limited local powers
but left regulation of water resources in the
new provinces in federal hands. In 1930 the
federal government transferred control of the
natural resources in Alberta and Saskatchewan
to those provinces but retained significant
control over water resources under the
terms of a new Water Resources Act.

Supporters of the Northwest Irrigation Act,
and of later Canadian legislation regulating
the use of water for irrigation purposes, insist
that the clear enunciation of basic principles
and easily understood and enforceable detailed
regulations resulted in an almost complete
absence of the kind of litigation pertaining
to irrigation laws in other, mainly U.S.,
jurisdictions.


Ted D. Regehr
University of Sasketchewan and University of Calgary




Dawson, A. S. Irrigation Development in Western Canada,
Address to the Calgary Board of Trade, April 15, 1921. Calgary:
Calgary Board of Trade, 1921. U.S. Department of
Agriculture. Irrigation Laws of the Northwest Territories of
Canada and of Wyoming. J. S. Dennis. Washington DC:
Government Printing Office, 1901.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>