<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pe.026</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Fish</field>
      <field name="author">Peters, Edward J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




FISH

Aquatic habitats in the Great Plains region
were historically dominated by rivers and
streams with associated wetlands and few natural
lakes. Native fishes are typically riverine
species that are in many cases adapted to
strong current, turbid water, and a wide range
of water temperatures. However, many species
that require clear water and cool temperatures
are found as relict populations in springs and
headwater streams. The native and introduced
fish fauna are an important link in food chains
for many species and are significant economic
resources for many communities.

The native fish fauna of the Great Plains
includes representatives of twenty-eight families
and more than 100 species. Several other
families and many species have been introduced.
The minnow family (Cyprinidae) is the
most diverse with more than forty species native
to the region. Other species-rich families
include suckers (Catostomidae), catfish (Ictaluridae),
perch (Percidae), and sunfish (Centrarchidae).
The fathead minnow (Pimephales
promelas), sand shiner (Notropis stramineus),
and red shiner (Cyprinella lutrensis) are some
of the most widespread species. Other species,
like the Topeka shiner (Notropis topeka), plains
minnow (Hybognathus placitus), and plains
topminnow (Fundulus sciadicus), are nearly
confined to the Great Plains.

Before European American settlement, the
south-central portion of the region, covering
Kansas and part of Colorado, was the most diverse,
with 109 native species from twenty families.
The north-central region (Nebraska, South
Dakota, Wyoming) had ninety-three native species
from twenty-two families while the northern
Plains states' (North Dakota, Montana) native
fishes numbered seventy-six species from
nineteen families. The Canadian (Manitoba,
Saskatchewan, Alberta) and southern (Oklahoma,
Texas, New Mexico) portions of the
Great Plains were the least diverse with fifty-eight
and sixty-two species respectively. Both
regions had seventeen native families, but the
southern region included representatives of two
families (Characidae, Cyprinodontidae) and
eight species found native nowhere else in the
Plains. The northern states and Canadian regions
contribute two families (Salmonidae,
Cottidae) and four species to the native fauna.
The Great Plains fish fauna shows a strong influence
of its connection to the Mississippi drainage.
However, representatives of northern and
southwestern faunas are also in evidence.

Since the onset of European American settlement,
many of the rivers have been dammed
to produce reservoirs ranging in size from
small farm ponds to large impoundments.
Reservoirs and ponds have provided new habitats
where exotic species have flourished after
being introduced. Introduced sport fish, especially
members of the families Salmonidae,
Moronidae, and Centrarchidae, prey upon
and compete for food with many native species.
Aquatic habitats have also been altered or
destroyed by chemical pollution, channelization,
erosion, siltation, and water depletion.
Habitat alteration, pollution, and introduction
of nonnative species have led to the demise
of many local populations. Introductions
of mosquito fish (Gambusia affinis) have competed
with a number of native minnows and
killifish, such as the plains topminnow. Habitat
protection and restoration measures have been
initiated by conservation organizations to prevent
continued losses from the native fish
fauna, but many populations are already in
serious jeopardy or have been extirpated.


Edward J. Peters
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Brown, C. J. D. Fishes of Montana. Bozeman: Montana State
University, 1971. Cross, Frank B., and Joseph T. Collins. Fishes
in Kansas. Lawrence: University of Kansas Natural History
Museum, 1995. Lee, David S., Carter R. Gilbert, Charles H.
Hocutt, Robert E. Jenkins, Don E. McAllister, and Jay R.
Stauffer Jr. Atlas of North American Freshwater Fishes. Raleigh:
North Carolina Biological Survey, Publication No.
1980-12, 1980.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>