<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.wat.030</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Spanish Water Law</field>
      <field name="author">Brescia, Michael M.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SPANISH WATER LAW

Spaniards who explored and settled the Great
Plains from the sixteenth through the early
nineteenth centuries brought with them a set
of legal and cultural values about water that
had been fostered over the centuries in Spain
and later in central Mexico. The arid and
semiarid stretches of northern New Mexico,
southern Colorado, and western Texas, which
constituted the far northern frontier of New
Spain, shaped settlement patterns as colonists
sought water to sustain rural economic activities.
Access to, and control over, this natural
resource influenced the rhythms of daily
life and not infrequently precipitated conflict
between individuals and communities. As a
result, knowledge and application of Spanish
water rights became the purview of farmers,
lawyers, judges, and irrigators.

Spanish water law in America was heir to a
long and dynamic legal tradition that began
in Spain under the Roman Empire and continued
after subsequent invasions by Germanic
and Muslim peoples. In 1265, Alfonso X
ordered the codification of disparate legal
codes and customs and, although elements of
Germanic and Islamic law can be found in the
compilation, the Siete Partidas was the adaptation
of Roman Law to a medieval Spanish reality.
With a few modifications and additions
over the years, the Siete Partidas remained the
primary legal code that governed water rights.
After the Spanish conquest of Mexico and
Peru in the sixteenth century, the general
principles of Spanish jurisprudence were
given a distinctly American context in a legal
code written specifically for Spain's vast empire.
In 1681, the Spanish crown promulgated
the Recopilación de las leyes de los reynos de las
Indias, constituting the foundation of Spanish
water law in America. It vested original ownership
of all land, water, and minerals in the
Spanish Crown, which was empowered to alienate
from its domain these resources to private
individuals, towns, and informal rural
communities.

Spanish jurisprudence recognized two kinds
of property rights that are fundamental to understanding
Spanish water law. Surface water
was propiedad imperfecta, which meant that
it was subject to qualification and measured
against the rights of others. The Spanish civil
law of property did not recognize riparian
rights to running streams or rivers. If a piece
of property fronted on a stream, for example,
the owner could only use the water for domestic
purposes. The Spanish Crown did convey
surface water rights, however, for agricultural
or industrial purposes through a specific grant
(merced de agua). On the far northern frontier
of New Spain a judicial procedure known as
repartimiento de aguas often was used to convey
such rights. But it was more common for
surface water to be granted automatically if
the land classification itself reflected a conveyance
(e.g., if a plot of land was designated
as tierras de pan llevar, or irrigable land, then
the subsequent grant carried water rights).
Groundwater, however, was propiedad perfecta.
Ownership of spring water and rainwater
was nearly absolute, and landowners could
not be easily deprived of these waters once
conveyance was extended, even if use of it
caused damage to neighbors.

Three social entities with juridical personality
competed for water on Spain's far northern
frontier: Spanish towns, Indian pueblos,
and informal rural communities known today
as acequia (ditch) associations. Judges who
presided over water disputes allocated resources
according to seven principles: just
title, prior use (not the same as prior appropriation
in Anglo common law), need, legal
right, intent, noninjury to third party, and equity
and the common good. The dry expanse
of the Great Plains fashioned a legal atmosphere
that eschewed water monopolies, and
judges applied a combination of these principles
to facilitate community harmony and social
tranquility. Even after Mexico's independence
from Spain in 1821, judges continued to
employ these principles as Spanish water law
maintained its full vigor.

Moreover, Spanish water law survives today
in the Great Plains because the Treaty of
Guadalupe Hidalgo, which ended hostilities
between the United States and Mexico in 1848,
obliged the American government to respect
the property of those Mexicans who suddenly
found themselves residing north of the newly
created boundary. Since water was considered
property under Spanish and Mexican law, the
U.S. courts act as surrogates for Hispanic water
law.

See also HISPANIC AMERICANS: Guadalupe Hidalgo, Treaty of; Hispano Homeland.


Michael M. Brescia
State University of New York, Fredonia




Ebright, Malcolm. Land Grants and Lawsuits in Northern
New Mexico. Albuquerque: University of New Mexico
Press, 1994. Meyer, Michael C. Water in the Hispanic
Southwest: A Social and Legal History, 1550–1850. Tucson:
University of Arizona Press, 1996. Tyler, Daniel. The Mythical
Pueblo Rights Doctrine: Water Administration in Hispanic
New Mexico. El Paso: Texas Western Press, 1990.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>