<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.sr.001</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Sports and Recreation</field>
      <field name="author">Stuyt, Jeff Wishart, David J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SPORTS AND RECREATION

In many respects, sports and recreation in
the Great Plains are no different from those
activities in other North American regions.
Every weekend, parents take their boys and
girls to play in local soccer leagues, college
football teams compete for honors on the
gridiron, and golfers stride the fairways. But
in important ways, there are attributes of
sports and recreation that are specific to the
Great Plains or are particularly emphasized in
the Great Plains and that are, therefore, distinguishing
characteristics of the region's personality.
Six-man football, for example, is a Plains
innovation, a response to a sparse population
in rural areas and the inadequate supply of
players for the conventional game. There are
annual events such as the Calgary Stampede,
the Crow Fair, and the Sturgis Motorcycle
Rally that are purely Plains affairs, and there
are the great sportsmen and sportswomen
such as Jim Thorpe, Gordie Howe, and Nancy
Lopez whose achievements have brought distinction
to the region. More mundanely, there
is the small-town ritual of "cruising around"
from the Dairy Queen to the cornfields and
back; the tractor pull, a featured event at
county and state fairs; and the softball game, a
true community event and intergenerational
activity. Any discussion of sports and recreation
in the Great Plains, however, must start
with Native American games, which were
played throughout the region for centuries.



Native American Traditions

Traditionally, Native American games were
inseparable from their religions. Native American
creation stories often involved contests
between two opposing Twin Gods armed with
clubs or bows and arrows. Games were replays
of those creation stories while at the same
time providing forums for achievement, recreation,
and gambling.

Native American games fall into two broad
categories: games of chance and games of dexterity.
The former includes dice games and
hidden ball games; the latter includes archery,
the snow snake, the hoop and pole game, and
various ball and running games. Many of
these games were played throughout Native
North America, but all had their local expressions
in the Great Plains.

Dice games, involving dice made from many
different materials, were played by every Plains
tribe. They were generally played at night after
the day's labor was done, and they sometimes
went on all night, with considerable stakes involved.
More often than not, they were played
by women. Blackfeet women in Montana, for
example, used four elaborately etched bison
rib bones as dice. Sitting opposite each other,
the women threw the dice on the ground,
adding scores according to which side was up,
until a winning score of twelve was attained.
Omaha and Cheyenne women used plum
stones with patterns burned into one side, and
the dice were thrown into a wooden bowl or
basket.

The hand game was one of the most widely
played games of chance. Because it was done
entirely by gesture, it could be played between
members of different tribes who did not speak
each other's language. In this game, an object
made of bone, wood, shell, or hide was moved
rapidly from hand to hand by one of the players.
The opposing player, carefully tracking the
sleight of hand, had to judge which hand held
the object. The performance was accompanied
by singing, which started out low and built to a
crescendo as the swaying player switched the
object back and forth until a hand was chosen.
This was a man's game and often an occasion
of competition between members of different
tribes. There is an account of such a game on a
Kiowa calendar from 1881-82. A Kiowa leader,
Buffalo Bull Coming Out, was challenged by
an Apache chief and medicine man. Both
claimed the supernatural powers necessary to
win. A large crowd waged prized possessions
on the outcome, and the victory went to the
Kiowa chief.

Games with bows and arrows were ubiquitous
in the Great Plains and took many
forms. For example, Pawnee boys or men
would try to shoot arrows across another arrow
that had been placed on the ground. The
winner took all the arrows. In one Mandan
version, young men, having paid an entry fee
of a bison robe or other valued item, would
shoot arrows in the air, one after the other.
The winner who kept the most arrows in the
air at one time took the prizes home.

The snow snake was another game of dexterity
that was played wherever frozen conditions
prevailed. Played by men and women,
young and old, it involved sliding polished
rocks, shaped bones, or spears along a track in
the ice or snow. The player who slid the implement
the farthest or the most accurately to a
designated point was the winner.

The hoop and pole game, in a great variety
of versions, was played throughout the region.
A hoop made of wood, often covered with
rawhide and netted in various designs, was
rolled down a flattened track. The contestants
(two men) tried to throw rods through the
hoop or across the hoop as it started to fall.
Again, there was gambling on the outcome of
the game, but this did not obscure its religious
implications. The Skidi Pawnee, for example,
played the game to attract the bison, the rods
representing bison bulls and the hoop a bison
cow.

Lacrosse was played on the Northern Great
Plains and in Indian Territory in the second
half of the nineteenth century, although it
was more common in eastern North America.
Shinny, played with a curved wooden bat and
a wooden or buckskin ball, was more prevalent
on the Plains. Shinny was particularly a
woman's game, although it was also played by
men and sometimes by men against women.
The objective was to knock the ball through
the opponent's often-distant goal. Footraces
were also common, and, for a man, being a
celebrated runner, especially over long distances,
was valued only behind being a successful
warrior and hunter.

Many of these games died out as European
American games and sports were adopted. Of
the introduced sports, none was more suited
to Native American skills and tradition than
rodeo, which continues the horsemanship
skills of the Plains Indians. Continuity is also
apparent in other developments. The contemporary
powwow combines ceremony, gift giving,
and the athleticism and grace of dance
competition. Gaming, which so rapidly developed
on reservations in the 1990s, clearly continues
the deeply rooted Native American tradition
of gambling. Long-distance running
remains a Native American specialty, epitomized
by Billy Mills, a Lakota from Pine Ridge
Reservation who shot from the pack during
the final 200 meters of the 10,000-meter final
race at the 1964 Tokyo Olympics, breaking the
Olympic record in the process. And in any list
of the twentieth century's top athletes, Jim
Thorpe of the Sauk and Fox Tribe of Oklahoma
must surely rank near the top.



Sports and Recreation on the Great Plains Frontier

On the overland trails in the 1840s and 1850s
and on the farms and ranches that were the
foundation of nineteenth-century Plains society,
there was little time for sports and recreation.
On the trails, in the evening, when the
horses were tethered and the dinner dishes
cleared away, the sounds of a fiddle and laughing
dancers might attest to a brief period of
recreation before the serious business of a
good night's sleep intervened. On the farm,
the end of the harvest became an occasion for
celebration and perhaps a community picnic,
and work tasks like quilting and raising barns
were facilitated by bringing neighbors together
in a social event.

The Great Plains frontier was not only
rural, however. In fact, towns were often created
first: there had to be central places to
provide land offices, goods and services, and
market outlets for prospective farmers. These
towns were points of connection, via railroad,
telegraph, and newspaper, to the larger and
more sophisticated cities to the east. Fads and
fashions diffused westward, including new varieties
of recreation and sports.

At the booming Kansas cattle towns of
Wichita, Caldwell, and Dodge City in the 1880s
there were two distinct seasons of recreational
activities and two distinct social groups to pursue
them. During late spring and summer, the
cattle drives reached the towns, and the streets
and saloons became a constant carnival. During
the fall and winter season, the towns were
left to their sedate, permanent populations and
their respectable church socials and dances.
These two groups represent, perhaps in exaggerated
form, the larger American society of
the time: the growing middle class, with its
Victorian mores, emphasizing hard work and
self-control, values that were antithetical to exciting
sports and idle recreation; and the underclass
(along with debauched aristocrats),
which placed a much higher premium on play.

When the cattlemen reached the railhead
towns, the respectable population withdrew.
The towns filled up with actors, musicians,
and other showmen. Bustling street scenes featured
cockfights, bear baiting, pugilists, organ
grinders with their monkeys, and tightrope
walkers. The saloons and dance halls
throbbed. The only time the two social strata
mixed were when the circus (a European import)
came to town or at an occasional polo
game, which seemingly was genteel enough for
the upper crust yet a natural for the cowboys.

When the cowboys left, resident social life
took over. Culture was emphasized, with traveling
acting troupes staging Shakespeare as
well as popular melodramas. An opera house
was essential. Light opera, particularly Gilbert
and Sullivan, dominated the stage. Drama and
literary societies flourished: the dawn of the
"machine age" had ushered in an era of leisure
for the middle classes, and in the Victorian
era, leisure was to be used in edifying ways.

Individual, though again genteel, sports became
popular in the 1880s. Croquet, suitable
for women constrained by corsets, was the rage
in the Kansas cattle towns in the 1880s. It provided
a suitable context for courting. The contemporaneous
American bicycle craze, however,
did not take hold in Plains towns where
the streets were often mud and everyone rode
horses or, another innovation, drove a horse
and buggy. Roller-skating was also very popular
and the only one of the individualized
sports to be commercialized. In 1884, for example,
the citizens of Caldwell converted the
lower floor of the Grand Opera House into a
65-by-15-foot rink. Not to be outdone, the following
year Dodge City opened a skating rink
and opera house with a 100-by-300-foot floor
and a gallery for spectators, a relatively new
development in sports and recreation.

Organized spectator sports were in their infancy
in the 1880s throughout North America.
Horse racing was an attraction for the citizens
of the cattle towns, but baseball was the main
spectator sport. Settlers coming into Kansas
brought the sport with them. By 1867 Leavenworth
was home to the Frontier Baseball
Club, and by the 1880s there were competitive
teams in Dodge City, Wichita, and Caldwell.
The rules favored the batter (more effective
overhand pitching was not permitted until
1884), which explains how Wichita could defeat
Emporia by a score of 58 to 27.

Plains towns were not only importers of
eastern fads; they also produced their own entertainers.
On July 4, 1882, William F. Cody first
featured his combined rodeo-circus-drama at
North Platte, Nebraska. By 1887 Buffalo Bill's
Wild West show was touring Europe. At the
same time, the Dodge City Cowboy Band, regaled
in exaggerated Western outfits, was playing
to enthusiastic reviews throughout the
Midwest. Significantly, these shows were not
as popular in their home states, where they
seemed phony, as they were in distant places,
where they confirmed stereotypes.

The late nineteenth century also saw the beginning
of organized sports in the Prairie
Province region of Canada. This was allowed
by the same developments that were taking
place in the United States, not least of which
were improved transportation systems that enabled
teams and spectators to move between
venues. But the situation in the Prairie Provinces
was di&#129;ãerent from that in the American
Great Plains in significant ways. A stronger
British heritage was expressed in the greater
popularity of sports such as cricket, rugby, soccer,
and especially curling. The long and frigid
winters reinforced the popularity of curling
and stimulated the growth of ice hockey as well
as indoor sports such as basketball. However,
the isolation of the Prairie Provinces from the
coasts, even after the completion of the Canadian
Pacific Railway in 1885, resulted in north.
south connections across the international
boundary, which eventually introduced a
strong American influence into the regional
sporting scene, displacing traditional British
sports.

The initial British influence on Prairie
Provinces sports and society is shown, for example,
in the founding of the Qu'Appelle,
Saskatchewan, hunt club in 1889. The club
purchased its hounds from the Toronto Hunt
Club. The earliest introduced competitive
team sports in the region were cricket and soccer.
There was a Northwest Cricket Club in
Manitoba, for example, in 1864. Soccer was
often played by North-West Mounted Police
teams against teams from local communities.
Curling, introduced from Scotland (and still
governed by the parent body based in Scotland
as late as 1900), was both a major competitive
sport and the main winter pastime of
urban and rural dwellers throughout the region.
Manitoba was generally the national
curling champion in the 1920s and 1930s.

By 1905 ice hockey was the main competitive
sport in the Prairie Provinces; every town, no
matter how small, had a rink and a team. From
its origins in Montreal in the 1880s, the game
expanded to Manitoba by 1890. In its early
years, ice hockey was a middle-class sport and
strictly amateur. The first city leagues in Winnipeg,
Regina, and Edmonton were sponsored
by colleges, banks, newspapers, and churches.
The institutionalization of ice hockey in the
schools ensured a steady supply of players, and
gradually Prairie Provinces teams were able to
compete with the established eastern teams. In
1920, at the Antwerp Olympics, the Winnipeg
Falcons proved that the Canadians were the
best in the world by winning all their games
and the gold medal. The tradition has continued:
the Edmonton Oilers of the 1980s were
one of the finest teams of all time.

The Prairie Provinces, however, were also
receptive to the developing American national
sports, basketball, baseball, and football. This
was largely the result of the northward migration
of Americans across the forty-ninth parallel
in the late nineteenth and early twentieth
centuries. The Mormon community in Raymond,
in southern Alberta, was particularly
influential in the establishment of basketball.
In this area, basketball was also aided and
abetted by the warm chinook winds, which
frequently melt the ice, thus impeding outdoor
curling and ice hockey. Basketball caught
on widely: from 1915 to 1940 the Edmonton
Grads were the best women's team in the
world.

Baseball and American football (with Canadian
variations) developed at the expense of
cricket and rugby, demonstrating the growth
of the American influence on Canadian society
in general. Baseball became the main
summer sport and recreational activity in the
Prairie Provinces soon after 1900. No sports
day or Dominion Day in a small town was
complete without an intercommunity game.
At the professional level (money was involved
in Canadian baseball from the start), teams
from Edmonton and Winnipeg were playing
American rivals from Grand Forks, Fargo, and
Jamestown by 1905. Similarly, Canadian football
teams, often associated with universities,
were competing against teams from North
Dakota by 1920. Clearly, in the arena of competitive
sports in the early twentieth century,
the Northern Great Plains and the Prairie
Provinces were part of the same region.



Twentieth-Century Scenes

In the twentieth century, Plains sports, like
sports elsewhere in North America, became institutionalized
and commercialized to an extent
that could not have been imagined when organized
sports were in their infancy in 1900. Baseball
led the way, complete with its hierarchy of
leagues, its famous stadiums, and its World Series.
Top players, both heroes and villains, were
as famous as Hollywood stars. Far from this
glamour, in small towns throughout the Plains
young men played in the summer minor
leagues, dreaming of emulating their heroes or
at least of making enough money to attend
college. For two generations before 1950, baseball
held the promise, an illusion for most, of a
life beyond the local.

After 1950 television changed the nature of
sports (for example, adding at least thirty
minutes of commercials to each professional
football game) and moved the spectator into
the living room. This, in turn, changed recreational
patterns, resulting in some people
spending a substantial amount of time in the
armchair in front of television sports. Countering
this, and partly in reaction to it, was the
rise of mass participation in sports and leisure
activities as the foundation for a healthy lifestyle.
Indeed, in the second half of the twentieth
century, as the following examples demonstrate,
some people's identities became
linked as much to what they did in their leisure
time as to what they did for a job.

Football, particularly college and high
school football, is the preeminent competitive
sport and a powerful shaper of community
identity over much of the Great Plains. The
professional game is also important but less
pervasive on the American Plains, because the
region's teams are few (the Denver Broncos
and the Kansas City Chiefs) and in peripheral
locations. In the Prairie Provinces, the Canadian
version of football (with its larger field,
twelve-man teams, and three downs to advance
the ball ten yards) is well represented
in successful professional teams in Calgary,
Edmonton, and Winnipeg. But there, ice
hockey has pride of place in both allegiance
and participation.

College football on the American Great
Plains is more than a sport. For better or
worse, the prestige and self-respect of states
are intimately connected to the fortunes of
their university football teams. There has, indeed,
been great success: the University of
Oklahoma was national champion in 1950,
1955, 1956, 1974, 1975, and 2000, the University
of Nebraska–Lincoln won the honor in 1970,
1971, 1994, 1995, and 1997 (shared), and the
University of Colorado was the nation's best
college team in 1991 (shared). Eleven Heisman
Trophy winners have rushed and passed their
ways out of Plains universities. Stadiums are
consistently filled on game days. Memorial
Stadium in Lincoln, Nebraska, temporarily
becomes the state's third largest population
concentration when the Cornhuskers are
playing at home. Iconography abounds as
supporters don their team's colors, and team
flags proclaim allegiance up and down the
block. Stores, restaurants, and bars do more
business than the rest of the week combined.
Universities do well too: the football coach is
often the highest paid employee, and successful
teams like Nebraska have athletic department
budgets (garnered from merchandise
sales, concessions, television contracts, and
game receipts) that small countries might well
envy.

The heart of Plains football, however, beats
fastest in the innumerable small towns that
punctuate the region's sparsely populated
spaces. Local high school teams are emblems
of community pride. Their successes are proclaimed
on the sign that greets the visitor to
the town (Class C State Champions, 1954),
and their failures are lamented in taverns and
coffee shops. Within the Great Plains, there is
no more important high school football tradition
than in Texas and Oklahoma.

Sports geographer John Rooney has proven,
quantitatively, that the Southern Great Plains
is one of the two most important areas of high
school football in the United States, producing
more players for the college game than any
others. (The other region is the northern Appalachians
of Pennsylvania, Ohio, and West
Virginia, significantly, an early source for
many migrants to the Texas and Oklahoma oil
fields.) The counties centered on the Texas oil
towns of Midland and Odessa, the Texas Panhandle,
and a broad zone reaching from about
Abilene, Texas, into western Oklahoma turn
out approximately four times as many college
football players per capita than the national
average. Rugged individualism, the lack of alternative
outlets for achievement, deep-rooted
traditions, and strong community support are
some of the reasons for this preeminence. In
some small towns in Texas, more than 50 percent
of the males try out for the football team,
and stadium capacities often exceed the communities'
populations. There is a dark side to
this, however. Enthusiasm crosses over into
fanaticism, performance in the classroom becomes
less important than performance on the
field, and people's lives are collapsed into football,
which is, after all, only a game.

Rodeo is also more prominent in the Great
Plains than in other Canadian and American
regions. The sport emerged from the Plains
open range cattle era and remains closely connected
to ranching. The first "cowboy tournaments"
("rodeo," from the Spanish rodear,
which means "to encircle," was not used until
the early twentieth century) took place on the
range in the 1870s, as practical skills of roping
and riding were displayed in competitions between
different outfits. The contests evolved,
attracted spectators, and moved from the
range to towns. Early competitions were often
associated with Wild West shows, which featured
bucking, roping, and steer-wrestling
competitions. Cheyenne Frontier Days, first
held in 1897 (and held annually since that
time), initially combined these rodeo contests
with Wild West activities such as sham battles
and stagecoach holdups.

As rodeo evolved, its procedures were formalized,
and professional governing bodies
were organized. The Rodeo Association of
America was formed in 1928, later to mature
into the Professional Rodeo Cowboys Association.
The Canadian Rodeo Association was organized
in 1944. In 1929 the Rodeo Association
of America began naming an all-around champion
based on performances in bareback riding,
bull riding, calf roping, saddle bronc riding, and
steer wrestling. These events remain standard in
any rodeo, regardless of location. Barrel racing is
included in some rodeos but often as a side
event: in the predominantly male world of competitive
rodeo, this is the only event that women
and girls are allowed to enter. Women as rodeo
queens, do, however, play important roles in
rodeos, especially in promoting the event. There
are separate women's rodeos, sponsored by the
Women's Professional Rodeo Association of
Blanchard, Oklahoma, and the greatest of all
women rodeo stars, Barbara Tad Lucas, is from
the Plains. There is also a junior circuit, with
another Plains organization, the Little Britches
Rodeo Association of Colorado Springs, a major
sponsor. The primacy of the Great Plains
region in this sport is further confirmed by the
location of the headquarters of the Professional
Rodeo Cowboys Association in Colorado
Springs and the Canadian Rodeo Association
in Calgary.

The prestigious rodeos such as Cheyenne
Frontier Days and the Calgary Stampede are
major economic and cultural events. In the
1980s, by one estimate, more than $3 million
flowed into Cheyenne businesses during rodeo
days. So ingrained is cowboy culture in
the thoroughly modern city of Calgary that
when a new indoor sports arena was constructed
for the 1988 Winter Olympics it was
named the Saddledome, and the roof was
shaped accordingly. But, like high school football,
the foundations of rodeo are local. In
hundreds of communities from spring to fall,
at fairs and carnivals, at colleges and impromptu
affairs, the cowboy heritage of the
Great Plains is celebrated in human-animal
competitions, reinforcing the regional sense
of rugged individualism.

Hunting, of course, also harks back to the
region's recent frontier past, to a time when
relations with nature were adversarial. Hunting
for food may not be the necessity that it
once was, but there is no denying that hunting
retains its elemental role in Plains life. In every
one of the Plains states, adults hunt, fish, and
participate in other wildlife-associated recreation
to a degree well above the national average.
In North Dakota, for example, in 1985
45 percent of the adult population hunted,
fished, or engaged in such "nonconsumptive"
activities as wildlife observation and activity.
These sporting and recreational activities
earned $108 million for North Dakota that
year from trip-related expenses, equipment,
and permits. Some of this income is applied to
wildlife preservation.

However, only 18 percent of North Dakotans
hunt exclusively. In fact, there is concern
in Plains states that hunting is a dying tradition.
Although more women are hunting, the
total number of hunters has been falling in
recent years. Young people are not joining the
ranks of hunters as much as in the past, despite
efforts by states, through hunter education
courses, to encourage them to do so. Opposition
groups such as the Fund for Animals may
be partly responsible for the decline of hunting.
In the late 1990s the Fund for Animals
offered a mountain bike valued at $1,000 to the
first Wyoming youngster to turn in his or her
permit for a special elk hunt and give up hunting
for a season. No one took up the offer, but
it does underscore the serious nature of activism
against hunting. Other societal trends
such as urbanization and multiple jobs, which
reduce leisure time, may also be causes of the
decline of participation in hunting.

Hunting and fishing are also controversial
in other ways in the Great Plains. The landmark
case Montana v. United States, which
was decided by the Supreme Court in 1981,
concerned the right of the Crow tribe to regulate
hunting and fishing on lands within its
reservation owned by non-Indians. The Court
agreed that the Crows have the right to regulate
non-Indian hunting on Indian lands on
the reservation but denied that they have the
right to regulate non-Indian hunting on non-Indian
lands unless hunting threatened the
tribe's political or economic security. Reservations
up and down the Plains are patchworks
of Indian and non-Indian lands, so hunting
and fishing on reservations becomes a complicated
matter, both practically and legally, involving
contentious issues of sovereignty between
tribes and states.

There is ample opportunity for Great Plains
residents and visitors to enjoy the physical environment
and cultural heritage of the region
in lands set aside expressly for that purpose.
Innumerable state parks, many of them the
product of the Civilian Conservation Corps in
the 1930s, are scattered throughout the Great
Plains. North of the international boundary
provincial parks provide similar hunting, fishing,
and scenic amenities.

National parks are relatively few (Theodore
Roosevelt National Park in North Dakota,
Badlands and Wind Cave National Parks in
South Dakota, Carlsbad Caverns National
Park in New Mexico, Riding Mountain National
Park in Manitoba, and Elk Island National
Park in Alberta), but there are many
national monuments, national historic sites,
and national recreation areas throughout the
region.

As might be expected, national forests are
also few. Indeed, the presence of any–for example,
the McKelvie National Forest in the
Nebraska Sandhills, which, after frequent
fires, looks more like a savanna than a forest–may
well seem like an ecological anomaly. The
Great Plains, however, stand out on the map
of national grasslands: seventeen of the twenty
largest sites in the United States are in the region,
including the largest, the Little Missouri
National Grassland of North Dakota. That
state also has the nation's major concentration
of national wildlife areas, places put aside for
the protection of endangered species or for
the conservation of animals for hunting. Fully
108 of the total 844 national wildlife areas in
the United States are in the prairie pothole
lands of North Dakota.

Finally, it should be noted that from Denver
and Calgary as well as from smaller urban
concentrations in the lee of the Rocky Mountains,
ski slopes and other sporting and recreational
riches of the High Country are right
at hand. Plains residents may be proud of
their wide horizons and flowing grasslands,
but that's no reason to eschew convenient
mountains.



Future Scenarios

Given the accelerating pace of change in Great
Plains sports and recreation over the last century,
from the croquet craze in the Kansas cattle
towns to the proliferation of spectator
sports options in the age of television, it is
difficult to anticipate future scenarios. New
legislation can radically alter the sporting
scene in a relatively brief period of time. Title
IX of the Education Amendments Act of 1972,
for example, ushered in a new era of competitive
women's sports at American universities.
There is now no fiercer rivalry in Plains sports
than the Texas Tech.University of Texas women's
basketball game. Changes in society can
mean the demise of traditional sports. With
continuing rural depopulation and associated
school consolidation, six-man football will
probably fade from the scene. Changes in
technology can produce unforeseen opportunities
for recreation. The abandonment of
railroad tracks and their conversion into biking,
hiking, and bridle trails (Rails to Trails)
have greatly enhanced recreation in the Great
Plains in recent years, allowing access into the
countryside instead of around the perimeters
of gridded farmland. Through satellite dishes,
cable, and the Internet, Great Plains residents,
no matter how isolated, now have easy access
to international sports such as soccer or rugby
that may well compete with national sports
like football and rodeo for allegiance in the
future. Still, the hold of those homegrown
sports is tenacious. They are rooted in the region's
past, and they continue to define its
identity.



See also CITIES AND TOWNS: Cattle Towns /
GENDER: Rodeo Queens / IMAGES AND ICONS: Cowboy Culture; Friday Night Football; Wild West Shows / LAW: Montana v. United States /
MUSIC: Frontier Opera Houses.


 

Jeff Stuyt
Lubbock, Texas
David J. Wishart
University of Nebraska-Lincoln



Bissinger, H. G. Friday Night Lights: A Town, a Team, and a
Dream. New York: HarperCollins, 1990. Culin, Stewart.
Games of the North American Indians. Bureau of American
Ethnology, 1902-3. Washington DC: Government Printing
Office, 1907. Fredriksson, Kristine. American Rodeo: From
Buffalo Bill to Big Business. College Station: Texas A&amp;M
University Press, 1985. Haywood, C. Robert. Victorian
West: Class and Culture in Kansas Cattle Towns. Lawrence:
University Press of Kansas, 1991. Howell, Maxwell L., and
Reet A. Howell. History of Sport in Canada. Champaign IL:
Stipes Publishing Company, 1985. Lawrence, Elizabeth Atwood.
Rodeo: An Anthropologist Looks at the Wild and
Tame. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1982. Metcalfe,
Alan. Canada Learns to Play: The Emergence of Organized
Sport, 1807-1914. Toronto: McClelland and Stewart
Ltd., 1989. National Survey of Fishing, Hunting, and Wildlife-Associated
Recreation: North Dakota. Washington DC:
Department of the Interior, 1989. Rader, Benjamin G.
American Sports: From the Age of Folk Games to the Age of
Televised Sports. Englewood Cliffs NJ: Prentice-Hall, 1996.
Rooney, John F., Jr. A Geography of American Sport: From
Cabin Creek to Anaheim. Reading MA: Addison-Wesley
Publishing Company, 1974. Zinser, Charles I. Outdoor Recreation:
United States National Parks, Forests and Public
Lands. New York: John Wiley and Sons, 1995.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>