<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.na.063</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Metis</field>
      <field name="author">Ens, Gerhard J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




METIS


Métis traders, 1872-74


The term "Metis," from the French meaning
"mixed," is used by scholars to designate individuals
and groups who identify their antecedents
with historical fur trade communities,
and it refers to people who possess a distinctive
sociocultural heritage and sense of selfidentification.
These descendants of Native
American women and European men forged a
new identity that was distinct from Indigenous
bands and from the European American
world of the trading posts. The Metis of the
Great Plains could be found almost anywhere
the fur trade predominated, and by the early
nineteenth century distinct communities were
emerging in the valleys of the North Saskatchewan,
Assiniboine, and Red Rivers in British
North America and the Missouri River and its
tributaries in U.S. territory.

 These communities varied considerably, depending
on the locality in which they arose, the
Native American bands they were allied to, the
ethnicity and nationality of the fur trade fathers,
and the particular roles they played
within the fur trade economy. What they had
in common was that they were bicultural communities
that functioned as intermediaries
or brokers between European American fur
traders on the one hand and trapping bands
on the other. It was in these interstitial spaces
that unique Metis identities were forged. Being
Metis had many advantages in these fur
trade worlds. It was an ethnic positioning that
allowed individuals to cross boundaries separating
Native American and European American
societies. It allowed for flexibility in selfdefinition,
whereby an individual could accentuate
those personality and kinship aspects to
allow entry into both worlds. Some of these
communities used "Metis" to identify themselves,
though other terms were used, including
Michif, Bois Brules, Chicot, "Half-Breed,"
and "Mixed-Blood," among others.

Although these Metis bands were found
across the Northern Plains from the Missouri
to the Athabasca River, Metis political identity
in the early nineteenth century was focused on
the Red River Settlement. Their assertion of
political rights arose there first in relation to
the fur trade wars between the North West
Company and the Hudson's Bay Company
following the establishment of the Red River
Settlement in 1811. The Plains Metis, closely
tied to the various bourgeois of the North
West Company by consanguinity and employment,
were encouraged to oppose the Hudson's
Bay Company's efforts to impose any authority
over them. This conflict, which ended
in violence and the deaths of twenty-one colonists
at the Seven Oaks Massacre in 1816, came
to be seen by the Metis as the initiation of a
"new nation."

Acting as buffalo-hunting provisioners and
trappers in the fur trade of the Great Plains, the
Metis considered themselves independent of
both fur trade and tribal control. By the 1840s
the buffalo-robe trade, complementing the
summer provisioning hunt, resulted in the establishment
of sizable winter villages wherever
buffalo could be found. This move into the
territory of the Sioux, Crees, and Blackfoot
caused violent confrontations, the most famous
of which was the Battle of Grand Coteau,
on June 16-19, 1851. Here Metis buffalo hunters
from the Red River came under sustained attack
from Sioux near the Missouri River. Attacked
by a much larger force, the Metis circled
their two-wheeled Red River carts to corral
their horses and oxen and to shelter their
women and children. The men established a
perimeter the distance of a gunshot by scraping
gun pits in the prairie sod, and from these
rifle pits they inflicted enough casualties that
the Sioux eventually broke off the attack.

In order to alleviate such hostilities, attempts
were made to broker peace treaties between
the Metis and the various tribal groups.
In 1858 the Metis, Sioux, and Ojibwas met in a
Grand Council north of the Sheyenne River,
to the west of Devils Lake (present-day North
Dakota), to set tribal boundaries and establish
peace among the three groups. The Me;tis,
though closely associated with the Ojibwas of
the region, were recognized as a separate political
and military force and were given the
right to hunt in Sioux territory. Still, conflicts
would continue to erupt between the Metis
and various tribal groups throughout the
1860s and 1870s.

In the treaties negotiated between the
United States and Native American groups
west of the Great Lakes, various bands insisted
that treaties provide some compensation for
their "mixed-blood" brothers not living as Indians
or as part of the band. When the Red
River Metis heard that the American government
was planning to negotiate a treaty with
the Pembina and Red Lake Chippewas (Ojibwas),
many decided to relocate to the American
side of the boundary to take advantage of
the benefits of this treaty. During the negotiations
the Metis claimed that it was their country
and that they had long defended and maintained
it against the encroachments of enemies.
The treaty that was signed between the United
States and the Pembina Chippewas on September
20, 1851, however, did not include the Metis
as signatories because the government believed
it should not treat with people who it regarded
"as our quasi citizens." The government negotiator
did stipulate that he would not object to any
just or reasonable treaty stipulation the Indians
might choose to make for the Metis' benefit.

With the transfer of Rupert's Land to Canada
in 1869–70, the Red River Metis, led by Louis
Riel, initiated a political movement to guarantee
their rights in the new political order. The Manitoba
Act of 1870, which brought the Red River
Settlement into the Canadian Confederation,
granted the Metis both land rights and some
semblance of constitutional recognition. The
rush of settlers into Manitoba after 1870, and the
continuing profitability of the buffalo-robe
trade, however, induced many Metis to sell their
landholdings and move farther west. In 1884
Riel, now claiming to be a religious prophet, led
another movement, the North-West Rebellion,
aimed at recapturing the political power the
Metis had lost in the Red River Settlement. Centered
in the communities of the South Saskatchewan
River, this movement eventually resulted
in armed rebellion against the Canadian state in
1885. The uprising was crushed, and Riel was
hanged for treason on November 16, 1885.

Following the North-West Rebellion of 1885
and the demise of the fur trade in the Plains,
the Metis lost much of their political influence
and cohesiveness. They dispersed northward
and westward, with many also fleeing to Montana
and North Dakota to escape expected reprisals.
There they joined preexisting Metis
communities that had been established during
the heyday of the fur trade. Although Metis
communities survived into the twentieth century
in both the United States and Canada,
poverty, demoralization, and prejudice against
them led many individuals to suppress their
biracial heritage and identity. Since the 1970s,
however, social, cultural, and political developments
that have legitimized ethnicity
have produced a renaissance of Metis identity
and political activity throughout the Northern
Plains and Prairie Provinces. In 1982 the Metis
were recognized as one of Canada's Aboriginal
Peoples under section 35(2) of the Constitution
Act.

See also LAW: Pierre-Guillaume Sayer Trial / PROTEST AND DISSENT: Riel, Louis / WAR: North-West Rebellion; Red River Resistance; Seven Oaks Massacre.


Gerhard J. Ens
University of Alberta



Ens, Gerhard. J. Homeland to Hinterland: The Changing
Worlds of the Red River Metis in the Nineteenth Century.
Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 1996. Foster, John E.
"Wintering, the Outsider Male and Ethnogenesis of the
Western Plains Metis." Prairie Forum 19 (1994): 1–13. Peterson,
Jacqueline, and Jennifer S. H. Brown, eds. The New
Peoples: Being and Becoming Metis in North America. Winnipeg:
University of Manitoba Press, 1985.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>