<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.med.035</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Omaha World-Herald</field>
      <field name="author">Zuegner, Carol</field>
      <field name="text">

 




OMAHA WORLD-HERALD

In 1885 a young, wealthy lawyer named Gilbert
M. Hitchcock and four business partners decided
that the booming city of Omaha, Nebraska,
needed an independent newspaper.
Hitchcock founded the Omaha Daily World on
August 24, 1885, promising a newsy newspaper
for business people. The paper struggled financially
in the early years, but Hitchcock,
who provided most of the capital and owned
almost all the paper's stock, paid $30,000 for
the competing morning Herald, and on July 15,
1889, the combined Omaha World-Herald hit
the streets.

Hitchcock's independent stance didn't last,
and his interest in Democratic politics helped
turn the paper Democratic by 1888. The turn
came just in time to boost the political career
of young politician William Jennings Bryan.
In 1894 Hitchcock and Bryan worked out an
arrangement that put Bryan on the World-Herald masthead as editor in chief. Bryan
wanted a platform for his beliefs, and Hitchcock
thought Bryan's editorials would help
boost the paper's circulation. Bryan, who received
a salary and free rail passes as editor,
was mostly absent. Political reporter and editor
Richard Metcalfe rewrote Bryan's notes
into editorials. The arrangement failed to
build circulation, and Bryan left the paper two
years later when he first won the Democratic
nomination for president.

Hitchcock, who continued as head of the
newspaper during his own political career of
three terms in the House of Representatives
and two terms as a senator, died in 1934. His
son-in-law Henry Doorly became president of
the World Publishing Company, the publisher
of the World-Herald. More familiar with the
business side of running a newspaper, Doorly
worked to standardize ad policies and practices.
He became disenchanted with the New
Deal and Democrats, switching the paper's
political allegiance to the Republican Party.

In 1937 the World-Herald became the only
paper in the city after the demise of the Hearstowned
Omaha Bee-News. After Doorly's retirement
in 1955, Walter E. Christenson took
over. Harold W. Andersen succeeded Christenson,
followed by John A. Gottschalk in 1989.

The World-Herald, owned by Hitchcock
and family members since 1885, attracted the
interest of Samuel Newhouse of the Newhouse
newspaper chain in 1962. This interest
prompted Omaha construction executive Peter
Kiewit to make a successful bid for the
paper to keep the ownership local. After Kiewit's
death in 1979, ownership was divided,
with about 80 percent going to nonunion
employee-stockholders and the remaining 20
percent to the Peter Kiewit Foundation.

A regional newspaper with morning and evening
editions, the World-Herald is distributed
across Nebraska and into surrounding states.
The paper now takes a moderate conservative
stance. In 2001 production switched to a new
100-million-dollar press and plant in downtown
Omaha.

The World-Herald has won three Pulitzer
Prizes. The first went to longtime editor Harvey
Newbranch for a 1919 editorial written after
a mob lynched a black prisoner. Newbranch's
editorial called for sanity. In 1943 the
paper won the Public Service Pulitzer for collecting
about six million tons in a scrap metal
drive. Photographer Earle Bunker won the
third Pulitzer in 1944 for a photo of a soldier
returning to his family.

See also AFRICAN AMERICANS: Omaha Race Riot / CITIES AND TOWNS: Omaha, Nebraska.


Carol Zuegner
Creighton University




Limprecht, Hollis J. A Century of Service, 1885–1985.
Omaha: Omaha World-Herald Company, 1985. Roesgen,
Bill. "Staying the Course." American Journalism Review 21
(1999): 40–46.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>