<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ag.029</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Exotic Animals</field>
      <field name="author">Mungall, Elizabeth Cary</field>
      <field name="text">

 




EXOTIC ANIMALS

Exotic animals, animals living outside their
native areas, are increasing in number in
the Great Plains. These additions to hunting,
ranching, and farming operations, plus rare
species in private preservation efforts, are
mainly hoofed animals of wildlife species with
antlers or horns. A few novel domestics, like
llamas, join the mix. In the early 1990s, ostriches,
emus, and rheas were also promoted,
but markets for these large, flightless birds are
more limited than for hoofed exotics.

Exotics are raised variously for meat, feathers,
hides, eggs, and, in the case of the emu, for
oil that is used in cosmetics. Within the Great
Plains, exotics activity varies with environment
and politics. Texas, with huge, private
ranches and varied environments, stresses all
types and has the most animals (15,735, representing
fifty-six varieties, in Great Plains
counties). Species on the Texas Plains include
aoudad (Ammotragus lervia) from North Africa,
axis deer (Axis axis) from India and Sri
Lanka, blackbuck antelope (Antilope cervicapra)
from India, fallow deer (Dama dama)
from Europe and Asia Minor, red deer (Cervus
elaphus) from Europe, and various forms
of ibex and wild goat (Capra spp.) from
Asia and Africa. In New Mexico, free-ranging
aoudad predominate. There, the state dominates
exotics activity, and public hunting is the
objective. Northward, the main species are
winter-hardy deer, such as fallow and red deer.
These are mainly found in the drier western
zones of the Northern Plains and in Canada
where agricultural alternatives are fewer. Canadian
exotics farming is an addition to more
prevalent experiments with farming, herding,
or culling native wildlife.

Increasing numbers of wildlife ranches, deer
farms, and escaped exotics have prompted
restrictions to prevent disease and interbreeding
with native fauna. Wildlife departments
often disapprove of exotics because of these
negative possibilities or the added competition
for space or forage. Thus, it is agricultural
rather than wildlife interests that are promoting
growth of exotic activity in the Great
Plains.


Elizabeth Cary Mungall
Texas Woman's University




Mungall, Elizabeth Cary, and William J. Sheffield. Exotics
on the Range: The Texas Example. College Station: Texas
A&amp;M University Press, 1994. Traweek, Max S. Statewide
Census of Exotic Big Game Animals. Austin: Texas Parks
and Wildlife Department, 1995.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>