<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.art.009</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Bywaters, Jerry (1906-1989)</field>
      <field name="author">Carraro, Francine</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BYWATERS, JERRY (1906-1989)

As an artist, art critic, museum director, and
art educator, Williamson Gerald Bywaters,
known as Jerry Bywaters, reshaped art in
Texas. The son of Porter Asburn and Hattie
Williamson Bywaters, he was born in Paris,
Texas, on May 21, 1906. After graduating from
Southern Methodist University (SMU) in 1926,
he traveled in Europe, Mexico, and New England
and studied at the New York Art Students
League. Upon his return to Dallas, Bywaters
became a spokesman for a group of
young artists, including Alexandre Hogue,
Otis M. Dozier, and Everett Spruce, who
found inspiration in the Texas landscape.

Bywaters produced a significant body of
landscape, still life, and portrait paintings,
lithographic prints, and public murals. Most
of his works were produced between 1937 and
1942. His paintings include Self-Portrait (1935),
Sharecropper (1937), and On the Ranch (1941),
now at the Dallas Museum of Art; Where the Mountain Meets the Plains at SMU; and
Oil Field Girls (1940) at the Jack S. Blanton
Museum of Art, the University of Texas. A
regionalist, Bywaters's work is characterized
stylistically by a cohesive concern for local
subjects portrayed with strong compositions,
clear light, and earthy colors.

Bywaters successfully competed in federally
sponsored New Deal mural competitions: he
completed six projects in Texas, including a
series of panels in collaboration with Alexandre
Hogue at the Old City Hall in Dallas; a
series of panels at the Paris Public Library;
one mural each in the post offices of Trinity,
Quanah, and Farmersville; and three murals
in the Parcel Post Building in Houston. As art
critic for the Dallas Morning News, Bywaters
wrote hundreds of articles in the 1930s. He
served from 1943 to 1964 as director of the
Dallas Museum of Fine Arts while teaching at
SMU. As director, Bywaters recognized the educational
possibilities of the art museum and
produced several excellent exhibitions. In the
mid-1950s he faced accusations that the museum
was exhibiting works by Communists;
undaunted, Bywaters and his colleagues upheld
the standard of freedom of expression. At
SMU he served as chairman of the Division of
Fine Arts and director of the Pollack Galleries
at the Owens Fine Arts Center.

Bywaters wrote and produced catalogs for
exhibitions, published an art magazine, and
edited art books. His work with the Southwest Review included writing articles on the development
of regional art as well as serving as
art editor and illustrating articles. After retirement
from SMU, he served as regional director
of the Texas Project of the Archives of American
Art, Smithsonian Institution, and continued
to curate exhibitions. In 1981 Bywaters
presented SMU a gift of his papers to form the
Jerry Bywaters Collection on Art of the Southwest.
In 1972 he was elected a life member of
the Dallas Art Association; in 1978 he received
the Distinguished Alumni Award from SMU;
in 1980 the Texas Arts Alliance recognized him
for distinguished service to the arts in the
state; and in 1987 SMU acknowledged his distinctive
career with an honorary doctorate.
Until his death on March 7, 1989, Bywaters
lived in Dallas with his wife of fifty-eight
years, Mary McLarry Bywaters.


Francine Carraro
Texas State University-San Marcos




Carraro, Francine. Jerry Bywaters: A Life in Art. Austin:
University of Texas Press, 1994.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>