<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.062</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Prairie Schooner</field>
      <field name="author">Lemon, Lee T.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




PRAIRIE SCHOONER

Cover image of the Summer 2010 edition of the University of Nebraska's "Prairie Schooner" publication


The Prairie Schooner, founded in 1926 at the
University of Nebraska by Lowry C. Wimberly,
is widely recognized as one of the premier
literary magazines in the world. It has
been cited by the Washington Post for its "fabulous fiction" and by the Dictionary of Literary Biography and Writer's Digest as one of the top
ten magazines publishing poetry.

The Prairie Schooner's prose and poetry are
regularly reprinted in collections such as Best American Poetry, Best American Short Stories,
Best American Essays, the O. Henry anthology
of short stories, and the Pushcart Prize anthology.
The Schooner has also won recognition
for special issues devoted to specific national
and ethnic literatures.

A consistent goal of the Prairie Schooner editorial
staff has been to publish works of excellent
young writers. That group has included,
among many others, Joyce Carol Oates, Eudora
Welty, Octavio Paz, Truman Capote,
Cynthia Ozick, Tennessee Williams, Raymond
Carver, and Richard Russo. Willa Cather, Mari
Sandoz, Loren Eiseley, Wright Morris, Ron
Hansen, Ted Kooser, and Kathleen West are
among the prestigious Nebraska contributors.

The Prairie Schooner is supported by the
University of Nebraska through the Department
of English and the University of Nebraska
Press. Its distinguished editors have been
Wimberly (1926–56), Karl Shapiro (1956–63),
Bernice Slote (1963–80), Hugh Luke (1980–
87), and Hilda Raz (1987–present).

Perhaps the best summation of the Schooner's
history appeared in the Literary Magazine Review
several years ago: "[The] Prairie Schooner
rolls along, avoiding the quagmires of fads and
schisms, steadfastly defining the American
idiom."


Lee T. Lemon
University of Nebraska-Lincoln





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>