<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pd.022</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Freemen</field>
      <field name="author">Weinberg, Leonard</field>
      <field name="text">

 




FREEMEN

The Freemen, a lineal descendent of the Posse
Comitatus, is part of the antigovernment "Patriot"
movement that sprang to life after the
passage of federal gun-control legislation (the
Brady Bill) and the violent confrontations between
the FBI and the Randy Weaver family at
Ruby Ridge, Idaho, in 1992 and the Branch
Davidian religious sect at Waco, Texas, in
1994. In general, "Patriots" believe that the
federal government is tyrannical in character
and under the control of a malevolent "New
World Order" directed by the United Nations
or a worldwide Jewish conspiracy. This justifies,
in their minds, the formation of armed,
private militias aimed at defending citizens
against the threat from Washington DC.

A Freeman is, in theory, anyone who claims
to be a sovereign citizen. According to the doctrine,
the United States consists of two types of
citizens. First are the descendants of individuals
who were American citizens before the
Civil War and whose status was determined by
the Bill of Rights. Second are the descendants
of individuals whose rights were assigned to
them by the Fourteenth Amendment and subsequent
legislation. Citizens of the first kind
are potentially "sovereign." These Freemen
may dissolve the bonds that exist between
themselves and the United States by refusing to
obtain driver's licenses or automobile registrations,
recognize the jurisdiction of state and
federal courts, or pay income taxes. In practice,
Freemen have grouped together in townships
located on property belonging to one or more
of the individuals involved. Members of this
community then claim sovereignty for the
township, a status that places it beyond the law,
or so they believe.

The most widely known of these Freemen
townships was the Justus Township located on
the Clark ranch near Jordan, Montana. In
1996 its members engaged in an eighty-eight-day
standoff with authorities who were seeking
to evict some members from the premises
and arrest others on a variety of federal and
state criminal charges. In contrast to the Ruby
Ridge and Waco incidents, this event ended
peacefully on June 13, 1996, with the surrender
of the Freemen. On July 8 a federal jury in
Billings convicted the leader of the group of
bank fraud and other charges.

Freemen are vulnerable to criminal charges
because of their propensity for issuing bogus
checks and money orders and threatening to
"arrest" judges and other public officials with
whose decisions they disagree. In dealing with
such officials, it has become common for
Freemen to organize their own "common
law" courts, which then may issue fake "liens"
against the property of the offending public
officeholder. On some occasions these spurious
"courts" have found individuals guilty of
various offenses and threatened to carry out
"sentences" against them. Many Freemen are
drawn to Christian Identity theology, which
mixes unorthodox biblical understandings
with straightforward racism. They believe that
God has chosen white, Nordic yeomen, much
like the Freemen themselves, to rule America.

Prior to the 1996 Justus Township episode,
Leroy Schweitzer, Roy Schwasinger, and other
Freemen leaders were able to earn a living by
conducting seminars in which farmers, ranchers,
and other beleaguered rural folk were
trained in the techniques of tax avoidance
through the invocation of what observers referred
to as "legal magic." After the conclusion
of the Justus Township standoff and the subsequent
criminal prosecutions, the Freemen
movement fell on hard times.


Leonard Weinberg
University of Nevada, Reno




Dyer, Joel. Harvest of Rage: Why Oklahoma City Is Only
the Beginning. Boulder CO: Westview Press, 1997. Stern,
Kenneth S. A Force upon the Plain: The American Militia
Movement and the Politics of Hate. New York: Simon and
Schuster, 1996. Wessinger, Catherine. How the Millennium
Comes Violently. New York: Seven Bridges Press, 2000.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>