<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ind.014</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Coal</field>
      <field name="author">Daly, Daniel J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




COAL


Profile of the Coal-Producing Regions in the Great Plains for 1997
State/ProvinceMajor coal-producing regionNumber of minesProduction millions of tonsTotal employmentReverse base millions of tonsExports percentage
KansasWest Interor30.36679760
MontanaFort Union North Central Powder River841.0070848,81575
New MexicoRaton Mesa11.2540
North DakotaFort Union629.586579,4700
WyomingPowder River Bighorn2020266.582,77725,97190
U.S. total38388.764,24985,232
AlbertaGreat Plains623.472,5259,36725
SaskatchewanFort Union413.005133,0700
Canadian total1036.473,03812,437
Canadian total1036.473,03812,437
Total48375.237,28797,669


The Great Plains' coal resources occur in nine
major regions, but the bulk of resources and
production occurs in the five coal regions of
the Northern Great Plains and Prairie Provinces.
These five regions, which contain lowrank
subbituminous and lignite coals of late
Cretaceous to early Tertiary age, are the Great
Plains Coal Region of Alberta; the Fort Union
Coal Region of western North Dakota, eastern
Montana, southern Saskatchewan, and southwestern
Manitoba; the North Central Coal
Region of north-central Montana; and the
Powder River and Big Horn Coal Regions of
northern Wyoming and southeastern Montana.
Major coal deposits in the Southern and
Central Plains include the high-sulfur bituminous
coals of eastern Kansas (the Western
Interior Coal Region) and north-central
Texas (the Southwestern Coal Region), the
low-sulfur bituminous coking coal of northeastern
New Mexico and southeastern Colorado
(the Raton Mesa Coal Region), and the
subbituminous coals in the Denver Coal Region
of northeastern Colorado and southeastern
Wyoming.

Coal has provided a local source of fuel for
Great Plains farms, ranches, towns, railroads,
and industries from early European American
settlement into the modern era. By the end of
World War II, production in the Plains had
peaked at just a few percent of the more than
600 million tons mined in the United States
and Canada. Production bottomed out in the
late 1950s and early 1960s, reflecting increasing
displacement of coal by oil and gas. Beginning
in the late 1960s, however, a growing demand
for electrical power, concerns over oil and natural
gas supply, and the demand for coals low
in sulfur and ash to meet government emissions
standards initiated a period of explosive
growth in the coal industry. Much of this
growth occurred in the Northern Plains and
Prairie Provinces in the form of more than
twenty new mines, several with adjacent power
plants.

Area mining, a type of surface mining used
where coal seams are relatively horizontal and
the surface terrain is nearly level, accounts for
nearly all mining in the Great Plains. Area
mining utilizes draglines to remove overburden,
and the coal is then removed using
power shovels and loaders. As each strip of
overburden is removed, it is deposited as a
spoil ridge in the area from which coal has
already been excavated. Individual dragline
cuts may be 100 to 200 feet wide and extend
for thousands of feet. Several square miles
may be excavated over the life of a mine.

Land productivity and water availability
and quality are particularly significant issues
in the semiarid range and farmlands of the
Northern Great Plains, and mining companies
are required to reclaim mined land. To
ensure land productivity in mined areas, top-soil
and subsoil are removed by scrapers and
stockpiled prior to mining. Following mining,
the spoil ridges are shaped in a manner reflecting
the premining topography, the soil is
replaced, and the sites are revegetated. The
recontoured spoil density, initially about 25
percent greater than the original material, decreases
over time to about 20 percent of the
original material. Differential subsidence,
with the potential for ponding, salinization,
and disrupted cultivation, can be addressed in
large part through materials placement and
grading practices.

In the premining landscape, reducing conditions
prevail at depths greater than thirty
feet, but excavation brings these materials into
contact with oxygen. As a result, recharge
through spoil banks and newly reclaimed areas
produces groundwater characterized by elevated
concentrations of dissolved solids, elevated
concentrations of sodium and sulfate,
and increased alkalinity. In most areas, carbonates
and hydroxides provide a high natural
buffering capacity that precludes significant
acid mine drainage. Surface and groundwater
quality improves with time, but the disruption
of groundwater flow resulting from the removal
of the coal and the aquifers in the overburden
cannot be fully remedied within the
mined area.

In 1997 Great Plains coal production stood
at 375 million tons from forty-eight mines, accounting
for nearly 33 percent of the combined
U.S.-Canadian output. The 337 million tons
produced from the thirty-four mines in Wyoming,
North Dakota, and Montana accounted
for 78 percent of U.S. low-rank production, 31
percent of total U.S. production, and nearly 90
percent of total Great Plains production. The
36.5 million tons from the ten mines in the
Prairie Provinces accounted for 42 percent of
total Canadian production and 10 percent of
total Great Plains production. New Mexico
and Kansas contribute the remaining 1.6 million
tons, or 0.4 percent, of Plains production.
Mines in Montana and Wyoming are producing
at only three-quarters of capacity. Most of
the subbituminous coal mined in Wyoming
and Montana is shipped out of state for use in
coal-fired power plants. In contrast, the lignite
of North Dakota and Saskatchewan is mainly
utilized by mine-mouth power facilities.

In the Great Plains, 99 percent of coal production
is from surface mines. The 85 billion
tons in demonstrated surface-minable reserves
in the Northern Plains states of the
United States, including the 19 billion.ton reserve
of the Wyodak seam in the Powder River
Coal Region, are su.cient to last for nearly
250 years at current production levels and represent
nearly half of the demonstrated surface
mine reserves of the United States. Employment
at Plains surface mines stood at approximately
7,200 workers in 1997. Productivity
levels (tons of coal per miner per hour) for
surface mines in 1997 in Wyoming (35.4),
Montana (23.6), and North Dakota (17.8) were
well above the U.S. surface mine average of
9.5, reflecting economies of scale and relatively
low overburden to coal thickness ratios. Coal
severance taxes are levied in all states with
Plains-based coal production.

The Powder River Coal Region of northeastern
Wyoming and southwestern Montana
contains North America's thickest and most
extensive low-sulfur coal seams, including the
seventy-foot-thick Wyodak seam, and the region's
269 million–ton production accounts
for 70 percent of Plains production and 23
percent of combined U.S.-Canadian production.
Most of the coal is transported out of
state, with over half going to just six states in
1997 (Texas, Missouri, Illinois, Oklahoma,
Wisconsin, and Iowa). Most Powder River region
coal is produced from federal lands.

Great Plains coal resources have also figured
in unconventional types of coal-based
energy and commodities. Since 1983 lignite
from the Beulah-Zap seam in the Fort Union
Coal Region has been the feedstock for the
large-scale production of substitute natural
gas at the Great Plains Coal Gasification Plant
near Beulah, North Dakota. The Powder River
and Raton Mesa Coal Regions are significant
areas of coalbed methane exploration and development.
Between 1972 and 1988, a variety of
federal and private entities conducted field
tests in Wyoming, including tests at two sites
in the Powder River Coal Region, designed to
evaluate the technical and environmental feasibility
of underground coal gasification in
low-rank coals. Weathered low-rank coal,
known as Leonardite, has been used as an additive
in drilling fluids and as a soil amendment.
Coal combustion by-products such as
fly ash and bottom ash have been used for
concrete, engineered fills, aggregate, soil stabilization,
and ceramics.


Daniel J. Daly
University of North Dakota




Energy Information Administration. Coal Industry Annual 1997: U.S. Department of Energy. Energy Information
Administration, December 1998. Keystone Coal Industry Manual. Chicago: Intertec Publishing Company, 1998.
Wood, G. H., Jr., and W. V. Bour. Coal Map of North America. Washington DC: U.S. Geological Survey, 1998.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>