<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pd.027</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Haire, Robert (1845-1916)</field>
      <field name="author">Galler, Jr., Robert W.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




HAIRE, ROBERT (1845-1916)

Political and social activist Robert Emmett
Haire was born on August 29, 1845, in Freedom,
Michigan. He graduated from normal
school in Ypsilanti, Michigan, served as a
sailor on the Great Lakes, studied law at the
University of Michigan, and then joined the
clergy of the Roman Catholic Church. Haire
formally studied theology at the University of
Louvain in Belgium and Saint Mary's of the
West in Cincinnati, and remained an independent
scholar of literature, economics, and linguistics
throughout his life. He took the middle
name William prior to his ordination in
Detroit, Michigan, on March 1, 1874.

Haire relocated to Dakota Territory in 1879
after serving as a priest in Detroit and Flint,
Michigan. He built a sod church and braved
the extremes of the Great Plains climate to tend
forty-two mission stations between southwestern
Minnesota and present-day southeastern
North Dakota. With his outgoing personality,
he cultivated friendships with both
Protestants and Catholics. Attracted by Haire's
activism, the Presentation Sisters established
Saint Luke's Hospital and a parochial school
in Haire's newly created parish in Aberdeen,
South Dakota. Haire also published the Dakota
Catholic American newspaper to promote social
reform in the Northern Plains. His advocacy
brought support to the issues of prohibition,
women's suffrage, workers' rights,
and increased voter participation in the political
process. His reformist agenda and presidency
of the newly established Dakota Knights
of Labor, however, prompted Bishop Martin
Marty to suspend him from parish work in
May of 1890.

Haire remained a practicing Catholic priest
throughout his life, but in his later years he
became increasingly involved in politics. He
gave strong speeches at Populist Party conventions
and specifically promoted the statewide
initiative and popular referendum that South
Dakota adopted in 1897. Haire's leadership
skills led state Republicans to name him commissioner
of charities and corrections and
Populist governor Andrew E. Lee to nominate
him to the state board of regents. By 1900
Haire also claimed founding membership in
the Socialist Party, and he remained active in
the local branch until his death on March 4,
1916. Catholics and Protestants from diverse
backgrounds filled Sacred Heart Church to attend
Haire's funeral, testimony to the influential
life of this Great Plains activist.

See also POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT: Populists (People's Party).


Robert W. Galler Jr.
Western Michigan University




Atwood, E. Francis. A Memoir of the Life of Father Robert
W. Haire: Pioneer, Priest, and Scholar, Founder of Socialism
in the Dakotahs. Sisseton SD: Socialist Party, 1916. Sannes,
Erling N. "Knowledge Is Power: The Knights of Labor in
South Dakota." South Dakota History 22 (1992): 400–430.
Webb, Daryl. "'Just Principles Never Die': Brown County
Populists, 1890–1900." South Dakota History 22 (1992):
366–99.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>