<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.gen.016</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Gendered Space</field>
      <field name="author">Guelke, Jeanne Kay</field>
      <field name="text">

 




GENDERED SPACE

Both gender and space in society are abstract
concepts that reflect power relations, the gendered
division of labor, and societal concepts
of propriety. The boardrooms of banks symbolize
and enclose more power than smalltown
kitchens, for example, and each entails a
sense of proper activities to be conducted
within them. The former space is still more
associated with men; the latter, with women.
Because the Great Plains is so closely associated
with spatial concepts like distance and
"wide-open spaces," gendered space has much
to do with how Great Plains residents and outsiders
understand this region. Great Plains
history and literature provide many examples.

Deborah Fink's study of Nebraska farmwives
from 1880 to 1940 shows that they were
far more socially isolated and restricted in
their mobility than were their husbands. Although
both husband and wife could take the
team and wagon to town, women initially
found few spaces accessible to them beyond
the general store, and even fewer spaces where
mothers could bring small children. Male
farmers, in contrast, would frequent various
farm supply stores or chat with male friends in
the saloon or livery stable–spaces no "respectable
woman" would invade. Such experiences
further discouraged rural women from traveling
beyond their farms, thus limiting their opportunities
for friendships with town dwellers
who might have welcomed farm women's
visits. The automobile, telephone, and emergence
of women's groups (quilting circles, for
example) diminished these barriers, essentially
by reconfiguring space: the time-distance
equation changed and new female spaces developed.
Subsequently many farm women
took jobs in town, such as teaching school, to
supplement the family's agricultural income,
and thus they became less isolated than husbands
devoted to full-time farming.

Despite many rural women's involvement
in the heavy farmwork and men's involvement
with domestic chores, farm space still
seems gendered to many people: the fields,
pastures, and barn are encoded as male space;
thehouse and garden, as female. Thus, European
emigrants who had longstanding traditions
of women haying and harvesting in the
fields faced prejudices from their native-born
Anglo-American or Anglo-Canadian neighbors
in the Great Plains, who found the immigrants'
"foreign" division of space and labor
improper.

These social realities encouraged popular
legends about the female Plains settler's maladaptation
to its wide-open spaces and her
preference for the settled East. Willa Cather in
her short story "The Wagner Matinee" poignantly
describes a former music teacher
stranded on an isolated Nebraska farm. The
bleakness of her surroundings contrasts with
the rich cultural opportunities of Boston,
where she weeps during a concert on one of
her rare trips away from home. In Hamlin
Garland's Moccasin Ranch, homestead wife
Blanche lives close enough to town to escape
her Dakota claim shanty at every opportunity
for trips to the post office or general store.
When winter blizzards further isolate her,
she nearly goes mad and elopes with the storekeeper.

Recent research, however, demonstrates
that nineteenth-century women's dread of
isolation was by no means universal. Some
single women homesteaders associated their
remote situations with financial independence
and with freedom from excessive social
restrictions placed on eastern women. Female
travelers from the eastern United States and
Europe taking the transcontinental railroad
across the Great Plains also sometimes observed
the expansive landscape with enthusiasm
and expressions of personal release.

Masculine spatial legends equally abound.
Most common is the Old West interpretation
of the Plains as empty space to be transformed
through settlers' ranching, plowing, fencing,
railroading, and similar activities. European
American men, accordingly, do not merely
occupy space, they build it.

Because the meanings of gendered space
vary with specific societies, times, and places,
how Great Plains residents exemplify them
can rapidly change. Today, with more integrated
boardrooms and kitchens, fewer gendersegregated
spaces exist than in the past; however,
the football field (or in Canada, the ice
hockey rink) and male locker rooms, the altars
of Catholic churches, and meeting rooms of
businesswomen's associations are contemporary
examples.


Jeanne Kay Guelke
University of Waterloo




Cather, Willa. "A Wagner Matinee." In The Troll Garden.
Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1983: 94–101. Fink,
Deborah. Agrarian Women: Wives and Mothers in Rural Nebraska, 1880–1940. Chapel Hill: University of North
Carolina Press, 1992. Garland, Hamlin. The Moccasin Ranch: A Story of Dakota. New York: Harper and Brothers,
1909.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>