<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pd.018</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Estevan Strike</field>
      <field name="author">Bright, David</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ESTEVAN STRIKE

On September 29, 1931, almost 400 striking
coal miners clashed with local police and the
Royal Canadian Mounted Police (RCMP) in
the streets of Estevan, Saskatchewan. The battle
lasted less than an hour but left three men
dead and twenty-three seriously injured. It
was Canada's worst day of labor-related violence
since "Bloody Saturday" in Winnipeg
(June 21, 1919), and before long Estevan's day
of infamy became known simply as "Black
Tuesday."

Miners in the Estevan-Bienfait region had
long complained about their seasonal employment,
low wages, and atrocious working
and living conditions. However, they lacked a
vehicle to voice such grievances until the summer
of 1931, when they formed a branch of the
Mine Workers Union of Canada (MUWC). By
September they had managed to organize virtually
the entire workforce.

Coal operators refused to deal with the new
union, complaining that it was connected to
the procommunist Workers Unity League. In
response, the MUWC held a strike vote and on
September 8 brought the coalfields to a standstill.
Over the next two weeks, the rcmp and
private police were brought into the area to
maintain order and protect property while
employers unsuccessfully attempted to reopen
the mines using nonunion men.

Hoping to mobilize public support, striking
miners proposed to parade through the streets
of Estevan. Although advised by town officials
that this would not be permitted, the strikers
proceeded as planned, and on September 29, accompanied
by their wives and children, they
descended upon the town in a convoy of cars
and trucks. An early scuffle with the police resulted
in the fatal shooting of one miner, which
in turn sparked the riot. Subsequent criminal
trials and a Royal Commission attempted to
allocate responsibility for the breakdown in
civil order, but given conditions within the
industry, "Black Tuesday" is probably best understood
as a tragic accident that had long
been waiting to happen.


David Bright
University of Calgary





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>