<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.war.027</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Mackenzie, Ranald (1840-1889)</field>
      <field name="author">Pierce, Michael D.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MACKENZIE, RANALD (1840-1889)

Ranald Slidell Mackenzie was one of the most
capable officers in the frontier army and
would probably be one of the most famous
were it not for the circumstances of his retirement
and death. Mackenzie was born on July
27, 1840, near Tarrytown, New York. He entered
the U.S. Military Academy at West Point
in 1858 and graduated first in his class in 1862.
During the Civil War, Mackenzie gained a reputation
for bravery and distinguished leadership
and finished the war with the rank of
major general.

After the war, Mackenzie served briefly with
the Army Corps of Engineers before being assigned
to a field command. In 1871 he was
given command of the Fourth Cavalry Regiment
with the rank of colonel. In the next few
years Mackenzie pioneered the use of large
bodies of troops on the Llano Estacado in
Texas, fought several engagements with Comanches
and Kiowas, and led a controversial
raid on a Kickapoo village in northern Mexico.
Mackenzie's most famous fight was his
victory at the Battle of Palo Duro Canyon,
which was instrumental in putting an end to
the Red River War. In 1876 Mackenzie participated
in Gen. George Crook's campaign
against the Northern Plains Indians. He spent
the rest of his active career as a roving troubleshooter
on the Texas border and in New
Mexico, Arizona, and Colorado.

In November 1883 Mackenzie, now a brigadier
general, established his headquarters in
San Antonio as the new commander of the
Department of Texas. By this time he was behaving
in an erratic manner, and his condition
quickly deteriorated. After an incident
that left him beaten and tied to a wagon wheel,
Mackenzie's aides put him on a train to New
York, where he was briefly committed to the
Bloomingdale Asylum. He was released after a
few weeks but never regained mental stability.
He died on January 19, 1889, almost forgotten
by the general public, and was buried at West
Point, New York.


Michael D. Pierce
Tarleton State University




Pierce, Michael D. The Most Promising Young Officer: A
Life of Ranald Slidell Mackenzie. Norman: University of
Oklahoma Press, 1993. Wallace, Ernest, ed. Ranald S. Mackenzie's
Official Correspondence Relating to Texas, 1871-1879. Lubbock: West Texas Museum Association, 1967-68.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>