<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.wat.041</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Winters Doctrine</field>
      <field name="author">Longo, Peter J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




WINTERS DOCTRINE

The judicially crafted Winters Doctrine (1908)
provides water for the needs of Native Americans
who reside on federally reserved lands.
This judicial guarantee, while not absolute, is
highly significant given the demands for this
critical natural resource in a region where water
is often not abundantly available.

Water policy in the Great Plains is shaped
by powerful political forces. Economic demands
translate into political pressures and
ultimately into water law. State water laws are
generally designed to allocate water for "beneficial
uses," following the doctrine of prior appropriation.
Stressing uses, rather than needs,
is inconsistent with Native American ideals,
whereby water, like other aspects of the environment,
is connected to a higher sacred
order. Consequently, European American water
schemes have often been in conflict with
Native American concepts.

In 1908, however, Native Americans prevailed
in the landmark case Winters v. United
States. The case involved the Gros Ventres and
Assiniboines of the Fort Belknap Reservation
in Montana and their right to use the water of
the Milk River. When farmers upstream diverted
water from the river, the United States
brought an injunction against them, reasoning
that this left insufficient water for agriculture
on the reservation. The farmers appealed.
On January 6, 1908, the Supreme Court ruled
in favor of the United States and the Native
Americans, arguing that the establishment of
the Fort Belknap Reservation entitled the Native
Americans to perpetual use of the water
that it contained. Their rights were "reserved"
at the date of establishment (1888), and, contrary
to the doctrine of prior appropriation,
those rights could not be lost through nonuse.

The Winters Doctrine was a major victory
for all Native Americans, serving notice that
state laws are secondary to federally reserved
water rights and preventing prior appropriation
schemes from extinguishing Native American
needs. In 1976, in Cappaert v. United
States, the doctrine was extended to groundwater
use on or near federally created reservations.
Subsequently, however, an increasingly
conservative Supreme Court has ruled against
tribes in a number of water rights disputes.
While the Winters Doctrine protects Native
American water rights, this protection is still
vulnerable to changes in the prevailing political
climate.


Peter J. Longo
University of Nebraska at Kearney




Burton, Lloyd. American Indian Water Rights and the
Limits of Law. Lawrence: University Press of Kansas, 1991.
Hundley, Norris. "The Winters Decision and Indian Water
Rights: A Mystery Reexamined." In The Plains Indians
of the Twentieth Century, edited by Peter Iverson. Norman:
University of Oklahoma Press, 1985: 77–106.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>