<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ct.004</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Abilene, Texas</field>
      <field name="author">McComb, David G.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




AMARILLO, TEXAS

Located in the center of the Texas Panhandle,
Amarillo, with a population of almost 175,000
in 2000, straddles the Potter and Randall
county line and serves as the seat of government
for Potter County. The population is 77
percent white, 15 percent Latino, 6 percent African
American, and a small percentage of
other groups. It is a marketing point for cattle,
wheat, corn, sorghum, natural gas, oil,
and helium. Amarillo is a crossroads and has
served that function throughout its history.

When the Fort Worth and Denver Railway,
after a delay during the depression of the
1870s, resumed its northwestward march into
the Texas Panhandle, James T. Berry, a real
estate promoter, led a group of merchants
from Colorado City to establish a new town
site along the railroad route. In 1887 they laid
out a grid of streets near Amarillo Lake, also
known as Wild Horse Lake. At first called
Oneida, the town's name was soon changed to
Amarillo, which means "yellow" in Spanish.
Supposedly, Spanish shepherds or traders had
previously named the area for an abundance
of yellow flowers or perhaps for the yellow
soil of the creek banks. Local cowboys, having
been promised a town lot by Berry, cast the
decisive votes for Amarillo as the new county
seat on August 30, 1887. This political designation,
along with the railroad and the supply of
water, gave Amarillo the necessities of life.

The railroad arrived in 1887, bringing merchants,
cattle buyers, and settlers. By 1890
Amarillo was one of the world's busiest cattleshipping
points. The town site lay on low
ground, however, and after soaking rains in
the spring of 1889 the town was moved to a
higher location established by rancher Henry
B. Sanborn and barbed wire–fencing magnate
Joseph F. Glidden. The railroad opened a second
depot, and voters transferred the county
seat in 1893. Citizens incorporated the town in
1899 and established a council-manager form
of city government in 1913, a system used to
the present day.

Amarillo continued to grow. Three more
rail lines had arrived by 1903. In the first decade
of the twentieth century Amarillo acquired
a hospital, an independent school district,
an electric service, a trolley system, a
public library, and a rowdy bowery. Although
the population reached 9,957 in 1910, it was
still a raw town, as Mary H. Turner of Chicago
observed in 1902. Men spoke only about the
cattle business; there were no sidewalks and
no trees; rattlesnakes sunned themselves on
the small golf course; and a black bull wandering
the streets opened home fence gates in
order to eat the planted flowers.

Oil explorers found natural gas near Amarillo
in 1918 and petroleum in 1921. The nearby
Cliffside gas field, with its high natural helium
content, began producing in 1927 and resulted
in the construction of a federal government
helium plant four miles west of town. The
government produced the inert gas until 1970,
when an excess of helium in the nation made
production unnecessary. Amarillo still bills itself
as the "Helium Capital of the World." After
the dust storms and poverty of the Great
Depression, World War II brought economic
relief in 1942 with the opening of the Amarillo
Army Air Force Field for training pilots and
the nearby Pantex Ordnance Plant for producing
bombs. The airfield closed in 1946, reopened
in 1951, and then closed again in 1968.
The federal government converted the Pantex
plant in 1951 to the production and deconstruction
of chemical and nuclear explosives.
Fears about radioactive poisoning and reports
of unsafe environmental conditions have resulted
in occasional protests and have left a
shadow of concern that remains to the present
time. Still, the Pantex plant was Amarillo's
largest employer, and there has been relatively
little pressure on Pantex to prioritize environmental
protection.

After a decline in population of 8 percent
following the closing of the airfield, Amarillo's
population had rebounded to 149,230 by 1980.
In 1971 the city took over a part of the airfield
for an airport, which is now served by six passenger
airlines, and Interstates 40 and 27 now
traverse the city, dividing it into quarters. Natural
gas, petroleum, cattle, agriculture, and
transportation remain Amarillo's main economic
supports.


David G. McComb
Colorado State University




Henderson, H. Allen. "Amarillo, Texas." In The New Handbook of Texas, edited by Ron Tyler. Austin: Texas
State Historical Association, 1996: 1: 140–42. Key, Della
Tyler. In the Cattle Country: History of Potter County.
Amarillo: Tyler-Berkley, 1961. Price, B. Byron, and Frederick
W. Rathjen. The Golden Spread. Northridge CA: Windsor
Publications, 1986.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>