<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fol.028</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Mock Weddings</field>
      <field name="author">Taft, Michael</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MOCK WEDDINGS

The mock wedding is a folk drama that flourishes
in the small communities of the Great
Plains and is as strong a tradition today as it
was more than 100 years ago. While the drama
may take a number of forms, all mock weddings
are theatrical parodies of the marriage
ritual, in which members of a community
dress as a wedding entourage and stage a
mock ceremony. Players have specific roles–
such as bride, groom, minister, ring bearer,
and bridesmaids–and there is usually a script,
either written or oral, in which several of the
players have speaking parts.

Especially in earlier times, this drama was
performed informally by teenage girls as playful
preparation for marriage. Children of both
sexes also performed mock weddings–often
called Tom Thumb weddings–under adult
supervision, either as a school play or as part
of a fund-raising benefit. Similarly, all-male
groups, such as volunteer fire departments,
would stage "womenless weddings" as a way
of raising money.

While these forms are popular in various
parts of North America, there is one kind of
mock wedding tradition that is stronger in the
Great Plains than in the rest of the continent.
This drama involves both men and women actors
who cross-dress, and it is characterized
by ad-libbing, bawdy behavior, and general
horseplay. Often the bride is a very large
man, while the groom is a particularly petite
woman. Outrageous costumes, masks, and
props usually add to the parodic nature of the
performances.

Although this form of mock wedding is
sometimes staged as a fund-raiser, it is usually
part of a larger community celebration of a
marriage or, more likely, a milestone wedding
anniversary. As part of a couple's twenty-fifth
anniversary, for example, friends, family, and
neighbors will hold a celebration. The honored
couple may be regaled with speeches
(often of a "roast" variety) and locally composed
songs or poems. Gifts, food, drink, music,
and dancing are all part of this celebration.

Unannounced, a mock wedding procession
enters the hall and takes over "center stage."
Amid laughter, jeers, and expressions of dismay,
the procession arranges itself in a typical
wedding tableau. The minister usually begins
with a "dearly beloved" speech, a parody of
the liturgy. This is followed by the saying of
vows, which often reveals embarrassing characteristics
or stories about the honored couple,
a ring ceremony involving a jar-sealer ring
or other sight gag, and the kissing of the bride,
which sometimes devolves into a wrestling
match. The ceremony might be augmented
with other scenes, such as the entrance of a
girlfriend with babe in arms.

Obviously, this drama honors the anniversary
couple through good-natured mockery.
But it is also a form of commentary on rural
and agrarian life, especially through some of
the vows, which often concern the less savory
aspects of farm work ("Do you promise
to clean the slaughterhouse mess, and not
love and honor your husband any less?"). As
women are generally the organizers of mock
weddings, these dramas tend to comment on
the many roles that women must fulfill on the
family-run farm or ranch. The cross-dressing
itself emphasizes the blurring of divisions between
men's and women's work on the farm.
These commentaries are well understood by
actors and audience alike.


Michael Taft
American Folklife Center
Library of Congress




Butala, Sharon. Luna. Saskatoon: Fifth House, 1988. Taft,
Michael. "Folk Drama on the Great Plains: The Mock
Wedding in Canada and the United States." North Dakota History 56 (1989): 16–23. Taft, Michael. "Men in Women's
Clothes: Theatrical Transvestites on the Canadian Prairie."
In Undisciplined Women: Tradition and Culture in Canada,
edited by Pauline Greenhill and Diane Tye. Montreal:
McGill-Queen's University Press, 1997: 131–38.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>