<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ha.032</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Peñ, Federico (b. 1947)</field>
      <field name="author">Straayer, John A.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




PEÑA, FEDERICO (b. 1947)

Federico Fabian Peña was born and raised in
South Texas. By age fifty-two he had logged a
distinguished political career as a Colorado
state legislative leader, Denver's mayor, and
the head of two major federal agencies as a
member of President Bill Clinton's cabinet.

Born in 1947 in Laredo, Texas, as one of
six children, Federico Peña was raised in
an upper-middle-class Hispanic family. His father,
a Texas A&amp;M University graduate, was a
successful cotton broker. Peña's ancestors had
helped in the founding of Laredo, and several
held elective posts during the Civil War. His
lineage, therefore, was one of both economic
and political participation and success.

Peña's early schooling was in English-speaking
Catholic schools in Brownsville, Texas, he
was a top performer in both academics and
athletics. Federico went on to the University of
Texas in Austin for his bachelor of science and
law degrees (1969 and 1972, respectively). In
1973 he moved to Denver where he worked
with the Mexican-American Legal Defense
Fund and as a private attorney, focusing primarily
on civil rights cases and voting issues.

Federico Peña's elective political career began
at age thirty-one in the Colorado House
of Representatives. In search of an aggressive
leader, the Democrats selected Peña as minority
party leader in only his second term. Then,
in a surprise move, the promising young lawmaker
abandoned legislative life at the end of
that term in 1983 to run for mayor of Denver.
A virtual unknown, Peña challenged fourteen-
year incumbent mayor Bill McNichols
and won a close and improbable victory.
Peña's campaign slogan was "Imagine a Great
City," and it featured a high-energy, streetlevel
approach to politics and an aggressive
voter registration drive bolstered by an estimated
4,000 volunteers. The new mayor's first
term was rocky; he inherited a municipal budget
deficit and a depressed local economy.
Peña sought to "open City Hall" and establish
a plan for economic recovery, but critics said
he was slow to establish his cabinet, and an
initial push for a new convention center failed.

In the face of opposition, Peña sought a second
term. On the eve of the election he was
roughly twenty points down in the polls, but
again he won a close election. With an economic
strategy in place, and with more experience,
Mayor Peña launched a number
of extremely successful capital development
projects. His reputation solidified, he once
again surprised observers by rejecting a run
for a third term. Peña had recently married
Ellen Hart, a world-class distance runner.
They'd begun a family and he wanted more
time at home.

But within a year Peña was back in public
life, first on President Clinton's transition
team, and then for four years as secretary of
transportation and two years as secretary of
energy. In 1998 Peña returned to Denver with
his wife and three young children, entering
the business world as senior adviser with Vestar
Capital Partners.

Federico Peña's career in politics was marked
by major achievements as well as by the criticism
that comes with public life. Critics characterized
him as indecisive in his first mayoral
term, and in his second he was the object of a
failed recall movement. But Peña was also the
force behind a new Denver airport, convention
center, performing arts center, and library,
as well as improvements in streets,
parks, and neighborhoods. Denver gained a
major league baseball team during his tenure.
In Washington, Peña successfully reduced government
personnel and cost levels and championed
the causes of mass transit and technology.
He was a relentless champion of civil
rights and civil liberties. Peña's expressed philosophy
was that personal success flows from
hard work and vision, and community success
rests upon leadership, inclusion, participation,
and investment. The route to Denver's
International Airport is along Peña Boulevard.

See also CITIES AND TOWNS: Denver, Colorado.


John A. Straayer
Colorado State University





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>