<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.arc.004</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Barns</field>
      <field name="author">Humstone, Mary H.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BARNS


Dairy barn, Kranzburg, South Dakota


The barn is the defining architectural feature
and the central focus of the Great Plains farm.
Most Great Plains barns were multipurpose
buildings designed for hay storage and shelter
for draft horses and cows. Variations include
dairy (milking) barns, sheep barns, and barns
designed primarily for grain storage.

Barn design is influenced by the origins and
traditions of the barn owner and builder, the
type of agriculture for which the barn is used,
and the building materials that are available
locally. The first settlers in the Great Plains
brought with them barn-building traditions
Dairy barn, Kranzburg, South Dakota
from Europe and eastern North America, but
the scarcity of timber in the Great Plains inhibited
the building of the large, multistory,
multipurpose, timber-frame barns that were
common farther east. Post-and-beam barns
constructed of heavy timbers with mortise-and-
tenon joints are rare in the Great Plains.

Barn building in the Great Plains did not
really take off until the coming of the railroads,
which increased the availability of dimension
lumber and wire nails. These changes in transportation
and building technology, combined
with the invention of the hay fork and hay
track for loading hay in the barn, resulted in
a revolution in barn design. The old, heavy,
timber-frame construction was abandoned in
favor of the lighter, more versatile balloon
framing using dimension lumber.

The typical late-nineteenth- to early-twentieth-
century barn of the Great Plains is a
rectangular two-story structure, consisting of
a low-ceilinged main floor topped by a huge
haymow. The main floor is divided into stalls
for draft horses or mules and a few dairy cows
as well as bins for grain. The development
of the double-sloped gambrel roof, which is
most frequently associated with barns today,
allowed as much as 50 percent more hay storage
than the single-sloped gable roof and
eliminated crossbeams, allowing for efficient
use of a hay track to load hay. The desire for
ever larger clearspan space in the haymow
eventually led to the development of arched
roofs constructed of rounded trusses, which
became popular in the first few decades of the
twentieth century.

Another common barn design in the Great
Plains is the midwestern three-bay barn, also
called the feeder barn or hay barn. This light
timber-frame barn is divided into three sections,
or bays, under a long, sloping gable
roof. The center section is used for floor-to-ceiling
hay storage. The two side bays hold
stalls for animals and sometimes bins for
grain storage. This style of barn was popular
with farmers whose main need was for a dry
storage area for hay rather than for livestock
shelter.

Land-grant universities had a widespread
influence on early-twentieth-century barn design
in the Great Plains. Agricultural engineers
developed innovative building designs
for all types of farming purposes. They designed
special barns for housing dairy cows,
hogs, and horses and for storing hay, grain,
and machinery and distributed the plans to
farmers nationwide through the cooperative
extension service. With the availability
of ready-made plans and even mail-order
barns, barn design became more standardized
throughout the country, although regional
variations and ethnic building traditions continued
well into the twentieth century. The
stone barns in the Flint Hills of Kansas and the
log barns of the Laramie Plains of Wyoming
are two examples of Plains regional variations
based on available building materials and local
building traditions.

An example of the influence of the landgrant
universities is the Wisconsin dairy barn.
Although dairy farming is not extensive in the
Great Plains, this standard dairy barn still appears
as a feature of the Great Plains landscape.
Built to specifications provided by the
University of Wisconsin–Madison, the dairy
barn is distinguished by its rectangular shape
(generally, 36 feet wide and up to 100 feet
long), north-south orientation, and rows of
small windows along the basement walls. The
low stable area, designed for milking cows,
was topped by a large gambrel roof, which
provided ample storage space for hay. As silos
gained popularity in the late nineteenth century,
they were attached to the end or the side
of the dairy barn.

Round and polygonal barns were also designed
by agricultural engineers at land-grant
universities and promoted as efficient for
milking cows and feeding cattle. Although
these unusual barns are not common, all
Plains states have a few examples. Most are
now considered local landmarks, and many
have been actively preserved.

Most barns were built by farmers themselves,
sometimes with the help of professional
barn builders. Some builders developed
distinctive styles that can still be recognized
in certain localities. While most barns have
little ornamentation, elements of architectural
styles such as Italianate scroll work, Gothic
pointed gables, and even western false fronts
were sometimes incorporated into barn design.
Some barns also display evidence of regional
craftsmanship in brick, stone, and
woodwork. Cupolas, used for ventilation,
provided the farmer or barn builder with an
opportunity to add a special flourish to the
barn to distinguish it from those around it.

By the 1950s construction of the multistory
barn had virtually ceased and was replaced by
the single-story pole barn. Unlike the traditional
American barns, which housed several
activities under one roof, modern pole barns
are specifically designed for a single purpose.
They feature huge, open interior spaces, allowing
easy access for large machinery. In
spite of the predominance of metal-clad pole
buildings on farms across North America, the
traditional gambrel-roofed barn persists as
the symbol of American agriculture, appearing
in everything from advertising of farm
products to logos of agricultural organizations
and corporations.

The decline in the number of farms and in
farm acreage in the Great Plains has resulted
in the loss of many traditional barns. Even on
working farms, these barns face an uncertain
future. Barns designed specifically for the
storage of loose hay or the hand milking of
cows outgrew their original usefulness decades
ago. When the tractor replaced the draft
horse for plowing and other farm chores,
stalls for horses were no longer needed. Farmers
found haymows ine.cient and sometimes
structurally inadequate for storing baled hay.
As agriculture became more specialized, many
farmers sold their livestock altogether, and
barns that had once been the center of the
farm operation stood empty.

In spite of the widespread loss, there are still
many traditional barns in use across the Great
Plains. Some have remained in constant use
and have been adapted to fit the changes in
agricultural practice and technology. For instance,
on many dairy farms, wooden stalls
gave way to stanchions and later free stalls,
and mechanical milking and waste removal
systems were added and improved over the
years. In some cases a new milking parlor
was built, and the old barn is now used for
housing dry heifers and raising calves. In the
Northern Plains, where many farmers have
sold all their livestock and produce only crops,
traditional barns have been converted to store
large quantities of hay or grain or to shelter
farm equipment. These changes usually involve
enlarging doorways and sometimes raising
or removing the haymow floor to open up
the interior space.

The sheer size of barns and their simple,
functional design have made them treasured
architectural landmarks as well as utilitarian
structures. While many barns have been lost
to development or neglect, a significant number
of farmers across the country have maintained
their older barns and adapted them for
modern farming uses.


Mary H. Humstone
National Trust for Historic Preservation




Gyrisco, Geoffrey M., ed. The Farm Landscape: A Bibliography of the Architecture and Archaeology of Farmsteads and Settlements in Wisconsin and in the Areas of Origin of Its Settlers in the United States and Europe. Madison: State
Historical Society of Wisconsin, 1997. Halsted, Byron
David. Barn Plans and Outbuildings. New York: Orange
Judd Company, 1918. Noble, Allen G., and Hubert G. H.
Wilheim, eds. Barns of the Midwest. Athens: Ohio University
Press, 1995.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>