<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fol.023</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Grinnell, George Bird (1849-1938)</field>
      <field name="author">Wishart, David J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




GRINNELL, GEORGE BIRD (1849-1938)

Portrait of George Bird Grinnell
          

George Bird Grinnell was not from the Great
Plains—he was born into a wealthy family in
Brooklyn, New York, on September 20, 1849–
but his studies of Plains Indians, and especially
his role in the preservation of their histories,
are fundamental to the region's legacy.

A mediocre student, Grinnell nevertheless
graduated from Yale in 1870. That same year
his interest in the Great Plains was kindled
during a paleontology expedition along the
route of the Union Pacific Railroad when he
met William F. Cody and accompanied the
Pawnees on a bison hunt. He was with George
Armstrong Custer in the Black Hills in 1874 as
a naturalist, and later, as editor of Forest and
Stream, he shaped the early years of the American
conservation movement. It was his publications
on Native American customs and
oral traditions, however, that particularly distinguished
his life.

Starting with Pawnee Hero Stories and Folk-Tales (1889), and continuing through Blackfoot Lodge Tales (1892), The Cheyenne Indians: Their History and Ways of Life (1923), and By Cheyenne Campfires (1926), Grinnell collected
and preserved the Indians' own histories with
a sensitivity that was often lacking in the studies
done by his contemporaries. While he
shared his contemporaries' social Darwinist
views that Native Americans had to give way
to "civilization," and while he may not, as
Richard Levine has argued, really have understood
the implications of the "folktales" he
collected, Grinnell let the Pawnees, Blackfeet,
and Cheyennes tell their own stories, in their
own way. Those stories survive as vivid insights
into their views of themselves and of
their position in nature.

Although he spent portions of most years
in the Great Plains learning and recording
(and serving as treaty commissioner for the
U.S. government), Grinnell continued to be
based in New York City. He died there on
April 11, 1938, having suffered a series of heart
attacks over the previous decade.


David J. Wishart
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Levine, Richard. "Indians, Conservation, and George Bird
Grinnell." American Studies 28 (1987): 41–55. Parsons,
Cynthia. George Bird Grinnell: A Biographical Sketch. Lanham
MD: University Press of America, 1992. Reiger, John F.
"Dedication to George Bird Grinnell." Arizona and the West 21 (1979): 1–4.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>