<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.art.053</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Rock Art</field>
      <field name="author">Hartley, Ralph J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ROCK ART


Rock art, southeastern Colorado, Fort Carson Military Reservation.


Rock art in the Great Plains consists of both
petroglyphs (markings that have been pecked,
scratched, incised, or abraded on natural rock
surfaces) and pictographs (painting on nonportable
rock surfaces). Petroforms (sometimes
called geomorphs, in which large stones
or boulders have been used to outline anthropomorphic,
zoomorphic, or geometric forms)
are found primarily in the northeastern U.S.
Plains and southern Saskatchewan. Petroglyphs
and/or pictographs have been recorded
in all states of the Great Plains. Rock art was
noted in the journals of European American
explorers, but it was not until the 1930s that
petroglyphs and pictographs were thoroughly
documented and interpreted for professional
publication.

The placement of petroglyphs and pictographs
is highly variable in the Great Plains.
In the Northern Plains rock art is found in
and around major geologic uplifts, especially
where rock surfaces are exposed on canyon
walls and in rock shelters. On the open Plains
rock art is found on sandstone or limestone
where streams have cut the underlying bedrock
and on boulders on talus slopes and hogbacks.
Petroglyphs on isolated boulders also
occur along the Missouri River in the Dakotas,
in southern Alberta and Saskatchewan, and in
central Texas and southern Oklahoma. Rock
art in the Central Plains is rarer; however, proto-historic
and early historic Native Americans
used rock shelters intensively in the Dakota
sandstone of the Smoky Hills region of northcentral
Kansas, where they depicted representational
images. Native Americans also made
petroglyphs on sandstone bluffs in central
Oklahoma. In the Northern Plains some rock
art is believed to be associated with bison
jumps and kill sites. It is generally acknowledged,
however, that in prehistoric social environments
the role of rock art as a means of
communication varied with its social context.
The places where it was produced are usually
understood to have had special meanings and
functioned, along with myths and stories, to
maintain social cohesion.

Despite difficulties in the accurate dating of
rock art, it is known that some of the oldest
rock art in the Plains is found in the Black Hills
of western South Dakota, eastern Wyoming,
and the Wyoming Basin. These areas have rock
art thought to predate 10,000 B.P. and also
contain sites ranging through the Archaic period
(7500.2000 B.P.). The art is primarily on
exposed vertical cliffs and at the base of canyon
walls. Zoomorphic figures, usually wapiti (elk)
or mountain sheep, are the predominant representations.
Some depictions of hunting are
found, such as game nets or corrals and the
spearing of animals by humans. Some of the
most heavily varnished petroglyphs depict apparent
hoof prints, vulvas, and grooves. Pictographs
depicting orange to light red finger
lines and handprints in central Montana are
believed to be more than 3,000 years old.

Archaic hunters and gatherers in southern
Texas, where the Pecos River, Devils River, and
Rio Grande meet, created rock art—considered
to be some of the most impressive prehistoric
art in the world—in dry rock shelters.
Dramatic polychrome pictographs of detailed
life-size human-feline composites and anthropomorphic
figures with feathers, wings, claws,
horns, and weapons are documented. The
oldest rock art, the Pecos River style, is nearly
4,000 years old. Farther north along the Pecos
River at Lewis Canyon are more than 250 pictograph
sites and more than 900 petroglyphs.
The petroglyphs, many on flat rock surfaces,
consist of abstract geometrical designs and
representational figures of human hands as
well as deer, bison, and bird feet. Depictions
of atlatls, a weapon of the Archaic, suggest, in
association with other cultural remains, production
of the petroglyphs between 9,000 and
1,000 years ago. In some of the older glyphs
human figures appear to brandish some kind
of lance or other weapon. Rock shelters in
the Wichita Mountains of Oklahoma contain
near life-size anthropomorphic figures and
geometric petroglyphs painted with red and
yellow ochre.

Pictograph images of animals and anthropomorphs
on a massive schist formation at
Long Lake along the Manigotagan River in
southern Manitoba are thought to have been
produced during the middle to late Archaic.
In the Milk River valley of southern Alberta a
complex of 93 sites and 280 separate rock art
panels constitutes one of the largest concentrations
of rock art in the Northern Plains.
This area, the Writing-on-Stone Provincial
Park, includes petroglyphs ranging from up to
1000 years old through the postcontact period
(A.D. 1725–1850). Boulder alignments, many
considered solstice-aligned configurations,
are found in southern Saskatchewan. Some
of the alignments were probably constructed
2,000 years ago; others, based on astronomical
calculations, may have been constructed in
the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries.

Rock art in southeastern Colorado, including
many zoomorphic or anthropomorphic
representations, has been intensively studied,
especially in the rock shelters of the Purgatoire
River area. Some rock art in this area is associated
with rock structural remains that suggest
Native American vision quest activities.
Ages of these images range from the middle
Archaic (c. 3500 B.P.) to the late Ceramic stage
(c. 250 B.P.). A cluster of dry caves and rock
shelters in the canyon country of Black Mesa
in the Oklahoma Panhandle contain petroglyphs
and pictographs of bison and anthropomorphs,
associated with perishable artifacts
such as sandals, basketry, and skin
bags, that range in age from the late Archaic
through the Woodland (A.D. 200–1000). The
Black Hills of South Dakota include many examples
of prehistoric rock art. Stylistic analyses
suggest that a chronological sequence of
rock art, ranging from the late Paleo-Indian to
the early historic period, is reflected in at least
seven distinct styles of petroglyph and pictograph
imaging. Pecked petroglyphs are also
documented, especially in Whoop-Up Canyon
in the Black Hills.

The diversity of prehistoric rock art in the
Great Plains is indicative of the region's varied
modes of social organization and economic
systems. Advances in the technology of direct
dating will help in assigning rock art to its
cultural a.liations, but an understanding of
why the markings were made in the places
they occur will challenge researchers for years
to come and, indeed, may never be known.

See also NATIVE AMERICANS: Paleo-Indians.


Ralph J. Hartley
Midwest Archeological Center




Francis, Julie E., and Lawrence L. Loendorf. Ancient Visions: Petroglyphs and Pictographs of the Wind River and Bighorn Country, Wyoming and Montana. Salt Lake City:
University of Utah Press, 2002. Kirland, Forrest, and W.
W. Newcomb Jr. The Rock Art of Texas Indians. Austin:
University of Texas Press, 1967. Sundstrom, Linea. Rock Art of the Southern Black Hills. New York: Garland, 1990.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>