<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.sr.015</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Dude Ranching</field>
      <field name="author">Borne, Lawrence R.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




DUDE RANCHING

Dude ranching has long been an important
part of recreation in the Great Plains. The first
dude ranches were generally family-operated
cattle ranches that diversified during hard
economic times by offering services to travelers.
Known as dudes, these people visited
ranches to ride horses, fish, and take part in
cattle ranch activities. Dude ranches first appeared
in the late nineteenth century, and they
continue to operate at the beginning of the
twenty-first century.

One of the early dude ranches was the Custer
Trail Ranch, founded in 1879 by Howard,
Willis, and Alden Eaton at Medora, Dakota
Territory. The brothers were hosts to visitors in
1882, and in the following year Howard Eaton
led guests on the first of his many pack trips
to Yellowstone Park. The primary interest for
most dudes was horseback riding, but eventually
they wanted to experience other outdoor
adventures such as cattle drives, fishing trips,
and visiting mountainous country and national
parks. In order to satisfy their guests
better, the Eaton brothers moved their operation
in 1904 to the Bighorn Mountain area in
Wyoming. Eatons' Ranch has operated there
since that move. By the 1890s dude ranches had
also developed in Colorado, Wyoming, and
Montana.

In 1926 railroad officials helped dude ranchers
form the Dude Ranchers Association (DRA),
an organization that continues to operate. The
number of dude ranches reached its peak in the
1930s, when it was estimated that there were
more than 350 in the United States and 1 in
Canada. Then the numbers declined, partly due
to the Great Depression but also to changing
habits of travelers and more varied tourist destinations.
The DRA directory for 2000 lists 105
member ranches in the United States and 3 in
Canada. Most are located in Colorado, Wyoming,
and Montana.


Lawrence R. Borne
Northern Kentucky University




Borne, Lawrence R. Dude Ranching: A Complete History.
Albuquerque: University of New Mexico Press, 1983. Rodnitzky,
Jerome L. "Recapturing the West: The Dude Ranch
in American Life." Arizona and the West 10 (1968): 111–26.
Roundy, Charles G. "The Origins and Early Development
of Dude Ranching in Wyoming." Annals of Wyoming 45
(1973): 5–25.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>