<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.afam.014</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Civil Rights</field>
      <field name="author">Gordon, Jacob U.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CIVIL RIGHTS


African American men and women demonstrate


African Americans in the Great Plains were
subjected to some of the same racial discrimination
they faced in the South. They have
often been denied equal opportunities, experienced
violence, and been victimized by racial
profiling. The Great Plains has also been
the setting for important legal cases and protest
movements of the civil rights movement.

Racial unrest and violence against African
Americans were widespread in the United
States during the early twentieth century.
From individual lynchings to mob violence
against entire communities, whites lashed out
against African Americans. Between 1917 and
1923 the United States experienced a series of
deadly race riots. From Tulsa, Oklahoma, to
Omaha, Nebraska, and many communities in
between, African Americans were attacked,
beaten, and killed by mobs. Tulsa was the site
of one of the deadliest race riots in American
history. On May 31 and June 1, 1921, white
mobs attacked Tulsa's black community, destroying
thirty-five city blocks and killing indiscriminately.
Official counts list only thirtynine
deaths, but historians' and witnesses' accounts
push the potential number of deaths
up to 300. During the 1990s steps were taken
to rectify the wrongs perpetrated against Tulsa's
African American population. Seventyfive
years after the fact, and six decades after
his death, J. B. Stradford, a black Tulsa businessman,
was cleared of charges connected to
the riot. Descendants of Stradford traveled
from around the country to witness a ceremony
in October 1996 in which authorities
absolved him of charges that he had incited
the riot. The Race Riot Commission was established
in 1997 to investigate the riot and pay
restitution to survivors. In 2001 a report was
submitted to the Oklahoma legislature recommending
the direct payment of reparations to
the survivors.

An important step in the battle for civil
rights was the 1954 Supreme Court decision in
Brown v. The Board of Education of Topeka.
This case was one of five segregation lawsuits
selected by the NAACP in 1950 to challenge the
"separate but equal" rule in the federal courts.
On May 17, 1954, Chief Justice Earl Warren
read the Court's decision, which was that
"separate but equal" did not belong in public
education. Although this landmark legal triumph
did not instantly end school segregation,
it destroyed the constitutional foundation
upon which legalized segregation rested
and made future gains possible.

In the late 1950s, however, many Great
Plains communities still denied African Americans
access to the same schools, churches,
restaurants, and other public accommodations
used by whites. Within this setting,
young African Americans in Wichita, Kansas,
and Oklahoma City, Oklahoma, launched
what may have been the first sit-ins of the civil
rights movement. Beginning on July 12, 1958,
several Wichita youths, under the direction of
the local NAACP Youth Council, began a sit-in
at the Dockum Drug Store in order to end the
city's segregation policy. The Wichita sit-in
ended on August 7 when the store announced
that all customers would be served without
regard to race. Spurred on by the victory in
Wichita, eight Oklahoma City youths entered
the Katz Drug Store on August 19 and requested
service. After just two days the store
desegregated its lunch counter. Great Plains
sit-ins undoubtedly influenced the larger sitin
movement that swept through the South
in 1960.

During the 1960s black student unions
emerged on college campuses to challenge racial
inequalities in the educational system.
The black student union at the University of
Kansas, for example, demanded, among other
things, the establishment of a black studies
department, institutional commitment to the
recruitment and retention of black students,
the hiring of African American faculty and
administrators, and the formation of an allblack
pompon squad in protest of the university's
all-white squad. In response, the University
of Kansas opened the Office of Minority
Affairs in 1969 and one year later created the
Department of African and African American
Studies. Black student unions also appeared
on high school campuses. The activism of
Lawrence (Kansas) High School's black student
union led to the introduction of black
history courses and a black American heritage
week, black representation on cheerleading
squads, and the formation of the Lawrence
Branch of Concerned Black Parents, Inc.

More recently, the National Conference on
Race and Ethnicity in American Higher Education
(NCORE) has worked on civil rights issues
in higher education. Founded in 1988 by
the University of Oklahoma College of Continuing
Education, ncore assists institutions
of higher education by creating inclusive educational
environments, programs, and curricula,
improving campus racial and ethnic
relations and expanding opportunities for educational
access and success by culturally diverse
and traditionally underrepresented populations.
ncore attracts more than 1,500
students, scholars, administrators, policymakers,
and civil rights leaders each year.

By the 1990s many people opposed a.rmative
action policies. In 1996 the United States
Supreme Court let stand a state court ruling in
Hopwood v. University of Texas that led to the
end of affirmative action in Texas public colleges
and universities. The number of African
Americans at the University of Texas law
school dropped sharply. The Supreme Court's
ruling also had a national impact. It triggered
California's Proposition 209 in 1997, outlawing
the use of gender and race in hiring, contracting,
and university admissions.

A more recent civil rights issue is the racial
profiling of African Americans. An example of
this in the Great Plains occurred in August
1998 when Rossano V. Gerald and his young
son Gregory crossed the Oklahoma border
into a nightmare. A career soldier and a highly
decorated veteran, Gerald, a black man of
Panamanian descent, was stopped twice in
thirty minutes by the highway patrol. During
the second stop, which lasted two-and-a-half
hours, troopers terrorized Gerald's twelve-year-
old son with a police dog. Troopers
placed both father and son in a closed car with
the air conditioning off and fans blowing hot
air, warning that the dog would attack if they
attempted to escape. Halfway through the episode,
perhaps realizing the extent of their lawlessness,
the troopers turned off the patrol
car's video evidence camera.

Another example of racial profiling took
place at Oak Park Mall in Overland Park,
Kansas. The mall security officer in Dillard's
department store harassed two black women
and accused them of shoplifting. It turned out
that the two women were innocent and the
security guard was profiling African Americans
under the instructions given to him by
Dillard's management. The two women filed a
discrimination lawsuit and were awarded $1
million by the jury in December 1997.

The battle for civil rights in the Great Plains
has had its own particular history, but it is
not fundamentally different from the national
trend. The perception that only the South was
racist is a myth of the American past. In fact,
the struggle for civil rights is an American
journey, involving all American regions.

See also LAW: Brown v. The Board of Education
of Topeka.


Jacob U. Gordon
University of Kansas




Harrison, Maureen, and Steve Gilbert, eds. Civil Rights
Decisions of the United States Supreme Court: The 20th
Century. San Diego: Excellent Books, 1994. Orum, Anthony
M. Black Students in Protest: A Study of the Origins
of the Black Student Movement. Washington DC: American
Sociological Association, 1972. Walters, Ronald. "The
Great Plains Sit-in Movement, 1958–60." Great Plains
Quarterly 16 (1996): 85–94.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>