<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ea.031</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Scots</field>
      <field name="author">Sunter, Ronald M.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SCOTS


A woman dancing the Highland fling in Scottish costume, Denver, Colorado, between 1904 and 1910


Frontiersmen of Scottish origin were attracted
to the Great Plains long before the region was
permanently settled by European Americans.
Americans and Canadians of Scottish descent
were among the first to venture into the area,
and if those of Ulster Scots heritage such as Kit
Carson and Davy Crocket are included, the
numbers become still more impressive.

The Hudson's Bay Company and its rivals
for the fur trade recruited much of their
staff either directly from Scotland–particularly
from the Orkney Islands–or from the
largely Highland Scots population of Glengarry
County in eastern Ontario. But the
Hudson's Bay Company did not remunerate
its workers very well, and a considerable number
of dissatisfied former company employees
transferred to the American Fur Company, including
Kenneth McKenzie, the "King of the
Missouri," who presided over the fur trade on
the Northern Great Plains in the 1830s from
his base at Fort Union. The Hudson's Bay
Company continued to actively seek employees
in Scotland until well after World War II,
long after its economic interests had shifted
from the fur trade to land development and
department store investments. Highlanders
were also a major component of the Earl
of Selkirk's Red River Settlement, founded in
1812.

Other Scots who made their mark in the
Great Plains were political refugees such as Allan
Pinkerton, the founder of the well-known
detective agency, who emigrated to North
America as a result of his involvement in radical
politics in Glasgow in 1842. Scottish investors
financed much of the cattle boom of the
1880s in the Great Plains. The Matador Land
and Cattle Company, founded by two Americans
and later sold to a consortium of Dundee
businessmen, was one of the most significant
and long-lasting ranching corporations. Under
the management of Murdo Mackenzie, a
native of Tain, in Rosshire, Matador extended
its operations from Texas to New Mexico,
Oklahoma, Nebraska, South Dakota, Montana,
and Saskatchewan. The Scottish-owned
Matador landholdings in Texas were not broken
up until 1951. Other Scots of note in the
livestock industry included the Eighth Earl of
Airlie, who chaired the Prairie Land and Cattle
Company and the Dundee Land Investment
Company, and John Sutherland Sinclair, a
North Dakota rancher who had emigrated in
1875 at the age of seventeen. It has been estimated
that in the late 1870s and 1880s three-quarters
of all foreign investment in ranching
in America came from Scotland. Scots also invested
in mortgage companies, mining, and
railroads, many of which were also financed in
Scotland.

Scotland provided more than its share of
migrants in the late nineteenth and twentieth
centuries. While an increasing proportion of
these migrants came from urban communities
in lowland Scotland and gravitated to major
cities in the United States and Canada,
many also headed to the Great Plains seeking
land. The Montana writer Ivan Doig, in his
novel Dancing at the Rascal Fair (1987), describes
the emigration of an apprentice wheelwright
and a wheelworks clerk from the Scottish
county of Forfar to "Scotch Heaven"
in northwestern Montana. Doig's Angus Mac-
Caskill and Rob Barclay must have been typical
of many Scots artisans who saw a bright
future in the ownership of land, which was
virtually impossible in Scotland, where the
tenanted farms were rarely offered for sale.
Artisans and skilled farmworkers, who were
numerous in Scotland during the nineteenth
century, often found emigration to the Great
Plains a much more attractive proposition
than the alternatives open to them at home.
They applied the skills learned in their homeland
to stock farming and crop production,
and although new methods of dryland
farming had to be learned, the industrious
producer could hope to make a success as a
landowner in the Great Plains. One of these
emigrants, the South Dakota rancher Scotty
Philip (a native of Auchness, near Lossiemouth),
was instrumental in saving the Plains
bison from extinction.

See also: AGRICULTURE: Ranches / INDUSTRY: McKenzie, Kenneth.


Ronald M. Sunter
University of Guelph




Donaldson, Gordon. The Scots Overseas. London: Robert
Hale, 1966. Jackson, W. Turrentine. The Enterprising Scot: Investors in the American West after 1873. Edinburgh: Edinburgh
University Press, 1968. Pearce, W. M. The Matador Land and Cattle Company. Norman: University of Oklahoma
Press, 1964.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>