<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.gen.009</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Colby, Clara (1846-1916)</field>
      <field name="author">Riedesel, Laureen</field>
      <field name="text">

 




COLBY, CLARA (1846-1916)

Clara Bewick Colby, Nebraska's most prominent
suffragist, was a newspaper editor and
lecturer whose personal commitment to equal
rights resulted in a national career and an international
reputation. Born in England on
August 5, 1846, she emigrated to Wisconsin in
1854. She entered the University of Wisconsin
in 1865 and studied coursework previously offered
only to men. Initially denied the right to
graduate, she was subsequently recognized as
the 1869 class valedictorian and hired as an
instructor by the University of Wisconsin. She
later left that position over a dispute concerning
gender pay equity. In 1872 she married
Leonard Wright Colby and moved to Beatrice,
Nebraska. The couple adopted a three-yearold
boy, Clarence, from an orphan train in
1885. Leonard later (1891) returned from the
Wounded Knee Massacre with a Sioux child
named Zintkala Nuni (Lost Bird) and adopted
her himself while Clara was away lecturing on
suffrage issues. Clara and Leonard Colby were
formally divorced in 1906.

Colby strove to bring culture to her Plains
hometown by establishing a public library and
a community theater. In 1878 she invited suffragists
Elizabeth Cady Stanton and Susan B.
Anthony to lecture in Beatrice. She then began
traveling as a national women's suffrage
speaker. Colby was one of Elizabeth Cady Stanton's
"girls" or "lieutenants." In 1881 she was
one of the organizers of the Women's State
Suffrage Association in Nebraska and served as
its president from 1885 to 1898. In 1883 she
became the editor and publisher of the Woman's Tribune, a national suffrage newspaper she
created to bring events and perspectives to
readers in isolated locations. From 1886 to 1889
the Woman's Tribune was the official publication
of the National Woman Suffrage Association.
In 1888 the newspaper was published in a
daily edition of 12,500 during the International
Council of Women in Washington DC. This
was the first time a daily paper for women had
been edited and published by a woman. Considered
by Susan B. Anthony to be the best
writer of the women's movement, Colby was
Anthony's first choice as a biographer. In 1889
Colby received the first press correspondent's
pass issued to a woman to cover the Spanish-
American War. She was one of the members of
the Revising Committee of the controversial
Woman's Bible, published from 1895 to 1898. In
1904 Colby moved to Oregon to continue suffrage
work there. The Woman's Tribune ceased
publication in 1909, although Colby optimistically
intended to continue when funds became
available.

In the last years of her life, Colby lectured in
Britain and other European locations and
served as a delegate to the International Moral
Education Congress (London, 1908); International
Women Suffrage Alliance (Amsterdam,
1908); International Races Congress (London,
1911); International Woman Suffrage Convention
(Budapest, 1913); and the International
Peace Conference (The Hague, 1913). Clara
Bewick Colby died September 7, 1916, in Palo
Alto, California, four years before the passage
of the Nineteenth Amendment establishing
women's suffrage as law.


Laureen Riedesel
Beatrice Public Library




Brown, Olympia, ed. Democratic Ideals: A Memorial Sketch of Clara B. Colby. Washington DC: Federal Suffrage
Association, 1917. Colby, Clara Bewick. Papers. State Historical
Society of Wisconsin, Madison. Jerry, E. Claire.
"Clara Bewick Colby and the Woman's Tribune, 1883-
1909: The Free Lance Editor as Movement Leader." In A Voice of Their Own: The Woman Suffrage Press, 1840-1910,
edited by Martha M. Solomon. Tuscaloosa: University of
Alabama Press, 1991, 110-28.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>