<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fol.030</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Nicknames</field>
      <field name="author">Callary, Edward</field>
      <field name="text">

 




NICKNAMES

Nicknames have long been especially popular
among two groups: self-promoters and those
who consider themselves beyond the limits of
ordinary rules of conduct. The Plains, especially
in the nineteenth century, was filled with
characters who were self-promoters and had a
disdain for established authority. William F.
Cody was first on the list of self-promoters.
"Buffalo Bill" said it all; a little of the reality of
the Plains and a lot of its myth and folklore is
distilled in this nickname. Less well known
today is his Wild West show rival, Gordon
William Lillie, or "Pawnee Bill."

The great majority of nicknames, however,
went to outlaws such as John Henry "Doc"
Holliday (who was a real "Doc," a dentist
from Georgia). The Doolin Gang (the "Oklahombres")
alone boasted "Dynamite Dan"
Clifton, George "Bitter Creek" Newcomb,
Richard "Little Dick" West, George "Red
Buck" Waightman, and William "Little Bill"
Raidler. Those on the side of the law rarely
had public nicknames; the Earp brothers, the
most famous lawmen of the Plains, did not.
Two who straddled the fence between law and
lawlessness, however, William Barclay "Bat"
Masterson and James Butler "Wild Bill" Hickock,
were best known by their nicknames.

Since early Plains society to a degree was
one of rough equality, it is not surprising that
women used nicknames for the same purposes
as men. Martha Canary was every bit as
much a self-promoter as Buffalo Bill, and she
found that calling herself "Calamity Jane" (ostensibly
because she got mixed up in so much
trouble) did the trick. As with the men, most
of the nicknames of women in the Plains went
to those who, if not exactly criminals, were at
least on the fringes of proper society, especially
the prostitutes and madams. Ella Watson,
who earned her nickname "Cattle Kate"
because she took cattle (often stolen) in payment
for her services, and "Diamond Lil"
Powers, the Denver madam, are two of the
better-known.

Much of the nicknaming in the Plains has
disappeared, but it reminds us that nicknames
are means of creating images and public personae,
and their bearers wear them proudly,
often flaunting society's norms in the process.


Edward Callary
Northern Illinois University





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>