<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.arc.016</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Depression Architecture</field>
      <field name="author">West, Carroll Van</field>
      <field name="text">

 




DEPRESSION ARCHITECTURE

New Deal agencies during the administration
of President Franklin D. Roosevelt reshaped
the public landscape of the Great Plains. From
1933 to 1942 the Federal Emergency Relief Administration
(FERA), the Public Works Administration
(PWA), the Civilian Conservation
Corps (CCC), and the Works Progress
(later Work Projects) Administration (WPA)
placed a federal facade on the region's public
architecture.

Architectural historians identify two primary
substyles associated with New Deal architecture:
Government Rustic, which is associated
with many parks projects of the CCC
and the National Park Service during these decades,
and PWA or WPA Modern, with the designation
depending on the sponsoring agency.

Government Rustic grew out of park designs
based on the natural resources and landscape
of the mountain West and the Adirondacks
of New York. At first glance, the exposed
log beams and rough stonework characteristic
of the style have little association with the rolling
prairies of the Great Plains, but once the
National Park Service in 1938 published its architectural
guides, Park and Recreation Structures and Park Structures and Facilities, Government
Rustic became codified as the only
proper park architecture. Government Rustic
style reflected a close relationship to nature
not only in the materials used in the buildings
but also in how the structures seemingly rose
from the ground themselves, linking the style
to the design ideas and assumptions of master
Prairie school architect Frank Lloyd Wright.
The stone and log interpretive pavilion at the
Double Ditch Village State Historic Site near
Bismarck, North Dakota, is similar in its material
and construction to many other Government
Rustic structures found in the region's
state and federal parks.

County courthouses located throughout
the Plains document the popularity of pwa or
wpa Modern style. In Casper, Wyoming, the
Natrona County Courthouse, designed by
Karl Krusmark and Leon Goodrich, imaginatively
ties together the past and present
by using frontier images and quotations on the
building's modern-styled facade. The Sheridan
County Courthouse in Plentywood, Montana,
is much more restrained in its modern
styling, reflecting both the isolated location of
the county seat and the county's limited financial
means. The New Deal–sponsored courthouses
symbolized more than the federal presence;
they also reminded depressed residents
of the national government's commitment to
the region and the residents' ever-deepening
dependence on the largesse and policies of
the federal government. In this way the courthouses
symbolically confronted the muchprized
independence of westerners because
their commanding presence within the local
townscape ironically spoke more of dependence
than independence.

There was more to the New Deal landscape
of the Plains than new public parks and courthouses.
Post offices, city halls, and community
halls were constructed in many smaller towns;
most of these buildings still serve their original
purpose. Schools were priority projects for
many state FERA agencies; in North Dakota,
for example, FERA built 8 schools and renovated
1,604 others. The PWA and WPA built
hundreds of other schools, often in popular
revival styles. The PWA-sponsored Holmes
School in Lincoln, Nebraska, was in a restrained
Colonial Revival style, while the PWA
school in Fort Scott, Kansas, was a full statement
of Colonial Revival design, complete
with finials, cupola, and Palladian windows.
The WPA school in Kadoka, South Dakota, reflects
a Pueblo Revival design quite out of
place in its Black Hills setting. The popularity
of the revival styles also was evident in
the many new classrooms, libraries, stadiums,
and auditoriums constructed on college and
university campuses. Besides the new education
buildings, the addition of libraries and
community buildings such as the Art Deco.
styled Sonotorium (an outdoor theater) in
Kearney, Nebraska, and the new Art Museum
in Wichita, Kansas, enriched town life.

New Deal agencies also transformed much
of the infrastructure of Plains agriculture, industry,
transportation, and urban services. In
Montana's lower Yellowstone River valley, CCC
work crews improved and expanded existing
irrigation projects of the U.S. Reclamation
Service. Modern bridges, new highways, airports,
sidewalks, and sewage treatment plants
improved urban living. Dam and powerhouse
construction on rivers such as the Colorado,
Missouri, and North Platte improved urban
water supplies, provided more water for irrigation,
and created new sources for electricity.
At some projects, modernity and tradition existed
side by side. The dam and town site at
Fort Peck, Montana, contained a Swiss chalet–
like theater, which is strangely out of place on
the flat, treeless prairie of eastern Montana
and stands in sharp contrast to the modern
concrete and steel spillway of the dam.

Efforts at historic preservation and land
conservation, often in association with park
development, were widespread. At the Chateau
de Mores, a historic house museum in
Medora, North Dakota, WPA-funded employees,
working together with state historical
society officials, cataloged artifacts, furnished
the house, and developed its first interpretive
tours. Land reclamation efforts led by the ccc
created most of the region's initial wildlife reserves
and migratory refuges, expanded existing
shelterbelts while creating many new ones,
and planted trees in reforestation and town
beautification schemes.

The impact of New Deal agencies in the
Great Plains landscape was immense and
long-lasting. The most architecturally imposing
public buildings in many of the region's
towns date to that era, while the reordered
landscapes represented by dam reservoirs,
new parks, and urban infrastructure shape
everyday perceptions and experiences.

See also POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT: New Deal.


Carroll Van West
Middle Tennessee State University




Cutler, Phoebe. The Public Landscape of the New Deal.
New Haven CT: Yale University Press, 1985. Short, C. W.,
and R. Stanley-Brown. Public Buildings: Architecture under the Public Works Administration, 1933 to 1939. Washington
DC: Government Printing Office, 1939. West, Carroll Van.
"'The Best Kind of Building': The New Deal Landscape of
the Northern Plains, 1933-1942." Great Plains Quarterly 14
(1994): 129-41.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>