<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.law.050</field>
      <field name="titleMain">United States v. Sioux Nation of Indians</field>
      <field name="author">Scherer, Mark R.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




UNITED STATES V. SIOUX NATION OF INDIANS

In United States v. Sioux Nation of Indians
(1980), the U.S. Supreme Court held that an
1877 act of Congress, by which the United
States wrested control of the Black Hills of
South Dakota from the Sioux Indian Nation,
constituted a "taking" of property under the
Fifth Amendment, giving rise to an obligation
to fairly compensate the Sioux. The Court affirmed
a prior decision of the court of claims,
which had awarded the Sioux $17.1 million for
the taking of the Black Hills, and further held
that the tribe was entitled to interest on that
amount from 1877. By the late 1990s, the
amount due the Sioux had risen to more than
$600 million–a payment that the tribe still
refuses to accept, choosing instead to continue
to seek the return of the land itself.

The 1980 decision represented the judicial
culmination of more than sixty years of litigation
and lobbying in the Court of Claims, the
Indian Claims Commission, the U.S. Congress,
and the Supreme Court, in which the
Sioux sought retribution for more than a century's
worth of bad faith and fraudulent dealings
relating to the Black Hills. The fundamental
basis for the continuing claim is the
1868 Fort Laramie Treaty, in which the government
pledged that the Great Sioux Reservation,
including the Black Hills, would be
permanently preserved for the "absolute and
undisturbed use and occupation" of the tribe.
The treaty further provided that no change to
the reservation boundaries would be effective
unless approved by at least three-fourths of
the adult male population of the Sioux Nation.
In 1877 Congress enacted a statute that,
in effect, unilaterally abrogated the provisions
of the 1868 treaty. The act codified the terms of
a new treaty, signed under military duress by
only about 10 percent of the adult male Sioux
population, under which the Sioux purportedly
ceded another 7 million acres, including
the Black Hills, to the United States.

Some forty years after losing the Black Hills
under those dubious circumstances, the Sioux
embarked upon a long judicial and legislative
quest for their return. In 1920 they brought
suit in the Court of Claims, alleging that the
government had taken the Black Hills without
just compensation in violation of the Fifth
Amendment. The Court of Claims ultimately
dismissed that claim in 1942, and the Sioux
then reasserted their arguments before the Indian
Claims Commission, beginning in 1946.
The commission held that the 1877 act was in
fact a compensable taking for which the Sioux
were entitled to $17.5 million, without interest.
On appeal, however, the Court of Claims
again dismissed the Sioux claim, holding that
the tribe's arguments were barred by the
Court's 1942 decision. There the matter stood
until 1978, when the Sioux obtained a special
act of Congress authorizing a new review of
the tribe's Black Hills claim without regard to
the earlier decisions of the Court of Claims.
This time the Court of Claims held that the
government had indeed acted in bad faith in
taking the Black Hills and that the Sioux were
entitled to $17.1 million in damages, plus interest
from 1877. When the Supreme Court
affirmed the Court of Claims ruling in 1980,
the Sioux's long decades of legal tenacity were
seemingly vindicated.

Yet even before the Sioux achieved this
monumental Supreme Court victory, controversy
arose within the tribe and between some
members of the tribe and their attorneys over
whether or not a monetary judgment should
even be sought, much less accepted. For growing
numbers of Sioux, monetary compensation
was not acceptable as a resolution of their
claims.only the return of the sacred Black
Hills themselves would suffice. Those sentiments
have controlled subsequent events in
this prolonged drama, and the Sioux continue
to refuse to accept the payment dictated by the
Court's decision.

See also NATIVE AMERICANS: Sioux.


Mark R. Scherer
University of Nebraska at Omaha




Lazarus, Edward. Black Hills, White Justice: The Sioux Nation versus the United States, 1775 to the Present. New York:
HarperCollins, 1991. Pemberton, Richard, Jr. "'I Saw That
It Was Holy': The Black Hills and the Concept of Sacred
Land." Law and Inequality: A Journal of Theory and Practice
3 (1985): 287–311.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>