<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.062</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Pettigrew, Richard (1848-1926)</field>
      <field name="author">Staggers, Kermit L.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




PETTIGREW, RICHARD (1848-1926)

One of the first two U.S. senators from South
Dakota and a successful businessman, Richard
Franklin Pettigrew was born July 23, 1848, in
Ludlow, Vermont, to abolitionist parents who
maintained a station on the Underground Railroad.
When he was young his family moved to
Wisconsin, where he graduated from Evansville
Academy in 1864, attended Beloit College for
two years, and studied law at the University of
Wisconsin.

In 1870 Pettigrew settled in Sioux Falls, Dakota
Territory, where he earned his living as a
surveyor and lawyer before establishing himself
as a prominent real estate broker. During
the next twenty years his business interests expanded
to include railroads, mining, and agriculture.
Politically astute, he was first elected
to the territory's legislature in 1872 as a Republican
and later served on the territorial
council before winning the position of delegate
to the U.S. Congress in 1880.

After South Dakota achieved statehood in
1889, Pettigrew served twelve years in the U.S.
Senate. During his first term in office, the
Panic of 1893 ruined his business investments,
which caused him to abandon his Republican
principles for the lure of populism. He advocated
the issues of free silver and government
regulation of large businesses while personally
attacking Republicans and their positions on
the gold standard and the annexation of Hawaii
and the Philippines. These views eventually
doomed his reelection efforts for a third
term in the Senate. Disgruntled, he moved to
New York City, where he lived for ten years
and amassed another personal fortune before
returning to Sioux Falls. He died on October
5, 1926, leaving to the community his home to
be used as a museum that would preserve the
Pettigrew legacy.


Kermit L. Staggers
University of Sioux Falls




Hendrickson, Kenneth E., Jr. "The Public Career of Richard
F. Pettigrew of South Dakota, 1848–1926." South Dakota
Department of History Report and Historical Collections
34 (1968): 143–311. Pettigrew, Richard Franklin.
Papers. Siouxland Heritage Museums, Sioux Falls SD.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>