<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ind.006</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Automotive</field>
      <field name="author">McConnell, Curt</field>
      <field name="text">

 




Automotive

Never a large industry in the Great Plains, automaking
nonetheless flourished until the 1930s.
The region's small factories often sold directly to
motorists, thereby eliminating transportation
costs and agents' markups, and provided services
unknown in the East: free driving lessons,
lifetime warranties, and sometimes a chance for
customers to help build the car they would own.

Nebraska and Kansas each had half a dozen
companies that saw serious, sustained production
prior to World War II. In Kansas,
Topeka's Smith Automobile Company (1902–
12) sold 1,200 hand-built autos nationally. The
Great Smith's advanced semiautomatic transmission,
built-in icebox, and colorful stunts–
climbing Pikes Peak in a blizzard, driving six
days nonstop on rain-soaked Texas roads–
won it many fans.

The lightly populated Dakotas, Montana,
New Mexico, Oklahoma, and Wyoming saw
little automaking activity. The popular Montana
Special, which sold well in Big Sky Country
from 1911 to 1916, was actually a Minnesota
product. Denver supplied Colorado's bestknown
autos: the Colburn, famed for racing,
and the Fritchle Electric, which Oliver P.
Fritchle advertised widely in 1908 during a
grueling trek over bad roads from Lincoln,
Nebraska, to New York City.

A shift in demand from open to closed cars
and the advent of the moving assembly line
forced automakers to invest more heavily in
machinery, particularly after World War I.
Consolidation marked the 1920s. Except for a
few makers of luxury autos (for whom quality,
not price, was all-important), smaller factories
failed. A few of the region's automakers
survived by producing fire engines, truck bodies,
street cleaners, and other specialty machines.

Now a few large companies dominate the
automobile industry, and manufacturing is
concentrated in Ontario, in the case of Canada,
and in Michigan and Ohio, in the United
States. Great Plains states accounted for just
less than 10 percent of U.S. output in 1996.
General Motors plants in Oklahoma City,
Arlington, Texas (just east of Fort Worth), and
Fairfax, Kansas (northeastern Kansas City)
and the Ford Motor Assembly Plant in Kansas
City, Missouri, are the hubs of the region's
production.

See also TRANSPORTATION: Automobiles.


Curt McConnell
Lincoln, Nebraska




Kimes, Beverly Rae, and Henry Austin Clark Jr. Standard Catalog of American Cars, 1805–1942. Iola WI: Krause Publications,
1989. McConnell, Curt. Great Cars of the Great Plains. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1995. Ward's Automotive Yearbook. Southfield MI: Ward's Communications,
1997.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>