<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.edu.038</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Tribal Colleges</field>
      <field name="author">Braithwaite, Charles A.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




TRIBAL COLLEGES

Thirty-eight tribal colleges across the United
States and Canada enroll 30,000 students from
more than 200 Native American and First Nations
tribes. Tribal colleges are unsurpassed
in their ability to provide the knowledge and
skills Indian students need to become successfully
employed, and their job placement rates
are high. In addition, 42 percent of graduates
from these colleges continue their education
in other postsecondary institutions. Indian
students who transfer from tribal colleges are
four times more likely to complete four-year
degree programs than those who enter mainstream
institutions as freshmen.

Twenty-five tribal colleges are located in the
Great Plains: seven in Montana, five in North
Dakota, four in South Dakota, three in Alberta,
two in Nebraska, two in New Mexico,
one in Kansas, and one in Saskatchewan.
Maskwacis Cultural College in Alberta was the
first tribally controlled college in Canada. In
July 1988 the Legislative Assembly of Alberta
passed the Maskwacis Cultural College Act,
which established the college as a private post-secondary
institution with authority to grant
certification to students at the certificate and
diploma levels. Since then, Maskwacis Cultural
College has grown to offer nine one- and
two-year program certificates and eight bachelor's
degrees. Founded in 1884 as an Indian
boarding school, Haskell Indian Nations
University in Lawrence, Kansas, became the
first federally chartered Indian college in the
United States in 1970. Two tribally controlled
colleges in the Great Plains were founded in
1971: Oglala Lakota College in Kyle, South Dakota,
and Sinte Gleska University in Rosebud,
South Dakota. Most recently, Little Priest
Tribal College was chartered in Winnebago,
Nebraska, in 1996.

In the United States tribal colleges are situated
on land that is considered to be federal
trust territory. This means that individual
states are not required to provide any funding,
making most tribal colleges dependent upon
the federal government's treaty obligation and
trust responsibility to provide education for
Native American tribes. With unemployment
on Native American reservations ranging
from 30 to 70 percent, the greatest challenge
faced by administrators, faculty, staff, and students
at tribal colleges is funding. This is reflected
in the White House Executive Order
on Tribal Colleges and Universities (1998),
which lists increasing core funding for operations
as the first priority for the thirty federal
departments and agencies involved in tribal
college education.

The mission statements of the twenty-five
tribal colleges in the Great Plains stress three
fundamental concepts. First, all of the colleges
focus on the importance of students understanding
their sense of self-identity. For example,
Dull Knife Memorial College in Lame
Deer, Montana, states that the college operates
"in the belief that all individuals should be
treated with dignity and respect." A second
common concept emphasized by tribal colleges
is the preservation and perpetuation of
their Native cultures. Blackfeet Community
College in Browning, Montana, for example,
which serves students from both Montana
and Canada, states that, "most importantly, it
is the mission of Blackfeet Community College
to serve as a living memorial to the Blackfeet
Tribe, in preserving the traditions and
culture of a proud and progressive people."
Finally, tribal colleges stress the importance of
students being able to understand the differences
between Native culture and Western society.
For example, Cankdeska Cikana Community
College in Crow Agency, Montana
(formerly Little Hoop Community College),
states that "the mission of Cankdeska Cikana
Community College is to provide comprehensive
post-secondary education which addresses
both traditional and contemporary aspects
of learning. The College focuses on
educating our students to live successfully by
assisting each in reaching a goal that is desirable
and attainable for their needs in this
multi-cultural world." These examples, or
philosophies, may well explain why tribal colleges
are so successful in educating Native
peoples.


Charles A. Braithwaite
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




American Indian Higher Education Consortium and the
Institute for Higher Education Policy. Tribal Colleges: An
Introduction. Washington DC: Tribal College Research and
Database Initiative, 1999.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>