<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.afam.035</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Pickett, Bill (1870-1932)</field>
      <field name="author">Slatta, Richard W.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




PICKETT, BILL (1870-1932)

Credited with inventing bulldogging (steer
wrestling), Willie M. "Bill" Pickett performed
with Wild West shows and rodeos for several
decades. In recognition of his athletic prowess
and crowd-pleasing abilities, in 1971 he became
the first African American cowboy inducted
into the National Rodeo Cowboy Hall
of Fame in Oklahoma City.

One of thirteen children, Pickett was born
in Travis County, Texas, thirty miles northwest
of Austin. His ancestry was African American,
Caucasian, and Cherokee. Growing up in
rural Texas ranch country, Will, as he was
known in his youth, learned to read brands
and toss a rope. By his own account, one day he
watched a small dog bite a cow's lip and successfully
control the large animal. Pickett decided
that he could do likewise and first demonstrated
his lip-biting technique to a group of
cowboys in 1881.

Pickett worked on various central Texas
ranches during the late 1880s and 1890s. He
married Maggie Turner in 1890 and together
they raised nine children. In partnership with
his brothers, he started the Pickett Brothers
Bronco Busters and Rough Riders Association
in Taylor, Texas, advertising that "We ride and
break all wild horses with much care. Catching
and taming wild cattle a specialty."

During the early 1900s Pickett demonstrated
his toothy bulldogging technique at
county fairs and other gatherings throughout
the Great Plains. In 1904 he performed at
Cheyenne Frontier Days. The following year
Pickett joined the famous Miller Brothers'
101 Ranch Wild West Show. Over the next several
years he performed with Tom Mix, Guy
Weadick, Milt Hinkle, and other Wild West
show stars. Later Pickett estimated that he
bulldogged some 5,000 steers during his long
career.

While working with the 101 outfit, Pickett
became known as Bill rather than Will. Strong,
athletic, compact (five feet seven inches, 145
pounds), and mustachioed, he dressed like a
Spanish bullfighter. The 101 program listed
him as "the Dusky Demon who throws steers
with his teeth." In late 1908 he brashly agreed
to take on a Mexican fighting bull. The bull
gored both Pickett and his prized mount
Spradley, one of several times that Pickett was
injured.

In the 1920s Pickett mostly retired from
competitive bulldogging but continued to
give exhibitions. He starred in a few Western
movies that showcased his rodeo feats. Pickett
returned to work for Zack Miller and continued
to break horses. His wife's death in
March 1929 devastated Pickett, but he continued
to work on the Miller ranch. He died at
the 101 Ranch on April 2, 1932, after being
kicked in the head by a horse. Miller's eulogy
aptly summarized Pickett's achievements as
the "greatest sweat and dirt cowhand that ever
lived–bar none."

See also FILM: 
Miller Brothers / 
IMAGES AND ICONS: Wild West Shows.



Richard W. Slatta
North Carolina State University




Hanes, Bailey C. Bill Pickett: Bulldogger. Norman: University
of Oklahoma Press, 1977, 1989. Johnson, Cecil. Guts:
Legendary Black Rodeo Cowboy Bill Pickett. Fort Worth:
Summit Group, 1994. Russell, Don. The Wild West: A History
of the Wild West Shows. Fort Worth: Amon Carter
Museum, 1970.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>