<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.sr.038</field>
      <field name="titleMain">National Forests</field>
      <field name="author">Zinser, Charles I.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




NATIONAL FORESTS

The geographical extent of the National Forest
System in the Great Plains is approximately
equally divided between land designated as
national forest and as national grassland. The
national grasslands occur in semiarid environments
that are characteristic of the greater
portion of the Great Plains. With the exception
of the two national forests in Nebraska,
the national forests occur in areas of higher
elevation, including many uplifted mountain
ranges, where a cooler and more humid climate
prevails.

Only three national forests are totally within
the Great Plains: the Black Hills National
Forest (South Dakota, Wyoming); the Nebraska
National Forest (Nebraska); and
the Samuel R. McKelvie National Forest (Nebraska).
All of the Custer National Forest
(South Dakota, Montana) is in the Great
Plains except for the portion in the Middle
Rockies west of Red Lodge, Montana, and another
portion west of the Bighorn National
Recreation Area, Montana. Approximately
half of the Lewis and Clark National Forest
(Montana) is found in mountainous uplifts
that are surrounded by the Great Plains: the
Big Snowy Mountains, the Highwood Mountains,
and the Little Belt Mountains. The other
part of the Lewis and Clark National Forest is
located where the Great Plains end and the
Northern Rocky Mountains rise to the Continental
Divide. Almost half of the Helena
National Forest (Montana), in the Big Belt
Mountains east of Helena, and a portion of
the Gallatin National Forest (Montana), in the
Bridger Range and Crazy Mountains northeast
of Bozeman, are also within the Great
Plains. The three national forests wholly within
the Great Plains and the parts of the other
four that are within the Great Plains total
about 4 million acres, a very small percentage
of the 187 million acres in the 155 national
forests found across the entire nation.

Many people are surprised to learn that the
seventeen national grasslands that cover 3.8
million acres in the Great Plains are part of the
National Forest System. This represents 95 percent
of the total acreage classified in this category
in the twenty national grasslands of the
National Forest System. Originally, many of
these grassland areas were plowed for farming,
but because of poor soil, recurrent drought,
and other factors, they were eroded and were
purchased by the federal government during
the 1930s and early 1940s and taken out of
cultivation. They were managed by the Soil
Conservation Service from 1938 through 1953.
Through proper management, the grasslands
were largely revegetated. A large portion of this
land was transferred to the states and nonfederal
and other federal agencies. The remaining
land was designated by the secretary
of agriculture as national grasslands, and in
1953 the Forest Service was charged with administering
them. In 1960 an administrative
order designated 3,804,000 acres as nineteen
national grasslands.

Black Hills National Forest covers 1.25 million
acres in western South Dakota and adjacent
eastern Wyoming. It extends across much
of the Black Hills uplift dome. The plains surrounding
the Black Hills have altitudes of
3,000 to 3,500 feet, compared with an altitude
of 7,242 feet for Harney Peak, the highest
point in the United States east of the Rocky
Mountains. From a historic lookout tower on
the summit of Harney Peak, one has a panoramic
view of parts of South Dakota, Nebraska,
Wyoming, and Montana as well as the
granite formations and cliffs of the 10,000-acre
Black Elk Wilderness, a unit of the National
Wilderness Preservation System. Numerous
caves, including Wind Cave National
Park, are located on the limestone plateau that
immediately surrounds the central crystalline
core of the Black Hills. Two scenic byways
providing access to the forest are the Peter
Norbeck (70 miles) and Spearfish Canyon
(twenty miles). The Forest Service provides
more than 100 developed recreation sites.
There are more than 600 miles of trails open
to hikers, mountain bikers, cross-country
skiers, snowmobilers, and horse and motorbike
riders. Mount Rushmore National Memorial
is surrounded by the national forest.

The Nebraska National Forest (142,000
acres) and Samuel R. McKelvie National Forest
(116,000 acres) include the only human-planted
forests in the National Forest System.
The Nebraska National Forest consists of two
different sections separated by 150 air miles.
In central Nebraska in the Sandhills is the
human-planted Bessey District. In northwest
Nebraska naturally occurring ponderosa pine
is found in the Pine Ridge District, which occupies
the north-facing Pine Ridge Escarpment.
Seventy miles north of the Bessey
District in the Sandhills of north-central Nebraska
is the Samuel R. McKelvie National Forest.
Developed recreation facilities in the two
national forests are primarily in the Bessey
District. Visitors seeking a developed campground
or lodging in the Pine Ridge District
are well served by adjacent Chadron State Park,
Nebraska&#129;fs first state park. There is a small
campground in the Samuel R. McKelvie National
Forest at Steer Creek. The 9,600-acre
Soldier Creek Wilderness Area in the Pine
Ridge District is one of only two units of the
National Wilderness Preservation System in
Nebraska (the other is at Fort Niobrara National
Wildlife Refuge). Also in the Pine Ridge
District, south of the Soldier Creek Wilderness
Area, is the Pine Ridge National Recreation
Area. Horseback riding is a popular activity in
both the wilderness and national recreation
areas. The same forest supervisor in Chadron,
Nebraska, who is responsible for the administration
of the Nebraska and Samuel R. Mc-Kelvie
National Forests is also responsible for
administering three national grasslands: the
Oglala National Grassland (94,480 acres) located
west of Chadron in northwestern Nebraska;
the Buffalo Gap National Grassland
(595,538 acres) in southwestern South Dakota;
and the Fort Pierre National Grassland (115,997
acres) located south of Pierre in central South
Dakota.

The 1.3 million–acre Custer National Forest
extends in a scattered pattern of over 300 miles
from northwestern South Dakota to southcentral
Montana. Much of the forest is surrounded
by rolling prairie and farmland. In
the Sioux Ranger District in southeastern
Montana and the northwestern corner of
South Dakota, the eight separate units of federal
land are often described as islands of green
in a sea of rolling prairie. These national forestlands
are hills or mesas covered with ponderosa
pine. Two significant National Natural
Landmarks are located in this district: the Castles,
a massive limestone uplift that resembles
a medieval castle; and Capitol Rock, a white
limestone uplift that resembles the nation's
capitol. To the west, still in southeastern Montana,
is the Ashland Ranger District, which has
the largest grazing program of any national
forest ranger district. The area is rich in coal
and wildlife.

Four national grasslands are administered
by the Custer National Forest. The 1,028,051-acre
Little Missouri National Grassland in
western North Dakota is the largest and most
diverse national grassland in the United States.
The grassland surrounds the Theodore Roosevelt
National Park and consists of rolling prairie
and spectacular badlands scenery. The Little
Missouri National Grassland also contains
the largest free-roaming herd of elk in North
Dakota as well as the only herd of bighorn
sheep, excellent populations of sharp-tailed
grouse, numerous archaeological sites, and
rich dinosaur fossil beds. This is cattle and oil
and gas country. Trail riding, hiking, and big
game and bird hunting are popular recreation
activities. The Sheyenne National Grassland
(70,268 acres), in the extreme southeastern
corner of North Dakota, is composed of rolling
sand dunes vegetated by tall prairie grass
and contains the largest population of prairie
chickens in the state. The Cedar River National
Grassland (6,717 acres) is located in southern
North Dakota along the South Dakota border
west of the Standing Rock Indian Reservation,
and the Grand River National Grassland
(155,075 acres) is located in northwestern
South Dakota along the North Dakota border.
They are composed of rolling mixed-grass
prairie, some badlands, and river bottoms.
The Canadian goose is common to this area,
and pheasant, sharp-tailed grouse, other waterfowl,
antelope, and mule and white-tailed
deer are also hunted. The grasslands provide
important seasonal forage for livestock.

The 1.8 million.acre Lewis and Clark National
Forest is scattered over seven separate
mountain ranges in west-central Montana.
Almost half of this national forest is in the
Rocky Mountain Division, which is located
outside of the Great Plains. The six remaining
mountain ranges, in the Jefferson Division of
the forest, spring from the surrounding prairie
lands, creating a majestic rise in the flattened
agricultural landscape. The Highwood,
Little Belt, Castle, Big Snowy, Little Snowy,
and northern portions of the Crazy Mountains
are included in this division.

The Thunder Basin National Grassland
(571,971 acres) is located in the Powder River
Basin of northeastern Wyoming and administered
by the Douglas Ranger District of the
Medicine Bow–Routt National Forests. Almost
all of the grassland provides forage for
livestock. The ancient sediments below the
surface contain enormous coal, oil, and gas
reserves; other resources include uranium and
bentonite, a type of clay mineral with many
uses. Six surface coal mines operate on the
Thunder Basin National Grassland; the Black
Thunder is the largest surface coal mine in
North America. There are diverse recreational
activities but no developed campgrounds and
no potable water.

There are two national grasslands in
Colorado–the 435,319-acre Comanche National
Grassland in the southeast and the 193,060-acre
Pawnee National Grassland in the northeast.
and one in Kansas–the 108,175-acre
Cimarron National Grassland. These national
grasslands are administered as ranger districts
of the Pike.San Isabel National Forests. The
Comanche National Grassland is located in
two separate units–the Timpas Unit near La
Junta and the Carrizo Unit near Springfield.
The Comanche is characterized by diverse and
often spectacular landscapes, ranging from
short and midgrass prairies to deep canyons
and arroyos branching off the Cimarron and
Purgatoire River valleys. The land is managed
for many natural and cultural resources, including
wildlife, recreation, water, livestock,
and minerals as well as for the protection of
archaeological, historic, and paleontological
resources. Wagon ruts of the Mountain Route
of the Santa Fe Trail may be observed in many
locations. A wealth of paleontological, prehistoric,
and historic sites can be experienced
at the Picket Wire Canyonlands, which were
added to the Comanche in 1991. There, along
the banks of the Purgatoire River, is found one
of the largest known trackways of dinosaur
footprints in the world.

The Pawnee National Grassland is located
in two units, one thirty miles east of Fort Collins
and the other on the Wyoming border
twenty miles northeast of Greeley. Photographers,
bird-watchers, and hikers will find the
Pawnee Buttes, in the East Unit of the grassland,
an interesting landmark. The buttes are
sedimentary rock formations, half a mile
apart, rising 350 feet above the Plains. The
cliffs in this area are a preferred nesting area
for many birds of prey. The Crow Valley Recreation
Area, in the West Unit, is the only
camping facility in the Pawnee.

The Cimarron National Grassland, the
largest parcel of public land in Kansas, is a
midgrass prairie and is located in the extreme
southwestern corner of the state. Rock cliffs,
cottonwood groves, grassy fields, yucca, and
sagebrush are scattered throughout the rolling
to hilly land. There are ten fishing ponds, hiking
trails, three picnic areas, and one campground.
Also located on the Cimarron National
Grassland are twenty-three miles of the
historic Santa Fe Trail, the longest portion of
the trail with public access. Oil and gas is being
produced from twenty-three fields within
the grassland. The White Arrow Travel Management
System restricts motor vehicle travel
in and along the Cimarron River corridor. It is
designed to decrease the amount of resource
damage caused by motorized vehicles, to preserve
wildlife habitat along the river, and to
protect the soil.

The Kiowa (New Mexico), Rita Blanca
(Texas, Oklahoma), McClelland Creek (Texas),
and Black Kettle (Oklahoma, Texas) National
Grasslands are administered by the Cibola National
Forest, with forest headquarters in Albuquerque,
New Mexico. The first two are operated
out of the Clayton Ranger District in
Clayton, New Mexico, and the latter two are
operated out of the Black Kettle Ranger District
in Cheyenne, Oklahoma. The Kiowa National
Grassland (136,417 acres) consists of two discontinuous
areas in northeastern New Mexico. The
westernmost of these two sections includes fifteen
miles of the Canadian River Canyon, an
800-foot-deep canyon that forms a wildlife island
for mountain lions, wild turkey, bald and
golden eagles, mule deer, antelope, bear, Barbary
sheep, and waterfowl. The one developed
recreation site in the Kiowa National Grassland
is the Mills Canyon Campground. There are still
two miles of wagon ruts visible along a portion
of the Cimarron Cutoff of the Santa Fe Trail.
The Rita Blanca National Grassland (92,989
acres) straddles the border in the extreme
southwestern corner of the Oklahoma Panhandle
and the extreme northwestern corner of the
Texas Panhandle. The two developed recreation
areas in the Rita Blanca are the Thompson
Grove Picnic Area in Texas and the Felt Picnic
Area in Oklahoma. The McClelland Creek National
Grassland (1,449 acres) is located midway
between Amarillo and the Oklahoma border in
the Texas Panhandle and has the distinction of
being the smallest national grassland in the
country. Its central feature is 350-acre Lake
McClelland, with facilities for water sports, fishing,
and camping. The Black Kettle National Grassland
(31,286 acres) is almost entirely in western
Oklahoma, except for a 575-acre tract that surrounds
63-acre Lake Marvin in the Texas Panhandle.
There are two camping areas at Lake
Marvin. Most of the other recreational use in
the grassland takes place at Dead Indian, Skipout,
and Spring Creek Lakes in Oklahoma.

The Caddo National Grassland (17,784
acres) and Lyndon B. Johnson National Grassland
(20,309 acres) are located in north-central
Texas, north and northeast of the Dallas-Fort
Worth metropolitan area. They are sparsely
forested and provide grazing lands for privately
owned livestock. They also provide recreation
areas and lakes, hunting and fishing,
and habitat for wildlife. Oil and gas wells are a
common sight on the grasslands. The Caddo
National Grassland contains three lakes, two of
which have developed recreation sites. The one
developed recreation area in the Lyndon B.
Johnson National Grassland is at Black Creek
Lake. The National Forests in Texas administer
these national grasslands from the supervisor's
office in Lufkin, Texas. The National Grassland
Ranger District is located in Decatur, Texas.

See also PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT: Badlands; Black Hills.

U.S. Forest Service website.


Charles I. Zinser
Plattsburgh State University




Zinser, Charles I. Outdoor Recreation: United States National
Parks, Forests and Public Lands. New York: John
Wiley and Sons, 1995.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>