<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.rel.045</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Sheldon, Charles (1857-1946)</field>
      <field name="author">Allen, Richard</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SHELDON, CHARLES (1857-1946)

Born February 26, 1857, at Wellsville, New
York, son of a poor congregational preacher,
Charles Monroe Sheldon was the author of
some thirty Christian social novels, including
In His Steps (1897), a phenomenally successful
instructional novel. His latter youth was
spent in the Dakotas. Subsequently educated
at Brown University and Andover Theological
Seminary, he ministered at Waterbury, Vermont,
for two years before accepting a call to
Central Congregational Church in Topeka,
Kansas (1889), where he remained for the rest
of his life.

Sheldon began writing in his teens and seems
never to have stopped. At Central Church he
delivered Sunday evening serial sermons dealing
in a fictional manner with the challenge to
church and society of a host of contemporary
ills: unemployment, poverty, the alienation of
upper and lower classes, exploitation by landlords,
racial discrimination, the menace of the
liquor trade, sensationalism in the media, corruption
at city hall, labor extremists and radical
nostrums, hypocrisy in the churches, and the
failure of philanthropy and the gospel of wealth
to cure an ailing world. First published by installment
in religious magazines and then as
full novels, Sheldon's works reflected his own
unceasing activism as a social reformist minister.
He made an indelible impact, bringing
the larger world of Christian social reform
to Topeka and the Great Plains and making
the region's single most important contribution
to the popular Christian social movement
that was at the core of early-twentieth-century
progressivism.

In His Steps was the best-seller among a
growing genre of Christian social novels welling
up out of the 1870s and 1880s, whose success
owed much to the widespread Protestant
proscription of reading secular fiction but
probably owed more to the anxiety among
middle- and upper-class Protestants in the face
of dramatic social changes undermining both
their sense of community and their sense of
social control. Entirely unsophisticated in plot,
characterization, theology, or social analysis,
the novels prescribed a simple, enduring formula:
"What would Jesus do?" Sheldon presented
the resulting encounter of upper- and
middle-class Protestants with working-class
America in unabashedly sentimental and
melodramatic terms that touched the consciences
of millions.

Sheldon gave no sign of the radical Christian
socialism of George Herron in Iowa or
W. D. P. Bliss in Boston, with whom he, however,
had considerable contact, and he seems
not to have recognized the strain of labor
Christianity among labor leaders like Eugene
Debs, although he saw more potential in the
working class than was normally allowed in
midcentury Christian novels. Like his counterpart
best-selling western Canadian Christian
social novelist Ralph Connor (Rev. C. W.
Gordon), Sheldon's locus of social progress lay
in changing the hearts of persons of standing,
which linked him in certain ways with the
contemporary revivalism of Dwight Moody.
Sheldon died in Topeka on February 24, 1946,
after a long, active retirement increasingly
focused on the cause of world peace.

See also LITERARY TRADITIONS: Gordon, Charles W.


Richard Allen
Hamilton, Ontario




Boyer, Paul S. "In His Steps: A Reappraisal." American
Quarterly 23 (Apr. 1971): 60–78. Ferré, John P. A Social
Gospel for Millions: The Religious Bestsellers of Charles
Sheldon, Charles Gordon, and Harold Bell Wright. Bowling
Green OH: Bowling Green State University Press, 1988.
Miller, Timothy. Following in His Steps. A Biography of
Charles M. Sheldon. Knoxville: University of Tennessee
Press, 1987.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>