<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pe.021</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Coyotes</field>
      <field name="author">Thomas, Phillip Drennon</field>
      <field name="text">

 




COYOTES

"Coyote at Ridgefield National Wildlife Refuge, 2008" by Rebecca Richardson


The most opportunistic of all North American
predators, the coyote (Canis laterans) was familiar
to Native Americans, early travelers, and
settlers in the Great Plains. Their characteristic
yip and resonant howling earned them the title
"song dog of the prairie." Figuring prominently
in the religious traditions of the Plains
Indians, the coyotes of the Great Plains were
observed by Lewis and Clark, who termed
them the "prairie wolf." Thomas Say of the
Stephen Long expedition in 1823 provided
more specific information on this ubiquitous
western animal and gave it its scientific name.

Smaller in size than its relative the wolf,
coyotes usually weigh between eighteen and
thirty pounds, are born in litters of five to
seven pups, and live up to eighteen years. They
are remarkably adaptable animals that can live
in almost any environment. As native fauna
was reduced through settlement and as domesticated
animals were raised in the Great
Plains, the omnivorous coyote began to prey
upon the chickens, pigs, cattle, and sheep of
the emerging farms and ranches. Coyote predation
became a problem for European American
settlers, and the resources of local, state,
and federal government were called upon to
address this problem. In the latter half of the
nineteenth century, state bounties were placed
on coyotes. Trappers hunted, poisoned, and
trapped them, but there was only limited success
in reducing their numbers. Coyotes remain
as one of the most persistent and distinctive
members of the fauna of the Great
Plains.


Phillip Drennon Thomas
Wichita State University




Leydet, François. The Coyote: Defiant Songdog of the West.
Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1977. Van Wormer,
Joe. The World of the Coyote. Philadelphia: J. B. Lippincott
Company, 1964.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>