<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.arc.052</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Volga German Architecture</field>
      <field name="author">Koop, Michael H.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




VOLGA GERMAN ARCHITECTURE

Volga German folk buildings represent an unusual
synthesis of central European and Russian
building forms and construction methods.
Not unlike the Black Sea German settlers
in the Great Plains, the Volga River immigrants
relied upon homeland prototypes in
the development of a distinctive architectural
heritage.

The first permanent houses built by Volga
Germans in Russia, called semelanka, were
built according to an official plan devised by
the Colonists Welfare Office. The characteristic
semelanka was a two- and often threeroom
dwelling of one story with a gable roof
and central chimney. The gable end faced the
street, and the entrance to the house was along
the side facing the courtyard. The semelanka
was later replaced with the more spacious
kolonistenhaus, a long, narrow house that
combined both living quarters and barns under
a single roof. The kolonistenhaus was
characteristically tripartite in plan but two
rooms deep and with space for six or more
rooms.

Volga Germans throughout the Plains region
and especially in Kansas and Nebraska
built both the one- and one-and-one-halfstory
rectangular four-room with central
chimney house they had known in Russia. The
Volga preference for the hipped roof is also
evident in their houses, although the gableroofed
variant is common as well. Although
Volga Germans in the Great Plains used construction
materials similar to those used by
Black Sea Germans such as batsa (sun-dried
bricks made from puddled clay), Volga builders
in Colorado, Kansas, and Nebraska also
used limestone when available. Both log and
stone had been common building materials in
Russia.

In addition to expressing their traditional
preferences through house form and use of
materials, Volga Germans also demonstrated
their cultural identity in urban areas by establishing
compact villages with gridlike street
patterns. In the South Bottoms neighborhood
of Lincoln, Nebraska, existing lots were subdivided,
resulting in an extremely compact
settlement of narrow parcels. The long, narrow
lots facilitated the construction of traditional
houses oriented with their gables facing
the street. When settlers in Marion County,
Kansas, laid out the town of Gnadenau, the
land was divided into twenty narrow parcels,
each containing sixteen acres. Four sections
surrounding the village were also divided
among the twenty village settlers. A single
east-west road bisected the village, and all
houses were constructed on the north side of
the road. Despite having a church, several
stores, and two schools, the village was disbanded
a few years later. Although the Kansas
village failed, it nevertheless represents efforts
by Volga Germans to maintain a strong sense
of community and, more important, to resist
change and slow assimilation into mainstream
American society.

See also EUROPEAN AMERICANS: 
German Russians.


Michael H. Koop
Minnesota Historical Society




Petersen, Albert J. "The German-Russian House in Kansas:
A Study in Persistence of Form." Pioneer America 8
(1976): 19–27.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>