<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.wat.040</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Wild and Scenic Rivers</field>
      <field name="author">Haas, Dan</field>
      <field name="text">

 




WILD AND SCENIC RIVERS

In 1968 the U.S. Congress created the National
Wild and Scenic Rivers System. Intended to
protect selected rivers exhibiting "outstandingly
remarkable" values, the Wild and Scenic
Rivers Act declared, "the established national
policy of dam and other construction . . .
needs to be complemented by a policy that
would preserve other selected rivers . . . in
their free-flowing condition to protect the water
quality . . . and to fulfill other vital conservation
purposes." Federal agencies and others
involved in river conservation have long debated
whether the intent of Congress was to
establish a system that would protect only a
few "crown jewel" rivers, or whether rivers
representing all physiographic regions of the
country and all various river types should be
included. Whatever the congressional intent,
what cannot be overlooked is that few of the
rivers of the Great Plains have received this
unique protection since 1968. Through 1998,
only parts of three rivers–the Upper Missouri
in Montana, the Missouri between South Dakota
and Nebraska, and the Niobrara in Nebraska–have
been included in the National
Wild and Scenic Rivers System.

This lack of wild and scenic river designations
is an indicator of socioeconomic values
rather than a reflection on the quality of rivers
in the Great Plains. Wild and scenic rivers tend
to be concentrated in areas where there is a
great deal of public land–for example, Alaska
and the Pacific Northwest–where concerns
over impacts on private lands are less pronounced.
This is not to say, however, that rivers
of the Great Plains are less deserving of inclusion
in the National Wild and Scenic Rivers
System. In January 1982, the National Park Service
released the Nationwide Rivers Inventory
that identified rivers that, at first inspection,
were potentially eligible for designation.
Through this and subsequent revisions, more
than fifty rivers within the Great Plains have
been identified as deserving further study or
consideration as wild and scenic rivers.

The designated wild and scenic rivers in the
Great Plains, and those listed on the Nationwide
Rivers Inventory, are generally characterized
by abundant plant and animal species diversity
due to the presence of water and travel
corridors. Humans were also drawn to Great
Plains rivers: the designated rivers have important
cultural and historical significance,
such as the route of Lewis and Clark along the
Missouri River and the cultural landscape of
ranching along the Niobrara River. It should
be noted, however, that human impacts are
not readily apparent within the designated
boundaries of these rivers; they were designated
in large part because they represent presettlement
conditions.

Canada also has a national rivers program.
Established in 1984, the Canadian Heritage
Rivers System is a cooperative program, developed
and run by the federal, provincial, and
territorial governments. As established, the
program has little regulatory authority, instead
relying on the foresight and good intentions of
the involved governments. The objectives of
the program are to give national recognition
to Canada's outstanding rivers and to ensure
long-term management and conservation of
their natural, cultural, historical, and recreational
values. None of the Prairie Provinces'
rivers has received Heritage River designation
to date.

See also PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT: Niobrara Ecotone.


Dan Haas
National Park Service




Coyle, Kevin J. The American Rivers Guide to Wild and
Scenic River Designation: A Primer on National River Conservation.
Washington DC: American Rivers, 1988. Interagency
Wild and Scenic Rivers Coordinating Council.
Wild and Scenic Rivers Reference Guide. Washington DC:
U.S. Departments of the Interior and Agriculture, 1997.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>