<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ind.059</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Uranium Mining</field>
      <field name="author">Amundson, Michael A.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




URANIUM MINING

Several Great Plains states have been home to
uranium production since 1945. Beginning in
1947, the Atomic Energy Commission offered
government subsidies, including guaranteed
prices and discovery bonuses, to stimulate uranium
production for America's cold war defense.
A uranium rush ensued, and claims were
staked throughout the region. Successful
mines and processing mills near Edgemont
and Pine Ridge, South Dakota, and the Wyoming
towns of Shirley Basin, Jeffrey City, and
Douglas produced and sold uranium concentrate,
or yellowcake, to the federal government.
The program was so successful, however, that
supply exceeded government demand, and the
industry collapsed in the late 1960s.

Following the close of the government program,
the energy crisis of the 1970s fueled the
expansion of nuclear power plants and created
another uranium boom. This time, the mills
at Edgemont, Jeffrey City, and Shirley Basin
produced yellowcake for commercial power
companies. But after environmental fears following
the Three Mile Island accident in
March 1979 stopped further nuclear generator
construction, the industry again collapsed,
and most mines and mills were closed by 1985.
Since then, the new and comparably inexpensive
extraction technique of in situ mining,
during which solvents are pumped directly
into the underground ore body, allowed to
dissolve and leach out the uranium, and then
pumped back to the surface, has made Nebraska
one of the leading uranium-producing
states in the country. Uranium mining is still
active in Saskatchewan, but the mines are located
to the north of the Plains portion of that
province.

Although comparatively little uranium is
currently produced in the Great Plains, former
uranium mines and mill sites face costly
environmental remediation and continuing
maintenance and radiation checks.


Michael A. Amundson
Northern Arizona University




Albrethsen, Holger, and Frank E. McGinley. Summary History of Domestic Uranium Procurement under U.S. Atomic Energy Commission Contracts: Final Report. Grand
Junction CO: U.S. Department of Energy, 1982.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>