<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pe.057</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Soils</field>
      <field name="author">Lewis, David</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SOILS

Soil is the product of the weathering action of
climate and biological organisms on the parent
material as modified by the topography of
the site and the time the parent material has
been in place. Parent materials are those geologic
deposits that have remained stable long
enough for a soil to form in them. In the
Plains, parent materials are for the most part
medium textured and calcareous. Plains soils
formed under forest and later under grasses.
Most upland soils are old enough for weathering
to have formed soil horizons in the upper
meter of the parent material. Humus content
is normally higher in soils of the Northern
Plains than in those farther south; this is associated
with soil temperature gradients. Lime
tends to exist at a more shallow depth in soils
of the drier western Plains than in those of the
eastern Plains, if all else is equal. In addition
High Plains soils tend to contain as much as
60 percent volcanic ash. Topography affects
the microclimate of the site and often affects
age and ultimately the soil that is forming
there. If the condition of all of the interacting
factors is known, it is possible to predict soil
conditions at any given site.

 Classification systems are used to name
soils. The United States currently classifies soil
with six levels of abstraction: order, suborder,
great group, subgroup, family, and series. In
Canada the same number of levels are used but
with a slightly different approach: order, great
group, subgroup, family, series, and type. The
U.S. system recognizes "type" but considers it
to be a phase of a series rather than a separate
taxonomic level. Families in the U.S. system
are defined on criteria such as particle size
class, mineralogy, temperature groups, and
several others. Canadian soils are all "frigid" by
the U.S. family designation, because their average
temperature at twenty inches is less than
46ºF. Mesic and thermic categories (46-59ºF
and greater than 59ºF, respectively) are characteristic
of the Southern Plains. Differences in
the two classification systems are not great
enough to interfere seriously with field operations
along the forty-ninth parallel, and both
serve their purposes well.

The archetypal Plains soil is classified as an
Ustoll in the United States and a Chernozemic
soil (Boroll in the United States) in Canada.
Chernozemic soils (Borolls) formed in association
with tall to short prairie grasses in a
semiarid climate and in a temperature zone
where the average annual soil temperature is
between 32ºF and 49ºF. For example, a soil in
the Elstow series in the Prairie Provinces is in
the Chernozemic order, Dark Brown great
group, Eluviated subgroup, Elstow series, and
Elstow loam type. No family is identified. A
similar soil in the United States is the Holdrege
Series, which falls in the fine silty mixed
mesic family, Typic subgroup, Argiustoll great
group, Ustoll suborder, and Mollisol order.

Sand fields (dunes and sand sheets), as well
as alluvial-colluvial deposits, also exist in many
parts of the region. Soils on these deposits are
very recent and are classified in the same order
(Entisols) to recognize their lack of development.
These sandy soils (Psamments) tend to
be very low in the organic agents that bind soil
particles together into aggregates. This, and
the constant bombardment of sand-size particles
at the surface, causes sand particles to dislodge
and blow in the wind if they are exposed.
Southwest Kansas, the Oklahoma and Texas
Panhandles, southeastern and northeastern
Colorado, and northeastern New Mexico are
at risk of this. By far the largest area threatened,
however, is the Sandhills region of Nebraska.
Roughly one-third of the state consists of
aeolian sand that is currently mobile in certain
areas and is in delicate balance with its current
grass vegetation and the "blow out" areas that
continually form. During the 1930s–the longest
drought in the Plains in recent time–as
much as one-half the topsoil was lost from
more than 20 million acres of Plains land.
Considering parent material, topography, and
soil age, in the windy climate of the Plains,
wind erosion is a significant and continuing
hazard.

The soils of the Plains can be very productive
in most areas if there is water to irrigate
them and if accepted erosion-control
measures are practiced. Minimum tillage and
windbreaks are very useful in this respect. Nitrogen
fertilizer is needed for the high crop
yields expected, but natural levels are more
than adequate for the range grasses that cover
large parts of the region. Organic matter has
declined, but its condition is such that the
amounts remain adequate on the siltier soils,
at least. Shortages of elements such as phosphorus,
zinc, and sulfur are critical for cropland
in some areas because of the low acidity
of the soils. If they are carefully managed and
treated as part of a fragile ecosystem, the
soils of the Great Plains can continue to supply
a large part of the earth's food supply for
generations.


David Lewis
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Department of the Interior. Soil Working Group on the
Ogallala Aquifer. Missouri Basin-Great Plains Caucus.
Washington DC: Government Printing Office, 1980: 2-11.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>