<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fol.006</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Chinook Stories</field>
      <field name="author">Morris, Peter S.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CHINOOK STORIES

A dry, westerly wind, the adiabatically warmed
chinook blows down the eastern face of the
Rocky Mountains onto the adjacent foothills
and plains. While capable of blowing any season
of the year, the chinook's presence is most
salient during the winter, when its relative
warmth provides a stark contrast to frigid
continental-polar air masses. Its ability to melt
and sublimate away thick coverings of snow in
a matter of days or even hours has led to the
common but apocryphal story that chinook is
an "Indian" word for "snow eater." In fact, the
Great Plains chinook owes its name to the Pacific
Northwest fur trade, where a vaguely similar
westerly breeze flowed up the lower Columbia
River from the vicinity of the Chinook
Indian villages; British Canadian and American
settlers transplanted the chinook name
first to the interior Columbia Plain and then,
by the 1880s, to the northwestern Great Plains.

The dramatic changes in winter weather the
chinook can bring have made it the inspiration
of regional folklore and imagery. Frances
Fraser, for example, recounts a Blackfoot story
of a boy who gained status among his band by
freeing the wind from the custody of the bear
in the mountains: "[E]ver since then, the snow
can be deep, and the cold bitter, but, in a short
while, the Chinook will come blowing over the
mountains, and everyone is happy again." The
first white settlers likewise celebrated the chinook,
making its snow-removing capabilities
the stuff of regional environmental legend.
Among the frontier yarns that were spun was
the story of the man who hitched his team of
horses to a post one snowy evening only to
awake the next morning to find his horses dangling
from the church steeple. Another oftentold
story describes a horse-drawn sleigh racing
a chinook home: as the horses struggled
through chest-deep snow, the front runners of
the sleigh sloshed through mud while the back
runners kicked up dust. Another variant of this
story has the man driving the sleigh in front
suffering frostbite while his children in back
catch sunstroke. More than just a source of
amusement, Plains ranchers touted the chinook's
snow-removing capabilities as an ally
that made available nutritious winter grasses
to tender-snouted cattle, thus reducing–or
eliminating, as some mistakenly believed—the
need for cut hay and winter shelter. The brutal
winter of 1886–87 tragically demonstrated that
such wishful thinking was naive. As the region's
open-range herds were decimated by
blizzard conditions, ranchers cast a yearning
eye toward the western mountains, sentiments
which the Yellowstone Journal and Live Stock Reporter captured in a short ad: "WANTED–A
rip-roaring, snow-eating, polar-paralyzing
chinook. . . . Must have it!" Later, the winter of
1885–87 would be eulogized by Montana cowboy
artist Charles M. Russell in a simple sketch
of a rib-exposed steer called "Waiting for a
Chinook."

While its effects are not entirely benign,
with property-damaging gusts that can desiccate
and erode farmers' soils, the chinook
continued to be celebrated throughout the
twentieth century as a welcome winter relief.
Such celebration of the mild chinook has been
particularly pronounced in southern Alberta,
which local boosters, only partially tongue-incheek,
describe as Canada's "Banana Belt,"
and which the regional tourism industry officially
markets as "Chinook Country." The
chinook also is a well-recognized presence
among the communities along Colorado's
Front Range, even serving for a few years
(1969-72) as the name for a Denver-based underground
weekly newspaper; as explained in
the inaugural issue, Chinook was chosen because
it is a "warm wind that comes from the
mountains. It sometimes brings great upheaval,
but more often it brings gentle warmth
and good vibrations."

See also PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT: Chinooks.


Peter S. Morris
Santa Monica College




Burrows, Alvin T. "The Chinook Winds." Journal of Geography
2 (1903): 124–36. Fraser, Frances. The Bear Who Stole the Chinook: Tales from the Blackfoot. Vancouver: Douglas
and McIntyre, 1990. Morris, Peter S. "Regional Ideas and
the Montana-Alberta Borderlands." Geographical Review
89 (1999): 469–90.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>