<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.art.008</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Butcher, Solomon (1856-1972)</field>
      <field name="author">Koelling, Jill Marie</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BUTCHER, SOLOMON (1856-1927)

Solomon D. Butcher's photographs made the
sod house an American icon. No other photographer
captured settlement in the Great
Plains with such insight into the experience of
homesteading.

Butcher was born on January 24, 1856, in
Burton, Virginia. His father moved the family
to Illinois four years later, and it was there that
Butcher spent his childhood and first learned
the science of photography. Butcher spent one
term at the Henry Military School in Henry,
Illinois, but soon gave that up to work as a
traveling salesman.

In 1880 Butcher's father again moved on,
this time to Nebraska. Solomon gave up
his job as a salesman and went along. It took
them approximately six weeks to reach the
northeastern corner of Custer County, where
Butcher's father, Butcher himself, and his
brother George, who also made the trip, filed
homestead claims. It took Butcher only two
weeks to realize he was not made for homesteading,
and he returned his claim to the government.
There followed a brief attempt at the
study of medicine in Minnesota, marriage,
and his return to the Sandhills of Nebraska.

By the fall of 1882 Butcher was teaching
school and trying to amass enough money to
purchase land and photographic equipment.
Shortly thereafter he opened what became the
first photographic gallery in Custer County,
Nebraska. Over the next few years, Butcher
moved his family from town to town, never
quite escaping from financial ruin. But in
1886, possibly driven by depression over yet
another financial crisis, Butcher struck on
an idea: he would produce a photographic
history of Custer County, Nebraska. For almost
three decades, he traveled across the Nebraska
Sandhills photographing homesteaders
in their environment. He did more than
take portraits of people; he placed them
within the context that defined their existence.
Butcher understood the commitment it took
to homestead, and he also realized that this
experience was short-lived and would never
happen again.

The sheer volume of images produced by
Butcher offers an unparalleled look at the life
of homesteaders. Butcher's care to include the
landscape, the sod house, and the saplings so
carefully tended speaks to his desire to record
the space, not just the face, of homesteading.
He recorded the impact of homesteading, not
just the act. Butcher practiced environmental
portraiture at its finest. In some photographs
the people are such a small part of the image
that they are barely detectable. In others they
take center stage but are surrounded by the
material trappings of homesteading: stoves,
birdcages, tables, chairs, photographs of absent
family members.

Butcher created a detailed and comprehensive
view of homesteading, but his images also
offer insight into the craft of photography in
the late nineteenth century and open the door
to countless stories about the settlers themselves.
Through his images we are transported
to the mud and sweat that was the settlement
of the Great Plains. Solomon Butcher died in
Greeley, Colorado, on May 26, 1927.

See also ARCHITECTURE: Sod-Wall Construction
/ PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT: Sandhills.


Jill Marie Koelling
Nebraska State Historical Society




Butcher, Solomon D. Pioneer History of Custer County, Nebraska and Short Sketches of Early Days in Nebraska.
Broken Bow NE: Solomon D. Butcher and Ephraim Swain
Finch, 1901. Carter, John E. Solomon D. Butcher: Photographing the American Dream. Lincoln: University of Nebraska
Press, 1985.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>