<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ha.039</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Sam Sabá Mission and Presidio</field>
      <field name="author">Weddle, Robert S.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SAN SABÁ MISSION AND PRESIDIO

Franciscan missionaries and Spanish soldiers
established Mission Santa Cruz de San Sabá
and Presidio de San Luis de las Amarillas
on the San Saba River near present-day Menard,
Texas, in 1757 to Christianize the eastern
(Lipan) Apaches. Though failing to win
Apache converts in significant numbers, the
attempt brought the Spaniards into conflict
with the Comanches and allied "northern
tribes." Less than a year after its founding, on
March 16, 1758, an estimated 2,000 Indians
sacked and burned the log mission. The "protecting"
presidio was powerless to intervene.
The mission president, Fray Alonso Giraldo
de Terreros, Fray José de Santiesteban, and at
least six other mission occupants were slain.
The mission was never rebuilt.

The presidio commander, Col. Diego Ortiz
Parrilla, led a 600-man expedition to punish
the attacking Indians in 1759 but was repulsed
at the fortified Taovaya (Wichita) village on
the Red River. Nineteen Spaniards died and
many others were wounded. His failure, added
to the mission attack, emphasized the Native
American's enhanced warfare capabilities,
with Spanish horses and French firearms. Participants
in the mission attack included not
only Comanches of the Texas High Plains but
also members of the Caddoan confederacies of
eastern Texas and western Louisiana and the
intervening Wichita groups.

Ortiz Parrilla, going to Mexico to report,
offered recommendations for dealing with the
changes, but he was replaced as the commander.
In his stead, Felipe de Rábago y Terán
was sent to hold the post and maintain Spanish
prestige. The presidio was temporarily
abandoned in 1768 and closed for good in
1770. The San Sabá Mission episode signaled
Spain's retreat from its northernmost Texas
outpost and the reshaping of its entire northern
defense system.

See also WAR: San Sabá Mission, Destruction of.


Robert S. Weddle
Bonham, Texas




Weddle, Robert S. The San Sabá Mission: Spanish Pivot in Texas. Austin: University of Texas Press, 1964.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>