<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ag.046</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Hay</field>
      <field name="author">Gray, Alan</field>
      <field name="text">

 




HAY

Approximately 65 million tons of perennial
legume and grass hay crops are produced annually
on about 30 million acres of the Great
Plains in the United States and Canada. Within
the United States, this includes 24 million tons
of alfalfa hay produced on 9 million acres and
26 million tons of grass hay produced on the
remaining 14 million acres. Variations in
length of growing season, soil fertility, available
water, and plant species produce wide variations
in the yield of hay crops in the Great
Plains. Depending on the year, an additional 15
to 20 million tons of hay baled from crop aftermath
and annual grass crops could be added to
the total. Sixty-five million tons of stacked hay
would extend 27,357 miles (10 percent more
than the distance around the equator), if packaged
as large rectangular bales (1,800 pounds)
and loaded on standard forty-eight-foot semitrailers
at the rate of twenty-four bales per
trailer!

Alfalfa hay production ranges from five
harvests (10 tons per acre) on intensively managed,
irrigated stands in the Southern Great
Plains to only one harvest (1.5 tons per acre)
from dryland stands in the higher elevations
and latitudes of the north. An improved, cool
season perennial grass such as Timothy may
yield as much as 5 tons per acre from one
harvest with intensive fertilization and irrigation
in the northern latitudes. Average
yield of native grass hay in the Central Great
Plains, harvested once per season, is less than
a ton per acre, but yield could be double
or greater with above-average precipitation.
In the Southern Plains, intensively managed
stands of an improved, warm season perennial
grass (i.e. Bermuda grass) may yield 5 to 7 tons
per acre in one growing season. Because of its
bulk and relative ubiquitous occurrence, most
hay is consumed locally, except when adverse
conditions, such as drought, necessitate shipments
from surplus to deficit areas.


Alan Gray
University of Wyoming




More, Kenneth, and Michael Collins, eds. Forages. Ames:
Iowa State University Press, 1995.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>