<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fil.040</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Little Big Man</field>
      <field name="author">Zimmerman, Larry J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




LITTLE BIG MAN

Little Big Man DVD Cover
    

Little Big Man, released in 1970 and directed
by Arthur Penn, is based on a novel of the
same title (1964) by Thomas Berger. Berger
and Calder Willingham wrote the screenplay.
The film, shot on location in Montana and
Canada, is a revisionist history of the mythic
Old West, reflecting the social turmoil of the
late 1960s.

The central character, Jack Crabb (Dustin
Hoffman), is nearly 120 years old and in a
home, where he relates his life story to a young
writer. After their parents are killed by Native
Americans on the way west, Jack and his sister
are taken into a Cheyenne village. His sister
escapes, but Jack is raised Cheyenne, in particular
by Old Lodge Skins (Dan George).

The story is braided with characters who
move in and out of the narrative as Jack
ages. Later "rescued" from captivity, Crabb is
caught between the worlds of the Cheyennes
and European Americans. He moves through
life as a gunfighter, a failed store clerk, a muleskinner,
a drunkard, and a military scout, but
he always moves back to the Cheyennes in
order to center his life. The story is told with
hyperbole, as a tall tale would be, but with deft
humor and irony.

The entire film is a classic retelling of every
Western ever written or made. The segments
in the European American world are often the
most humorous. Jack's religious education is
overseen by a missionary and his lusty wife,
who later reappears as a saloon prostitute.
He assists a snake oil salesman and is tarred
and feathered. His tutelage as a gunfighter is
overseen by his "manly" sister, Caroline, and
Wild Bill Hickok. His stint as an inept businessman
includes his marriage to an illtempered
immigrant woman, who henpecks
him. As a drunkard, he ends up becoming a
muleskinner and scout for George Armstrong
Custer.

Jack's movement in and out of the Native
American world is also humorous, but the
Cheyennes are presented as victims. Jack is
present at the Sand Creek Massacre, after
which he takes a Cheyenne wife, only to see
her, her sisters, and his child killed by the Seventh
Cavalry on the Washita River. He lives to
fight in the Battle of Greasy Grass (Little Big
Horn), where a childhood rival rescues him
from being killed.

The portrayals of the Old West and Native
Americans are exaggerated in every way. The
film marks the beginning, however, of showing
Native Americans as close to nature, spiritual,
and victims of the white man. Little Big Man was among the first films that made an
effort to be ethnographically accurate in its
Native American segments. It may also be the
first portrayal of Custer as vainglorious and,
by the time of the Washita River massacre and
Little Big Horn, a raving lunatic. Little Big Man reflects the growing resistance to the
Vietnam conflict but also incorporates other
themes of the day, including more open sexuality,
an exposure of religious hypocrisy, and
an awareness of environmental issues.

See also LITERARY TRADITIONS: The Western.


Larry J. Zimmerman
University of Iowa




Kasdan, Margo, and Susan Tavernetti. "Native Americans
in a Revisionist Western: Little Big Man." In Hollywood's Indians: The Portrayal of the Native American in Film, edited
by Peter C. Rollins and John E. O'Connor. Lexington:
University Press of Kentucky, 1998: 121–36.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>