<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.044</field>
      <field name="titleMain">McMurtry, Larry (b. 1936)</field>
      <field name="author">Grover, Dorys Crow</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MCMURTRY, LARRY (b. 1936)

Writer Larry McMurtry


Born June 3, 1936, in Wichita Falls, Texas, to
Hazel Rugh McIver and Jefferson McMurtry,
Lawrence Jefferson McMurtry grew up with
ranch hands and cowboys. He received a
bachelor of arts degree from the University of
North Texas and a master of arts degree from
Rice University and studied creative writing
at Stanford. He married Josephine Ballard on
July 15, 1959; they divorced in 1966. He has one
son, James Lawrence. McMurtry taught creative
writing at Rice from 1963 to 1969 and
now lives in Archer City, Texas, where he runs
a bookstore called Booked Up.

McMurtry has published twenty-one novels
and much nonfiction, and he has received
numerous literary awards. His trail-driving
novel, Lonesome Dove (1985), received the
Spur Award of the Western Writers of America, the Texas Institute of Letters Prize, and a
Pulitzer Prize (1986). McMurtry has written
sequels to all of his most popular books. He
followed the characters of Lonesome Dove in
sequels, prequels, and the television miniseries
films The Streets of Laredo (1995), Return
to Lonesome Dove (1993), and Dead Man's Walk (1996), but he has never managed to improve
on the originals. The Last Picture Show
(1966) was reprised in Texasville (1987), and
Duane's Depressed (1999) and other works are
linked by their characters.

What makes McMurtry's Lonesome Dove
one of the best Westerns ever written is his
ability to combine a rip-snorting story full
of wonderful characters with a history of and
elegy for America's westward migration. Lonesome Dove joins Horseman, Pass By (1961) and
Leaving Cheyenne (1963) as McMurtry's Texas
trilogy. McMurtry's In a Narrow Grave (1968)
collects many of his published essays.

Most of McMurtry's novels have a certain
wistfulness. Sadness and laconic humor, occasioned
by loneliness and an awareness of the
uncertainties of life, run through his work in
an insistent refrain.

See also FILM: Hud; The Last Picture Show.


Meredith McClain
Texas Tech University




Lich, Lera Patrick Tyler. Larry McMurtry's Texas: Evolution of the Myth. Austin: Eakin, 1987. Reynolds, Clay, ed. Taking Stock: A Larry McMurtry Casebook. Dallas: Southern
Methodist University Press, 1989.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>