<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.wat.033</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Union Colony</field>
      <field name="author">Wishart, David J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




UNION COLONY

The Union Colony of Greeley, Colorado, was
one of the most successful irrigation-based
settlements in the Great Plains. It was organized
by Horace Greeley, who, following his
own famous advice, traveled west in 1859 and
included a visit to Colorado. Ten years later, he
sent a colleague, Nathan Meeker, to search out
a suitable site for a colony based on irrigated
farming. A site near the junction of the Cache
la Poudre and South Platte Rivers was chosen
in 1870–a block of land purchased from the
Denver Pacific Railroad–and by May colonists
were arriving from Chicago, Buffalo,
Boston, and New York.

Requirements for membership in the colony
included a $155 fee and a good moral character.
From the beginning, the success of the
colony depended upon control of water. In
exchange for their fee, colonists received a
farming tract of five, ten, twenty, or forty acres,
the size increasing with distance from the central
hub of Greeley, as well as guaranteed water
rights. Within a month, water was flowing
through ditches to cultivated fields of wheat,
corn, and vegetables. Within a year, thirty-six
miles of main canals had been built, and a grid
of lateral ditches brought a potential 60,000
acres within reach of irrigation. The largest
canal was twenty-seven miles long, thirty feet
wide, and four and one-half feet deep and carried
water from the floodplain to the adjacent
benchlands. The town of Greeley flourished,
reaching a population of 1,500 in May of 1871.
The growth was sustained, and by 1873 the
colony structure was unable to accommodate
the expansion and was disbanded. However,
from this successful start, Greeley and the surrounding
area have remained one of the most
productive portions of the Colorado Piedmont
and are still a center of irrigated farming.


David J. Wishart
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Willard, James F. The Union Colony at Greeley, Colorado,
1869–1871. Boulder: University Press of Colorado, 1918.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>