<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.039</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Livesay, Dorothy (1909-1996)</field>
      <field name="author">Thompson, Lee Briscoe</field>
      <field name="text">

 




LIVESAY, DOROTHY (1909-1996)

Born in Winnipeg on October 12, 1909, to journalist
parents, Dorothy Livesay over some sixty-five
active writing years published twenty-one
volumes of poetry, four of fiction and nonfiction
prose, and a myriad of articles, reviews,
forewords, agitprop and docudramas, edited
volumes of the creative writing of others, journalistic
pieces, and uncollected individual short
stories and poems. She spent only two phases of
her life–her first and sixth decades–in the
Prairies and would engage intensely with most
of the other places she lived–British Columbia,
Ontario, New Brunswick, Africa, England, and
France. But Livesay's writing throughout bore
the indelible psychic imprint of that first landscape,
the Canadian Great Plains: its openness
and multiethnicity were powerful influences on
her work.

Livesay's family moved to Ontario in 1920,
but when she was in her twenties, a moderately
Marxist Livesay passed back through the
Prairies on a promotional tour for a new leftist
periodical. Prairie laborers were mobilizing
to break out of the long-standing grip of the
Great Depression, which in Canada had hit
their region the hardest, and Livesay's contact
with Prairie workers from coal miners to
sugar beet harvesters encouraged her creative
combining of art with her agenda for social
change. That aspect of Prairie inspiration continued
to inform her thought and technique
in her subsequent years in British Columbia
and abroad.

Later in life, a seasoned writer and academic,
she took two positions as writer in residence
in the Great Plains: 1968–71 at the University
of Alberta (Edmonton) and 1974–76 at
the University of Manitoba. She helped found
a new literary journal, CV/II, that was a supportive
venue for emerging Prairie writers. In
the 1980s she spent summers near the Icelandic
community at Gimli, Manitoba. These
years saw a literary revisiting of her Prairie
origins in some poems of Plainsongs (1969,
expanded 1971) and particularly in the linked
stories entitled A Winnipeg Childhood (1973),
expanded and renamed Beginnings (1988).
Those stories follow a lightly disguised Dorothy
("Elizabeth") through a vivid rendering of
her childhood in a Prairie city, charming readers
with its descriptive simplicity, its magicrealist
treatment of the commonplace, and its
fluid, rhythmic prose.

Livesay absorbed and developed the Canadian
Prairie's early-twentieth-century optimistic
vision of infinite possibilities, of a new
and egalitarian society, passionate and fresh.
One must note, however, that she also shared
the no less historical Prairie sense of isolation,
alienation, exclusion, and marginalization. Yet
that personal perspective dovetailed productively
with another Great Plains element, the
multicultural patchwork of Winnipeg, which
shaped her lifelong interest in social justice
and equality and the rights of minorities, a
conviction embodied in verse dramas such as
her liberatory treatment of the hitherto reviled
Métis leader Louis Riel, "Prophet of the
New World." The inherent drama of the Prairies,
its strong horizontals and majestic skyscapes,
the enormity of spaces and intense
contrasts of light: all seem connected with
both Livesay's preoccupation with nature as
well as her gravitation to polarities and complementarities
in human relations and the
universe. Dorothy Livesay died in Victoria,
British Columbia, on December 29, 1996.

See also PROTEST AND DISSENT: Riel, Louis.


Lee Briscoe Thompson
University of Vermont




Thompson, Lee Briscoe. Dorothy Livesay. Boston: Twayne,
1987. University of Manitoba Department of Archives. The Papers of Dorothy Livesay: A Research Tool. Winnipeg:
University of Manitoba, 1986.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>