<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ha.048</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Zamora, Bernice (b. 1938)</field>
      <field name="author">Hutchison, Sharla</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ZAMORA, BERNICE (b. 1938)

Chicana poet Bernice Zamora is best known
for her collection of poems, Restless Serpents.
First published in 1976, this collection established
Zamora's reputation as an important
poet. Zamora was born on January 20,
1938, in the small rural community of Aguilar,
Colorado, where her family roots extend back
several generations. Her parents, Victor and
Marjorie Ortiz, eventually moved the family
to Pueblo. The influence of the southern Colorado
landscape and its rugged terrain of
mountains and volcanoes would become a
lasting feature in her work, as would the regional
culture.

Zamora received her bachelor of arts degree
from Southern Colorado University in 1970,
her master of arts degree from Colorado State
University in 1972, and her doctorate from
Stanford University in 1986. In addition to her
career as a poet, Zamora has taught classes in
Chicano studies, ethnic studies, and literature
at the University of California at Berkeley,
University of San Francisco, Santa Clara University,
and Stanford University. Zamora has
also coedited anthologies of Chicano writing.
Her collected poems in Restless Serpents were
republished with a series of new poems under
the title, Releasing Serpents, in 1994.

A variety of themes and influences culminate
in Zamora's poetry: Chicano cultural traditions,
gender discrimination, cultural suppression,
labor exploitation, spiritual questions,
identity conflict, and love. The regional
setting of southern Colorado and, more generally,
the American Southwest, figures prominently
in her work as she explores such questions.
Chicano writers often locate Aztlan,
the homeland of the Aztecs, within the region
of northern New Mexico and southern Colorado.
Zamora integrates Aztec references and
images in her writing as she explores themes
and questions about cultural heritage and the
effects of colonization in the contemporary
world of the American Southwest.


Sharla Hutchison
University of Oklahoma




Bruce-Novoa, Juan. Chicano Poetry: A Response to Chaos.
Austin: University of Texas Press, 1982. Sánchez, Marta
Ester. Contemporary Chicana Poetry: A Critical Approach to an Emerging Literature. Berkeley: University of California
Press, 1985.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>