<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.sr.016</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Edmonton Grads</field>
      <field name="author">Lappage, Ronald S.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




EDMONTON GRADS

The Edmonton Commercial Graduates (Grads)
dominated women's basketball in North America
during the interwar years. Percy Page started
the team in 1915 with students and graduates
from Edmonton's McDougall Commercial
High School, where he was a teacher, and only
twice during the Grads' twenty-five years did
girls who had not been at McDougall High play
for the team.

From 1915 until the team disbanded in 1940,
when their practice area was taken over for
military purposes, the Grads won 502 of 522
games. At one point in their history they had a
winning streak of 147 games, followed by a 78-game
winning streak. They won their first Canadian
title in 1922 and never surrendered it. In
1923, against Cleveland, they won the first international
series for the Underwood Trophy.
They defended it successfully for seventeen
years. The Grads competed in Fédération
Sportive Féminine Internationale (FSFI) championships
held in the same cities as the men's
Olympics on four occasions (1924, 1928, 1932,
and 1936) and won the unofficial world championship each time, with twenty-seven consecutive
victories.

Everywhere the Grads played they drew
large crowds, including the record attendance
of 6,792 for an Underwood Trophy match
against the Chicago Taylor-Trunks in Edmonton
in 1930. However, the Grads did not forget
their Prairie roots, and they staged basketball
exhibitions in several small Alberta communities.
Coach Page expected his Grads to behave
"like ladies" both on and off the court,
and his teams established a reputation for
sportsmanship, dedication, and determination.
Significantly, they demonstrated that
they could play the more vigorous men's rules
and yet retain their femininity. When asked
about the Grads' secret of success, Page replied,
"They were champions because they
were whole-hearted, sport-loving girls in
whom the spirit of the Prairie was born and
bred."


Ronald S. Lappage
Lakehead University




Fitness and Amateur Sport Canada. For the Record: Canada's
Greatest Women Athletes. Toronto: John Wiley and
Sons Canada Ltd., 1981. Kidd, Bruce. The Struggle for Canadian
Sport. Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 1996.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>