<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fil.020</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Drylanders</field>
      <field name="author">Kerr, Don</field>
      <field name="text">

 




DRYLANDERS

Drylanders theatrical release poster
    

Drylanders (1963) was the first feature film
made by the National Film Board of Canada.
Directed by Don Haldane, it chronicles thirty
years in the lives of a family who homestead,
farm, live, and suffer under the power of nature
in the Great Plains. The film was made on
location in the Swift Current area in southwestern
Saskatchewan in 1961, premiered there
in 1963 to an enthusiastic audience, and went
on general release in 1964. Originally planned
as a television program for the Canadian
Broadcasting Corporation, which showed little
interest in it, it became a ninety-five-minute
black-and-white feature, which was reduced to
seventy minutes for general release and is now
available in four parts for teaching English as a
second language.

The story is organized in two major sequences,
1907–9 and 1928–38. It begins in the
spring of 1907 after the terrible winter of 1906–
7, when Dan (James Douglas) and Liza Greer
(Frances Hyland) and their two small sons arrive
at their quarter section, which is a survey
post, the major feature on that treeless land.
There is a sod house building bee, a dance, a
blizzard, and the first crop–and the hail that
destroys it. That sense of hope and disaster is a
prelude to the more devastating second sequence:
the bumper crop of 1928 is followed by
the great drought, during which the younger
son (Don Francks) leaves for the city, the older
son (William Fruet) stays (though there is only
dust), neighbors leave, the father dies without
hope, and the rains come, leaving Liza to say at
the end of the film, "We're starting over again."

Between these two sequences a long montage,
sometimes using license plates to chart
the passage of time, disposes of World War I,
in which the eldest son fights, his marriage,
and the many years of good times on the farm.
The montage, however, is out of sync with
what goes before and comes after–the sequences
that evoke an emotional response to
the joys and tribulations of the Greer family.
Are those invisible twenty years part of the
twenty-five minutes Haldane was forced to
cut? There is a successful second montage of
the younger son walking the city; the closed
warehouses, shut gates, soup kitchens, owners
shaking their heads, letters home, riding the
rail, and so on succeed, in the method of
Eisenstein, to create a powerful metaphor for
the unemployed single man in the city.

Drylanders is a film about farmers and nature,
not about farmers and markets. There
are haunting images of the Greers against the
beautiful and harsh environment: the oxen
and cart against a prairie sunset, the father
disappearing over a snowbank in a blizzard,
the dust swallowing house and barns, the lone
farmer standing tall in the field. There are,
however, no banks, no cost-price squeeze, no
grain exchange, and no farmer protests. We
know the drought eats money as well as hope,
but there's no boom-bust to accompany it.

The film is really about the human heart
and farming the Great Plains, not about the
balance sheet. A central theme is hope and its
obverse, despair, which is the trajectory the
father suffers. It is his optimism and hope that
bring the family west and help him survive the
growing skepticism of his wife and early setbacks.
When he loses all hope during the Depression
and dies in 1938 after years of despair,
that's a terrible pattern of defeat offset only by
his wife's growing resolve to stay in the place
she hated and now calls home no matter what.
When the minister tells her not to lose hope,
she replies, "Trouble with hope is it has to be
fed," and of Dan's death she says, "The prairie
had betrayed him." In Drylanders no one wins
easily.

In style Drylanders is a film that declares
itself a film, in its voice-overs, balancing of
light and shade, elaborate camera angles, long
montage sequences, and obvious symbolism
and poetry. There is a great deal of pleasure to
be gained from its style, from the photography
of Reginald Morris, the music of Eldon Rathburn
(who scored more than a hundred films
at the National Film Board from 1944 to 1976),
the literate script of Charles Cohen, and the
acting, especially that of Frances Hyland
(whose "educated" pronunciation seems right
for a woman of 1907), though all the performances
are good.

The film must finally be judged on its ability
to move us, to make us feel the hope and
despair of the homesteader and farmer in the
Great Plains, in this case, the prairie of Saskatchewan.
That opening night audience in
Swift Current felt that emotion.


Don Kerr
University of Saskatchewan




Evans, Gary. In the National Interest: A Chronicle of the
National Film Board of Canada from 1949 to 1989. Toronto:
University of Toronto Press, 1991. Morris, Peter. The Film
Companies. Toronto: Irwin, 1984.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>