<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.asam.020</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Sou, Chin Lin (1837-1894)</field>
      <field name="author">Monnett, John H.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SOU, CHIN LIN (1837-1894)

One would have trouble explaining "westward
expansion" to Chin Lin Sou. Chin was a Cantonese
immigrant in his twenties when he
came to San Francisco in the early 1860s fleeing
the bloody civil war that started with the
T'ai P'ing Rebellion of 1850. By 1864 the Central
Pacific Railroad's Charles Crocker employed
hundreds of overseas Chinese workers.
"Crocker's Pets," as they were called, blasted
grades and cuts through Donner Pass in the
Sierras and on across Utah's Great Basin.
From that memorable time in his life, Chin's
"frontier" pushed east rather than west.

Following the driving of the "golden spike"
at Promontory Point, Utah Territory, on May
10, 1869, Chin Lin Sou found himself in the
employ of Gen. Grenville Dodge's Union Pacific
Railroad, working to bring its tracks
up to government standards. This opportunity
brought him across the Rocky Mountains
to the Great Plains of Nebraska. In 1870 a
group of Denver businessmen, including H.
A. W. Loveland, financed the construction of
the Denver Pacific Railroad, a north–south
line connecting Denver and Colorado to the
transcontinental trunk line at Cheyenne, Wyoming.
Chin served as a foreman of the Chinese
labor crew that brought the project in
under budget.

Chin Lin Sou stayed in Colorado, locating
in Central City, where he made modest profits
in mining investments. Sometime in the late
1870s he was financially able to bring his family
from China. They settled in Denver where,
by 1880, he operated several businesses. He
likely witnessed the terrible "Hop Alley" riots
on October 31, 1880, when irate white residents
burned and pillaged the Chinese neighborhood
of downtown Denver along 18th and
Lawrence Streets. Chin died in 1894 a pillar of
Denver's Chinese community. He was buried
in the city's Riverside Cemetery. Today a
stained-glass window portrait in the Colorado
state capitol commemorates Chin Lin Sou as
Colorado's leading Asian pioneer leader.

See also CITIES AND TOWNS: Denver, Colorado.


John H. Monnett
Metropolitan State College of Denver




Melrose Francis. "Rocky Mountain Memories." Rocky Mountain News, May 20, 1984. Monnett, John H., and
Michael McCarthy. Colorado Profiles: Men and Women Who Shaped the Centennial State. Niwot: University Press
of Colorado, 1996.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>