<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.rel.030</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Judaism</field>
      <field name="author">Sturman, Gladys</field>
      <field name="text">

 




JUDAISM

In terms of numbers of adherents, Judaism has
never had a large presence in the Great Plains.
In 1990 only two counties–El Paso County,
Colorado, home to Colorado Springs, and
Tarrant County, Texas, with Fort Worth–had
as many as two Reform Judaism congregations,
and only twenty-one other counties
in the region had even a single congregation.
Most were urban counties, such as Cass
County (with Fargo) and Burleigh County
(with Bismarck), North Dakota. There were
even fewer Conservative and Orthodox Judaism
congregations in the region. Yet Judaism
has been part of the religious landscape of
the Plains since the beginnings of European
American settlement. Eventually, Jews would
come from all over Europe and from other
parts of North America. Many came first as
peddlers and became merchants, newsmen,
and politicians; relatively few came as homesteaders
and not many of those stayed on
the land.

Denver, for example, was founded in 1858
by merchants and prospectors drawn to the
gold rush. Among these were at least ten Jews,
who gathered on Rosh Hashanah for what is
believed to be the first religious services held
in the city. While firmly attached to their Jewish
heritage, these pioneers were apparently
not observant Jews; most felt the need for a
service only on Rosh Hashanah, with prayer
being conducted by the most knowledgeable
man. An early need was a Jewish cemetery,
and usually the first organization was the Jewish
Burial Society. This would frequently evolve
into the Hebrew Benevolent Society, the core
organization for the development of synagogues,
welfare services, and schools.

Jews came to the Great Plains in significant
numbers in the late nineteenth century
from eastern Europe and Russia, where anti-Semitism
was on the rise. By 1890, for example,
there were 1,000 Jews in Omaha, Nebraska.
Others, sponsored by such agencies as
the Industrial Removal Office (founded in
New York in 1901), sought to make a living on
the land. By 1910 there were at least 1,200 Jewish
farmers in central North Dakota. Jewish
farm families also settled in southern Alberta.

Maintaining culture and religion was difficult
in these thinly settled areas. There were
usually not enough people in a given area to
establish a synagogue, hire a rabbi, support
a kosher butcher, or maintain a cheder (Jewish
elementary school). In Burleigh County,
North Dakota, Jewish women arranged for a
Bismarck rabbi to rotate from one locale to
another, teaching Hebrew to children, performing
ritual slaughtering of animals, and
conducting services. But generally, rural Jewish
settlers stayed on the land only long enough
to prove up their homesteads. Then they sold
the property and moved to towns within, and
beyond, the Great Plains.

Because the Jews of the Great Plains came
from every quarter of Europe and from every
economic class, there were sometimes ethnic,
political, and theological tensions. For example,
in 1884 the Reform rabbi of Denver's Temple
Emmanuel was told to stop ridiculing Orthodox
Jews, and in the 1930s Zionist versus
anti-Zionist arguments swept through Jewish
communities. In the Wichita German Jewish
community in the late nineteenth century, Reform
Judaism was embraced by those who
sought a degree of cultural assimilation. Dietary
laws were relaxed, and prayer was given
in English rather than Hebrew. Weekly services
took place in homes and were often conducted
by a layman. Later Jewish arrivals in
Wichita from eastern Europe practiced a more
traditional faith, forming a Hebrew congregation
in 1906. But the tensions between the two
groups were minor: there were so few Jews
that religious compromise was imperative if
the community was to survive.

Today the Jews of the Great Plains are largely
urban. Communities are under the aegis of the
Jewish Federation of each city. However, folk
wisdom has it that, in any small town in which
a Jew would wish to settle there would be a Jew
there to meet him, or her, at the station.

See also EUROPEAN AMERICANS: Jews.


Gladys Sturman
Western States Jewish History




Gaustad, Edwin Scott, and Philip L. Barlow. New Historical
Atlas of Religions in America. Oxford: Oxford University
Press, 2001. Rothman, Hal. "'Same Horse, New Wagon':
Tradition and Assimilation among the Jews of Wichita,
1835–1930." Great Plains Quarterly 15 (1995): 83–104.
Schulte, Janet E. "'Proving Up and Moving Up': Jewish
Homesteading Activity in North Dakota, 1900–1920."
Great Plains Quarterly 10 (1990): 228–44.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>