<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pe.050</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Rattlesnakes</field>
      <field name="author">Smith, Geoffrey R.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




RATTLESNAKES

A Prairie Rattlesnake


Rattlesnakes (Crotalus spp. and Sistrurus spp.)
are found throughout the Great Plains, with ten
species (nine Crotalus, one Sistrurus) ranging
from northern Mexico up through the Prairie
Provinces of Canada. They live in a number of
diverse habitats, including deserts, grasslands,
and woodlands. In the Great Plains, rattlesnakes
are often associated with prairie dog towns.

During winter, large groups of rattlesnakes
can often be found in hibernacula (cavities or
burrows where they overwinter), sometimes
with other species of snakes. Rattlesnakes give
birth to live young, and litter sizes range from
one to twenty-five, often depending on the
size of the female. Rattlesnakes feed on small
mammals, birds, or in some cases, reptiles and
amphibians, using infrared sensors located in
pits in the front of their heads to locate their
prey (hence the name pit vipers). Rattlesnakes
have a keen ability to track prey they have
envenomated and released. The toxicity of rattlesnake
bites varies with the species and size
of the snake. Rattlesnake venom causes the
necrosis of living tissues and, in some species,
includes neurotoxins that affect the nervous
system of the prey.

Dangerous and feared, rattlesnakes are
widely represented in the folklore, myths, art,
and literature of Native American and European
American peoples of the Great Plains.
Their dangerous reputation (often exaggerated)
has led to such traditions as the "rattlesnake
roundup" that involves the slaughter
of many individuals. Roundups, along with
habitat fragmentation, have resulted in drastic
consequences for the long-term persistence of
rattlesnake populations.


Geoffrey R. Smith
William Jewell College




Klauber, L. M. Rattlesnakes: Their Habits, Life Histories,
and Influence on Mankind. Berkeley: University of California
Press, 1956. Rubio, M. Rattlesnake: Portrait of a Predator.
Washington DC: Smithsonian Institution Press, 1998.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>