<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.med.046</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Television Shows</field>
      <field name="author">Walklin, Larry</field>
      <field name="text">

 




TELEVISION SHOWS

DVD Cover for Gunsmoke, Season 1
       

The Great Plains became an important component
of television programming soon after
the medium became successful on a national
level. Programs included documentaries as
well as traditional entertainment.

Noncommercial educational (later called
public) broadcasting led the way with a series
entitled Great Plains Trilogy. The thirty-nine
half-hour programs were produced in the
1950s by Jack McBride of KUON-TV at the University
of Nebraska. The first thirteen programs
dealt with the paleontology of the region.
The second set of thirteen programs
considered archaeology. The third group emphasized
Great Plains history. The Ford Foundation
provided the funding, and the series
was broadcast on educational/public television
stations.

In commercial broadcasting many popular
programs about life on the American frontier
did not indicate specific locations. Others that
might be related to the Great Plains such as
Little House on the Prairie were actually filmed
in other areas. Dallas, the highest-rated commercial
network program of the early 1980s,
included episodes about the Texas Plains even
though the city is peripheral to the region.

One of the best known of the series clearly
identified with the Great Plains was Gunsmoke
(CBS, 1955-75), which starred James Arness as
U.S. marshal Matt Dillon. Gunsmoke, which
continued to enjoy success as a syndicated off-
network rerun, was set in Dodge City, Kansas,
in the 1870s and 1880s. The show's twenty
years on the network included thirty-minute
as well as sixty-minute versions. Amanda
Blake (Kitty), Milburn Stone (Doc), Dennis
Weaver (Chester), and Burt Reynolds (Quint)
were key characters in this depiction of life in
a western Kansas cattle town.

Several other westerns were specifically set
in the Plains. The Dakotas (ABC, 1963) included
Larry Ward, Chad Everett, and Jack
Elam as U.S. marshals. The Cowboys (ABC,
1974) featured a cattle drive from a New Mexico
ranch to Dodge City, Kansas, with a trail
crew consisting of eleven nine- to fifteen-year-old
children. The Cisco Kid (syndicated, 1951),
based on the O. Henry character and probably
the first television series to be filmed in color,
involved a Robin Hood hero (played by Duncan
Renaldo) and his partner, Pancho (Leo
Carillo), in New Mexico during the 1890s.
Buckskin (NBC, 1958 and 1965) cast Sallie Brophie
as a widow hotel owner in 1880s Montana.
Tommy Nolan played her son Jody who,
seated on corral fence, plays his harmonica
and narrates each story. Branded (NBC, 1965)
placed Chuck Conners in southeastern Wyoming
in the 1870s as a former soldier trying to
clear his name. Alias Smith and Jones (ABC,
1971–73) followed two bank robbers who, after
ending criminal careers, are promised pardons
if they prove themselves worthy for
twelve months in Kansas during the 1890s. A
comedy Western, F Troop (ABC, 1965–67), featured
Forrest Tucker, Larry Storch, and Ken
Berry in the Union army in 1866 in Kansas.

Some programs were not located in identifiable
states or towns but depicted the region
more generally. One example, How the West Was Won (ABC, 1977), a three-part miniseries
about a Virginia family homesteading in the
Great Plains, brought former Gunsmoke star
James Arness back to the region with costars
Eva Marie Saint and Bruce Boxleitner. Another
example, Wagon Train (NBC, ABC, 1957.
65), followed a wagon master (Ward Bond until
his death in 1960, when he was replaced by
John McIntire) who led pioneers from a starting
point at St. Joseph, Missouri, across the
Plains to final destinations in the Far West.
The eight-hour miniseries Lonesome Dove
(CBS, 1989) offered solid performances by
Robert Duvall, Tommy Lee Jones, and Anjelica
Huston during a cattle drive from Lonesome
Dove, Texas, to Montana. Return to Lonesome Dove (CBS, 1993) continued the
story with Barbara Hershey and William Peterson
as the stars.

A different type of series, Route 66 (CBS,
1960-64), followed the adventures of two young
men, played by Martin Milner and George Maharis,
as they drove a white Chevrolet Corvette
through the Great Plains and points west on that
famous highway. The series benefited from successful
recordings of the theme song, which was
written by Nelson Riddle.

Television programming tends to follow
audience trends. Much of the emphasis in the
Great Plains followed the interest in Westerns
during the early years of the medium. When
the Western declined in popularity, the Great
Plains tended to fade from the screen. But as
specialized locations returned to popularity,
programming such as the Lonesome Dove
miniseries and documentaries on the Oregon
Trail, Lewis and Clark, and Native Americans
have brought the focus back to the region.

See also IMAGES AND ICONS: Dodge City, Kansas / LITERARY TRADITIONS: The Western / TRANSPORTATION: Route 66.


Larry Walklin
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Phillips, Louis, and Burham Holmes. TV Almanac. New
York: Macmillan Publishing Company, 1994. Terrace, Vincent.
Complete Encyclopedia of Television Programs. New
York: Barnes, 1979.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>