<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.art.019</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Emma Lake Artists' Workshops</field>
      <field name="author">Hobin, Kate</field>
      <field name="text">

 




EMMA LAKE ARTISTS' WORKSHOPS

Artist workshops have been held at Emma
Lake, Saskatchewan, since 1935. Augustus F.
(Gus) Kenderdine, an artist trained at the
Academie Julian in Paris and an instructor in
the fledgling Department of Art at the University
of Saskatchewan in Saskatoon, established
a summer art camp on an eleven-acre boreal
forest peninsula on the shores of Emma Lake.
He convinced Dr. Walter Murray, first president
of the University of Saskatchewan, that
the art camp could perform a vital role
in the offerings of the department, and in
1936 the Murray Point Art School at Emma
Lake was officially incorporated as a summer
school program. Participants were teachers
and artists who came from all over the province
to learn how to teach art in Saskatchewan
schools.

After Kenderdine's death in 1947, a new
generation of Saskatchewan artists came of
age or moved into the province, including
Kenneth Lochhead, Arthur McKay, Ronald
Bloore, Ted Godwin, and Douglas Morton—
popularly referred to as the Regina Five. In
1955 Kenneth Lochhead, director of the Regina
College School of Art, proposed a two-week
workshop at Emma Lake to follow the Murray
Point Art School classes. The workshop concept,
based on modernist art, was established
to keep Prairie artists in touch with art centers
such as New York and Toronto. The internationally
renowned Emma Lake Artists' Workshops
became an established annual event and
continued virtually unchanged until the last
workshop was held in 1995.

Since the mid-1960s the site has also been a
provincial research area under the auspices of
the University of Saskatchewan Department
of Biology for biologists and other researchers.
It is the most northerly field station in
Saskatchewan and one of the few sites in Canada
that specifically examines the boreal forest.
It was declared as a game preserve in 1962.
In 1989 the site was officially designated as
Emma Lake Kenderdine Campus in recognition
of Gus Kenderdine. Currently, the site
thrives as a summer campus for artists workshops
for both university and community
programs.


Kate Hobin
University of Saskatchewan




Kate Hobin Papers, Emma Lake Kenderdine Campus
Files, Community Arts Program, Extension Division,
University of Saskatchewan, Saskatoon. O'Brian, John, ed.
The Flat Side of the Landscape–The Emma Lake Artists'
Workshops. Saskatoon, Saskatchewan: Mendel Art Gallery,
1989.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>