<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.afam.036</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Sanders, Barry (b. 1968)</field>
      <field name="author">Finchum, G. Allen</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SANDERS, BARRY (b. 1968)


Barry Sanders, 1988


Barry Sanders, who was born in Wichita, Kansas,
on July 16, 1968, is considered one of the
greatest running backs to ever play football.
Following a noteworthy high school career,
Sanders was not widely recruited by the major
colleges because of his relatively diminutive
stature (five feet eight inches). However, Oklahoma
State University took a chance on the
small but determined Sanders. After two years
as one of the best kick-return specialists
in college football, in 1988 Sanders had the
most prolific season running the football in
college football history. That year Sanders ran
for 2,628 yards, a National Collegiate Athletic
Association record, and scored thirty-nine
touchdowns, winning the Heisman Trophy as
the nation's best player. Sanders was taken as
the third choice in the 1989 National Football
League (NFL) draft by the Detroit Lions, for
whom he played ten seasons. During his nfl
career Sanders rushed for 15,269 yards and was
the nfl Rookie of the Year in 1989 and the
Player of the Year in 1997.

Sanders's legacy as a running back is as one
of the most elusive runners in the game, and
his misdirection-runs at both the college and
professional levels continue to be seen on
"highlight reels" when great running backs are
discussed. Following the 1998 season Barry
Sanders surprised the football world by retiring
from the nfl needing less than 1,500 yards
to become the most prolific runner in NFL
history. Sanders continues to reside in the Detroit
area, although he remains active in the
Wichita area through his generous support of
his home church.


G. Allen Finchum
Oklahoma State University




Oklahoma State 2001 Football Media Guide. Stillwater: Oklahoma State University Athletic Department, 2001.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>