<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.na.110</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Sovereignty</field>
      <field name="author">Barsh, Russel</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SOVEREIGNTY

Sovereignty originally referred to the political
attributes of a European king. To be sovereign
was to be "above everything." Sovereignty was
thought to reside in the physical person of the
ruler. The formation of the Swiss Confederation
in 1291 and the United Provinces (now the
Netherlands) in 1581 introduced a new kind of
actor on the political stage: democratic republics
that did not have individual dynastic
rulers. The seventeenth-century Dutch jurist
Hugo de Groot (or Grotius) and eighteenthcentury
Swiss jurist Emmerich Vattel wrote
pioneering legal treatises arguing that sovereignty
resides collectively in society itself—
that is, in the state and its citizens.

European ideas of sovereignty were culturally
applicable to some Aboriginal American
contexts. The agricultural city-states of the
Mississippi Valley were governed by individual
chiefs, as attested by early French descriptions
of the city of Natchez. On the whole, however,
the chiefs and councils of Indian tribes did not
assert absolute lawmaking power over their
people.

This was especially true in the Great Plains
where, as John Moore has demonstrated for
the Cheyennes, group boundaries and leadership
remained flexible and could change from
season to season. Households not only realigned
themselves and chose new leaders
within the nation, but they often left the nation
altogether, for a season or many years, to
travel and hunt with relatives in other nations.
While the nation collectively defended a distinct
territory with which it identified historically
and ceremonially, its constituent families
and clans, and its leadership, could be
extremely fluid. When the camp crier announced
that a respected man planned to
break camp at dawn, households individually
chose whether to follow him.

Great Plains nations were patches in a boundless,
endlessly changing web of kinship relationships,
landscapes, and languages. Mobility
within this web was sufficient to prevent any
persistent concentrations of political power. At
the same time, solidarity was sufficient to repel
intruders who lacked legitimate claims to local
hospitality. Although Great Plains nations
could mobilize a formidable military power, as
the U.S. Army learned, their leaders generally
lacked the institutional means or authority to
regulate daily life.

To be sure, most Great Plains nations had
"police societies," which could promote good
behavior and intervene in disturbances within
the camp. In extreme cases, camp police could
confiscate malefactors' possessions or even
banish them from the community altogether,
but only to the extent such actions were supported
by collective opinion. When internal
disputes could not be resolved by means of
negotiation and compromise between families,
there was always the option of departure
from the camp. A leader misguided enough to
try to impose his will on the people would
find himself without followers. Plains leaders
earned their influence through courage, hard
work, and generosity, and they retained it by
setting a good example and by respecting the
autonomy of others. They were "slow thinkers
and silent eaters," as Severt Young Bear puts it
so well.

It is accordingly difficult to translate "sovereignty"
into Plains Indian languages without
changing its meaning. In Lakota, Cree,
and Blackfeet societies, for example, "sovereignty"
is translated into phrases such as "we
do things our own way" or "we are ourselves."
This equates sovereignty with freedom rather
than power. It has no reference to the existence
or legitimacy of states, rulers, or human
laws.

Early European explorers nevertheless frequently
referred to chiefs as "kings" and
showered them with presents in the manner
of European court ceremony. What is more
important historically and legally is the fact
that British, French, Spanish, and Dutch colonists
routinely made treaties with Indian nations
for trade, military alliances, and the
right to build settlements in tribal territories.
Warfare and diplomacy with Europeans enhanced
the status, wealth, and influence of individual
Indian leaders within their own societies.
The governance of Indian nations
gradually became more centralized and coercive,
adopting more and more the political
culture of Europeans. Meanwhile, ironically,
Europeans began to question whether Indian
nations were entitled to be respected as sovereign
and independent states—especially after signing treaties that placed them under the
protection of European kings.

The first generation of American legal scholars
turned to the writings of Grotius and Vattel
to explain how a republic could claim to enjoy
sovereignty in its diplomacy with European
kings. John Marshall, who was secretary of state
under President John Adams and then chief
justice of the Supreme Court, applied Vattel's
legal principles to Indian tribes in the case of
Worcester v. Georgia (1832). Indian tribes continued
to be "distinct, independent political
communities, retaining their original natural
rights," Marshall concluded, even where they
had placed themselves under Europeans' protection
by treaty. Although the Worcester decision
made it clear that tribal sovereignty was
limited only by Indians' consent—in a treaty—
Marshall's earlier dictum in Cherokee Nation v.
Georgia (1831) that Indian tribes are "domestic
dependent nations" was resuscitated by late-nineteenth-
century judges and has introduced a
fundamental ambiguity into the issue of tribal
sovereignty. More than a century later, Felix Cohen,
a lawyer for the Bureau of Indian Affairs
from 1933 to 1948, coined the term "residual
sovereignty" to describe the political authority
of Indian tribes, and it has continued to be used
by lawyers and judges in the United States.

The application of the principle of sovereignty
to Native American tribes has changed
significantly over time. According to Worcester,
the sovereignty of an Indian tribe is limited
only by the express terms of its treaties with the
United States. From 1890 to 1903, however, the
U.S. Supreme Court upheld a number of federal
laws that interfered with Indian property
in violation of treaties, reasoning that Congress
has superior sovereignty or "plenary
power" over Indians. Finally, in Oliphant v.
Suquamish Indian Tribe (1978), the Supreme
Court ruled that accepting the protection of
the United States implicitly stripped Indian
tribes of political powers that are "inconsistent
with their status" as Indians.

As a result of court decisions, the sovereignty
of Native American tribes today is limited
by what the tribes surrendered by treaty,
what Congress has imposed on tribes by legislation,
and what the courts consider to be "inconsistent
with their status." Depending on
the way particular courts interpret treaties and
laws, Indian tribes' residual sovereignty can be
very great, or nearly nonexistent.

In Canada, a constitutional monarchy in
which the queen is the sovereign and head of
state, the courts have not applied the term sovereignty
to Indian nations. About half of the
territory of Canada was acquired through Indian
treaties made in the name of the Crown
between 1724 and 1929, however, and most of
the rest has been acquired through "modernday
treaties" made since 1975. Since the 1970s,
moreover, Canada's Indian nations have insisted
that, although they respect the Crown,
they possess "unsurrendered sovereignty" of
their own. The government of Canada continues
to resist this argument, although it has
acknowledged as a matter of national policy
that Indian nations possess an "inherent right
to self-government."

Canada amended its national constitution
in 1982 to include, among other changes,
a declaration that "the existing aboriginal
and treaty rights of the aboriginal peoples of
Canada are hereby recognized and affirmed."
Indian leaders argue that sovereignty and self-government
are Aboriginal rights. This argument
has not yet been tested in the Supreme
Court of Canada, but it was strongly supported
by the Royal Commission on Aboriginal
Peoples, a seven-member national policy
review body that was established in 1992 and
published its final report four years later.

Sovereignty has taken on new meanings for
Indian nations in the twentieth century as a
result of wider economic and cultural changes
and conflicts. The process of centralization of
power, which began during the treaty-making
period, was enhanced by legislation creating
elected tribal lawmaking bodies–in the United
States by the Indian Reorganization Act in 1934
and in Canada by amendments to the Indian
Act in 1951. Federal funding of tribal government
operations, mining of tribal lands, and
(in the United States) profits from tribally
owned gambling casinos have given many Indian
tribal governments large infusions of cash
and have turned tribal leaders into corporate
managers and employers. Jurisdictional disputes
with surrounding state and provincial
governments have forced the tribes to assert
exclusive territorial lawmaking and lawenforcing
powers through the courts. More
and more, Native American tribes are exercising
sovereignty in the European sense of
the word.

At the same time, U.S. and Canadian Indian
nations no longer insist on complete independence,
but rather a limited sovereignty similar
to that of individual states within the American
federal system, or individual provinces in
Canada's confederation. They tend to accept
the inevitability of some degree of congressional
(or parliamentary) power over their lives
and responsibility for their well-being, while
demanding the greatest possible authority
over their own territories and citizens. In Canada,
this kind of arrangement has sometimes
been described as "shared sovereignty," a cooperative
political partnership under a freely
agreed division of labor.

Although similar political changes have
been taking place in Indian communities
throughout the United States and Canada,
some conflicts over power and resources have
been specific to the Great Plains. Plains agriculture
has long been based on economies of
scale—that is, farming and ranching as much
acreage as possible as a single unit. There was
considerable pressure on federal officials to
open large Indian reservations to leasing or
permanent settlement, once the surrounding
lands had been fenced. The mechanization of
agriculture and soaring grain prices during
World War I added to the demand for more
acreage. The U.S. and Canadian governments
both responded by facilitating the leasing of
land within Indian reservations and the diminishment
of reservation boundaries.

In the United States, Indian tribes have
struggled unsuccessfully to maintain jurisdiction
over all of the lands within their original
reservation boundaries, including non-Indian
settlements. The Supreme Court has taken the
view that Congress intended to break up the
larger Plains Indian reservations rather than
place settlers under the authority of Indian
governments. Several Sioux reservations have
been considerably reduced (or "disestablished")
as a result. The most recent Supreme
Court decision, South Dakota v. Yankton Sioux
Tribe (1998), concluded that Congress intended
to dissolve the Yankton Sioux Indian
Reservation when it purchased land for settlers
from the tribe in 1892. An earlier decision,
Brendale v. Confederated Tribes (1989), ruled
that Indian governments lack authority over
predominantly non-Indian settlements inside
Indian reservations.

In Canada, leasing and cutoffs are the subjects
of hundreds of unresolved land claims in the
Prairies. Although the Canadian federal government
has accepted responsibility for settling
these claims on a case-by-case basis through
negotiations, Indians have criticized delays and
inadequate compensation. In Guerin v. The
Queen (1985), Canada's Supreme Court ruled
that federal officials have a "fiduciary responsibility"
to manage Indian land prudently for Indians'
benefit, and that they must pay for any
losses attributable to mismanagement. The
Royal Commission on Aboriginal Peoples called
for the establishment of a tribunal, like the former
U.S. Indian Claims Commission, to expedite
the processing of land claims.

Meanwhile, water has been replacing land
as the main source of friction between Indian
tribes and their non-Indian neighbors. Irrigation
has surpassed mechanization as the competitive
edge in farming the Great Plains, and
limited supplies of water must be rationed between
long-established non-Indian farms and
Indian reservations. In a 1908 decision, Winters
v. United States, the U.S. Supreme Court
reasoned that Congress necessarily intended
to include su.cient water for Indian farming
when it set land aside as reservations. Indian
tribes in the Missouri and Colorado River watersheds
have used this legal principle to gain
ownership of water and to build their own
irrigation systems. Their right to sell unneeded
water back to non-Indians is now in
dispute.

Irrigation promises to be a growing source
of conflict over water allocation in the Saskatchewan
River basin, comprising much of
southern Alberta and central Saskatchewan.
Special Indian water rights have not yet been
recognized by Canadian courts, however. To
establish an "aboriginal right," according to
Canada's Supreme Court in R. v. Van der Peet
(1997), Indian nations would need to prove
that water played a significant role in Aboriginal
culture, and that it was neither expressly
surrendered through treaty nor explicitly expropriated
by Parliament. Since most of the
Indians of the Saskatchewan River basin were
originally hunters who only began farming
and ranching after settling on reserves in the
1880s, it may be difficult for them to convince
the courts that they enjoy an Aboriginal right
to water.

The growing importance of water in the
struggle over Indian sovereignty in the Great
Plains highlights the issue of change in Indian
nations' political organization and social values.
In the arid Plains, water was an object of
great reverence and careful stewardship. Important
ceremonies, sacred bundles, and pipes
were dedicated to water and water dwellers,
such as the "beaver bundles" among the Blackfoot
and Plains Crees. People exercised collective
stewardship of water and shared its use;
they did not contemplate altering its flow or
allowing anyone to enjoy special privileges.
Many Indian governments today associate water
rights with large-scale reclamation projects,
construction jobs, centrally managed agribusiness,
cash flow, and political power.

In the Great Plains context, then, sovereignty
has come to be associated more strongly
with the power of institutions than with the
freedom and responsibility of members of society.
To a large extent, this shift in perspective
is an understandable and justifiable response
to continuing encroachments by Europeans
and their governments. Indian nations built
statelike institutions and greater power because
they needed power to defend themselves.
But the power to defend is also potentially the
power to oppress people and to disrupt ecosystems.
Acquiring sovereignty in the European
sense brings new kinds of choices and
responsibilities. Many contemporary North
American Indians would share the critical
viewpoint of Meskwaki (Sauk and Fox) poet
Ray Young Bear, who wrote, "By replacing the
window of the Cosmic Earth Lodge with aluminum
panelling, we encouraged a sudden
gust of wind to tear it apart, which made us
cringe as the other elements gathered around
us in force."

See also WATER: Winters Doctrine.


Russel Barsh
University of Lethbridge



Moore, John H. The Cheyenne Nation: A Social and Demographic
History. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press,
1987. Young Bear, Ray A. Remnants of the First Earth. New
York: Grove Press, 1996. Young Bear, Severt, and R. D.
Theisz. Standing in the Light: A Lakota Way of Seeing.
Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1994.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>