<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.018</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Erdrich, Louise (b. 1954)</field>
      <field name="author">Coleman-Hall, Philip R.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ERDRICH, LOUISE (b. 1954)

Louise Erdrich
  

Since 1984, when she published the collection
of poems Jacklight, Louise Erdrich has stood
out as one of the more captivating and original
voices not only in Native American literary
circles but also in contemporary American literature
generally. Erdrich's popular and critical
success stems from her ability to craft
evocative narratives that draw heavily on oral
storytelling traditions and other aspects of
Native American culture.

Born in Little Falls, Minnesota, in 1954, and
raised in Wahpeton, North Dakota, Erdrich is
a member of the Turtle Mountain Band of the
Anishinabe (Chippewas), but she also has
German-immigrant roots. She has drawn on
these two traditions in her fiction while examining
the challenges of coming to terms with
mixed ancestry and celebrating the vitality
of Chippewa history, culture, tradition, and
community in the face of European American
intrusion. Drawing on storytelling traditions
of the Chippewas, Erdrich repeatedly constructs
fictions that employ multiple narrators,
including a dog in The Antelope Wife
(1998), and span several generations, producing
what one writer has called a "layered"
point of view. But if her narrative style appears
nonlinear and disjointed to the reader, what
readily emerges is Erdrich's strong sense of
place. These stylistic and thematic features
have prompted critics and reviewers to compare
Erdrich's North Dakota landscape to Nobel
Prize–winning author William Faulkner's
Yoknapatawpha County, especially as they
emerge in her well-known tetralogy (Love Medicine, 1984; The Beet Queen, 1986; Tracks,
1988; The Bingo Palace, 1995; and The Antelope Wife, 1998), which focuses on three Chippewa
families and others on and around the reservation.
Erdrich does not shy away from difficult
issues such as alcoholism and broken
families that confront Native communities;
however, by infusing her tales with humor,
folklore, and spirituality, Erdrich treats her
subjects with both compassion and sensitivity.


Philip R. Coleman-Hull
Bethany College




Bruchac, Joseph. Survival This Way: Interviews with American Indian Poets. Tucson: University of Arizona Press,
1987. Smith, Jeanne Rosier. Writing Tricksters: Mythic Gambols in American Ethnic Literature. Berkeley: University
of California Press, 1997.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>