<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.afam.031</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Micheaux, Oscar (1884–1951)</field>
      <field name="author">Fontenot Jr., Chester J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MICHEAUX, OSCAR (1884-1951)

Oscar Devereaux Micheaux
     

Oscar Micheaux was born on January 2, 1884,
in Metropolis, Illinois. The details of his early
life are obscure, but he may have worked in
Chicago as a stockyard hand and Pullman porter.
Inspired by Booker T. Washington's philosophy
of economic empowerment through
landownership and black business development,
Micheaux took out a homestead in 1904
on part of the Rosebud Reservation in South
Dakota. After establishing a successful farm,
despite the attempts of his white neighbors
to sell him inferior farming equipment and
animals, the death of his wife during childbirth,
and the hostile physical environment,
Micheaux turned to writing novels that reflected
his experiences: The Conquest: The
Story of a Negro Pioneer (1913); The Forged
Note: A Romance of the Darker Races (1915);
The Homesteader (1917); and The Wind from
Nowhere (1941). He considered these novels as
another business venture; he controlled their
production from start to finish by submitting
to the press printworthy originals of his manuscripts,
paying in cash for their publication,
and distributing them door-to-door to African
Americans throughout the Midwest and
South. His novels appealed to African Americans
because they presented a critique of black
urban life and offered a solution: they should
abandon the cities and look to the Great Plains
as a place where they could build an alternative
to American urban society.

Micheaux's attempts to popularize his novels
led him to filmmaking. In 1918, having
established the Western Book and Supply
Company in Sioux City, Iowa, to produce and
distribute his novels, he was contacted by
George P. Johnson, general booking manager
of the black-owned and operated Lincoln
Film Company of Los Angeles, California.
Johnson, who also operated an office in
Omaha, Nebraska, had read The Homesteader
and raised the possibility of producing a film
version. In May 1918 Micheaux traveled to
Omaha to sign a contract with Johnson to film
The Homesteader. But Micheaux's desire to
supervise the actual filming of the production,
combined with his lack of experience in directing,
caused the contract to fall through.

So Micheaux formed his own film company,
the Micheaux Film and Book Company,
with offices in Sioux City and Chicago. As he
had done previously with the Western Book
and Supply Company, Micheaux sold stock in
the newly formed film and book company to
white farmers around Sioux City. He finally
raised enough money from selling shares to
produce The Homesteader as an eight-reel film
in 1918. In all, Micheaux would produce more
than forty-four all-black-cast films nationally,
some of which were distributed in Europe.
His films were widely distributed because of
his refusal to propagandize them. He felt that
black people did not want racial propaganda
like that evident in many of the films produced
by Hollywood and some of the white
independents. Instead, they wanted a good
story–films that reflected the social, economic,
and political conditions under which
African Americans existed in America.

Taken to task for casting light-skinned African
Americans in leading roles, for imitating
the manners and sensibilities of white society,
and for using his people as "plastic" models,
Micheaux did not attempt to shield himself
from criticism. Writing in the Philadelphia
Afro-American on January 24, 1925, Micheaux
commented, "I do not wish anyone to construe
this as a request for the suppression of
criticism. Honest, intelligent criticism is an
aid to the progress of an effort. The producer
who has confidence in his ideals, politics [sic]
constructive criticism. But he also asks fairness,
and fairness in criticism demands a familiarity
with the aims of the producer, and a
knowledge of the circumstances under which
his efforts were materialized." Nonetheless,
many of his critics categorized his films as
second-rate "underground" films.

These criticisms ignore the fact that Micheaux
produced films under difficult circumstances.
He always lacked the funds necessary
to achieve high technical standards, to produce
special effects, and to stage massive action
scenes. He usually did all the work in his
productions except for perfunctory tasks. He
wrote scenarios, supervised filming, and handled
the bookkeeping. His pictures took an
average of ten days to shoot and usually cost
between $10,000 and $20,000. Once the production
of a film was under way, Micheaux
would often make a contract with a theater to
supply him with money in return for the theater
receiving first screening rights. He would
take several of the actors with him on the train
to visit prospective patrons. The actors would
perform a couple of scenes from the script
for the theater manager while Micheaux emphasized
the importance and marketability of
the script.

In 1920 Micheaux's brother, Swan, joined
him as manager of the Micheaux Film and
Book Company. In 1921 the corporation had a
cash dividend of 25 percent and established an
office in New York City. The distribution and
financial office remained in Chicago under
supervision of Swan Micheaux and Charles
Benson. Micheaux was enterprising enough to
secure a number of firms to distribute his
films: Tiffany Tolliver and W. R. Crowell distributed
his films in the East from a branch
office in Roanoke, Virginia, while A. Odanes,
owner of the Verdun Theater in Beaumont,
Texas, distributed the films in the Southwest.

Between 1918 and 1931 Micheaux produced
twenty-seven films, most of which were silent.
His first all-sound feature was The Exile (1931),
which was made from his novel The Homesteader.
Between 1931 and 1940 he produced
and directed sixteen all-sound features. In
1948 he wrote the screenplay for and directed
The Betrayal for Astor Pictures Corporation.
The screenplay was adopted from Micheaux's
novel The Wind from Nowhere; it was his last
known film activity. This film opened in a
white movie theater in downtown New York
to poor reviews. Lack of financial resources
forced Micheaux to file a voluntary petition of
bankruptcy in 1948.

When Micheaux died in Charlotte, North
Carolina, on March 25, 1951, his film corporation
was virtually bankrupt. Nevertheless, Oscar
Micheaux's entrepreneurial activities won
him the distinction as the first independent
African American film director and producer.
His legacy is kept alive through the Micheaux
Film Society of Oakland, California.



Chester J. Fontenot Jr.
Mercer University




Bogle, Donald. Toms, Coons, Mulattos, Mammies and
Bucks. New York: Viking Press, 1973. Cripps, Thomas.
Slow Fade to Black. New York: Oxford University Press,
1977. Fontenot, Chester J. Jr., "Oscar Micheaux: Black
Novelist and Filmmaker." In Vision and Refuge: Ethnic
Writers on the Great Plains, edited by Frederick Luebke.
Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1980: 109–25.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>