<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pd.005</field>
      <field name="titleMain">American Indian Movement</field>
      <field name="author">Reinhardt, Akim D.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




AMERICAN INDIAN MOVEMENT


American Indian Movement, Wounded Knee, South Dakota, March 2, 1973


Eddie Benton Banai and Clyde Bellecourt, two
Ojibwa prisoners at Minnesota's Stillwater
Prison, began organizing fellow Native American
inmates in 1963, preaching a doctrine of
Indian pride and self-reliance. After receiving
parole the following year, Bellecourt took his
message to Minneapolis. By 1968 he and Banai
had teamed up with two more Ojibwas, George
Mitchell and Dennis Banks. They named their
group Concerned Indian Americans. Unhappy
with that acronym, they settled upon
the American Indian Movement (AIM).

AIM monitored police actions to prevent
and report brutality, fought discrimination in
jobs and housing, and set up survival schools
to equip Indian children with life skills for the
urban environment and provide them alternative
views of Native history unavailable in
public schools. Its approach was also pan-Indian; since the Indian ghettos of American
cities contained people from different reservations
and tribes, AIM did not represent any
single one of them. Instead, they focused on
local issues that affected all Indians.

At first, the organization solicited government
funds and donations from religious
groups. But by 1968 frustration from dealing
with these organizations led AIM to adopt
a stance that was antagonistic toward mainstream
America. They also began to extend
their efforts beyond Minnesota. In 1970 an
AIM chapter was founded in Cleveland by Russell
Means, a Lakota who was born on the Pine
Ridge Reservation in South Dakota. Major
chapters were subsequently added in Milwaukee,
Denver, Chicago, and San Francisco.
Throughout its existence, AIM's power structure
was largely decentralized, with individual
chapters retaining substantial authority and
frequently concentrating on local issues. In
addition, its national leaders, including Banks,
Means, Bellecourt, and Santee Dakota John
Trudell, generally led by force of personality
and with support from their followers and
colleagues.

AIM went beyond urban concerns and made
inroads on the Pine Ridge Reservation when
it organized protests in nearby Gordon, Nebraska,
in early 1972. A Lakota from the reservation,
Raymond Yellow Thunder, had been
abducted, publicly humiliated, and beaten to
death in the town by white racists. When they
were charged with involuntary manslaughter
instead of murder, many Pine Ridge Lakotas
were outraged. AIM marched on the town and
forced concessions from local authorities and
the governor, thus cementing its presence and
reputation on the reservation.

Later that year, AIM moved onto the national
stage through its involvement in the
Trail of Broken Treaties, a large-scale civil
rights march in Washington DC the week before
the presidential election of 1972. When
the marchers arrived, inadequate sleeping accommodations
and federal red tape led to an
altercation with police at the Bureau of Indian
Affairs (BIA) building, which quickly turned
into a riot. The marchers occupied the building.
During the standoff, AIM took control of
the occupation and dealt with the media and
federal negotiators. The occupation ended after
less than a week when the government paid
AIM more than $66,000 to transport people
back home.

After the BIA building incident, AIM was
condemned by Pine Ridge tribal chairman
Dick Wilson, who himself was embroiled in a
major political dispute; many people on the
reservation accused him of corruption and intimidation.
As conditions became increasingly
violent, AIM came to the support of Wilson's
opponents. After Means announced he
would run against Wilson in the next election,
Wilson had him temporarily jailed.

Tensions increased when the federal government
stationed FBI agents and U.S. marshals
on the reservation in the midst of Wilson's
impeachment trial. After Wilson was
acquitted amid confusing circumstances, his
opponents decided to make a stand by seizing
Wounded Knee, the site of the 1890 massacre
of as many as 300 Lakotas by the U.S. Seventh
Cavalry. AIM readily supported them. They
jointly occupied the hamlet of Wounded Knee
on February 27, 1973, and were immediately
surrounded by marshals, FBI agents, BIA police,
and Wilson's private army, known as the
"goon squad."

During the ensuing siege, AIM again took
control of the situation, dealing with the national
media and negotiating with the federal
representatives. After seventy-one days, endless
negotiations, the shooting death of two
aim supporters, and the paralysis of one marshal,
the siege ended on May 8. It signaled the
beginning of the end of AIM.

From then on, aim endured a two-pronged
attack from the federal government. First, a
long series of trials against AIM's leaders was designed
to bankrupt the organization through
costly legal fees and keeping its leaders tied up
in court. Meanwhile, the FBI used counter-intelligence
programs, later deemed illegal, to
infiltrate and disrupt the organization. Government
repression reached its zenith with the conviction
of prominent AIM member Leonard Peltier
in the 1975 shooting deaths of two FBI agents
on the Pine Ridge Reservation. During the trial,
the government intimidated witnesses, manufactured
evidence, and committed numerous
other infractions. Nonetheless, Peltier was sentenced
to two consecutive life terms in 1977.
Efforts to win his freedom have since gained
international attention, and Amnesty International
currently recognizes him as one of the
most important political prisoners in the world.

Meanwhile, a virtual civil war between AIM
and the "goons" plagued Pine Ridge during
Wilson's post–Wounded Knee tenure (1973–76), resulting in more than fifty unsolved
murders of AIM members and supporters. In
1979 the mother-in-law, wife, and three children
of AIM's national chairman, John Trudell,
were killed in an arsonist's fire. The cause
of the fire, which was started while Trudell
was protesting the Peltier verdict, remains
unsolved.

Bankruptcy, paranoia, and repression, combined
with AIM's decentralized structure and
leadership patterns, led to a spiraling decline
within the organization. Individual leaders increasingly
worked on their own projects, political
and otherwise, and by the 1980s AIM was
defunct as a national entity. The FBI closed its
active files on AIM in July 1979. Today, a scattering
of local chapters continues to work on local
issues, and individual members of national
prominence continue to invoke the movement's
name on behalf of their own programs.

See also MUSIC: Trudell, John / WAR: Wounded Knee Massacre.


Akim D. Reinhardt
Towson University




Churchill, Ward, and Jim Vander Wall. Agents of Repression:
The FBI's Secret War against the Black Panther Party
and the American Indian Movement. Boston: South End
Press, 1988. Smith, Paul Chaat, and Robert Allen Warrior.
Like a Hurricane. New York: New Press, 1996.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>