<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ct.024</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Ghost Towns</field>
      <field name="author">Wishart, David J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




GHOST TOWNS

Ghost towns–towns that are extinct or so diminished
in population and function as to be
virtually extinct–are the most common category
of towns in the Great Plains. Daniel C.
Fitzgerald, author of Faded Dreams, estimates
that there are 6,000 such places in Kansas
alone. Towns withered on the land and disappeared
from the maps even in the very first
years of Plains settlement as speculative ventures
failed or highly mobile populations
moved on to better opportunities, generally
to the west. (For example, Omadi in northeastern
Nebraska, founded in 1856, emptied
out to the Colorado gold mines in 1859.)
Ghost towns are still being created as the rural
population that once sustained them thins,
leaving schools and stores closed, young people
gone, and perhaps only an elevator or a
church as a reminder of a more vibrant past.

In the Rocky Mountains the archetypical
ghost town was the product of a collapsed
mining boom, and there are examples of such
towns in the Great Plains also. Hundreds of
Black Hills mining towns lasted only as long
as the gold, often only months. In Crawford
County in southeastern Kansas, dozens of
clapboard company towns sprang up during
the coal boom of the early twentieth century,
went into protracted decline in the 1930s, and
disappeared when the mine shafts were sealed.
Just to the south, in Cherokee County, a similar
cycle in lead and zinc mining left towns like
Treece (which once sustained a population
of 749) abandoned. Farther south again, oil
towns (like Three Sands in Noble County,
Oklahoma, founded in 1921) started quickly,
roared briefly, then, as the oil and gas became
too expensive to tap, went into a long decline.

In the Great Plains, however, the characteristic
ghost town is the diminished rural service
center. After farm mechanization reduced
the need for labor on the land and automobiles
increased the distance that farmers could
travel to the elevator and implement store,
there were simply too many of these towns,
which had been founded during the horseand-
buggy era when farmers needed local access
to goods and services. The first towns
to drop out of the network were the "inland
towns," those places that never secured a railroad
and that were, therefore, at a great competitive
disadvantage. As John C. Hudson
shows in his detailed study of town building
and competition in northern North Dakota in
the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries,
farmers would generally make a longer
trip to a railroad town to buy cheaper goods
rather than shop locally at the more expensive
inland town store. Consequently, the inland
towns went under. Many successful railroad
towns of the late nineteenth century such as
Blaine in Pottawatomie County, Kansas, also
fell victim to transportation changes. After
the 1930s, as railroad companies consolidated
their lines, Blaine was left stranded inland.
Its grass-covered Main Street is now deserted
and lined with crumbling buildings that once
housed hotels, livery stables, retail outlets, and
a bank. Only the St. Columbkille Catholic
Church remains (albeit with drastically reduced
services) to recall the better times.

The number of towns in the Great Plains
continues to decrease as the rural population
shrinks. In North Dakota all but six of the fifty-three
counties lost population during the
1990s. Nelson County, for example, in the
northeastern part of the state, suffered a 17 percent
population decline during those years.
There, the neat Norwegian town of Whitman
is not yet a ghost town, but it is heading in that
direction: its four bars, two general stores, and
grain elevator are closed; deaths far exceed
births; the Lutheran church still offers services
but only to twelve members.

Towns like Whitman are still greatly valued
by their residents not just for nostalgic reasons
but as good places to raise a family. But in
those parts of the Plains too far from prosperous
cities to serve as dormitory suburbs,
from the major highways to reap the benefits
from gas stations, restaurants, and motels, and
from the "oases" where abundant surface or
groundwater provides the irrigated agriculture
that sustains feedlots, implement dealers,
and grain processing, many of the settlements
seem destined to dwindle, eventually to join
the ranks of ghost towns.


David J. Wishart
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Fitzgerald, Daniel C. Faded Dreams: More Ghost Towns of Kansas. Lawrence: University Press of Kansas, 1994. Hudson,
John C. Plains Country Towns. Minneapolis: University
of Minnesota Press, 1985. Kilborn, Peter T. "Boom in
Economy Skips Towns on the Plains." New York Times,
July 2, 2000: 1, 13.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>