<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pd.020</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Farmers Holiday Association</field>
      <field name="author">Vollan, Charles</field>
      <field name="text">

 




FARMERS HOLIDAY ASSOCIATION

The Farmers Holiday Association, active from
1932 to 1937, served as the nominal organization
behind a protest movement by mostly
midwestern and Great Plains farmers in reaction
to more than ten years of depressed farm
income. During World War I farmers met increased
worldwide demand for food by increasing
their farm sizes and mechanizing
their operations. Both strategies proved to be
problematic following the post-World War I
crash of the farm economy that occurred when
foreign markets contracted and wartime price
controls ended. After a decade of neglect by the
major political parties, many farmers looked
to protest movements and third parties as
the Great Depression compounded their economic
difficulties.

The Farmers Holiday Association grew out
of the National Farmers Union, an organization
that lobbied for farm aid and tariff reform,
as well as operating purchasing and sales
cooperatives. The name referred to the famous
"Bank Holiday," farmers noting that if bankers
could take a holiday to reorder their business,
they should be allowed to do the same. The
National Farmers Union and the Farmers Holiday
Association remained closely linked, in
part because the primary leader of the Farmers
Holiday Association, Milo Reno, had also been
the head of the Iowa Farmers Union. Milo
Reno remained central to the organization
well past its peak in 1933, and the Iowa chapter
was the strongest and most active branch of the
organization. Although the organization was
national, it received greatest support in the
Upper Midwest and Northern Great Plains:
Iowa, Nebraska, Minnesota, Wisconsin, South
Dakota, and North Dakota drew the largest
number of followers. Each state chapter acted
independently. In Nebraska, the Communist
Party attempted to gain some degree of control,
but despite considerable activity and media
exposure, it had only limited influence.

Most members owned property or had recently
become tenants. Association members
never constituted a majority of farmers in any
region, which weakened their position and
virtually guaranteed conflict with their neighbors.
The core concept of the movement, cost
of production, centered on the belief that
farmers must make a profit on their commodities.
In an era when many commodities sold
for less than they cost to produce, this idea
had obvious appeal. Under the system proposed
by the Farmers Holiday Association,
farmers would be allowed to grow all they
wanted, and the federal government would
mandate a price high enough to cover the
costs of mortgage, seed, equipment, and labor
plus guarantee a profit on commodities intended
for the domestic market. The government
would then sell the surplus on world
markets at true market value. Similar ideas,
embodied in the McNary-Haugen Bill, failed
to win enough support to override President
Calvin Coolidge's vetoes in the 1920s. Other
positions advocated by the organization included
tariff reform and currency inflation.

The mechanism for change would be the
farm strike, or "holiday." The original plan, as
conceived by Reno and advocated by him as
early as 1921, would call for farmers to cease
selling their products or buying anything
from anyone. What gave the movement power
and importance was the unplanned radical
behavior of its members, who, acting without
instructions from official leadership, barricaded
roads and forced nonstriking farmers to
turn away from their markets. Strikers, barricade
runners, and law enforcement officers
all committed acts of violence. There were a
few deaths.

Of almost equal importance to the barricades
were efforts to stop farm foreclosure
sales by transforming them into "penny" or
"Sears and Roebuck" sales. Farmers refused to
bid more than pennies on the dollar for foreclosed
property, even threatening those who
attempted to enter higher bids. Following the
sale the property would be returned to the
original owner. In many cases striking farmers
found active sympathy from state and local
politicians and from local law enforcement
agencies.

The largest strike lasted from early August
to early September 1932 but was successful
only in Sioux City and Omaha. Nationally, the
planned uprising of farmers failed to materialize.
Other strikes failed to achieve their stated
goals, but they did pressure the authorities to
take action to relieve the crisis. Among the
most important results were agreements by
major lenders to temporarily halt farm foreclosures
and legislation enacting statewide
moratoriums on foreclosures in Nebraska,
South Dakota, and Minnesota.

The power of the Farmers Holiday Association
declined with the election of Franklin D.
Roosevelt to the presidency in 1932. Milo Reno
urged a temporary halt to action in the belief
that Roosevelt supported cost of production.
But Roosevelt's secretary of agriculture, Henry
Wallace, was opposed, favoring instead control
of production coupled with payments for
acres taken out of service, and these measures
were embodied in the Agricultural Adjustment
Act. Although Farmers Holiday Association
leaders threatened continued strikes, the
organization lost its ability to influence farmers,
now mollified by the receipt of government
checks. In its latter years, the organization
and its leader, Milo Reno, flirted with
supporters of radical action, including Huey
Long, Father Charles Coughlin, and Francis
Townsend, but the movement never again
achieved its earlier levels of success. While the
strikes were failures, the organization and its
members did bring the desperate plight of the
Midwest and Plains farm community to the
attention of the nation, which resulted in New
Deal farm relief legislation.

See also POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT: New Deal.


Charles Vollan
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Dyson, Lowell K. Red Harvest: The Communist Party and
American Farmers. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press,
1982. Shover, John. Cornbelt Rebellion: The Farmers' Holiday
Association. Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 1965.
White, Roland, ed. Milo Reno: Farmers' Union Pioneer.
Iowa City IA: Athens Press, 1941.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>