<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.081</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Wiebe, Rudy (b. 1934)</field>
      <field name="author">Grace, Sherrill</field>
      <field name="text">

 




WIEBE, RUDY (b. 1934)

Canadian author Rudy Wiebe was born on
October 4, 1934, near Fairholme, Saskatchewan,
four years after his parents emigrated from Russia.
Growing up in a German-speaking community,
Wiebe did not learn English until he attended
school.

Wiebe's best-known novels are set in the
Canadian Prairies and explore the lives of
Mennonites, his own people, as well as those
of historic First Nations and Métis leaders and
contemporary Canadians who struggle to understand
their regional, cultural, and personal
history. Peace Shall Destroy Many (1962) describes
a community in Saskatchewan during
World War II. The Blue Mountains of China
(1970) traces the migrations of Mennonite refugees
from Russia to China, South America,
and Canada, where a contemporary Mennonite
demonstrates his faith by carrying a
cross beside the Prairie highway. In his next
two novels, The Temptations of Big Bear (1973)
and The Scorched-Wood People (1977), Wiebe
focuses on events culminating in the 1885 rebellion
that led to the arrests of Native leaders
Big Bear and Poundmaker and to the execution
of Louis Riel. The Temptations of Big Bear, which won the 1973 Governor General's
Literary Award for fiction, is often considered
Wiebe's masterpiece. Among his other works
are A Discovery of Strangers (1994), an epic
novel about the first Franklin expedition into
the Canadian Northwest, which also won a
Governor General's Literary Award for fiction;
collections of short stories, including
River of Stone: Fiction and Memories (1995); a
novella about Albert Johnson called The Mad Trapper (1980); a play about the Prairies called
Far as the Eye Can See (1977); essays; and the
autobiographical work, Playing Dead: A Contemplation Concerning the Arctic (1989), in
which Wiebe meditates upon the power of
stories to create identity and a sense of place.

Wiebe has taught English and creative writing
at the University of Alberta since 1967. In
1987 he was awarded the Royal Society of Canada's
Lorne Pierce Medal.

See also NATIVE AMERICANS: Big Bear / RELIGION: Mennonites.


Sherrill Grace
University of British Columbia




Grace, Sherrill. "Western Myth and Northern History:
The Plains Indians of Berger and Wiebe." Great Plains Quarterly 3 (1983): 146–56. Van Toorn, Penny. Rudy Wiebe and the Historicity of the World. Edmonton: University of
Alberta Press, 1995.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>