<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.sr.032</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Jackson, Phil (b. 1945)</field>
      <field name="author">Holmes, Roger</field>
      <field name="text">

 




JACKSON, PHIL (b. 1945)

Born on September 17, 1945, in Deer Lodge,
Montana, and brought up in Williston, North
Dakota, Phil Jackson is one of the most successful
coaches in the history of the National
Basketball Association. Between 1990 and
2002 Jackson's Chicago Bulls and Los Angeles
Lakers teams won nine NBA championships.
Through the 2001-2002 season, Jackson had
the highest career-winning percentage in NBA
history in regular season games (.738) and
play-off games (.742).

Jackson's success is a study in contrasts. At a
time when the NBA vigorously promotes its
individual stars, he wins by preaching selfless
team play. In a game requiring the highest levels
of physical skill, he emphasizes the mental
and spiritual condition of his players. The
coaching philosophy underpinning this approach
is an amalgam of influences ranging
from Jackson's native Great Plains to the Far
East. "The day I took over the Chicago Bulls,"
he writes in his book Sacred Hoops, "I vowed to
create an environment based on the principles
of selflessness and compassion I'd learned as
a Christian in my parents' home; sitting on
a cushion practicing Zen; and studying the
teachings of the Lakota Sioux." The son of two
Pentecostal ministers, Jackson was a devoted
student of the Bible, and his parents had hopes
of him entering the ministry. He was also a
gifted athlete, a pro prospect in baseball and a
standout basketball player on the 1963 Williston
High School state championship team. He
accepted a basketball scholarship to the University
of North Dakota, where he played under
future NBA coach Bill Fitch. While twice
earning all-American honors on the court,
Jackson studied psychology, philosophy, and
religion in the classroom and became involved
in the charged politics of the Vietnam War era.
He graduated in 1967.

A second-round draft choice of the New
York Knicks in 1967, Jackson spent ten of his
thirteen seasons with that team. He was never
a star, but the gangly six-foot-eight-inch Jackson
was a valuable role player on a team that
featured several future NBA Hall of Fame players,
including Bill Bradley, the future senator
and presidential candidate. During this time
Jackson broadened his personal horizons, exploring
various religious and meditative traditions
and conducting summer basketball
clinics on the Pine Ridge Reservation in South
Dakota.

In 1978 Jackson was traded to the New Jersey
Nets and got his first taste of coaching as
a player/assistant coach. After retiring as a
player, he spent the 1980s learning the coaching
craft and paying his dues in the Continental
Basketball Association and the Puerto
Rican summer leagues. In 1987 Jackson accepted
an assistant coaching job with the Chicago
Bulls, a team with a prodigiously gifted
young player named Michael Jordan and a
losing record. In 1989, frustrated by more mediocre
seasons, Bulls' management offered the
head coaching job to Jackson. Within two
years, the Bulls were NBA champions. By the
end of the 1990s Jackson was recognized as
one of the game's all-time great coaches, a reputation
solidified by his continued success as
head coach of the Los Angeles Lakers.


Roger Holmes
Lincoln, Nebraska




Jackson, Phil, and Hugh Delahanty. Sacred Hoops. New
York: Hyperion, 1995.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>