<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pe.068</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Wind</field>
      <field name="author">Stooksbury, David Emory</field>
      <field name="text">

 




WIND

In popular imagination and folklore wind is
the weather element that typifies the Great
Plains. From the warming chinook winds of
the High Plains to howling blizzards and
threatening tornadoes, wind shapes how residents
and others view the Plains. Wind is an
important player in the mythology of Great
Plains Native Americans, and the wind is frequently
mentioned in other Plains literature,
including The Wonderful Wizard of Oz. Homesteaders
made frequent mention of the wind in
their journals. None of this is surprising: apart
from some coastal regions, the Great Plains is
the windiest portion of North America.

Since the beginning of homesteading on the
Plains, wind has been primarily associated
with disaster. Blizzards have meant catastrophe
for the cattle industry. Grass fires fanned
by wind have raced across the landscape, destroying
buildings and fences while at the
same time renewing the Plains ecosystem.
Tornadoes have brought death and destruction
to the region, obliging residents to build
storm cellars and to reinforce rooms for protection.
Farmers and ranchers have planted
shelterbelts to shield fields from soil erosion,
crops from moisture loss, and cattle from
wind-driven snow.

But wind is also a natural resource for
the Great Plains. For more than 150 years,
ranchers and farmers have used windmills to
pump groundwater, without which settlement
would have been severely restricted. During
the 1930s and 1940s, small electric wind generators
were used on remote homesteads to
power radios. With the coming of inexpensive
and reliable grid-based electricity, the electric
wind generator all but disappeared from the
Great Plains. By the 1990s, however, largescale
wind projects were being developed in
Alberta, North Dakota, Colorado, Kansas, Nebraska,
Texas, and Wyoming. It is likely that
wind will again become an important energy
resource for Plains residents.

The power of the wind also has a major
impact on the topography of the Great Plains.
Soil erosion and deposition shapes the topography
of the region. During the drought
years of the 1930s, tons of topsoil were transported
east by the wind from the Southern
and Central Plains. Despite conservation efforts,
blowing dust from plowed fields and
tumbleweeds piled against fences are still emblematic
scenes on the Great Plains.

See also INDUSTRY: Wind Energy.


David Emory Stooksbury
University of Georgia





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>