<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.sr.035</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Mantle, Mickey (1931-1995)</field>
      <field name="author">Krause, Kent</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MANTLE, MICKEY (1931-1995)

"New York Yankees centerfielder and Hall of Famer Mickey Mantle about 1953" (Photograph by Bowman Gum)
 

One of the most recognized names in baseball
history, Mickey Mantle starred for the New
York Yankees in the 1950s and 1960s. Born in
Spavinaw, Oklahoma, on October 20, 1931, he
later moved with his family to nearby Commerce.
Mantle's father, a lead and zinc miner,
spent countless hours developing his son's
baseball talent. While growing up, Mantle
played on numerous local sandlot and youth
teams. He graduated from Commerce High
School in 1949 and was signed by the Yankees
to play for their Class D minor-league team in
Independence, Kansas. In 1950 he played in
Joplin, Missouri, for a Class C team, and in the
off-season he returned to Oklahoma to work
with his father in the mines.

After an impressive spring training in 1951,
Mantle was promoted by New York to the major
leagues. Over the next eighteen seasons the
"Commerce Comet" established himself as
the greatest switch-hitter in the game's history.
Among his numerous achievements, Mantle
led the league in home runs four times and
won three most valuable player awards and
one Triple Crown. Elected to the National
Baseball Hall of Fame in his first year of eligibility,
he finished his career with a .298 batting
average and 536 home runs. Mantle's impressive
statistics could have been even better had
he not been plagued by numerous injuries.
Following his retirement, Mantle's legend
grew, and he was still a hero to millions in the
1990s. After decades of heavy drinking, he required
a liver transplant in June 1995 and died
on August 13 of the same year.


Kent M. Krause
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Borst, William A. "Mantle, Mickey Charles." In A Biographical
Dictionary of American Sports: Baseball, edited
by David L. Porter. Westport CT: Greenwood Press, 1987.
Falkner, David. The Last Hero: The Life of Mickey Mantle.
New York: Simon and Schuster, 1995. Mantle, Mickey,
with Herb Glick. The Mick. Garden City NY: Doubleday,
1985.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>