<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.rel.002</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Adventism</field>
      <field name="author">Knight, George R.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ADVENTISM

Seventh-day Adventism, which arose in the
northeastern United States in the 1840s, holds
several doctrinal beliefs. Distinctive of their
doctrinal system, and reflected in the denomination's
name, is a belief in the perpetuity
of the seventh-day Sabbath as the day
of rest for Christians and a belief in the visible
and literal return of Jesus Christ in the not too
distant future. The denomination is evangelical
in the sense that it holds for salvation by
grace through faith. The church worldwide
now has a presence in 205 of the 230 nations
recognized by the United Nations.

Members of the Seventh-day Adventist
Church first settled in the Great Plains at
Omaha, Nebraska, in 1858. As of 1999 the region
hosted approximately 50,000 of the 10
million Adventists worldwide. That membership
is distributed rather evenly across the
Great Plains. The Mid-America Union Conference
(headquartered in Lincoln, Nebraska)
is the administrative unit that is responsible
for most of the region. The southern part of
the Great Plains falls within the jurisdiction of
the Southwestern Union Conference (Burleson,
Texas), while the Canadian Union Conference
(or Seventh-day Adventist Church in
Canada, with headquarters in Oshawa, Ontario)
includes the northern part. Those administrative
units supervise the work of eleven
local conferences that are included in or intersect
the Great Plains. The membership in
the Great Plains is, in general, proportionate
among the various racial groups of the region.
The major exception to that generalization is
Native Americans. Although Adventists have
missions to the Native American population,
those missions have not prospered in relative
proportion to other Adventist work in the
region.

Adventists in the Great Plains sponsor a
large number of elementary schools, several
secondary schools ("academies"), and three
tertiary institutions: Union College in Lincoln,
Nebraska; Southwestern Adventist University
in Keene, Texas, near the southern edge of the
Plains; and Canadian University College near
its northern boundary in College Heights, Alberta.
The church also operates several medical
facilities in the Great Plains. The most significant
are the PorterCare hospitals in Denver,
Louisville, and Littleton, Colorado; the Central
Texas Medical Center in San Marcos,
Texas; and the Huguley Memorial Medical
Centers west of Fort Worth, Texas.


George R. Knight
Andrews University




Dick, Everett. Union College of the Golden Cords. Lincoln
NE: Union College Press, 1967. Knight, George R. A Brief
History of Seventh-day Adventists. Hagerstown MD: Review
and Herald, 1999. Neufeld, Don F., ed. Seventh-day Adventist
Encyclopedia. Hagerstown MD: Review and Herald,
1996.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>