<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.edu.011</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Center for Great Plains Studies at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln</field>
      <field name="author">Stubbendieck, James</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CENTER FOR GREAT PLAINS STUDIES AT THE UNIVERSITY OF NEBRASKA-LINCOLN

The Center for Great Plains Studies at the
University of Nebraska–Lincoln is the oldest
and largest interdisciplinary regional research
and teaching center in the United States. It was
founded by Paul A. Olson and chartered in
1976 by the board of regents of the University
of Nebraska. Two grants from the National
Endowment for the Humanities and many
donations received through the University
of Nebraska Foundation financed the center's
beginnings. Continued support is provided
by the Friends of the Center for Great Plains
Studies. The purpose of the center is to foster
the study of people and the environment in
the Great Plains. The center's activities embrace
the three-part mission of education, research,
and service of a comprehensive landgrant
university. The center is administered in
the College of Arts and Sciences.

The center's Great Plains Art Collection includes
significant paintings, sculptures, and
photographs of the region and the American
West and a library of western Americana. Several
exhibits each year feature portions of the
twelve-million-dollar permanent collection as
well as works from other institutions and individuals.
The exhibits are displayed in the
center's Christlieb Gallery, located in Hewit
Place, which was constructed in 2000.

The center has 180 fellows elected from the
four campuses of the University of Nebraska.
Fellows conduct research, teach, and provide
service directly relating to the Great Plains.
A twelve-member board of governors elected
from the fellows provides advice to the center's
director. Academics at other institutions
may be elected as associate fellows.

Undergraduate students may major or minor
in Great Plains studies, and masters and
doctoral candidates may specialize in Great
Plains studies. The monthly Paul A. Olson
Seminars in Great Plains Studies present topics
of interest to students, faculty, and members
of the community. The annual symposium
addresses regional topics and attracts a
regional, national, and international audience.
Research and creative activity includes publication
of the refereed journals Great Plains
Quarterly, devoted to regional essays in the
humanities, and Great Plains Research, which
examines the natural and social sciences.
Plains Song Review publishes essays, poems,
and short stories by students and regional authors.
The thirteen-volume Journals of the
Lewis and Clark Expedition, edited by Gary
Moulton, was completed in 2001. This Encyclopedia
of the Great Plains is also a project of the
Center for Great Plains Studies.

UNL Center for Great Plains Studies website.


James Stubbendieck
University of Nebraska-Lincoln





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>