<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.med.020</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Freeman, Legh (1842-1915)</field>
      <field name="author">Huntzicker, William E.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




FREEMAN, LEGH (1842-1915)

Legh Freeman was born on December 4, 1842,
in Culpeper, Virginia. During the Civil War he
served as a telegraph operator in the Confederate
army. He was captured in 1864 but later
released after swearing allegiance to the Union
and agreeing to serve in the American West. In
April 1865 Freeman arrived at Fort Kearny,
Nebraska, where troops were needed to guard
the Oregon Trail. After being mustered out of
the service late in 1865, Freeman acquired
some old printing equipment and began editing
and publishing the Kearney Herald. He
was joined in 1866 by his brother Frederick,
and when the Union Pacific moved past Kearney
that fall, the brothers packed up their
equipment, renamed their paper the Frontier Index, and moved to North Platte. Sometimes
called the "press on wheels," the Frontier Index
then moved from one railroad construction
camp to the next, including the future towns
of North Platte, Nebraska; Julesburg, Colorado;
Laramie, Wyoming; and Ogden, Utah.

One study of Freeman's extant editorials
found that 25 percent promoted town sites, 16
percent discussed local nonpolitical affairs,
15 percent local politics, 7 percent Indian issues,
and 5 percent the newspaper itself. In
his editorials he vociferously attacked Mormons,
Chinese, Indians, politicians, opposition
editors, construction-camp lawlessness,
and President Ulysses S. Grant. On at least one
occasion Freeman's biting editorials cost him
his press and nearly his life. On November 20,
1868, in Bear River City, Dakota Territory
(soon to be Wyoming Territory), a mob of
infuriated railroad workers destroyed Freeman's
printing equipment and drove him out
of town.

Freeman never stayed in one place too long.
Like the mountain men he emulated, the editor
tried to stay ahead of advancing settlement.
Freeman's brother Fred and later his
wife, Ada, sometimes ran the paper while he
traveled and sent home columns. Freeman
stayed in the newspaper business long after
the completion of the transcontinental railroad:
he published newspapers in Utah, Montana,
and Washington. He married three times
and had four children. His later years were
spent in Washington, where he published the
Washington Farmer and became involved in
the populist movement. Representing himself
as the "Red Horse Candidate," Freeman failed
twice to obtain a senatorial seat and finished
last in the 1914 North Yakima mayoral election.
He died February 7, 1915, in North Yakima,
Washington.

See also CITIES AND TOWNS: "Hell on Wheels" Towns.


William E. Huntzicker
Bemidji State University




Heuterman, Thomas H. Movable Type: Biography of Legh R. Freeman. Ames: Iowa State University Press, 1979. Lent,
John A. "The Press on Wheels: A History of the Frontier
Index." Journal of the West 10 (1971): 662–99. Wright, Elizabeth.
Independence in All Things, Neutrality in Nothing: The Story of a Pioneer Journalist of the American West. San
Francisco: Miller Freeman Publications, 1973.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>