<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.003</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Alberta</field>
      <field name="author">Leeson, Howard A.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ALBERTA


Alberta Legislature building, Edmonton


Anchoring the northwestern edge of the Great
Plains and nestled against the Rocky Mountains,
the province of Alberta, Canada, is a
unique blend of European and North American
influences, a blend that has produced a
political system characterized by strong leaders,
strong political parties, and strong governments.
Interestingly, this uniqueness can
be traced to the influence of those who settled
the Great Plains on both sides of the forty-ninth
parallel. It is a prime example of how
geography and human migration have intersected
to produce new political behavior.

Canada is a federal state. Like other federations
it has a system of government that constitutionally
divides power between central
and constituent governments. In Canada the
latter are called provinces. The institutions of
government are modeled largely on the British
parliamentary system as it existed in the
nineteenth century. There is an elected legislature
in each province, with a cabinet consisting
of a premier and ministers who are members
of the House. Although the Queen is
nominally the provincial head of state, in
practice this position is occupied by an appointed
official called the lieutenant governor.
Elections are held on a regular basis, usually
every four years, and are contested by several
political parties, many of which have unique
roots in the province.

Alberta was created in 1905 as one of the
new provinces carved out of the old Northwest
Territories, which had stretched from
Manitoba north to the Arctic Ocean and west
and south to the Rocky Mountains. For political
reasons the Liberal government of Sir Wilfrid
Laurier ignored the advice of those supporting
a single province and created several
provinces instead. The result was Alberta,
Saskatchewan, and an enlarged Manitoba, increasing
the number of provinces in Canada
by two.

Initially the politics of Alberta followed the
traditional British and Canadian model, with
elections contested by the Liberal and Conservative
Parties. The Liberals, under the leadership
of A. C. Rutherford, were in power between
1905 and 1921. However, powerful social
and economic forces, together with the influx
of settlers from the midwestern United States,
changed the system dramatically after World
War I.

Alberta, like most of the Great Plains jurisdictions,
was a society rooted in the agricultural
development of the incredibly fertile
land of the Prairies. It was a society largely
dependent on the production and export of
grains. As with any such society, it was subject
to the boom and bust cycle of a single industry.
Thus, when prices for agricultural products
dropped dramatically after 1919, farmers
and their supporters looked for solutions to
the economic crisis.

They found their solution in radical populist
politics. The person most responsible
for promoting this approach was Henry Wise
Wood, an immigrant from the midwestern
United States, who brought with him strong
ideas about individualism and group government.
These found resonance and took root in
the Alberta of the 1920s. Together with other
farmers he founded the United Farmers of Alberta
(UFA), a movement that contested and
won the 1921 election. In defeating the Liberals
the UFA began a trend that continues to this
day. No political party that has been elected to
govern Alberta has ever returned to power after
it was defeated.

Populist politics dominated the Alberta
scene from 1921 until after World War II. In
the mid-1930s the UFA faltered as a result of a
series of internal scandals. It was completely
wiped out in the 1935 election. Its place in
government was taken by a new political party
called Social Credit, which ran for the first
time in that year under the leadership of William
Aberhart, a Protestant minister. Social
Credit won a stunning landslide victory in its
first electoral contest.

Although Social Credit was a populist party,
it differed in many important respects from its
predecessor. Its basic ideology was taken from
the teachings of Maj. Clifford Douglas, an
Englishman who proposed a comprehensive
monetary policy for dealing with the role of
government in society. While these ideas were
soon discarded in practice, the party continued
to espouse them in theory until the late
1960s. Finally, while the UFA had been radical
democrats, Social Credit was more plebiscitarian
and less tolerant of political dissent. After
the death of Aberhart in 1943 the party
elected E. C. Manning, a protégé of his. (In
2000 his son, E. P. Manning, headed the Reform
Party at the national level in Canada.)
Social Credit stayed in power until 1971.

The discovery and exploitation of huge oil
and gas reserves in Alberta after World War II
dramatically changed the economic and social
landscape of Alberta. In twenty years the
province moved from a largely rural agricultural
society to an urban, resource-based
community. This brought with it some political
changes. In 1971, after thirty-five years in
office, the Social Credit Party was defeated.
Peter Lougheed, a Calgary lawyer, led the new
Progressive Conservative government. It was
strongly particularistic and protective of the
oil industry and its benefits. It had several
confrontations with the federal government
over natural resources and the revenue from
them.

After 1982, when the New Democratic Party
under Grant Notley became the Official Opposition,
politics in the province seemed to be
adjusting to a left-right division. Notley's
death in 1984, and the inability of his successors
to hold on to their position, however,
resulted in a return to one-party dominance.
The Liberal Party, which has not regained
power since 1921, is now the Official Opposition,
but the Progressive Conservative Party
has been firmly in office for twenty-seven
years.

The history of politics in Alberta has been
dominated by two characteristics. The first is a
strong sense of political alienation. Albertans
have tended to see their role in Canada as undervalued
and ignored. This strong sense of
grievance has led them to elect representatives
who are prepared to "fight for Alberta and the
west." The second is the plebiscitarian nature
of politics in the province. Most governments
have received strong mandates, with little opposition.
However, once rejected, parties have
forever remained excluded. In a sense, despite
the present strong economic base and the obvious
wealth of the province, Albertans continue
to exhibit the political behavior of an
earlier, more marginal time. Grievance and
alienation, once instilled in a political culture,
are difficult to remove.

The politics of Alberta today is as fascinating
as it was at the turn of the twentieth century.
It is a prime example of how the geographical
features and settlement patterns of
the North American Great Plains have shaped
social and political behavior to create unique
and interesting societies.

See also INDUSTRY: Petroleum, Canada / PROTEST AND DISSENT: Aberhart, William.


Howard A. Leeson
University of Regina




Calderola, Carle. Society and Politics in Alberta. Toronto:
Methuen, 1979. Dyck, Rand. Provincial Politics in Canada.
Scarborough, Ontario: Prentice-Hall Canada, Inc., 1995.
MacGregor, James G. A History of Alberta. Edmonton:
Hurtig Publishers, 1972.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>