<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ea.028</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Mores, Marquis de (1858-1896)</field>
      <field name="author">Daly, Janet</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MORES, MARQUIS DE (1858-1896)

The Marquis de Mores was a part-time resident
of the Badlands of western Dakota Territory
for only three years, 1883–86, but the
French nobleman left his mark on the region's
history. The village he founded and named
after his wife, Medora, is a thriving tourist site
where the tall, brick chimney of his meatpacking
plant still stands as a lonely symbol of his
ambitious business enterprises.

Born in Paris on June 14, 1858, Antoine-
Amedee-Marie-Vincent-Amat Manca de Vallombrosa
was well educated and fluent in English,
German, and Italian. He fell in love
with a young American woman, Medora von
Hoffman, the daughter of a wealthy New York
banker, and they were married on February
15, 1882, in Cannes, France. Working in
his father-in-law's Wall Street bank, de Mores
looked for investment opportunities, and in
April 1883 he chose a site near the Little Missouri
River in the Dakota Badlands as the
place to make his entrepreneurial dreams a
reality. He formed a corporation known as the
Northern Pacific Refrigerated Car Company
and began buying cattle and building abattoirs,
a meatpacking plant, and a railway spur
to provide growing eastern markets with fresh
meat shipped directly from the range in refrigerated
railcars. In addition, the Marquis
built a large home (today known as the Chateau
de Mores State Historic Site), a hotel, a
Roman Catholic church, blocks of businesses,
and a brick home for his in-laws. Many of the
structures still stand.

The Marquis and his family typically spent
part of the year, from the late spring to the
early fall, in Medora, where despite the challenges
of his cattle and ranching operations,
the Marquis found time, money, and energy to
invest in sheep and horses, ship salmon in
from the Columbia River, and begin a stage
and freight line between Medora and Deadwood
in present-day South Dakota. Though
the Marquis had the financial backing of
his father-in-law, his many business ventures
failed: opposition from other meat dealers in
Chicago and New York limited his beef distribution
efforts, and the stage line lost its bid
for the mail contract, which left it unprofitable.
Though the Marquis participated in
stockmen's associations and entertained guests
such as fellow rancher Theodore Roosevelt, he
could not escape controversy. Charged with
the 1883 murder of a Badlands cowboy, Riley
Luffsey, the Marquis was tried and acquitted
three times. The de Mores family left Medora
in the fall of 1886, but the Marquis continued
to attract attention. When he moved from the
United States to France, his anti-Semitic positions
and views on social reform brought
him disapproval and arrest. In June 1896 he
was killed in North Africa and was buried in
Cannes, France.


Janet Daley
State Historical Society of North Dakota




Arnold O. Goplen. The Career of the Marquis de Mores in the Badlands of North Dakota. Bismarck: State Historical
Society of North Dakota, 1994. Virginia Heidenreich-
Barber, ed. Aristocracy on the Western Frontier: The Legacy of the Marquis de Mores. Bismarck: State Historical Society
of North Dakota, 1994. D. Jerome Tweton. "The Marquis
de Mores and His Dakota Venture: A Study in Failure."
Journal of the West 6 (1967): 521–34.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>