<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ct.049</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Small Towns</field>
      <field name="author">Engel, Matthew R.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SMALL TOWNS


Tribune, Kansas


Small towns in the Great Plains generally developed
as a result of a connection to a transportation
network that linked the town and
the surrounding area to the more densely settled
regions to the east. The basic economic
role of most small towns was and still is to
serve as nodes of collection for agricultural
goods produced in the region for transport
outside the region and as supply centers for
area residents. Resource extraction is the economic
basis for several communities, but
this is a far less common role. Northwestern
North Dakota, for example, has a network of
towns dedicated to coal mining, and southern
Saskatchewan has multiple communities engaged
in mining potash, but resource-oriented
towns are vastly outnumbered by agricultural
towns.

The early small towns (Nebraska City in
Nebraska Territory and Yankton in Dakota
Territory, for example) developed along the
Missouri River, but it was the railroads that
were responsible for the creation of the greatest
number of small towns on the Plains. Railroad
officials or their agents spaced communities
at specific intervals along lines in an
effort to maximize economic efficiency. The
distance a farmer could transport grain to an
elevator determined the space between each
elevator and thus between each accompanying
town. This town pattern, introduced in the
latter decades of the nineteenth century, is
still evident today: grain elevators remain the
dominant town feature looming on the horizon
at regular intervals as one travels through
the region.

Standardized morphology characterizes
railroad communities. Towns bisected by
tracks, Main Streets perpendicular to the
tracks in a T-town pattern, and Main Streets
crossing the tracks are all characteristic forms
on the Plains. The ascendancy of towns along
rail corridors occurred largely at the expense
of small towns dependent on river transportation,
especially those unable to attract the new
mode of transportation. Today, however, the
importance of the railroad for each community
is vastly diminished from the days when
the railroad was often the sole connection to
the larger world.

The transportation revolution in the twentieth
century altered the economic foundation
of Great Plains communities. The rise of the
automobile and the construction of a road
network have been the greatest factors affecting
the fate of these small communities. The
automobile allowed rural consumers as well as
residents of small trade centers to bypass local
merchants in favor of cheaper and larger selections
in higher-order regional centers or
even metropolitan areas. In South Dakota and
Nebraska, where license plates designate the
county in which a car is registered, rural consumers
can be easily identified in the parking
lots of malls in Rapid City, Sioux Falls, Lincoln,
and Omaha. With the railroad tracks
grassed over or torn up altogether and with
residents shopping and attending school in
larger towns, many small towns (particularly
those under 500 population) have gone into
protracted decline. Their Main Streets have
a gap-toothed appearance, with a significant
number of buildings abandoned or in a state
of disrepair.

The case of Purcell, Oklahoma, thirty miles
south of Oklahoma City, serves as an example
of how outside forces buffet small places.
Founded by the Santa Fe Railroad in 1887, the
town became a major node of the railroad in
southern Oklahoma. Purcell weathered the
Great Depression better than many small communities
on the Southern Plains, but most of
the employment related to the railroad was
consolidated in Oklahoma City after the end
of World War II. A line, still used, passes
through town. Its main function now is the
transportation of agricultural goods to the national
market. No longer tied to the fortunes
of the railroad, the community was forced to
adjust to a new role in order to survive. Today
the local chamber of commerce touts Purcell's
proximity to Interstate 35 and the Oklahoma
City metropolitan area as assets. While Amtrak
has a stop in Purcell, most of the functions
related to the railroad are long gone, and
tourism is now the main source of revenue.
The town's Main Street reflects this tourist
orientation. Businesses designed to capture
the tourist dollar such as antique shops are
interspersed among businesses catering to the
local residents such as lawyers and insurance
offices.

A second challenge for small towns is the
impact of agricultural restructuring. As farms
and ranches in the region become larger in
size and fewer in number, the total number of
spenders and consumers in the small towns
decreases. The slow decline in the number of
jobs in the area affects the communities in a
manner similar to towns dependent on a declining
mining sector, although the slide is
much more gradual. The decreasing number
of dollars spent in town from the hinterland
drastically impairs the economic health of the
community.

A variety of efforts may be made to add jobs
to a town and arrest its decline. While many
small or medium-size meat-processing facilities
have operated in Plains towns for decades,
several experienced dramatic change
after meat-processing companies constructed
large facilities in their communities. As older,
higher-wage facilities in the eastern Midwest
closed, new plants opened in cities such as
Lexington, Nebraska, Garden City, Kansas,
and Guymon, Oklahoma. The influx of people
to these communities in the years immediately
following the construction of the
plants greatly altered their ethnic character.
For example, Lexington had a population of
6,601 in 1990. Ten years later, the population
had increased to 10,011, of whom 5,121
were Hispanic. Changes in the composition of
school population, religion (especially increased
Roman Catholicism), cuisine, the visible
landscape, and many other aspects of life
have enriched places like Lexington, but the
rapidity of change has also brought stress to
long-established residents for whom continuity
was long the norm.

Small towns that diversify economically
tend to be more secure. For instance, the presence
of a state or private college provides
insulation from shifts in the agricultural economy.
Communities also seek economic diversity
by competing with each other for new
correctional facilities. Prisons virtually guarantee
a constant payroll for the community,
with wages that are usually higher than those
paid by existing local jobs. Sterling, in northeast
Colorado, is one such place that succeeded
in attracting a prison and is now tied
to the criminal justice economy of the state.

Today several of the towns with the brightest
prospects are those that lie along a major
transportation corridor such as one of the interstates
crossing the Plains. For these towns,
the market comes to them in the form of motel
and restaurant customers or truck repairs
and gasoline sales. Towns adjacent to a metropolitan
area have also prospered. A significant
segment of workers residing in such towns departs
to the nearby city for daily employment.
Dell Rapids, South Dakota, for example, is
twenty miles north of Sioux Falls by interstate
or U.S. highway. Many of its 3,000 residents
commute to Sioux Falls, helping to buoy the
economy and maintain the population base of
the town. The economic base of Dell Rapids
has shifted from its traditional agricultural
and quarrying roles to that of a commuter
exurb.

From their inception to the present day,
small towns in the Great Plains have been economically
bound to the metropolitan areas of
Canada and the United States. Whether they
served (or still serve) as bases of resource extraction
or as points of collection for agricultural
goods, a main purpose was and is to
move raw materials out of the region to the
more densely settled areas of each country.
Processing and refining activities were generally
located on the margins of the Plains or
outside the region. The new meat-processing
plants represent an overall shift of placing
value-added industry on the Plains, at least
for one economic function. However, the
processing centers require large markets to
consume their products; thus the linkages
to higher-order places remain fundamentally
unchanged. In a similar fashion, the new prisons
are linked to metropolitan areas in the
sense that a significant portion of the incarcerated
population originates from the cities.
Therefore, much of the recent economic development
of prospering small towns on the
Plains is still dependent on their ties to larger
places.


Matthew R. Engel
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Hudson, John C. Plains Country Towns. Minneapolis:
University of Minnesota Press, 1986. Hurt, Douglas A.
"Railroad Influence on a Small Town Main Street: A View
of Purcell, Oklahoma." North American Geographer 1
(1999): 64-79. Stull, Donald D., Michael J. Broadway, and
David Craig Griffith, eds. Any Way You Cut It: Meat Processing and Small-Town America. Lawrence: University
Press of Kansas, 1995.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>