<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.art.017</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Dunn, Harvey (1884-1952)</field>
      <field name="author">Miller, John E.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




DUNN, HARVEY (1884-1952)

Harvey Thomas Dunn gained a high reputation
during his lifetime as a magazine illustrator,
war artist, and art teacher, but his longterm
significance became apparent only after
his death, as appreciation grew for the prairie
scenes he had painted during the last three
decades of his career. Donated to South Dakota
State College in 1950, two years before his
death, these evocative oil paintings might earlier
have gained him recognition along with
Thomas Hart Benton, Grant Wood, and John
Steuart Curry as a leading regionalist artist
had the art world been more aware of them.

Harvey Dunn was born on March 8, 1884,
on a rural homestead near Manchester in eastern
Dakota Territory, the son of William
Thomas Dunn and Bersha Dow Dunn, who
had moved there from Wisconsin. Uninterested
in farming and fascinated with drawing,
he obtained his first art training in the preparatory
department at South Dakota Agricultural
College in Brookings before going on
for further instruction at the Chicago Art Institute
and from the famous illustrator Howard
Pyle in Wilmington, Delaware.

After opening his own studio near that of
his former teacher, Dunn became immediately
successful as a magazine illustrator for
Scribner's, Harper's, the Saturday Evening Post,
and other publications. He was in great demand
from advertising agencies as well. The
drawings and paintings he executed as one of
eight official artists assigned to the American
Expeditionary Force in France during World
War I are among our most important documents
of that conflict.

After the war, magazine illustrating held
less appeal for Dunn, and he devoted increasing
amounts of time to teaching (his
students included Dean Cornwell and John
Steuart Curry) and painting prairie scenes of
the area in which he had grown up. Dunn died
of cancer at his Tenafly, New Jersey, home on
October 29, 1952. In later years Dunn's paintings
were frequently used in books and articles
as illustrations depicting life on the Plains
around the turn of the century.


John E. Miller
South Dakota State University




Howell, Edgar M. "Harvey Dunn: The Searching Artist
Who Came Home to His First Horizon." Montana 16
(1966): 41–56. Karolevitz, Robert F. Where Your Heart Is: The Story of Harvey Dunn, Artist. Aberdeen SD: North
Plains Press, 1970.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>