<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.na.057</field>
      <field name="titleMain">La Flesche, Susan (1865-1915)</field>
      <field name="author">Mathes, Valerie Sherer</field>
      <field name="text">

 




LA FLESCHE, SUSAN (1865-1915)

Photograph of Susan La Flesche Picotte


Physician and Indian reformer Susan La Flesche
Picotte was born in June 1865, the youngest
daughter of Joseph La Flesche, last traditional
chief of the Omaha tribe. Joseph's commitment
to education is reflected in her education. She
attended the local Presbyterian mission school,
the Omaha Agency Indian School, the Elizabeth
Institute for Young Ladies in Elizabeth, New
Jersey, and Hampton Normal and Agricultural
Institute in Virginia, where she graduated
in May 1886. Supported by the Connecticut
Branch of the Women's National Indian Association,
she attended the Woman's Medical
College of Pennsylvania, graduating in March
1889 at the head of her class. Following an
internship at the Woman's Hospital in Philadelphia,
she returned to her reservation to
practice medicine.

For the next four years, as government physician
at the Omaha Agency Indian School,
she dispensed medicine and encouraged tribal
members to become Christian. Her religious
dedication was rewarded years later, when in
1905 she was appointed medical missionary by
the Presbyterian Board of Home Missions.
Working out of the Blackbird Hills Presbyterian
Church, she read the Bible in the Omaha
language and held church services.

Ill health forced her resignation as government
physician in 1893. She married Henry
Picotte, a Sioux Indian from the Yankton
Agency, and upon regaining her strength, resumed
her medical practice in Bancroft and
later in Walthill, Nebraska, among both Indians
and whites. She lobbied for required
medical inspection of schools, sanitary ice
cream dishes and spoons, and free school
drinking fountains; fought against tuberculosis
and the common housefly; and campaigned
against alcohol following the death of her
hard-drinking husband. In addition, she organized
the Thurston County Medical Association,
served on Walthill's health board, chaired
the State Health Committee of the Nebraska
Federation of Women's Clubs, and organized a
hospital for Walthill in 1913. She also helped
organize a new church for Walthill, was active
as president of the church missionary society,
participated in a new chapter of the Eastern
Star, and supported various community projects,
lectures, and concerts.

In 1909, when the government arbitrarily extended
the trust period for protecting Omaha
land an additional ten years, she was chosen
unanimously by the tribe to head a delegation
to Washington DC. The Omahas were subsequently
declared competent to rent or lease their
lands and handle their own monies.

A product of the nineteenth-century reform
movement and its assimilationist policy,
she in turn helped her people prepare for
the twentieth century. She died on September
18, 1915, and was buried in the Bancroft cemetery.


Valerie Sherer Mathes
Sanoma, California




Mathes, Valerie Sherer. "Iron Eyes' Daughters: Susette and
Susan La Flesche, Nineteenth-Century Indian Reformers."
In By Grit and Grace: Eleven Women Who Shaped the American
West, edited by Glenda Riley and Richard Etulain.
Golden CO: Fulcrum Press, 1997: 135–52. Mathes, Valerie
Sherer. "Susan La Flesche Picotte, M.D.: Nineteenth-
Century Physician and Reformer." Great Plains Quarterly
13 (1993): 172–86. Tong, Benson. Susan La Flesche Picotte,
M.D.: Omaha Indian Leader and Reformer. Norman: University
of Oklahoma Press, 1999.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>