<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.war.046</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Strategic Air Command</field>
      <field name="author">Hughes, Scott D.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




STRATEGIC AIR COMMAND

The Strategic Air Command (SAC) was established
on March 21, 1946, to deter threats from
communist nations, prevent nuclear warfare,
and wage the cold war. SAC served to project a
global military presence as the bomber leg of
the United States nuclear triad that included
submarine-launched missiles and land-based
intercontinental ballistic missiles. Not solely
devoted to deploying nuclear weapons, SAC
made significant contributions to conventional
warfare in Vietnam and Iraq during the
Gulf War.

SAC languished from inadequate funding
and unclear direction during its first years under
commander Gen. George C. Kenney. As a
result of the Berlin blockade and airlift of 1948,
however, the mission of SAC crystallized. The
Berlin crisis had exposed serious structural
and logistical problems that threatened the
ability of the United States to enforce its policy
of containment against the Soviet Union. In
response, Gen. Curtis E. LeMay assumed command
of SAC and set about building a credible
airborne fighting force. After moving its headquarters
from Andrews Field, Maryland, to
Offutt Air Force Base near Omaha, Nebraska,
LeMay instituted fundamental changes in
training, housing, food services, and recreation.
A pragmatic leader, LeMay prepared SAC
for a war that could begin at any time and for
air combat and bombing missions that would
have to be deployed immediately. By 1949,
when the Soviets exploded their first atomic
bomb, SAC had mobilized its resources and
crew competence to levels sufficient to meet
this new challenge.

In the wake of the Soviet nuclear detonation,
the beginning of the Korean War, and
new initiatives detailed under NSC-68, the National
Security Council's blueprint for waging
the cold war, the role of SAC in the worldwide
defense of American interests grew. By 1950
SAC had 225 atomic bomb-carrying aircraft
(including B-29s, B-50s, and thirty-four B-36s).
As cold war relations deteriorated and both the
United States and the Soviet Union developed
thermonuclear weapons, SAC expanded its role
in providing strategic defensive and offensive
capabilities. In June 1955 SAC accepted delivery
of the first B-52, the jet bomber that became its
trademark symbol. In January 1957 SAC headquarters
moved to a new control center. From
a two-tiered building, comprised of a threestory
aboveground administrative structure
and a three-story belowground war command
center, SAC coordinated its global presence,
controlling both bomber and missile systems.

In late 1957, under its new commander,
Gen. Thomas S. Powers, SAC assumed its wellknown
motto, "Peace Is Our Profession." Also
during 1957, with cold war tensions increasing,
the American military establishment put
its nuclear forces on alert status. This condition
continued until September 28, 1991, when
President George H. W. Bush issued a stand-down
order, ending a thirty-five-year period
when American nuclear weapons were on
launch-ready status and a certain percentage
of the American nuclear bomber force continuously
remained airborne. SAC ceased to exist
on June 1, 1992, when the U.S. Strategic Command
(USSTRATCOM), also headquartered at
Offutt Air Force Base, took over control of
the nation's strategic forces for the post-cold
war era.

Strategic Air Command website.


Scott D. Hughes
Albuquerque, New Mexico




Hopkins, J. C., and Sheldon A. Goldberg. The Development
of SAC, 1946-1986: The Fortieth Anniversary History.
Offutt Air Force Base, Nebraska: Office of the Historian,
1988.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>