<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.law.020</field>
      <field name="titleMain">In Cold Blood</field>
      <field name="author">Rocha, Guy Louis</field>
      <field name="text">

 




IN COLD BLOOD

In Cold Blood film poster
     

In Cold Blood is the compelling and controversial
account of the brutal murder of Herb,
Bonnie, Nancy, and Kenyon Clutter inside
their farmhouse near Holcomb, Kansas, on
November 15, 1959, and of their murderers,
Richard Eugene Hickock and Perry Edward
Smith. Truman Capote's Edgar Award–winning
work catapulted him to the peak of his
career with its release in 1965. The country was
still recovering from the rampage of mass
killer Charles Starkweather in Nebraska and
Wyoming (he was executed on June 25, 1959)
when another horrible slaying traumatized
the nation's heartland. The innocence associated
with rural America was shattered, and
the phrase "it can't happen here" seemingly
did not apply anymore.

Shortly after reading about the killing of the
Clutter family, Capote, accompanied by his
childhood friend, author Harper Lee, traveled
to Holcomb on assignment for the New Yorker
to do his investigative research. He interviewed
Dick Hickock and Perry Smith after they were
captured in Las Vegas, Nevada, and returned to
the Finney County jail. Capote followed their
lives for more than five years, from the trial in
Garden City and subsequent conviction for
first-degree murder, through the numerous
appeals, and ultimately to their execution on
April 14, 1965, at the state penitentiary in Lansing,
not far from where Hickock had grown
up in Olathe. Capote watched Hickock die;
however, he had grown much too close to
Smith, a mixed-blood Western Shoshone from
Nevada, to witness his execution, and he ran
from the building where the hangings were
staged.

The fascination with what transpired that
night outside Holcomb in remote southwestern
Kansas and the events that followed continues
unabated. Within two years after Capote's
work was published, a motion picture by
the same name was released. The "semidocumentary,"
directed by Oscar-winner Richard
Brooks, received four Academy Award nominations
in 1968. More recently, a TV movie
aired in 1996, and the A&amp;E Channel featured
the Clutter murders and In Cold Blood in its
American Justice series.

In 1997 Doubleday published George Plimpton's
book Truman Capote. Plimpton, in focusing
on Capote through the eyes of those
who knew him prior to his death in 1984, explored
the author's motives in creating what
he claimed was a new genre, the "nonfiction
novel." The Modern Library in 1999 ranked In
Cold Blood 96th among its top 100 nonfiction
books.


Guy Louis Rocha
Nevada State Library and Archives




Algeo, Ann M. The Courtroom as Forum: Homicide Trials by Dreiser, Wright, Capote and Mailer. New York: P. Lang,
1996. Capote, Truman. In Cold Blood: A True Account of a Multiple Murder and Its Consequences. New York: Random
House, 1965. Plimpton, George. Truman Capote: In Which Various Friends, Enemies, Acquaintances, and Detractors Recall His Turbulent Career. New York: Nan A.
Talese/Doubleday, 1997.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>