<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ind.005</field>
      <field name="titleMain">American Fur Company</field>
      <field name="author">Wishart, David J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




American Fur Company

Chartered on March 29, 1808, by the New York
legislature, the American Fur Company was
John Jacob Astor's bid to establish a fur empire
that would reach from the Great Lakes to
the Pacific Northwest. Astor failed to realize
this ambition (his Pacific Fur Company, a
worldwide trading scheme pivoted at Fort Astoria
at the mouth of the Columbia River,
foundered in 1813), but until it suspended payments
on September 6, 1842, the American
Fur Company dominated the fur trade of the
Great Lakes and the Central and Northern
Great Plains.

Astor and his right-hand man, Ramsey
Crooks, were slow to enter the fur trade of
the Great Plains: their policy always was to
let others make mistakes first, then move in
and take over. Their first tentative move was
made in 1821, when the American Fur Company
made an arrangement with the St. Louis
firm of (Bartholomew) Berthold and (Pierre
Jr.) Chouteau to supply their trade goods.
Within five years, the American Fur Company
had absorbed its competition and established
a virtual monopoly over the fur trade from the
Platte River to the Canadian boundary and
from the Missouri River to the Rocky Mountains.
This monopoly would be periodically
challenged by pretenders, but the American
Fur Company had the resources to outprice
and outlast its opponents and the political
clout to discredit them.

By 1834 the American Fur Company was
operating a network of trading posts that
spanned the Central and Northern Great Plains.
Three major depots–Fort Union (1829), at the
mouth of the Yellowstone; Fort Pierre (1832),
near the junction of the Cheyenne and Missouri
Rivers; and Fort Laramie (1834), on the
North Platte–were the organizational hubs
in this system, and numerous regional posts
served the trade of specific tribes or bands. No
Native Americans who wanted to trade–and
by 1834 they all did–were without an outlet.
They were the primary producers in a global
trading system that began on the Plains with
the collection and processing of robes and
pelts and ended in the fur marts of London
and Leipzig. The Missouri River, with steamboat
navigation after 1832, was the artery of
the commerce, and St. Louis was its main control
point, funneling furs to markets in the
eastern United States and Europe and trade
goods from Europe and elsewhere to Native
American consumers on the Plains. The economic
system was regulated by a constant flow
of correspondence from the trading posts
through St. Louis to Europe and back. The
American Fur Company kept an agent, Curtis
M. Lampson, in Europe to monitor market
conditions and maintained contracts with
various European firms for the importation
of, for example, beads (Alessandro Bertolla
of Venice) and knives and traps (Hiram Culter
of She.eld). This was truly an international
enterprise.

In the halcyon years of the early 1830s, the
American Fur Company was exporting at least
25,000 bison robes a year from the Great
Plains. But even then Astor could see the writing
on the wall. Competition, often involving
the flagrant use of alcohol as a trade inducement,
was escalating, and the price for beaver
pelts was falling as silk became the new preferred
raw material for top hats. In 1834 Astor,
old and ailing, sold the Northern Department
of the American Fur Company to Ramsay
Crooks and the Western Department to the St.
Louis firm of Pratte, Chouteau and Company.
Under the direction of Pierre Chouteau Jr.,
the fur-trade system established by the American
Fur Company would continue to operate
on the Plains until the 1860s, when it was enveloped
by waves of settlers.


David J. Wishart
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Lavender, David. The Fist in the Wilderness. Lincoln: University
of Nebraska Press, 1998. Wishart, David. The Fur Trade of the American West, 1807–1840: A Geographic Synthesis.
Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1992.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>