<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.mus.014</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Dixie Chicks</field>
      <field name="author">Brink, Pamela H.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




DIXIE CHICKS

The Dixie Chicks
    

The Dixie Chicks erupted onto the national
music scene in 1998 with their major label debut
album, Wide Open Spaces. Sisters Emily
Erwin Robison and Martie Erwin Seidel
founded the group in 1989 with Laura Lynch
and Robin Macy, gaining regional acclaim as a
close-harmony bluegrass band that always delivered
with a honeysuckle sound and virtuoso
instrumentation. Macy left in 1992 and Lynch
in 1995. Late in 1995 the Erwin sisters joined
their solid musicianship with the craggy, soulful
vocal talents of Lubbock native Natalie
Maines to develop a musical sound with a decidedly
West Texas edge that has proved to be
just the right blend for winning millions of
new converts as well as die-hard country fans
to their distinctive interpretation of rocking
Texas roots music.

Wide Open Spaces won a plethora of awards,
including a Grammy for best country album,
the National Association of Record Merchandisers
Award for best-selling recording by a
new group, and the Country Music Association
Award for album of the year, among many
other accolades. In 2002 Wide Open Spaces
won the group a place in the Guinness Book of World Records for the best-selling country
debut album of all time.

Fly, the band's second album, followed
close behind their first and won them Grammys,
Billboard awards, and Country Music Association
awards in both 1999 and 2000 for
their talents and the album. Their 1999 tour
promoting Fly gained a life of its own, making
the Dixie Chicks a pop-culture phenomenon,
with young and enthusiastic audiences flocking to their innovative performance spectaculars
to hear old-fashioned banjo and fiddle
music and contemporary lyrics tuned to a
new age.

The Dixie Chicks are consummate musicians.
They play their own lead instruments,
do their own sessions work, and write their
own songs. With the success of Wide Open Spaces they gained the commercial opportunity
to write many of the songs they recorded
on Fly, including "Ready to Run" and
"Cowboy Take Me Away" by Martie Seidel and
Marcus Hammon, "Don't Waste Your Heart"
by Emily Robison and Natalie Maines, "Sin
Wagon" by Natalie Maines, Emily Robison,
and Stephany Smith, and "Without You" by
Natalie Maines and Eric Silver.


Pamela H. Brink
Associated Authors and Editors, Inc.





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>