<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pd.009</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Bloor, Ella R. (1862-1951)</field>
      <field name="author">Nutter, Kathleen Banks</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BLOOR, ELLA R. (1862-1951)

Ella Reeve "Mother" Bloor was a feminist and
labor organizer who dedicated her life to the
cause of America's industrial workers and
farmers. She was born on Staten Island, New
York, on July 8, 1862, and brought up in comfortable
upper-middle-class circumstances.
As a young woman she was drawn to the suffrage
and prohibition movements, and after
1902 she devoted herself to labor issues, investigating,
for example, the Chicago meatpacking
industry and demonstrating for the rights
of working women and their children. In 1919
she broke with the Socialist Party because
many in its ranks supported World War I, and
she joined the newly formed American Communist
Party.

In 1929 the Communist Party sent Bloor, then
sixty-seven years old, to work with farmers in
North and South Dakota. For the next five years
much of her focus was in the Great Plains. In
1930 Bloor married North Dakota farmer and
fellow Communist Andrew Omholt, and a year
later she joined the United Farmers League as an
organizer in the Dakotas and Montana. The
United Farmers League fought bank foreclosures
and organized mass demonstrations,
often with Bloor literally leading the parade.
When the unrest spread into Iowa and Nebraska
as the "Farmers Holiday" movement grew,
Bloor continued her role as featured speaker,
especially during the dramatic Milk Strike of
1932 in Sioux City, Iowa. She frequently worked
alongside her oldest son and party comrade, Hal
Ware. In 1934, while protesting on behalf of
striking women chicken pluckers in Loup City,
Nebraska, Bloor was arrested for the thirty-sixth
and final time in her long career. In 1935, after
multiple appeals failed, the then seventy-three-year-old woman served thirty days in an Omaha
jail–an event that received much sympathetic
press even in mainstream publications.

Hailed in a 1937 Life magazine piece as the
"grand old woman of the U.S. Communist
party," Bloor spent her final active years fighting
fascism at home and abroad. She died in Richlandtown,
Pennsylvania, on August 10, 1951.


Kathleen Banks Nutter
Smith College




Bloor, Ella Reeve. Papers. Sophia Smith Collection, Smith
College, Northampton MA. Bloor, Ella Reeve. We Are
Many. New York: International Publishers, 1940. Dyson,
Lowell K. Red Harvest: The Communist Party and American
Farmers. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1982.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>