<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.wat.036</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Water Quality</field>
      <field name="author">Spalding, Roy F.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




WATER QUALITY

The Great Plains contains the High Plains (or
Ogallala) Aquifer, the largest aquifer system in
the United States that stretches from South
Dakota to Texas, and has a myriad of rivers,
lakes, and prairie wetlands. Vast amounts of
groundwater are contained within the sands
and gravels with silt lenses of the Miocene age
Ogallala Formation, the Brule and Arikaree
Formations in western Nebraska, and overlying
Quaternary age sands and gravels.

Water quality indexes as measurements of
the suitability of water for irrigation, human
and animal consumption, and fish and wildlife
have been developed by the U.S. Environmental
Protection Agency (EPA) and the U.S.
Department of Agriculture (USDA). Different
limits of exposure are based on human and
plant health and environmental considerations.
No single compilation of water quality
over the vast Plains region exists, though various
local assessments have been made. Investigations
of groundwater quality in the High
Plains Aquifer in the early 1980s were an outgrowth
of studies of water depletion from irrigation.
The investigations confirmed that
mining of groundwater by irrigators since the
1940s had lowered the groundwater table by
more than 100 feet in parts of Texas, eastern
New Mexico, the Oklahoma Panhandle, and
Kansas. Follow-up studies indicated that water
table declines greater than forty feet occurred
from 1980 to 1995. Total dissolved
solids (TDS), a measure of water purity, increased
from north to south in the aquifer,
suggesting an association between mining and
deteriorating quality. Very high TDS levels occurred
in the Ogallala Formation groundwater
beneath southwestern Kansas and the
Texas Panhandle. According to the usda salinity
scale, irrigation with this groundwater will
promote development of saline soil conditions
that render the soil useless. High TDS
levels are generally encountered in deeper,
older waters that have become more mineralized
with time. Upward movement of naturally
occurring chemicals from underlying
bedrock is a major source of increased TDS. In
Kansas and Texas, underlying Permian age
bedrock contains salt beds and saline water,
providing high amounts of tds to the Ogallala
Aquifer. Wells in these areas also generally
contain elevated sodium concentrations that
are known to adversely affect plant growth
and soil properties.

Although the Ogallala Aquifer has received
intense scrutiny, the focus of Great Plains water
quality concern is now on the impact of
agrichemicals and the generation of animal
wastes by agriculture. Areas that are most sensitive
to contamination are alluvial valleys
with less than fifty feet to groundwater. These
river and stream valleys generally have rich,
well-drained bottomland and terrace soils
that are heavily irrigated by shallow wells and
have been row-cropped for decades. Agriculture,
the economic mainstay of the Great
Plains, is heavily reliant on agrichemicals.
In areas vulnerable to leaching, underlying
groundwater commonly contains nitrate and
herbicides in levels that may adversely a&#129;ãect
human health. Nebraska and Kansas have very
high incidences of nitrate in well water. The
nitrate is derived from commercial fertilizer
and animal waste and exceeds public health
limits. The herbicides atrazine and metolachlor
are used throughout the region on corn
land and are frequently detected in surface
water and in many shallow aquifers. In soils
and water, pesticide transformation occurs,
and the resulting degradates are often detected
in concentrations that considerably exceed
those of the parent pesticides. These degradate
compounds may present a future health hazard
and environmental concern. Pesticides are
also a problem in surface water. Each spring,
pesticides are flushed from farms in the Great
Plains in runo&#129;ã. These pesticides accumulate
in lakes and reservoirs and can be introduced
into municipal wells situated next to creeks
and rivers. In addition to nitrate, ammonia
from animal and human waste lagoon overflows
has been responsible for several fish
kills in the Plains. Other chemicals found in
groundwater include carbon tetrachloride
and ethylene dibromide, which were used as
fumigants and commonly occur beneath and
near grain elevators.

Contaminants associated with military
bases and industries are also a problem in the
Great Plains region. In these locations the
groundwater may be contaminated with munitions
such as RDX and TNT as well as the
commonly used degreaser trichloroethylene.
Large trichloroethylene plumes in Hastings,
Nebraska, and Wichita, Kansas, are the result
of industrial solvent disposal.


Roy F. Spaulding
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Exner, Mary, and Roy F. Spalding. Occurrence of Pesticides
and Nitrate in Nebraska's Ground Water. Lincoln: University
of Nebraska Water Center, 1990. Kolpin D. W., E. M.
Thurman, and D. A. Goolsby. "Occurrence of Selected
Pesticides and Their Metabolites in Near-Surface Aquifers
of the Midwestern United States." Environmental Science
and Technology 30 (1997): 335–40.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>