<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.006</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Butala, Sharon (b. 1940)</field>
      <field name="author">Fiamengo, Janice</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BUTALA, SHARON (b. 1940)

Sharon Butala is best known for her descriptions
of the physical and spiritual geography
of her corner of southwestern Saskatchewan,
near the Montana border, where she lives with
her husband, Peter Butala, a cattle rancher. In
1996 the Butalas dedicated a portion of their
ranch land to Nature Conservancy Canada so
that the beauty of the native shortgrass prairie
could be preserved. Butala's literary work has
similarly been dedicated to preserving and
communicating the aesthetic and cultural
meanings of the prairie, especially the complex
relationships between farming people
and the land they work.

Born Sharon LeBlanc on August 24, 1940, in
northern Saskatchewan near Nipawin, Butala
moved to Saskatoon at age thirteen. After
graduating from St. Mary's Roman Catholic
School, she attended the University of Saskatchewan,
where she earned a bachelor's degree
in English and art. A decade later she
returned to the university for a bachelor's degree
in education, specializing in learning disabilities.
She married Peter Butala after her
first marriage ended, leaving her urban life
behind and embarking on a difficult but fruitful
period of reflection, observation, and self-discovery
through writing.

Butala's first published work was Country of the Heart (1984), which was nominated for the
W. H. Smith/Books in Canada First Novel
Award. Subsequent to this successful debut,
she has written extensively, publishing two
collections of acclaimed short stories (Queen of the Headaches, 1985; Fever, 1990), five more
novels, two nonfiction accounts, and a collection
of essays (Coyote's Morning Cry, 1995).
She has also written six unpublished plays. Of
special interest is her loosely connected novel
trilogy about life in rural Saskatchewan, comprised
of The Gates of the Sun (1986), Luna
(1988), and The Fourth Archangel (1992). Luna
portrays the special challenges and rewards of
rural women's lives, while The Fourth Archangel
presents a visionary and compassionate
account of the provincial farm crisis. These
novels belong to the tradition of regional realism,
with elements of the mythic and the magical.

Butala's first foray into nonfiction, The Perfection of the Morning (1994), tells of the slow
process by which she learned to see nature
truly. The book remained on best-seller lists
for more than a year and brought Butala considerable
recognition within Canada. In her
sixth novel, The Garden of Eden (1998), Butala
expanded her geographical parameters to
Ethiopia, but her focus remained the capacity
of the land to heal and human responsibility
for its restoration and protection. Wild Stone Heart (2000), a companion volume to The Perfection of the Morning, chronicles Butala's
respectful exploration of a 100-acre field of
unplowed land; seeking to connect with the
wild and with an Indigenous worldview in
order to heal her spiritual malaise, she investigates
the Aboriginal and settler pasts to uncover
layers of unknowable presence. While
maintaining her interest in emotional journeys
and the beauty of the land, Butala's later
work has increasingly turned to considerations
of the mystical.


Janice Fiamengo
University of Saskatchewan-Saskatoon





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>