<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.041</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Mandel, Eli (1922-1992)</field>
      <field name="author">New, William H.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MANDEL, ELI (1922-1992)

Elias Wolf Mandel, the Canadian poet and critic,
was born to a Jewish family in Estevan, Saskatchewan,
on December 3, 1922. He grew up
there and in Regina, and he was always influenced
by his western origins. He first left the
Prairies in 1943, when he served in Europe with
the Canadian Army Medical Corps. Returning
in 1945, he completed his bachelor's (1949) and
master's (1950) at the University of Saskatchewan
in Saskatoon, then left again to complete a
doctorate (on the writings of Christopher
Smart) at the University of Toronto (1957).
Mandel's academic appointments took him to
St. Jean (Quebec), Edmonton (Alberta), and
(after his separation from his first wife, the
poet Miriam Mandel) to York University in
Toronto, where he remained as professor of
English and humanities from 1967 until he suffered
a major stroke in 1989. He died on September
3, 1992.

Author and editor of twenty books, Mandel
acquired a substantial reputation as a theorist
of Canadian poetry (as in Another Time, 1977,
and the anthology Contexts of Canadian Criticism,
1971) and as a poet. Early commentaries
on his work (e.g., on Black and Secret Man,
1964) described it as mythic, seeing in it the
influence of Northrop Frye. Later commentary,
responding to Stony Plain (1973), Out of Place (1977, with photographs by his second
wife, the critic Ann Mandel), Life Sentence
(1981), and Dreaming Backwards (selected
poems, 1981), recognized that the influences
on his work are more wide-ranging. Mandel's
interest in mysticism, his wit, and his fascination
with doubles, ambiguity, chaos, and the
paradox of being an individual in a socially
interdependent world, for example, derive
from his personal travels (in India, Spain,
Peru), his readings in George Steiner and others,
and his Jewish Prairie heritage. Increasingly,
he meditated on what this heritage
meant to him, not so much as a set of received
religious traditions but as an accumulation of
memories that he associates with place.


William H. New
University of British Columbia




Cooley, Dennis. Eli Mandel and His Works. Toronto: ECW
Press, 1992. New, W. H. "Interim Conclusion: Reading Eli
Mandel's 'The Madwomen of the Plaza de Mayo.'" In Inside the Poem, edited by W. H. New. Toronto: Oxford
University Press, 1992: 160–64.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>