<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.058</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Poetry</field>
      <field name="author">Kooser, Ted</field>
      <field name="text">

 




POETRY

Nearly all the poetry written in the Great
Plains during the last 150 years can be placed
in two general categories. In the nineteenth
and early twentieth centuries, poetry written
in the literary forms of, for example, Keats or
Byron was considered respectable, while poetry
whose form and rhetoric were an extension
of its subject matter was only beginning
to seek legitimacy. Imitative poems occasionally
made use of the locale or the culture in
which the poet lived and wrote, such as the
epic and iambic heroic pioneer and Native
American poems of John G. Neihardt, but,
generally, the main aspiration of the imitative
poet was to create what was considered to be
respectable "classical" literature, as if to establish
the fact that civilization was indeed possible
far from the traditional seats of refinement.
The worldwide emergence of literary
realism established the legitimacy of poems
whose forms were "organic"–poems whose
free forms seemed a natural extension of content.
In the early twentieth century the balance
began to tip toward a poem that disdained
classical influences while attempting to respond
to the life and culture of the poet's immediate
locality. Today, poets writing work of
this latter kind far outnumber those writing in
classical forms, though Plains poetry of all
forms does have at least one distinguishing
tradition, that of reporting news from the
frontier.

Much of Plains literature written during the
period of settlement–stories, poems, essays,
and newspaper columns–described the joys
and sorrows of life on the edge of American or
Canadian civilization. Authors customarily
addressed their work to a remote, comfortably
situated audience, an audience ignorant of
what a sod house in Nebraska or a homestead
shack in Saskatchewan might offer. It made
perfect sense for writers to make such reports
because, after all, they had no other audience.
Most of the readers in both countries were still
"back east." Those frontier writers' principal
tools were scenic description and action-filled
anecdote, and the emotional stance was one of
hard-bitten acceptance of circumstances.

The tradition of reporting from the frontier
continues today. During the past 150 years,
easterners have come to expect Plains writers
to continue writing steady-eyed reports from
the "edge of civilization," even though the
frontier has long since passed on west and
sunk out of sight in the Pacific. For example,
Thomas McGrath's epic poem Letter to an Imaginary Friend, one of the twentieth century's
genuine masterpieces, is in part a report
from the frontier of North Dakota.

The contemporary poetry most readily
identified as Great Plains writing still follows
these general parameters: it is descriptive, anecdotal,
noncelebratory, and generally accepting
of circumstances. It continues to be the
expectation of eastern readers that poets "out
there" will continue to provide reports on living
conditions in rural America. Sometimes,
in an attempt to sell itself to the established
eastern literary community, which still maintains
authority in matters literary, Plains poetry
has suffered by trying to be too entertaining,
too clever, too anecdotal, and obsequious
toward an eastern audience. A poet who lives
in Kansas and who writes in the manner of,
say, the New York school–in which setting
and environment are suppressed in favor of a
more cerebral, talky, unanchored or nonlocal
poetry–may find it difficult to find acceptance
either in the East or in Kansas.

Probably the most important, most highly
acclaimed Plains poet was the late William
Stafford (1914-93), who spent his boyhood in
Kansas and who continued to write tellingly
and movingly about life on the Plains even
after he moved to Oregon. Stafford's most notable
poems adhere to the traits mentioned
above: they are descriptive and anecdotal, and
though loss and misery may be described,
Stafford never pities himself or the people
whose lives he portrays. Generous with his
praise for the Kansas landscape and its people,
he is never inappropriately boosterish. The
people in his poems, such as a small-town
spinster schoolmistress dying of cancer in old
age, are ennobled by Stafford's dispassionate
account of their uncomplaining struggles.
Much of Stafford's best work fits into the category
of reports from the frontier.

There are hundreds if not thousands of poets
living on the Plains in the twenty-first century,
many having considerable talent and national
recognition. Some of these authors, like
the Cherokee writer Diane Glancy, are talented
poets and fiction writers as well. Linda
Hasselstrom, a ranch woman from South Dakota,
is an accomplished poet, diarist, and essayist.

Poetry on the Canadian Prairies is perhaps
even more ubiquitous than on the U.S. side.
Canada Council and provincial writers guilds
not only provide subsidies for publication but
also support reading tours by poets and other
writers and poet-in-residence grants for libraries
in major cities and many small towns.
Louis Riel, Canada's most celebrated western
rebel, was also an accomplished poet, and his
heirs are legion. Just a few are Di Brandt and
Bonnie Burnard, Louise Halfe and Beth Cuthand,
Dennis Cooley and Anne Szumigalski,
Fred Wah and Robert Kroetsch.

Like all authors, Plains poets are at their
best when they focus their talents on trying to
write well rather than trying to write what is
expected of them. Paying too much attention
to the expectation and entertainment of outside
readers and publishers can lead to the
weaknesses of glibness and redundancy. But,
on the other hand, bowing to their own traditions,
Plains poets continue to have an irrepressible
urge to tell the people what life is
really like out in this land of wide horizons.


Ted Kooser
Garland, Nebraska





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>