<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fol.032</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Personal Experience Narratives</field>
      <field name="author">Hathaway, Rosemary V.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




PERSONAL EXPERIENCE NARRATIVES

Personal experience narratives are those that
relate an event from the first-person perspective.
In the folk tradition of the Great
Plains, such narratives have been preserved
and transmitted in a variety of modes–via
letters and diaries as well as orally–and often
function to document the history of the region
in miniature.

The most significant contrast between personal
experience narratives and other folknarrative
genres has to do with the sense of
"private ownership" often attached to personal
experience narratives. While other narrative
genres follow fairly stable structural and
thematic patterns, personal experience narratives–
being rooted in the teller's own experiences
and perceptions—tend to be idiosyncratic
in their form and content, although
such narratives can become more traditional
in the sense that their form often stabilizes
with repetition. Thus, one of the critical functions
of personal experience narratives is the
role they play in shaping and conveying the
identity, values, and aesthetics of their respective
tellers. Personal experience narratives play
a crucial role in constructing identity; they are
one of the primary means by which individuals
"perform" their identity for others, and
also one of the vital ways in which people construct
their own internal sense of identity.

Taken collectively, then, such stories can
form a life history of one person, or–if examined
in broader contexts–they can help shape
family, local, and regional histories. In particular,
personal experience narratives as a
genre have been taken up for study by those
interested in women's history; since the dominant
tellers of many traditional folk-narrative
genres have been men, scholars have looked to
personal experience narratives as an overlooked
genre by which women express themselves.

This trend is especially important in terms
of the Great Plains, as evidenced by the many
recently recovered and published diaries by
women journeying west during the age of expansion,
as well as by more contemporary life
histories of Great Plains women. As Lillian
Schlissel notes, aside from the Civil War, "no
other event of the [nineteenth] century . . .
evoked so many personal accounts as the
overland passage." While formally different
from orally transmitted personal experience
narratives, such literary accounts nevertheless
form a critical part of our understanding of
Great Plains history and heritage. These historical
personal experience narratives, represented
in diaries and letters, document perceptions
of the Plains and early multiethnic
encounters. In her comparative study of women's
diaries of the westward journey, for example,
Schlissel excerpts the journal of Rebecca
Ketcham, a single woman traveling from Ithaca,
New York, to Oregon to become a school-teacher,
who–upon realizing she has been
charged more than other travelers in her
group and made to work as well–decides that
she "shall find more time to write hereafter."
Schlissel also relates the story of Clara Brown,
a slave who–after purchasing her own freedom
and setting up a laundry in the mining
camps of Colorado–sponsored wagon trains
to help other freed slaves to migrate west after
the Civil War. These narratives include evocative
descriptions of the Plains during this era
that capture the sense of newness and inspiration
they could evoke, such as this passage
recorded by Lydia Allen Rudd during her
crossing in 1852: "Left the Missouri river for
our long journey across the wild uncultivated
plains. . . . As we left the river bottom and
ascended the bluffs the view from them was
handsome! In front of us as far as vision could
reach extended the green hills covered with
fine grass."

Many of the personal narratives recounted
in such texts can be found in oral tradition and
family histories as well. The multitude of similar
narratives suggests that the stories are probably
apocryphal; even so, they can be very accurate
barometers of historical development
and change. One such narrative has become so
prevalent that it earned its own title of sorts,
"Goldilocks on the Oregon Trail." The story
recounts the allegedly historical fact of a Native
American chief becoming so enamored of a
young woman (who invariably has beautiful
blonde or red hair) that he offers the men in
the party an entire herd of horses, cattle, or
some other treasure in exchange for the "exotic"
beauty. While this story is told in many
families as "true," it clearly cannot be documented;
nevertheless, its popularity and themes
tell us much about how both early settlers and
their contemporary descendants wish to remember,
or imagine, Native American reactions
to white encroachment. Captivity narratives–
again, whether transmitted verbally or
in writing–also document one side of the
story of early encounters. As such, these types
of narrative, true or not, become a significant
part of our understanding of Plains history.

Since the inception of the American Folklore
Society in 1888, folklorists have been interested
in documenting and preserving the customs
and oral traditions of Plains Indians, an
interest that has resulted in fieldwork recordings
and transcriptions that work to balance
out Anglo-American narratives of settlement.
One of the great ethical dilemmas in early
fieldwork with Native Americans, however,
was that fieldworkers' own biases led them either
to misunderstand or deliberately misrepresent
their informants' narratives. Contemporary
folklorists and anthropologists
collecting personal experience narratives from
individuals of all groups, but particularly from
traditionally underrepresented groups, are
making a more concerted effort to collaborate
with their informants in a reciprocal way that
allows the person's words to stand on their
own. Anthropologist Sally McBeth's collaborative
work with Shoshone elder Essie Burnett
Horne, for example, represents an attempt to
voice a traditionally underrepresented aspect
of Great Plains history in as direct and unmediated
a way as possible. Horne's life story,
which begins on the Wind River Reservation
in Wyoming, traces the development of one
woman's pan-Indian and pan-Plains identity
through her years as a student at the Haskell
Indian School in Lawrence, Kansas, to her becoming
a teacher herself at Indian schools in
Oklahoma and North Dakota, before retiring
to the White Earth (Chippewa) Reservation in
Minnesota. All along she offers a counternarrative
to the Indian schools' policy of assimilation
by showing how, instead, the schools allowed
"multitribal alliances" to be forged.

Thus, the personal experience narrative,
while seemingly simple and limited in scope,
can lend tremendous insight not only into the
identity of a single person but into the history
of the Great Plains itself.

See also AFRICAN AMERICANS: Brown, "Aunt" Clara / 
GENDER: Captivity Narratives.


Rosemary V. Hathaway
University of Northern Colorado




Horne, Esther Burnett, and Sally McBeth. Essie's Story: The Life and Legacy of a Shoshone Teacher. Lincoln: University
of Nebraska Press, 1998. Schlissel, Lillian. Women's Diaries of the Westward Journey. New York: Schocken
Books, 1982. Stahl, Sandra Dolby. Literary Folkloristics and the Personal Narrative. Bloomington: Indiana University
Press, 1989.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>