<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.gen.035</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Slaughter, Linda (1843-1911)</field>
      <field name="author">Handy-Marchello, Barbara</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SLAUGHTER, LINDA (1843-1911)


Linda Slaughter, ca. 1880.


Linda Warfel Slaughter was a journalist, historian,
and women's rights advocate in North
Dakota. Born February 1, 1843, in Cadiz, Ohio,
and educated at Oberlin College, she settled in
Bismarck in 1872. She was appointed superintendent
of schools for Burleigh County in
1873. Though women could not vote at that
time, she was elected to the position several
more times until 1882. In 1876 Slaughter was
appointed deputy superintendent of public
instruction for Dakota Territory.

Slaughter wrote regularly for the Bismarck Tribune and other papers. Her fiction was
thinly disguised commentary on social life in
the military and the politics of the Indian
campaigns. Her essays at first criticized women's
public suffrage and temperance activities
and advocated "true womanhood" as women's
proper role.

By the late 1880s Slaughter was a Washington
correspondent for Dakota Territory newspapers.
By then embracing the women's rights
movement, she served as vice president of the
Woman's National Press Association, attended
the 1888 meeting of the International Council
of Women, served on the national executive
committee of the National Woman Suffrage
Association, supported Belva Lockwood's
presidential campaigns, and became an organizer
for the Knights of Labor. In 1892 Slaughter
attended the Populist Party convention,
becoming the first woman to vote in a national
convention for a presidential candidate.

In 1889 Slaughter organized the Ladies' Historical
Society of Bismarck and North Dakota.
As president, she collected and preserved records
of North Dakota's early history. In 1895
she negotiated a merger with the fledgling
State Historical Society, assuring women the
right to vote and hold office in the new organization.

Slaughter continued to write history until
very late in her life. Her last articles, four on
Sitting Bull for Sports Afield (1903–4) and a
lengthy piece for the State Historical Society
(1906), are on early settlement, military activity,
and Indian resistance. She died in St.
Cloud, Minnesota, on July 3, 1911.

See also MEDIA: Bismarck Tribune.


Barbara Handy-Marchello
University of North Dakota




Burgum, Jessamine Slaughter. Zezula, or Pioneer Days of the Smokey Water Country. Valley City ND: Getchell and
Nielsen, 1937. Slaughter, Linda Warfel. Fortress to Farm or Twenty-three Years on the Frontier, edited by Hazel Eastman.
New York: Exposition Press, 1972.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>