<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.na.017</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Calumet Ceremony</field>
      <field name="author">Eifler, Mark A.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CALUMET CEREMONY

Native Americans used the calumet ceremony
throughout the Plains to trade between different
tribes, or between different bands of the
same tribe, for food and other needed items.
The ceremony evolved in the thirteenth century,
possibly among the Wichitas. During the
early thirteenth century the climate of the
Plains was wetter, supporting more bison and
encouraging more tribes to move into the region.
Subsequently, as the weather turned
drier, many tribes, caught without adequate
food supplies following a poor hunt or a local
drought, needed to trade with neighbors to
survive. In time, the calumet ceremony not
only provided food but also often became a
primary bond between bands and tribes.

In its fullest form, the calumet was a long
and complex ceremony, but even the more
common shorter version involved several days
of ritual feasting, gift giving, singing, and
dancing. The ceremony climaxed with the
presentation of the calumet pipe, which made
unrelated peoples one "family" through the
working of a fictional kinship. Leaders of different
bands adopted each other as father or
son. Exchanges of gifts then went on for several
days, in the later stages accompanied by
exchanges between the men and women of
each band, who acquired the same fictive
father-son relationship to the other band as
that established by their leaders. A leader's calumet
relationships were considered permanent,
and leaders were expected to maintain a
number of calumet relationships with other
tribes, bands, and villages. The calumet ceremonies
also allowed men and women from
different bands to meet and court each other,
and often trade bonds between bands were
supplemented by matrimonial bonds.


Mark A. Eifler
University of Portland




Blakeslee, Donald J. "The Plains Interband Trade System:
An Ethnohistoric and Archeological Investigation." Ph.D.
diss., University of Wisconsin, Milwaukee, 1975. Fletcher,
Alice C. The Hako: Song, Pipe, and Unity in a Pawnee
Calumet Ceremony. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press,
1996.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>