<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fil.027</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Gray, Coleen (b. 1922)</field>
      <field name="author">Umland, Samuel J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




GRAY, COLEEN (b. 1922)

Coleen Gray
    

Coleen Gray was born Doris Jensen on October
23, 1922, in Staplehurst, a small town in
eastern Nebraska. She attended Hamline University
in St. Paul, Minnesota, where she became
interested in dramatics. After a series of
appearances in little theaters, she landed her
first, uncredited role in the Hollywood musical
State Fair (1945). The following year she had a
bit part in yet another musical comedy, Three Little Girls in Blue (1946), also uncredited.
In 1947, however, she appeared as the honest,
faithful wife of criminals in two famous films
noir, Kiss of Death and Nightmare Alley, in
which she established herself as a competent
actress capable of playing leading roles. Perhaps
her most complex role was that of the
abusive nurse, Ann Sebastian, in the disturbing
noir The Sleeping City (1950), about corruption
in a large city hospital. She also appeared
in many Westerns and action films, among
them Howard Hawks's Red River (1948), in
which she played Fen, the lovely woman whom
Thomas Dunson (John Wayne) leaves behind,
in effect condemning her to death.

In all, Gray appeared in about thirty-eight
motion pictures, making very few after 1960,
the year she was cast in the Universal horror
film The Leech Woman, a mediocre picture in
which she was quite good. She continued to
appear on television, playing guest roles in
various series, but these appearances also diminished,
and after 1972 she retired from acting
altogether. She made a brief return with a
role in Cry from the Mountain (1986), made by
the Reverend Billy Graham.


Samuel J. Umland
University of Nebraska at Kearney




Katz, Ephraim. The Film Encyclopedia. New York: Thomas
Y. Crowell, 1979. Silver, Alain, and Elizabeth Ward, eds.
Film Noir: An Encyclopedic Reference to the American Style.
Woodstock NY: Overlook Press, 1979.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>