<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.law.047</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Texas Rangers</field>
      <field name="author">Ellis, Mark R.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




TEXAS RANGERS


Texas Rangers, between 1890 and 1900


The Texas Rangers are the oldest state law
enforcement agency in the United States.
Throughout their storied history they have
gone through several transformations and
have performed an array of duties. A symbol
of the American West and immortalized
in film and print, the Texas Rangers have a
worldwide reputation and are mentioned in
the same breath with elite law enforcement
agencies such as the Royal Canadian Mounted
Police and Scotland Yard.

The origins of the Texas Rangers date back
to 1823, when Stephen F. Austin appointed ten
frontiersmen to defend the nascent Texas settlements
from Indian attacks. These early
ranger companies operated as loosely organized
and irregular units until 1835, when a
more permanent body was created. When the
Texas Revolution broke out in 1836, the rangers
served in a limited capacity as scouts, couriers,
and escorts. Several rangers died defending
the Alamo.

The Texas Rangers played an important role
in defending the frontier under the Lone Star
flag of the Republic of Texas. Under the leadership
of Capt. John "Jack" Coffee Hays, the
rangers became an experienced and feared
fighting unit. Their effective use of the Colt
revolver helped popularize the weapon. During
the Mexican War (1846-48), Hays's rangers
served as scouts, spies, and cavalrymen under
generals Zachary Taylor and Winfield
Scott. Mounted and heavily armed, the Texas
Rangers earned a reputation as fiercely independent
fighters. Because of their ruthless
pursuit of Mexican guerrillas and their rough
treatment of citizens, their Mexican counterparts
labeled them "los diablos tejanos" (the
Texas devils).

From the end of the Mexican War to 1874,
the rangers saw little action. The U.S. Army
guarded the Texas frontier, leaving the rangers
with few responsibilities. They reappeared in
1874, when the state legislature created several
ranger companies to deal with Indian attacks
in West Texas, Mexican bandits along the Rio
Grande, and the growing number of outlaws
and desperadoes that infested Texas. In a military
role, they assisted the U.S. Army in crushing
Comanche and Kiowa resistance during
the 1870s. As lawmen, the Texas Rangers traveled
thousands of miles while tracking criminals.
They gained fame by restoring peace in
civil conflicts such as the Sutton-Taylor Feud
and by capturing Great Plains outlaws such as
gunfighter John Wesley Hardin and train robber
Sam Bass.

With the end of the Indian wars and the general
establishment of law and order, the duties
and responsibilities of the rangers changed. In
the 1910s and 1920s rangers guarded the Mexico-
Texas border from Mexican revolutionaries,
enforced prohibition laws, and policed oil
boomtowns. In 1935 the Texas Rangers became
a professional law enforcement unit when they
were incorporated, along with the state highway
patrol, into the newly created Texas Department
of Public Safety (DPS). Since then
they have been the investigative body of the
dps. Modern-day rangers travel by car, plane,
boat, helicopter, and only occasionally by
horse. They still do not wear a uniform; the
ranger badge is the only common accouterment
worn by all rangers. Although their
numbers remain small (only 106 rangers were
on duty in 1997), the Texas Rangers continue to
be the elite of Texas law enforcement.


Mark R. Ellis
University of Nebraska at Kearney




Gillett, James B. Six Years with the Texas Rangers, 1875– 1881. New Haven CT: Yale University Press, 1925. Samora,
Julian, Joe Bernal, and Albert Peña. Gunpowder Justice: A Reassessment of the Texas Rangers. Notre Dame IN: University
of Notre Dame Press, 1979. Webb, Walter Prescott.
The Texas Rangers: A Century of Frontier Defense. Austin:
University of Texas Press, 1965.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>