<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ag.006</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Agricultural Meteorology</field>
      <field name="author">Marten, James</field>
      <field name="text">

 




AGRICULTURAL METEOROLOGY

Agricultural meteorology is the behavior of
the atmosphere in relation to crops and soils.
In the Great Plains, agriculture is dependent
on the atmosphere in many ways. The atmosphere,
in turn, links the Great Plains to other
parts of the globe. This linkage is forged by air
masses entering and leaving the region. These
air masses provide plants with a dynamic and
renewable source of carbon dioxide and water
and modify other contributing factors, such
as light and leaf temperature.

With no geographic barriers to the movement
of Arctic air from the north or Gulf
air from the south, Great Plains weather is
characterized by alternate intrusions of warm
and cold air, and the region therefore experiences
high variability in temperature, cloudiness,
humidity, and precipitation during all
seasons. Temperatures are harsh during winter,
particularly in the Northern Plains, where
perennial plants retreat into dormancy and
farmers grow annual crops, like spring wheat.
Summer provides desirable temperatures for
plant growth and development.

The energy required to successfully grow
wheat, corn, soybeans, hay, and other crops
mainly comes from abundant sunshine. Of
course, without the atmosphere to absorb energy
and emit a portion of it back to the earth
(the greenhouse effect) the surface temperatures
would be too low to support life. The
atmosphere also exchanges energy through
contact with the underlying surface of the
ground as air masses pass through the region.
This amount of energy is governed by the
speed, humidity, and temperature of the air
and the temperature and humidity of the underlying
surface. Changes in the Plains landscape
from natural grasslands to managed
croplands, pastures, and windbreaks altered
the disposition of atmospheric energy in the
local climate. Irrigation also changes the local
climate: in a dry field much of the energy goes
into heating the overlying air, whereas in an
irrigated field much of the available energy
goes into evaporation and transpiration.

Growing season precipitation accounts for
a large fraction of the annual precipitation.
Soil moisture is frequently depleted during
the growing season but replenished during
winter and early spring, thereby providing a
buffer to plants against dry weather that may
occur early in the growing season. Evaporation
from soils and transpiration from plants
draw on stored soil moisture and increase
with greater plant biomass, higher temperatures,
solar radiation, and wind speed. Evaporation
and transpiration decrease with increases
in atmospheric humidity. Drought
occurs when soil moisture falls below the
amount required to meet the crops' need for
water.

The main influence of the atmosphere on
agriculture is the control exerted by the water
and energy on crop production. The atmosphere,
however, has other impacts on agriculture.
For example, in wet periods the frequent
formation of dew on plant leaves (leaf
wetness) will increase crop damage due to
plant diseases. Drought conditions favor other
pests, like spider mites in corn.

Agricultural meteorologists monitor
weather in order to quantify both the potential
resources and possible damages associated
with the dynamic atmosphere. Proper use of
this information in decision making can both
reduce risk and increase profit associated with
agriculture, thus contributing to the goal of
sustainable agricultural production in the
Great Plains.

See also PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT: Climate.


Kenneth G. Hubbard
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Rosenberg, N. J., B. L. Blad, and S. B. Verma. Microclimate:
The Biological Environment. New York: John Wiley and
Sons, 1983.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>