<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.mus.016</field>
      <field name="titleMain">The Flatlanders</field>
      <field name="author">Wilkinson, Andy</field>
      <field name="text">

 




THE FLATLANDERS

The Flatlanders' album cover (1972)
       

In the arts, events need not last long to have
long-lasting impact. Such is the case with the
Flatlanders, a Lubbock, Texas, band from the
early 1970s. Though they were together scarcely
over a year and produced only one recording,
which wasn't released until almost a decade after
they'd gone their separate ways, the influence of
their music has spanned generations, genres,
and geography.

Joe Ely, Jimmie Dale Gilmore, and Butch
Hancock had become acquainted during their
high school years in Lubbock. Reconnecting
there in the summer of 1971, they discovered
their mutual interests in blues, old-time country
music (especially the works of Jimmie
Rodgers), and songwriting. The three began
performing together, with Jimmie Dale handling
the lead vocals, Joe adding harmonica
and Dobro, and all playing acoustic guitar and
singing harmonies. From time to time, they
were joined by several other musicians native
to the Llano Estacado: John Reed on guitar,
Sylvester Rice on acoustic bass, Tony Pearson
on mandolin, and Steve Wesson on saw (a carpenter's
ripsaw, bent and played with a violin
bow).

The band, called the Flatlanders in celebration
of the region's topography, cut several
demo tracks at a small studio in Big Springs,
Texas. Those led to a recording session in
Nashville in February 1972, when Ely, Gilmore,
and Hancock recorded seventeen songs, joined
by Tommy Hancock on fiddle, Rice on acoustic
bass, and Wesson on saw. Gilmore and Butch
Hancock each wrote four of the tunes, Lubbock
native Al Strehli wrote two, and Al's sister
Angela wrote another. The selections were
augmented with classic songs by Jimmie Rodgers,
Willie Nelson, A. P. Carter, and Harry
Choates. The company for whom the session
was done, Plantation Records, only released
two 45s for airplay: "Dallas" and "Jole Blon." It
wasn't until 1980 that an English label, Charly
Music, released an LP (The Flatlanders: One Road More) with all seventeen cuts.

The Flatlanders scattered soon after the
release of the two singles, but their music
has continued to influence new generations of
audiences and musicians. In particular, Joe
Ely and Jimmie Dale Gilmore are now internationally
known for their songwriting, performing,
and recording careers, and Butch
Hancock has developed a cultlike reputation
for his writing. In 1990 Rounder Records released
a CD reissue of fourteen songs from the
Nashville session. Aptly, it was entitled More a Legend than a Band.


Andy Wilkinson
Lubbock, Texas





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>