<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fil.008</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Brooks, Louise (1906-1985)</field>
      <field name="author">Gladysz, Thomas</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BROOKS, LOUISE (1906-1985)


Louise Brooks, ca. 1928.


Actress, dancer, and writer on film, Louise
Brooks is perhaps best known for her role as
Lulu in the silent film Pandora's Box (1929).
She was born Mary Louise Brooks on November
14, 1906, in Cherryvale, Kansas, to Leonard
and Myra Brooks, a lawyer and touring
speaker, respectively. Her first stage role was at
age four; she later performed as a dancer at
local clubs and fairs in southeastern Kansas.
At age fifteen Brooks joined the Denishawn
Dance Company, the leading modern dance
troupe in America. After two years with Denishawn,
Brooks left the company and landed
parts as a chorus girl in George White's Scandals
and as a specialty dancer in the Ziegfeld
Follies. She had the distinction of being
the first person to dance the Charleston in
London.

Brooks's performance in the Follies led to a
tryout in the movies. Her early films include
The American Venus (1926), It's the Old Army Game (1926), The Show-off (1926), and Love 'Em and Leave 'Em (1926), all of which were
social comedies typical of the era. Subsequent
dramatic roles include A Girl in Every Port
(1928), Beggars of Life (1928), and The Canary Murder Case (1929). Brooks appeared as Lulu,
a femme fatale, in G. W. Pabst's German production
of Pandora's Box in 1929, one of the
great films of the silent era. She also starred in
Pabst's Diary of a Lost Girl (1929) and in the
French production Prix de beauté (1930).

Brooks's career had declined by the mid-
1930s. After a brief sojourn in Wichita, the
once-celebrated actress settled in New York
City, where she lived for more than a decade
in obscurity. She later moved to Rochester,
New York, and began writing; her first article
appeared in 1956. Over the next three decades,
Brooks contributed numerous essays to various
film journals. Her highly acclaimed 1982
book, Lulu in Hollywood, includes essays
about her life and the careers of other movie
stars. Brooks's legendary beauty and distinctive
bob hairstyle have been celebrated in numerous
films, plays, novels, poems, comic
strips, artwork, and songs. She died of a heart
attack in Rochester on August 8, 1985.


Thomas Gladysz
Louise Brooks Society




Brooks, Louise. Lulu in Hollywood. New York: Knopf,
1982. Jaccard, Roland. Louise Brooks: Portrait of an Anti-Star. New York: Zoetrope, 1986. Paris, Barry. Louise Brooks. New York: Knopf, 1989.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>