<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ind.008</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Biotechnology</field>
      <field name="author">McCann, Peter B.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




Biotechnology

Biotechnology, with a particular emphasis on
agricultural biotechnology, is a relatively recent
but immensely important addition to the
industrial base of the Great Plains. The Nature
Biotechnology Directory identifies 119 biotechnology
companies in the U.S. Great Plains,
with 68 in Texas and 30 in Colorado (though
not all are located in the Plains portion of these
states). Of states that are completely in the
Plains region, Kansas has 11 such firms, Nebraska
8, South Dakota 1, and North Dakota
none. In the Canadian Prairie Provinces, Saskatchewan
is the hub of the industry, and a
closer look at agricultural biotechnology there
serves to elucidate what is being achieved.

Saskatchewan is the largest producer of
food and feed grains among the ten provinces
of Canada, and its economy is dominated by
agriculture. Saskatoon is a recognized world
center for agricultural biotechnology. Sustainable
agricultural production is the objective of
Saskatoon's agbiotech community as it moves
ahead with research and development to improve
crops of the Great Plains such as wheat,
barley, canola, flax, peas, and beans and to
find innovative uses for those crops.

Insect-resistant crops yield 8 to 10 percent
more per acre than conventional crops, canola
growers gain two bushels per acre with herbicide-
tolerant varieties, and a new wheat variety
yields 13 percent higher than the best conventional
variety. All this can be achieved with
reduced mechanical inputs, reduced chemical
and fertilizer use, and reduced equipment and
labor cost while at the same time promoting
environmental stewardship by reducing fuel
usage and greenhouse gas emissions and reducing
tillage. These agronomic advances represent
the first of three waves of agbiotech development,
with the second and third waves
just beginning.

The second wave of crops being developed
in Saskatchewan uses biotechnology to provide
improved quality traits, often stacked on
top of and incorporating the benefits from the
agronomic traits of the first wave such as herbicide
tolerance. Seeds with healthier edible
oil profiles, high-stearate oilseeds that do
not require hydrogenation, improved animal
feeding qualities, and special nutritional traits
such as high-lysine content are examples.

The third wave of agbiotech products goes
beyond food uses of crops into the area of industrial
and pharmaceutical products. Within
a few years, farmers will be growing ultrahigh-
value crops that have been engineered to
produce biopolymers–plastics from plants,
vehicle fuels and lubricants, vaccines for animal
and human use, and a whole range of
value-added products often collectively referred
to as products of molecular farming.
Renewable sources of energy and chemical
feed stocks from agriculture should become
commonplace within the next twenty years.

These second and third wave crops bring
with them the decommoditization of crops
from the Great Plains as extra value is added to
crops that have up until now been sold at generally
low world commodity prices. These "designer
crops" require segregation during harvest,
storage, and transportation in order to
preserve their identity and integrity through
to the end user, which will in turn change
the traditional grain-handling systems of the
Great Plains.

Saskatchewan's agricultural biotechnology
community is actively involved in all three
waves and has grown to a critical mass that
now includes some forty biotech companies
and institutions that employ approximately
2,000 people. Saskatchewan's agbiotech companies
were generating around $150 million in
annual sales in the late 1990s. With nearly 40
percent of Canada's agbiotech firms located in
Saskatoon, Saskatchewan is the country's top
center for agricultural biotechnology. The
forty biotechnology enterprises currently (in
2000) operating in Saskatoon are four times
the number active in the city in 1994, and new
agbiotech companies are being formed at a
rate of three or four per year.

More than 100 agbiotech research and development
projects are under way at the many
research centers in Saskatoon. They include
the development of transgenic vaccines for
cattle and hogs, the development of probiotic
products to enhance gastrointestinal function
in animals with the objective of increasing feed
utilization, gene mapping in cattle and hogs
targeted at increased productivity and improved
carcass quality, and improved animal
feeds and feed processing. Biotech developments
on the crop side include agbiological
products such as biofertilizers, biopesticides,
and the application of microbial metabolites in
both these areas; micropropagation of native
trees and grasses for land reclamation; plant
growth regulation; genetic engineering for tolerance
to crop stress factors such as drought,
heat, and cold; herbicide resistance for cereal,
vegetable, and pulse crop species; molecular
farming to produce therapeutic molecules in
oilseeds; development of new crop types such
as a new oilseed crop from a member of the
mustard family; and the reduction of anti-nutritional
compounds in existing crops.


Peter B. McCann
Ag-West Biotech Inc.





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>