<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.rel.044</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Sanapia (1895-1984)</field>
      <field name="author">Reinhardt, Akim D.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SANAPIA (1895-1984)

Sanapia (Memory Woman), the last known
Comanche Eagle Doctor, was born at Fort Sill,
Oklahoma, in the spring of 1895. She was one
of the most powerful Native women in the
Plains during the middle decades of the twentieth
century. Her father was a converted
Christian and her mother was a traditional
Comanche-Arapaho. Sanapia's mother, maternal
uncle, and maternal grandmother were
Eagle Doctors, and her grandmother reared
the girl in traditional Comanche ways.

From ages seven to thirteen Sanapia was
educated at the Cache Creek Mission School
in southern Oklahoma. Thereafter, she began
training with her mother. She was reluctant at
first, but her uncle had cured her of influenza
as a child and had made her promise to pursue
training as an Eagle Doctor when she was
older. He named her Memory Woman to remind
her of her pledge. Training included
learning herbal medicine, healing skills (including
sucking), and eagle power. Tradition,
however, stipulated that she could not begin
practicing until after menopause.

Sanapia was married three times, the first
time, briefly, at the age of seventeen. When her
second husband (with whom she had two
children) died in the 1930s, Sanapia's grief led
her to a period of drinking, gambling, and
depression. In 1945 she healed a child at her
sister's behest, and subsequently she assumed
her role as an Eagle Doctor. She eventually
incorporated elements of the Native American
Church and Christianity into her traditional
teachings.

By the 1960s she was the last surviving Comanche
Eagle Doctor with maximum powers.
Concerned that she would not be able to pass
on her powers before dying, she allowed anthropologist
David E. Jones to write an account
of her life and her healing powers. They
produced a book in 1972, which she hoped
would serve as a training manual for the future
generations.

See also NATIVE AMERICANS: Comanches.


Akim D. Reinhardt
Towson University




Jones, David E. Sanapia, Comanche Medicine Woman.
New York: Holt, Rinehart and Winston, 1972.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>