<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.045</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Mansfield, Mike (1903-2001)</field>
      <field name="author">Unruh, Angela</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MANSFIELD, MIKE (1903-2001)

Michael Joseph Mansfield was born in New
York City on March 16, 1903. He was five years
old when his mother died, and shortly thereafter
he moved to Great Falls, Montana, to live
with his father's aunt and uncle. His father
remained in New York, where he was a hotel
porter. Although his career took him to many
other places, Mansfield once said that he always
felt a homesickness when absent from
Montana.

After serving in the navy (he enlisted at the
age of fourteen), the army, and the marines, he
returned to Montana in 1922 and worked in
the Butte mines for the next eight years, first as
a miner, then as a mucker and mining engineer.
Although he had not even completed
grade school, Mansfield gained admittance to
the Montana School of Mines in Butte in 1927.
After his first year, he transferred to Montana
State University (later the University of Montana)
in Missoula, where he received bachelor's
and master's degrees in 1933 and 1934,
respectively. His thesis, on Korean-American
relations, anticipated a lifelong interest in
Asia. He stayed at the university as an administrator
and teacher of Latin American and Far
Eastern history until 1942. After entering politics,
he retained his position as professor of
history at the university on permanent tenure.

Mansfield was elected to the U.S. Congress
on the Democratic ticket in 1942, carrying
eleven of seventeen counties in Montana's
First District. He served five terms in Congress.
Surviving attacks at the height of Mc-
Carthyism for his views on China, he was
elected senator from Montana in 1952. Although
he won fewer counties than his opponent,
Republican Zales Ecton, he was elected
with a plurality of 6,600. Mansfield's support
came mainly from a belt of counties in the
northern half of the state, extending, with few
interruptions, from its western to its eastern
boundaries. He served in the Senate until 1977.
In the early 1960s he was the leading advocate
in Washington for stopping the war in Vietnam.
As Senate majority leader from 1961 to
1977 (the longest any member ever held that
position), Mansfield played a major role in the
passage of landmark domestic legislation, including
the Civil Rights Act of 1964, the Voting
Rights Act of 1965, reduction in the voting age
from twenty-one to eighteen, and Medicare,
as well as sundry foreign policy landmarks,
including the rapprochement between the
United States and China. He held the post of
American ambassador to Japan from 1976 to
1988 under Presidents Jimmy Carter and Ronald
Reagan.

Mike Mansfield died in Washington dc on
October 5, 2001, one year after the death of his
wife, Maureen, to whom he was married for
sixty-eight years.


Angela Unruh
The Maureen and Mike Mansfield Foundation




Mansfield, Mike, and Michael S. Sample. Mike Mansfield's
Montana. Billings: Goatrock Productions, 1972. Waldron,
Ellis. An Atlas of Montana Politics since 1864. Missoula:
Montana State Press, 1958.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>