<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pd.013</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Cannon, James Patrick (1890-1974)</field>
      <field name="author">Ryan, James G.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CANNON, JAMES PATRICK (1890-1974)

Ranking Communist Party (CPUSA) figure,
American Trotskyist movement founder, and
longtime Socialist Workers Party leader, James
Cannon was born in Rosedale, Kansas, on February
11, 1890. Poverty radicalized his immigrant
father, John, a laborer in a foundry. John
introduced the young James to Irish nationalism,
the Knights of Labor, populism, and finally
the Socialist Party. James displayed a deep
and lifelong anger at capitalism and the injustices
it spawned. He left high school to organize
for the Industrial Workers of the World.
Soon he joined the Socialist Party and rose
rapidly among its left wing. Cannon had taken
a path that would make him an acquaintance
of nearly all the era's celebrated radicals.

After Earl Browder's imprisonment during
World War I, Cannon edited Workers World,
the organ of the Socialist Party in Kansas. In
1919 the party expelled its left wing, and Cannon
became prominent in the nascent Communist
underground. He held important St.
Louis and Cleveland posts, then transferred to
New York City in 1921. There he helped head
the Workers Party, a legal organization, after
the "Red Scare" subsided and V. I. Lenin
shifted toward nonrevolutionary tactics. Between
1922 and 1928 Cannon served on the
Communist International's presidium and
headed International Labor Defense, a leftist
legal support group. He also backed William Z.
Foster's faction of what had become the CPUSA.

Cannon's life took a dramatic turn in 1928
while he was in the Soviet Union. In Moscow,
Leon Trotsky offered compelling criticism of
Joseph Stalin and the Soviet Union's direction.
Cannon returned to the United States carrying
Trotsky's writings. That October, Cannon and
100 followers were driven from the cpusa.
They called themselves the Communist League
of America (Left Opposition), began publishing
a newspaper, The Militant, and later a magazine,
New International. From that time on,
Cannon would consider Trotsky the custodian
of authentic Bolshevik values. The League
helped lead a sensational Minneapolis Teamster
strike, fused with A. J. Muste's followers,
and in 1936 entered the Socialist Party. The
Trotskyists were expelled the following year,
and Cannon founded the Socialist Workers
Party in 1938. By 1939 the movement had 1,000
American members and a following in labor
and intellectual circles.

Success brought schism during the early
months of World War II. Socialist Workers
Party figures Max Shachtman and James
Burnham argued that the Stalinists constituted
a new bureaucratic class in the Soviet
Union. Cannon, like Trotsky, considered the
Soviet Union's nationalized economy worth
defending, despite Stalin's dictatorship. In
early 1940 Shachtman's faction became the
Workers Party. In 1941 federal authorities used
the Smith Act to imprison Cannon and seventeen
other Socialist Workers Party figures and
Minneapolis Teamsters. Supposedly their organizations
had advocated the violent overthrow
of the U.S. government; actually they
opposed American foreign policy. Cannon
served thirteen months at Sandstone Penitentiary.
During the McCarthy era, a public that
drew few distinctions among radicals persecuted
the Socialist Workers Party and Communist
Party alike.

Cannon retired in 1953 but lived to see the
"New Left" of the 1960s and 1970s. He died on
August 21, 1974, believing that Vietnam War resisters,
African Americans, Hispanics, women,
youth, and gays were taking a permanent step
toward socialism in the United States.


James G. Ryan
Texas A&amp;M University at Galveston




Cannon, James Patrick. Papers. Wisconsin State Historical
Society, Madison WI. Wald, Alan. "James P. Cannon." In
Biographical Dictionary of the American Left, edited by
Bernard K. Johnpoll and Harvey Klehr. Westport CT:
Greenwood Press, 1986: 62–65.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>