<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.tra.035</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Stagecoaches</field>
      <field name="author">Lass, William E.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




STAGECOACHES

Stagecoaches were vehicles that transported
passengers, mail, and light freight over designated
routes. Patterned after the English
coach and four, which was introduced into the
American colonies, the name of the vehicles
described both the enclosed carriage and traveling
in stages between stations.

Stagecoaching in the Great Plains was stimulated
by the California gold rush and the
need for faster service than could be supplied
by wagons. In 1857 James E. Birch of the California
Stage Company contracted with the
federal government to run a biweekly mail
service over the 1,500-mile route from San Antonio,
Texas, to San Diego, California. But the
next year the contract was awarded to the Butterfield
Overland Mail. After the outbreak of
the Civil War the Overland Mail was transferred
to the central or California route that
ran through the Platte River valley and South
Pass. Butterfield subcontracted with Russell,
Majors and Waddell, the leading overland
freighters, to run stages from the Missouri
River to the recently opened Colorado gold
fields. After the bankruptcy of Russell, Majors
and Waddell, Ben Holladay, who came to be
known as the Stagecoach King, dominated the
business for several years before selling out
to Wells, Fargo and Company in 1866. Wells
Fargo and many local companies adjusted to
the construction of transcontinental railroads
by providing feeder service to those lines.
Stagecoaching was finally discontinued after
the establishment of railroad networks.

The Concord, manufactured in Concord,
New Hampshire, was the most famous stagecoach.
Because of its large size, rugged construction,
and attractiveness, it was preferred
by large companies. As a symbol of frontier
life the stagecoach has captured the popular
imagination, which continues to be fed by
movies and television.


William E. Lass
Mankato State University




Greeley, Horace. An Overland Journey from New York to
San Francisco in the Summer of 1859. New York: C. M.
Saxton, Barker and Company, 1860. Winther, Oscar Osburn.
The Transportation Frontier: Trans-Mississippi West,
1865–1890. New York: Holt, Rinehart and Winston, 1964.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>