<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.061</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Posey, Alexander (1873-1908)</field>
      <field name="author">Ballard, Charles</field>
      <field name="text">

 




POSEY, ALEXANDER (1873-1908)


Alexander Posey, 1908


Alexander Lawrence Posey, a well-known
Muskogee Creek poet and journalist, lived in
Indian Territory during the turbulent years
prior to and one year beyond Oklahoma statehood.
He is best remembered for a series of
humorous and politically insightful articles
printed while he was the owner and editor of
the Eufaula Journal. "Fus Fixico Letters," some
seventy-two in all, became a weekly feature of
Posey's newspaper and made use of voices and
personae of traditional Creek Indian figures to
comment on territorial politicians, elections,
members of the Dawes Commission, the issues
of coming statehood and an Indian state
to be called Sequoyah, as well as the general
resistance to "progress" and land allotments
led by the Creek historian Chitto Harjo.

Posey was born near present-day Eufaula,
Oklahoma, on August 3, 1873, the first child
of Nancy and Lewis Henderson Posey. He received
his postsecondary education at Bacone
Indian University, Muskogee, Oklahoma,
where he gained some recognition as a budding
poet and as a writer of commencement
orations. He was elected as a clerk in the Creek
House of Warriors and appointed as superintendent
of the Creek Orphan Asylum near Okmulgee.
He married Minnie Harris, a school-teacher
from Farmington, Arkansas. In his
writings, Posey emphasized the importance of
conforming to the new American society and
to what he felt were progressive viewpoints.

Although he had achieved a national journalistic
reputation, his interests had expanded
to include tribal folkways, land development,
and even oil and gas speculation. But his life
was cut short by a tragic drowning accident on
the morning of May 27, 1908. He was survived
by his young wife and two children.


Charles Ballard
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Littlefield, Daniel F., Jr. Alex Posey: Creek Poet, Journalist, and Humorist. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press,
1992. Posey, Alexander. The Fus Fixico Letters, edited by
Daniel F. Littlefield Jr. and Carol A. Pretty Hunter. Lincoln:
University of Nebraska Press, 1993.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>