<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.wat.014</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Mead, Elwood (1858-1936)</field>
      <field name="author">Fassett, Gordon W. MacKinnon, Anne</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MEAD, ELWOOD (1858-1936)

Elwood Mead was born on a farm near Patriot,
Indiana, on January 16, 1858, and was
educated at Purdue University. He would go
on to write the laws (though they were seldom
adopted in full) that became the late-nineteenth-century
model for water management in Great Plains and Rocky Mountain
states. Mead ended his career as commissioner
of the U.S. Bureau of Reclamation.

Mead first became interested in irrigation
in Colorado when he taught math and physics
at Fort Collins in 1882. He was appointed assistant
state engineer in 1885. Three years later
he became the first territorial engineer of Wyoming.
In 1889–90, at the age of thirty-one,
Mead wrote the water law in the constitution
and statutes for the new state of Wyoming,
aiming to avoid other western states' mistakes
and create a new system of active state ownership
and supervision of water. Mead believed
water law could foster strong agricultural
communities, and he sought to eliminate
speculation in water rights. Under Mead's system,
putting water to use and filing a claim
could not create a legal right to use water, as
had been the case in most of the West. He
required water users to obtain state permits;
the permits could be denied if a project was
deemed unwise. A panel of engineers served as
the primary tribunal in matters of establishment,
loss, and change of water rights. Water
rights were tied to actual use on designated
land to avoid speculation, a concern that
means cautious analysis of transfers of water
rights in Wyoming even today.

Mead's system was influential throughout
the Great Plains, Rocky Mountains, and Canada.
Nebraska adopted the entire system; most
states (for example, Oklahoma, North Dakota,
and South Dakota) balked at supplanting
judges with engineers and adopted only
the permit system portion.

Mead left Wyoming in 1898 for a career in
what he called social engineering–designing
irrigation colonies and promoting rural settlement
programs in Australia, California, and
Washington State. He became commissioner
of the Bureau of Reclamation in 1924. He later
mentored New Dealers on rural community
building and masterminded the Hoover Dam
(creating his giant namesake Lake Mead) on
the Colorado River. Mead died in Washington
DC on January 16, 1936.


Gordon W. Fassett
Cheyenne, Wyoming
Anne MacKinnon
Casper, Wyoming




Kluger, James R. Turning on Water with a Shovel: The
Career of Elwood Mead. Albuquerque: University of New
Mexico Press, 1992. Mead, Elwood. Papers, 1900–42. Water
Resources Center Archives, University of California,
Berkeley.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>