<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ct.007</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Brandon, Manitoba</field>
      <field name="author">Everitt, John C.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BRANDON, MONTANA

Brandon, the "Wheat City," is located on
the Assiniboine River in southwestern Manitoba.
It is the second largest urban place in
Manitoba. Although Manitoba was founded
in 1870, the current site of Brandon as well as
most of its hinterland were not included in the
province until expansion took place in 1881.
This territorial growth was closely related to
the building across the Prairies of the Canadian
Pacific Railway. Incorporated in 1882,
Brandon was founded in May 1881 as a divisional
point by the railway's Gen. Thomas
Rosser.

Brandon grew rapidly, reaching a population
of 15,000 by World War I. Following the
initial boom, growth was slow but steady, the
population total reaching 20,000 only in the
late 1940s and just under 40,000 by 1996.
However, recent developments have led to
a projected population of 45,000–and even
50,000 by some boosters–in the next few
years.

Brandon has principally acted as a service
center for its agricultural hinterland. It has
never had any of the advantages for manufacturing
that are noted by location theorists.
Many of the industries such as flour milling
that were built during the early growth
period were closely related to the agricultural
base. This trend has continued to the present.
Simplot Chemicals and Ayerst Organics have
boosted the industrial sector in Brandon, and
the opening of a huge pork-processing plant
by Maple Leaf led to the recent boosting of
Brandon's population projections.

Politically, Brandon can be characterized as
a rather conservative city within a more conservative
area of the province. However, in
the recent past the city has acted more like
Winnipeg and other Manitoba urban areas in
its electoral behavior. In 1969 the New Democratic
Party won the provincial riding of Brandon
East and added the other city riding of
Brandon West. Although later this seat reverted
to the Progressive Conservative Party,
the New Democratic Party won both Brandon
East and Brandon West when it swept back
into provincial power in 1999.

The future of Brandon seems more secure
than that of many of the surrounding smaller
settlements, as it is likely to continue to grow
in population as well as to continue to dominate
its trade area of approximately 200,000
people, which it serves as a service and education
center. In this context, Brandon University,
Assiniboine Community College, a federal
experimental farm, and an Agricultural
Extension Center are valuable assets, along
with various other branches of the provincial
government. Brandon is trying to improve its
image as a pleasant place to live and as a place
in which to retire. It is also trying to attract
tourists by developing a parks and recreation
area along the Assiniboine River.

As the face of agriculture changes regionally,
it is possible that "Wheat City" will become
a misnomer and that "Pork City" might
become more appropriate. For the most part,
however, the face that Brandon presents to the
world is likely to change more in detail than in
grand sweep.


John C. Everitt
Brandon University




Welsted, John, John Everitt, and Christoph Stadel, eds.
Brandon: Geographical Perspectives on the Wheat City. Regina:
University of Regina, Canadian Plains Research Center,
1988. Welsted, John, John Everitt, and Christoph Stadel,
eds. The Geography of Manitoba: Its Land and Its People. Winnipeg: University of Manitoba Press, 1997.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>