<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pe.027</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Flora</field>
      <field name="author">Keeler, Kathleen H. Locklear, James H.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




FLORA

More than 2,900 species of vascular plants
from some 730 genera in 159 families grow in
the Great Plains. The vast majority (all but 81
species in 8 families) are angiosperms (flowering
plants). For plants the Great Plains has
one of the most stressful climates: hot summers,
cold winters, frequent droughts, with
dramatic seasonal and annual variation. Consequently,
the plants that dominate the region
are herbaceous grasses and forbs (wildflowers)
derived from the plant families of temperate
regions rather than trees or plants from
families of tropical regions. The families with
the most genera and species are sunflowers
(Asteraceae), with more than 100 genera and
430 species, grasses (Poaceae, 76 genera, 260
species), sedges (Cyperaceae, 13 genera, 220
species), and legumes (Fabaceae, 34 genera,
158 species, or 46 genera, and 178 species if
Caesalpinaceae and Mimosaceae are included
in the Fabaceae). The precise numbers are
subject to revision as taxonomists improve
their understanding of the flora, but the pattern
is unlikely to change. Other groups with
numerous species are mustards (Brassicaceae),
lilies (Liliaceae), umbels (Apiaceae),
mints (Lamiaceae), and the penstemon family
(Scrophulariaceae).

Compared to North American deserts and
forests, Plains ecosystems formed very recently.
Consequently, there are only about 100
endemic species and no endemic genera or
families. The most common endemic species
are composites (Asteraceae, 27 species), and
legumes (Fabaceae, 21 species, especially Astragalus).
Surprisingly, there are no endemic
grasses.

Plants that are naturally rare in this region
tend to occur in restricted habitats, especially
at the western edge of the region, or in scattered
microhabitats, such as salt marshes.
However, reduction of formerly widespread
ecosystems such as tallgrass and midgrass
prairies to tiny fragments is putting many previously
common species at risk of extinction.
In addition, changes in land use, such as continuous
grazing and reduction of fire, pose
threats to some species: If a plant decreases
under grazing, or requires fire to prosper, it
may decline even if the area is otherwise undisturbed
and well managed. Historically,
both grazing and fire occurred episodically,
and some species relied on the changing conditions.

Approximately 12 percent of all Plains species
have recently been introduced to the region:
plants from the eastern United States
(previously excluded by drought, recurrent
fire, and absence of tree cover), plants from
the western United States (previously unable
to cross the mountains), and plants from Europe,
Asia, and occasionally Africa and South
America brought by humans. Some of these,
such as Salsola (tumbleweeds), are able to invade
natural ecosystems, but most introduced
plants remain associated with humans. These
can be expected to steadily increase in number
and diversity where human impact increases.
The introduced plants form the basis for an
ongoing evolution of the flora, in some cases
changing in response to Plains conditions,
and in other cases hybridizing with their native
relatives to form new varieties and possibly
species.

Great Plains flora is dominated by perennial
herbs, plants that die back to the roots
each winter then resprout in the spring. Trees
are abundant on the edges of the region and
in the larger river valleys of the eastern Plains.
Beyond these areas, trees and shrubs, because
they are more injured by prairie fires than
herbs (especially grasses), were historically
found only in areas protected from fire, such
as near cliffs or on islands and at bends in
rivers. A few shrubs–lead plant (Amorpha
canescens), for example–survive well within
the open grassland. Others, such as sumac
(Rhus) and dogwoods (Cornus), rapidly increase
in unburned prairie.


Kathleen H. Keeler
University of Nebraska-Lincoln
James H. Locklear
Nebraska Statewide Arboretum




Great Plains Flora Association. Flora of the Great Plains.
Lawrence: University Press of Kansas, 1986.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>