<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ag.078</field>
      <field name="titleMain">XIT Ranch</field>
      <field name="author">Dagel, Kenneth C.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




XIT Ranch

The XIT Ranch encompassed more than three
million acres across ten counties on the Llano
Estacado in western Texas. Considered the
largest cattle ranch in the world, the XIT also
leased land in the Dakotas and in Montana.
The XIT stretched for more than 200 miles in
the Texas Panhandle and had 575 miles of outside
fence. The first 22,000 cattle arrived from
Fort Concho in 1885 and the number maintained
on the XIT eventually grew to 150,000.
The ranch, which employed as many as 100
cowboys, was organized into seven divisions
with a headquarters at Channing. The brand
XIT was the idea of Ab Blocker, a trail driver
who persuaded management that any good
brand should be easy to make with a simple
iron, but also be difficult to brand over by
rustlers.

The land the XIT was established on was sold
by the state of Texas to the Chicago-based Capitol
Syndicate Company in 1882. This became
the Capitol Freehold Land and Investment
Company, Ltd., in 1885, which included investors
from the United States and Britain. The
Syndicate Company received title to the land
in exchange for constructing a new capitol
building in Austin. The Capitol building, completed
in 1888, ultimately cost $3,224,593.45,
which meant the Syndicate Company paid
$1.07 per acre for the land that would become
the XIT. Because of the high price of land and
the declining prices of cattle, the XIT was dismantled
in the early twentieth century. The
last XIT cattle, 13,560 head, were sold in November
1912, and the vast ranch was sold in
large parcels to other ranchers and in small
acreages to farmers from 1901 to the 1950s.


Kenneth C. Dagel
Missouri Western State College




Haley, J. Evetts. The XIT Ranch of Texas and the Early Days
of the Llano Estacado. Norman: University of Oklahoma
Press, 1953. Nordyke, Lewis. Cattle Empire: The Fabulous
Story of the 3,000,000 acre XIT. New York: William Morrow
and Company, 1949.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>