<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.083</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Wiseman, Adele (1928-1992)</field>
      <field name="author">Panofsky, Ruth</field>
      <field name="text">

 




WISEMAN, ADELE (1928-1992)

Canadian writer Adele Wiseman was born on
May 21, 1928, and raised in Winnipeg, Manitoba.
Her parents had emigrated from the
Ukraine in 1923 and spent two years in Montreal
before settling in Winnipeg's North End,
a vibrant enclave of Jewish, German, Ukrainian,
and Slavic immigrants. Wiseman earned
a bachelor of arts degree in English and psychology
from the University of Manitoba in
1949. Following graduation, she lived in London,
Rome, and New York, where she wrote
and worked at a number of jobs. From 1964 to
1969 Wiseman lived in Montreal, where she
taught English at Sir George Williams (now
Concordia) University and Macdonald College
of McGill University. She was later writer
in residence at several Canadian universities
and head of the May Studios (Writing Program)
at Banff Centre for the Arts.

Wiseman wrote two novels, The Sacrifice,
which received the Governor General's Literary
Award for fiction in 1956, and Crackpot
(1974). Both novels employ biblical metaphors,
are set in (the unnamed city of ) Winnipeg,
and explore the lives of Jewish immigrants
who settle on the Canadian Prairies. The Sacrifice is the tragic story of a butcher who
murders a local temptress. The biblical story
of Abraham and Isaac resonates throughout
Wiseman's narrative. Her own Abraham–
once proud and certain–is transplanted from
the Old to the New World, where he loses his
third son and his precarious hold on life in a
novel that charts the demise of a patriarch.
Crackpot shifts from tragic to comic mode and
experiments with narrative form and perspective.
The work celebrates the resilience of
Hoda, an obese Jewish prostitute whose life,
like Abraham's, is shattered by moral and spiritual
challenges.

Wiseman also wrote two plays (The Lovebound,
ca. 1960; Testimonial Dinner, 1978);
two books for children (Kenji and the Cricket,
1988; Puccini and the Prowlers, 1992); and three
works of nonfiction (Old Markets, New World,
1964; Old Woman at Play, 1978; Memoirs of a Book Molesting Childhood and Other Essays,
1987). Her correspondence with fellow writer
and friend is available in Selected Letters of Margaret Laurence and Adele Wiseman (1997).

See also CITIES AND TOWNS: Winnipeg, Manitoba.


Ruth Panofsky
Ryerson Polytechnic University




Greene, Elizabeth, ed. We Who Can Fly: Poems, Essays and Memories in Honour of Adele Wiseman. Dunvegan, Ontario:
Cormorant Books, 1997. Panofsky, Ruth, ed. Room of One's Own 16 (1993). Adele Wiseman issue. Adele Wiseman
Papers, York University, Toronto.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>