<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pd.049</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Strong, Anna Louise (1885-1970)</field>
      <field name="author">Frost, Molly Spitzer</field>
      <field name="text">

 




STRONG, ANNA LOUISE (1885-1970)

Anna Louise Strong was a foreign correspondent
and social activist whose midwestern
idealism and pioneering spirit led her to extended
stays in Russia and China. Although
never a member of the Communist Party, she
sympathized with the Communist cause and
wrote of its struggles with a vibrant naivete,
believing that a new era of human progress
had arrived.

Anna Louise Strong was born on November
25, 1885, in a two-room parsonage in
Friend, Nebraska, where her father, Sydney
Strong, was a Congregational minister who
was deeply involved in progressive movements.
When she was not yet two, family lore
relates, a late summer cyclone lifted her from
the front yard and deposited her, relatively unscathed,
in the cow pasture some distance
away–an archetypal Plains experience.

Sydney Strong's ministry took the family to
various midwestern locations such as Cincinnati,
Ohio, and Oak Park, Illinois. A diligent
and precocious student, Anna finished high
school at fifteen, graduated from Oberlin College
summa cum laude, and became, at age
twenty-three, the youngest woman to receive a
doctorate from the University of Chicago.

In Kansas City in 1911, Strong was director
of the Child Welfare Exhibit Program, an organization
dedicated to improving the wellbeing
of urban children. It was there that she
embraced socialism and decided to devote her
life to progressive social causes. In 1919, as editor
of the Seattle Union Record, she played an
important role in the Seattle General Strike. In
1921 she traveled to the new Soviet Union,
which became her principal home until 1949,
when she was expelled by Stalin as a suspected
spy. During this time she made yearly trips
and lecture tours back to the United States,
while also covering revolutionary developments
in China, Mexico, and Spain. Shunned
by both the American right and left and labeled
a Soviet spy during the McCarthy era,
she lived and wrote in California until she decided
to take up residence in China in 1958.

Strong was warmly received by the Chinese
Communist leaders, who saw her as a valuable
propaganda mouthpiece they could use in
their dealings with the West. She had interviewed
Mao Tse-tung in 1946 at the Communist
headquarters in Yenan, where he first used
the term "paper tiger" to refer to Western imperialists.
Her death in Beijing in March 1970
was an occasion for public mourning and a
state funeral. She is buried in the Revolutionary
Martyrs' Cemetery in Beijing.


Molly Spitzer Frost
George Washington University




Strong, Anna Louise. China's Millions. New York: Coward-McCann,
1928. Strong, Anna Louise. I Change Worlds. New
York: Holt, Rinehart and Winston, 1935. Strong, Tracy, and
Helene Keyssar. Right in Her Soul: The Life of Anna Louise
Strong. New York: Random House, 1983.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>