<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.med.045</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Telegraph</field>
      <field name="author">Jepsen, Thomas C.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




TELEGRAPH

The electric telegraph played an important
role in the lives of the inhabitants of the Great
Plains from its first appearance in the region
in the 1860s until well into the twentieth century.
Work on a coast-to-coast telegraph line
in the United States began when Congress
passed the Pacific Telegraph Act in 1860. The
Western Union Telegraph Company supervised
the construction of the line, which ran
from Omaha, Nebraska, through Laramie,
Wyoming, to San Francisco, California. Upon
its completion in October 1861, the transcontinental
telegraph spelled an end to the
Pony Express, which had operated during its
construction.

Some of the construction crews used electric
batteries to give shocks to the Arapaho
and Cheyenne inhabitants of the region and
frighten them away, creating an atmosphere of
hostility between the Native Americans and
the telegraph companies. After the Sand Creek
Massacre in 1864, the Native Americans realized
that the telegraph could be used to summon
troops, and they began a campaign to
tear down the wires in what is now western
Nebraska, eastern Colorado, and southern
Wyoming. This continued until 1869, when
the lines were moved to the trackside of the
newly completed Union Pacific Railroad. As
in the United States, the completion of a
cross-country telegraph system in western
Canada preceded the building of the transcontinental
railway. The Canadian Pacific
Railway Telegraph was operational clear to the
Pacific Coast ten years before the completion
of the transcontinental Canadian Pacific Railway
in 1885.

Tributary lines soon connected major
towns and cities to the main line. A mutually
beneficial relationship grew up between the
telegraph companies and the railroads. Western
Union telegraph operators were stationed
in each railroad depot and used the telegraph
to signal train movements from one station to
the next. When operators were not busy with
train orders, they sent personal messages,
received commodity reports, and arranged
shipments for local farmers and merchants.
Although the stereotypical telegraph operator
in western lore is a male, women also worked
as telegraphers. The percentage of women
telegraphers in the Plains states grew from approximately
5 percent in 1870 to 10 percent in
1900.

During the 1870s and 1880s populists and
members of the Grange movement accused
the railroad and telegraph companies of manipulating
commodity prices and shipping
rates. The Interstate Commerce Commission,
established in 1887 to regulate railroad shipping
rates, was chartered to regulate the telegraph
industry as well in 1910. The use of the
telegraph began to decline after 1900 as it was
replaced by the telephone for personal messages
and by centralized traffic-control systems
for railroad use. The depot telegrapher
lived on in movies like Western Union (1939)
and Kansas Pacific (1953) as a nostalgic symbol
of a bygone era.

The problems of settling and governing the
Great Plains were those of time and space; the
telegraph solved these problems elegantly by
compressing the time required to communicate
between widely separated cities, towns,
and forts from days to mere seconds. For
newspaper editors the telegraph meant the
swift arrival of news from the East. For farmers
the telegraph provided a means to arrange
the shipment of crops and cattle. And for all
ordinary men and women the telegraph enabled
personal communications with distant
friends and family.

See also TRANSPORTATION: Railroads, United States; Railways, Canada.


Thomas C. Jepsen
National Coalition of Independent Scholars




Burnet, Robert. Canadian Railway Telegraph History. Etobicoke,
Ontario: Telegraph Key and Sounder, 1997. Gabler,
Edwin. The American Telegrapher: A Social History, 1860– 1900. New Brunswick NJ: Rutgers University Press, 1988.
Jepsen, Thomas. "The Telegraph Comes to Colorado: A
New Technology and Its Consequences." Essays and Monographs in Colorado History 7 (1987): 1–25.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>