<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.065</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Riggs, Rollie Lynn (1899-1954)</field>
      <field name="author">Justice, Daniel Heath</field>
      <field name="text">

 




RIGGS, ROLLIE LYNN (1899-1954)
 
"A scene from The Cherokee Night by Lynn Riggs as presented at the Provincetown Playhouse by the Community Theatre Division of the Federal Theatre Project, July 1936"


One of Oklahoma's finest playwrights and poets,
confidant to Joan Crawford and Bette
Davis, and critically acclaimed contemporary
of Eugene O'Neill and Tennessee Williams,
Rollie Lynn Riggs was an enigma to most who
knew him during his short life. He spent his
professional career exploring the unique character
and spirit of Oklahoma and its precursor,
Indian Territory, while shrouding his personal
life from public scrutiny. As an acculturated
allotment-era Cherokee and a closeted gay
man in the first part of the twentieth century,
Riggs traveled across the country and the
world in search of both artistic acclaim and
security. The latter eluded him to the end of
his life.

Born in Indian Territory on August 31, 1899,
near present-day Claremore, Oklahoma, Riggs
was educated briefly at the University of Oklahoma
in Norman and lived at various times in
Santa Fe, Paris, Chicago, New York, and Hollywood.
His poetry and plays focus almost exclusively
on the land and people of rural
Oklahoma, and he wrote with a dedication
to respectfully and accurately representing
the speech, philosophies, and cultures of his
youth. His poetry follows in much the same
fashion but also includes deeply reflective and
melancholy elegies and poems of alienation
and solitude. His most famous play, Green Grow the Lilacs (1929), became the model in
1943 for the Rodgers and Hammerstein musical
Oklahoma! His only play to focus on Indian
issues was also his favorite: The Cherokee Night
(1930). Lynn Riggs died in New York City on
June 29, 1954, of cancer.

See also FILM: Oklahoma!


Daniel Heath Justice
University of Toronto




Braunlich, Phyllis Cole. Haunted by Home: The Life and Letters of Lynn Riggs. Norman: University of Oklahoma
Press, 1988.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>