<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.war.029</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Military Bases</field>
      <field name="author">Wishart, David J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MILITARY BASES

The Great Plains, with wide-open spaces permitting
weapons testing and troop maneuvers
in empty areas and flight practice under clear
skies, as well as interior-of-the-continent security,
is a major military region. From Offutt
Air Force Base just south of Omaha, Nebraska,
the United States Strategic Command
(USSTRATCOM) wields its awesome power over
a vast arsenal of bombers, missiles, submarines,
subsidiary bases, and about 119,000 military
and civilian personnel worldwide. The
Canadian Land Command is also Plainsbased,
with its headquarters at Winnipeg,
Manitoba. Altogether, in 1995, there were fifty-seven
military bases in the Great Plains, their
distribution reaching from Canadian Forces
Air Base at Cold Lake, Alberta, to Laughlin Air
Force Base at Del Rio, Texas. These bases include
air force, army, or land command, national
guard and reserves, as well as military
medical centers, training sites, arsenals, and
combat ranges. (Recruiting stations, though
they are strictly speaking also bases, are excluded
from this count.)

Some of the bases are massive, both in terms
of personnel and extent. In 1995 Fort Carson
Army Base, for example, on the south side of
Colorado Springs, Colorado, had 16,200 active
duty personnel and stretched over 373,000
acres, and Fort Sill Army Base at Lawton,
Oklahoma, had 17,795 men and women on
active duty. Eight other bases had more than
5,000 active personnel. Some bases, however,
have only small maintenance staffs. Pueblo
Army Depot, fourteen miles to the east of
Pueblo, Colorado, has two people on active
duty, and the Cornhusker Army Ordnance
Plant at Grand Island, Nebraska, has a lonely
staff of one.

Military bases, as frontier forts, had proliferated
in the Great Plains in the 1860s and
1870s at the height of the Indian wars. Most
of these posts were closed by the 1890s as the
Indians, defeated more by famine and disease
than in battle, were restricted to reservations.
Some of the contemporary bases, however,
link back to nineteenth-century military posts.
Fort Leavenworth Army Base, at Leavenworth,
Kansas, was founded in 1827, and Fort Riley,
just west of Manhattan, Kansas, has been an
army base since 1853. Military installations
again proliferated during World Wars I and II,
but most were disassembled when the wars
ended. Others were continued: seventeen of
the contemporary American bases were established
from 1941 to 1943. These include Goodfellow
Air Force Base near San Angelo, Texas;
Cannon Air Force Base near Clovis, New Mexico;
and Ellsworth Air Force Base near Rapid
City, South Dakota.

The larger military bases are substantial settlements
in their own right. Fort Carson, in
addition to its active personnel, employed
more than 4,000 civilians in 1989 and was
home to 39,000 family members. There were
four schools on the base, a day-care center for
287 children, a 195-bed hospital, and various
stores. Relatively few Plains towns can boast a
population and array of services like this.

Because military bases are such an integral
part of the settlement fabric in many parts of
the Great Plains, a base closing can be calamitous
to the functioning of nearby communities.
Recent closures include Canadian Forces
bases in Penhold and Calgary, Alberta, Lowry
Air Force Base in Denver, and Carswell Air
Force Base in Fort Worth, Texas. Some proposed
closures were resisted. Goodfellow Air
Force Base was scheduled to be closed in 1978.
It was saved by the energetic campaigning of a
"Blitz Committee," formed by the San Angelo
City Council, aided by the behind-the-scenes
lobbying of Sen. John Tower. Nevertheless, a
military base is a precarious foundation for
the local economy, particularly in phases of
reduced government expenditures.


David J. Wishart
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Cragg, Dan. Guide to Military Installations. Harrisburg PA:
Stackpole Books, 1988. Evinger, William. Directory of
United States Military Bases Worldwide. Phoenix: Oryx
Press, 1995. Hoover, Karl D. Base Closure: Politics or National
Defense Issue? Goodfellow Air Force Base, Texas,
1978-1981. San Angelo TX: Headquarters Air Training
Command History and Research Office, 1989.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>