<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.mus.044</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Territory Bands</field>
      <field name="author">Berg, Chuck</field>
      <field name="text">

 




TERRITORY BANDS

The term territory band refers to those Plains
and midwestern dance bands of the 1920s and
1930s that played throughout an expansive
geographic area extending from Texas in the
south to Nebraska in the north and from St.
Louis in the east to Denver in the west. Typically,
territory bands were headquartered in
the region's major cities, principally, Kansas
City, Oklahoma City, Dallas, Houston,
Omaha, St. Louis, and Denver. These urban
centers, responding to demands for Jazz Age
and Swing Era dance music as well as accompaniments
for "silent" films, supported large,
diversified musical communities. Traveling
bands, drawn from such big city talent pools,
were assembled by bookers for strings of onenighters
at rural dance halls in the small towns
of the surrounding "territory." Unfortunately,
the history of territory bands, especially during
the 1920s, is sketchy because these ensembles
seldom, if ever, had opportunities to
record. Among the more than 100 traveling
dance bands active in the 1920s were those of
Alphonso Trent (Dallas), Doc Ross (Oklahoma
City), Troy Floyd (San Antonio), Walter
Page (Oklahoma City and Kansas City), and
Jesse Stone (Kansas City).

In the 1930s, with the Plains hit hard by the
Great Depression, economic necessity brought
many of the region's best musicians to Kansas
City, a wide-open town where whiskey and jazz
flowed twenty-four hours a day, thanks to political
boss Tom Pendergast. Aside from supporting
its own vibrant nightlife, Kansas City
became the center for the area's territory
bands. This concentration of so much jazz talent
was significant in consolidating a distinctive
Kansas City style. Erasing the last influences
of the contrapuntal New Orleans
tradition by replacing tuba with string bass
and banjo with guitar and by expanding the
size of groups from combos to big bands, the
easygoing and swinging Kansas City style also
capitalized on blues and riff-based ensembles,
which, while pleasing dancers, also encouraged
virtuoso soloing. During the 1930s, the
Kansas City-based bands of Bennie Moten,
Walter Page, Count Basie, and Jay McShann all
took their turns touring the Plains as territory
bands.


Chuck Berg
University of Kansas




Kansas City Jazz Museum. Kansas City . . . and All That's Jazz. Kansas City MO: Andrew McMeel Publishing, 1999.
Pearson, Nathan W., Jr. Goin' to Kansas City. Urbana: University
of Illinois Press, 1988. Russell, Ross. Jazz Style in Kansas City and the Southwest. Berkeley: University of
California Press, 1971.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>