<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.med.007</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Brokaw, Tom (b. 1940)</field>
      <field name="author">Cornette, M. L.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BROKAW, TOM (b. 1940)


Tom Brokaw


Tom Brokaw, editor, author, and TV anchor,
was born in Webster, South Dakota, on February
6, 1940. Brokaw's parents belonged to the
generation that would later be featured in his
1998 best-seller, The Greatest Generation. During
World War II his father, Red Brokaw, was
an operator of construction machinery and
snowplows on a small air force base at Igloo in
western South Dakota. His mother, Jean, was
a typical 1940s housewife. Later the family
moved to Yankton, South Dakota, where Brokaw
worked at a local radio station, KYNT. He
graduated from Yankton High School, where
he met his wife, Meredith Auld, a former Miss
South Dakota.

Brokaw attended the University of Iowa in
Iowa City but later finished his college degree
at the University of South Dakota at Vermillion.
His first professional job on television
was in Sioux City, Iowa, with KTIV-TV. From
1962 to 1965 he worked in Omaha for kmtv.
Then in 1965 he joined WSB-TV in Atlanta,
Georgia. NBC News scouts liked the young investigative
reporter's coverage of the civil
rights movement, and in 1973 he was hired as
nbc White House correspondent. He became
cohost of the Today show in 1976, a position
he held until 1981. He was then appointed anchor
of the NBC Nightly News.

Brokaw's coverage of world and national
news has included the signing on the White
House lawn of the historic Middle East peace
agreement, the fall of the Berlin Wall, and
human-rights abuses in Tibet as well as the
first exclusive U.S. one-on-one interview with
Mikhail Gorbachev and an interview with the
Dalai Lama. He was the first anchor to report
from the site of the Oklahoma City bombing
and from the scene of the 1996 TWA Flight 800
tragedy. In 1999 he did the first North American
television interview with Russian prime
minister Yevgeny Primakov and was the first
of the network evening news anchors to travel
to Tirana, Albania, during the NATO air strikes
in the former Yugoslavia.

Awards for his investigative reporting are
numerous. They include a Peabody Award for
his report "To Be an American" and Emmy
Awards for his "China in Crisis" special reports
and for his reports on the 1992 floods in
the Midwest. He received the Dennis Kauff
Memorial Award for Lifetime Achievement in
Journalism from Boston University and the
Lowell Thomas Award from Marist College.
He was inducted into Broadcasting and Cable
TV's Hall of Fame in 1977. He is also a recipient
of the Neuharth Award, presented by the Freedom
Forum every fall at the University of
South Dakota. The Tom Brokaw Award is presented
yearly to an outstanding South Dakota
media person.


M. L. Cornette
University of South Dakota




Brokaw, Tom. The Greatest Generation. New York: Random
House, 1998.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>