<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.afam.010</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Brooks, Gwendolyn (1917–2000)</field>
      <field name="author">Bolden, B.J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BROOKS, GWENDOLYN (1917–2000)

Photograph of Gwendolyn Brooks (poetryfoundation.org)
       

Gwendolyn Brooks was born in Topeka, Kansas,
on June 7, 1917, to native-born Kansans
Keziah Corine Wims and David Anderson
Brooks. Her mother was born in Topeka,
Kansas, attended Topeka High School and
Emporia Normal, and later became the fifthgrade
teacher of Monroe School in Topeka.
Her father was born in Atchison, Kansas, but
his family moved to Oklahoma when he was
nine, and he remained there until he completed
high school. He then attended Fisk
University in Nashville, Tennessee, where he
planned to pursue a medical career, but he left
the university at the end of his first year. David
and Keziah met during the summer of 1914
and married in July 1916. Gwendolyn, one of
their two children, was born June 7, 1917,
in Topeka, Kansas. The family relocated to
Chicago when Gwendolyn was five weeks of
age, and she lived there for the remainder
of her life, developing a fierce identity as a
Chicagoan.

Gwendolyn's parents recognized her early
talents in creative expression and nurtured her
desire to write. Her mother regularly relieved
her of household chores and taught her the art
of oral recitation during Gwendolyn's preschool
years. Likewise, her father, who revered
books and education, provided her with a
writing desk and bookcases to house her growing
collection of literary works. Brooks began
rhyming around the age of seven and compiling
poetry notebooks by eleven. Brooks's
first poem, "Eventide," was published in American
Childhood magazine in 1930. By 1934
Brooks had become a regular contributor to
the Chicago Defender newspaper and, in a twoyear
period, published more than seventy-five
poems in the weekly poetry column "Lights
and Shadows."

Brooks attended public schools in Chicago
and graduated from Forrestville Elementary
School, Englewood High School (1934), and
Wilson Junior College (1936). In 1938, when
they were both twenty-one years old, Gwendolyn
Brooks married Henry Lowington
Blakely II, and together they had two children,
Henry III and Nora. Their first home was a
kitchenette apartment, located at 43rd and
South Park on Chicago's South Side. In 1941
Brooks had her first formal poetry lessons
when Inez Stark Cunningham, a Chicago socialite
and editor of Poetry: A Magazine of
Verse, volunteered to teach a poetry class at
Chicago's South Side Community Art Center.
Out of this a.liation, Brooks broadened her
poetic traditions and techniques and, in 1943,
won the Midwestern Writers Conference Poetry
Award.

During her life, Gwendolyn Brooks published
more than twenty books, including poetry,
prose, fiction, and autobiography. Her
first poetry collection was A Street in Bronzeville
(1945); her second one, Annie Allen
(1949), won her the Pulitzer Prize in May
1950. She was the first black writer to win the
prize. She published one novel, Maud Martha
(1953), a children's poetry collection, Bronzeville
Boys and Girls (1956), and a third volume
of poetry, The Bean Eaters (1960). Brooks remains
highly acclaimed for her adroitness in
merging character vignettes developed from
the society that surrounded her and intertwining
those stories with the complex structures
of European poetic forms like the sonnet,
folk and literary ballads, terza rima, and
rhyme royal. Additionally, she honed the
rhythmic flow of form using rhetorical strategies
like anaphora, alliteration, and polyptoton.
In much of her poetry after In the Mecca
(1968), Brooks was not as form-conscious,
often employing free verse to tell a succinct
story but still manipulating story and structure
with the flourish of repetition, as in anadiplosis
and epistrophe, in place of her former
strict metrical lines.

Brooks was highly acclaimed for her poetry
and was the poet laureate of Illinois from 1968
to 2000. She held the post of distinguished
professor of English at Chicago State University
from 1989 to 2000. In 1985 she became the
29th Consultant in Poetry to the Library of
Congress. She was a member of the American
Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters; the
recipient of the National Endowment for the
Arts Lifetime Achievement Award in 1989; the
only American to receive the Society for Literature
Award, University of Greece, 1990;
the National Endowment for the Humanities'
Jefferson Lecturer, 1994; and a National Book
Awards Medalist for Distinguished Contribution
to American Letters, 1994. In 1995 she
received the National Medal of Arts at the
White House; in 1998 she was inducted into
the International Literary Hall of Fame for
Writers of African Descent; and in 1999 she
was inducted as the sixty-fifth poet into the
Academy of American Poets. She died in her
Chicago home on December 3, 2000.




B.J. Bolden
Chicago State University




Bolden, B. J. Urban Rage in Bronzeville: Social Commentary
in the Poetry of Gwendolyn Brooks, 1945–1960. Chicago:
Third World Press, 1999. Melhem, D. H. Gwendolyn
Brooks: Poetry and the Heroic Voice. Lexington: University
Press of Kentucky, 1987.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>