<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.084</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Voting Patterns, Canada</field>
      <field name="author">Lambert, Geoffrey</field>
      <field name="text">

 




VOTING PATTERNS, CANADA

The three Prairie Provinces are often regarded
as a single entity. In fact, their political histories
and voting patterns are quite different.

When Manitoba entered the Canadian
Confederation in 1870, its population was
mainly Métis. By the turn of the century the
dominant group was of Ontario British stock.
Later waves of immigration from eastern Europe
(especially the Ukraine) and, more recently,
from South and Southeast Asia and
parts of Latin America added diversity to the
social fabric and political culture of the province.
It was, however, the Ontario immigration
that had the most profound effect on
Manitoba politics.

Manitoba is the most politically competitive
of the three provinces and arguably the least
likely to support radical new parties. In common
with other provinces, Farmer and progressive
parties did well in the period between
the two world wars. However, since the late
1950s the major trends have been the habitual
weakness of the Liberals (who last won a Manitoba
provincial election in 1953) and the regular
alternation in office of the New Democrats
and the Progressive Conservatives. In the eight
elections between 1969 and 1995, only twice
was a government granted a majority of more
than five seats in the fifty-seven-member legislature.
The New Democrats and Progressive
Conservatives have each formed the government
after four of those elections. On only one
occasion have the Liberals done well enough
even to form the Official Opposition.

It has been argued that a diagonal line can be
drawn across Manitoba, cutting right through
the capital city and dividing the province into
two political regions. The Progressive Conservatives'
loyal base has been among the largely
Anglo-Saxon and Mennonite farmers of the
province's southwest and the business and professional
communities of the south end of
Winnipeg. North of the line are the descendants
of the later-arriving ethnic communities
who settled on the less-productive land and
who tend to vote center-left. Parties win or lose
elections depending on their ability to win
seats straddling the line.

Saskatchewan has been described as "social
democratic." It felt the Ontario influence less
than did Manitoba and has had a larger measure
of British, eastern European, and American
immigration. Its "left-wing" tendencies
are demonstrated by the fact that the New
Democratic Party and its predecessor, the Cooperative
Commonwealth Federation, have
held power most of the time since 1944. In a
province of small cities and towns, the New
Democratic Party, as in Manitoba, does best
in the larger communities, but here it also
does well in rural areas. Saskatchewan was
probably the province worst hit by the Depression,
and it has a long history of cooperatives
and other collective action in the farming
community. The major challenger has been
the Liberals. The Progressive Conservatives
have formed only two governments since the
Depression.

Alberta is commonly regarded as the most
"American" of Canadian provinces. Its early
settlers (many of them indeed midwestern
Americans) brought with them more individualism
(and evangelicalism) than was to be
found in the other two provinces. The prosperity
brought by the oil, gas, and agricultural
sectors (Alberta is the wealthiest and lowesttaxed
Canadian province) has bred an American-style distaste for government, and as a result
basic conservatism is more acceptable
there. By contrast, the other Prairie Provinces
are less vibrant economically and more dependent
on federal government largess.

Alberta has a history of electing parties to
power for long periods and with huge majorities.
The Liberals held office from the province's
entry into Confederation in 1905 until
1921. The United Farmers of Alberta then held
office until 1935. Social Credit (a mix of social
conservatism, populism, free enterprise, and
unorthodox monetary doctrine) then held office
for thirty-six years, sustained in power by
the booming oil industry. The old-fashioned
image of the party and a desire for change led
to their replacement by the Progressive Conservatives
in 1971. They still held office in 1998.
Social Credit has disappeared, the New Democratic
Party is weak outside Edmonton and
the north, and the Liberals have only recently
revived as a viable alternative.

What the three provinces have in common
is the greater strength of the right-of-center in
the rural areas, the left-of-center in urban core
areas, and a relatively high level of competition
in the suburbs. Ethnicity is also a factor.
Further, the substantial First Nations vote, if
mobilized, has tended to go center-left in all
three provinces. Where the provinces differ
most is in the relative strength of the left-right
forces and in the particular parties that have
served as a mouthpiece for different interests.

There is perhaps greater affinity among
them when one examines voting for the federal
House of Commons. All three provinces,
to a greater or lesser extent, share the belief
that the West has been badly treated by governments
dominated by Central Canada (Ontario
and Quebec). There have been disputes
over resource policy, government discretionary
spending, tariff policy, boundaries, and
the status of Quebec and the French language,
among others. For the last forty years the Liberals
(who have been in power nationally
most of the time) have enjoyed only occasional
support on the Prairies, Alberta being
especially resistant to Liberal allures. Even at
the height of Liberal popularity elsewhere, the
Prairies have remained unimpressed. Both the
Progressive Conservatives and the New Democratic
Party have had strong representation
(though the latter has been weak in Alberta).
The long-simmering aftermath of the ill-fated
CF-18 decision in 1986 (a highly controversial
aircraft maintenance decision) manifested itself
in the dramatic rise of the Reform Party
in the elections of 1993 and 1997. Reform,
founded in 1987, favors neoconservative economics
and social conservatism. The long-dominant
Progressive Conservatives won no
seats in the region in 1993, and only one in
1997. The New Democratic Party won a small
number of seats, while the Liberals did best in
Manitoba.


Geoffrey Lambert
University of Manitoba




Dyck, Rand. Politics in Canada: Towards the Turn
of the Century. 3rd ed. Scarborough, Ontario: Prentice-Hall, 1995.
Wiseman, Nelson. "The Pattern of Prairie Politics."
In Party Politics in Canada, 5th ed., edited by Hugh G.
Thorburn. Scarborough, Ontario: Prentice-Hall, 1985: 242–59.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>