<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.na.084</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Pitaresaru (ca. 1823-1874)</field>
      <field name="author">Blaine, Martha Royce</field>
      <field name="text">

 




PITARESARU (ca. 1823-1874)

Pitaresaru (Petalesharo) is a Pawnee name
meaning "Chief of Men" or "Man Chief." Two
or more outstanding chiefs of this name were
members of the Chaui band of the Pawnee
(there was also a famous Skiri Pawnee chief
named Pitaresaru who died in the devastating
smallpox epidemic of 1830–31). The elder
Pitaresaru of the Chaui band was born in the
late eighteenth or early nineteenth century.
His name is on the 1833 treaty whereby the
Pawnee ceded what is now southern Nebraska
to the United States. His son is believed to
have been born around 1823 and died as head
chief in 1874 in Nebraska, the Pawnee tribal
homeland.

The younger Pitaresaru was described as
being over six feet tall and of good appearance.
He became a chief when he was twenty-nine.
He devoted his life to the good of his people,
and, as an excellent orator, he attempted to
mollify the U.S. government in its often unreasonable
demands and treatment. Pitaresaru's
name appears first–indicating his primary
importance among all four Pawnee bands–on
the 1857 treaty in which the Pawnees ceded the
balance of their ancestral lands, retaining only
a small reservation on the Loup River. Although
honoring his own culture, Pitaresaru
accepted U.S. government schools so that
Pawnee children could learn to read and write
the white man's words. He sought to maintain
the sovereignty of tribal leaders and forcefully
criticized negligent and dishonest agency employees.
When his reservation-bound people
endured hunger in the 1860s, he successfully
pleaded that the tribe be allowed to go on the
bison hunt, an activity that countered government
policy of spatial restriction and conversion
of the Pawnees into farmers.

When pressure came for the removal of the
Pawnees from Nebraska to Indian Territory, at
first he was resolutely against it, but later he
agreed to the removal with a heavy heart. In
1874, before this sad migration was made, Pitaresaru
died under mysterious circumstances;
he was shot in the leg by parties unknown and
subsequently perished from gangrene.

It was later said by a Skiri Pawnee that
Pitaresaru ruled all the bands and was a great
man. Today, some of his warrior songs are still
sung by the Pawnee people in Oklahoma.


Martha Royce Blaine
Oklahoma City, Oklahoma



Blaine, Martha Royce. Pawnee Passage: 1870–1875. Norman:
University of Oklahoma Press, 1990. Dunbar, John
B. "Pitalesharu." American History Magazine 5 (1880):
340–42.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>