<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.056</field>
      <field name="titleMain">New Mexico</field>
      <field name="author">Garcia, Jose Z.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




NEW MEXICO

In 2000 New Mexico had a population of 1.8
million, a per capita income of $19,936, one of
the lowest in the nation (which in 1999 averaged
$26,412), and a state government that
spent around $6.5 billion, including transfers
from the federal government of around $1.6
billion. The state has one large city, Albuquerque,
and a varied economy, including
high technology, military complexes, agriculture,
mining, and tourism. The population is
varied and includes twenty-three Indian tribes,
Hispanics with multigenerational roots, pioneer
ranchers, migrant professionals, new retirees,
artists, scientists, and tourism specialists.
Geographically, analysts distinguish
the Indian Northwest, Hispanic North, Little
Texas (the Plains of New Mexico), Albuquerque,
and the Southwest Borderlands, each with
distinct political behaviors.

At the time of the Spanish conquest, New
Mexico was populated by small groups of Navajos
and Apaches, and some 30,000 Pueblo
Indians scattered in villages along the Rio
Grande and west as far as Zuni and Acoma. In
1598 Don Juan de Oñate led a group of settlers
from Central Mexico to what is now Espanola,
New Mexico, extending the Spanish Empire
northward by several hundred miles. His successor,
Pedro de Peralta, founded Santa Fe as a
capital in 1610, and Franciscan missionaries
began a lengthy period of conversion of Natives
to Catholicism. In 1680 a revolt by Pueblo
Indians forced colonists to retreat until control
was regained in 1692. The area remained
remote from Spanish rule, however, and under
continuous threats from Apache, Navajo,
Ute, and Comanche raiders during the eighteenth
century.

Isolated even more by the instability that
followed Mexican independence from Spain in
1821, New Mexicans began trading with Anglo-Americans through the Santa Fe Trail. After
annexation of Texas in 1845, expansionists
pressured President James K. Polk to harden
his position in a dispute with Mexico over the
western boundary. Negotiations failed and the
United States declared war in May 1846. Gen.
Stephen Kearny marched into New Mexico,
ending Mexican control. U.S. troops invaded
Mexico at Veracruz, and Mexico ceded California,
Arizona, Nevada, Utah, Colorado, and
New Mexico in 1848. In 1850 the Territory of
New Mexico, including modern New Mexico,
Arizona, and parts of Nevada and Colorado,
was established, and the boundary with Texas
set. The Gadsden Purchase of 1853 fixed the
southern boundary, and in 1861 the creation
of the Territory of Colorado established New
Mexico's northern boundary. When Arizona
was separated from New Mexico in 1863, New
Mexico's present boundaries were stabilized.

During the territorial period, Spanish-speaking
New Mexicans lost much property in
predatory land grabs led by unscrupulous
agents with political connections. Indians resisting
U.S. authority fared even worse. The
Apaches' Mescalero lands were invaded by the
U.S. Army in 1863, and the tribe was relocated.
Col. Kit Carson attacked the Navajos' farmlands
at Canyon de Chelly in 1864, forcing
6,000 to surrender in the face of starvation.
The Navajos were relocated 300 miles away for
four years. When a constitution was written in
1911, a year before statehood, Hispanics, who
outnumbered Anglos, secured guarantees protecting
language and citizenship. Although
granted U.S. citizenship in 1924, Indians did
not vote in state and national elections in New
Mexico until the late 1940s, and even later in
local elections. Hispanic and Indian incomes
in New Mexico are still significantly lower than
those of Anglos.

In spite of these difficulties, following political
reforms in the 1960s Indians and Hispanics
in New Mexico integrated more easily
into the state's political system. Comprising
about 40 percent of the state's population,
Hispanics are greatly overrepresented in the
Democratic Party, which is dominant in most
counties at the local level. In the legislature
Hispanics have held most leadership positions
since the early 1970s. Two recent governors
were Hispanic. With only 11 percent of the
state's population, Indians commonly elect
legislators in districts with large Indian populations.
Navajos also vote in elections for the
Navajo Nation, headquartered in Arizona.

Culturally, the Plains area of New Mexico
(roughly the eastern third of the state) is the
legacy of Anglo ranching and farming pioneers
who settled about a hundred years ago.
Some of the land was in the Permian Basin
and was exploited for oil during the 1920s and
1930s. This area is known as "Little Texas," a
designation that summarizes a conservative
political culture, a dwindling oil economy,
and proximity to Texas. In-migration of Hispanics
has recently begun to change the demographic
composition and political culture
of the region.

New Mexico has a bicameral legislature, unsalaried,
which alternates each year between
thirty- and sixty-day sessions. The governor,
whose powers are relatively weak, shares the
executive branch with an elected treasurer, attorney
general, auditor, secretary of state,
commissioner of public lands, and public regulatory
commission. In spite of its diverse population,
New Mexico has voted for the winning
presidential candidate in all elections since
statehood except for 1976, when New Mexico
voted slightly in favor of Gerald Ford's losing
campaign, and 2000, when the state supported
Vice President Al Gore. For national offices,
including the U.S. Senate and House, the state
is competitive between the two major parties,
but for local offices most counties vote strongly
Democrat.

Twentieth-century notable political figures
include Dennis Chavez, who led a mass migration
of Hispanics from the Republican to
the Democratic Party during the 1930s and
went on to a distinguished senatorial career;
Gov. Bruce King, who created a thirty-year
Democratic governing coalition of ranchers,
liberal urbanites, and Hispanics; Sen. Pete
Domenici, a Republican who attracted broadbased
support from Democrats after 1972; Jerry
Apodaca, who reorganized state government
efficiently in 1974 after becoming the
first Hispanic governor elected in half a century;
and Republican governor Gary Johnson,
whose use of the veto became legendary in the
late 1990s.

See also HISPANIC AMERICANS: Maxwell Land Grant.


Jose Z. Garcia
New Mexico State University




Vigil, Maurilio E., Michael Olsen, and Roy Lujan. New
Mexico Government and Politics. Lanham MD: University
Press of America, 1990.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>