<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.art.031</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Herd, Stan (b. 1950)</field>
      <field name="author">Dooley, Michael C.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




HERD, STAN (b. 1950)


Stan Herd. Sunflower Field, near Eudora, Kansas, 1896.


Since the late 1970s Stan Herd has created
monumental portraits and other images by
plowing, planting, and mowing on tracts of
farmland in the Great Plains.

Born in 1950 in Protection, Kansas, and
raised in an area that was formerly Kiowa
hunting grounds, Herd has frequently chosen
his subjects and perfected his methods to reflect
his admiration for Native American spiritual
attitudes toward the land as well as his
concern for contemporary environmental issues.
As a youth Herd was struck by images of
the colossal pre-Columbian drawings on the
desert floor of the Andes Mountains and later
by his aerial view from a small plane of a
farmer turning over the rich Kansas earth.
Herd's first project, completed in 1979, was a
portrait of the Kiowa chief Satanta, whose heroic
exploits had made him a symbol among
the Kiowa of resistance to European American
encroachment. Herd began by gridding off a
pencil sketch from a photograph of Satanta
and transferring this scheme to the land by
means of numbered flags. The artist then followed
these guides on tractor, pulling a brace
of disc rotors behind him to etch the final
image into the soil. Herd soon discovered the
challenge posed to his image by the vagaries of
weather and unpredicted wild plant growth
and in the course of ensuing projects would
learn ways to gain more control over the ecology
of his earth art. This included abandoning
for the most part his "subtractive" plowing
method in favor of images produced through
the strategic plantings of crops, as, for example,
his Sunflower Field of 1985-87.

Herd's special concern for the struggles of
Native peoples to maintain their culture is exemplified
in Little Girl in the Wind (1990), a
portrait of a Kansan Kickapoo woman and the
first of a planned Nation's Portrait series addressing
the hardships of Indigenous women
in their lands of origin. In a similar vein, Medicine Wheel (1992) was a cooperative venture
with faculty members Dan Wildcat and Leslie
Evans of Haskell Indian Nations University.
Conceived as a Native American response to
the quincentennial celebrations of Columbus's
arrival in the New World, the wheel was
dedicated with a Flame Spirit Run during
which Native American leaders carried flames
from the circle's center outward in the four
compass directions. As intended, Medicine Wheel has since become a place of prayer and
meditation for all peoples of the surrounding
community.

One issue Herd has continually wrestled
with is the relationship between art and the
business world. In 1988 he created Cola Wars
for the Ottawa, Kansas, Arts Council. First
etching the outline of two crushed Coke and
Pepsi cans in a field, Herd then gathered close
to 1,000 volunteers wearing all red or blue
clothing to temporarily fill in the images of
the cans. The anticommercial intention of this
living earth sculpture was to emphasize how
advertising produces a throw-away consumer
culture, resulting in a landscape blighted with
trash. Nevertheless, in subsequent years Herd
has come to accept the occasional necessity for
corporate patronage, carefully screening for
companies he deems socially responsible and
that offer artistically challenging projects.
In considering his first such venture, Absolut Vodka (1990), Herd was impressed with the
activism in Iroquois Native American issues
evinced by the CEO of Absolut's American distributing
company.

Herd's recent projects include the whimsical
Ancient Fish Maze, an image after the
80-million-year-old fossils of Xiphactinus
found in Kansas. Cut from a dormant alfalfa
field outside Lawrence, the contours of the
prehistoric fish are filled in with a complex
maze design. A portrait of Amelia Earhart,
commissioned by the aviator's hometown of
Atchison, Kansas, to celebrate the 100th anniversary
of her birth, is taking shape from native
stone and perennial grasses and will be the
artist's first truly permanent land work. As
with many of Herd's projects, numerous assisting
volunteers make the Earhart portrait a
community-wide effort.

See also GENDER: Earhart, Amelia.



Michael C. Dooley
University of Iowa




Herd, Stanley J. Crop Art and Other Earthworks. New York:
Harry N. Abrams, 1994. Kinsey, Joni L. Plain Pictures: Images of the American Prairie. Washington DC: Published
for the University of Iowa Museum of Art by the Smithsonian
Institution Press, 1996.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>