<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ea.021</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Italians</field>
      <field name="author">Laegreid, Renee M.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ITALIANS


Italian-owned Val Verde Winery, Del Rio, Texas


Italian immigrants entered the Great Plains
first as missionaries such as Fra Marco da
Nizza (1495-1558) and Eusebio Francisco Kino
(1645-1711), and later as adventurers such as
Count Leonetto Cipriani (1816-1888) and Italian
American Charles Siringo (1855-1928).
Since Italy was not a unified country until
the Risorgimento (1860-70), early sojourners
were either in the service of Spain or France or
were individual agents. In the mid-1800s the
combination of economic and political conditions
encouraged some Italians, like the
six officers and enlisted men in Gen. George
Armstrong Custer's Seventh Cavalry Regiment, to find adventure on the Plains. After
1869 the transcontinental rail line brought
Italian journalists and tourists to the Great
Plains; their letters and published travel memoirs
provided information about the people,
geography, and potential jobs to countrymen
back home.

Italian emigration began in earnest in the
late 1880s, when political and economic upheaval
coincided with natural disasters. A
rapid rise in Italy's population increased pressure
on the land, which in many areas had
been farmed to the point of exhaustion; years
of poor rainfall contributed to famines and
poverty; and in 1887 a devastating outbreak of
malaria left 21,000 dead. Leaving one's village
in search of work in other parts of Europe was
a tradition in Italy. Between 1886 and 1890,
however, there was a significant increase in
emigration from Italy, and by 1890 immigration
to America surpassed movement to other
parts of Europe. Until 1886 Italian immigrants
were predominantly from the Piedmont, Venetia,
and Lombard areas in northern Italy. By
the 1890s, however, 90 percent of those leaving
were from the south, or mezzogiorno, especially
Abruzzi, Calabria, Campania, and Sicily.
From 1891 to 1910, the years of heaviest Italian
emigration, 880,908 immigrants came to the
United States. Although exact numbers are
difficult to determine, approximately 24,000,
or about 3 percent of the total, moved to the
Great Plains. During this same period approximately
62,633 Italians, roughly 4 percent
of the total immigrant population, moved to
Canada, with 6,650, or about 10 percent of
them, finding their way onto the Plains.

Perhaps as many as 70 percent of Italian
immigrants were contadini, peasants who in
Italy had lived in town and farmed a few acres
in the surrounding countryside. With few exceptions,
Italian immigrants on the Plains
came to work in railroad and mining camps
or as urban laborers. Railroad and mining
companies recruited heavily to bring Italian
workers to the Plains, offering cheap transportation
and higher wages than in Italy. In
a few instances padroni such as Antonio Cordascoi,
the Montreal labor broker for the Canadian
Pacific Railway, directed immigrants
to jobs on the Canadian Plains, but most Italians
found work through word of mouth.

In the states of the Great Plains, according
to 1910 census data (here aggregated by country),
Colorado had the largest total population
of Italians (14,375), with approximately 6,885
living in the Plains. In Texas 1,554 of the total
number of Italians (7,190) lived on the Plains,
and in Montana 2,568 out of all Italians (6,592)
made the Plains their home. In Nebraska 66
percent of the state's 3,799 Italian immigrants
lived in the city of Omaha and another 14 percent
in Lincoln, with the remainder scattered
throughout the state. Seventy-five percent of
the 3,517 Italian immigrants in Kansas lived in
that state's southeastern coal-mining district.
In Oklahoma, 72 percent of the state's total
Italian immigrants (2,564) lived in the Great
Plains. In Wyoming 1,086 of the statewide total
(1,962) were in the Plains, and in New Mexico
1,237 out of a total of 1,958 Italians were in the
Plains. In South Dakota the 1,158 Italians lived
mainly on land along the rail lines, and in
North Dakota 1,262 Italian immigrants were
recorded in 1910, although by 1920 only about
400 remained in the state.

Prior to 1880, Canadian immigration policy
restricted southern European settlement; it
was not until 1881, when construction of the
Canadian Pacific Railway increased demand
for unskilled labor, that Italians began to emigrate
in large numbers, increasing from an
average of 360 per year to more than 1,000 per
year, with a peak of 27,704 in 1913. The immigration
pattern was similar to that in the
United States; the majority of Italians who
ventured into the Canadian Plains found jobs
with the railroad or in the coalfields. One notable
difference was that Canadian Italians
would often move on, to Toronto, Montreal,
Vancouver, or the United States, to avoid
harsh winters and to find work. It was not
until the Canadian mines began to close in the
1940s that the numbers of Italians in Plains
urban areas, particularly Edmonton and Winnipeg,
began to accumulate in appreciable
numbers. Between 1945 and 1960, in both
Canada and Italy, immigration policies encouraged
a new wave of immigration to Canada,
consisting mainly of skilled laborers. Although
as many as two-thirds of these new
immigrants stayed in the larger eastern cities,
urban centers on the Plains such as Calgary,
Edmonton, and Winnipeg experienced
substantial population growth. For example,
Winnipeg's Italian population increased from
1,743 in 1951 to 4,216 in 1961.

All across the Great Plains, Italians worked
together to help newly arrived immigrants
find jobs and places to live. Small boarding
houses provided familiar food, language, and
a comforting family atmosphere. Churches
and schools were quickly established, as were
mutual aid societies, such as the Dante Alighieri
Society and the Christopher Columbus
Society. The societies also served as sites for
labor union meetings in mining regions. "Little
Italy" neighborhoods developed in urban
areas such as Omaha, Edmonton, and Sheridan,
Wyoming. Italian-English newspapers
were published in Omaha and Edmonton.
Many Italians who decided to remain in the
Plains gradually worked up from their initial
menial jobs to own shops, farms, or businesses
and became active in local politics. As many as
50 percent of all Italian immigrants, however,
returned to Italy once they had saved money to
buy land or improve their ancestral farm.

In both Canada and the United States, immigration
legislation in the 1920s and early
1930s, combined with Benito Mussolini's efforts
to reduce emigration, dramatically reduced
the flow of Italian immigrants, although
the movement was never eliminated
entirely. By the late twentieth century, Italian
immigrants were no longer contadini looking
for manual work or skilled workers arriving
with families, but were university students
and professionals searching for educational
and career opportunities difficult to find in
Italy.

See also FOLKWAYS: Siringo, Charles.


Renee M. Laegreid
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Carbone, Stanislao. Italians in Winnipeg: An Illustrated History. Winnipeg: University of Manitoba Press, 1998.
Kathka, David. "The Italian Experience in Wyoming." In
Peopling the High Plains: Wyoming's European Heritage,
edited by Gordon Olaf Hendrickson. Cheyenne: Wyoming
State Archives and Historical Department, 1977: 67–
94. Rolle, Andrew. Westward the Immigrants: Italian Adventurers and Colonists in an Expanding America. Niwot:
University Press of Colorado, 1999.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>