<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.art.043</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Miller, Alfred Jacob (1810-1874)</field>
      <field name="author">Tyler, Ron C.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MILLER, ALFRED JACOB (1810-1874)

Alfred Jacob Miller, born in Baltimore on January
2, 1810, to George Washington Miller and
Harriet Jacob, was one of the earliest trained
artists to cross the Great Plains. Following
study in Paris and Rome in 1833, the young
Miller returned to Baltimore and established
a studio. After his parents died, Miller left
Baltimore and moved to New Orleans in the
spring of 1837.

That is where he met Capt. William Drummond
Stewart, the second son of Scottish
nobility, veteran of the Napoleonic Wars,
sportsman, and a seasoned traveler who had
attended the annual rendezvous of fur trappers
and traders in the Rocky Mountains on several
occasions. Stewart planned to attend the 1837
rendezvous and, thinking that it might be
his last, employed young Miller to document
the trip.

Miller arrived in St. Louis in April 1837.
There he visited with Gov. William Clark, the
prominent explorer and superintendent of Indian
Affairs, and spent time in Clark's museum
in preparation for the trip. Stewart and
Miller left Westport in May, along with fortyfive
men and twenty carts loaded with trade
goods to exchange for pelts at the rendezvous.
They followed the Kansas and Little Blue
Rivers to the Platte River, with Miller documenting
every segment of the trip. They took
the North Fork of the Platte past Chimney
Rock, Scotts Bluff, and Fort Laramie, all of
which Miller rendered in colorful watercolor.
He also depicted Independence Rock, Devils
Gate, Split Rock on the Sweetwater River, and
the Continental Divide, arriving, finally, at
Horse Creek in the Wind River Mountains,
where trappers and Indians had gathered for
the 1837 rendezvous.

Miller remained at the rendezvous for about
three weeks. Following another couple of
weeks hunting in the mountains with Stewart,
Miller returned to New Orleans to begin working
on the paintings that Stewart had commissioned.
Stewart, meanwhile, had learned that
his older brother John had died, that he had
inherited the family estates and titles, and that
he must soon return to Murthly Castle, the
family estate just outside of Perth, Scotland.

Miller had made dozens of sketches. From
them he first prepared a small album of
eighty-seven wash and watercolor sketches for
Stewart and then set to work on several large
oil paintings that Stewart intended as decoration
for Murthly. Stewart loaned eighteen of
Miller's oils to the Apollo Gallery in New York
for exhibition from May to July 1839 before
shipping them to Scotland. Miller accepted
Stewart's invitation to come to Murthly to
continue his painting and remained there for
approximately a year, painting both western
and religious scenes. He returned to Baltimore
in the spring of 1842 and spent the remainder
of his life there.

The 1837 trip was the only western journey
that Miller made, but he kept his field sketches
and continued to fulfill commissions from
them throughout his life. The most notable
commission was that of William T. Walters,
who ordered 200 watercolors from 1858 to
1860. Miller also sold several paintings to
Charles Wilkins Weber that were chromo-lithographed
for his books, The Hunter-Naturalist: Romance of Sporting; or, Wild Scenes and Wild Hunters and The Hunter-Naturalist: Wild Scenes and Song-Birds.

Miller saw the West through the lens of the
romantic artist, depicting the many Indians at
the rendezvous as noble savages and the Plains
and mountains as a garden. There are large
collections of his work at the Joslyn Art Museum
in Omaha, the Walters Art Gallery
in Baltimore, and the Gilcrease Museum in
Tulsa. He died in Baltimore on June 26, 1874.


Ron C. Tyler
University of Texas at Austin




Troccoli, Joan Carpenter. Alfred Jacob Miller: Watercolors of the American West. Tulsa: Gilcrease Museum, 1990.
Tyler, Ron. Alfred Jacob Miller: Artist as Explorer. Santa Fe
NM: Gerald Peters Gallery, 1999. Tyler, Ron, ed. Alfred Jacob Miller: Artist on the Oregon Trail. Fort Worth: Amon
Carter Museum, 1982.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>