<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.arc.028</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Herminghaus, Ernst (1890-1965)</field>
      <field name="author">Sutton, Richard K.</field>
      <field name="text">

 



Administration Building, Texas Tech University, William Ward Watkin, architect



HERMINGHAUS, ERNST 1890-1965

Born December 31, 1890 and raised in Lincoln
Nebraska, Ernst H. Herminghaus became
in 1915 the first practicing landscape architect
residing in Nebraska. His design career
spanned fifty years and included landscape
projects for the Nebraska State Capitol, Lincoln's
Pioneers Park, and numerous private
gardens.

Herminghaus graduated in horticulture
from the University of Nebraska in 1913 and
from the landscape architecture program at
the Harvard Graduate School of Design in
1915. An enthusiastic plant expert, Herminghaus
taught landscape design and history in
the University of Nebraska's architecture program
during the early 1930s. During both
world wars, Herminghaus worked on designs
for military bases at Hastings, Nebraska,
and Hanford, Washington, and in Alaska and
England.

Because he learned design under Frederick
Law Olmsted and Henry Vincent Hubbard at
Harvard, Herminghaus's designs for Pioneers
Park and private residences read like a Beauxarts
pattern book for landscapes. Herminghaus
used Pioneers Park's rolling topography
to highlight a series of sequential views within
and beyond the park. Distant views focused
on the Nebraska State Capitol tower, and internal
views terminated at large sculptures.
The park's first 160 areas are exclusively devoted
to a series of carefully linked, informally
planted spaces. Tight spatial control in this
rural park was created by dense plantings of
conifers. Expression of his rich plant vocabulary
resulted in a varied palette of deciduous
trees and shrubs. Pioneers Park has been
placed on the National Register of Historic
Places.

Herminghaus's 1933 plan for the Nebraska
State Capitol grounds reveals that he understood
the visual needs of the building and
landscape better than the architects. Elements
of the plan include a broad lawn with carefully
placed deciduous trees and a foundation
planting of large evergreens. The lack of ornamental
shrubs keeps the viewer focused upon
the building's rich architectural detail. However,
in the capitol's interior courtyards the
full ornamental expression of Herminghaus's
horticultural knowledge is seen in formal
plantings of bright seasonal flowers and diverse
shrub borders. Herminghaus's Nebraska
State Capitol landscape plan was the state's
largest planting project up to that time.

Herminghaus was more than a mere technician.
He was also a teacher, and he inspired
humanistic goals in his design work. After
his death on September 20, 1965, in Newton,
Connecticut, Ernst Herminghaus's ashes were
scattered in Pioneers Park.


 

Richard K. Sutton
University of Nebraska-Lincoln



Sutton, Richard K. "Ernst Herminghaus, Landscape Architect."
Nebraska History 66 (1985): 372–91.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>