<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.tra.015</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Hill, James (1838-1916)</field>
      <field name="author">Poole, Keith T.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




HILL, JAMES (1838-1916)

James J. Hill, known as the Empire Builder,
was one of the most important railroad leaders
of the nineteenth century. He was born
September 16, 1838, in Eramosa Township,
Ontario, and died in St. Paul, Minnesota, on
May 29, 1916. Hill built the Great Northern
Railway and merged it with the Northern Pacific
and Burlington Railroads to form a transcontinental
railroad that connected Puget
Sound with the Great Lakes and the Gulf of
Mexico. This railroad system later became the
Burlington Northern Railroad.

Hill began his business career in St. Paul,
Minnesota, in 1856 as a bookkeeper for a
steamboat company. By the 1860s he was a
transportation agent handling freight transfers
to and from wagons, railroads, and steamboats.
This experience enabled him to enter
the coal business in the late 1860s, the steamboat
business on the Red River of the North in
1870, and the railroad business in 1878. During
1877 Hill formed a group–later dubbed "The
Associates"–consisting of himself, Norman
Kittson, Donald Smith, George Stephen, and
John S. Kennedy to gain control of the bankrupt
St. Paul and Pacific Railroad. The Associates
renamed the railroad the St. Paul, Minneapolis
and Manitoba (SPM&amp;M), and with
Hill as president the railroad became a great
success. Hill was a sophisticated manager who
built his railroads to the highest standards.

Hill built the SPM&amp;M north along the Red
River to the Canadian border and received a
Minnesota land grant for completing it on
time. He transported immigrants (many from
Norway and Sweden) north before the winter
was over at low rates and sold them homesteads
from the Minnesota land grant at $2.50
to $5.00 an acre. This allowed settlers to be
on the land in time to plant a crop that
spring, and it built up the population around
the railroad.

Hill used this same technique when he expanded
the SPM&amp;M (later renamed the Great
Northern) into Montana in the late 1880s and
to Puget Sound in 1893. He charged a nominal
fee to transport immigrants in return for their
settling along the route. The Great Northern
was the only transcontinental built without
public subsidies and the only one that did not
go bankrupt in the 1890s.

Hill was a strong supporter of soil conservation
and scientific farming. He traveled extensively
throughout the upper Midwest and
Northwest making public speeches at county
fairs, encouraging farmers to adopt more advanced
methods of farming. He published numerous
articles on his views of farming and
the value of education. However, Hill's efforts
were not always successful. Many of the farmers
who were induced by Hill to settle the high
plains of Montana failed.

In 1896 Hill established steamship service
between Seattle and ports in Asia, making
Seattle a world port. In 1901 Hill and Edward
H. Harriman engaged in a titanic battle for
control of the Burlington and Quincy Railroad.
With the aid of J. P. Morgan, Hill eventually
won control of the Burlington, enabling
him to complete his vision of a transportation
empire that linked Asia with the Great Lakes
and the Gulf Coast. Hill was known as the
Empire Builder largely because he built up
population around his railroads rather than
building his railroads around a population.


Keith T. Poole
Carnegie Mellon University




Martin, Albro. James J. Hill and the Opening of the Northwest.
St. Paul: Minnesota Historical Society Press, 1976.
Stover, John F. American Railroads. Chicago: University of
Chicago Press, 1997.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>