<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ct.018</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Denver, Colorado</field>
      <field name="author">Noel, Thomas J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




DENVER, COLORADO


Denver, Colorado


Denver, the capital of Colorado, was established
by a party of prospectors on November
22, 1858, after gold was discovered at the confluence
of Cherry Creek and the South Platte
River. The town founders named the dusty
crossroads after James W. Denver, governor
of Kansas Territory, of which eastern Colorado
was then a part. Other gold discoveries
sparked a mass migration of some 100,000
people in 1859–60, leading the federal government
to establish Colorado Territory in 1861.

The "Mile High City's" aggressive leadership,
spearheaded by William N. Byers,
founding editor of the Rocky Mountain News,
and Territorial Governor John Evans, insisted
on the removal of the original inhabitants,
Cheyennes and Arapahos, from the area. Denverites
then built a network of railroads that
made their town the banking, minting, supply,
and processing center for Colorado and
neighboring states. Between 1870, when the
first railroads arrived, and 1890, Denver's population
grew from 4,759 to 106,713. In a single
generation it became the second most populous
city in the West, second only to San Francisco.
Although initially founded as the main
supply town for Rocky Mountain mining
camps, Denver also emerged as a hub for High
Plains agriculture, with breweries, bakeries,
and meatpacking and other food-processing
plants as well as farm and ranch equipment,
barbed-wire, and windmill manufacturing.

Economic depression during the 1890s and
repeal of the Sherman Silver Purchase Act
in 1893 abruptly ended Denver's first boom.
Growth began again after 1900 but at a slower
rate. Stockyards, brickyards, canneries, flour
mills, and leather and rubber production
powered the city. Of the many Denver-area
breweries, only Coors has survived, and it is
now the nation's third largest producer.

Regional or national headquarters of many
oil and gas firms fueled much of Denver's
post.World War II growth and resulted in an
eruption of forty- and fifty-story high-rises
downtown in the 1970s. Denver's economic
base has also come to include skiing and tourism,
electronics, computers, aviation, and the
nation's largest telecommunications center. As
the regional center of a vast mountain and
Plains hinterland, Denver boasts more federal
employees than any city except Washington
dc. Since the 1940s, the large federal center,
augmented by state and local government
jobs, has stabilized the city's boom-and-bust
cycle, but an overreliance on a nonrenewable
resource returned to haunt the city during the
1980s oil bust. When the price of crude oil
dropped from $39 to $9 a barrel, Denver sank
into a depression, losing population and experiencing
the highest office vacancy rate in the
nation. Prosperity has since returned.

Visually, Denver is notable for its predominance
of single-family housing and its brick
buildings. Good brick clay underlies much of
the area, while local construction lumber is
soft, scarce, and inferior. Even in the poorest
residential neighborhoods, single-family detached
housing prevails, reflecting the western
interest in "elbow room" as well as the spacious,
relatively flat High Plains site, where
sprawling growth in all directions except west
is unimpeded by geographic obstacles.

Denver always has been obsessed with transportation
systems. Fear of being bypassed began
early when railroads and later airlines
originally avoided Denver because of the
14,000-foot-high Rocky Mountain barrier just
west of town. To secure Denver's place on national
transportation maps, the city opened a
new five-billion-dollar airport in 1995. The
fifty-five-square-mile Denver International
Airport is the nation's largest in terms of area
and capacity for growth, prompting boosters
to call it the world's largest. Denver is a sprawling
city in a state of long distances and mountainous
obstacles. To tackle those distances and
tough terrain, Coloradoans have become dependent
on cars. Denver has one of the highest
per capita motor vehicle ownership rates in the
country, with almost one licensed vehicle for
every man, woman, and child. In the 1990s
Denver built an outer ring of freeways, which
immediately became congested. Even after the
Regional Transportation District began building
a light-rail system, highway congestion has
remained the number one complaint of many
Denverites.

By 2000 the metro area had reached a population
of 2.1 million, three-fourths of whom
live in the suburban counties of Adams, Arapahoe,
Boulder, Denver, Douglas, and Jefferson.
Roughly 20 percent of the core city population
have a Spanish surname, 13 percent are African
American, 2 percent Asian, and 1 percent Native
American. Denver has elected Latino
(Federico Pena, 1983-91) and African American
(Wellington Webb, 1991-2003) mayors in
recent years and has enjoyed relatively smooth
race relations. Notable institutions in the city
include the Denver Museum of Natural History,
the Denver Public Library, the Colorado
History Museum, the Denver Art Museum,
and the Denver Center for the Performing Arts
as well as the U.S. Mint and major-league baseball,
basketball, football, hockey, and soccer
teams.

The "Rocky Mountain Metropolis" boomed
during the 1990s as the eastern suburb of Aurora
became Colorado's third largest city and
the western suburb of Lakewood became the
fourth largest. Even the core city and county of
Denver gained population in the 1990s for the
first time since the 1970s, climbing to 555,000 in
the 2000 census. Thanks to landmark districts
preserving venerable business and residential
areas as well as the 1990s opening in the core
South Platte River valley of Coors Baseball
Field, Elitch Gardens Amusement Park, Ocean
Journey Aquarium, the Pepsi Athletic Center,
and many new housing projects, downtown
Denver is booming along with its suburban
fringe at the dawn of the twenty-first century.

See also AFRICAN AMERICANS: Webb, Wellington and Wilma / ASIAN AMERICANS: Denver Chinatown / 
HISPANIC AMERICANS: Peña, Federico / MEDIA: Denver Post.


Thomas J. Noel
University of Colorado at Denver




Leonard, Stephen J., and Thomas J. Noel. Denver: Mining Camp to Metropolis. Niwot: University Press of Colorado,
1990.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>