<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.asam.017</field>
      <field name="titleMain">National Japanese American Student Relocation Council</field>
      <field name="author">Asato, Noriko</field>
      <field name="text">

 




NATIONAL JAPANESE AMERICAN STUDENT RELOCATION COUNCIL

The National Japanese American Student
Relocation Council was the primary civic organization
that helped 4,000 nisei (second-generation
Japanese Americans) leave concentration
camps and enter some 600 colleges
and universities in states outside the Pacific
Coast exclusion zones (California and western
Washington, Oregon, and Arizona) during
World War II.

In 1942 the U.S. government uprooted over
120,000 Japanese Americans from their West
Coast homes "for their security" and sent
them first to army-administered assembly
centers and then to more permanent concentration
camps (euphemistically called relocation
camps or internment camps) operated
by the War Relocation Authority (WRA).
Nisei, who were American citizens by birth,
outnumbered the first generation (issei) by
more than 30,000; their median age was seventeen.
More than 2,500 nisei had been attending
college in Pacific Coast states at the beginning
of the war. Although college admission and
work release were the only initial ways to leave
the camps, many colleges refused to accept any
nisei. The Relocation Council, a collective of
several regional organizations, began operations
on May 29, 1942, with Robbins W. Barstow,
president of Hartford Seminary, as the
first national director. The group was supported
by the YMCA, the YWCA, church groups
(especially Quakers), government agencies,
educators, and the Japanese American Citizens
League. The three major functions of the
Council were to coordinate with the FBI and
the WRA to obtain clearance for the nisei
and for the colleges that accepted them, to
raise funds for scholarships, and to work with
Japanese Americans in the camps to increase
morale and encourage the pursuit of higher
education.

Between July 1942 and July 1946 more than
fifty institutions of higher learning in Great
Plains states accepted a total of 991 students:
505 in Colorado, 197 in Nebraska, 83 in Wyoming,
73 in Texas, 42 in Kansas, 30 in Montana,
29 in South Dakota, 22 in Oklahoma,
and 10 in North Dakota. The University of
Nebraska was one of the first universities to
respond to the nisei's plight, admitting 80 students
by 1943. The university had originally
decided on a cap of 10 students but gradually
increased this to 120. Five of the major participating
institutions–University of Colorado,
University of Denver, Denver Art Institute,
Colorado State College of Education, and
Colorado State College of Agriculture and
Mechanical Arts–were located in Colorado,
reflecting Gov. Ralph Carr's hospitable attitude
toward Japanese Americans.

Not all the nisei students were admitted
with the help of the council; some applied
independently, inspiring other nisei to pursue
higher education. Recently, however, Gary
Okihiro has argued that, although the work of
the Student Relocation Council was antiracist,
by working closely with the WRA it assisted the
government's policy of relocating Japanese
Americans and therefore accepted the racist
implication that the Japanese Americans
themselves were to blame for the reaction
against them.


Noriko Asato
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




James, Thomas. "Life Begins with Freedom: The College
Nisei, 1942–1945." History of Education Quarterly 25 (1985):
155–74. O'Brien, Robert W. The College Nisei. Palo Alto
CA: Pacific Books, 1949. Okihiro, Gary Y. Storied Lives: Japanese American Students and World War II. Seattle:
University of Washington Press, 1999.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>