<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.rel.007</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Branch Davidians</field>
      <field name="author">Kerstetter, Todd M.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BRANCH DAVIDIANS

The Branch Davidian sect emerged in 1955 from
a Seventh-day Adventist reform movement in
Central Texas and became widely known in 1993
when federal agents surrounded the group's
property outside Waco, beginning a fifty-one-day
siege that ended in the fiery deaths of most
members.

The Branch Davidians trace their roots to
a Seventh-day Adventist reform movement
founded by Bulgarian immigrant Victor Houteff
in Los Angeles. After a 1929 visionary experience,
Houteff began teaching what he
claimed was his divinely inspired true interpretation
of scripture, thus implying inaccuracies
in Seventh-day Adventist practices.
Local church leaders charged Houteff with
heresy, prompting him to move with his followers
to Central Texas. The Davidians agreed
with most Seventh-day Adventist doctrine,
but Houteff taught his followers that his scriptural
interpretations constituted part of an
emerging truth, in which Seventh-day Adventist
apostasy prevented Christ's return and
the apocalyptic events that would usher in the
Kingdom of God on earth.

Houteff's wife, Florence, assumed the group's
leadership after Victor's death in 1955. Florence
Houteff almost immediately published her revelation
that the apocalypse would occur on April
22, 1959. When the apocalypse failed to materialize,
the Davidians fell into chaos, and Ben
Roden, leader of a splinter group dating to 1955
known as the Branch Davidians (this group referred
to Jesus Christ as the Branch), emerged
as the new leader. When Roden died, his wife,
Lois, a prophetess in her own right, took
charge. George Roden, Lois's son, fought successfully
to gain control in 1985, temporarily
defeating his main rival, Vernon Howell,
whom Lois Roden apparently intended as her
successor. In 1988 Howell, who two years later
legally changed his name to David Koresh,
wrested control of the group's Mount Carmel
community from Roden, marking the beginning
of the group's most tragic era.

Koresh assumed leadership when the Branch
Davidian community faced economic and political
crises, and he used the situation to consolidate
power and turn the group in new theological
directions. Koresh averted a financial crisis
by successfully soliciting monetary contributions
to pay back taxes for the Mount Carmel
commune. He developed automobile restoration
and weapons businesses to provide the
group with continued income. Koresh secured
his leadership by converting new members and
convincing them that he was descended spiritually
from King David and was a "sinful messiah"
on a mission from God to initiate Armageddon.
Koresh prophesied an apocalyptic
battle pitting Branch Davidians against the
American army, ushering in the Kingdom of
God on earth, in which the Branch Davidians
would play an important role. He also convinced
many followers that his mission included
fathering a new line of God's children. Koresh
created the "House of David"–the women who
became his spiritual wives–and produced a
number of offspring. These innovations created
jealousies within the group and objections,
from within and without, to the induction of
underage girls into the House of Koresh.

Combined with alleged violations of weapons
laws, the group's social innovations brought
increasing attention from outsiders, including
the media, anticult activists, and state and federal
agencies. Agents from the U.S. Bureau of
Alcohol, Tobacco, and Firearms raided Mount
Carmel on February 28, 1993, but withering fire
from the main residence killed four agents and
injured twenty more, thus creating a standoff.
The Federal Bureau of Investigation assumed
control of the situation that same day and led a
fifty-one-day siege. On April 19, 1993, the FBI
used two M-60 tanks and four Bradley vehicles
to inject tear gas into the Mount Carmel dwelling
intermittently for six hours in hopes of
flushing the Branch Davidians out of their
stronghold. At about noon, a fire swept through
Mount Carmel, killing many of the seventy-four
of the Branch Davidians inside; others died of
gunshot wounds, apparently inflicted by themselves
or others inside Mount Carmel.

The April 1993 tragedy bears similarities to
the Wounded Knee Massacre of 1890. Both involved
religious groups dominated by prophecy
and antagonistic to the United States and its
dominant cultural and social values, and both
groups suffered massive loss of life in conflicts
with federal agencies. The events raised questions
about the extent of religious freedom in
the Plains and the federal government's role in
enforcing cultural values and law and order in
the region.


Todd M. Kerstetter
Texas Christian University




Tabor, James D., and Eugene V. Gallagher. Why Waco?
Cults and the Battle for Religious Freedom in America.
Berkeley: University of California Press, 1995. Wright,
Stuart A. Armageddon in Waco: Critical Perspectives on the
Branch Davidian Conflict. Chicago: University of Illinois
Press, 1995.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>