<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.040</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Lemke, William (1878-1950)</field>
      <field name="author">Shelley, Fred M.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




LEMKE, WILLIAM (1878-1950)

William Lemke, North Dakota politician and
unsuccessful third-party presidential candidate,
was born in Stearns County, Minnesota, on
August 13, 1878. His family moved to Towner
County, North Dakota, in 1883. He graduated
from the University of North Dakota in 1902,
earned a law degree at Yale University in 1905,
and returned to Fargo to practice law. In 1915
Lemke became legal adviser to the Nonpartisan
League and played an instrumental role
in the League's dominance of North Dakota
politics. He was elected attorney general of
North Dakota in 1920 but was recalled a year
later.

In 1932 Lemke was elected to the House of
Representatives as a Republican, although he
supported Democrat Franklin D. Roosevelt.
After Roosevelt refused to support Lemke's
proposals for farm mortgage refinancing and
bankruptcy, Lemke broke with the president.
Backed by a coalition of Roosevelt's opponents,
including Father Charles Coughlin, Dr.
Francis Townsend, and supporters of the recently
assassinated Huey Long, Lemke ran for
president in 1936 as the candidate of the Union
Party. Lemke hoped to win enough votes to
force the election into the House of Representatives,
but he won fewer than a million votes.

After his defeat, Lemke resumed his House
career. He ran unsuccessfully for the Senate in
1940 but returned to the House in 1942, where
he remained until his death in Fargo on May
30, 1950. During his later years in Congress he
emphasized natural resources, and he played
an instrumental role in establishing the Theodore
Roosevelt National Park in North Dakota's
badlands.

See also PROTEST AND DISSENT: Nonpartisan League.


Fred M. Shelley
Southwest Texas State University




Blackorby, Edward C. Prairie Rebel: The Public Life of William
Lemke. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1963.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>