<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.074</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Stegner, Wallace (1909-1993)</field>
      <field name="author">Harrison, Dick</field>
      <field name="text">

 




STEGNER, WALLACE (1909-1993)

Wallace Stegner, one of the West's most important
authors not only as novelist and short
story writer but as historian and environmentalist,
made major contributions to both
American and Canadian western literatures.
Born in Lake Mills, Iowa, on February 18,
1909, to George and Hilda Paulson Stegner,
he grew up in towns across the West, wherever
his father's restless frontier spirit led
the family. Most influential in Stegner's development
were the childhood years in Eastend,
Saskatchewan, from 1917 to 1920 and his
youth in Salt Lake City. He earned a bachelor
of arts degree from the University of Utah and
a master's and doctorate from the University
of Iowa.

Stegner combined his writing with a distinguished
teaching career that extended from
Harvard to Stanford, where he founded the
creative writing program and directed it from
1945 to 1971. His first book of fiction, Remembering Laughter, won the Little Brown Novelette
Prize in 1937, and he went on to write or
edit thirty-two books of history, biography,
and fiction, including a dozen novels, as well
as scores of articles on the land and literature
of the West.

One of Stegner's greatest achievements was
his contribution to a sense of place for traditionally
uprooted westerners. He gave the
western landscape a concrete, vivid, sensory
presence on the page, and among the most
intensely realized of his western places are the
Saskatchewan Plains in his major autobiographical
novel, The Big Rock Candy Mountain
(1943), and in Wolf Willow (1962), the
book of history, reminiscence, and fiction that
became an inspiration to Canadian Prairie regionalists.
"Place" also encompasses the people
and culture of the West, which became
Stegner's explicit subject in nonfiction writings,
including the essays in The Sound of Mountain Water (1969) and histories such as
Mormon Country (1942).

While Stegner loved the land, he expressed a
lifelong ambivalence toward western American
culture. His major writings are charged
with a fundamental opposition between frontier
individualism and civilizing community.
In fiction it takes the dramatic form of tension
between characters such as the restless frontiersman
Bo Mason and his humane and cultivated
wife, Elsa, in The Big Rock Candy Mountain.
In Stegner's most celebrated novel, The Angle of Repose (1971), the polarities are more
balanced. Frontier engineer Oliver Ward's succession
of idealistic failures are as admirable, in
their way, as Susan Ward's devotion to culture
and human relations. As historian and environmentalist,
Stegner was less ambivalent.
He saw westerners as cut off from their past by
a frontier myth that obscures and distorts it,
and he warned of the folly of unbridled individualism
in an environment where survival
depends on cooperation. Central to his environmentalism
is his biography of conservationist
John Wesley Powell, Beyond the Hundredth Meridian (1954), and articles in national
magazines kept him at the forefront of the
movement.

Recognition of Stegner's achievements gathered
momentum in his mature years, including
a Pulitzer Prize for The Angle of Repose
at age sixty-two and a National Book Award
for The Spectator Bird at sixty-eight. Stegner
remained an active, major writer, publishing
the novel Crossing to Safety (1987), his Collected Stories (1990), and two collections of essays
in the last six years before his death on
April 13, 1993.


Dick Harrison
Sechelt, British Columbia




Arthur, Anthony. Critical Essays on Wallace Stegner. Boston:
G. K. Hall, 1982. Rankin, Charles E. Wallace Stegner: Man and Writer. Albuquerque: University of New Mexico
Press, 1996. Robinson, Forrest G., and Margaret G. Robinson.
Wallace Stegner. Boston: Twayne, 1977.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>