<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.art.013</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Catlin, George (1796-1872)</field>
      <field name="author">Dippie, Brian W.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CATLIN, GEORGE (1796-1872)

George Catlin, artist and visionary, achieved
fame for his gallery of Indian portraits and
scenes based on his travels in the American
West from 1832 to 1836. Born in Wilkes-Barre,
Pennsylvania, on July 26, 1796, Catlin trained
as a lawyer before moving to Philadelphia in
1821, determined to make his mark as an artist.
He specialized in miniature portraits, exhibited
regularly, and, despite some evident
technical limitations, became a member of the
Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts in
1824. Bored with portraiture, he was already
nurturing the idea of becoming a historical
painter when he moved to New York in 1827
and the next year married Clara Gregory. He
found his direction as an artist, he recalled,
after encountering a visiting delegation of Indians
and concluding on the spot that painting
the Indians in their western wilderness
would be his life's work.

Confident his efforts would command public
support, Catlin moved to St. Louis in
the spring of 1830 and two years later fully
launched his career as an Indian painter when
he boarded a steamboat for the 1,800-mile
journey up the Missouri River to Fort Union,
in the heart of Indian country. His five-month
excursion yielded 170 paintings, with Crows,
Blackfeet, and Mandans prominently featured.
Subsequently, Catlin toured the Southern
Plains (1834) and traveled up the Mississippi
(1835-36), painting as he went. He
described his experiences in letters to the
newspapers, collected in 1841 as Letters and
Notes on the Manners, Customs, and Condition
of the North American Indians, and between
trips exhibited his growing collection as Catlin's
Indian Gallery. Besides more than 300
portraits of men and women from some fifty
tribes, he displayed 200 paintings of western
Indians engaged in their daily activities.

Catlin rightfully insisted that he was the
first European American artist to offer the
world a representative picture of Indian life
based on personal observation. He characterized
the West as "vast country of green fields,
where the men are all red"–an apt description
of his landscapes and group scenes. They were
rendered in shorthand fashion, though he had
a knack for the distinctive features of costume
and terrain. Catlin's real gift was portraiture.
His style was idiosyncratic, and he struggled,
often unsuccessfully, to master anatomy. But
he captured individual likenesses, and his artistic
deficiencies never compromised his obvious
admiration for the subjects before him.

Catlin formed his Indian Gallery without
government patronage but turned to Congress
in May 1838, confident it would reward
his enterprise by purchasing his collection.
Repeatedly frustrated in this hope, he commenced
a lecture career that eventually transformed
him into a full-time showman rather
than the disinterested advocate for Indian
rights he always fancied himself to be. Certain
he would find a more receptive audience in
Europe, he moved his family to England in
November 1839, then to Paris in 1845. Despite
flattering attention from crowned heads and

commoners, a book recounting his experiences
abroad (Notes of Eight Years' Travels and Residence in Europe, with His North American Indian Collection, 1848), private commissions,
and numerous get-rich-quick schemes, Catlin
slid into financial ruin. In 1852 his creditors
seized his Indian Gallery. Bereft of his life's
work, Catlin entered a period of relative obscurity
and some remarkable accomplishments.
He painted a second Indian gallery of
nearly 300 oil "cartoons" recapitulating his
original collection and another 300 showing
Indians of the Northwest Coast and South
America encountered on three trips he made
in the 1850s. He also published several books,
including two directed at younger readers
(Life amongst the Indians, 1861, and Last Rambles amongst the Indians of the Rocky Mountains and the Andes, 1867), and an important
ethnographic study amplifying observations
made among the Mandan Indians in 1832 (O-Kee-Pa, 1867). In 1871, after an absence of
more than three decades, Catlin returned to
the United States and exhibited his Cartoon
Collection in New York and Washington DC.
He died in Jersey City on December 23, 1872.

Today, visitors to the National Museum of
American Art and the National Gallery of Art
can sample both Catlin collections in the capital
city of a nation that never extended him
patronage but now treasures his enduring
contribution to the American heritage.


Brian W. Dippie
Montana Secretary of State's Office




Lucey, Donna. Photographing Montana, 1894–1928: The Life and Work of Evelyn Cameron. New York: Alfred A.
Knopf, Inc., 1990. Raban, Jonathan. Bad Land: An American Romance. New York: Vintage Books, 1996. Shirley,
Gayle. "Evelyn Cameron, Frontier Photographer." In More Than Petticoats: Remarkable Montana Women. Helena MT:
Falcon Publishing, 1995: 74–83.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>