<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.tra.039</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Water Transportation</field>
      <field name="author">Henderson, Norman</field>
      <field name="text">

 




WATER TRANSPORTATION

People have always used Plains rivers for transport,
but it has never been easy. The nature of
the Plains and its rivers conspires against water
transport, and many are the explorers and entrepreneurs
who set out in boats and ended up
on foot or horseback. In the eyes of many,
horses and trains came to be seen as the "natural"
ways to travel the Plains. In 1931 the historian
Walter Prescott Webb went so far as to
suggest that since the Lewis and Clark Expedition
traveled so much by water, resorting to
land travel only when forced to, the expedition
experienced little of the "Plains proper" and
was therefore not really a Plains venture. Yet a
river view of the Plains, although to the modern
mind somewhat unusual, is as legitimate
as an overlander’s perspective.

Native Americans were the first to travel
Plains rivers. They used the bullboat, a roughly
circular, framed, tublike craft. Made from bent
willow branches and buffalo skins sewn with
sinews, the bullboat is light enough for one
person to carry slung over the shoulders. Although
ingeniously simple technology, the
bullboat has serious limitations. When wet,
the skins rot quickly, so a boat might last only
a few days. Bullboats are also difficult to
steer and impossible to paddle upstream. Bullboats
were primarily useful to cross rivers like
the Missouri or for extended one-way trips
downstream.

European explorers and traders introduced
the birch-bark canoe to the Plains, a craft indigenous
to the northeastern North American
woodlands. The newcomers experienced
roughly a century and a half of frustration
trying to push out onto the Plains with this
"foreign" technology. Birchbark canoes require
almost daily repair, but on the Plains
there were no birch trees for bark, nor pine
trees for pitch, nor spruce trees for gum.

The rivers themselves work against canoe
travel too. Plains rivers tend to meander, slowing
progress. They are typically shallow and
full of shifting sand and mud bars that ground
the traveler's craft, and they conceal snags that
pierce the hull. Northern Plains rivers in particular
have highly seasonal flows and are shut
down by ice in winter. Unlike those in boreal
North America, water linkages between Plains
watersheds are usually nonexistent, which
means that the traveler in any case must develop
some overland transport alternative for
travel between river systems. The experiences
of explorers like Pierre Gaultier de Varennes,
sieur de La Vérendrye, who abandoned his canoes
on the Assiniboine River in 1738, Zebulon
Pike, who exchanged his boat for horses
along the Osage River in 1806, Stephen Long,
who ascended the Platte River in 1820 by land,
and Henry Hind, who abandoned his canoes
on the Qu'Appelle River in 1858, are illustrative
of the limitations of canoes in the Plains.

Alongside continuing canoe traffic, timber
small craft, both flat-bottomed and keeled,
were employed on Plains rivers by fur traders,
travelers, and explorers. These were sturdier
than canoes, but the flat-bottomed boats were
only effective going downstream, while keelboats
were often grounded. Both types were
variously rowed, poled, or even sailed, depending
on conditions. It was common, too,
for keelboats to be hauled upstream by men or
pack animals.

In the nineteenth century steamboats inherited
all the Plains river navigation problems of
small boats and were also vulnerable to high
winds. Steamboats were active in both the Canadian
and American Plains but were most
important on the Missouri River. In 1832
a steam-driven side-wheeler reached Fort
Union at the junction of the Yellowstone and
the Missouri. From then on steamers regularly
rode the high spring waters at least as far
as Fort Union and, when conditions allowed
it, continued on farther, with shallow-draft
steamers reaching as far as Fort Benton in 1859.

These steamers gave the American Fur
Trading Company an advantage over its rivals,
particularly the Hudson's Bay Company to the
north, in the contested Plains borderlands between
the Missouri and South Saskatchewan
Rivers. In fact, steam and small boat transport,
di.cult as they were, are at the root of the
division of the Plains between America and
Canada. Although the international boundary
appears quite unrelated to natural features, the
forty-ninth parallel roughly divides the Plains
into Hudson Bay and Gulf of Mexico watersheds
and reflects the division of fur trader
influence between the British operating out of
Hudson Bay and the American traders operating
from the Mississippi watershed.

From the 1860s onward railroads began to
cut into Plains steamer cargoes, putting an
end to most commercial tra.c by 1890. After
World War I the U.S. federal government took
a renewed interest in inland waterways, and
there was a slow increase in traffic. There are
now two significant routes, both completed in
the 1970s, maintained for river freight between
the Mississippi River and the eastern Plains.
The Missouri is kept navigable as far upstream
as Sioux City, while the Arkansas-Verdigris
project maintains a nine-foot channel as far as
Catoosa, near Tulsa. Modern commercial traffic
primarily consists of boat-barges. Typically,
several flat-bottomed barges carrying
bulk goods are tied together in a "tow" and
pushed by a diesel-driven towboat.

Lacking the axis of the Mississippi to work
from, there has been no rebirth of commercial
water traffic on the Canadian Plains. Given the
high cost of waterway construction and maintenance
and modern environmental concerns,
it seems unlikely there will be expansion of the
limited U.S. Plains routes either.

The most important modern cargoes of the
typical Plains river flow by below the surface–agricultural
runoff and urban effluent. Ecologist
James Malin was correct to emphasize that
the natural state of Plains rivers was muddy
and brown, but modern farming, especially
cultivation, increases soil runoff, while Plains
cities contribute effluent to natural flows. The
resulting sediment load is carried by Plains
currents until it is dropped in dam reservoirs
or in slow-moving rivers like the Mississippi.
This transport is not costless, for infilling reservoirs
lose their e.ciency, dredging to maintain
navigability is expensive, and sedimentladen
water is difficult or impossible to use for
many domestic and industrial purposes. Many
of these costs fall on people downstream of the
Plains.

See also WATER: Rivers.


Norman Henderson
University of East Anglia, England




Henderson, Norman S. "The Canoe as Failure on the Canadian
Plains." Great Plains Research 6 (1996): 3–23.
Hunter, Louis C. Steamboats on the Western Rivers: An
Economic and Technological History. New York: Dover,
1993.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>