<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.na.031</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Gros Ventres</field>
      <field name="author">Fleming, Walter C.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




GROS VENTRES

The Gros Ventres are an Algonquian-speaking
people from the area of the Great Plains between
the Missouri River, Montana, and the
Saskatchewan River in the Canadian Prairies.
Their own name is A'aninin or A'ani, meaning
"Clay People," derived from their belief
that they were made from white clay found on
the river bottoms.

The Gros Ventres are among the least known
tribes of the Northern Plains, partly the consequence
of mistaken identity. The name Gros
Ventre ("Big Belly" in French) is a misnomer
that originated from a mistranslation of the
gesture for the A'aninin in the Plains sign language.
The Crees referred to the Gros Ventres
as the Water Falls People, Falls Indians, or
Rapid Indians because the tribe occupied territory
inclusive of the southern branch of the
Saskatchewan River, where rapids are frequent.
The sign for them was the passing of the
hands over the body like water falling. This
was mistranslated as a sign representing a large
stomach, and hence they became known as the
Big Bellies, or Gros Ventres. Adding to the confusion,
the Gros Ventres are also known as the
"Atsinas" in some ethnological sources, a
Blackfoot word meaning "Belly People." To
distinguish them from the Hidatsas, also
known as the Gros Ventres, sometimes they
were called the "Gros Ventre of the Prairies."

Earliest mention of the Gros Ventres places
them in the region of the Saskatchewan River
in the eighteenth century, far removed from
their kindred, the Arapahos. When and where
these two tribes split is not known. Trappers
and traders of the Hudson's Bay Company
and the North West Company located the
Gros Ventres on the South Saskatchewan
River between 1775 and 1790. As the Gros Ventres
ventured farther west and south, they
quickly adopted the lifestyle of the Northern
Plains. They became mobile and followed the
buffalo herds for their primary source of food
and clothing. They lived in easily moved tipis
and excelled at the elaborate and beautiful
beadwork and quillwork of that region.

Like other Plains tribes, the Gros Ventres'
spiritual practices were rich and complex.
Their principal tribal ceremony was the Sun
Dance, or "Sacrifice Dance." Their major religious
possessions were sacred pipes. The
Gros Ventres once possessed ten such pipes,
but now have only two; the Flat Pipe and the
Chief Medicine Pipe, or Feathered Pipe, are
revered as a direct link to the supernatural.
Each spring, the two medicine pipes are used
to secure blessings from the One Above.

During the early part of the nineteenth century,
the Gros Ventres were driven farther
south to the Missouri River country by the
Crees and Assiniboines. In the 1820s one band
of the Gros Ventres joined the Arapahos in the
Cimarron Valley, in the present-day Oklahoma
Panhandle. The Gros Ventres band remained
there for five years before traveling
back north in 1833.

The reunited Gros Ventres took up a precarious
position on the Northern Plains, settling
in an area between the Blackfoot to the
west, the Assiniboines to the east, and the
Crows toward the south. Smallpox epidemics
had struck the tribe in 1781, 1801, and 1829, significantly
reducing their numbers. The great
smallpox epidemic of 1837–38 devastated the
Blackfoot and the Assiniboines but left the
Gros Ventres and the Crows comparatively
undisturbed. The Crows proved an enduring
enemy, and warfare continued between the
two tribes even into the reservation period.

Unlike many other Northern Plains tribes,
the Gros Ventres generally remained on good
terms with non-Indians. They patronized the
American traders at Fort McKenzie and were
considered among the more receptive tribes in
the region. Jesuit missionaries, including Father
Pierre-Jean De Smet and Father Nicolas
Point, made sporadic visits to the Gros Ventres
and found them generally amicable but
resistant to Christianization. Isaac Stephens,
governor of Washington Territory, held council
with the Gros Ventres, as part of the Blackfoot
nation, in 1855, out of which came a treaty
formalizing relations between the tribe and
the United States and pressing for intertribal
peace on the Northern Plains.

Gold was discovered in what is now Montana
in 1862, bringing more and more non-
Indians through the hunting territories that
supported the Blackfeet, Assiniboines, Crows,
and Gros Ventres. The completion of the
Union Pacific Railroad in 1869, and the Northern
Pacific Railroad in 1883, brought increasing
numbers of settlers and made the region less
remote. The impact of such rapid settlement
greatly reduced the game herds, particularly
the bison, already dwindling in numbers. The
last of the buffalo herds had disappeared from
the Northern Plains by the time the Gros Ventres
were confined to the Fort Belknap Reservation
in north-central Montana in 1888. At
that time, their population stood at 964, and
their tribal numbers fell to a low of 576 in 1900.

In 1935 the tribe reorganized its government,
the Fort Belknap Indian Community
Council, under the terms of the Wheeler-
Howard Act (Indian Reorganization Act). In
the twentieth century the tribe petitioned the
U.S. government for compensation for questionable
land transfers in the nineteenth century
and battled with mining corporations in
an effort to maintain its land base and protect
the environment. Despite sharing the Fort
Belknap Reservation with the Assiniboines,
the Gros Ventres have worked to maintain a
distinct culture. There are now few fluent
Gros Ventre speakers; however a vigorous
program to teach the language begins in primary
school and culminates in classes at a local
community college. Their economy is agriculturally
based, but the federal and tribal
governments remain the primary employers,
and unemployment remains high. In 2000 the
Gros Ventres numbered some 3,000 members,
the majority living on the 652,593-acre Fort
Belknap Reservation.


Walter C. Fleming
Montana State University-Bozeman




Bryan, William L., Jr. Montana's Indians: Yesterday and
Today. Helena MT: American and World Geographic Publishing,
1996. Flannery, Regina. The Gros Ventre of Montana:
Part I, Social Life. Washington DC: Catholic University
of America Press, 1953. Horse Capture, George, ed. The
Seven Visions of Bull Lodge. Lincoln: University of Nebraska
Press, 1992.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>