<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.rel.010</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Catholic Sisterhoods</field>
      <field name="author">Carroll, James T.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CATHOLIC SISTERHOODS

Catholic sisterhoods are groups of Roman
Catholic women who are bound by the vows
of poverty, chastity, and obedience to live in a
community and to serve the church in a wide
range of ministries, especially education,
health care, and social services. These women
arrived in the Great Plains in the 1860s to establish
schools, hospitals, and churches for
Native Americans from Dakota Territory to
Texas. They were among the first representatives
of the Catholic Church to reach the frontier
for purposes of evangelization. As the sisterhoods
attracted more members in later
years, they founded a large number of institutions
to serve the Catholic population in
the Great Plains, including elementary and
high schools, colleges, orphanages, homes for
women, hospitals, and nursing homes. Much
of the Catholic infrastructure in the Great
Plains was established by religious sisters.

Between fifty and sixty Catholic sisterhoods
serve in the Great Plains today. These groups
vary widely in terms of membership, lifestyle,
and apostolic activity. The largest groups include
the Sisters of Saint Joseph of Carondelet
(St. Louis, Missouri), Order of Saint Benedict
of Pontifical Jurisdiction (Yankton, South Dakota),
Religious Sisters of Mercy (Omaha, Nebraska), and the Sisters of the Presentation of
the Blessed Virgin Mary (Aberdeen, South Dakota).
The smallest community is the Oblate
Sisters of the Blessed Sacrament, who minister
to Native Americans in Rapid City and Marty,
South Dakota. In the Prairie Provinces the
most prominent Catholic sisterhoods are the
Grey Nuns and the Sisters of Saint Anne.

Since the Second Vatican Council (1965) the
sisterhoods have liberalized their rules on dress,
cloister, and the types of work they perform.
The new areas of ministry include reaching out
to the poor and marginalized as directors of
soup kitchens, social workers, hospice caretakers,
and coordinators of low-income housing and
improving the condition of Native Americans.

See also LAW: North Dakota Anti-Garb Law.


James T. Carroll
Iona College




Coburn, Carol, and Martha Smith. Spirited Lives: How
Nuns Shaped Catholic Culture and American Life, 1836–1920.
Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press,
1999. Peterson, Susan. "Religious Communities of Women
in the West: The Presentation Sisters' Adaptation to the
Northern Plains Frontier." Journal of the West 21 (1982):
65–70. Peterson, Susan. "Widening Horizons: Catholic
Sisterhoods on the Northern Plains, 1874–1910." Great
Plains Quarterly 5 (1985): 125–32.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>