<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ha.003</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Baca, Polly (b. 1941)</field>
      <field name="author">DeSipio, Louis</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BACA, POLLY (b. 1941)

Polly Baca's career is filled with firsts. She was
the first Latino (and the first minority) to be
elected to the Colorado Senate and the first
Latina to serve in the leadership in any state
senate or to be nominated by a major party to
run for U.S. Congress (an election she lost).

Baca is a lifelong Coloradan, and most of
her public service has been in Colorado. She
was born in Weld County on February 13, 1941,
and grew up in Greeley and Thornton. In 1962
she received her bachelor of arts degree at Colorado
State University. Baca was drawn into
politics as part of the first campaign to harness
Latino voters, the 1960 "Viva Kennedy" campaign.
Her campaign work initiated a series of
political jobs, first with unions, then with the
Democratic Party and the United Farm Workers.
Baca tapped these experiences when she
successfully ran for the Colorado House of
Representatives in 1974 and the Colorado State
Senate in 1978. She left the Colorado legislature
to run unsuccessfully for U.S. Congress in
1986. Baca received two appointments in the
Clinton administration. In 1993 she was appointed
director of the U.S. Office of Consumer
Affairs. She left this position in 1994 to
return to Colorado as Rocky Mountain regional
director for the General Services Administration.

After leaving public service in 1998, she began
her own consulting firm and worked as a
full-time volunteer with the Center for Contemplative
Living, which is dedicated to renewing
the contemplative dimension of the
Gospels in everyday life. Polly Baca holds honorary
degrees from the University of Northern
Colorado at Greeley and Wartburg College. In
2000 Baca was inducted into the Colorado
Women's Hall of Fame.


Louis DeSipio
University of California, Irvine





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>