<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.gen.019</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Hired Girls</field>
      <field name="author">Handy-Marchello, Barbara</field>
      <field name="text">

 




HIRED GIRLS

The hired girl was in demand on the farms of
the Great Plains. Though sought after, she was
often spurned if her work habits, language
skills, and personal habits did not meet the
standards of her employer. In spite of the need
for supplemental labor on nonelectrified
farms, the supply of girls available to do domestic
work between 1870 and 1940 seldom
met the demand, perhaps because the hired
girl's pay ran about half that of the hired man.

In the Great Plains, hiring out daughters
was a common practice among nearly all
immigrant ethnic groups. The money they
earned usually returned, at least in part, to
their families, perhaps to support the educational
goals of younger siblings. The work also
served as training in running a household,
and for those who obtained work in homes of
native-born Americans, an opportunity to
learn the English language and Americanstyle
housekeeping.

The rural domestic was not confined to the
house proper. She was especially valued if she
could milk cows and separate the cream, feed
chickens and gather eggs, harness horses, and
perhaps take a few turns in the field. The lack
of definition in the job often drove rural girls
to urban homes where the pay was better and
the tasks limited to the house.

Child care was usually a part of the hired
girl's work, and because it interfered with the
other assigned duties it was often a major
source of discontent. Yet the domestic filled
every aspect of the role the farm woman vacated
when seasons of intense work, such as
harvest, demanded her labor in the fields. For
some hired girls, this exposure was enough to
convince them to leave farm life behind. City
work often led to marriage and life in an urban
setting.

The hired girl often went to work at a very
young age. Hired girls as young as seven took
on child care and minor household and barnyard
tasks. Often these very young girls had
lost one or both parents or were born out of
wedlock and had no place in their mother's
subsequent family. By the age of twelve, most
young girls were considered capable of managing
housework, barnyard chores, and child
care for a couple of weeks while a woman recovered
from childbirth. After the age of sixteen,
young women who had completed their
education, or who sought income to support
more education, took positions near home or
farther away, with enough understanding of
the demand for their labor to arrange for the
most advantageous situation. If pay was withheld,
the work too demanding, or the atmosphere
too oppressive, they could easily find
another position. The advantage of mobility
might fade for a widow or divorced woman
who had to turn to domestic work to support
herself and her children.

The demand for domestics in the rural
Great Plains guaranteed that women, even
those with little education or some social
handicap such as an illegitimate child, could
find work at any time. The quality of the experience
varied with the domestic's age, family
status, and ability to maintain some control
over the selling of her labor.


Barbara Handy-Marchello
University of North Dakota




Coburn, Carol K. "Learning to Serve: Education and
Change in the Lives of Rural Domestics in the Twentieth
Century." Journal of Social History 25 (1991): 109–22. Dudden,
Faye E. Serving Women: Household Service in Nineteenth-Century America. Middletown CT: Wesleyan University
Press, 1983.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>