<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.068</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Ross, Sinclair (1908-1996)</field>
      <field name="author">Stouck, David</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ROSS, SINCLAIR (1908-1996)

James Sinclair Ross was born on a homestead
near Prince Albert, Saskatchewan, on January
22, 1908. His parents separated when he was
seven, and he was raised by his mother on a
series of Saskatchewan farms where she made
her living as a housekeeper. After grade eleven
schooling, he joined the Royal Bank of Canada
in 1924 and, with the exception of service
in the Canadian Army in England from 1942
to 1946, continued with the bank in several
Saskatchewan towns, Winnipeg, and Montreal
until his retirement in 1968. He died in
Vancouver on February 29, 1996.

Ross is best known for three titles. The Lamp at Noon and Other Stories (1968) collects
the works of short fiction he wrote in the 1930s
and 1940s. These stories chronicle the physical
and psychological hardships of living and
working on isolated Prairie farms during the
drought and depression of the 1930s. They
dramatize the heroic determination that kept
the settlers from defeat as well as the pride that
cut them off from nearly all contact with others.
Ross's major novel, As for Me and My House (1941), is the story of the Reverend Philip
Bentley and his unnamed wife, their loveless
marriage, and their efforts to escape from
the small Prairie town in which they are living.
Like Ross's short fiction, As for Me and My House is set against a 1930s background of dust
storms and economic hardship that gives the
novel dramatic and historical authenticity.
But its lasting interest derives from the way the
story is told: in a series of diary entries from
Mrs. Bentley's point of view and in a taut,
lyrical prose style that renders for the imagining
eye both the beauty and the harshness of
the Prairie setting. Ross's last novel, Sawbones Memorial (1974), is the story of a small Saskatchewan
community that looks back over its
past on the evening of the local doctor's retirement
party. Critics have praised the comic exposure
of small-town meanness and prejudice
and the skill with which Ross handled an experimental
dramatic form. Ross's other two
novels, The Well (1951) and Whir of Gold (1970),
have earned less critical and popular interest.


David Stouck
Simon Fraser University




McMullen, Lorraine. Sinclair Ross. Boston: Twayne, 1979.
Stouck, David, ed. Sinclair Ross's "As for Me and My House": Five Decades of Criticism. Toronto: University of
Toronto Press, 1991.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>