<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ha.037</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Rivera, Tomás (1935-1984)</field>
      <field name="author">Serrato, Phillip</field>
      <field name="text">

 




RIVERA, TOMÁS (1935-1984)

Tomás Rivera is one of the most important
writers who emerged from the Chicano movement
of the 1960s. A member of a Mexican
American migrant farmworker family, he was
born in Crystal City, Texas, on December 22,
1935, and grew up in Texas, Iowa, Minnesota,
Michigan, Wisconsin, Ohio, and North and
South Dakota. His novel, short stories, and
poetry portray the experiences of Mexican
American families who traverse the Great
Plains and Midwest in search of work as farm
laborers. Notable about Rivera's work is his
commitment to capturing the humanity of
workers who must endure inhumane living,
working, and traveling conditions. Although
some of his narratives and poems are set specifically
in Iowa, Minnesota, and Texas, most
settings are unidentified, which seems an appropriately
general way to represent the common
experiences of migrant workers spread
throughout the Great Plains, Midwest, and
West.

In the novel . . . y no se lo tragó la tierra (. . .
And the Earth Did Not Devour Him, 1971) and
the short stories collected in The Harvest
(1989), Rivera presents Mexican Americans'
migratory experiences as haunted by racism
and desperate struggles to survive. It is through
these portrayals, though, that Rivera manages
to present Mexican American migrants as
uniquely strong people who refuse to let adversity
break their search for better lives.

An important theme in Rivera's work is the
devastating effect that migrants' constant mobility
has on their sense of home and on their
ability to maintain a sense of community
among themselves. The poem "The Searchers"
(1976) is a powerful meditation on how
migrants' meandering precipitates a feeling of
alienation from the land they travel over, sleep
on, and work on.

Rivera also published several critical essays
about Chicano literature, and two years before
his death he published "The Great Plains
as Refuge in Chicano Literature" (1982). In
this essay he elaborates on the conflicting
meanings that the Great Plains and Midwest
have held for Mexican Americans since the
late nineteenth century. He indicates that in
the 1880s, Mexican laborers began streaming
into the Great Plains and Midwest–which
they dubbed simply El Norte (the North)–in
search of economic opportunity as well as an
escape from the particularly cruel treatment
they received as laborers on ranches in Texas.
In El Norte, Texas Mexicans and Mexican immigrants
worked as cowhands, sheep shearers,
and railroad hands. Ultimately, Rivera captures the contradictory meanings that the
Great Plains and Midwest held for migrant
workers when he points out that they were
places where Mexicans encountered exploitation,
respect, disillusionment, exhausting
work, and the prospect of a new life, all at the
same time.

Tomás Rivera died in Fontana, California,
on May 16, 1984.


Phillip Serrato
Sullerton College




Lattin, Vernon E., Rolando Hinojosa, and Gary D. Keller,
eds. Tomás Rivera, 1935–1984: The Man and His Work.
Tempe AZ: Bilingual Review Press, 1988.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>