<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.arc.003</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Baled Biomas Buildings</field>
      <field name="author">Murphy, David</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BALED BIOMASS BUILDINGS

The idea of using bales of hay as building
blocks emerged in the North Platte River valley
after the appearance of mechanical baling
equipment in the latter half of the nineteenth
century. Although there were relatively few
baled hay buildings, the technique was nonetheless
a significant architectural innovation
of the Great Plains.

Processed from the material body of the
place (usually from either prairie flora or agricultural
waste), the technology came to be
centered in the Sandhills of Nebraska. Other
structures were built on the nearby High
Plains of Nebraska, Wyoming, and South Dakota.
The historic period of importance dates
from about 1900 to 1940, but a contemporary
resurgence–principally using oat, wheat, and
rye straw–has already surpassed the original
in numerical and spatial significance.

Bales were used structurally as giant building
blocks, stacked in the running bond common
to masonry construction, with the constituent
materials positioned either vertically
or horizontally in the block. Bales were set in
either mud or concrete mortar or were simply
stacked one upon another. Wooden or metal
rods often pinned the bales together and secured
window and door frames to the walls.
Plates were likewise fastened to the tops of
walls. Roofs were most often of the hipped
type, which allowed for even compression
along all walls and obviated the need to raise
the wall high into a gable end. After a short
period of settling or sometimes an extended
period of occupancy, the exterior of the bales
was fitted with chicken wire and then plastered
with clay, lime, or cement stucco. Interior
walls were typically lime plastered.

Buildings constructed from bales were economical
structures with outstanding thermal
qualities. Sturdy far beyond expectation,
properly built and maintained structures have
an indefinite life span. One century-old dwelling
still stands west of Alliance, Nebraska. Evidence
exists that the material in old baled
buildings does not readily deteriorate, and
cattle will still eat hay from old bales. While
most constructions were intended as dwellings,
others were used as schools, a service
garage, a two-story restaurant, and a church.

The postmodern resurgence of the technology
emanated from research by folklorist
Roger L. Welsch, principally from articles that
appeared in the 1973 alternative publication,
Shelter. Most contemporary buildings use
bales either as infill for post-and-beam structures
or veneering for light wooden frames,
but structural bale walls, now dubbed the
"Nebraska style," also enjoy renewed popularity.
The renaissance is centered in the American
Southwest but is significantly international
in scope. The diffusion back into the
Plains began in the 1990s.

See also FOLKWAYS: Welsch, Roger.


David Murphy
Nebraska State Historical Society




Myhrman, Matts, and Judy Knox. "A Brief History of Hay
and Straw as Building Materials." Last Straw 1 (1993): 1, 4–
5, 18–19; 2 (1993): 16–17, 19, 23; 6 (1994): 17–18. Steen,
Athena Swentzell, Bill Steen, and David Bainbridge. The
Straw Bale House. White River Junction VT: Chelsea Green
Publishing Company, 1994. Welsch, Roger L. "Sandhill
Baled-Hay Construction." Keystone Folklore Quarterly 15
(1970): 16–34.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>