<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pe.023</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Eiseley, Loren (1907-1977)</field>
      <field name="author">Sorensen, Jacquelynn</field>
      <field name="text">

 




EISELEY, LOREN (1907-1977)

Loren Eiseley


Loren Corey Eiseley was born September 3,
1907, in Fremont, Nebraska, and was the only
child of Daisy Corey and Clyde Edwin Eiseley.
After briefly residing in both Fremont and
Aurora, the family settled in Lincoln, where in
1925 Loren completed his public schooling,
the first member of his family to do so. Having
been introduced to the natural history museum
on the University of Nebraska campus at
age twelve and returning often to be fascinated
by its archeological and anthropological exhibits,
he entered the university that fall intent
on majoring in science. It was at Nebraska
that he experienced his first scientific expedition
as part of the South Party (Morrill Paleontological
Expedition of 1931–33). Professor
C. Bertrand Schultz, leader of the expedition,
honored Eiseley some years later by naming a
fossil oreodont after him (hadroleptauchenia
eiseleyi).

Eiseley graduated from the university in
1933 with a Bachelor of Arts in sociology and
English and received a doctorate in anthropology
at the University of Pennsylvania in 1937.
After brief tenure at the University of Kansas
and Oberlin College in Ohio, where he served
as chair of the Department of Sociology and
Anthropology, he returned to Pennsylvania
where he remained for thirty years until he
ended his teaching career as Benjamin Franklin
Professor of Anthropology and the History
of Science.

Although his formal education and subsequent
livelihood would emphasize scientific
application, Eiseley maintained a dedicated
and productive interest in literature and composition.
In fact, his fiction won him awards
from Atlantic Monthly as a high-school senior
and citation in the Distinctive Index of Best
Short Stories of 1936, and he wrote three collections
of poetry. But it was Eiseley's combination
of scientific analysis and poetic sensibility
that brought him his greatest acclaim. In
books like The Immense Journey (1957) and
Darwin's Century: Evolution and the Men who
Discovered It (1958), he interpreted natural
history for a wide audience. Eiseley conveyed
a sense of awe and wonder when he wrote
about nature, a spiritual yearning that reverberated
with his readers.

During his lifetime, Eiseley was awarded
thirty-six honorary degrees, memberships in
distinguished scholarly societies–including
the National Institute of Arts and Letters–and
was appointed by President Lyndon Johnson
to the President's Task Force on the Preservation
of Natural Beauty. He was the twelfth recipient
of the Distinguished Nebraskan Award.
Loren Eiseley died in Philadelphia on July 9,
1977.


Jacquelynn Sorensen
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Christianson, Gale E. Fox at the Wood's Edge: a Biography
of Loren Eiseley. New York: Henry Holt and Company,
1990. Heidtmann, Peter. Loren Eiseley: A Modern Ishmael.
Hamden CT: Archon Books, 1991.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>