<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.tra.037</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Transcontinental Motor Convoy</field>
      <field name="author">White, Tom</field>
      <field name="text">

 




TRANSCONTINENTAL MOTOR CONVOY


Caught in time between prairie schooners and eighteen-wheelers, the 1919 khaki-covered truck train exits Nebraska.


In August 1919 thousands of people in Nebraska
and Wyoming greeted U.S. army soldiers
with curiosity, patriotic cheer, and generous
amounts of food and drink as they
drove a convoy of early heavy trucks across the
Great Plains.

Among the caravan's nearly 300 soldiers
was twenty-eight-year-old Lt. Col. Dwight D.
Eisenhower, who became the supreme allied
commander during World War II and, in 1952,
the thirty-fourth president. President Eisenhower
initiated the Federal Highway Trust
Fund, which built the nation's 46,000-mile interstate
highway system, and he would later
credit the convoy experience for teaching him
that a quality paved-road system is essential to
a nation's economic and military security.

Officially named the Transcontinental Motor
Convoy of 1919, the caravan was composed
of eighty-one army vehicles and numerous
nonmilitary autos and trucks. Its main objective
was to determine the military value of
assorted vehicles the army had acquired but
not put into service during World War I. The
convoy also served as a war game, a recruiting
drive, a campaign for long-haul trucking, and,
not incidentally, a parade observed by millions
along its route.

For more than sixty-two bone-jarring days
the truck train traveled 3,251 miles from Washington
dc to San Francisco on the Lincoln
Highway, which later became U.S. Route 30.
In 1919 the Lincoln Highway through Nebraska
and Wyoming was mostly a rough dirt
road, often little more than a deeply rutted
trail with weak or nonexistent bridges. The
convoy needed twenty days to forge its way
through the two Plains states. West of North
Platte, Nebraska, the soldiers and machines
became mired in a 200-foot stretch of quicksand
for more than seven hours.

Overcoming the obstacles of rudimentary
vehicles and rugged road conditions with hard
work and persistence, the convoy reached San
Francisco on September 6 with 90 percent of
the vehicles that started still running. Beyond
its military value, the convoy helped make
the case to the nation that improving crosscountry
roads was a federal, not just a local,
priority–a point Eisenhower would make as
president.

See also POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT: Eisenhower, Dwight D.


Tom White
Lincoln, Nebraska





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>