<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.edu.023</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Libraries</field>
      <field name="author">Wertheimer, Andrew B.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




LIBRARIES

Little is known of the earliest libraries in the
Great Plains, but they probably resembled antebellum
collections elsewhere in book-scarce
frontier communities. Nascent frontier communities
established private libraries such
as those in the village of Omaha, Nebraska,
where in 1856 residents wanted to boost settlement
and provide competition for saloons.
These libraries laid the foundations for public
libraries once legislation allowed for municipal
support of publicly held, free-circulating
libraries.

By the time settlers migrated to the Great
Plains, the library movement in North America
was already maturing from its British and
Colonial New England origins as parochial,
mercantile, and social into a profession led by
public and college librarians. Events such as
the establishment of the American Library Association
(ALA) in 1876 and Melvil Dewey's
founding of the first modern library school at
Columbia University eight years later signified
this homogenization of "library economy,"
which Dewey summarized as providing "the
best reading for the largest number at the least
expense."

Development of libraries varied in each
community, often depending on the energy
of social reformers possessed by the "library
spirit." Many libraries owe their origins to
women's clubs, which raised funds for reading
rooms by memberships, lectures, and bake
sales before turning their library over to the
city. Such gifts were often prompted by the
desire for matching grants offered by Andrew
Carnegie and other philanthropists to construct
local temples of knowledge.

Statehood was another factor in the growth
of libraries, as legislatures allowed communities
to raise mill levies for their support.
This legislation varied in each jurisdiction.
In Oklahoma, for example, school districts
were originally charged with library operation
in 1889. It wasn't until 1901 that the territorial
legislature allowed cities with a population
over 2,500 to charge a mill levy to support
publicly held libraries. The small size
of many Great Plains communities likely retarded
library development, because numerous
communities could only afford small
collections that opened for just a few hours
and were staffed by "born" librarians rather
than trained ones.

The establishment of the Laramie County
Library in Cheyenne, Wyoming, in 1886 pioneered
the first county library system, which
since has become the model for modern library
service in North America. In Saskatchewan
the province not only allowed municipalities
to tax for library support in 1905 but
also offered an additional grant; however, library
development was slow until the province's
Commonwealth Cooperative Federation
government created the Regional Library
in 1950. Readers in the Southern Great Plains
were further disadvantaged by Jim Crow laws,
which segregated libraries and left many African
Americans without access. For example,
racial conflict, masquerading as an anti-
Communist crusade, led to the downfall of
Bartlesville, Oklahoma, librarian Ruth Brown
in 1950. After thirty years of service, Brown
was fired for ostensibly circulating subversive
materials, but the real reason was her affiliation
with the Congress of Racial Equality.

State library commissions were also strong
promoters of public libraries. For example,
North Dakota's Public Library Commission,
established in 1907, operated traveling libraries
(cases with sixty books or fewer on loan to
communities for up to six months) and advised
communities on library development.
These traveling libraries contributed to the
hunger for reading in rural parts of the state. A
year later the commission established the Legislative
Reference Bureau, which was based on
Wisconsin's progressive example. However, in
1919 the commission became involved in a political
fight between the Nonpartisan League
and opponents over "socialistic" books in
traveling libraries. As a result of the weakened
Library Commission and the end of Carnegie
grants to libraries, little progress was made in
providing service to rural parts of North Dakota
until counties received permission to operate
libraries in 1945. Sparse populations and
an aversion to taxes, though, meant that few
such initiatives passed until the 1955 Library
Services Act, which supported rural library
development as part of federal initiatives during
the cold war to improve education and
literacy. Throughout the Great Plains, federal
aid through the WPA and other agencies created
during the Great Depression provided extension
librarians to many rural communities
that previously were without service.

Among the first libraries in the Plains were
state and territorial ones that grew on the exchange
of government documents. The dates
of establishment for these early libraries are
Texas (1846), New Mexico (1850), Kansas
(1855), Nebraska (1856), Colorado (1863),
South Dakota (1865), Montana (1865), Manitoba
(1870), Wyoming (1871), Oklahoma
(1893), Alberta (1906), North Dakota (1907),
and Saskatchewan (1953). Other special libraries
in the Great Plains also developed, including
law libraries, medical libraries, and corporate
information centers. The history of the
Great Plains is preserved in many state and
provincial historical society libraries and archives
as well as in the Dwight D. Eisenhower
Library and Museum (Abilene, Kansas), the
Johnson Presidential Library (College Park,
Texas), and the Bush Presidential Library
(Austin, Texas), which are operated by the National
Archives and Records Administration.
These libraries, together with local and academic
libraries, are repositories for books, periodicals,
and archival papers that encompass
the print culture of the Great Plains.

The largest collections in the Plains are
those of the research universities of the states
and provinces. In good years these libraries
grew along with their fledgling institutions of
higher learning. Indeed, their growth was instrumental
in the growth of all Plains libraries,
because their librarians taught in the pioneering
programs of library schools, pioneered library
legislation on the state level, and encouraged
the state library associations that
fostered professional librarianship. Research
libraries at state schools, inspired by the vision
of the Morrill Act of 1862, not only provide
material for students and faculty but also offer
service to citizens through reference assistance
and book circulation via interlibrary loan.
Special collections and archives at research libraries
contribute to the preservation of the
cultural life of the Great Plains. The extensive
papers and correspondence of writer Mari
Sandoz, for example, are at the University of
Nebraska-Lincoln. The Harry Ransom Humanities
Research Center at the University of
Texas at Austin is one of the world's richest
collections of archives and manuscripts, including
those of New Mexico author Alice
Corbin Henderson, and papers of writers
D. H. Lawrence, Tennessee Williams, Isaac
Bashevis Singer, and publisher Alfred A.
Knopf. Some of the more important special
collections at Canadian university libraries include
the papers of the Thistledown and Turnstone
regional literary presses and the diaries
of Icelandic immigrant Simon Simonarson at
the University of Manitoba, members of the
Regina Five art movement at the University of
Regina, and author W. O. Mitchell at the University
of Calgary.

Professional education for librarianship has
been available in the Great Plains since Gertrude
Shawan established a ten-week sequence
at Kansas State Normal School (later Emporia
State University) in 1902. It was typical of
the apprentice classes run by larger public and
academic libraries from which early library
workers were recruited. Unlike many schools
that were closed as education became more
professional, the School of Library and Information
Management at Emporia State University
survived and now offers professional
master's and doctoral degrees. Library science
was also taught at the University of Denver
between 1932 and 1985 and again after 1995.
The predecessor to the School of Library and
Information Studies at the University of Oklahoma
was established in 1929, and the University
of Alberta established a graduate program
in 1968. Texas is unique in that it has three
professional schools, two at the University
of North Texas in Denton and one at the University
of Texas at Austin. Many other colleges,
especially normal schools, once offered
teacher-librarian courses to prepare school librarians,
but these were not graduate programs
accredited by the ALA.

Although recent library literature focuses
on technological developments, historical reflection
suggests that libraries' traditional
functions of providing access to information
and recreation perhaps have not changed
greatly. However, libraries and archives are increasingly
faced with questions of how to preserve
both digital and paper records of life in
the Great Plains as well as offer access to the
wider world.


Andrew B. Wertheimer
University of Wisconsin-Madison




Passet, Joanne E. Cultural Crusaders: Women Librarians in
the American West, 1900–1917. Albuquerque: University of
New Mexico Press, 1994. Robbins, Louise S. The Dismissal
of Miss Ruth Brown: Civil Rights, Censorship and the American
Library. Norman: University of Oklahoma Press,
2000.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>