<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ct.005</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Billings, Montana</field>
      <field name="author">Guizlo, Mark</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BILLINGS, MONTANA

Billings, located in south-central Montana, is
the state's largest city, with a population of
89,847 in 2000. Billings is the seat of Yellowstone
County (2000 population, 129,351). To
the north of the city stands the Rimrocks, a
sandstone formation that rises approximately
300 feet above the Yellowstone valley; to the
south lies the Yellowstone River. With abundant
game and the Yellowstone River, the site
of present-day Billings was a center for hunting
and trading well before homesteaders established
a permanent settlement there in
1877. The original town of Coulson was served
by steamship but was overshadowed when a
town site was chosen along the newly developed
Northern Pacific Railroad in 1881. The
city was named for Frederick Billings, president
of the Northern Pacific Railroad. Early
historical figures include Calamity Jane and
Wild Bill Hickok.

As the largest city within a 500-mile radius,
Billings is a major regional service center for
the Northern Plains and Rocky Mountains.
Economic activities include medical and retail
services, oil refining, agricultural processing,
telecommunications, and tourism. Educational
institutions include Montana State University.
Billings and Rocky Mountain College.
Billings is also the location of regional offices
of federal and state agencies.

Billings and Yellowstone County have experienced
substantial growth in recent years,
predominantly on limited available river valley
farmland. In general, environmental issues,
including land use, water resources, and
wildlife management, are controversial. City
and county governments are challenged by
the prospects of planning and growth management
in a state with little historic success in
those endeavors. In addition to low-density
suburban development on the city's edge,
downtown Billings experienced significant redevelopment
in the 1990s after a two-decade
decline in retail and business activities. The
city center is now home to numerous art galleries,
museums, and restaurants.

Annual events include the North American
Livestock Exposition and the Montana Fair,
the largest annual agricultural fair in the state.
Billings is home to several museums. The
Western Heritage Center, a regional history
museum, is located in the original Parmly Billings
Library building, a structure that was designed
by the Frederick Billings family to replicate
the library at the University of Vermont.
The Peter Yegen Jr. County Museum, which
focuses on frontier history, is located at the top
of the Rimrock cliffs, immediately adjacent to
Billings Logan International Airport. The recently
renovated and expanded Yellowstone
Art Museum is located in the former county
jail and is one of the largest contemporary art
museums in the western United States.

Attractions within an hour's drive of Billings
include the Pryor and the Beartooth
Mountains, the Little Bighorn Battlefield National
Monument, the Bighorn National Recreation
Area, Pictograph Cave State Park, and
Chief Plenty Coups State Park. Thirty miles
east of Billings stands Pompeys Pillar National
Monument, where William Clark chiseled his
first initial, last name, and the date, July 25,
1806, in the sandstone formation. This is the
only remaining physical evidence of the Lewis
and Clark Expedition. The site is owned by
the Bureau of Land Management and has
been recommended for status as a national
monument.

See also MEDIA: 
Billings Gazette.


Mark Guizlo
Montana State University-Billings




Small, Lawrence. A Century of Politics on the Yellowstone.
Billings MT: Rocky Mountain College, 1983. West, Carol
Van. Capitalism on the Frontier: Billings and the Yellowstone Valley in the Nineteenth Century. Lincoln: University
of Nebraska Press, 1993. Winks, Robin. Frederick Billings: A Life. New York: Oxford University Press, 1991.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>