<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ag.076</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Wildlife and Agriculture</field>
      <field name="author">Case, Ronald M.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




WILDLIFE AND AGRICULTURE

Habitat destruction, degradation, and fragmentation,
brought about primarily from agricultural
development, have greatly changed
the landscape of the Great Plains and, concomitantly,
the wildlife that reside there. More
than 325 million acres in the Great Plains are
farmed. Only 1 percent of the original tallgrass
prairie remains. The oak savanna, small
in area in the Great Plains, is also greatly reduced.
Both ecosystems were largely converted
to farms. The mixed grass prairie has
been impacted to a lesser extent, although
it also has been substantially reduced. The
shortgrass prairie is relatively intact, although
portions have been degraded through overgrazing
and fire suppression. Mixed grass and
shortgrass prairies that were grazed were less
severely altered by agriculture. Wetlands were
drained, converted to agriculture, or lost due
to lowering the water table caused by irrigation.
Habitat fragmentation may result in the
demise of area-sensitive species (those needing
a minimum size habitat). Further, isolation
of habitats makes it easy for small populations
to become extinct and difficult for
colonizers to repopulate an area.

Prior to European American settlement the
Great Plains was teeming with wildlife: large
ungulates such as bison, pronghorns, deer,
elk, and bighorn sheep; predators, such as
wolves, grizzly bears, and black bears; prairie
dogs in the billions; and numerous turkeys
and prairie chickens. Millions of acres of wetlands
provided breeding habitat for waterfowl
and resting and feeding areas for other migratory
birds. All that changed with settlement
by European Americans. The large ungulates
were decimated through wanton shooting,
unregulated harvest, and as a military strategy
to deprive Native Americans of a source of
food. Although this was not the direct effect of
agriculture, the decline of those animals was
seen as necessary so that cattle could flourish
and the prairie could be converted to farmland.
Predators perceived as a threat to livestock
or animals that competed for forage
with livestock were eliminated; or at least,
efforts were made to eliminate those animals.

Relatively few species are endemic, or
unique, to the Great Plains. Endemic birds
that are declining include mountain plover,
Sprague's pipit, Cassin's sparrow, and lark
bunting. Endemic mammals that are declining
include white-tailed jackrabbit, Franklin's
ground squirrel, black-tailed prairie dog, and
swift fox. Two birds native to the Great Plains–
McCown's longspur and the ferruginous
hawk–experienced an increase in population
over the past twenty-five years. Both species
are characteristic of shortgrass prairies and
thrive in moderate to heavily grazed systems.

The Great Plains now consists of extensive
areas of cultivated crops. The net result of
this habitat uniformity has been a loss of richness
in the number of species. At a distance
croplands may appear like grasslands, but
their management results in barren areas after
harvest. Existing small areas that cannot be
farmed because of thinness of soil or terrain,
as well as areas that have been planted with
trees, create "edge," which is ideal habitat for
some species. Examples of species that have
responded positively to farm habitats include
ring-necked pheasants (an exotic), northern
bobwhite, blue jay, house sparrow (another
exotic), raccoon, opossum, red fox, and
coyote.

In turn, wildlife has a significant impact on
agriculture. In the United States, annual losses
of agriculture to wildlife are about $500 million,
with over half of that attributed to damages
to field crops. Economic benefits from
wildlife are also substantial. For example, estimated
annual benefits associated with whitetailed
deer in the United States are nearly $20
billion. However, those benefits are diffuse
and shared by various businesses and communities,
whereas damages impact the agriculturalist
directly.

See also PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT Endangered Species.


Ronald M. Case
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Licht, Daniel S. Ecology and Economics of the Great Plains.
Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1997. Noss, Reed F.,
and Allen Y. Cooperrider. Saving Nature's Legacy: Protecting and Restoring Biodiversity. Washington DC: Island
Press, 1994. Samson, Fred B., and Fritz L. Knopf, eds.
Prairie Conservation: Preserving North America's Most Endangered Ecosystem. Washington DC: Island Press, 1996.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>