<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.tra.021</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Mormon Trail</field>
      <field name="author">Buckley, Jay H.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MORMON TRAIL

The Mormon Pioneer National Historic Trail
stretches 1,297 miles from Nauvoo, Illinois, to
Salt Lake City, Utah. Although the Mormons,
members of the Church of Jesus Christ of
Latter-day Saints, did not actually blaze the
trail and did not travel it exclusively, their improvements
and extensive use permanently affixed
their name to it.

The first part of the Mormon exodus commenced
on February 4, 1846, when 1,600 Mormons
crossed the Mississippi and began the
journey to Kanesville (Council Bluffs, Iowa)
and Winter Quarters (Florence, Nebraska). In
1847 a group led by Brigham Young began the
second portion of the trail, tracing the Platte
River's north bank and joining the Oregon-California
Trail at Fort Laramie. Four hundred
miles later, at Fort Bridger, they diverged from
the Oregon-California Trail and continued
west to the Great Salt Lake. From 1846 until the
completion of the transcontinental railroad in
Promontory, Utah, in 1869, 70,000.80,000
Mormons emigrated west over the Oregon-California
and Mormon Trails. Approximately
6,000 died along the route.

In 1849 a Perpetual Emigrating Fund was
established to enable converts to borrow
funds for their trip and repay them after settling
in Utah. During the late 1850s Mormon
leaders also cut travel time and expenses by
implementing two-wheeled handcart travel.
Between 1856 and 1860, ten companies comprising
2,962 Mormons used this successful
mode of transportation. In 1856, however, the
Martin and Willie Companies left too late in
the year and were trapped by the Wyoming
winter. More than 200 perished before a rescue
party arrived.

The Mormon Trail experience was highly
organized and less marked by disease or Indian
attack than other overland journeys. It served
as an initiation, a rite of passage, and was
a unifying element for early Mormons. Dramatic
reenactments and celebrations of the
Mormon Trail occurred in 1897, 1947, and 1997.
In 1947 a "Centennial Caravan" consisting of
seventy-two automobiles with simulated covered
wagon tops and plywood oxen made the
journey from Nauvoo to Salt Lake. In 1996 and
1997 an estimated 10,000 joined the sesquicentennial
wagon train for a day, a week, or more.
The Pioneer Cemetery and Mormon Trail
Center at Historic Winter Quarters, Rebecca
Winter's grave near Scottsbluff, Nebraska, Fort
Caspar in Casper, Wyoming, the Mormon
Handcart Visitors Center on the west side of
Devil's Gate, Wyoming, and "This Is the Place"
State Park in Salt Lake City memorialize the
trail, portions of which are still visible in western
Nebraska near North Platte and Sutherland
and in various places in Wyoming.

See also RELIGION: Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints.


Jay H. Buckley
Brigham Young University




Hafen, LeRoy R., and Ann W. Hafen. Handcarts to Zion:
The Story of a Unique Western Migration, 1856–1860. Lincoln:
University of Nebraska Press, 1992. Kimball, Stanley
B. Historic Sites and Markers along the Mormon and Other
Great Western Trails. Urbana: University of Illinois Press,
1988. Stegner, Wallace. The Gathering of Zion: The Story of
the Mormon Trail. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press,
1981.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>