<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.sr.019</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Football, Canadian</field>
      <field name="author">Cosentino, Frank</field>
      <field name="text">

 




FOOTBALL, CANADIAN

Because Canada was a British colony, Canada's
football had its roots in the United Kingdom.
It was the version in vogue at the British public
school of Rugby that arrived in Canada
through immigration, the civil service, and
military garrisons.

By the 1860s the game was being played in
Montreal, where a city group, the Garrison,
and McGill University formed teams. In 1874
McGill took its hybrid form of the Rugby
game to Harvard University and introduced
it to the United States. Harvard in turn promoted
it to neighboring academic institutions.
Changes in the traditional British game
were much slower in Canada than in the
United States. In 1882 the scrum method of
putting the ball in play was modified slightly
in Canada by "heeling" it back to the quarterback;
in the United States it was snapped back,
a regulation that was not accepted universally
in Canada until 1921.

Even though it was understood that the Canadian
game was different from English rugby,
that term continued to be used in Canada
until the 1950s. Growth of the game was assisted
by the formation of governing bodies,
regional and national. The Quebec Rugby
Football Union (QRFU) was formed in 1882;
the Ontario Rugby Football Union (ORFU) in
1883; the Canadian Rugby Union (CRU) in 1892;
the Canadian Intercollegiate Rugby Football
Union (CIRFU) in 1898; the Interprovincial
Rugby Football Union (IRFU) in 1907; and the
Western Interprovincial Rugby Football Union
(WIRFU) in 1911. The latter was the governing
body for unions in Manitoba, Saskatchewan,
and Alberta. Dominion championships have
been held since 1892. A new trophy, the Grey
Cup, named after Governor-General Lord
Grey, was introduced in 1909 and symbolized
Canadian football supremacy. In 1966 the CRU
turned over the trusteeship of the cup to the
Canadian Football League (CFL) and changed
its name to the Canadian Amateur Football
Association (CAFA).

Teams representing cities in the Great Plains
have played a major role in the development of
Canadian football. In 1921 the Edmonton Eskimos
were the first western team to challenge
for the Grey Cup; the Winnipeg Blue Bombers
won that trophy in 1935, the first western team
to do so. They were greatly aided by the nine
American players the team had recruited from
the so-called Swede belt of the Dakotas and
Minnesota. That action caused the CRU to impose
a restriction on the number of Americans
who could play in the national championship.
In 1998 team rosters were thirty-seven players:
sixteen imports (typically Americans), eighteen
nonimports (typically Canadians), and
three quarterbacks (no restrictions).

In 1948 the Calgary Stampeders turned the
national championship into a celebration
when supporters arrived in Toronto, the site
of the game, with western regalia, horses,
chuck wagons, "cowboys and Indians," and
flapjack breakfasts. The Edmonton Eskimos
won consecutive Grey Cups in 1954, 1955, and
1956. In a 1998 poll, Jackie Parker of that era
was selected as the top player ever to play in
the CFL. The Eskimos later won five consecutive
cups from 1978 to 1982. Regina was the
host of the Grey Cup game of 1995. It was also
the first time that an American team, the Baltimore
Stallions, won the Grey Cup when they
defeated the Calgary Stampeders 37 to 20. It
will probably be the last for some time, since
all the American teams disbanded after the
season, cutting short the American expansion
experiment by the CFL.

Professional football in Canada is under the
direction of the CFL and had eight teams in
1998: Montreal Alouettes, Toronto Argonauts,
Hamilton Tiger-Cats, and Winnipeg Blue
Bombers in the Eastern Division; Saskatchewan
Roughriders, Calgary Stampeders, Edmonton
Eskimos, and British Columbia Lions
in the Western Division. The field is 110 yards
long and 65 yards wide. End zones are 20 yards
long. There are twelve players on each team.
The rules allow unlimited motion by the backs
and three downs to make ten yards. Opposing
teams are separated by a one-yard scrimmage
line. Scoring is six points for a touchdown,
one for the extra point after, three for a field
goal, two for a safety touch, and one for a
single point from a punt or missed field goal
where the ball is not returned from the end
zone.

Canadian university football is under the
aegis of the Canadian Intercollegiate Athletic
Union (CIAU). It has a national championship
and trophy, the Vanier Cup, also named for a
Canadian governor-general, Georges Vanier.
Playoffs are held among the champions of the
four regions: Atlantic University Athletic Association
(AUAA), Ontario Universities Athletics
(OUA), Ontario-Quebec Intercollegiate Football
Conference (OQIFC), and Canada West
Universities Athletic Association (CWUAA).
Junior football as well as recreational flag and
touch football are promoted by the CAFA and
its provincial affiliates.

Recreationally, as flag football grows in popularity
with girls as well as boys, impromptu
games of throwing, catching, running, and
kicking are as common as traditional Prairie
games of baseball, soccer, road hockey, and
curling.


Frank Cosentino
York University




Cosentino, Frank. Canadian Football: The Grey Cup Years.
Toronto: Musson Book Company, Ltd., 1969. Cosentino,
Frank. A Passing Game. Winnipeg: Bain and Cox, 1995.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>