<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pe.014</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Bluebonnets</field>
      <field name="author">Kirpatrick, Zoe Merriman</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BLUEBONNETS

Bluebonnets (respecttexas.org)

    
Bluebonnets are lupines that bring to mind
visions of beauty and spectacular color. These
wildflowers of the Legume family (Fabaceae,
alternately Leguminosae), genus Lupinus, are
breathtaking in full bloom, covering prairies
and hills with carpets of solid color ranging
from blue-purple to deep blue, pale blue to
creamy-white, or pink. There are close to a
dozen species that grow within the Great
Plains from Texas to Canada.

Bluebonnets are winter annuals, or perennials,
that form rosettes in the fall and flowers
in the spring. The alternate leaves are palmately
compound, bearing four to fifteen
leaflets (usually five or seven). Pea-like flowers
in terminal clusters have five uniformly colored
petals consisting of two wing petals, two
keel petals, and an erect banner petal bearing a
central white spot, yellow in some species, that
turns burgundy-red with age. Interestingly,
the main pollinators of bluebonnets, bees and
bumblebees, are drawn to the white spot in
their nectar search and shun the red spot,
which indicates nectar is no longer available.

Emblematic of Texas, bluebonnet is the
state flower, but arguments existed for seventy
years as to which species should be the "official" one. In 1971, the legislature passed a law
naming all the species of Lupinus found within
the state the official flower. The loveliest
and most conspicuous one is Lupinus texensis
of central Texas.

The genus name derives from the Latin
lupus, meaning "wolf." The five leaflets were
thought to resemble wolflike tracks, and long
ago these plants were blamed for robbing the
soil of nutrients. Now we know that nodules
on the roots contain nitrogen-fixing bacteria,
Rhizobium spp., that actually enrich the soil.


Zoe Merriman Kirkpatrick
Post, Texas




Kirkpatrick, Zoe Merriman. Wildflowers of the Western
Plains. Austin: University of Texas Press, 1992. McGregor,
R. L., coordinator, and T. M. Barkley, ed. Atlas of the Flora
of the Great Plains. Ames: Iowa State University Press,
1977. Shinners, L. H. "The Bluebonnets (Lupinus) of
Texas." Field &amp; Laboratory 21(1959): 149–53.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>