<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pe.033</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Hayden, Ferdinand Vandeveer (1829-1887)</field>
      <field name="author">Shambaugh-Miller, Michael</field>
      <field name="text">

 




HAYDEN, FERDINAND VANDEVEER (1829-1887)

From 1853 to the late 1870s, Ferdinand Hayden
was known to the Sioux as "man-who-picks-up-
stones-running." To his contemporaries in
the sciences, he was either a fine geologist or
an entrepreneur who gave the government
and land speculators the information needed
to sell large tracts of western land. For the
eager U.S. public Hayden was the man who
provided a series of government-financed
guides to the Great Plains and the Rocky
Mountains.

Hayden was born in Westfield, Massachusetts,
on September 7, 1829. He graduated
from Oberlin College in 1850, and then earned
a degree in medicine from Albany Medical
School in 1853. His true love, however, was
geology.

Hayden's extensive exploration of the American
West began immediately upon his graduation
with his first visit to the White River Badlands
of Nebraska and South Dakota as an
employee of James Hall, arguably the most
respected paleontologist of the period. This
trip was followed the next two seasons by an
expedition funded by private interests that surveyed
the upper Missouri River basin up to the
mouth of the Bighorn River. The summers of
1856 and 1857 found Hayden accompanying his
first governmental survey, the Warren expedition
of Topographical Engineers, to examine
the Yellowstone River and the region to the
north. In 1858 Hayden joined his longtime
friend, F. B. Meek, on a private survey of northeastern
Kansas. In 1859 Hayden again joined
the U.S. Topographical Engineers as the surgeon
and naturalist of Cap. W. F. Raynolds's
expeditions that, in two years, traversed the
area of the upper Missouri, the Yellowstone,
and the Bighorn Mountains. Hayden's explorations
were interrupted in 1861 by the Civil
War, which was the only time he truly used his
medical degree, but were quickly resumed in
1866 when he returned to the Badlands under
the sponsorship of the Academy of Natural
Sciences of Philadelphia.

In 1867, Hayden took charge of a geological
survey of Nebraska, an enterprise that he expanded
into the most comprehensive scientific
survey ever made of the American West.
Through his reports of his expeditions to Nebraska
and adjacent territories in 1867, southern
and eastern Utah in 1868, southern and
eastern Wyoming in 1870, the upper Yellowstone
in 1871, eastern Montana in 1872, Colorado
from 1873 to 1876, eastern Idaho and
western Wyoming in 1877, and finally, the remaining
sections of Wyoming in 1878, Hayden
made the Great Plains known to the American
public. The Yellowstone report was instrumental
in the creation of Yellowstone National
Park; the Colorado report was partly responsible
for rapid settlement of that state in the
late 1870s; and the Nebraska report clarified
that the Great Plains was not a Great American
Desert, but a richly endowed region, in
which even the Sandhills of Nebraska would
"yet become a fine pasture ground for herds of
sheep, cattle, and horses."

Hayden's surveys, along with those of Clarence
King, George Wheeler, and John Wesley
Powell, were absorbed into the U.S. Geological
Survey in 1879. Hayden was retained by the
survey as a staff geologist. After three years in
Washington, Hayden's health began to deteriorate,
and it was thought that a field assignment
might help to rejuvenate him. He was
assigned to the usgs office in Montana. Hayden
remained there until 1886, when it became
obvious that his health was not going to
improve, and he was forced to resign his position.
He returned to Philadelphia where, after
being confined to his home for more than a
year, he died on December 22, 1887.


Michael Shambaugh-Miller
University of Nebraska Medical Center




Bartlett, Richard A. Great Surveys of the American West.
Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1962. Foster,
Mike. Life of Ferdinand Vandeveer Hayden: Strange Genius.
Niwot CO: Roberts Rinehart, 1994.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>