<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ag.061</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Sorghum</field>
      <field name="author">Peterson, Gary C.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SORGHUM


Production of hybrid grain sorghum on the Texas High Plains


Sorghum (Sorghum bicolor [L.] Moench) is a
major food, feed, and fiber crop of northeast
African origin. It is considered the world's
fifth most important cereal. In the United
States sorghum grain is primarily a feed crop,
while in Africa, Asia, and parts of Latin America
its primary use is as a food. The United
States accounts for about 9 percent of the
world's sorghum acreage and 25 percent of
grain produced. Kansas, Nebraska, and Texas
yield about 80 percent of the sorghum produced
in the United States.

Modern grain sorghum is a product of human
ingenuity. Cultivated sorghum has morphologically
distinct, genetically diverse races
that can be intercrossed. The species is a self-pollinating
perennial that is grown in temperate
areas as an annual, but it is handled as a
cross-pollinating crop for hybrid production.
Sorghum is especially useful in areas too hot
and too dry for crops such as corn. It is classified
into four groups: grain sorghum, which
includes old types such as kafir, milo, and feterita,
as well as dwarf combine-type hybrids
grown primarily for grain; forage sorghum,
which are types grown primarily for forage, silage,
or molasses; grass sorghum, types grown
for hay and pasture; and broom corn, which
possess long, stiff panicle branches that are
used to make brooms.

Identification of cytoplasmic-genetic male
sterility in the 1950s led to development of
grain, forage, and grass hybrids. Grain sorghum
hybrids are of a plant height suitable for
combine harvest. The grain may be processed
in several ways depending on use as a feed
(cattle, poultry, or swine) or food. Forage type
hybrids often contain high stalk sugar and are
used as silage. Grass or grazing hybrids are fine
leaved, thin stemmed, and used primarily for
grazing, green-chop, hay, or green manure.
Grain yield of sorghum has more than tripled
since hybrids became commercially available
in 1956. The dramatic increase in grain yield
may be attributed to improved plant genetics–
causing significant improvements in adaptation,
maturity, stalk quality, insect resistance,
disease resistance, grain quality, and
drought tolerance–and improved management,
including herbicides, fertilizer, irrigation,
and soil and water conservation practices.
Sorghum may be rotated with other
crops–for example, a sorghum-fallow-wheat
rotation or cotton-sorghum rotation depending
on the location. More sorghum is grown
dryland than irrigated. Sorghum produces excellent
irrigated yields, although irrigated
acreage has declined as producers shift production
to higher value crops.

Sorghum acreage declined from 18.3 million
acres in 1983 to 9.4 million acres in 1998.
Declines have been particularly marked in
Kansas. Primary factors are the 1985 Farm Bill,
which placed sorghum at a comparative disadvantage
relative to corn, and improvements
in corn drought tolerance that enabled corn to
move into marginal production regions traditionally
planted in sorghum. However, no
other crop has the versatility of sorghum for
diverse production systems, range of planting
dates, and maturity. Producers turn to sorghum
when other crops fail due to drought or
other factors and sorghum will remain key to
Great Plains crop production in the twenty-first
century.


Gary C. Peterson
Texas A&amp;M University Agricultural Research and Extension Center, Lubbock




Bennett, William F., Billy B. Tucker, and A. Bruce Maunder.
Modern Grain Sorghum Production. Ames: Iowa State
University Press, 1990. Doggett, H. Sorghum. New York:
Longman Scientific and Technical, 1988.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>