<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.med.005</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Bismarck Tribune</field>
      <field name="author">Collins, Ross F.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BISMARCK TRIBUNE

The Bismarck Tribune was established in 1873,
the first newspaper in Dakota Territory. The
remote northern half of Dakota Territory saw
few permanent European American settlers
until the Northern Pacific Railroad reached
the Plains in the early 1870s. In the spring of
1873 a young Civil War veteran sensed an opportunity
behind the railroad construction
crews. Clement A. Lounsberry had worked for
several Minnesota newspapers. In May 1873,
after his coverage of Minnesota's state legislature
ended, he moved printing equipment by
the first railcar into Bismarck. Issue number
one of the Bismarck Tribune was published in
July.

Most new western towns built around the
advancing railroad attracted bawdy houses
and lawless drifters, and early Bismarck was
no exception. "Colonel" Lounsberry, who
kept his old Civil War rank, as was the fashion
at the time, hoped to establish order through
editorial. Lounsberry asked for a "vigilance
committee" to respond to town troublemakers.
Dance-hall proprietors Dave Mullen and
Jack O'Neil perceived this as a threat. Heavily
armed, they confronted Lounsberry at the Tribune
office. In characteristic words of the
"fighting editor" common to the western
frontier, Lounsberry claimed he challenged
them to go ahead and shoot, boasting that he
had "heard bullets fly before." The saloon
owners demurred, however, and merely asked
him to refrain from issuing attacks in their
direction.

The Tribune began publishing daily in 1881.
Always a relatively small daily (1996 circulation
was 31,161), it nevertheless became nationally
known for its coverage of two events.
In 1937 it received a Pulitzer Prize for its series
"Self-Help in the Dust Bowl," aimed at farmers
battling the droughts of the 1930s. Better
known, however, is its renown as the first
newspaper to break the story of "Custer's Last
Stand." Gen. George Armstrong Custer left for
his last battle from Fort Abraham Lincoln,
near Bismarck. Lounsberry sent along reporter
Mark Kellogg. Kellogg became one of
the casualties of the famous June 25, 1876, battle.
His bloodstained notes found their way
back to Bismarck, where Lounsberry hogged
the town's single telegraph line for twenty-two
hours to transmit the story as sometime correspondent
for the New York Tribune. The
eastern editors at first did not believe him,
however, and held the story long enough for
Lounsberry's own paper to get the scoop.

Lounsberry remained publisher until 1884,
when he sold the paper to Marshall Jewell,
who had been job shop manager. While still a
relatively small daily by national standards,
the Tribune has traditionally distributed over
a vast geographical area in a sparsely populated
state. By a 1960s comparison, the Tribune
still counted a geographic circulation twice
that of newspapers in similarly sized eastern
cities. Because the Bismarck paper reached so
far, however, distribution costs were also three
times higher.

In the first quarter of the twentieth century
the Tribune faced competition from five other
newspapers publishing from the state capital.
Even in 1930 its circulation was only 6,000,
compared to 11,000 claimed by the German-language
weekly Der Staats-Anzeiger. By 1970,
however, the Tribune claimed 17,086 subscribers
and the German-language paper only
989. Today the Tribune is the third largest daily
in the state after the Grand Forks Herald and
Fargo-Moorhead Forum. It is owned by Lee
Enterprises.


 

Ross F. Collins
North Dakota State University



Lounsberry, Clement A. North Dakota: History and People.
Chicago: S. J. Clarke Publishing Company, 1917. Robinson,
Elwyn. History of North Dakota. Fargo: Institute for
Regional Studies, North Dakota State University, 1995.
Schmidt, Paul C. "The Press in North Dakota." North Dakota History 31 (1964): 216–22.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>