<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.gen.033</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Saskatchewan Women Grain Growers</field>
      <field name="author">Smith, David E.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SASKATCHEWAN WOMEN GRAIN GROWERS

Founded in 1913, the Women's Section of the
Saskatchewan Grain Growers Association
played a major role in the advancement of
such causes as women's suffrage, public health
and medical care, prohibition, the Canadianization
of the immigrant, and the propagation
of the cooperative ideal. Although born of the
Saskatchewan Grain Growers Association, the
Prairies' pioneer agrarian organization, with
origins that preceded the creation of Saskatchewan
(1905), the Women Grain Growers was
not its auxiliary. Viewing themselves as both
farm women and farmers, the leaders of the
Women Grain Growers–most prominent
among them Violet McNaughton, Francis
Beynon, and Zoa Haight–claimed, and received,
full constitutional status with the parent
body as well as the right to form their own
locals and meet separately if they so desired.
Three of their members were also guaranteed
seats on the board of directors of the Saskatchewan
Grain Growers Association.

By 1919 there were 6,000 women members
in the Women Grain Growers and in the locals
of the Saskatchewan Grain Growers Association;
that is, approximately one in six of
the total membership. The Saskatchewan
Women Grain Growers became the model on
which women's sections of the United Farmers
of Alberta, Manitoba, and Ontario was
patterned.

Full participation by women in the affairs
of the Saskatchewan Grain Growers Association
and the Women's Section preceded by six
and eight years, respectively, the first exercise
of the right to vote by women in provincial
and federal politics. As such, any study of
women and politics in Canada must give
prominence to these agrarian organizations.

Leaders of the Saskatchewan Women Grain
Growers played an influential role in the move
of traditional farmers to the political left, as
witnessed by the introduction of the Wheat
Pool in 1924 and the amalgamation of the
Saskatchewan Grain Growers Association and
the more radical Farmers Union of Canada in
1926. A separate women's section of the new
United Farmers of Canada–Saskatchewan
Section disappeared after 1930, when that organization
experimented–more faithfully on
paper than in practice–with an early form of
affirmative action.


David E. Smith
University of Saskatchewan




Marchildon, Randolph George. "Improving the Quality of
Rural Life in Saskatchewan: Some Activities of the Women's
Section of the Saskatchewan Grain Growers, 1913–
1920." In Building Beyond the Homestead: Rural History of the Prairies, edited by David C. Jones and Ian MacPherson.
Calgary: University of Calgary Press, 1985: 89–109.
Taylor, Georgina M. "'Ground for Common Action': Violet
McNaughton's Agrarian Feminism and the Origins of
the Farm Women's Movement in Canada." Ph.D. diss.,
Carleton University, 1997.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>