<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pd.038</field>
      <field name="titleMain">National Farmers Union</field>
      <field name="author">Field, Bruce E.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




NATIONAL FARMERS UNION

The National Farmers Union (officially the
Farmers Educational and Cooperative Union
of America) originated in Point, Texas, in
1902. Farmers Union members saw themselves
as continuing earlier efforts by the Farmers
Alliance, the Populist Party, and the greenback
and free silver movements to minimize the
power of monopolies and enhance opportunities
for small family farmers to achieve social
and economic equality in the United
States. The organization spread throughout
various regions of the nation, but by the end
of World War II was most firmly established in
the Great Plains, with its most active affiliates
in Nebraska, Kansas, Oklahoma, Montana,
and the Dakotas.

The Farmers Union has consistently argued
that U.S. government policies often contribute
to an unholy alliance between big business
and government, which leads to corporate
domination of U.S. society. It has opposed
protective tariffs as favoring large business enterprises
and, in the field of agriculture, has
criticized the American Farm Bureau Federation
as an arm of the National Association of
Manufacturers. The Farmers Union's rejection
of a survival of the fittest approach to
economic life led it to support the 1949 Brannan
Plan calling for agricultural prices to seek
their own levels in the marketplace while allowing
government supports for smaller producers
when prices fell below what was considered
a fair return. The Farmers Union's
concern for equity also led the organization to
cooperate closely with organized labor, particularly
in its opposition to the 1947 Taft-Hartley Act and its support for the 1946 Full
Employment Act.

More than any other general farm organization,
the Farmers Union paid particularly
close attention to links between domestic and
foreign policy, and it especially criticized U.S.
policies abroad in the early years of the cold
war. The Union claimed that the actions of
the Truman administration, particularly the
Marshall Plan to revitalize postwar Europe,
contributed to the decline of the small family
farmer by helping generate what it termed artificial
scarcity at home. The Farmers Union
hoped that the United States would move toward
a foreign policy stressing, as it believed
President Roosevelt had, international cooperation
over military and economic competition.
The Union's position on U.S. foreign
policy generated accusations that the organization
sympathized with communists, and
the State Department and the House Un-American Activities Committee both kept a
close watch on the activities of various Farmers
Union spokesmen. Such scrutiny during
the height of McCarthyism led to occasional
rifts between the national organization and its
various state and regional affiliates, a few of
which, because of their exceptionally vocal
criticism of U.S. policy, were eventually expelled
from the Farmers Union.

Despite its outspoken views and its occasionally
raucous history, the National Farmers
Union still exists. With headquarters in both
Washington dc and Denver, Colorado, an announced
membership of 300,000 farm and
ranch families, and a Web site, the Farmers
Union still promotes the contributions rural
America can make to a healthy U.S. society.


Bruce E. Field
Northern Illnois University




Field, Bruce E. Harvest of Dissent: The National Farmers
Union and the Early Cold War. Lawrence: University Press
of Kansas, 1998. Flamm, Michael W. "The National Farmers
Union and the Evolution of Agrarian Liberalism, 1937–1946."
Agricultural History 68 (1994): 54–80. Pratt, William
C. "The Farmers Union, McCarthyism, and the Demise
of the Agrarian Left." Historian 58 (1996): 329–42.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>