<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.sr.026</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Hall of Fame Museums</field>
      <field name="author">Danilov, Victor J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




HALL OF FAME MUSEUMS

There are almost forty major Halls of Fame in
the Great Plains region, with the greatest
number in Texas (nine), Oklahoma and Kansas
(six each), and Colorado (five). There are
three in the Plains region of Canada.

Many of these Halls of Fame are museums,
such as the National Softball Hall of Fame and
Museum in Oklahoma City; the Pro Rodeo
Hall of Fame and the Museum of the American
Cowboy in Colorado Springs; the National
Motorcycle Museum and Hall of Fame
in Sturgis, South Dakota; and the Olympic
Hall of Fame and Museum in Calgary, Alberta.
Some of the Halls of Fame are museums
by other names, such as the National Cowboy
Hall of Fame and Western Heritage Museum
in Oklahoma City; the National Agricultural
Center and Hall of Fame in Bonner Springs,
Kansas; and the wonderfully titled Gallery of
Also Rans in Norton, Kansas.

A number of Halls of Fame are only part of
larger museums, including the Roller Skating
Hall of Fame in the National Museum of Roller
Skating in Lincoln, Nebraska; the International
Space Hall of Fame in the Space Center
in Alamogordo, New Mexico; the Petroleum
Hall of Fame in the Permian Basin Petroleum
Museum, Library, and Hall of Fame in Midland,
Texas; and Canada's Aviation Hall of
Fame in the Reynolds-Alberta Museum in
Wetaskiwin, Alberta.

Sometimes Halls of Fame are housed in
other types of facilities. For example, the
North Dakota Sports Hall of Fame is in the
Jamestown Civic Center; the United States
Racquetball Hall of Fame is in the United
States Racquetball Association headquarters in
Colorado Springs; the National Baseball Congress
Hall of Fame is in Lawrence-Dumont
Stadium in Wichita, Kansas; and the National
Fish Culture Hall of Fame is in the D. C. Booth
Historic Fish Hatchery in Spearfish, South
Dakota.

Halls of Fame take many forms. The National
Hall of Fame for Famous American Indians
in Anadarko, Oklahoma, is primarily an
outdoor sculpture garden; the West Texas
Walk of Fame is on a sidewalk outside the
Lubbock Memorial Civic Center in Texas; and
the Denver Broncos' Ring of Fame is displayed
along the facade of Mile High Stadium. Hall of
Fame facilities range from a few hundred feet,
such as the 325-square-foot National Fish Culture
Hall of Fame, to several hundred thousand
feet, such as the 220,000-square-foot National
Cowboy Hall of Fame and Western
Heritage Museum in Oklahoma City.

Most often, Halls of Fame are started by
individuals or groups of people interested in
the subject matter. They want to honor outstanding
achievement, encourage the activity,
and promote the area. Others are initiated by
sports clubs, professional associations, or governmental
bodies. Hall of fame inductees–which
run from a handful to thousands–usually
are honored with plaques, biographical
information, photographs, and displays of
memorabilia and artifacts. Some exhibits also
make use of interactive displays and slide,
film, and video presentations.

Many Halls of Fame are visited by only a few
thousand people a year, but some are extremely
popular, attracting large crowds.
These include the National Cowboy Hall of
Fame and Western Heritage Museum, which
has an annual attendance of 300,000, and the
International Space Hall of Fame at the Space
Center, which attracts about 200,000 visitors
each year.

See also EDUCATION: Museums.


Victor J. Danilov
University of Colorado-Boulder




Danilov, Victor J. Hall of Fame Museums: A Reference
Guide. Westport CT: Greenwood Press, 1997.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>