<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ag.025</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Custom Combining</field>
      <field name="author">Isern, Thomas D.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CUSTOM COMBINING

Custom combining, the harvesting of grain
crops by itinerant combine crews, not only
plays an important role in production on the
Plains but also is the basis for a distinctive
style of life rooted in the family business.

Prior to the advent of the combined harvester,
or combine, small grains on the Plains
were harvested with binders or headers and
then threshed with stationary separators powered
by steam or gas traction engines. Labor
was a mix of migrant, local, and family
sources. Farmers owned the harvest machinery;
custom operators owned the threshing
machinery. Combines were first used in the
winter wheat areas of the Central Plains in the
1920s and, with windrowers as complements,
were adopted in the spring wheat areas of the
Northern Plains and Prairie Provinces some
twenty years later. Farmers generally owned
their own combines, and the flow of migrant
labor diminished.

The shortage of labor and machinery during
World War II, coupled with the wartime
resurgence of wheat production, precipitated
custom combining, as harvesters took to the
roads on itineraries stretching from Texas to
Saskatchewan. Perhaps 500 machines were in
itinerant operation in 1942, and in 1947 researchers
documented more than 8,000 in
Kansas. The most dramatic episode of the war
era was the Massey-Harris Self-propelled Harvest
Brigade of 1944, when Massey-Harris of
Toronto received a special allocation of steel to
put 500 additional custom combines into the
field.

The 1947 film Wild Harvest, starring Alan
Ladd, Robert Preston, and Dorothy Lamour,
depicted custom harvesters as a wild bunch,
and indeed, the early years were marked by
men traveling without families. The business
persisted, however, and underwent a transformation
into a stable, family-oriented enterprise.
Custom combining survived for two
reasons, the first being that it was a sound,
economical adaptation of practice in regional
agriculture. It freed farmers of the necessity
of capital investment in combines and allowed
maximum use of these valuable machines.
The second reason was that, like farming,
custom combining became a family tradition,
with outfits and routes passed down through
the generations.

Custom combiners operate along defined
routes harvesting mainly for the same farmers
year after year. They charge for their work
by the acre, with additional charges for high
yields and bushel charges for hauling. Families
and crews are housed in trailer homes. An
important change in operations took place
beginning in the 1960s with the advent of irrigated
feed grains, corn, and milo on the
Southern Plains. This encouraged most custom
operators to curtail the northern ends of
their itineraries and take on lucrative fall harvesting
on the Southern and Central Plains.

A major study of custom combining in 1971
found 3,431 outfits transporting 7,551 combines,
but numbers have decreased slowly
since then. In particular, the international aspect
of the business has diminished. Combine
crews were allowed to cross the boundary between
the United States and Canada under an
executive agreement of 1942 and annual renewals
thereof, but fewer than seventy do
so today. An organization of American operators
called U.S. Custom Harvesters, formed in
1983, has opposed Canadian crews operating
in the United States. The Association of Canadian
Custom Harvesters, formed the same
year, has defended the Canadians' right to
work there.

The greatest number of custom combiners
comes from the Southern and Central Plains—
over the years some 30 percent from Kansas,
30 percent from Oklahoma, and 10 percent
from Texas. Prominent among them are Mennonite
operators from central Kansas, who entered
custom harvesting as a strategy for extending
their agricultural way of life.


Thomas D. Isern
North Dakota State University




Isern, Thomas D. Custom Harvesting on the Great Plains: A
History. Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1981.
Lagrone, William F., and Earle E. Gavett. Interstate Custom
Combining in the Great Plains in 1971. Washington DC:
Economic Research Service, U.S. Department of Agriculture,
1975.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>