<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fol.022</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Grave Markers</field>
      <field name="author">Brown, John Gary</field>
      <field name="text">

 




GRAVE MARKERS


Portion of the Davis Memorial in Hiawatha, Kansas


In Wyuka Cemetery in Lincoln, Nebraska, an
aircraft pioneer is buried beneath the smashed
propeller of his plane. Nearby, in Nebraska
City, a prominent insurance salesman rests
next to a life-sized replica of his rolltop desk,
and the founder of Arbor Day, J. Sterling Morton,
is remembered by an exquisite twelvefoot
limestone tree. A Garden City, Kansas,
boy who loved his car is buried under the actual
engine, and his name appears on the valve
cover. Another Kansan, from Attica, used his
tombstone to rail against the evils of the Democratic
Party. In the small town of Hiawatha a
husband and wife are depicted at every stage
of their lives together in an enormous ensemble
of statuary that cost a fortune during
the Great Depression. A young man from
Tulsa, Oklahoma, poses on his motorcycle,
and an inscription below the porcelain photograph
says simply, "I'd rather be drag racing."
A traveling salesman from Lincoln, Kansas,
is symbolized by a sculpted suitcase and the
misspelled inscription, "Here is where he
stoped last."

Grave markers are erected for the departed,
but it is the living who are truly served by
these monuments. Ritual burial of the dead
and the marking of this passage are defining
phenomena for virtually all of civilization.
The humble tombstone provides a venue for
the listing of cultural and spiritual values, and
a chance for individuals or groups to record
their grief and voice their hope. In many cases
they also provide humanity with a welcome
excuse for artistic expression. In the Great
Plains, skillful and passionate people have left
such distinctive monuments in the cemeteries
that dot the landscape from Texas to Canada.

Although professional sculpture from Europe
was sometimes imported by grieving
families, most grave markers in the Great
Plains were made by vernacular artisans working
with local materials. Those in wagon trains
and in fly-by-night mining camps carved
markers quickly from wood. Immigrant Spanish
stonecutters created decorative Catholic
crosses, while their northern European counterparts
imitated the illustrated tablets of England.
Germans who had lost the sponsorship
of Catherine the Great emigrated from Russia
and erected iron crosses much like those in the
Old Country, but in western Kansas many of
these were produced using plumbing pipe and
other utilitarian provisions. Epitaphs were
brought from the British Isles and gradually
infused with an American flavor, providing
the visitor with a poetic glimpse of the deceased's
character, or at least the sensibilities of
those who had loved him. Italian immigrants
brought a tradition of statuary with them,
contributing angels and portraiture, executed
in the round. Poorer enclaves and subcultures
with no tradition of sophisticated sculpture
would resort to concrete and other mixed media,
but all of these efforts would shine with
creativity compared to the cookie-cutter granite
stones that emerged later in the twentieth
century.

As might be expected, small town and rural
cemeteries bristled with orthodox religious
symbolism and Gothic gingerbread. Stones
featured the anchor, a symbol of hope, fingers
that pointed to heaven, and the weeping willow
tree, which, like the Christian church,
flourished in every part of the world. Jewish
stones abounded with graven images, including
the hands of benediction that identifies
the Kohanim, the traditional priests of Israel,
the lion of Judah, and the cup of the Levites.
Later, urban mausoleums sported Egyptian
Revival motifs or Art Deco designs. Generic
symbols for death, such as the spilled flowerpot,
the broken urn, and the inverted torch,
appeared as society moved to a more secular
view of life. Firemen, policemen, and fraternal
organizations set up umbrella monuments to
preside over their casualties. The Woodsmen
of the World sold insurance policies to thousands
of frontier families and erected grave
markers in the form of tree stumps or stacked
logs with individual names, resembling God's
cord wood for the final blaze of judgment.
Rows of lambs pointed out the frightful attrition
that faced children on the frontier. Young
women died in childbirth and were remembered
by low-relief roses carved in limestone.

In the mid–twentieth century, cemeteries
began to imitate the tract housing of the suburbs,
and identical stones made of granite became
almost universal. Soon these vertical
markers would be laid flat so that lawn mowers
could more easily be used. The cemetery
became more a business and less a community
institution. Finally, tombstones would be
eliminated altogether, replaced by plaques and
subterranean receptacles for the temporary
use of flowers.

Happily, Americans have risen up against
this unnatural anonymity. Images on markers
are again attempting to portray the individual
person, and porcelain photographs have reappeared.
In the Great Plains it is now not unusual
to see a farmer's grave marker that features
his tractor, or some manifestation of the
land itself. Outstanding older monuments are
finally being sporadically sheltered and preserved.
The grave marker is an important way
for us to tell the next generation who we were
and to help preserve our collective cultural
identity.

See also ARCHITECHTURE: Cemeteries.


John Gary Brown
Lawrence, Kansas




Ariés, Phillippe. The Hour of Our Death. New York: Alfred
A. Knopf, Inc. 1981. Jackson, Kenneth T., and Camillo J.
Vergara. Silent Cities: The Evolution of the American Cemetery.
New York: Princeton Architectural Press, 1989. Marion,
John Francis. Famous and Curious Cemeteries: A Pictorial, Historical, and Anecdotal View of American and European Cemeteries and the Famous and Infamous People Who Are Buried There. New York: Crown Publishers, Inc.,
1977.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>