<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.rel.006</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Bland, Salem (1859-1950)</field>
      <field name="author">Allen, Richard</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BLAND, SALEM (1859-1950)

Born August 26, 1859, in Lachute, Quebec, and
educated in that province, Salem Goldworth
Bland moved to Winnipeg, Manitoba, in 1903
to teach New Testament and church history at
Wesley College after twenty years as a popular
Methodist minister in eastern Ontario and
Quebec. Over the next sixteen years he had a
remarkable impact across the Prairie Provinces,
where he was in great demand as a
preacher of uncommon eloquence and as a
popularizer of liberal theology and the Social
Gospel. Well-read in secular as in theological
matters, he was at once a proponent of German
historical critics of the Bible like Adolf
Harnack and of reform Darwinists like Henry
Drummond and Benjamin Kidd. He became
increasingly radical as a result of his association
with agrarian, labor, and social reform
activists. His outspokenness about the exploitation
of Prairie farmers by the grain trade
and of Winnipeg newcomers by employers
and landlords who were often active churchmen
led to a falling out with wealthy laymen
who had at first welcomed him.

Invited to address the convention of the
Saskatchewan Grain Growers Association in
1913, he sparked an abortive move toward
third-party politics. His dismissal from Wesley
College in 1917 on grounds of financial restraint
was an academic freedom cause celebre
across the West. For a time he was a columnist
for the Grain Growers Guide and a lecturer on
the Chautauqua circuit. He was courted to
run in the wartime election of 1917 but deferred
to a returned soldier, Major G. W. Andrews,
thus signaling the high hopes he held
for a major social and political reconstruction
after the war under the inspiration of returning
soldiers. He would express this view in a
small but wide-ranging and controversial
book, The New Christianity (1920). Thought
by some to be one of the instigators of the
Winnipeg General Strike of mid-1919, he had
by that time moved to a Toronto pastorate and
would soon begin a twenty-year career as a
regular columnist for the Toronto Daily Star
under the byline of "The Observer." He died
in Toronto on February 6, 1950.

See also PROTEST AND DISSENT: Grain Growers Associations.


Richard Allen
Hamilton, Ontario




Allen, Richard. "Salem Bland and the Spirituality of the
Social Gospel: Winnipeg and the West, 1903–1913." In
Prairie Spirit: Perspectives on the Heritage of the United
Church of Canada in the West, edited by Dennis L. Butcher,
Catherine Macdonald, Margaret McPherson, Raymond
Smith, and A. McKibbon Watts. Winnipeg: University of
Manitoba Press, 1985: 217–32. Allen, Richard. The Social
Passion: Religion and Social Reform in Canada. Toronto:
University of Toronto Press, 1971.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>