<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.na.079</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Otoe-Missourias</field>
      <field name="author">Wishart, David J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




OTOE-MISSOURIAS

The Otoe-Missourias were two separate peoples
until they amalgamated in the last years of the
eighteenth century. Members of the Chiwere
group of Siouan speakers, they were driven
westward from the Great Lakes region in the
seventeenth century by the Sioux, who were also
moving westward under pressure emanating
from the expanding orbit of European colonization.
By 1714 the Otoes were living in a village
on the Salt Creek tributary of the Platte River
in what is now eastern Nebraska. They occupied
that vicinity for the remainder of
the eighteenth century. The Missourias joined
them there in 1798 after the Sauks and Foxes
had driven them out of their former homeland
of present-day northwest Missouri. From
that time on the Otoe-Missourias were one
nation, though the Missourias remained a distinctive
constituent throughout the nineteenth
century.

They lived, like the neighboring Pawnees
and Omahas, in earth lodge villages and divided
their subsistence activities between intensive
farming at the villages, biannual bison
hunts out on the Plains, and a wide array of
food collection. They calibrated their annual
cycle closely to the signs and rhythms of the
physical environment, and they sanctified
their activities with ceremonies that enlisted
the support of sacred powers. Their way of life
worked because they spread their subsistence
base over a broad spectrum of Plains resources,
and in 1800 they sustained a population
of more than 1,000 people.

But the outside world crowded in, and with
the fur traders, missionaries, Indian agents,
and settlers came disease and resource depletion.
By 1804, when Lewis and Clark passed
by, the Otoe-Missouria population had been
reduced by smallpox to fewer than 800; subsequent
epidemics and depletion of game,
bringing famine, continued the downward
plunge to 600 by midcentury. Fur traders established
a post at Bellevue in the 1820s, just to
the east of the Otoe-Missouria village, and alcohol
became a disruptive force in their society.
Enmities that otherwise might have
been settled peacefully erupted into violence.
Head chief Big Kaw could not preserve unity,
and by the 1840s the Otoe-Missourias had
splintered into four separate villages.

Mired in poverty, and with starvation a
constant companion, they were forced to sell
their only resource, their land, merely to survive.
The United States obliged, as it needed
land on which to settle refugee Indians from
the eastern United States in the 1830s and
homes for settlers after 1854. The first sale
came in 1830 when, at the Treaty of Prairie du
Chien, the Otoe-Missourias surrendered their
claims to any lands east of the Missouri and
also sold a sliver of land in southeastern Nebraska
(the Nemaha Half-Breed Reservation)
for the resettlement there of mixed-bloods
from various tribes. A cession of about one
million acres in southeastern Nebraska followed
in 1833. The Otoe-Missourias received
4.1 cents an acre for this prime agricultural
land. As with subsequent payments for cessions,
the money was used by the United
States to provide annuities (blankets, farming
equipment, and other items) and to finance its
assimilation policy, which aimed to transform
communal Indians into self-supporting farmers
working on separate 160-acre allotments.
Even in 1881, when the Otoe-Missourias abandoned
Nebraska for Indian Territory, very
few, if any, of their men were farming.

When the Kansas-Nebraska Act of May 30,
1854, opened Nebraska for settlement by European
Americans, the Otoe-Missourias sold
their remaining homeland for 42.6 cents an
acre, retaining only a 162,000-acre reservation
straddling the Kansas-Nebraska boundary.
This was fertile country, and it soon became
clear that, as surrounding population pressure
mounted and land values escalated, the Otoe-
Missourias would have difficulty retaining it.
They lived there, poorly but still defiantly traditional,
for twenty-five years. Their agents
were generally corrupt until Quakers took over
in 1869. Under great pressure to change, and
with the old ways increasingly unfeasible, their
society cleaved into two opposing segments:
one, called the "stable faction" by the Quakers,
paid at least lip service to the assimilation policy;
the other, the "wild party," led by traditional
chiefs Medicine Horse and Ar-ka-ke-ta,
remained steadfastly traditional. When the
Otoe-Missourias migrated to Oklahoma Territory,
following the sale of their reservation in
two parts in 1876 and 1881, the division persisted
and was not healed until after 1890.

In Indian Territory, the Otoe-Missourias
settled on a 129,113-acre reservation in what is
now Noble County, Oklahoma. Their population
continued to plummet, dropping to 340
in 1894. Thereafter, their numbers gradually
rebounded to reach 1,550 by 1990. Their reservation
was completely allotted in 1907, but
when oil was discovered on their lands in 1912,
the trust status of their allotments was abrogated,
and fully 90 percent of their land base
was lost.

The Otoe-Missourias continued to resist the
United States' efforts to reshape them. They refused
to set up a constitutional government.
which would have abolished their traditional
tribal government.until 1984, and they have
used their resources to buy back some of their
lost lands. In the late 1940s, like most other
Plains tribes, they lodged their claims with
the Indian Claims Commission, and in 1955
and 1964 received awards of $1,156,035 and
$1,750,000 for lands that had been taken in
1830, 1833, and 1854 for payments "so low as to
shock the conscience." These awards, large at
first sight, diminished to small sums when allocated
to individuals. Still, it is remarkable–
in fact a triumph–that this small nation, despite
the loss of their homeland and the assault
on their way of life, has endured into the
twenty-first century. Their annual powwow,
held in July, and their continued coherence
around kinship groups, ceremonies, and social
gatherings, ensure the continuance of their
tribal identity.


David J. Wishart
University of Nebraska-Lincoln



Chapman, Berlin Basil. The Otoes and Missourias: A Study
of Indian Removal and the Legal Aftermath. Oklahoma
City: Times Journal Publishing Co., 1965. Edmunds, R.
David. The Otoe-Missouria People. Phoenix: Indian Tribal
Series, 1976. Wishart, David J. An Unspeakable Sadness:
The Dispossession of the Nebraska Indians. Lincoln: University
of Nebraska Press, 1994.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>