<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.mus.048</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Vee, Bobby (b. 1943)</field>
      <field name="author">Lindquist, John Arthur</field>
      <field name="text">

 




Bobby Vee



VEE, BOBBY (b. 1943)

Born Robert Thomas Velline on April 30, 1943,
in Fargo, North Dakota, Bobby Vee became
one of the more enduring popular musicians
of the mid– to late twentieth century. After
gaining entrance into his older brother's
combo because he knew the lyrics to the popular
songs of the day, Vee got his first major
exposure on the night of February 3, 1959, in
Moorhead, Minnesota, as one of the acts filling
in for Buddy Holly, Richie Valens, and the
Big Bopper, J. P. Richardson, who had died
that morning in a plane crash near Clear Lake,
Iowa. The success throughout the Northern
Plains and upper Midwest of his self-penned
and Holly-inspired "Susie Baby" led to his
signing with Los Angeles–based Liberty Records
in the fall of 1959. He achieved international
fame singing about the joys and angst of
teenage life and young adulthood on "Devil or
Angel," "Rubber Ball," "Take Good Care of My
Baby" (which stayed at number one on the
Billboard charts for three weeks in September
1961), "Run to Him," "The Night Has a Thousand
Eyes," "Come Back When You Grow Up,"
and dozens of other songs released on singles
and albums throughout the 1960s. In 1967 Vee
starred in the movie C'mon, Let's Live a Little,
in which he portrayed a rural folksinger adjusting
to college life.

Vee still plays to sold-out audiences throughout
Europe and North America. His high energy,
positively oriented stage show includes
his three sons, who also perform independently
as a rockabilly act called the Vees. At his
studio located near St. Cloud, Minnesota, Vee
continues to record and release songs, old and
new, on his Rockhouse label, including novel
arrangements and compositions that reveal a
diverse and occasionally avant-garde musical
intellect.


John Arthur Lindquist
University of Wisconsin-Madison




Nite, Norm N. Rock On: The Illustrated Encyclopedia of Rock N' Roll. New York: Thomas Y. Crowell Company,
1974. Rees, Dafydd, and Luke Crampton. DK Encyclopedia
of Rock Stars. New York: DK Publishing, 1996.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>