<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.054</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Oral Traditions</field>
      <field name="author">Sommer, Barbara W.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ORAL TRADITIONS

Oral traditions are a body of unwritten information
and messages preserved in memory and
repeated through succeeding generations. In the
Great Plains, this information was originally
held by Native Americans. Oral traditions have
preserved much of the early history of the
Plains. Statements repeated from generation
to generation, often combining lore and fact,
retained information about human migrations,
conflicts among peoples, and changes in
societal patterns during the period that preceded
European contact. Information and
lore, sometimes contained in stories with
moral messages, were preserved about specific
places and geographical landmarks. The repeated
telling of this material, both for entertainment
and the maintenance of community
identity, preserved the knowledge.

European American migration to the Plains
brought people who, though they carried with
them their own set of oral traditions, often did
not understand the importance of Native
American oral traditions. Although much traditional
knowledge was lost, some survived in
oral form or became part of the written history
of the area. For example, in 1930 Nebraska
poet John G. Neihardt traveled to the Pine
Ridge Agency in South Dakota to interview
Oglala Lakota holy man Black Elk. The resulting
book, Black Elk Speaks, though shaped
and written by Neihardt, is an important and
revered repository of Lakota belief and history
from about 1850 to 1890.

Mari Sandoz drew on stories she had heard
as a child from Native American visitors to her
family's remote ranch in the Sand Hills of Nebraska
when she wrote Crazy Horse and other
books about Native Americans. Authors such
as Gerald Vizenor and N. Scott Momaday rely
on the oral tradition while working to identify
its role in modern literature. Most recent poetry,
fiction, and history of Native Americans
on the Plains contains information drawn
from oral traditions.

Oral history–as opposed to oral traditions
–began in the late 1930s with the advent of
modern technology and the availability of recording
equipment. Although oral history is
the collection of first-hand information from a
person, its collection techniques, including the
use of a tape recorder and a trained interviewer,
have been adapted for use in documenting
oral traditions. Interviews with
Native Americans in collections held at institutions
such as the University of Oklahoma and
the University of South Dakota are examples.

Information based on or drawn from oral
sources has grown with each succeeding movement
of people into the Plains. Stories about
the Oregon Trail, the Pony Express, contact between
Native Americans and European Americans,
pioneer settlement, cattle drives, and
professions such as store keeping, soldiering,
and teaching, among many others, have become
part of the Plains oral tradition and are
preserved in universities, historical societies,
and local archives. Oral traditions continue to
provide insight into the history of the Great
Plains and the changes that have occurred
throughout the years. Documented and defined
by modern research methods, as in Ian
Frazier's Great Plains, they help provide a
unique source of information that extends beyond
the written record, retaining the words
and stories of and about people and places that
might otherwise have been lost.

See also FOLKWAYS: Plains Indian Narratives.


Barbara W. Sommer
BWS Associates




Blaeser, Kimberly M. Gerald Vizenor: Writing in the Oral Tradition. Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1996.
Vansina, Jan. Oral Tradition as History. Madison: University
of Wisconsin Press, 1985.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>