<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ind.047</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Petroleum, United States</field>
      <field name="author">Paxton, Stanley T.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




PETROLEUM, UNITED STATES


Bartlesville, Oklahoma


Within a year of completing the first successful
crude-oil well in northwestern Pennsylvania
in 1859, opportunists from eastern states
were drilling for oil in the Great Plains. Using
tools and techniques honed in the central Appalachian
area, some of these early oil seekers
focused their efforts on natural seeps that occurred
near the town of Paola in east-central
Kansas. Though early wells were unsuccessful,
persistence paid off, and in 1893 there was a
promising oil discovery near Neodesha, Kansas,
that would grow into one of the first commercial
oil fields of the Great Plains. Realizing
the petroleum potential of the Neodesha area,
Standard Oil Company opened a refinery
there in 1902 to process the crude oil. This
early refinery, though clearly significant to
local economic development, was also symbolically
important to the region. The refinery
sent a strong signal to prospectors that oil had
the potential to become one of the economic
foundations of the Southern Great Plains.

Oil and gas fields are volumetrically significant
accumulations of hydrocarbon that have
pooled naturally in the crust of the earth. The
geographic position of these accumulations
beneath the U.S. and Canadian Great Plains is
due to a coincidence of a number of geologic
factors. Among these are a hydrocarbon
source rock (usually a shale from which the
liquid is initially derived) and a reservoir to
house the oil (usually a porous sandstone or
limestone layer). Another important factor is a
migration pathway for the hydrocarbon to
move from the source rock to the subsurface
reservoir rock. If one of these factors is absent
or incompletely developed, an oil field will not
form. Consequently, the present-day distribution
of commercial oil and gas fields in the
Great Plains is a reflection of where the coincidence
of these factors has been most favorable.

Hydrocarbon source rocks are a case in
point. The hydrocarbon source rocks present
beneath the Great Plains are a reflection of the
configurations of at least two ancient inland
seaways that extended throughout the Plains
and Rocky Mountain regions of North America.
Thick intervals of organic-rich mud settled
to the bottom of these ancient seaways.
Deep burial of this mud within the crust of the
earth helped to transform the mud into shales
with potent oil- and gas-generating potential.
At just the right combinations of temperature
and pressure and at different locations
throughout the Great Plains, oil was released
from these source rocks. Geologic conditions
in the Southern Great Plains were especially
conducive to the accumulation of hydrocarbons.
Consequently, due to differences in geology,
discovery dates of commercial quantities
of oil differed greatly from state to state.

The earliest commercial oil operation in the
Great Plains was the Florence field in Colorado.
Though oil was discovered at this site in
1862, it was not until the 1880s that both consumer
demand and infrastructure were adequate
for Florence to become a commercial oil
field. Then, following the Neodesha, Kansas,
success of 1893, exploratory wells were tapped
in surrounding counties in Kansas and Oklahoma.
The completion of the Nellie Johnstone
No. 1 well in 1897, situated east of the
newly founded city of Bartlesville, Indian Territory,
marked the first commercial oil well in
present-day Oklahoma. Oil production from
the Oklahoma Indian Territory o.cially began
in 1901. By the time Oklahoma achieved
statehood in 1907, the Southern Great Plains
was well on its way to becoming recognized as
a major petroleum province.

The Northern Great Plains was not to be
outdone. At about the same time that the mid-continent
area (North Texas, Oklahoma, and
Kansas) was coming into its own, a significant
volume of oil was also being produced at Salt
Creek field, Wyoming's first major Plains oil
field. Natural surface seepages had been noted
as early as 1889, and the field became commercially
viable in about 1908.

Back in the Southern Great Plains, a North
Texas oil boom commenced with discovery of
the Electra field in 1911, located to the west of
Wichita Falls, Texas. This was followed by numerous
other large oil field discoveries between
1911 and 1920 in North Texas, Oklahoma,
and Kansas. Many of these oil field
discoveries resulted in the rapid development
of new town sites or the growth of existing
nearby town sites. New oil fields in Texas included
Ranger, Breckenridge, Burkburnette,
and Northwest Burkburnette. New Oklahoma
fields were Cushing, Healdton, Garber, Hewitt,
and Burbank. The most impressive new
fields in Kansas were Augusta and El Dorado.
During this period of rapid oil field discoveries,
the Midcontinent was producing 30 percent
of the total U.S. crude oil. This total had
grown to 56 percent by 1920. In response to
these exploration successes, a new pattern of
railroad and pipeline transportation systems
emerged to support the production, refining,
and distribution of crude oil within the
Southern Great Plains and to areas located
outside of the Great Plains. By 1920, according
to the Oklahoma Geological Survey, Oklahoma's
crude oil was being processed in about
seventy refineries in Oklahoma and surrounding
states.

Despite these successes, the consumption of
petroleum products after World War I had increased
so dramatically that the production
and distribution capacity was strained beyond
limits. Refiners were unable to obtain adequate
supplies of crude oil, and some gasoline stations
had to close shop for days at a time. On
the heels of this demand for crude oil, Charles
N. Gould, former Oklahoma state geologist,
discovered one of the world's largest oil and
gas districts in the Texas and Oklahoma panhandles–
the Panhandle field–in 1920.

The Permian Basin, stretching across West
Texas and southeastern New Mexico, was beginning
to yield crude oil in this period as
well. The first commercial oil well in the Permian
Basin, completed in about 1921, was located
in Mitchell County, Texas. An oil rush in
the Permian Basin began with the completion
of the Santa Rita No. 1 well in 1923. This well
was located on land granted to the University
of Texas in an agreement dating to 1883. The
success of the Permian Basin contributed to
the growth of the Midland-Odessa area of
West Texas, located very near the geographic
center of the basin. In 1924 the Permian Basin
Artesia field was discovered across the border
in New Mexico. Hobbs field was discovered in
New Mexico in 1928. Oil production in this
portion of New Mexico resulted in population
growth for both Artesia and Hobbs, New
Mexico.

Following the success of the Florence and
Salt Creek fields, other significant oil field discoveries
were made in the Northern Great
Plains states. However, due to fundamental
differences in geologic history, fewer commercially
viable fields occur in the Northern than
in the Southern Plains. In Montana, the Kevin-
Sunburst field, located north of Shelby, was
discovered in 1922. The Cutbank field, near
Cutbank, Montana, was opened in 1934. In
Nebraska, the first successful oil field in the
eastern portion of the state was discovered in
1940 at Falls City in Richardson County. In
western Nebraska, the first commercially successful
well was the Mary Egging No. 1, drilled
in Cheyenne County in 1949 by Marathon Oil
Company (then known as the Ohio Oil Company).
This and adjacent wells were christened
the Gurley field. Significant oil production
from the Williston Basin of North Dakota began
in 1951 with the completion of the Clarence
Iverson No. 1 well, located near the towns of
Tioga and Minot. In South Dakota, some oil
production commenced in 1954 with the discovery
of oil in Harding County, located in the
northwestern corner of the state.

This regional production, of course, was
taking place against a backdrop of the world
context of global supply and demand. Following
the Panhandle field discovery, coupled
with production from other Great Plains
fields and other oil-rich regions across America,
the United States and the Great Plains entered
a period from 1921 to 1940 of petroleum
overabundance. Annual production in the
United States in 1920 was 443 million barrels
and was in balance with demand. By 1923 the
volume had expanded to 732 million barrels
per year, and the bloated industry headed into
a tailspin. Fortunes were lost and dreams
crushed during a time that overlapped the
Great Depression. From 1945 to 1973 the industry
slowly recovered through maintenance
of a managed balance between supply and demand.
Then from the Arab oil embargo in
1973 to about 1983, the petroleum industry of
the Great Plains rode a wave of high oil prices
fostered by global fears of oil-supply shortfalls.
In 1986, however, oil-rich Saudi Arabia
began to increase production in order to gain
more control over supply and pricing. This
action created an overabundance of oil and
placed downward pressure on oil prices. From
about 1984 to the present, the petroleum industry
has undergone unprecedented global
contraction. Emphasis on cost savings has
forced the major North American companies
to consolidate their operations in Houston,
Texas, and Calgary, Alberta. Consequently, the
remaining oil and gas wealth of the U.S. Great
Plains is mainly the domain of independent
investors and the small- to medium-size companies
of the region.

The contraction of the industry has been
very hard on the economies of the oil field
towns that grew up around the industry. For
instance, during the oil boom of the seventies,
the Permian Basin city of Midland, Texas, was
rumored to have more millionaires per capita
than any city in the United States. At the beginning
of the twenty-first century, however,
unemployment there hovered at 9 percent.
Economic growth in most of the oil towns in
the Southern Great Plains was momentarily
stunted by this downturn in the energy industry.
Northern Great Plains cities such as Casper
and Gillette, Wyoming, and Williston and
Dickinson, North Dakota, have also grappled
with this economic challenge.

According to U.S. Department of Energy
statistics for the year 2000, Texas led both the
Great Plains and the nation in daily crude-oil
production (1.2 million barrels from the Great
Plains, East Texas, and Gulf Coast fields).
(One barrel equals forty-two gallons of crude
oil.) Oklahoma is ranked fifth in the nation in
daily production (191,000 barrels), followed
by New Mexico, 184,000 barrels; Wyoming,
166,000 barrels; Kansas, 94,000 barrels; North
Dakota, 89,000 barrels; and Colorado, 50,000
barrels. Montana produces 42,000 barrels a
day, ranking it thirteenth. Nebraska is ranked
twenty-first, with a production rate of 8,000
barrels a day. South Dakota produces 3,000
barrels a day and is ranked twenty-fifth.

Despite years of exploitation, the proved reserves
of oil in the Great Plains still tend to be
located in the traditional oil-rich areas. In
1999 Texas ranked number one in the nation,
with proved reserves of 5,339 million barrels
(again, including the Great Plains and other
Texas oil provinces). This Texas total is double
the reserve estimate for all the remaining areas
of the U.S. Great Plains. New Mexico is second
in the nation, with proved reserves of 718 million
barrels, followed by Oklahoma, with 621
million barrels of reserves. Estimates for other
states include Wyoming, 590 million; Montana,
207 million; Colorado, 203 million; Kansas,
175 million; North Dakota, 53 million; and
Nebraska, 17 million barrels. South Dakota is
estimated to have less than 1 percent of the
total U.S. crude-oil reserves. To place these
numbers for the U.S. Great Plains into a
global context, Saudi Arabia has proved reserves
of 262,000 million barrels, or about 25
percent of the estimated proved reserves in the
world. Saudi Arabia's oil reserves are fifty
times larger than those of Texas.

In the early twenty-first century, the Great
Plains oil and gas producers compete on a
global stage where market forces and oil-rich
countries continue to determine the profitability
of the industry. Giant multinational
companies and the wealthiest petroleumproducing
countries are well poised to take advantage
of the latest computer-related technology
for the exploration and production of
hydrocarbons. These technologies have helped
to lower finding costs from $15 per barrel in the
1970s to less than $5 per barrel in 2002. Some of
these technologies such as 3d seismic (allowing
clearer images of subsurface rocks) and improved
drilling methods (directional-drilling
capabilities) have helped to lower finding costs
in the Great Plains.

In the future, one segment of the industry
that may witness continued growth in the
Great Plains is the natural gas industry. Natural
gas, an environmentally friendly alternative
to oil and coal, is growing in importance
as an energy source of choice. The rocks of the
Great Plains still contain an ample supply of
this untapped resource.


Stanley T. Paxton
Oklahoma State University




Mast, R. F., D. H. Root, L. P. Williams, W. R. Beeman, and
D. L. Barnett. Areas of Historical Oil and Gas Exploration and Production in the Conterminous United States. U.S.
Geological Survey Geologic Investigations Series, I-2582,
Reston, VA: Department of the Interior, 1998. Owen, E. W.
Trek of the Oil Finders: A History of Exploration for Petroleum.
American Association of Petroleum Geologists,
Memoir 6, Tulsa OK, 1975. Yergin, D. The Prize: The Epic Quest for Oil, Money, and Power. New York: Simon and
Schuster, 1991.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>