<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fol.020</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Fur Trade Lore</field>
      <field name="author">Wishart, David J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




FUR TRADE LORE

It is possible to identify two categories of fur
trade lore, drawn from the first four decades
of the nineteenth century when fur traders
were the predominant European American
presence in the Great Plains. The first category
involves the traders' own understandings–
largely communicated by word of mouth–of
such matters as the geography of the country
and the characteristics of the Native inhabitants;
the second relates to stories from the fur
trade, tales of traders' lives, especially of heroic
exploits, which have been passed down
over the years in both oral and written forms.

When the fur trade in the American Great
Plains first gathered momentum, following
the return of Lewis and Clark from their epic
journey with news of abundant beaver and
otter at the headwaters of the Missouri, there
was only a vague understanding of the geography
of the region. This explains why Manual
Lisa, who organized his first expedition to the
Northern Plains in 1807, believed that he
could forge a trading connection to Santa Fe
from the headwaters of the Missouri. Lisa was
possibly influenced by his partner, George
Drouillard, whose map of 1808 showed Santa
Fe to be only a few days' ride from the headwaters
of the Missouri. Such geographic misconceptions
were corrected over time through
often-bitter experience on the ground.

The discovery–for to Americans in 1824 it
was indeed a discovery–of South Pass by a
small band of trappers led by Jedediah Smith
provides an example of how lore was translated
into geographical knowledge. Americans
had probably crossed the Rocky Mountains
through South Pass in previous years (John
Colter in 1807, for example), but there had
been no "effective" discovery of this vital gateway
to the West. Smith, in the first of his great
explorations, remedied that. His party labored
through the Badlands of South Dakota
in the fall of 1823, then on past the Black Hills
to the Wind River Mountains, where they
went into winter camp with the Crows. Using
sand piled on a bison robe, the Crows modeled
the topography of the Rockies, showing
the trappers the convenient route around the
south edge of the Wind River Range. In March
of 1824 Smith and his men struggled through a
blizzard to cross South Pass, leading the way
for the hundreds of trappers who would trace
the Platte and Sweetwater Rivers through the
pass to the rendezvous over the next fifteen
years and for the far more numerous emigrants
to Oregon, Utah, and California who
followed in the 1840s.

Traders' views of the Indigenous peoples of
the Plains were also lore, in the sense that their
appraisals were based not on any objective reality
but on the Native group's utility to the fur
trade. The traders came to despise the Arikaras–
they labeled them the "Horrid Tribe"–
because of their resistance to the fur trade,
most dramatically in 1823 when they attacked
William Ashley's expedition to the upper Missouri,
leaving twelve Americans dead. The
Arikaras, of course, were only following their
own agenda: to preserve their middleman role
in the commerce by preventing Americans
from opening up their own trade with the upriver
Indians. By contrast, the Crows had a
good reputation. Their finished furs were regarded
as the best in the Plains, and, according
to trader Edwin Denig, they never killed
Americans and rarely stole from them.

Stories from the fur trade–our inherited
fur trade lore–abound. For example, the extraordinary
travels of the young Englishman
Henry Kelsey, while in the service of the Hudson's
Bay Company, are legendary, partly because
of their daring, partly because the exact
routes are clouded in mystery, and partly because
Kelsey's journals were not known to historians
until 1926. The fact that the journals
were also partly written in crude verse only
adds to the mystery. In 1690 Kelsey was sent
inland from Hudson Bay to connect distant
Indians to the fur trade. Accompanied by Indian
guides, Kelsey probably ascended the
Saskatchewan River and explored the Canadian
Plains over the following two years. He
contracted the Assiniboines and maybe the
Gros Ventres, and he was the first European to
record descriptions of bison and grizzly bears
in the Canadian West. Even if some of the
more fabulous events associated with his journey
are discounted, such as his reputed killing
of two grizzly bears with two shots, the sheer
accomplishment of his exploration and his
easy ability to fit in with the Indians (he knew
some Indian languages well) make Kelsey a
figure of mythological, as well as historical,
importance.

Fact and fiction merge in fur trade accounts,
especially in the dramatic memoirs of
trappers like Joe Meek and Robert Newell.
One book, The Lost Trappers, written by
David H. Coyner in 1859, was, in the words of
the eminent fur trade historian Hiram Martin
Chittenden, a "complete fabrication." The remarkable
story of Hugh Glass, however, seems
to be true, and no other piece of fur trade lore
has been so durable. In 1902, when Chittenden
wrote his classic American Fur Trade of the Far West, the saga of Hugh Glass was an oral tradition
among Plains folk. There had also been
three written accounts by that time, including
one in the Missouri Intelligencer in 1829. Subsequently,
Glass's exploits were included in
numerous fur trade books, retold as an epic
narrative poem in John G. Neihardt's The Saga of Hugh Glass (1915) and filtered through
Hollywood in the film Man in the Wilderness
(1971), with Richard Harris playing the lead.

The story is this: following the battle with
the Arikaras, Hugh Glass (who had been
wounded in the fight) set out for the Yellowstone
River with a party of trappers led by
Ashley's partner, Andrew Henry. Glass, an expert
marksman, was sent ahead to hunt and,
out there alone, he was attacked by a grizzly
bear and her cubs. Part of his throat was torn
out and his arms and legs were badly wounded.
When the rest of the party caught up, they
killed the bear and waited for Glass to die. But
Hugh Glass was unwilling to take that final
step, so Henry, anxious to get on with business,
persuaded two men (one of them a teenager
named Jim Bridger) to stay with him, then left
for the trapping grounds. A few days later the
two men rejoined Henry, reporting that Glass
had died.

They were almost right, but Glass was able
to crawl to a place where there was a spring and
wild cherries and buffaloberries within reach.
As his strength slowly returned, he resolved to
find the men who had abandoned him and
seek revenge. Living on berries, roots, and carcasses
of dead animals, he struggled across
more than 100 miles to Fort Kiowa, in presentday
South Dakota. There, though still badly
hurt, he joined another trapping party bound
for the upper Missouri, seeking his former
companions. He found them at their new post
at the junction of the Big Horn and Yellowstone
Rivers in December of 1823. Looking like
an apparition, Glass walked into the post and
up to Bridger, but taking into account his
youth, he forgave him. Glass later found the
other man who had left him at Fort Atkinson,
where he had joined the army, and he too was
forgiven. Hugh Glass's luck finally ran out
when he was killed by Arikaras in the winter of
1832–33.

Such stories are the stuff of fur trade history.
Probably no other period of the American
past has been represented so much by lore
and so little by systematic analysis. No doubt
the latter is needed, but hopefully not at the
expense of the drama that characterized European
Americans' initial encounter with the
dramatic physical and human environments
of the Great Plains and Rocky Mountains.

See also EUROPEAN AMERICANS: Kelsey, Henry / 
HISPANIC AMERICANS: Lisa, Manuel / 
INDUSTRY: Fur Trade.


David J. Wishart
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Chittenden, Hiram Martin. The American Fur Trade of the Far West. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1986.
Morgan, Dale Lowell. Jedediah Smith and the Opening of the West. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1953.
Saum, Lewis O. The Fur Trader and the Indian. Seattle:
University of Washington Press, 1965.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>