<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.afam.021</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Harris, Wynonie (1913-1969)</field>
      <field name="author">Collins, Tony</field>
      <field name="text">

 




HARRIS, WYNONIE (1913-1969)


Wynonie Harris on stage with the Lucky Millinder


Blues singer Wynonie Harris was a leading figure
in black music during the 1940s and early
1950s, and he developed a style that had a considerable
influence on early rock and roll. A
handsome man with striking blue-gray eyes
and a flashing smile, and with a voice powerful
enough to project over driving horn-led
bands, Harris was renowned as a charismatic
performer on stage and as a hard-drinking
hell-raiser and ladies' man off stage. He became
best known for his humorous, often risque
songs such as "Good Rockin" Tonight,"
"All She Wants to Do Is Rock," "Grandma
Plays the Numbers," and "Bloodshot Eyes."

Harris was born in Omaha, Nebraska, on
August 24, 1913, the illegitimate offspring of an
African American mother and a Native American
father. He worked as a dancer for several
years before becoming a singer. Influenced
and inspired by Jimmy Rushing and Big Joe
Turner, both big-voiced blues singers from
Kansas City, Harris learned his craft in the
clubs on Omaha's Near North Side, in particular
Jim Bell's Harlem Club. By the early
1940s he was calling himself "Mr. Blues" and
was a regular attraction at the Club Alabam
on Los Angeles's Central Avenue. His big
break came in 1944 when he was invited to
join Lucky Millinder's big band as the featured
male singer. With Millinder he recorded
"Who Threw the Whiskey in the Well," which
became a number-one hit on the black music
charts. Thereafter, Harris worked as a single,
playing residencies at the country's leading
black nightclubs and touring frequently. His
greatest commercial success came after he
signed with King Records in 1947 and recorded
"Good Rockin' Tonight." From then
until 1952 a string of hit records made him one
of the biggest-selling artists among African
American record buyers.

Harris's brand of good-time blues was a direct
precursor of 1950s rock and roll. Elvis
Presley, who recorded his own version of
"Good Rockin' Tonight" in 1954, is reputed to
have adopted some of his stage movements
after seeing Harris perform. Wynonie Harris
himself, however, was too old, too raunchy,
and too rooted in black musical traditions to
appeal to rock and roll's white teenage audience.
Harris never gave up the music business
completely, but from the mid-1950s onward he
worked mostly outside music. He died of
throat cancer in Los Angeles on June 14, 1969.



Tony Collins
London, England




Collins, Tony. Rock Mr. Blues: The Life and Music of Wynonie
Harris. Milford NH: Big Nickel Publications, 1995.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>