<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.038</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Landon, Alfred (1887-1987)</field>
      <field name="author">Loomis, Burdett A.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




LANDON, ALFRED (1887-1987)

Best remembered for his landslide defeat by
Franklin D. Roosevelt in the 1936 presidential
election, Alf Landon played a major role in
Kansas Republican politics from the early
1900s through his death in Topeka–at age
100–on October 12, 1987.

Born in West Middlesex in the western
Pennsylvania oil country on September 9,
1887, Landon moved with his family to Kansas
when the oil industry sought to exploit the
huge Mid-Continent deposits of the Southern
Plains. An astute businessman, Landon accumulated
an oil-based fortune by the 1920s,
and he increasingly turned his attention to Republican
politics, first behind the scenes, then
as state party chairman, and finally as governor
during the mid-Depression years (1933
through 1937).

Landon generally supported the Progressive
side of Republican politics, which he practiced
in a low-key and congenial style that emphasized
bridging differences without compromising
principles. As governor, he worked well
with the Roosevelt administration on agricultural,
petroleum, and welfare issues, among
others. Moreover, he lowered taxes and reformed
local government finances.

In 1935 Landon easily won reelection, the
only Republican governor in the nation to do
so. This success, in conjunction with his capacity
to bring together various party factions,
made him an attractive candidate for the 1936
Republican presidential nomination. Landon
represented new leadership for the "Grand
Old Party," and he won the nomination with
an almost unanimous vote of the convention
delegates. Landon waged an energetic and
responsible campaign, but Roosevelt overwhelmed
him in a defeat of historic proportions.
Landon received 38 percent of the major
party vote and won only eight electoral votes
(Maine and Vermont). For Landon, the results
would serve as his political epitaph for
the public at large, but he would remain active
in national, international, and Republican
Party affairs for most of the next fifty years.

Landon's internationalism came to the fore
as he articulated measured support for much
of Roosevelt's foreign policy in the late 1930s
and through the war years. He continued to
speak on international issues in the postwar
era, adopting positions that emphasized the
value of the United Nations and the need
to think seriously about world peace. At the
same time, he remained active in the Republican
Party, often seeking to influence the outcomes
of state and national decisions. However,
by the 1950s, with his failure to back
fellow Kansan Dwight Eisenhower for the Republican
presidential nomination, Landon
had become an outsider at both the state and
national levels.

For the last thirty years of his life Landon
played the role of a Republican elder statesman
and was an advocate for strengthening international
trade. A lifelong partisan, Landon
won bipartisan admiration for his independence,
experience, and civility. And he would
spend his last years observing the successes of
his daughter, Nancy Landon Kassebaum, as
she served with distinction in the U.S. Senate
and practiced the kind of moderate Republicanism
that he had long championed.


Burdett A. Loomis
University of Kansas




Landon, Alfred M. America at the Crossroads. Port Washington
NY: Kennikat Press, 1971. McCoy, Donald R. Landon
of Kansas. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1996.
Palmer, Frederick. This Man Landon. New York: Dodd,
Mead and Company, 1936.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>