<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.gen.038</field>
      <field name="titleMain">United Farm Women of Alberta</field>
      <field name="author">Langford, Nanci</field>
      <field name="text">

 




UNITED FARM WOMEN OF ALBERTA


UFWA meeting group, Heart Lake, Alberta, 1921


The United Farm Women of Alberta (UFWA)
was the first provincial organization of farm
women in Alberta. First established in 1915 as
an auxiliary to the United Farmers of Alberta
(UFA), the women at the 1916 convention
voted to make the ufwa a separate organization
with its own constitution and direction.

By 1915 many local women's groups were
already in place, with distinct names, purposes,
and procedures of their own. The UFWA
drew from women's experiences in these local
groups and from the procedures already developed
for the UFA to create a highly centralized
organization; most local initiatives
were funneled through and directed by the
central office and the provincial executive. A
yearly program, outlining the content and
structure of monthly meetings, was developed
at the provincial level and followed faithfully
by locals. An information bulletin on each
monthly topic was added in 1920. Three provincial
committees were formed in 1916 and
provincial conveners named to manage them.
They focused on health, education, and young
people's work, reflecting the organization's
focus on "social welfare" and "betterment of
rural life." More committees were added over
the years as the group broadened its focus to
include the legal status of women and children,
cooperative marketing, farm safety, and
environmental concerns. Issues such as property
rights for farm women, reproductive
rights, farm economics and marketing, stress
in farm families, child care in rural areas, access
to affordable medical care, rural depopulation,
and loss of schools and services
kept the organization lobbying and in advocacy
activities for decades, and maintained
its reputation as a respected voice for rural
communities.

The United Farm Women of Alberta was
responsible for innovations such as a Junior
Branch for Young People, Farm Young People's
Week at the University of Alberta, the
first Egg and Poultry Pool established in Canada
(1925), Farm Women's Week at Olds Agricultural
College, and the first rural chautauqua
held in Alberta (1937). The organization
was a major contributor to the election campaigns
that resulted in UFA governments in
Alberta from 1921 to 1935. The organization's
first president, Irene Parlby, was appointed as
the first female cabinet minister in Canada after
winning a seat in the 1921 election.

In 1949 the ufwa became the Farm Women's
Union of Alberta (FWUA). Significant
achievements of the FWUA include the launching
of a magazine for farmers (1949) and
building a leadership and citizenship camp for
young people in the foothills of the Rockies. In
1970, due to another organizational amalgamation,
this time with the Alberta Federation
of Agriculture, Unifarm was created, and
the women's organization chose the name
"Women of Unifarm." Significant achievements
of this period include the Matrimonial
Property Act (1979), giving women equality in
division of marital property; the publication
of the eighth edition of their renowned cookbook,
which brought the total number of
cookbooks sold to more than 100,000 copies;
and the introduction of Farm Safety Week and
the Farm Safety Hike, which garnered international
recognition for the organization.


Nanci Langford
Athabasca University




Carter, Eva. Thirty Years of Progress. Calgary: United Farm
Women of Alberta, 1944. Cormack, Barbara Villy. Perennials and Politics: The Life Story of Hon. Irene Parlby, LL.D.
Sherwood Park, Alberta: n.p., 1969. Langford, Nanci L. Politics, Pitchforks, and Pickle Jars: 75 Years of Organized Farm Women in Alberta. Calgary: Detselig Enterprises, 1997.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>