<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.na.024</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Crows</field>
      <field name="author">Frey, Rodney</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CROWS

The Crow people traditionally call themselves
Apsaalooke or Absaroka, commonly translated
as "Children of the Large-Beaked Bird." While
likely referring to the raven, this term was misinterpreted
by early trappers who began to
address the Apsaalooke as the Crows. The
Crows attribute their origins, as well as the
creation of the world, to the trickster Old Man
Coyote. The narrative begins with Old Man
Coyote traveling alone in a cold and wet world.
As four ducks flew over, Old Man Coyote asked
his younger brothers to dive beneath the waters
and bring up some earth so he could make
the land. The first duck dove but was unsuccessful,
as were the second and third ducks.
Finally, Old Man Coyote asked the fourth
duck, Hell Diver, to bring up some earth. The
duck dove deep and, after being down a long
time, surfaced with a small piece of mud. With
this earth Old Man Coyote traveled from east
to west and made the land, mountains, and
rivers, animals and plants, and gave them life.
But the world was still a lonely place. So Old
Man Coyote molded from the earth an image
he liked and blew a small breath into it. The
first man was made. Old Man Coyote was not
satisfied. He tried again and the first woman
was created. Old Man Coyote was no longer
alone. He taught the people how to live and
pray, giving them their language, clan system,
and ceremonies.

The historic migration of the Crows from
the Lake Winnipeg region of Canada into the
Bighorn and Yellowstone River basins of Montana
and Wyoming (probably before 1600)
predated the arrival of the horse. Horses were
acquired by 1750, and the Crows' economic life
was transformed from one of sedentary farming
to one of bison hunting. The horse became
an integral symbol of Crow identity and status.
Male leadership roles became predicated on
achieving a series of war deeds, such as touching
an enemy in combat or leading a successful
horse raid against an enemy. Among their enemies
were the Blackfeet, Cheyennes, and Lakotas.
The Sun Dance became a prominent
ceremonial expression, helping unite the tribe
and providing a means to obtain spiritual
power to avenge the death of a relative.

Despite the changes initiated by the adoption
of the horse, the Crows retained elements
of their former society. The Tobacco Ceremony,
the yearly planting and harvesting of
the sacred tobacco seeds, reflected their once-agrarian
orientation. The Crows also maintained
their matrilineal clan structure, and
even today's clan system is based on the thirteen
original clans. The Crow language is part
of the Siouan family, thus giving them a linguistic
affiliation with many other tribes of the
region. Today, up to one-third of the population
continues to speak their native language.

The central organizing principle around
which much of Aboriginal and contemporary
Crow society revolves is best understood in the
Crow term for clan, ashammaleaxia, literally
meaning "driftwood lodges." As an individual
piece of driftwood has difficulty surviving the
powerful eddies and boulders of the Yellowstone
or Bighorn Rivers, so too does an individual
Crow have difficulty surviving the river
of life, full of potential adversaries–formerly
Lakotas and Blackfeet but now unemployment,
substance abuse, and discrimination.
But in tightly lodging itself with other pieces of
driftwood along the riverbank, the driftwood
is protected. So, too, is an individual Crow
protected and nurtured when lodged securely
in an extensive web of kinship ties. These are
ties made up of both social and spiritual kinsmen
and maintained through an extensive pattern
of gift exchanges.

The values of ashammaleaxia are clearly evident
in oral traditions, kinship relationships,
and religious ceremonialism. The story of
Burnt Face is an example. A young boy is badly
scarred and subsequently ostracized. Burnt
Face fasts for several days in the Big Horn
Mountains. While on the mountain, he assembles
the "Big Horn Medicine Wheel" as a gift to
the Sun. Having given of himself, Burnt Face is
adopted by the Little People, who remove his
scar. He returns to his people and subsequently
becomes a great healer, having extended his
kinship ties to the Little People.

Of all kinship relations, that of aassahke, or
"clan uncle and aunt," is pivotal. A clan uncle
or aunt is any male and female member of
one's father's mother's clan. Such individuals
are to be respected, and gifts of food and blankets
are provided to them during giveaways.
In return, aassahke bestow on a child an "Indian
name," sing "praise songs" for accomplishments,
and offer protective prayer.

The principles of ashammaleaxia are expressed
in a sweat bath, a Catholic Mass, a
medicine bundle opening, a vision quest, a
peyote meeting, and a Sun Dance. In each instance,
individual prayer, the "gift" of sacrificing
food and water, or the medicine power of
a guardian spirit may be directed at a kinsmen
in need. The last "buffalo days" Sun Dance
was held in 1875, but with the assistance of the
Shoshones, the Crows were again performing
the Sun Dance by the 1940s. Today the Shoshone-
Crow Sun Dance has become fully integrated
into Crow family and religious life. As
many as 120 men and women participate in a
Sun Dance, several of which are held on the
reservation during June and July. Along with
the sponsor, each dancer has made a vow to
the Creator or his or her own spirit guardian
to go without food and water and "dry up" to
help another. Typically, dances last three days.
During the Sun Dance, individual participants
offer prayer for family members, collective
morning prayers are given for the welfare
of all peoples, the sick are "doctored" by medicine
men, and individual dancers may be
given a vision.

The ravages of smallpox in the 1830s, the
destruction of the bison, the confinement to a
reservation in 1868, and its subsequent reduction
by treaties and allotment in the late nineteenth
and early twentieth centuries all contributed
to a decrease in the population to a
low of 1,625 by the early 1930s. With improved
health care and economic opportunities, the
enrolled Crow population had risen to 10,000
by 1998. The Crow Indian Reservation of some
two million acres, of which nearly one-third is
owned by non-Indians, is located in southcentral
Montana.

Electing not to adopt most of the specific
provisions of the Indian Reorganization Act
of 1934, the Crows wrote their own constitution
in 1948. It established a general council
government made up of every adult member
of the tribe. The council elects four officers: a
chairman, vice chairman, secretary, and vice
secretary. It also establishes various governing
committees that oversee such activities as land
purchases, industrial development, housing,
education, and tribal enrollment.

The resilience of the Crow people is partly
the result of persistent great leadership, including
Plenty Coups, Pretty Eagle, Medicine
Crow, Robert Yellowtail, Angela Russell (a
state senator), Bill Yellowtail (a state senator
and regional director of the Environmental
Protection Agency), and Janine Pease Pretty
On Top (president of Little Big Horn College
and a 1994 MacArthur Fellow).

See also LAW: Montana v. United States / SPORTS AND RECREATION: Crow Fair.


Rodney Frey
University of Idaho




Frey, Rodney. The World of the Crow Indians: As Driftwood
Lodges. Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1987.
Hoxie, Frederick. Parading through History: The Making of
the Crow Nation in America, 1805–1933. New York: Cambridge
University Press, 1995. Lowie, Robert. The Crow
Indians. New York: Holt, Rinehart and Winston, 1935, rev.
ed. 1956.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>