<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.med.016</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Edmonton Journal</field>
      <field name="author">Wishart, David J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




EDMONTON JOURNAL

The first 1,000 copies of the Edmonton Journal
rolled off the presses at the back of the Shamrock
Fruit Store on November 11, 1903. The
paper's founders were John Macpherson, Arthur
Moore, and J. W. Cunningham, and the
Journal faced tough competition from the
well-established Edmonton Bulletin. In fact,
the Journal failed to show a profit for five
years. By 2002 the Journal employed 894 staff
and had an average daily circulation of 145,000
copies.

The Journal grew with Edmonton, which
was incorporated as a city in 1904. From its
inception the Journal sided with the Conservative
Party and therefore against the Bulletin,
whose co-owner, Frank Oliver, was a Liberal
cabinet minister. The Journal also was a champion
of the development of the "new Northwest,"
a booster for the city and region, especially
when economic times were hard in the
1920s and 1930s.

Under the control of John Imrie, who was
publisher from 1921 to 1941, the Journal moved
into a handsome new building on Bellamy
Hill in 1921; branched out into radio, launching
CJCA, Alberta's first radio station, in 1922;
and won a Pulitzer Prize in 1938, the first time
such an award had been made outside the
United States. The honor was given for the
paper's defense of freedom of the press in resisting
William Aberhart's Social Credit government's
bill to bring newspapers under government
control. The Journal battled the bill
in front-page editorials and all the way to the
Supreme Court, which ruled against the government
on March 4, 1938.

On January 20, 1951, the Bulletin stopped its
presses for good, leaving the Journal as Edmonton's
only daily newspaper until April 2,
1978, when the Edmonton Sun, a morning tabloid,
printed its first edition. The Journal's facilities
were improved to keep pace with its
expanded circulation, which had reached
95,881 in 1956. An addition doubled the size of
the paper's building in 1952, a press building
was added in 1955, and in 1980 the opening of
the Eastgate production plant, complete with
offset presses, inaugurated the modern era of
the Edmonton Journal. For five years, from
September 2, 1980, to April 8, 1985, the Journal
put out both evening and morning editions,
but thereafter, in keeping with nationwide
trends, the paper published only a morning
edition.

Recent years have seen the construction of a
new fifteen-million-dollar office complex,
which involved the demolition of the old 1921
structure, a landmark that city planners did
not want to see erased. (Parts of the old facade
were incorporated into the new structure.)
The Journal also put $1 million into becoming
part owner of the Edmonton Oilers, demonstrating
again that Edmonton's leading paper
not only reports the news of the city and region
but also is part of that news.


Daivd J. Wishart
University of Nebraska-Lincoln





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>