<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pe.052</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Roadrunners</field>
      <field name="author">Smith, Geoffrey R.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ROADRUNNERS

The roadrunner (Geococcyx californianus) is
primarily a ground-dwelling member of the
cuckoo family that inhabits the southern extremes
of the Great Plains region. The range
of the roadrunner extends across the southwestern
United States and into central Mexico.
The northern perimeter extends through the
Texas Panhandle and Oklahoma into southern
Kansas and west into southeastern Colorado.
Habitat preference varies widely within this
region but includes both desert conditions in
the south to grasslands in the north.

The adult roadrunner has a total body
length of about twenty-four inches and is designed
for speed. With its zygodactyl feet,
characterized by two toes forward and two
toes back, the roadrunner is an e.cient predator
on many species of insects and most
small reptiles, including the rattlesnake. Both
male and female have buff-colored undersides
with a mixture of black, bronze, and buff
feathers on the breast. Both sexes possess a
crest on top of the head.

Nesting habits of the roadrunner are consistent
throughout the Plains. Courtship begins
in the early spring with nests being constructed
in shrubs and small trees at heights of
from three to about fifteen feet. Nests are shallow
and from eighteen to twenty inches in
diameter. The first clutch of eggs (from a total
of two or three) is laid in late April to early
May. The incubation period lasts about eighteen
days, with both parents sharing all nesting
chores. Juveniles leave the nest at about
fourteen days of age and remain secluded in
underbrush for an additional eight to ten
days. Parenting chores by adults continue during
this period. Upon emergence after the tenday
seclusion period the juveniles are prepared
to fend for themselves.


Wyman Meinzer
Benjamin, Texas




Bent, Arthur Cleveland. Life Histories of North American
Cuckoos, Goatsuckers, Hummingbirds, and Their Allies.
New York: Dover Publications, 1948. Meinzer, Wyman. The
Roadrunner. Lubbock: Texas Tech University Press, 1993.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>