<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ag.065</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Suitcase Farming</field>
      <field name="author">Hewes, Leslie</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SUITCASE FARMING


Breaking sod in Greely County, Kansas, May 1925


Suitcase farming was, and to a limited degree
still is, carried on by farmers living more than
one county away from the land they farm. The
term was used as early as 1930 by the county
agent for Greeley County, in western Kansas,
although its characteristics were not defined.
The pattern, or basic ecology, of early suitcase
farming can be generalized in this way:
Cheap level grazing land in a zone of recurring
drought, a moderate distance west of established
wheat country that was already largely
mechanized, was invaded by farmers with
tractors and other farm machinery in a speculative
westward advance. The plow-up was so
substantial that a suitcase-farming frontier
can be recognized that included most of westcentral
and southwestern Kansas and small
areas in Colorado.

After an interruption by the drought and
depression of the 1930s, and the restrictions of
World War II, including gasoline rationing
and scarcity of machinery and parts, a second
advance of similar character carried wheat
farming still farther west, mainly into eastcentral
Colorado. Kiowa County was affected
most. Farmers from northwestern Oklahoma,
the Texas Panhandle, and urban bases in front
of the Rockies, in some cases former residents,
were involved, along with Kansans.

The decline in suitcase farming, due to unprofitable
operation, preference for local operators,
and locally to irrigation, already apparent
in the 1960s, has continued, so that
now suitcase farming is mainly a fleeting
memory in the history of settlement and agriculture
in the Central Great Plains. In aiding
great plow-ups, suitcase farming doubtless
contributed to Dust Bowl conditions in the
1930s and in the mid-1950s, but probably its
most lasting effect was to extend the production
of hard winter wheat westward several
hundred miles.


Leslie Hewes
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Hewes, Leslie. The Suitcase Farming Frontier: A Study in the Historical Geography of the Central Great Plains. Lincoln:
University of Nebraska Press, 1973.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>