<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.002</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Abbott, Grace (1878-1939)</field>
      <field name="author">Sorensen, John</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ABBOTT, GRACE (1878-1939)


Grace Abbott


Grace Abbott was perhaps the greatest champion
of children's rights in American history.
She was born (November 17, 1878) and raised
in Grand Island, Nebraska. Abbott was part of
an accomplished pioneer family. Her father
was the first lieutenant governor of Nebraska,
her mother was a leader of the early Plains
women's suffrage movement, and her sister,
Edith, was the first woman in American history
to become the dean of a major university
graduate school, the University of Chicago.
Grace Abbott herself was the first woman
nominated for a presidential cabinet post, secretary
of labor for Herbert Hoover, and the
first person sent to represent the United States
at a committee of the League of Nations.

As chief of the U.S. Children's Bureau from
1921 to 1934, Abbott was the highest ranking
and most powerful woman in the U.S. government
when the Depression hit. She was the
only trained social worker at the top political
levels in Washington, DC in those disaster-filled
days. Accordingly, she exerted a crucial influence
on the momentous relief and welfare
efforts that were developed in response to the
crisis.

A trusted associate of Nobel Prize–winner
Jane Addams, Abbott also made significant
contributions to the field of immigration
rights during her tenure as director of the Immigrants
Protective League of Chicago from
1908 to 1917. She was a vigorous leader in the
fight against child labor and a longtime crusader
for improved children's health care. She
was among the first female broadcasters to a
national audience, with "Your Child" on NBC
in the 1920s, and her trailblazing social service
work has been credited with leading the way
to the creation of the Social Security Act and
the United Nations' unicef program.

Abbott was a woman of intriguing contradictions:
a lifelong Republican Party member
and a lifelong liberal activist; a native of the
Plains frontier who spent much of her adult
life in the poorest immigrant quarters of urban
Chicago; and an unmarried woman who
was nicknamed "the mother of America's 43
million children."

Abbott's courageous struggles–to protect
the rights of immigrants, to increase the role
of women in government, and to improve the
lives of all children–demonstrate a remarkable
human ability to seek out suffering and
to do something about it. She was a bold and
defiant woman who changed our country
more profoundly than have many presidents.

Throughout her career, Abbott never lost
her profound love for her Great Plains homeland,
which she felt had so vitally contributed
to her character. As Edith Abbott wrote of her
sister, "To the end of her life, Grace was a
daughter of the pioneers–with the vigorous
'dash' of the pioneer who is able to accept
temporary defeat in the confident belief in ultimate
victory . . . even when the odds on the
other side are very great."

Edward Keating, congressional representative
from Colorado, summed up the feelings
of innumerable Americans when, following
Abbott's death on June 19, 1939, in Chicago, he
stood on the floor of the Congress and said,
quite simply: "To me there was something
about Grace Abbott which always suggested
Joan of Arc."

See also EDUCATION: Abbott, Edith.


John Sorensen
New York City




Abbott, Edith. "A Sister's Memories." Social Service Review
13 (1939): 351–408. Costin, Lela B. Two Sisters for Social
Justice: A Biography of Grace and Edith Abbott. Urbana:
University of Illinois Press, 1983. Sorensen, John. "My Sister
and Comrade: A Radio Portrait of Grace Abbott."
Aired on Nebraska Public Radio, Lincoln, January 20, 21,
and 22, 1997.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>