<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fol.040</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Shivarees</field>
      <field name="author">Taft, Michael</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SHIVAREES

Known also as serenading or belling, a shivaree
is a noisy, rowdy, and often bawdy community
celebration of a marriage. On the
wedding night, friends and neighbors would
gather outside the couple's bedroom window
banging pots and pans, playing musical instruments,
sometimes shooting off guns, and
demanding entrance to the newlyweds' home.
Once inside, the group might play practical
jokes on the couple, such as taking the labels
off cans, tying bells to the bedsprings, or
bringing livestock into the house. The tradition
might also include kidnapping one or
both of the newlyweds, tying them to trees,
dunking them in horse troughs, riding them
around town, abandoning them in the countryside,
or otherwise disrupting and delaying
the wedding night. Despite this rough treatment,
newlyweds were expected to act as gracious
hosts by offering the group food, drink,
and hospitality–or by paying the revelers to
leave.

While the tradition as practiced in the
Plains was usually a celebration in which the
community showed its approval of the marriage,
the European roots of this custom were
often far from benign. The original "charivari"
was usually a form of rough justice
wherein neighbors showed their displeasure
over an unequal marriage, an improper remarriage,
adultery, or a marriage in which
there was spousal abuse. In this older tradition,
the newlyweds might be publicly humiliated
(such as forced to ride backward on a
donkey), beaten, or even killed. As a custom in
the Plains during the nineteenth and early
twentieth centuries, however, the shivaree became
associated with neighborliness, community
spirit, and the recognition of marriage as
a stabilizing factor in frontier society.


Michael Taft
American Folklife Center
Library of Congress




Dary, David. Seeking Pleasure in the Old West. Lawrence:
University Press of Kansas, 1995. Johnson, Loretta T.
"Charivari/Shivaree: A European Folk Ritual on the American
Plains." Journal of Interdisciplinary History 20 (1990):
371–87. Kinsella, W. P. "Dangerous Consequences." In The Secret of the Northern Lights. Saskatoon: Thistledown
Press, 1998: 55–66.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>