<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.war.033</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Palo Duro Canyon, Battle of</field>
      <field name="author">Pate, J'Nell L.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




PALO DURO CANYON, BATTLE OF

A battle between Kiowas, Comanches, Cheyennes,
and 400 troopers of Col. Ranald S.
Mackenzie's Fourth U.S. Cavalry took place
early on the morning of Monday, September
28, 1874, deep in this great canyon of the Red
River, 1,000 feet below the level plains of the
Texas Panhandle. Some Tenth and Eleventh
U.S. Infantry assisted Mackenzie's command
at a base camp. His command comprised part
of a five-pronged campaign against several
bands of Native Americans who either had left
their reservations in Indian Territory for hideouts
in the Staked Plains or who had not yet
submitted to reservation life. The Palo Duro
Canyon fight was the largest engagement in
the Red River War and marked the end of the
Southern Plains Indians' military resistance.

Led by Tonkawa scouts, Colonel Mackenzie
marched his men most of the night, arriving
at the rim of the canyon at daybreak. They
made their way to the floor of the canyon
and attacked. Indian women and children retreated
up the canyon, while the men engaged
the soldiers in combat to allow their families
to escape. The Kiowa band was led by Mamanti,
the Comanches by O-ha-ma-tai, and
the small band of Cheyennes by Iron Shirt. By
noon the Indians had escaped, leaving their
lodges and horses behind. Mackenzie ordered
the lodges searched, then burned. The next
day he had his men shoot 1,048 horses to prevent
the Indians from recovering them. The
Indians straggled into the reservations, having
been left with no supplies for the approaching
winter. Mackenzie reported that three Indians
and one cavalry trooper died.

See also PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT: Caprock Canyonlands.


J'Nell L. Pate
Tarrant County Junior College, Fort Worth




Carter, Robert G. On the Border with Mackenzie. Washington
DC: Eynon Printing Co., Inc., 1935. Pate, J'Nell L.
"Colonel Ranald Slidell Mackenzie's First Four Years with
the Fourth Cavalry in Texas, 1871–1874." Master's thesis,
Texas Christian University, 1964.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>