<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.art.058</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Tallchief, Maria (b. 1925)</field>
      <field name="author">Livingston, Lili Cockerille</field>
      <field name="text">

 




TALLCHIEF, MARIA (b. 1925)

Born in Fairfax, Oklahoma, on January 24,
1925, Elizabeth Marie Tall Chief became the
first American classical dancer to earn international
acclaim as a prima ballerina. Her parents,
Alexander Joseph Tall Chief and Ruth
Parker, had acquired their wealth from Osage
oil money, and from her early years Elizabeth
Marie was schooled in music and dance. In
1930 Ruth moved the family to Hollywood,
California, specifically to advance the music
and dance careers of Elizabeth Marie and her
younger sister Marjorie. Elizabeth Marie's talents
as a pianist and dancer blossomed, and by
her senior year at Beverly Hills High School
she had chosen ballet for her career.

Elizabeth Marie joined the Ballet Russe de
Monte Carlo in 1942 and gained soloist status
in 1943, the same year she changed her name
to Maria Tallchief. Following her 1946 marriage
to George Balanchine, the Russian-born
choreographer acclaimed as the father of
American ballet, Tallchief became the first
American featured as a guest artist with the
Paris Opera Ballet. She joined Balanchine's
Ballet Society in 1947 and contributed to the
company's development into the New York
City Ballet the following year. Tallchief was
featured in twenty-two major works created
by Balanchine and is recognized as the prototype
for what is known today as the "Balanchine
ballerina." During her career with the
New York City Ballet, which ended in 1965, she
appeared as guest artist with companies such
as the American Ballet Theatre during its 1958
Russian tour and the Royal Danish Ballet. In
addition to honors bestowed on her by the
Osage Nation, the state of Oklahoma, and the
dance world, Tallchief was named Indian of
the Year in 1963. She received the Capezio
Award in 1965, a Kennedy Center Honors in
1996, and a National Arts Award in 1999.



Lili Cockerille Livingston
Tulsa, Oklahoma




Livingston, Lili Cockerille. American Indian Ballerinas.
Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1997. Reynolds,
Nancy. Repertory in Review: 40 Years of the New York City Ballet. New York: Dial Press, 1977.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>