<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.med.025</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Indian Country Today</field>
      <field name="author">Kerstetter, Todd M.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




INDIAN COUNTRY TODAY

Front-page snapshot of an issue of Indian Country Today newspaper


Indian Country Today is the most widely circulated
and arguably the most influential Native
newspaper in the world. Tim Giago (Nanwica Kciji, or Defender), Oglala Lakota, established
the weekly paper in 1981 as the Lakota Times.
Giago, born in 1934 on the Pine Ridge Reservation
and educated at the Holy Rosary Mission
School there, served in the U.S. Navy after high
school. He attended San Jose State College in
California and earned his bachelor's degree
from the University of Nevada-Reno. Giago
worked a variety of jobs before becoming an
Indian affairs columnist for the Rapid City Journal in Rapid City, South Dakota, in 1979;
he later became a full-time reporter. In 1981 he
established the Lakota Times to provide news
coverage for Pine Ridge. The paper expanded
to cover other reservations in the upper Midwest
and by 1986 was distributed to all reservations
in South Dakota, North Dakota, Nebraska,
and Montana. Unlike most Native
American papers, which tend to focus on one
tribe or reservation, the Lakota Times focused
on all tribes and reservations. The paper's offices
moved to Rapid City in 1989, and in 1991
the Lakota Times claimed a readership of 50,000.
By 1999 circulation had reached 77,000, with
pass-along readership estimated to be as high as
100,000.

With support from the Gannett Corporation,
publisher of USA Today, Giago expanded
to national coverage in 1992 and changed the
name of the paper to Indian Country Today.
The paper operated bureaus in Albuquerque,
New Mexico, and Spokane, Washington, and
used freelance reporters to cover other regions.
Giago has used the paper and pieces
written for national publications such as USA
Today, the New York Times, and Newsweek to
defend Lakota and other Native American interests.
He may be most widely known for
criticizing the use of Native Americans as
sports team mascots.

Standing Stone Media, Inc., an operation of
the Oneida Indian Nation of New York State,
bought Indian Country Today in December
1998. Corporate headquarters moved to New
York, but editorial headquarters remain in
Rapid City. The independent paper's sale to
a tribal entity raised concern among some
members of the Native American Journalists
Association, who feared the Oneidas might restrict
the paper's editorial voice. Early indications,
however, show that the tribe is not
changing the paper's editorial process. The paper
maintains a bureau in Washington dc and
has reporters in the Southwest, California,
Oklahoma, and the Northeast. An expanding
pool of correspondents provides national coverage.
The paper now claims distribution in all
fifty states and seventeen foreign countries,
and it operates an on-line version.


Todd M. Kerstetter
Texas Christian University




Andreassi, Diane. "Tim Giago." In Notable Native Americans,
edited by Sharon Malinowski. Detroit: Gale Research,
1995: 164–65. Fitzgerald, Mark. "A 'New Model' for
Tribal Ownership?" Editor &amp; Publisher, October 23, 1999:
22–26. Riley, Sam G. Biographical Dictionary of American Newspaper Columnists. Westport CT: Greenwood Press,
1995.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>