<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.na.111</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Spotted Tail (1823-1881)</field>
      <field name="author">Johansen, Bruce E.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SPOTTED TAIL (1823-1881)

"Portrait of Brule Lakota Sioux Chief Spotted Tail, ca. 1880. Photograph by Charles Milton Bell (Denver Public Library Repository)


Spotted Tail (Sinte Galeska), a major Brule
Sioux leader in the Plains Indian wars, was
born to a man named Chunka (Tangled Hair)
and a mother named Walks With Pipe, probably
along the White River of South Dakota.
Known as Jumping Buffalo in his youth, Spotted
Tail got his adult name from a striped raccoon
pelt that was given to him by a trapper.

In 1855 he was jailed at Fort Leavenworth in
retaliation for the defeat of Lt. John Grattan's
force the previous year by Brulés, though
Spotted Tail had not been involved in the incident.
Upon his release in 1856, he balanced
Lakota nationalism with conciliation to the
United States, as he was convinced of American
military superiority. By 1866 he had refrained
from hostilities against Americans,
unlike his nephew Crazy Horse.

Spotted Tail made several trips to Washington
dc on behalf of his people in the 1860s
and 1870s. During the most important visit, in
1875, Spotted Tail was among the Sioux chiefs
appointed by U.S. officials to negotiate the sale
of the Black Hills following George Armstrong
Custer's expedition there a year earlier.
Spotted Tail, who was one of the few Sioux
chiefs who understood the value to Americans
of the gold in the hills, demanded that the
government's offer of $6 million be declined,
but under duress he eventually agreed to its
sale.

In the 1870s tension arose between Red
Cloud and Spotted Tail after U.S. o.cials appointed
Spotted Tail as chief of the Sioux at
the Spotted Tail and Rosebud Agencies, eventually
replacing Red Cloud. Throughout the
1870s Spotted Tail was accused by Red Cloud
of pocketing the proceeds from a sale of tribal
land. Possibly as part of this dissension, Spotted
Tail was shot to death on August 5, 1881, by
Crow Dog, a Brulé subchief with whom he
had several disputes. Crow Dog's murder case
provided the gist of the Supreme Court case
Ex Parte Crow Dog (1883), in which the defendant
was eventually freed when the court
ruled that the United States had no jurisdiction
over the murder, which had occurred on
Indian land.

See also LAW: Ex Parte Crow Dog (Major Crimes Act) / WAR: Crazy Horse; Red Cloud.


Bruce E. Johansen
University of Nebraska at Omaha



Hyde, George E. Spotted Tail's Folk. Norman: University of
Oklahoma Press, 1961. Schusky, Ernest Lester. The Forgotten
Sioux. Chicago: Nelson-Hall, 1975. Utley, Robert M.
The Lance and the Shield: The Life and Times of Sitting
Bull. New York: Henry Holt, 1993.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>