<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ind.046</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Petroleum, Canada</field>
      <field name="author">Breen, David H.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




PETROLEUM, CANADA

The still-expanding petroleum industry in Alberta
has redefined the balance of economic
and political power within the Prairie Provinces
and the nation. The Western Canada
Sedimentary Basin is the chief geologic feature
relating to the occurrence of oil and gas.
Stretching from Canada's Northwest Territories
to South Dakota, it is a large basin within
a vast multibasin freeway that extends from
the Arctic islands through the Mackenzie
Delta and Central Plains in varying widths to
the Gulf of Mexico.

The first reported hint of the petroleum
wealth hidden beneath the basin's sedimentary
strata came from Alexander Mackenzie.
He noticed "bituminous fountains" while
traveling along the Athabasca River in 1788
and explained that the liquid bitumen, when
mixed with spruce gum, produced an excellent
caulking compound for canoes. Over the
following century many travelers viewed the
tar oozing from the rock and sand formation
along the riverbank. While some became captivated
by this potential El Dorado in the
northern wilderness, until the 1960s the region
remained too remote to attract much
more than scientific curiosity, especially when
there seemed to be promising possibilities in
more accessible areas.

The first indication of southern Alberta's
petroleum potential came in 1883 and was the
unexpected by-product of the Canadian Pacific
Railway's search for water along its right-of-
way through the dry belt west of Medicine
Hat. The company's drilling crew hit a natural
gas pocket, and, to their misfortune, the gas
ignited and consumed the drilling rig in a
great ball of fire. Subsequent discoveries confirmed
the location of significant gas fields in
the Medicine Hat area, and in 1904 a municipal
natural gas company was organized to
serve residential and commercial customers.
By 1912 both Lethbridge and Calgary were
connected by pipeline to southern Alberta's
prolific new gas fields. From this humble beginning
the industry grew on the strength of
continued gas field discoveries and an expanding
pipeline network that by the late
1950s spanned the continent.

The recognition that oil could be expected
to exist in combination with natural gas
prompted a parallel but prolonged search that
failed to yield a significant result until the
"Dingman discovery" in 1914. Located a short
distance southwest of Calgary, the discovery
identified what soon became known as the
Turner Valley oil field and launched a speculative
frenzy that distinguished western Canada's
first oil boom. Speculative excess and disappointing
results in the field brought the boom
to a quick end. Starved for capital, legitimate
local petroleum companies made little progress
over the following decade.

Further development of the field awaited the
arrival of outside capital, which eventually
came with Imperial Oil, a subsidiary of Standard
Oil of New Jersey. Imperial's interest was
stimulated as much by the activities of archrival
Shell as by the Dingman discovery. In
1920, to protect its interests in western and
northern Canada, Imperial launched an energetic
exploration and drilling program along
the Mackenzie River in the Northwest Territories,
in east-central Alberta, and, under the
direction of a new subsidiary company, Royalite
Oil Ltd., in the Turner Valley area. Success
came first in the North with an important
strike at Fort Norman in August 1920, but the
location was far too remote, and interest was
not rekindled until World War II. Drilling activity
in east-central Alberta was unrewarded,
but in the Turner Valley, on October 24, 1924,
Royalite No. 4 struck oil and ignited Alberta's
second oil boom. By year's end thirty-four
companies were drilling, and, supported by
modest finds, development continued through
the 1930s. Although production was very small
by Texas or Oklahoma standards, it was sufficient to meet regional demand and to turn Calgary
into a minor refining center. Perhaps
more important, field development and growing
production by 1938 compelled the creation
of Alberta's Petroleum and Natural Gas Conservation Board to address various matters of
oil field management, especially the contentious
issues of market sharing and "waste" gas
flaring.

The appointment of the first board chairman,
W. F. Knode, formerly of the Texas Railroad
Commission, underlines the extent of
American influence during the first decades of
petroleum production and regulation in western
Canada. An important factor shaping the
social and regulatory environment, one that
distinguishes the Canadian experience, is that,
unlike their U.S. cousins, the great majority of
Canadian homesteaders held only surface title
to their farm and ranch lands. Mineral rights
for the most part were retained by the crown,
which meant not only a different pattern in the
distribution of oil wealth but also that Knode
and subsequent Alberta regulators did not
have to contend with thousands of ranchers
and farmers who held mineral rights and who
were inclined to vociferously resist conservation
or other measures that would restrict development
and production. The regulatory
tradition that Knode and his colleagues put in
place was perhaps Turner Valley's most important
legacy in shaping the pattern of development
and production in the big oil fields discovered
after World War II.

The turning-point discovery that Albertans
had been waiting for since 1914 occurred on
February 13, 1947. Located about fifteen miles
southwest of Edmonton, Imperial Oil's Leduc
No. 1 discovered a prolific new oil field, and
the dramatic blowout and fire at Atlantic No. 3
a few months later signaled to the world that
the Alberta discovery was in the big league.
Turner Valley companies were joined by a host
of newcomers from Oklahoma, Texas, and
California. The string of big finds that quickly
followed launched the province on an oil
boom that, with but a few brief interruptions,
has continued to the present.

While Alberta's oil and natural gas emerged
as a significant contributor to Canada's postwar
economic prosperity, the impact at the
provincial level was of much greater significance.
The provincial economy was transformed.
By 1960 the value of exported oil and
gas products surpassed the returns earned
from agriculture. Alberta's burgeoning oilfired
economy produced the fastest population
growth rate of any Canadian province
and accelerated the urbanization trend that
had begun well before Leduc. The growing
petroleum industry shifted the economic center
of gravity from the eastern to the western
edge of the Prairie region, and Calgary captured
Winnipeg's historic role as the region's
dominant metropolis.

If oil transformed Alberta's economy, it did
not alter the province's political agenda. The
politics of wheat and the politics of oil were not
dissimilar. Sustained by petroleum revenues
and rock-solid electoral support, Alberta's premiers
emerged as formidable spokespersons
for western and, especially, Alberta's interests.
This hypersensitivity is manifest in the battery
of provincial legislation put forward with the
intent of forestalling federal interference in the
management of the province's oil and gas resources.
The bitter confrontation between Alberta
and Ottawa over the latter's imposition
of the National Energy Policy (1980) ultimately
led to a constitutional amendment (section
92A) affirming exclusive provincial control
over the exploration, development, and management
of nonrenewable natural resources.
Alberta's interests, shaped by both the needs of
the new economy and historical memory, coalesced
to reinforce in post-Leduc Alberta the
broad sense of alienation that had developed
throughout the preceding decades of agrarian
protest.

See also POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT: Alberta.


David H. Breen
University of British Columbia




Breen, David H. Alberta's Petroleum Industry and the Conservation Board. Edmonton: University of Alberta Press,
1993. Doern, G. Bruce, and Glen Toner. The Politics of Energy. Toronto: Methuen, 1985. Smith, Philip. The Treasure-Seekers: The Men Who Built Home Oil. Toronto:
Macmillan of Canada, 1978.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>