<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.law.030</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Masterson, Bat (1853-1921)</field>
      <field name="author">DeArment, Robert K.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MASTERSON, BAT (1853-1921)

The man destined to achieve fame and notoriety
as Bat Masterson, frontiersman, lawman,
and gunfighter on the frontiers of Kansas and
Texas, was born at Henryville, Quebec, Canada,
on November 26, 1853. Christened Bartholomew
and called Bart or Bat by his family,
he chose to use the name William Barclay
Masterson throughout his life.

Masterson grew up on farms in New York,
Illinois, and Kansas. He left his father's farm
in Sedgwick County, Kansas, in 1871 to hunt
buffalo and soon gained a reputation as a dead
shot and intrepid frontiersman. In June 1874
he was the youngest of twenty-eight buffalo
hunters at Adobe Walls, Texas, who withstood
an attack and siege by several hundred warriors
led by Quanah Parker. Masterson served
as a civilian scout in the Red River War of
1874-75. A shooting on January 24, 1876, at
Sweetwater (now Mobeetie), Texas, was the
basis for his gunfighter reputation. He killed a
soldier after the man shot a woman to death
and severely wounded Masterson. He served
as a city policeman at Dodge City, Kansas,
during that town's most uproarious years and
was elected sheriff of Ford County before
reaching the age of twenty-four. On April 9,
1878, after his brother, Dodge City marshal Ed
Masterson, was shot and killed, he avenged
that murder by killing one and wounding another
of the assailants.

Residing primarily in Colorado after 1880,
Masterson returned to Dodge City frequently,
most notably as a participant in an 1881 gunfight
in the town's plaza in which he shot and
wounded a local saloon man and as a member
(with Wyatt Earp and other gunmen) of
the Dodge City Peace Commission formed in
1883 to protect the interests of gambler Luke
Short. In 1902 Masterson left Denver for New
York City, where he became a well-known
boxing authority and sports columnist. He
died on October 25, 1921, in New York and is
buried there.

See also IMAGES AND ICONS: Dodge City, Kansas; Gunslingers / WAR: Adobe Walls, Battle of.


Robert K. DeArment
Sylvania, Ohio




DeArment, Robert K. Bat Masterson: The Man and the Legend. Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1979.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>