<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.na.058</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Languages</field>
      <field name="author">Awakuni-Swetland, Mark J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 





LANGUAGES

Classification of Native Languages of the Great Plains


CADDOAN
Arikara
Pawnee
Kitsai
Wichita
Caddo
Jumano (?)



ATHAPASKAN
Sarcee
Kiowa Apache
Jicarilla
Lipan
Jumano (?)



SIOUAN
Mandan
Hidatsa
Crow
Assiniboine
Stoney
Santee-Sisseton
Yankton-Yanktonai
Teton
Iowa
Otoe
Missouria
Winnebago*
Omaha
Ponca
Osage
Kanza (Kaw)
Quapaw*



ALGONQUIAN
Blackfoot
Arapaho
Atsina
Cheyenne
Sutai
Plains Cree
Plains Ojibwa
Kickapoo*
Fox-Sauk*
Peoria*
Miami*
Kaskaskia*
Ottawa*
Potawatomi*
Shawnee*
Delaware*



IROQUOIAN
Cherokee*
Seneca*
Wyandotte*



MUSCOGEAN
Choctaw*
Chickasaw*
Creek*
Seminole*



UTO-AZTECAN
Shoshone
Comanche
Jumano (?)



TANOAN
Kiowa
Jumano (?)



KLAMATH-MODOC
Modec*



SAHAPTIAN
Nez Perce*



ISOLATES
Tonkawa


* Removed to Great Plains by federal order

The Great Plains has long been the home to a
multitude of distinct Native voices. The language
of each family, band, community, or
nation has developed to embrace and describe
a dynamic life. Through their oral tradition,
communities transmit a rich heritage of spiritual,
historical, and practical knowledge to
their children. The tools of archeologists, linguists,
and historians can be combined with
the memories of Native elders to study the
rise, decline, and survival of these linguistically
diverse communities. One useful linguistic
device for organizing the many languages
of the Great Plains is the "family." It works
by placing languages and dialects into groups
that exhibit features suggesting a common linguistic
origin at some time in the past. Not all
languages can be so easily categorized. For example,
the Jumano language family of the
Southern Plains has been variously identified
as sharing features with the Athapaskan, Caddoan,
Uto-Aztecan, and more recently, Tanoan
language families.

Prior to the European advent of the Great
Plains in the 1500s, two language families, Caddoan
and Siouan, were already long represented
in the region, and several others could be found
along the perimeter. Caddoan speakers are
some of the oldest communities of the region to
survive into contemporary times. They were
distributed from the Southern Plains (Wichitas,
Caddos, and Kitsais), through the Central Plains
(Pawnees), to the Missouri River in the Dakotas
(Arikaras). Siouian speakers were the Mandans
and Hidatsas of the middle Missouri River and
the Crows of the Montana Plains. Except for the
Crows, these Caddoan and Siouan speakers
were agriculturalists residing near rivers.

Around the margins of the Great Plains were
many communities taking seasonal advantage
of bison resources. They represented a variety of
language families, including Siouan speakers
in the north and eastern periphery, Apachean
Athapaskan speakers along the western edge,
Uto-Aztecan and Tanoan speakers penetrating
from the western mountains and moving southward,
Algonquian speakers across the northern
regions, and some linguistic isolates such as the
Tonkawas in the south. The introduction and
spread of the horse after the 1750s, together with
increasing pressures from European American
interests, encouraged many of these groups to
become full-time Plains residents. Some entered
into trading arrangements with Plains agriculturalists,
Puebloans, or Spanish settlements.
Communication between these diverse groups
was facilitated by fictive kinship relations established
through ceremonial adoptions, intermarriage,
sign language, and the multilingual abilities
of many Plains residents.

In the 1800s the equestrian nomadic bison
hunters came to dominate the Great Plains.
Their lifestyle became the stereotyped image
of the region, including their use of sign language
for intergroup communication. While
there is no evidence of a single unified sign
system, the dynamics of trade, alliances, and
warfare created a need for a rich system of
nonverbal communication. The greater mobility
and contact with linguistically diverse
groups in the Great Plains made sign language
a necessity. Short-term alliances, such as the
one among the Cheyennes, Sioux, Arapahos,
Kiowas, Comanches, Apaches, and others
against the Utes, may have served to standardize
to some degree the gesture language in use
by Plains residents.

After 1830 the federal government sanctioned
the forced removal of many eastern, and some
western, Native American communities into the
Great Plains, which dramatically increased the
linguistic diversity of the region, adding new
voices from the Siouan, Algonquian, Muscogean,
Iroquoian, Klamath-Modoc, and Sahaptian
language families. However, catastrophic
epidemics and other pressures from
both inside and outside of the Native communities
worked against the survival of Indigenous
languages. Missionary and federal strategies
of assimilation operated to vilify and
reduce the use of Native languages and the
cultural identities and communities they supported.
The ongoing effect of such policies has
been the slow strangulation of many Native
voices. Languages such as Kitsai, Lipan, Missouri,
Quapaw, and Tonkawa have been silenced,
while many more have been weakened
to a whisper.

Language helps to carry a people's history,
culture, worldview, and wisdom. It is our great
fortune that a diversity of Native languages has
survived in the Great Plains. Geographic isolation
and local willpower have assisted some
communities in resisting assimilation to an
English-only existence. Many more communities
are joining a rising tide of Native American
language awareness, maintenance, and revival
efforts. However, their success is not
guaranteed. Revival strategies vary between
communities, due to differences in local needs,
values, and resources. All are faced with the
daunting task of securing a place for their
voices when the mainstream language has such
an overwhelming presence. Without vibrant
Native voices lifting into the air with song,
story, and prayer, how can we speak to our
children about the history of the Great Plains?


Mark J. Awakuni-Swetland
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Campbell, Lyle, and Marianne Mithun, eds. The Languages
of Native America: Historical and Comparative Assessment.
Austin: University of Texas Press, 1979. Hollow,
Robert C., and Douglas R. Parks. "Studies in Plains Linguistics:
A Review." In Anthropology on the Great Plains,
edited by W. Raymond Wood and Margot Liberty. Lincoln:
University of Nebraska Press, 1980: 98–109. Schlesier,
Karl H., ed. Plains Indians, A.D. 500–1500: The Archaeological
Past of Historic Groups. Norman: University of Oklahoma
Press, 1994.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>