<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.058</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Norris, George W. (1861-1944)</field>
      <field name="author">Landis, David</field>
      <field name="text">

 




NORRIS, GEORGE W. (1861-1944)

George William Norris represented Nebraska
for forty years in the House of Representatives
and U.S. Senate, passing significant liberal legislation
as a maverick Republican and Independent.
Norris was born on July 11, 1861, near
Clyde, Ohio. He grew up on his family farm,
where he learned temperance, fear of debt,
and Lincoln Republicanism from his widowed
mother. After graduating from Northern Indiana
Normal School (later Valparaiso University),
George failed as a lawyer in Walla
Walla, Washington, and Beatrice, Nebraska,
before moving to Beaver City and then McCook, Nebraska, where he married the daughter
of a prominent family and became county
attorney and then district judge.

In 1902 he was elected as a Republican to
Congress; he spent the next ten years in growing
disenchantment with Republican leaders
and extreme partisanship. He led a revolt of
insurgents and Democrats to limit the powers
of the Speaker of the House, Republican Joe
Cannon, in 1910, which earned Norris a chapter
in John Kennedy's Profiles in Courage. Election
to the Senate in 1912, again as a Republican,
gave Norris a national platform as a
political and economic democrat often at odds
with Republican leadership. He supported unreservedly
the initiative, referendum, recall, a
strong civil service, and abolishing the Electoral
College and the poll tax. He opposed the
excesses of partisanship.

Endorsing Franklin Roosevelt's successful
candidacy in 1932 changed Norris's role from
gadfly critic to architect of major legislation.
Economic democracy was the recurring theme
of Norris's legislation. The Norris-LaGuardia
Act of 1932 curtailed federal court injunctions
against labor unions. Norris introduced and
enabled passage that same year of the Twentieth
Amendment to the U.S. Constitution,
which ended lame-duck sessions of Congress,
notorious for special interest influence.

Norris took his greatest satisfaction from
passage of the Tennessee Valley Authority Act
in 1933, which harnessed hydroelectric power
under public ownership. Rural electric cooperatives
brought light and power to American
farms under the Norris-Rayburn Act of 1936.
In Nebraska, Norris successfully led the 1934
petition drive for a nonpartisan unicameral to
limit special interest and party boss influence.
His final Senate term was as an Independent,
and he lost his 1942 reelection bid. An autobiography,
The Fighting Liberal, was finished
eight weeks before his death at McCook on
September 2, 1944.


David Landis
Nebraska Legislature




Lowitt, Richard. George W. Norris: The Making of a Progressive,
1861–1912. Westport CT: Greenwood Press, 1963.
Lowitt, Richard. George W. Norris: The Persistence of a
Progressive, 1913–1933. Chicago: University of Illinois
Press, 1971. Lowitt, Richard. George W. Norris: The Triumph
of a Progressive. Chicago: University of Illinois Press,
1978.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>