<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.na.093</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Quapaws</field>
      <field name="author">Baird, W. David</field>
      <field name="text">

 




QUAPAWS

When first encountered by Europeans in the
1670s, some 15,000 to 20,000 Quapaws resided
in four permanent villages near the confluence
of the Mississippi and Arkansas Rivers. They
practiced a mixed economy of agriculture and
hunting. Socially they were divided into a myriad
of patrilineal clans and subclans. Known to
their Dhegiha-branch Sioux kinsmen (the Osages,
Omahas, Kanzas, and Poncas) as Ugaxpa,
or "Downstream People," the Quapaws entered
into trading and military alliances first
with the French and then with the Spanish.
The benefits of these relationships hardly compensated
for the costs of altered lifeways, weakened
social structures, and decimated population
(they were reduced to 575 persons by
1800).

In 1803, when the United States acquired
Louisiana, American authorities saw the Quapaws
as impediments to national expansion.
Thirty years later they forced the tribe, led by
Chief Heckaton, to remove from its Arkansas
homeland to a 150-square-mile reservation in
northeastern Oklahoma. The traumatic relocation
to Indian Territory divided the tribe
into two main groups, one living on the reservation
and the other along the Canadian
River. Most tribespeople engaged in bison
hunting; a few farmed successfully and sent
their children to missionary schools.

Tribal fortunes changed markedly with the
onset of the American Civil War. Although
tribal chiefs War-te-she and Ki-he-cah-te-da
signed a treaty with the Confederacy in 1861,
within a year the bands had retreated to Kansas
with other Indians sympathetic to the
Union. There the refugees suffered four years
of painful deprivation, resulting in the deaths
of one-half of the tribe.

The post–Civil War years brought little relief.
In an 1867 treaty with the United States,
tribal leaders exchanged reservation land for
annuity payments and educational stipends.
Led by the last hereditary chief of the Quapaws,
Tallchief, a majority of the tribespeople left
the reservation to live with their Osage kinsmen.
Those who remained leased the domain
to non-Indian agriculturists and admitted
"homeless" Indians to tribal citizenship. In
1893, fearing forfeiture of the reservation,
Quapaw leaders John Medicine and Abner W.
Abrams took the unprecedented action of allotting
it in 240-acre parcels to 234 enrolled
members of the tribe. Federal government approval
came after the fact.

In the 1920s and 1930s the discovery of rich
lead and zinc deposits on some individual allotments
changed the course of Quapaw history.
Because wealthy allottees were systematically
defrauded, the federal government
in 1908 revoked fraudulent leases, obtained
higher royalties, and shielded Indian income
from local, state, and federal taxes. But this
intervention also brought federal control of
mining royalties paid to individual allottees.
The hated bureaucratic restrictions, however,
did not prevent the Quapaws from engaging in
uncontrolled spending that left most of them
in poverty by 1940. Nor did it prevent a significant
number of the wealthy allottees, led by
Chief Victor Griffin, from embracing and supporting
the Big Moon peyote cult, which had
been introduced by John "Moonhead" Wilson
in the 1890s.

Because the status quo served the Quapaw
leadership well, it rejected the Indian Reorganization
Act of 1934 and then refused to organize
under the terms of the Oklahoma Indian
Welfare Act enacted two years later. The leadership
did file a claim under the provisions of
the Indian Claims Commission Act of 1946,
an action that in 1954 resulted in a favorable
judgment of nearly $1 million. In 1961 that
money was divided among 1,199 individual
Quapaws.

The commission award revitalized the Quapaws
both as a people and as a community.
Organized in 1956 as the Business Committee,
the tribal government adroitly diverted termination
pressures in the 1950s. At the beginning
of the twenty-first century it manages varying
enterprises ranging from a bingo parlor to a
quick-stop gasoline station, a nationally acclaimed
powwow, and a gleaming new office
building southeast of Quapaw, Oklahoma.


W. David Baird
Pepperdine University



Baird, W. David. The Quapaw Indians: A History of the
Downstream People. Norman: University of Oklahoma
Press, 1980. Baird, W. David. The Quapaws. New York:
Chelsea House, 1989.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>