<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.tra.012</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Electric Interurban Railways</field>
      <field name="author">Gery, Alan H.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ELECTRIC INTERURBAN RAILWAYS

Twenty electric interurban railways operated
during the early twentieth century in the
Great Plains. Most were built in the early
1900s, with commuters generating most of the
revenue. The light-rail interurbans used self-propelled
trolley cars resembling standard
streetcars. Unfortunately for the largely local
owners, almost all interurbans fell victim to a
combination of the Great Depression and the
rise of the automobile.

Half of the Great Plains interurban companies
and almost half of the 1,000 miles of
track were on the eastern edge of the Great
Plains in the Dallas and Kansas City, Missouri,
areas. Dallas had 350 miles of tracks, most of
them belonging to the Texas Electric Railroad,
which stretched north to Denison and south
to Waco. Kansas City had four short interurban
railways extending to Lawrence, Leavenworth,
and suburban Olathe and Zarah.

The interurbans were a series of unconnected
parts. Only four were built in the vast
area of Nebraska, South Dakota, North Dakota,
and the Prairie Provinces. In Manitoba, a
road connected Winnipeg to beach resorts on
Lake Winnipeg. South Dakota had the four-mile-long
Deadwood Central, and Omaha had
two glorified streetcar lines. Half a dozen other
interurbans ran in Kansas and Oklahoma:
small systems connected Pittsburg, Kansas,
with Joplin, Missouri, and the seventy-seven-mile-long
Union Electric Railway thrust south
from Parsons, Kansas, to Nowata, Oklahoma.
At the advent of interurbans, steam railroads
already ran through just about all of the important
urban centers, so no pressing need
existed for an interurban network. Few of the
region's interurbans came close to achieving
the inexpensive, frequent, and fast service
promised by their promoters.


Lawrence H. Larsen
University of Missouri-Kansas City




Hilton, George W., and John F. Due. The Electric Interurban
Railways in America. Stanford CA: Stanford University
Press, 1960.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>