<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.afam.034</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Parks, Gordon (b. 1912)</field>
      <field name="author">Kerstetter, Todd M.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




PARKS, GORDON (b. 1912)


Gordon Parks, in the director's chair


Gordon Parks overcame barriers of race and
poverty to become a noted photographer,
writer, filmmaker, composer, and painter. He
was born on November 30, 1912, and grew up
the youngest of fifteen children in a poor farm
family in Fort Scott, Kansas. During his midteens
his mother's death led him to leave
Kansas to live with relatives in St. Paul, Minnesota.
He stayed there briefly before entering
a nomadic phase during which he traveled
through much of the United States and later
the world. Parks played piano in brothels,
learned to play the trumpet, and began composing
music while trying to finish high
school. A stint singing and composing for a
band took him to New York City. When the
band's demise left him stranded and penniless,
he joined the Civilian Conservation
Corps in 1933. He later worked as a waiter on
the North Coast Limited, a luxury train that
ran from Chicago to Seattle.

In 1938, within a year of buying his first
camera at a pawnshop, Parks had his first photographic
exhibit in an Eastman Kodak store
in Minneapolis. He quickly developed his
photographic skills through incessant work,
including shooting events at Chicago's South
Side Community Art Center, fashion spreads
for department stores, portraits of wealthy
families, and photo essays about poverty on
Chicago's South Side. His work documenting
poverty earned Parks a Julius Rosenwald fellowship,
which he used to train with Roy
Emerson Stryker at the Farm Security Administration
(FSA) in Washington DC. After Parks
left the FSA he moved to Harlem and freelanced
for Glamour and Vogue. He joined Life
in 1948 and contributed to the magazine for
more than twenty years. Parks launched his
publishing career in 1947 with Flash Photography,
an instruction manual. He later wrote a
novel, The Learning Tree (1963), about growing
up as an African American in rural Kansas,
various books of poetry and photographs, and
two memoirs, A Choice of Weapons (1966) and
Voices in the Mirror: An Autobiography (1990).

Parks began consulting in the film industry
during the 1950s and became the first black
director of a major motion picture when he
brought The Learning Tree to the screen in
1969 for Warner Brothers–Seven Arts. He
continued directing with Shaft (1971), Shaft's Big Score (1972), Super Cops (1974), Leadbelly
(1976), and The Odyssey of Solomon Northrup
(1983), among others. In addition to directing,
Parks wrote the screenplay and musical score
for The Learning Tree and wrote the score for
Shaft's Big Score. He also composed a piano
concerto and the music and libretto for Martin,
a five-act ballet tribute to Martin Luther
King Jr. In recent years Parks has moved to
abstract color photography, using paint and
computer technology to alter his photos.



Todd M. Kerstetter
Texas Christian University




Parks, Gordon. A Choice of Weapons. New York: Harper
and Row, 1966. Parks, Gordon. Half Past Autumn: A Retrospective.
Boston: Bullfinch Press, 1997. Parks, Gordon.
Voices in the Mirror: An Autobiography. New York: Doubleday,
1990.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>