<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.na.035</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Hidatsas</field>
      <field name="author">Cox, J. Wendel</field>
      <field name="text">

 




HIDATSAS

The Hidatsas, an Indian people of the Northern
Plains, have lived in what is now westcentral
North Dakota for nearly a millennium.
The name "Hidatsa," which refers to
the willows growing on Missouri River sandbars,
was once applied to a single band but
later encompassed the entire people. Along
with the Mandans and the Arikaras, the Hidatsas
were the northernmost Plains people to
construct large, permanent earth lodge villages
and to practice agriculture intensively.
Composed in the early historic era of three
closely related bands–the Hidatsa-proper,
Awatixa, and Awaxawi–each spoke a distinct
dialect of Siouan language and maintained
unique identities and traditions of separate
origin. Awaxawi and Hidatsa-proper traditions
describe the people emerging from an
underground world near a large body of water,
often identified with Devils Lake in eastern
North Dakota, and a migration and later
meeting with the Mandans, a people with
whom the Hidatsa have been intimately associated
to the present day. The Awatixa, in contrast,
maintain they have always resided on the
Missouri River.

During the late eighteenth and early nineteenth
centuries, when European and European
American observers began to record their
encounters with Northern Plains Indians, the
Hidatsas lived in three villages perched on
bluffs near the junction of the Knife and Missouri
Rivers. Archeologists now believe the
Hidatsas, specifically the Awatixa, had established
themselves in the area as early as 1100
a.d. Although Hidatsas traveled widely and
maintained extensive ties, especially trade ties,
to other peoples throughout the Northern
Plains and beyond, their villages and river valley
environs remained at the heart of their
collective life. Villages, with their large numbers
of domed, multifamily earth lodges, were
principally the domain of Hidatsa women, as
well as the children and elderly in their care.
For men, villages were a place of return and
departure, as their lives frequently led them
abroad for hunting and raiding. Rivers provided
water, clay for pottery, places for recreation
and play, and avenues for travel. Spring
floods nourished the river-bottom gardens
cultivated by Hidatsa women that yielded an
abundance of corn, squash, beans, and sunflowers
for their own consumption and for an
extensive trade. Men found ample game, including
white-tailed deer, along wooded bottoms,
but they also turned to the High Plains
beyond to hunt bison and pronghorn antelope
with friends and family in semiannual hunts.

Clans and societies incorporated each Hidatsa
person and bound them together in mutual
obligation while also providing care,
identity, and community. Membership in the
seven or eight clans active in the historic era
was matrilineal and cut across the three Hidatsa
groups, integrating these distinct communities.
Men's and women's societies provided
various social services, and membership
changed over the course of an individual's life.
Likewise, religious observation and devotion
were woven throughout daily life. The Hidatsas
recognized their world as variously endowed
with spirits to be acknowledged and
respected, and prayer was offered frequently
in a recognition of, and request for, assistance
from the power inherent in all things. Individuals,
often male, pursued visions and sought
guidance even in childhood, presenting acts of
self-sacrifice as evidence of their reverence
and purpose. Rewarded with a successful vision,
an individual would make a small personal
bundle as a representation of powers to
be called upon for assistance. Larger bundles,
associated with clans or societies, afforded
power and protection but required observation
of unique ritual care by a trained owner.

The encounter with European and, later,
European American newcomers placed unprecedented
challenges before the Hidatsas.
Some aspects of change were welcome, including
the adoption of horses and the expansion
of the long-established Aboriginal trade network
to incorporate newcomers. But disease,
decline in population, and the necessity of defense
from the more numerous Sioux (Lakotas)
proved especially daunting. Before the
cycle of epidemics, the Hidatsas may have
numbered 5,000 to 6,000 people, but at least as
early as the 1780s their population began to
decline. In 1837 a smallpox epidemic killed half
of the Hidatsa people in a matter of months,
leaving only 1,200 to 1,400 survivors. These
losses, combined with even more devastating
losses suffered by the Mandans, led to the establishment
of a single, shared village, Likea-
Fishhook, in 1845. There the Mandans and
Hidatsas were joined by the Arikaras in 1862. In
1870 the three peoples were placed on the
eight-million-acre Fort Berthold Reservation
in present-day central North Dakota. By the
end of the nineteenth century, the Hidatsa
population had declined to some 400 people.

Early in the 1880s, in keeping with the government's
assimilation policy, the Hidatsas,
Mandans, and Arikaras were encouraged to
abandon Like-a-Fishhook Village and to establish
family farms on individual allotments.
While some Hidatsa families chose to do so,
many continued to reside in small towns and
communities–Lucky Mound, Shell Creek,
and Independence–established close to the
Missouri River, where they pursued ranching
and other enterprises. The size of the reservation
was reduced to less than one million acres
by allotments.

The 1930s saw a respite from overt demands
for assimilation and a revision of Fort Berthold's
tribal government as the Three A.liated
Tribes under the Indian Reorganization
Act (IRA) of 1934. But challenges continued.
With the construction of Garrison Dam during
the 1950s, some 156,000 acres of Fort Berthold
Reservation, home to 90 percent of the
tribal community, were flooded. Tribal leaders
had resisted the project but finally yielded to
congressional pressure and accepted a twelve-million-
dollar compensation package. Relocation
continued even as the water rose, and
many Hidatsas moved to the town of Mandaree.
An additional $143 million was appropriated
by Congress in 1992, but the dislocation
and disruption caused by the Garrison
Dam are felt to this day.

See also: WATER: Pick-Sloan Plan.


J. Wendel Cox
Arizona State University




Ahler, Stanley A., Thomas D. Thiessen, and Michael K.
Trimble. People of the Willows: The Prehistory and Early
History of the Hidatsa Indians. Grand Forks: University of
North Dakota Press, 1991. Gilman, Carolyn, and Mary
Jane Schneider. The Way to Independence: Memories of a
Hidatsa Indian Family, 1840–1920. St. Paul: Minnesota
Historical Society Press, 1987. Meyer, Roy W. The Village
Indians of the Upper Missouri: The Mandans, Hidatsas, and
Arikaras. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1977.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>