<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.gen.031</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Sacagawea (ca. 1780-1812)</field>
      <field name="author">Parsons, Gerald M.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SACAGAWEA (ca. 1780-1812)

"Sacagawea statue by Leonard Crunelle, Bismarck, ND, 2004-in front of the North Dakota State Capitol"


The only woman on Lewis and Clark's expedition,
Sacagawea was a young Shoshone who
had been captured by Hidatsa raiders near the
three forks of the Missouri River about 1800.
She married trader Toussaint Charbonneau
sometime before 1804. A son, Jean Baptiste,
called "Pomp" by Clark, was born to them in
February of 1805. Together, the family traveled
from the Mandan-Hidatsa villages in presentday
North Dakota to the Pacific and back.

Sacagawea has been the object of considerable
myth and misinformation; her contributions
to the expedition have been both exaggerated
and minimized. Clark thought more of
her contributions than did Lewis, though one
must consider here the eighteenth-century
tendency to discount contributions of nonwhite
peoples. In a letter to Charbonneau after
the expedition, Clark wrote, "Your woman diserved
a greater reward for her attention and
services on that rout than we had in our power
to give her." Lewis's view was more dismissive:
"If she has enough to eat and a few trinkets
I believe she would be perfectly content anywhere."

In fact, Sacagawea's contributions were real:
she provided important geographical data to
the party at various times, she helped as translator
with certain tribes, she rescued important
documents during a canoe mishap in May
1805, and, perhaps most important, she gave a
friendlier face to the Corps of Discovery. Clark
wrote that she "reconsiles all the Indians, as to
our friendly intentions, a woman with a party
of men is a token of peace."

Sacagawea died of a "putrid fever" in
December 1812 near present-day Mobridge,
South Dakota, at about age thirty-two. Jean
Baptiste and Sacagawea's daughter, Lizette,
lived with Clark at St. Louis for a time.

See also EUROPEAN AMERICANS: \
Lewis and Clark.


Gerald M. Parsons
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




McMurtry, Larry, "Sacagawea's Nickname." New York Review of Books 48 (September 20, 2001): 71–72. Moulton,
Gary, ed. The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition. 13
vols. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1983–2001.
Ronda, James P. Lewis and Clark among the Indians. Lincoln:
University of Nebraska Press, 1984.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>