<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.sr.050</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Sport Hunting</field>
      <field name="author">Taylor, J. Scott</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SPORT HUNTING

Although the cultural influence of hunting today
bears little resemblance to that experienced
by Native Americans prior to European
American settlement, the human desire to
hunt still dictates the seasonal activities of millions
of Great Plains inhabitants. These outings
not only affect hunters personally but also
generate revenue for rural economies and political
momentum for wildlife conservation.

As elsewhere, hunting in the Great Plains is
shaped by the diversity of game species present.
Owing to the region's paucity of exclusive
endemic bird and mammal species (i.e., those
found in the region and nowhere else), only
greater and lesser prairie chickens are hunted
exclusively in the Great Plains. However, because
the Plains encompass a zone where both
eastern and western species intermingle, the
region boasts perhaps the richest array of
game animals and hunting opportunities in
North America. Primary large game mammals
include white-tailed deer, mule deer, and
pronghorn antelope, with elk, moose, and
bighorn sheep occurring mainly in the montane
western or wooded northern peripheries
of the region. Furbearers such as coyote and
raccoon and small mammals such as cottontails
and fox squirrel are also widely hunted.
Primary game birds include ring-necked
pheasant, northern bobwhite, prairie grouse
(sharp-tailed grouse, sage grouse, and greater
and lesser prairie chickens), gray partridge,
scaled quail, wild turkey, mourning dove,
sandhill crane, and several species of ducks
and geese.

Opportunities to pursue these species are
enjoyed by more than two million hunters living
in states and provinces lying entirely or
partly within the Great Plains and by hundreds
of thousands more traveling from outside the
region. In the Plains states and provinces,
about 10 percent of the resident population
hunts (more than 90 percent of them males),
spending a total of 45 million days afield per
year. About 74 percent of Plains states hunters
pursue big game, 42 percent pursue resident
small game birds and mammals, and 28 percent
hunt migratory birds. In all, hunters
spend more than $3.7 billion per year during
the course of their activities in the Great Plains.

The considerable economic and social impacts
of hunting have affected regional biodiversity
and governmental responsibilities
for wildlife conservation. License fees and
excise taxes paid on hunting equipment are
spent by state and provincial wildlife agencies
to buy land for habitat protection and public
access, improve habitat on private land, and
enforce wildlife-related laws. These funds
have also been used to restore species such as
elk and wild turkey in areas of the Great Plains
where they had been absent for decades. Furthermore,
the ring-necked pheasant and gray
partridge, native to Asia and Europe, respectively,
were introduced in the Great Plains by
wildlife agencies and private individuals in the
early 1900s to provide additional hunting opportunities.
Both species thrived in agricultural
areas not generally habitable by native
game birds and have become firmly established.
In particular, the ring-necked pheasant
is now perhaps the most ubiquitous and well
recognized of the region's small game species
and is responsible for much of the revenue
and days afield associated with Great Plains
upland bird hunting. As a rather ironic testament
to its cultural importance, the Asian native
is the state bird of South Dakota.

Hunting-related customs and laws vary
markedly within the Great Plains. For example,
Kansas hunters traditionally shoot prairie
chickens in late fall as they fly into crop fields
to feed, whereas Nebraskans traditionally
walk through rangeland and shoot them as
they flush. However, perhaps most important
are regional differences in methods used to
gain access to hunt on private land, because
this is where most hunting occurs in the Great
Plains. In Texas, hunters (particularly those
pursuing deer, quail, and turkey) are generally
expected not only to gain trespass permission
but also to pay the landowner a daily or seasonal
access fee. Conversely, in North Dakota,
hunters may hunt private land without the
permission of the landowner unless the land
has been clearly posted otherwise. Obviously,
these variations in private land access can have
significant effects on hunter participation and
expenditures.

As might be expected from the diversity in
species and customs, there is also variation in
the reasons people hunt in the Plains. Residents
hunt as part of family or community
traditions, for food, to experience a tangible
connection with nature, or as a combination
of these and other motivations unique to each
individual. Hunters from outside the Plains
come for all the above reasons as well as to
take advantage of a quality or diversity of
hunting opportunities unavailable where they
live. Regardless of the reasons, people will
likely always hunt and in turn value places that
best provide the necessary ingredients for that
experience. Judged by this standard, the Great
Plains is one of the most highly regarded
hunting regions in North America.

See also NATIVE AMERICANS: Hunting.


J. Scott Taylor
Nebraska Game and Parks Commission




Federal-Provincial Task Force for the 1987 National Survey
on the Importance of Wildlife to Canadians. The Importance
of Wildlife to Canadians in 1987: Highlights of a National
Survey. Publ. CW66-103/1989E, 1989. Kellert, Stephen
R. "Attitudes and Characteristics of Hunters and
Antihunters." Transactions of the Forty-Third North American
Wildlife and Natural Resources Conference 43 (1978):
412–23. U.S. Department of the Interior, Fish and Wildlife
Service, and U.S. Department of Commerce, Bureau of
the Census. 1996 National Survey of Fishing, Hunting, and
Wildlife-Associated Recreation. Publ. FHW/96 NAT, 1998.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>