<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ct.044</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Roswell, New Mexico</field>
      <field name="author">Fleming, Elvis E.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ROSWELL, NEW MEXICO

Roswell, the largest New Mexico city in the
Great Plains, is situated in the Pecos Valley. It
grew out of the Indian wars and the cattle
kingdom of the 1860s. The army established
Fort Stanton in the Mescalero Apache country
in 1855 and the Bosque Redondo Reservation
in 1863 at Fort Sumner for Mescaleros and
Navajos. Texas cattlemen then drove their
longhorns into the territory to feed the soldiers
and Indians, with Charles Goodnight
and Oliver Loving blazing their famous trail in
1866, followed by John Chisum the next year.
In 1870 Van Smith built a hotel/saloon and a
store near the confluence of the Pecos River
and the Rio Hondo to serve the drovers passing
through on the cattle trails. He secured a
post office for Roswell in 1873 and named it for
his father. Smith did not advance the town,
but Joseph Lea arrived in 1877 and began to
develop the area. Later generations would call
him the "Father of Roswell."

There were few settlers in the area by 1890,
but events that stimulated growth began that
year. Well drillers discovered artesian water in
1890, and farmers started producing excellent
alfalfa and apples. Residents organized Chaves
County, incorporated Roswell (population
343 in 1890), and founded New Mexico Military
Institute, all in 1891. James Hagerman
built the Pecos Valley Railway to Roswell from
the south in 1894, then extended it northeastward
to Amarillo in 1899. With the local farming
and outside connections, Roswell's population
reached 2,049 in 1900, and the town
government was reorganized as a city in 1903.
Roswell continued to grow rapidly, reaching
6,172 in 1910 and 13,482 by 1940.

Roswell Army Airfield (RAAF) was opened
in 1942, and the Roswell prisoner of war camp
billeted 4,800 Germans during World War II.
In 1947 RAAF personnel recovered the remains
of what true believers call an unidentified
flying object. The "flying saucer" allegedly
crashed near Roswell, and the aliens on board
were killed–the so-called Roswell Incident.
raaf became Walker Air Force Base (WAFB) in
1948. Federal authorities installed missile silos
around WAFB in the early 1960s but soon dismantled
them. The closing of WAFB in June
1967 was a tremendous economic blow to Roswell,
as the declining population figures for
1960 and 1970—39,593 and 33,908—attest. Undeterred,
Roswell turned the former base into
the Roswell Industrial Air Center, with the
city airport, a bus factory, a college, and many
other installations. Retirees attracted by the
salubrious climate have also been an important
factor in the city's recovery.

Roswell's economy is still dependent upon
agriculture. Chaves County is a leading producer
of beef, sheep, wool, alfalfa, and cotton.
After 1960 area farmers added the production
of pecans, chilies, and especially dairy products.
More than forty dairies, most of them
established after 1980, operate in the Roswell
area. One of their markets is the world's largest
mozzarella factory near the city.

An annual celebration of the Roswell Incident
has made the city a tourist destination
and stimulated the building of a new convention
center and many new motels in the 1990s.
The population stood at 45,293 in 2000.

See also IMAGES AND ICONS: Roswell Aliens.


Elvis E. Fleming
Historical Society for Southeast New Mexico




Fleming, Elvis E., and Minor S. Huffman, eds. Roundup on the Pecos. Roswell NM: Chaves County Historical Society,
1978. Fleming, Elvis E., and Ernestine Chesser Williams.
Treasures of History. Roswell NM: Historical Society for
Southeast New Mexico, 1991, 1995. Shinkle, James D. Fifty Years of Roswell History, 1867-1917. Roswell NM: Hall-
Poorbaugh Press, 1964.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>