<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.sr.054</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Thorpe, Jim (1887-1953)</field>
      <field name="author">Cunningham, Russ</field>
      <field name="text">

 




THORPE, JIM (1887-1953)


Jim Thorpe


James Francis Thorpe, widely acknowledged
as the greatest American athlete of the twentieth
century, was born on May 28, 1887, near
Prague, Indian Territory, in what is now the
state of Oklahoma. His impoverished parents,
Hiram and Charlotte Thorpe, were members
of the Sauk and Fox Indian Nation. They gave
their son the Native American name Wa-Tho-Huk,
or Bright Path. To this day, Thorpe remains
the only American athlete to perform at
the world-class level in three major sports:
track and field, baseball, and football.

Thorpe grew up hunting, fishing, and
breaking horses with his twin brother, Charlie.
Charlie died of pneumonia at age nine,
and Thorpe came to believe he inherited a
measure of his brother's physical energy and
strength. Thorpe's mother died when he was a
teenager, and his father subsequently sent him
to the Carlisle Indian Industrial School in
Pennsylvania, one of several schools founded
by Richard Henry Pratt with the intent to assimilate
Native American youths into European
American society. After he enrolled at
Carlisle, Thorpe returned to the Great Plains
only intermittently throughout the remainder
of his life.

While playing halfback for Carlisle, Thorpe
earned football all-American honors in 1911
and 1912, leading Carlisle to the collegiate national
championship in 1912. Although he did
not become an official citizen of the United
States until 1917, Thorpe was a member of
the U.S. track and field team at the Olympic
Games of 1912 held in Stockholm, Sweden. His
gold medal performances in both the pentathlon
and decathlon inspired King Gustav V of
Sweden to remark, "You, Sir, are the greatest
athlete in the world." Thorpe's gold medals
were stripped from him by the Amateur Athletic
Association when it was revealed that he
had previously played semiprofessional baseball,
but these medals were posthumously restored
to him in 1982. It has been argued that
the worldwide publicity inspired by Thorpe's
accomplishments in Stockholm helped to ensure
the future viability of the Olympic Games.

After his triumph in Stockholm, Thorpe
signed a five-thousand-dollar contract to play
baseball with the New York Giants. He played
major-league baseball for seven seasons, with
New York, the Boston Braves, and the Cincinnati
Reds. In 1915 Thorpe agreed to play football
for the Canton Bulldogs. He led Canton
to unofficial world championships in 1916,
1917, and 1919. Thorpe went on to play football
for an assortment of teams, including the New
York Giants and the Chicago Cardinals. In
1920 he become the first president of the
American Football Association, which later
became the National Football League. After
retiring from sports, Thorpe worked as an actor
and casting director in Hollywood, lectured
around the country on Native American
culture, and during World War II served in the
U.S. Merchant Marine. He died in his trailer
in Lomita, California, on March 28, 1953. He is
buried in the eastern Pennsylvania town that
bears his name.

Thorpe was elected to the Pro Football Hall
of Fame in 1963. In 1999 the Associated Press
ranked Thorpe third on its list of the 100 top
athletes of the century, behind only Babe Ruth
and Michael Jordan. In the same year, both
the U.S. Senate and the U.S. House of Representatives
passed resolutions that designated
Thorpe "American Athlete of the Century."
Prior to the 2000 Super Bowl, ABC Sports honored
Thorpe as "Athlete of the Century," and
the National Football League renamed its
most valuable player award in his honor.


Russ Cunningham
Poway High School




Schoor, Gene. The Jim Thorpe Story: America's Greatest
Athlete. New York: Messner, 1951. Wheeler, Robert W. Jim
Thorpe: World's Greatest Athlete. Norman: University of
Oklahoma Press, 1981.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>