<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fil.013</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Cody, Iron Eyes (1907-1999)</field>
      <field name="author">Kilpatrick, Jacquelyn</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CODY, IRON EYES (1907-1999)

Iron Eyes Cody was best known as the "Crying
Indian" in the Keep America Beautiful advertising
campaign of the 1970s, but his Hollywood
credits span eight decades of film and
television history. His place and date of birth
are disputed, as is his ancestry, but he claimed
that he was born in Oklahoma in 1907 to Cree
and Cherokee ancestors. Whatever the case,
he spent most of his life in Hollywood or on
location. He is credited in forty-seven movies
and performed uncredited in at least that
many more. He not only acted in but also
worked as a consultant for films such as The Oregon Trail (1959) and The Unconquered (1947). He counted among his friends film legends Gary Cooper, Tim McCoy, Cecil B. De
Mille, John Ford, and many others.

One of Cody's first films was The Covered Wagon (1923). When the film premiered at
Grauman's Chinese Theater, Cody was one of
fifty Native Americans from the film who provided
a prologue filled with Native American
dancing and music. Cody danced and told
stories in sign language, which Tim McCoy
"translated." From that point on, Iron Eyes
Cody was one of the most visible Native
Americans in the entertainment industry.

About his involvement in the stereotypical
depictions of Native Americans, Cody said,
"When I first started in the film business, I had
no power and was there to do what I was told:
to make exciting Western entertainment. And
in the days of the big studios, you either did
what you were told or you didn't work. So
we made movies, we 'gave them what they
wanted,' as movies always did and continue to
do." Cody died on January 4, 1999, in Los Angeles,
California.


Jacquelyn Kilpatrick
Governors State University




Cody, Iron Eyes. Indian Talk: Hand Signals of the American Indians. Healdsburg CA: Naturegraph Publishers, 1970.
Cody, Iron Eyes, and Collin Perry. Iron Eyes: My Life as a Hollywood Indian. New York: Everest House, 1982.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>