<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pd.055</field>
      <field name="titleMain">United Farmers of America</field>
      <field name="author">Nugent, Amy</field>
      <field name="text">

 




UNITED FARMERS OF AMERICA

The United Farmers of Alberta (UFA) was established
in 1909 as an amalgamation of the
Alberta Farmers Association and the Alberta
Society of Equity, the latter an offshoot of the
American Society of Equity. The UFA's primary
aim was to ameliorate the vulnerable
economic position of Alberta farmers. It protested
the protective Canadian tariff on farm
equipment, lobbied for the regulation of marketing
practices at grain elevators, and called
for an end to government-endorsed railway
monopolies.

In 1912 the ufa endorsed women's suffrage
and encouraged farm women to become involved
in the organization. In 1915 the United
Farm Women of Alberta (UFWA) was formed,
campaigning for women's suffrage (gained in
1916), temperance, and rural health and education
standards. Unlike women's auxiliaries
in traditional Canadian political organizations,
the UFWA did not mainly bake cookies
and stuff envelopes. These women stood with
their UFA men as economically disadvantaged
farm workers, but they also used annual conventions
and agrarian newsletters to raise
their gender-specific concerns.

Physically removed from the national center
of power in Ottawa and disillusioned by
the corrupt and seemingly undifferentiated
national political parties, many in the ufa began
to advocate direct political action. Henry
Wise Wood, president of the organization
from 1916 to 1931, was a native Missourian
who had witnessed the failures of the Farmers
Alliance and the Populist Party. He was therefore
skeptical of direct political action by
farmers. Nevertheless, he became convinced
that direct involvement was needed, and he
advocated a theory of group government or
political representation based on occupation.

In 1916 the Nonpartisan League, fresh from
its political victories in North Dakota, entered
Alberta to mobilize farmers into political action.
Also in 1916 the UFA endorsed the Canadian
Council of Agriculture's "Farmers' Platform,"
which provided a clear statement of
agrarian political goals. Resolved to political
action, the ufa merged with the Nonpartisan
League in 1919 and contested the 1921 Alberta
election. The UFA ran only rural candidates,
cooperating in some instances with urban labor
candidates. It won the election and remained
in office until 1935. Wood refused the
premiership, which went instead to Herbert
Greenfield (1921-25), then to John Brownlee
(1925-34), and R. G. Reid (1934-35). Of particular
interest, in 1921 Irene Parlby, former
president of the UFWA, became the first woman
cabinet minister in Alberta.

Despite Wood's radical theories of group
government, the UFA governed in a conventional,
efficient manner, establishing wheat,
dairy, poultry, and livestock pools and improving
provincial health and education services.
With the onset of the Great Depression,
the UFA attempted to provide debt relief for
farmers, but its solutions were ineffective and
too orthodox for the Alberta electorate. In
1935 Social Credit swept the UFA out of office,
and the ufa then retreated from political activity.
Today the UFA operates farm supply
stores and petroleum outlets throughout Alberta,
sponsors rural youth groups, and remains
one of Canada's largest farmer-owned
agricultural organizations.

See also POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT: Alberta.


Amy Nugent
University of Calgary




Betke, Carl. "The United Farmers of Alberta, 1921–1935."
In Riel to Reform: A History of Protest in Western Canada,
edited by George Melnyk. Saskatoon: Fifth House Publishers,
1992. Morton, W. L. The Progressive Party in Canada.
Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 1950.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>