<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.mus.045</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Thomson, Virgil (1896-1989)</field>
      <field name="author">Berg, Chuck</field>
      <field name="text">

 




THOMSON, VIRGIL (1896-1989)
 
 Virgil Thomson, photographed by Carl Van Vechten, 1947
       

Virgil Thomson, classical composer and music
critic, was born on November 25, 1896, in
Kansas City, Missouri, where he learned piano
and played organ at his family's Calvary Baptist
Church. After serving in the army during
World War I, Thomson studied composition
and conducting in New York, Paris, and Boston.
He graduated from Harvard in 1923. Returning
to Paris in 1925, his home until 1940,
Thomson came under the influence of composition
pedagogue Nadia Boulanger and
French composer Erik Satie, whose clarity,
simplicity, and humor he admired.

Thomson's large body of work, which includes
operas, symphonies, chamber pieces,
songs, and film scores, while reflecting the
classicism of his formal studies, is largely
rooted in his early musical experiences in
Kansas City. Indeed, in his well-known scores
for the celebrated documentary films The River (1937), The Plow That Broke the Plains
(1936), and Louisiana Story (1948), the last of
which earned a Pulitzer Prize, Thomson incorporated
familiar American religious and
secular melodies. Even in his operas, most
famously, Four Saints in Three Acts (1934),
Thomson employed the musical vernacular of
his midwestern background, an example of
the "new simplicity" and growing nationalism
of American serious music of the 1930s.

In addition to composing, Thomson enjoyed
a successful career as a music journalist.
Having established himself in the pages of
Modern Music during the 1930s, he was commissioned
to write The State of Music (1939),
which argued that musicians should produce
their own music. On the strength of that
work, the New York Herald Tribune hired
Thomson as its chief music critic. During his
reign at the Tribune from 1940 to 1954, Thomson's
provocative commentaries were anthologized
in The Right of Judging (1948), Music Right and Left (1951), and Music Reviewed, 1940–54 (1967). In the 1970s and 1980s Thomson
devoted himself largely to teaching and
lecturing. He died in New York City on September
30, 1989.

See also FILM: The Plow That Broke the Plains.


Chuck Berg
University of Kansas




Rockwell, John. A Virgil Thomson Reader. Boston: Houghton
Mifflin, 1981.  Thomson, Virgil. Virgil Thomson. New
York: Alfred A. Knopf, Inc., 1966. Tommasini, Anthony.
Virgil Thomson: Composer on the Aisle. New York: W. W.
Norton, 1997.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>