<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.med.008</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Calgary Herald</field>
      <field name="author">Howard, Diane</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CALGARY HERALD

The Calgary (Alberta) Herald was first printed
in 1883 in a tent at the junction of the Elbow
and Bow Rivers. A teacher named Thomas
Braden and his friend, printer Andrew Armour,
produced the first issue. At that time it
was known as the Calgary Herald, Mining and Ranch Advocate and General Advertiser. The
first edition was four pages long and had a
circulation of 150 copies.

The Calgary Herald, financed by a five-hundred-
dollar interest-free loan from a Toronto milliner, Miss Frances Ann Chandler,
was a questionable enterprise during its first
few years. The cost for a year's subscription
was $3. By 1884 the founders had replaced
their tent with a shack and had hired their first
editor, Hugh St. Quentin Cayley. At that time,
Braden and Armour found that westerners
wanted more updated information about the
growing Riel Rebellion in the Northwest Territories.
One year later, the Calgary Herald
went daily. To meet demand, a new press was
purchased that could print up to 400 papers
an hour, if a strong man was turning the
crank. The paper was still experiencing growing
pains and financial uncertainty in 1894,
when J. J. Young took over the paper, saving it
from near bankruptcy.

During those early years, the Calgary Herald
was not so much published as improvised,
with updated news provided by bulletins from
passengers on the Canadian Pacific Railway.
By 1902 business had improved so much that
the newspaper bought the city's first two
Linotypes, which allowed fresh type to be cast,
a line at a time, from molten metal. This revolutionary
invention was used to publish the
daily paper for the next seventy years.

In 1906 James Hossack Woods was traveling
on holiday when he stopped in Calgary. The
journalist and advertising man met Young,
who offered Woods an option on half the Calgary Herald. A year later Woods approached
William Southam, who already owned the
Hamilton Spectator and the Ottawa Citizen, to
buy a share of the Herald. In 1908 Southam
bought 301 shares of the newspaper. Herald
circulation reached 20,000 in 1914, when
the advent of World War I placed extraordinary
demands on newspapers to provide
fast-breaking news. The Calgary Herald was
becoming an important source of news for
Alberta. In 1923 the paper was also influential
in founding the Alberta Wheat Pool, which
gave farmers more leverage for better grain
prices in the marketplace. The newspaper grew
and expanded over the course of the twentieth
century, covering news about the Great Depression,
both world wars, the economic recession
during the mid-1980s, and the 1988
Calgary Winter Olympics.

In the early 1990s competing media, new
technology, and changing lifestyles began to
restrict further growth of the Calgary Herald.
The eight-month strike of 230 Calgary Herald
newsroom and distribution-center employees
against owner Conrad Black in 1999.2000
also forced the newspaper to retool various
departments. New technological innovations
were implemented to increase the quality, accuracy,
and efficiency of the growing daily.

In November 2000, in Canada's largest media
deal to date, CanWest founder and chairman
Israel Asper bought the Calgary Herald
from Hollinger International Inc. chairman
Conrad Black. This latest transaction will
likely lead to the convergence of the printed
word of the Calgary Herald with the Internet
and broadcasting capabilities owned by Can-
West. As of September 2000 the Calgary Herald's circulation was at 114,533 daily Monday
through Thursday, 151,374 on Friday, 130,387
on Saturday, and 113,532 on Sunday.

See also CITIES AND TOWNS: Calgary, Alberta.


Diane Howard
University of Calgary




Sumner, Jeff. Gale Directory of Publications and Broadcast Media. 134th ed., vol. 2. Detroit: Gale Group, 2000. Vickers,
Reg. The Calgary Herald. Calgary, Alberta. 1982.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>