<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.art.037</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Jacobshagen, Keith (b. 1941)</field>
      <field name="author">Geske, Norman</field>
      <field name="text">

 





JACOBSHAGEN, KEITH (b. 1941)

A notable development in the artistic climate
of the Great Plains in the decades following
World War II has been the appearance of a
whole generation of painters of the prairie
landscape: Robert Sudlow, Anne Burkholder,
James Butler, Hal Holoun, Ben Darling, Ernest
Ochsner, and Keith Jacobshagen. Among
them Keith Jacobshagen has attained recognition
on the national scene with paintings of
exceptional quality. His is not the landscape of
the regionalist thirties, dominated by a dry
realism and ravaged by climate and social neglect.
Instead there is deeply personal, even
intimate perception at work. The landscape is
rich with the textures of weather, season, and
growth. His viewpoint is one of patient absorption,
an immersion in the specifics of
time and place and, in particular, the hours of
the early evening.

Jacobshagen was born on September 8,
1941, in Wichita, Kansas. A graduate of the
Kansas City Art Institute (1965) and the University
of Kansas at Lawrence (1968), he came
to the faculty of the University of Nebraska–
Lincoln in 1968 still working in the academic
version of current abstract expressionism.
Soon thereafter he centered his personal concern
on the rural landscape around him, and
his work took on the qualities that have identified
him among his contemporaries as a
master of the minutiae of the subject–of
cloud, smoke, the haze of distance. In some of
his works he has specified in marginal notations
the date, the time of day, the very sounds
and smells of being in that place. Most particularly,
he has matched the implied complications
of the presence of people on the
land to the natural drama of the sky.



Norman A. Geske
Lincoln, Nebraska




Geske, Norman A. Art and Artists in Nebraska. Lincoln:
Sheldon Memorial Art Gallery in Association with the
Center for Great Plains Studies, University of Nebraska–
Lincoln, 1983.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>