<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.051</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Mundt, Karl (1900-1974)</field>
      <field name="author">Miller, John E.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MUNDT, KARL (1900-1974)

Karl E. Mundt was a prominent farm-state Republican
who served in Congress for thirtyfour
years (five terms in the House and four in
the Senate). Born on June 3, 1900, in Humboldt,
South Dakota, Mundt became a high
school teacher and school superintendent in
Bryant, South Dakota, after graduating from
Carleton College (1923) and obtaining a master's
degree from Columbia University (1927).
In 1924 he moved to Madison, South Dakota,
where he taught and coached the debate team
at the Eastern State Normal School while also
engaging in an investment business with his
father. Although referring to himself as a liberal
Republican in getting elected to Congress
as representative of South Dakota's First District
in 1938, he quickly identified with the
conservatives in the party. His first major action
as a congressman was a successful effort
to remove from circulation the government
documentary film The Plow That Broke the
Plains, which depicted the devastating relationship
between mechanized farming and
the Dust Bowl.

World War II transformed Mundt from a
staunch isolationist into a committed internationalist.
Throughout his career he was
known primarily to those outside his home
state as an outspoken anticommunist. He
teamed up with fellow congressman Richard
Nixon on the House Un-American Activities
Committee during the 1940s and later stood
loyally behind Sen. Joseph R. McCarthy in his
crusade against alleged internal subversion.
Mundt maintained a strong electoral base in
his home state by backing price supports for
agriculture while maintaining a solid conservative
record on other issues. He was a joiner
who stayed in close contact with the electorate,
a.liating with many organizations, including
the Masons, the Elks, the Kiwanis, the
El Riad Shrine, and the Methodist Church. He
was also an enthusiastic conservationist and
active in the Izaak Walton League. A crippling
stroke in 1969 incapacitated him and forced
his retirement three years later. Mundt died in
Washington DC on August 16, 1974.

See also FILM: The Plow That Broke the Plains.


John E. Miller
South Dakota State University




Heidepriem, Scott N. A Fair Chance for a Free People: A
Biography of Karl E. Mundt, U.S. Senator. Madison SD:
Karl E. Mundt Foundation, 1988. Mundt, Karl E. Papers.
Karl E. Mundt Library, Dakota State University, Madison,
South Dakota.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>