<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.na.104</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Sarcees</field>
      <field name="author">Starlight, Jeanette Conaty, Gerald T.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SARCEES

The Sarcees (Sarsis) are an Athapaskan-speaking
people living along the eastern foothills of
the Rocky Mountains in southwestern Alberta.
In 1983 they formally adopted the name Tsuu
T'inas, which means "Many People" in their
own language.

According to Tsuu T'ina legend, all of the
Athapaskan-speaking people once lived together
in northwestern Canada and Alaska.
One winter, when the people were crossing
a frozen lake, a young boy asked his grandmother
to get him a stick that was protruding
from the ice. When she tried to pick it up, she
found the stick to be frozen fast in the ice. As
the old lady continued to pull and twist the
stick, the water was stirred up and the turbulence
angered the Underwater Creature. As
he rose, a great fissure split the ice. Terrified,
the people ran for shore. Those who headed
north became the Dines of Canada and
Alaska. Others moved southward, becoming
the Tsuu T'inas, Apaches, and Navajos.

Once in the south, the Tsuu T'inas may
have first occupied the upper drainages of the
Saskatchewan and Athabasca Rivers. By the
early nineteenth century they had moved farther
south and into a close alliance with the
Siksikas (Blackfoot proper). They lived primarily
along the central portion of the Bow
River and at sites along Wolf Creek (now
called Fish Creek), the Weasel Head section
of the Elbow River, and at Moose Mountain
which assumed sacred significance.

Through their close association, the Tsuu
T'inas adopted much of the material and sacred
culture of the Blackfoot. Methods and
tools for bison hunting and hide preparation,
as well as styles of tipis and clothing, all resemble
those of the Blackfoot. Because many
sacred objects were left with their northern
relatives, the Tsuu T'inas incorporated Blackfoot
ceremonies into their own belief system.
Today, the people are very private about
their beliefs and are reluctant to discuss them
publicly.

The Tsuu T'inas lived in kin-based groups,
which they referred to as clans. The leader of
the clan was acknowledged for his good judgment
and ability to bring about a consensus.
Individuals were free to move from clan to
clan, as they saw fit. The Tsuu T'inas presently
recognize five clans, although there may have
been more before the epidemics and starvation
of the late 1800s.

In 1877 Treaty Number 7 was signed between
the government of Canada and the Siksikas,
Piegans, Kainahs (Bloods), Stoneys, and
Tsuu T'inas. At that time, the population of
the Tsuu T'inas was estimated to be only 672
persons, and the government suggested that
the Tsuu T'inas be included on a large reserve
to be set aside for all of the Blackfoot. Bull
Head, an influential Tsuu T'ina leader, recognized
the importance of having their own
place to preserve their language and culture.
He argued successfully for a distinct reserve,
and a place was eventually set aside along the
Elbow River, near the North-West Mounted
Police post at Fort Calgary. By 1881, when the
Tsuu T'inas were settled on the reserve, the
population had dropped to about 450 persons;
it continued to decline over the ensuing
years.

In 2001 a population of about 1,100 lives on
the reserve. The city of Calgary abuts two of
its boundaries, while expanding rural subdivisions
encroach on the other edges. An elected
council of one chief and eleven council members
manage the affairs and revenues from resort
and golf course developments, oil and gas
exploration, and, until recently, rental for land
used as a military base. A large office complex
houses several federal government offices,
whose rent contributes to the tribal revenue.

The Tsuu T'inas have a cultural research
program that is actively collecting oral histories. This information is housed at the Tsuu
T'ina Peoples Museum.


Jeanette Starlight
Tsuu T'ina Peoples Museum
Gerald T. Conaty
Glenbow Museum



Jenness, Diamond. The Sarcee Indians of Alberta. Bulletin
no. 90, Anthropological Series no. 23. Ottawa: National
Museums of Canada, 1938.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>