<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ha.006</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Central Americans</field>
      <field name="author">Lindstrom, David P.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CENTRAL AMERICANS

Central Americans are one of the fastestgrowing
Latin American origin groups in the
United States. The 1990 U.S. census enumerated
1.3 million persons of Central American
origin, of whom slightly more than 1 million
were foreign born. Approximately 8 percent
of all Central Americans in the United States
reside in the ten states of the American Great
Plains, the vast majority in Texas.

The isthmus of Central America encompasses
the nations of Guatemala, Belize, Honduras,
El Salvador, Nicaragua, Costa Rica, and
Panama. There are an estimated 36 million
people in Central America, most of whom
are mestizos, but there also are Indigenous
groups, especially in Guatemala, and people of
African ancestry in the Caribbean coastal
areas. The United Nations projects that this
population will increase to 58 million by the
year 2025. Poverty is widespread: gross national
product per capita in 1997 ranged from
a low of $410 in Nicaragua to a high of $3,080
in Panama, compared to $29,080 in the United
States. Export agriculture dominates the economies
of Central America, with coffee, cotton,
bananas, beef, and sugar the leading products.
The industrial sector grew during the 1960s
and 1970s but remains small. With the exception
of Costa Rica and Belize, military governments
have been a common feature of the
political landscape in the region. Mounting
political tensions and public discontent with
the ruling regimes in El Salvador, Guatemala,
and Nicaragua erupted into civil wars in the
late 1970s and early 1980s. The 1990s saw the
restoration of peace and the establishment
of democratically elected governments in all
three countries.

During the worst years of the conflicts the
number of immigrants entering the United
States from El Salvador, Guatemala, and Nicaragua
grew dramatically. Close to two-thirds
of the roughly 1 million Central American immigrants
included in the 1990 U.S. census arrived
between 1980 and 1990. Advocates of U.S.
foreign policy in the region argued that immigration
from El Salvador and Guatemala was
economically motivated, and to support their
argument they pointed to well-established
patterns of international migration within the
region and significant differences in earnings
and living standards between the United States
and Central America. Critics of U.S. foreign
policy viewed Salvadoran and Guatemalan
immigrants in the United States as political
refugees in search of safe haven. The U.S. government
generally denied refugee status to immigrants
from the region. In spite of the legal
restrictions on immigration to the United
States, immigrants from Central America
came in large numbers, many without legal
documentation.

Central Americans began arriving in the
Great Plains in significant numbers during the
1980s as part of a larger stream of foreignborn
immigrants attracted to the region by
employment opportunities in new or expanding
meatpacking plants and other low-wage
industries. Intense competition and low profit
margins in meatpacking have made the industry
very dependent on unskilled immigrant
labor. The arrival of Mexican, Central American,
and Asian immigrants has transformed
many small towns with meatpacking plants,
like Lexington, Nebraska, and Garden City,
Kansas, into ethnically, linguistically, and culturally
diverse communities. The low wages
offered by meatpacking plants and the comparatively
low skill levels of many Central
Americans and other new immigrants have
also created greater levels of poverty in these
communities.

The relative youth and size of the new immigrant
streams have placed strains on the supply
of housing, education, medical care, and basic
services available in meatpacking communities.
School enrollments have soared, creating
overcrowding in classrooms, and there is a
growing demand for bilingual and English as a
Second Language programs. In the area of
health care, most of the current demand for
services is related to maternal and child health.
As the Central American population ages, the
demand will eventually shift to health services
for adolescents, adults, and the elderly.

Although they represent a small proportion
of all Central Americans in the United
States, Central American immigrants in the
Great Plains, along with other new immigrant
groups, will have an increasingly visible impact
on the towns and cities they inhabit because
of the comparatively small size and previous
ethnic homogeneity of these places.


David P. Lindstrom
Brown University




Lamphere, Louise, Alex Stepick, and Guillermo Grenier,
eds. Newcomers in the Workplace: Immigrants and the Restructuring of the U.S. Economy. Philadelphia: Temple
University Press, 1994. Stull, Donald D., Michael J. Broadway,
and David Griffith, eds. Any Way You Cut It: Meat Processing and Small-Town America. Lawrence: University
Press of Kansas, 1995.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>