<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.053</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Olsen, Tillie (b. 1913)</field>
      <field name="author">Pratt, Linda Ray</field>
      <field name="text">

 




OLSEN, TILLIE (b. 1913)

Tillie Olsen, author of Tell Me a Riddle, was
born Tillie Lerner on a farm near Mead, Nebraska,
on January 14, 1913. Like many other
Jewish immigrants in Nebraska, the Lerners
had left Russia after the failure of the 1905
revolution. The family moved to Omaha in
1917. Olsen's parents were active Socialists, and
her father, Samuel, ran for lieutenant governor
on the Socialist Party ticket in 1928. Her
early life was centered in the family's struggle
to make a living and its radical politics. At
Central High, Olsen read widely and wrote for
the school paper but was not a model student.
She dropped out of high school after joining
the Young Communist League in 1931. By 1934
she had moved to San Francisco, where she
married Jack Olsen and reared four daughters.

Olsen's first story, "The Iron Throat," appeared
in 1934 in the Partisan Review. The
story attracted attention, and Olsen participated
in the 1935 Writers Congress. In the 1940s
Olsen was active in union and other left-wing
activities. In 1961, after her mother's death,
Olsen published Tell Me a Riddle, a collection
of short fiction. The title story, based on her
parents' lives, focuses on a mother's memories
and the family's responses to her impending
death from cancer. Another story is "I Stand
Here Ironing." Both stories portray creative
women whose lives were subdued by the exigencies
of motherhood. These stories received
wide critical acclaim and resonated with the
emerging feminist ideas of the 1970s. In 1974
Olsen published Yonnondio, a novel of the
Great Depression she began in the early 1930s.
Yonnondio also draws on her family history
and midwestern roots. The novel focuses on
Mazie, a starry-eyed young girl, who moves
with her family from the farm to a large meatpacking
city like Omaha. In 1978 Olsen published
Silences, a book of nonfiction essays
about pressures that silence women as writers.

Olsen's fiction won national and international
notice in the 1970s. She is generally
considered a major figure among contemporary
women writers.


Linda Ray Pratt
University of Nebraska-Lincoln





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>