<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.rel.032</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Lutheranism</field>
      <field name="author">Anderson, Douglas Firth</field>
      <field name="text">

 




LUTHERANISM

Lutherans are members of a Protestant tradition
flowing from the life and thought of Martin
Luther, the sixteenth-century German
monk turned theologian, pastor, and family
patriarch. Lutherans became a major religious
group in the Great Plains of North America in
the latter half of the nineteenth century, and as
the twenty-first century began, they continued
to color the society and culture of various locales
in the Plains and their borderlands.

Theologically, Lutherans have identified
themselves as evangelical in that Luther in his
break with Roman Catholicism stressed the
Gospels and the evangel of justification by
faith in the gracious work of God in Jesus
Christ. An individual's ultimate standing before
God, in other words, is not gained by
moral works or by keeping God's law; rather, it
is by sola gratia (grace alone) and sola fides
(faith alone). Sola scriptura (Scripture alone)
has also been a key affirmation of Lutherans,
indicating that the canonical books of the
Bible, not any church office, institution, or
theological tradition, are the ultimate norm
for Christian life and thought. Nevertheless,
confessionalism has always been a strong component
in Lutheran identity. Next to the ecumenical
creeds of the early church, the two
most important confessional documents for
Lutherans have been the Augsburg Confession
(1530) and Luther's Small Catechism (1529).
These and other documents were gathered in
1580 into the Book of Concord, a collection
that remains formally important for Lutheran
theology.

Lutheran immigrants to the Great Plains
brought with them not only a strong theological
tradition but also conceptions of church
order and elements of an ethos that shaped
the social and cultural institutions they constructed.
In the German and Scandinavian
states from which the vast majority of Great
Plains Lutherans came in the nineteenth century,
Lutheranism was formally established. In
the Plains of North America, however, legal
nonestablishment, together with the vastness of
the region, reinforced the primacy of the local
congregation in Lutheran life. At the local level,
Lutheran leadership is still formally embodied
in the pastorate and also in elected lay officials.
The office of bishop has become widespread
among Lutheran groups, but as a useful administrative
office rather than one representing
apostolic succession. Above this local level, Lutherans
organized regional synods based largely
on differences in ethnicity. Only in the latter
half of the twentieth century, as ethnicity has
softened, has the plethora of Lutheran synodical
bodies represented in the Great Plains begun
to significantly diminish through mergers.
Since 1988 the vast majority of Plains Lutherans
are affiliated with either the Evangelical
Lutheran Church of America (ELCA) or the Lutheran
Church, Missouri Synod (LCMS), the
former theologically and socially more pluralist
than the latter.

An important aspect of a Lutheran ethos in
the North American Plains has been pietism, a
diffuse revitalization movement of the seventeenth
and eighteenth centuries that was later
reinforced by similar revitalization movements
in the nineteenth century. This pietist stream
reinforced among many Lutherans a stress on
personalizing belief. It also stressed the embodiment
of such commitment through "godly"
practices and the avoidance of "worldly" practices.
Also worth noting in a Lutheran ethos are
the patriarchal family, enacted by Luther himself
and carried on symbolically through the
present by the local pastor and his family, and
Lutheran corporate worship, which has consistently
stressed the proclamation of the Word,
the importance of the sacraments of baptism
and the Lord's Supper, and the role of music,
particularly chorales, in engaging the participation
of the entire community.

The arrival of Lutherans in the Plains began
with major migrations of Germans and, to a
lesser extent, Scandinavians to the central and
upper portions of the Mississippi River basin
in the 1840s and 1850s. The political and economic
upheavals of an industrializing and liberalizing
Europe were factors that prompted
emigration, but economic opportunity, particularly land, was the most pervasive pull.
By the time the American Civil War began
in 1861, Wisconsin, Minnesota, Missouri, and
a section of Texas had received thousands
of these Lutheran emigrants. The Englishspeaking
descendants of colonial-era Lutherans,
primarily concentrated in Pennsylvania,
and the more recent German-speaking Lutherans
centered in Ohio held relatively little
appeal for these newly arriving Lutherans. Instead,
the emigrants formed new synods, most
notably the Missouri Synod (1847), but also
Hauge's Synod (Norwegian, 1846), the Texas
Synod (German, 1851), the Norwegian Synod
(1853), and the Augustana Synod (Swedish,
1860). The founding of Augustana College in
Sioux Falls (now South Dakota) in 1860 foreshadowed
what this planting of Lutheranism
in the eastern borderlands of the U.S. Great
Plains would bring once the Civil War ended.

Lutherans secured their initial planting in
the Plains proper with two phases of settlement
after 1865. The earlier phase was in the
Northern Plains between roughly 1865 and
1900. The regional shape and depth of this
migration is suggested by the establishment of
Lutheran institutions of higher education. By
1900, in addition to Augustana College, the
following had been founded: Bethany College
(Augustana Synod) and Saint John's College
(Missouri Synod) in Kansas; Dana College
(United Danish), Midland College (General
Synod), and Concordia Teachers College
(Missouri Synod) in Nebraska; and Texas Lutheran
College (Texas Synod).

The second phase was the spilling over of this
migration into the Canadian Prairie Provinces
between 1890 and 1914. The Lutheran population
swelled enough so that in 1915 the General
Council of Lutherans organized the Saskatoon
Theological Seminary, Saskatchewan.

Lutheran communities in the Great Plains
have received their finest literary depiction to
date in the novels of Ole Rölvaag, who lived
and worked on a farm in South Dakota for
three years in the late 1890s before attending
Augustana College. Prior to World War I, Lutherans
in the Great Plains were comparatively
isolated geographically and insulated
culturally. Whether in Block Corners, Kansas,
Dalesburg, South Dakota, or some other German
or Scandinavian enclave in the Plains,
community life for observant Lutherans was
centered around church and school. The pastor
and, in the most conservative communities,
the Lutheran schoolteacher provided
the theological, social, and cultural leadership
locally that was integral to sustaining ethnic as
well as religious identity until well into the
twentieth century. The church building, and
sometimes a separate school building, provided
a material center for community life,
which was expressed formally in corporate
worship, in congregational and school events
such as picnics and mission festivals, and,
by the turn of the nineteenth and into the
twentieth century, women's groups and youth
groups as well. Home missions by various
Lutheran synods, while similar in most respects
to those undertaken by various anglophone
Protestant denominations, were limited
to organizing congregations among the sending
group's ethnic compatriots rather than
seeking to evangelize outside the ethnic group.

The twentieth century's world wars and economic
depression were major catalysts for undermining
isolation and insulation. Lutheran
ethnicity has not disappeared, however; it has
merely softened its tone and expanded and
blurred its borders. Radio storyteller Garrison
Keillor's Norwegian Lutherans, while fictional
and nostalgic, are evocative of a persistent
ethos as much Lutheran as it is ethnic, and
Lake Wobegon is a place almost as much Plains
as it is Prairie. As of 1990 the political units of
the Great Plains with the largest percentages of
the population expressing a Lutheran a.liation
are North Dakota (36 percent), South
Dakota (30 percent), and Nebraska (16 percent).
Such proportions suggest that, whatever
changes may come to Plains Lutherans as a
collective religious tradition and community,
they will remain a significant element in the
region.

See also LITERARY TRADITIONS: Rölvaag, O. E.


Douglas Firth Anderson
Northwestern College, Orange City, Iowa




Coburn, Carol K. Life at Four Corners: Religion, Gender,
and Education in a German-Lutheran Community, 1868.
1945. Lawrence: University Press of Kansas, 1992. Gjerde,
Jon. The Minds of the West: Ethnocultural Evolution in the
Rural Middle West, 1830-1917. Chapel Hill: University of
North Carolina Press, 1997. Nelson, E. Clifford, ed. The
Lutherans in North America. Philadelphia: Fortress Press,
1975.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>