<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.sr.014</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Curling</field>
      <field name="author">Patzke, Rick</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CURLING


Curlers from the Dakotah Curling Club, Drayton, North Dakota, 1900-5


The winter ice sport of curling was introduced
to the Great Plains by Scottish immigrants. The
minimal equipment needed–ice, brooms, and
stones–made it easy for these sportsmen to
continue the tradition, especially in the early
days when the playing stones weren't always
uniform. Curling involves two teams of four
players each alternately sliding stones (today,
each stone weighs forty-two pounds) along an
ice lane toward a target of concentric circles.
Points are scored for having more stones closer
to the "tee" (the center of the circles).

With long, cold winters and many ponds,
lakes, and rivers, the northern parts of the
Great Plains are especially suited for curling.
In the Canadian provinces of Manitoba, Saskatchewan,
and Alberta, the length of the
playing season quickly helped curling surpass
other sports such as baseball and cricket in
popularity. Curling developed as more than a
competitive game. During the winter the social
fabric of the Prairie communities centered
around each town's curling rink.

Just as the railroad's expansion helped establish
new settlements in western Canada
and the United States, so, too, did it help to
spread curling, especially when Scotsmen
were part of the railway gangs. Manitoba first
recorded curling in 1876, and by 1888 pioneers
there had formed the province of Manitoba
and Adjoining Territories branch of the Royal
Caledonian Curling Club of Scotland. A year
later the branch hosted the world's largest
bonspiel, or tournament, of the times, with
sixty-two rinks (teams) competing in Winnipeg.
In 1988 the 100th annual Manitoba
Curling Association bonspiel drew a world-record
1,280 rinks.

Curling was played in the territory of Saskatchewan as early as 1880, when tamarack
blocks shaped to resemble curling stones were
fitted with iron handles and slid across the
frozen Saskatchewan River. The dedication of
Saskatchewan's curlers is best illustrated by
the journey undertaken by a Prince Albert
team intent on playing in the 1890 Winnipeg
bonspiel. The foursome walked 200 miles,
their stones carted by ponies, just to catch a
train that required another three days to reach
Winnipeg. The roots of curling are still strong
in the province today: the Saskatchewan Curling
Association is the largest of its kind in the
world. At its peak in 1960–61, the association
had 578 member clubs. Among the province's
best-known curlers was Regina's Richardson
family rink, which in 1959 won the first of four
national and world championships in five
years.

Curling stones were also regularly thrown in
Alberta by the 1880s, shortly after the arrival
of the railroad. In 1959 Calgary's Big Four Curling
Club became the world's largest, boasting
forty-eight sheets divided between two levels.
Calgary was also the site of the first world
championship held outside of Scotland, in
1964, and of the Olympic curling demonstration
in 1988.

Curling filtered across the U.S. Great Plains
much as it did across Canada but with additional
influence from the north. Initial members
of the Manitoba Curling Association included
clubs in Butte, Montana, and St. Paul,
Minnesota. However, the sport has never become
as established in the United States as it
has in Canada, the "Curling Capital of the
World." The three Canadian Prairie Provinces
are each home to about 14 percent of that
country's estimated 1.5 million curlers. Altogether,
the twenty existing clubs in the seven
Great Plains states with curling (including
western Minnesota) have approximately 1,500
curlers out of 15,000 nationwide. North Dakota's
twelve clubs are the largest concentration
in the region. The Drayton Curling Club,
whose first "home" was a stretch of ice on the
Red River, celebrated its centennial in 2001.
The Great Plains states have been home to
twenty-four national curling champions in
the history of U.S. men's, women's, and mixed
events, including nine junior men's teams, two
of which won world titles.

Manitoba has produced twenty-five national
men's champions alone since the Canadians
first contested for a title in 1927. Saskatchewan
boasts eleven women's champions
and is also home to the team that won the
women's gold medal in the 1998 Winter Olympic
Games in Nagano, Japan, where curling
first became a full-medal sport. Alberta also
has many national champions, including
eighteen men's and thirteen junior men's
teams. Altogether, the three provinces have
also welcomed home thirty-one world curling
champions.


Rick Patzke
U.S. Curling Association




Argan, Wm. P. Saskatchewan Curling: Heartland Tradition.
Regina: Saskatchewan Curling Association, 1991. Haig,
Senator John T. 1948 Manitoba Curling Association Yearbook.
Winnipeg: Manitoba Curling Association, 1948.
Smith, David B. Curling: An Illustrated History. Edinburgh:
John Donald Publishers Ltd., 1981.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>