<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ha.001</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Hispanic Americans</field>
      <field name="author">Yeung, Malcolm Hu-DeHart, Evelyn</field>
      <field name="text">

 




HISPANIC AMERICANS

When Damasso Armendáriz left his South
Texas home in 1994 to work at Millard Processing
Services in Omaha, Nebraska, he
thought he was going to start a life that would
offer more than the one he was leaving. After
all, the recruiters from the pork-processing
plant had promised him free housing and a
managerial position. But as soon as Armendáriz
stepped into the jam-packed Ford Clubwagon,
the vehicle designated to transport Armendáriz
and several others from El Paso,
Texas, to Omaha, he knew that he had been
mistaken. And when he arrived in Omaha, he
found to his dismay that his housing consisted
of a rundown apartment with bug-infested,
torn-up furniture. The promised managerial
position did not materialize, and company officials
instead placed him on the processing
lines, a job that was not only grueling but dangerous.
It was a situation shared by the other
600 Mexicans and Mexican Americans working
in the plant.

Although Armendáriz's dismal tale took
place only six years from the twenty-first century,
his experience coming to El Norte was
not unique. He is but one of many who have
migrated from the south to the Great Plains
since the sixteenth century. Spaniards, Mexicans,
and Mexican Americans, joined recently
by Central Americans, have maintained a noticeable
presence in the Great Plains for almost
500 years; they have contributed their
labor and ideas to building settlements and
the Plains economy, and they have enriched
its culture.



The Spanish and the Plains, 1540-1821

The Spanish were the first Europeans to recognize
the importance of the Plains. Their
presence was initially established through the
gradual penetration of the Southern Plains by
exploration sponsored by the Spanish state
and military, wealthy ranchers and miners,
and the Catholic Church. Later, Spanish influence
emanated from settlements and colonies
around the Southern Plains.

It all started in the sixteenth century when
Spain, having secured Mesoamerica, turned
its colonization machine to the north. Álvar
Núñez Cabeza de Vaca, the second-in-command
of the ill-fated Pánfilo de Narváez expedition
to western Florida, skirted the Southern
Plains in his journey from the Texas coast
to Mexico City in 1528–36. He brought back
rumors of the mythical Seven Cities of Cíbola.
To investigate Cabeza de Vaca's report, Viceroy
Antonio de Mendoza sent Father Marcos de
Niza to the north in 1539. The Pueblo Indians
forced Father Marcos to turn back, but his
report of Cíbola, a magnificent Rio Grande
pueblo larger than any Mexican city, enticed
Viceroy Mendoza to appoint Francisco Vásquez
de Coronado to lead a large expedition
to occupy the region. When Cíbola proved to
be but an ordinary pueblo, Coronado took
thirty-six men east to the Southern Plains in
1541. There, according to a Pawnee captive
nicknamed El Turco, he would find the fabled
province of Quivira. From central Kansas,
beyond the land of "cattle and sky" (as the
expedition's chronicle described the flat,
bison-rich expanses of the Llano Estacado),
Coronado eventually found Quivira–a Wichita
Indian village with beautiful grass lodges
and well-tended cornfields, but no gold.

Coronado returned to Mexico in disgrace,
but the notion of wealth and a better life in
the north remained alive in New Spain. When
France and England entered the colonization
race in the late sixteenth century, Spanish officials began to worry that they might penetrate
the North American interior and threaten
their lucrative mines in northern Mexico. Settlement
was needed in the Rio Grande Valley
and beyond, and an official competitive settlement
contract was announced. After several
aborted attempts, Don Juan de Oñate,
a wealthy silver baron, took 500 settlers and
more than 1,000 head of stock north in 1598
and established a permanent colony in the Rio
Grande Valley. In 1609 a mission was built at
Santa Fe, which in 1610 became the capital of
the new royal province of New Mexico. By the
1620s a modest but entrenched Spanish colony,
with missions, ranches, and land grants, had
been established in the Rio Grande Valley. Except
for a brief interim during the Pueblo Revolt
in 1680.92, the colony persisted. The establishment
of New Mexico revolutionized life
among the Pueblo Indians, who felt the full
burden of repressive Spanish colonial rule, but
it also had enormous impact on the adjacent
grasslands. Due to the proximity of New Mexico
to the Southern Plains–only the narrow
and relatively passable Sangre de Cristo Range
separated them–their histories would be intimately
linked.

Meanwhile, rapid French expansion forced
the Spanish to act also in the east. By the late
1680s the French were exploring the lower Mississippi
Valley, and a few years later the French
unsuccessfully tried to plant a colony on the
east coast of Texas. New Spain responded by
officially creating the province of Texas in 1691
and sending its first governor, Domingo de
Terán, to lead church, civilian, and military
colonization efforts. Spain moved into East
Texas first, and by the 1710s it had established a
string of missions at the southeastern edge of
the Southern Plains. In an effort to connect
northern Mexico with its far-flung Texas outposts,
a presidio, San Antonio de Béjar, was
built in 1718, followed shortly by a mission, San
Antonio de Valero (later called the Alamo).
The French threat had created a strong commitment
by Spain to settle Texas and to occupy
the southern flank of the Plains. For the next
100 years the Texas colony and the Southern
Plains would have a complex, fluctuating relationship,
which profoundly affected both.

Although the Spanish endured on the borders
of the Southern Plains until the collapse
of the Spanish Empire in 1821, they never
made serious attempts to colonize the grasslands.
The nomadic and seminomadic hunters
of the Southern Plains–Apaches, Comanches,
Wichitas, and others–were an insurmountable
obstacle to the Spanish imperial system,
which was based on the exploitation of sedentary
agricultural Indians and their labor. The
futility of absorbing the Plains into the empire
became painfully clear in the early eighteenth
century, when Spain, in an effort to block
France's commercial expansion, tried to establish
a military presence in the region. Alarmed
by reports of French activities among the Pawnees
and Apaches, Governor Antonio Valverde
y Cosio commissioned Lieutenant Governor
Pedro de Villazur to lead an expedition to the
Platte River and to determine whether a presidio
in southeastern Colorado would serve to
eliminate the French threat. In 1720, traveling
with sixty Pueblos and forty-two Spanish
troops, Villazur marched to the confluence of
the Platte and Loup Rivers in central Nebraska,
farther than any Spanish expedition from New
Mexico would ever travel in the Great Plains.
There, Pawnees and Otoes with French guns
destroyed them. Villazur was killed along with
twenty-nine soldiers, one-third of New Mexico's
troops. Humiliated, the Spanish retreated
to their existing Rio Grande settlements.

A similar fate ended Spain's attempt to expand
its reach north of Texas in the 1750s.
Over the years Lipan Apaches, pressured by
southward-expanding Comanches, had repeatedly
asked for a mission and, thereby,
Spanish protection. In 1757 Spanish o.cials
finally responded to the Lipan requests by
sending six missionaries and 100 soldiers and
their families to build a mission and a presidio
on the San Saba River. The site, about three
miles east of the present town of Menard,
Texas, was chosen because it was suitable for
irrigated farming and was near a rich mineral
region. Yet within a year, Mission Santa Cruz
de San Sabá and Presidio de San Luis de las
Amarillas, the only Spanish mission and presidio
ever established in the Plains, lay in
ruins, destroyed by Comanches, Wichitas, and
Hasinais who wanted to prevent the Spanish-
Apache alliance. The attempt to extend the
Spanish frontier into the Texas Plains ended in
utter failure.

The Villazur and San Sabá disasters fundamentally
altered the history of the Great
Plains. During the remaining years of the
Spanish presence in the Americas, New Mexico
and Texas devolved into sleepy outposts
rather than serving as springboards for Plains
colonization. In the 1770s, when New Spain's
northern colonies were organized into a huge
semiautonomous administrative unit, the Provincias
Internas, the rationale for the arrangement
in New Mexico and Texas was to improve
the colonies' defensive, not expansive,
potential. But the absence of colonization did
not mean that there was no interaction between
the Spanish and the Plains. Throughout
the Spanish era, trade goods, animals, and microbes
were disseminated into the Plains, radically
changing both land and life.

Diseases spread from the colonies to the adjacent
grasslands, killing tens of thousands of
Indians who had no resistance against European
microbes. It is not known when the first
epidemics struck, but many scholars believe
that the Plains Indian population in 1700 was
only a fraction of what it was before contact.
But the colonies also benefited the Plains Indians.
The most positive exchange was the reintroduction
of horses to the grasslands. The
first horses probably came to the Plains in the
early seventeenth century, but the diffusion
accelerated greatly after the Pueblo Revolt,
when Pueblos and Plains Indians engaged in
active trade in horses left behind by the Spanish.
Within a few generations, the Plains Indians
reinvented themselves and became some
of the most refined hunting and equestrian
cultures in history.

In addition to microbes and animals, people
crossed the boundaries between the Spanish
colonies and the Plains. In the eighteenth
and early nineteenth centuries, Comanches
sold thousands of Apache and Pawnee captives
to New Mexico. The commerce in humans
was also encouraged by the Recopilación
of 1681, which obliged the Spanish to ransom
Native Americans enslaved by other Native
Americans. Called indios genózaros, these captives
lacked social status within either Spanish
or Puebloan society. With no land or property,
genózaros were put in new settlements
constructed as frontier outposts on the western
Plains border. There they constituted the
front line of defense protecting the Spanish
presence in the Southwest.

The movement of diseases, horses, and
people in and out of the Plains was abetted by
economic interaction. Initially, the Spanish.
Plains Indian trade grew out of necessity: the
Spanish needed Plains goods–hides, dried
meat, and tallow–and the Jumanos, Comanches,
and other Native American groups were
eager to obtain horses, metal goods, and firearms.
Later, as Spanish officials realized that
the Plains was beyond their military grasp,
they attempted to control the Plains Indians
through trade. In an effort to block French
and, later, American expansion into the Plains
and northern Mexico, the Spanish tried to
turn the Southern Plains into a buffer zone by
drawing the region's Indians into their commercial
orbit.

Spurred by these economic and political
motives, Spanish–Plains Indian trade flourished,
particularly in New Mexico. As they had
done for centuries, Plains nomads came every
year to Pueblo trade fairs, which in the eighteenth
century were increasingly dominated
by Spanish merchants. Texas, the poorer of the
two colonies, was slower to develop trade with
the Plains tribes. There was some trade at San
Antonio de Béjar. But in most cases the Indians
focused on raiding the poorly protected missions
and ranches for horses, mules, cattle,
and goods.

Before the 1780s the trade was also often
interrupted in New Mexico by raids launched
by Comanches and Apaches who were either
looking for horses and corn or trying to force
the Spanish into more favorable trade arrangements.
A new era in Spanish–Plains Indian
relations began in 1785-86, when the
Spanish governments in Texas and New Mexico
signed treaties with the Comanches. The
Spanish promised secure trade, gifts, and access
to guns, while the Comanches promised
to stop raiding. In addition, both agreed to
wage a joint war against the Apaches, which
led to sporadic Comanche-Spanish expeditions
against the few Apache bands still living
on the Plains margins.

The peaceful relations with the Comanches
after the 1780s also enticed Spanish and Puebloan
traders from New Mexico to venture
onto the open grasslands. Known as comancheros,
these traders flourished in the Plains
until the 1870s, exchanging bread, metal, tobacco,
guns, ammunition, and alcohol for
bison products, horses, and other Plains exports.
Contemporaries of the comancheros
were ciboleros, bison hunters from New Mexico,
who made annual winter hunting expeditions
to provide meat for their families and
hides for a burgeoning Santa Fe–Chihuahua
trade. Roaming the Llano Estacado from
semipermanent camps, the ciboleros may
have taken as many as 25,000 bison hides back
to New Mexico during the peak years of the
early nineteenth century.

Spain's role in the geopolitics of the Plains
was also changing. In 1763, as a result of the
French and Indian War, Spain gained Louisiana,
which at that time included all of the
Great Plains except for the far northern regions.
The new geopolitical arrangement allowed
the Spanish to relax their frontier defenses
in New Mexico and Texas. On the other
hand, the southward push of Canada-based
British fur traders in the late eighteenth century
forced Spanish officials to take action
in the Northern Plains. In an effort to block
British expansion, the officials promoted trade
and exploration along the upper Missouri
River, the commercial and transportation artery
of the Northern Plains. Enticed by a large
cash prize, French and Spanish merchants in
St. Louis formed the Missouri Company and
sent three exploring parties up the river between
1794 and 1796, reaching as far as the
Mandan villages in present-day North Dakota.

In 1800, however, military losses in European
wars forced Spain to return Louisiana to
France. Spain was soon shocked to find an
aggressive republic, the United States, on her
Provincias Internas border, following Napoleon's
sale of Louisiana to the Americans in
1803. Once again, Spain was restricted to the
Southern Plains. For the remainder of their
tenure in North America, the Spanish made
a concerted effort to keep the Americans out
of the Southern Plains, which they continued
to use as a buffer zone for Mexico's silver
mines. Spanish officials, for example, liberally
granted licenses to comancheros, for they
thought that the itinerant traders could help
to gather intelligence on American actions in
the Plains. Legally, because France and the
United States had not formalized the southern
border of the Louisiana Purchase, neither side
had a definite claim to the Southern Plains.

The Spanish–Plains Indian interaction remained
active until the collapse of the Spanish
Empire. A decade of unrest culminated in
the Mexican Revolution in 1821, which ended
three centuries of Spanish presence in North
America. Still, the Spanish legacy was profound.
Missions, presidios, and ranches had
fixed the Spanish and their institutions and
culture on the Plains margins. An amalgamation
of the Indigenous peoples and Spanish
gave rise to a dynamic mestizo culture, which
became an integral part of life in the Plains.
Politically, Mexico inherited Spain's claim to a
great portion of the Southern Plains, a demand
that was confirmed in the Adams-Onís
Treaty in 1819, just two years before the end
of Spain's hegemony. According to the treaty,
American and Spanish possessions were separated
in the east by the Sabine River (which
still separates Louisiana and Texas) and in the
north by the Red River and, west of the 100th
meridian, the Arkansas River. Although these
boundaries were largely abstractions that ignored
Native Americans' territorial claims,
the fact that Spain managed to claim such a
large portion of the Southern Plains testifies
to its significant historical role in the region.



Mexicans and the Plains, 1821-1846

The period of Mexican rule in New Mexico
and Texas was marked by growing political
instability, economic difficulties, and dismantling
of missions, presidios, and other colonial
institutions. New Mexico and Texas were isolated
from the political core of central and
southern Mexico and suffered from a lack of
governmental direction and from deteriorating
economic systems. Also a reflection of
their isolation from Mexico's core areas, New
Mexico and Texas began to be pulled into the
American orbit. The growing American influence
first contributed to the Texas Revolution
in 1836, then culminated in the annexation of
Texas and New Mexico by the United States in
1845 and 1848, respectively.

Yet these enormous changes created only
ripples in the Plains. Throughout the Mexican
period, comancheros continued to make trade
journeys among Comanches and Kiowas,
keeping in place the economic ties between
New Mexico and the Plains. Trade, albeit
more limited in scope, also continued on the
Texas frontier. However, the acute financial
problems of the Republic of Mexico made it
impossible for the frontier officials to abide by
the provisions of the Indian treaties, which
prompted the Comanches and Kiowas to escalate
their raiding activities in New Mexico and
Texas. In Texas an additional problem was the
relentless northward and westward thrust of
the settlement frontier, which gained momentum
in the 1820s as increasing numbers of
Americans and Europeans migrated to the
province. By 1833 a great portion of the Plains
south of the Arkansas River had already been
allocated to immigration agents called empresarios,
although the lands were still under
Comanche and Kiowa control. When settlers
pushed to the north, the Comanches and
Kiowas retaliated with raids. By 1840 raiding
had become so widespread that a virtual state
of war existed on the New Mexico and Texas
Plains border.

The most crucial development of the Mexican
period in the Plains was the expansion of
the private land-grant system onto the Llano
Estacado. This rose from the dread of American
territorial expansion, which was fueled
by growing American economic influence in
New Mexico after the opening of the Santa Fe
trade in 1821. Determined to eliminate the
American threat, Mexican governors in the
1820s and 1830s made huge land grants to the
Baubiens, Mirandas, and other leading families
of New Mexico. The recipients of the
grants agreed to put settlers on their lands,
which, the governors hoped, would fasten
Mexico's hold on the territory and act as a
barrier against American expansion. By the
early 1840s the whole western flank of the
Southern Plains from the Arkansas River to
the Canadian River had already been allocated
as private grants. Although Indian occupation
kept the assigned lands thinly populated, the
grants gave the Mexican elite a strong legal
claim to large portions of the Southern Plains
on the eve of American takeover.



Mexican Americans and the Plains, 1846-1900

The annexation of Texas pushed the United
States and Mexico toward war. Mexico had
never recognized Texas independence and
viewed the annexation as an act of aggression.
The United States did recognize the Republic
of Texas in 1837: because so many Americans
had migrated to Texas, it was considered a
logical extension of a growing empire that
would eventually reach to the Pacific. The
Plains proper, firmly in the possession of the
Indians, played a marginal role in this struggle.
However, because Texas claimed a southern
and western border all the way to the Rio
Grande, and because Mexico insisted on the
Nueces River, the Southern Plains was involved,
at least on the map, in an international
conflict. The Mexican American War of 1846.
48, although fought outside the Plains, still
had enormous ramifications for the region.
The Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo, which stipulated
the terms of the peace, transferred New
Mexico and part of Colorado to the United
States, extended the Texas boundary to the
Rio Grande, and, in effect, placed the Southern
Plains within the United States.

At first the United States focused its efforts
on the Rio Grande Valley in New Mexico and
in the San Antonio region in Texas. The immediate
goal was to absorb those economic
and population centers into the national system
by introducing American jurisdiction, establishing
representative governments, controlling
the Catholic Church, and remaking
land laws. While major economic, social, and
political changes were forced upon the Mexican
Americans of New Mexico and Texas, they
still retained their distinctive culture. They
clung to Catholicism, Spanish and Mexican
customs, and the Spanish language, and they
celebrated Mexican national holidays and
built adobe houses. They also demanded
power, better living conditions, and fair treatment.
During the latter part of the nineteenth
century, most of New Mexico's territorial delegates
to Washington DC were Mexican Americans.
In Texas, Tejano workers organized several
strikes.

Meanwhile, the Plains remained a periphery
where Mexican-born ciboleros and comancheros
could operate relatively undisturbed
by the federal government. In fact, the
comanchero trade reached its height as late as
the 1860s and 1870s, when the comancheros
began to traffic in cattle the Comanches stole
from Texas ranches. Texas longhorns found a
ready market among wealthy New Mexican
merchants, who had begun to produce meat
for federal beef contractors. Encouraged by
the burgeoning trade, comancheros started
to build semipermanent trading centers along
the well-traveled trade routes of the Llano
Estacado. These trading camps, which often
featured dugouts, stone houses, and rudimentary
irrigation systems, represented the first
substantial Mexican American settlements in
the Plains.

The confinement of Native Americans on
reservations by the mid-1870s paved the way
for an even more permanent Mexican American
settlement in the Plains. Pastores (shepherds)
from New Mexico filled the vacuum
left by the removed Comanches, Kiowas, and
Plains Apaches. Prompted by a growing market
for wool in the United States after the Civil
War, the pastores expanded their operations
from the Rio Grande and Pecos Valleys onto
the Llano Estacado, where abundant shortgrasses
provided plentiful forage for their
herds. Using the traditional Spanish transhumance
system, pastores moved their flocks
between summer and winter pastures, making
large circuits along old Indian and comanchero
trails. A mix of merino and Spanish
chaurro breeds, New Mexican sheep proved to
be well adapted to the Plains environment,
and their owners thrived.

As the number of pastores on the Llano
Estacado grew, they began to congregate into
small communities called plazas. By the 1880s
dozens of small and large plazas were distributed
along the Canadian River valley and
its tributaries, the core sheepherding region.
Besides their function as herding centers, the
plazas were nuclei of Mexican American culture
in the Plains. A typical plaza featured
a single line of adobe or rock houses surrounded
by a New Mexican.type stone wall.
An irrigation ditch, or acequia, provided water
for a fruit orchard and small fields of
corn, beans, melons, and peppers. Social
life revolved around fiestas, all-night bailes
(dances), traditional Mexican games such as
la pelota (a form of field hockey), and regular
Catholic services (the Catholicism practiced
in the plazas could differ considerably from
the Catholicism practiced elsewhere in New
Mexico and Texas, where there was much
more official church control). A nearby cemetery
signaled a long-term commitment to the
region.

The pastores flourished in the Plains until
the mid-1880s, when they were replaced by the
expanding open-range cattle industry. By the
1890s only a few pastores remained on their
shrinking pastures; most had been eliminated
by Anglo-American ranchers' barbed wire,
threats, and restrictive laws. Many retreated to
the urban areas of New Mexico, only to return
in large numbers to build railroads across the
Texas Panhandle in the late 1880s and 1890s.
Some pastores remained on the Llano Estacado
and began to work for the same cattle
barons who had dispossessed them. By the
1880s about one-fourth of all cowboys working
on the Plains cattle trails were Mexican
Americans. Through their labor, these Mexican
Americans made a significant contribution
to an industry that had already been
heavily influenced by Spanish and Mexican
ranching heritage. From the gear and methods
used, to its vocabulary, the Anglo-American
cattle industry of the Great Plains was built
on a Spanish-Mexican foundation. Anglo
cowboys, often working alongside vaqueros,
rode on Mexican stock saddles, garnished
their stirrups with "taps" (tapaderas), used the
lasso (lazo) or lariat (la reata), collected the
animals in annual roundups (rodeo or corrada),
and relaxed by engaging in rowdy
drinking binges (parrandas).

While Mexican Americans were making
important contributions to the social and economic
life of the Southern Plains, their hold
on the land was slipping away. The Treaty of
Guadalupe Hidalgo had promised to respect
the landholdings of Mexican citizens, but decisions
made in American courts and legislatures
undermined the principle. In 1854 the
first American surveyor-general to New Mexico
discovered multiple claims and overlapping
land grants. Confusion governed New
Mexican land policy, triggering more claims
and divesting many Mexican Americans of
their homes and fields. Furthermore, after the
introduction of the Homestead Act in 1862,
Mexican Americans also had to compete with
Anglo farmers for the land.

In 1891 Congress created the Court of Private
Land Claims to hear disputes in New
Mexico and Colorado. In a few years, Mexican
Americans lost more than 33 million acres.
Lawyers were paid for their services in land;
some attorneys amassed fortunes by taking
huge amounts of land from villages as fees.
Dispossessed Mexican Americans sought
work in Colorado as miners, in Texas as rail
workers, and on the Central Plains as betabeleros–
beet workers, planters, and harvesters.

Mexican Americans did not accept these
changes without resistance. In the late 1880s,
largely as a response to the uncertainty and
corruption surrounding land titles, a group of
Mexican Americans and sympathetic Anglos
organized a vigilante group called Gorras
Blancas, or White Caps. Operating mainly in
the New Mexico Plains, the Gorras Blancas
resisted fencing of the ranges by railroad companies,
cattlemen, and other land claimants
and sought to protect Hispano land grants.
They tore up railroad tracks and fences,
formed a local political party, and were instrumental
in obtaining legislative action to preserve
the grants.

By the end of the nineteenth century, the
culture of the Great Plains–its economy, architecture,
social customs, and ethnic fabric–
displayed strong traces of Spanish and Mexican heritage. This heritage reflected the long
tenure of Spanish and Mexican people in and
around the region, a tenure that had begun
with the first Spanish expeditions in the sixteenth
century. Around 1900 a new period began
in the history of Mexican Americans and
the Great Plains. Before 1900, Spanish, Mexican,
and Mexican American influence had
emanated to the Plains from the adjacent regions
of New Mexico and Texas. In the twentieth
century, however, people from all over
Mexico and from Central America began to
migrate to the Plains in search of employment
and to escape the economic or political conditions
in their home countries.



Latinos and the Plains in the Twentieth Century

During the twentieth century two important
trends emerged with reference to Mexicans
and Mexican Americans and the Great Plains.
First, they moved more widely throughout the
region. Migration to the Central Plains was
particularly significant, and that migratory
process was different from past migrations.
The displacement and the transitory aspects
of the migration of Mexicans and Mexican
Americans fueled labor abuses and unrest.
Some Plains industries, such as meatpacking,
became dependent upon Mexican and Mexican
American labor. Second, Mexican Americans
had begun to infiltrate the power structures
of American society, including political
offices. This new development reached the
highest levels of local, state, and national government.
Throughout these changes, Mexican
Americans retained significant aspects of their
culture, with their music, art, and culture developing
regional and national prominence.

Beginning in the 1880s the Mexican population
in the Great Plains began to increase, the
direct result of a transportation revolution created
by the railroad. Between 1882 and 1912 U.S.
rail corporations built four lines from the
heart of Mexico into California and New Mexico.
Following these lines (and often building
them) Mexicans traveled to Texas, Colorado,
and Oklahoma to work in booming coal and
agricultural industries. It was, however, the social
upheaval surrounding the Mexican Revolution,
which began in 1910, that pushed large
numbers of Mexicans into the United States
and the Great Plains. The first major wave of
immigration started in 1900. Most of these
"first wavers" settled in Kansas; a smaller number
made their way to other Central Plains
states. In 1900 the U.S. census counted only 182
Mexicans in Oklahoma, Kansas, Nebraska,
South Dakota, and North Dakota combined.
But by 1910 that number had increased to
11,384. Over the course of the following decade,
23,201 Mexicans migrated into these states, and
in the 1920s, 32,240 more followed. Actual
numbers were much higher; census authorities
have noted that these figures represent a gross
undercount of migratory Mexican immigrants.
Immigration halted in the 1930s, as the
Great Depression eliminated job opportunities
and some states started repatriation movements,
deporting both Mexicans and Mexican
Americans to Mexico. By 1940 this immigration
had lowered the region's Mexican and
Mexican American population to 8,452.

Most Mexicans in the Plains lived a migratory
life. They were mainly males, and they
frequently traveled back across the border,
visiting the families they had left behind in
Mexico. The nature of their employment,
moreover, was very transient, so Mexican migrants
frequently moved around within the
Plains. They labeled themselves solos, characterizing
the solitary migrant lives that most of
these immigrants led. The lives and work patterns
of solos, therefore, were the result of several
interrelated factors: the labor market, the
demands of employers, the convenience of rail
travel, and the desire to see their families.

Two other factors influenced the kind of
jobs that were made available to Mexican
workers. Racism excluded Mexicans from
skilled and semiskilled work; only unskilled
industrial and agricultural employment remained
open. Moreover, not only were the
majority of jobs unskilled and poorly paid, but
they were also seasonal. Railroad companies, a
major employer of immigrants, usually hired
from March through May or October. Sugar
beet growers, the other major employer, hired
in six-month cycles ending in November or
December. The seasonal nature of the solos'
employment left them with a period of time
during which they could return to Mexico or
the Southern Plains and see their families. This
travel was facilitated by the extensive rail networks
that crisscrossed the Plains and extended
well into Mexico. While the initial wave
of Mexicans came as solos, later waves of migrants
settled down permanently. After 1910
railroad companies came to the conclusion
that seasonal workers were less profitable than
permanent workers–a seasonal worker could
easily protest low wages by leaving his job and
finding a new one elsewhere. So rail companies
began hiring Mexicans in more permanent
positions. To encourage this they began transporting
entire Mexican families into the
United States and settling them in the company's
locale. By 1927 sugar beet companies
were copying railroad hiring practices. At the
end of the decade, the seeds of permanent
Mexican American communities in the Central
Plains had been planted, and the colonias
in the Southern Plains were replenished.

Migration patterns varied with the type of
employment. Mexicans employed in the rail
industry, traqueros, crossed the Mexico-U.S.
border at El Paso. There they were recruited to
work for railroads from all over the nation.
Traqueros heading to the Plains traveled first
to Kansas City, where most stayed to work for
the Santa Fe Railroad. A smaller number
moved on to other areas. Betabeleros, laborers
in the sugar beet fields, followed a different
migratory route. Sugar companies, in particular
the Great Western Sugar Company, recruited
thousands of Mexicans directly from
Mexico and brought them through New Mexico
and the Southern Plains. The numbers escalated
as the industry grew, increasing significantly
when World War I reduced domestic
labor supplies. In 1915 Great Western recruited
only 500 Mexican workers; in 1920 the company
hired 13,000 Mexicans, and in 1926,
14,500 Mexicans. As with traqueros, betabeleros
first gathered in Kansas City. From there,
they moved to the beet fields of northern Colorado,
Nebraska, Kansas, Wyoming, Montana,
South Dakota, and North Dakota. By
1920 Mexicans became synonymous with beet
workers in the Plains, and by 1927 they comprised
90 percent of all beet workers in the
region.

Despite the different routes of arrival and
their uneven distribution over Plains states,
betabeleros in the Plains demonstrated a
strong working-class solidarity. These workers
succeeded in organizing despite their migratory
lifestyles and the racism directed against
them by employers who had a free hand in
using union-busting tactics. The workers first
formed organizations such as the Comisión
Honorifica Mexicana to protest discrimination.
By World War I, with encouragement
from the Industrial Workers of the World, the
betabeleros organized to gain higher wages. In
the early 1920s they formed the Mexican Beet
Workers Committee, later Asociación de Betabeleros,
an organization aimed at improving
working conditions and ensuring fair employment
practices.

At its peak, the Asociación de Betabeleros
united some 10,000 workers from Colorado,
Nebraska, Kansas, Wyoming, and Montana.
When the American Federation of Labor
(AFL) rejected their efforts to affiliate, the
Asociacion aligned instead with communists
and socialists to form the United Front Committee
of Agriculture Workers in 1932. Although
they commanded a formidable membership
of 18,000, they were still not able to
strike successfully against the powerful sugar
companies of the Great Plains.

In 1935 several local beet-worker organizations
joined to form the Colorado Conference
of Beet Field and Agricultural Unions. They
then affiliated with the Agricultural Workers
Union, a branch of the AFL. In 1937 these
workers left the AFL to affiliate with the United
Cannery, Packing, and Agricultural Workers
of America (UCAPAWA), a branch of the newly
formed Congress of Industrial Organization.
ucapawa claimed some 18,000 to 20,000 Mexican
American beet workers in the Plains, of
whom 60 percent were Mexican-born and 40
percent American-born. But like the other
efforts at organization, UCAPAWA failed, in this
case because of the inept leadership of European
American organizers who knew little
about the beet industry or Mexican Americans.

Although the majority of Mexican Americans
in the Plains were betabeleros and traqueros,
some worked in other industries as
well. During World War I, Mexican Americans
were employed in the meatpacking industry in
Kansas, Oklahoma, and Nebraska. In 1921, 200
to 300 Mexican Americans worked in Kansas
City plants, and in 1927 approximately 600
worked in the South Omaha stockyards. They
also worked in the cotton fields of southern
Oklahoma and the mines of southeastern
Oklahoma and southern Colorado. In the
mining town of Lafayette, just outside Denver,
for example, Mexican Americans composed 52
percent of the miners between 1921 and 1928.

The economic hardships of the Great Depression
intensified racist attitudes toward
Mexican immigrants. Nativists, many of
whom belonged to trade unions, blamed
cheap Mexican labor for stealing jobs from
"hardworking Americans," meaning Anglos.
The U.S. government responded by implementing
a program designed to "repatriate"
undocumented workers. While for the most
part this program did not extend beyond California,
Arizona, and the Plains states of Texas
and New Mexico, Immigration and Naturalization
Service (INS) officials derived the idea
of mass deportation from the practices of a
Plains city. As early as 1921, metropolitan Denver's
county sheriff had independently ordered
his law enforcement department to bus
undocumented workers back to the Mexican
border.

While one segment of the American public
was aligned against Mexican immigration, another
segment, growers in the Southern Plains,
clamored for more low-paid Mexican workers.
Manpower shortages during World War II further
increased the need for labor. The federal
government responded by entering into an
agreement with the Mexican government that
created what later came to be known as the
Bracero Program. Through this 1942 agreement,
the Mexican government facilitated the
importation of temporary workers in exchange
for the guarantee that Mexican nationals
would have full protection under federal
laws.

The Bracero Program provided muchneeded
labor to several Plains states. There is,
however, a dearth of information about exactly
how many braceros entered the Plains,
where they went, and in what industries they
worked. Texas was probably the only Plains
state to receive large numbers of braceros.
They faced great difficulties there. Almost
from the outset of this program, the Mexican
government banned braceros from entering
the state because of racial abuses practiced by
Texas growers. A similar situation existed in
Wyoming. Consequently, after Wyoming received
just 650 braceros in 1942 and 1943, the
Mexican government prohibited its nationals
from working in the state. Both Texas and Wyoming
eventually regained access to braceros,
and Texas continued to import large numbers
until the end of the program in 1964.

Twenty years after the first repatriation program,
the federal government mounted yet
another initiative to deport undocumented
workers, ironically at a time when the Bracero
Program was still going strong. "Operation
Wetback" began in 1954 and lasted a little over
two years. Of the Plains states, only Texas and
New Mexico were targeted. In Texas, the ins
deported 81,127 "illegals" and intimidated an
estimated 500,000 to 700,000 undocumented
workers into leaving. Many deported workers
simply turned around at the border and reentered
the United States. In September of 1956
the ins officially terminated Operation Wetback,
proclaiming that it had cleared the targeted
states of all undocumented Mexicans.
This program had the devastating effect of allowing
increased employer exploitation of
their Mexican workers. If a Mexican worker
were to complain, the employer would simply
call the INS.

This abusive treatment of Mexicans and
Mexican Americans did not go unchallenged.
In the 1960s the Chicano movement started
in California and across the Southwest. One
valiant effort was that of César Chavez and
his United Farm Workers. One of the preeminent
leaders in this labor movement, Dolores
Huerta, was born in the Plains (in the nowdefunct
coal-mining town of Dawson, New
Mexico, in 1930), though she moved to California
as a child. By the end of the decade,
Chicano activism focused on three Plains
states: New Mexico, Colorado, and Texas.
From these states came three dynamic leaders.

Reies Lopez Tijerina was the first of these
leaders to emerge. Born in Falls City, Texas,
in 1926, Tijerina had labored as a youth on
Texas cotton plantations and in Colorado beet
fields. He began his political activities in New
Mexico in the early 1960s. Aiming to reclaim
land in New Mexico stolen from Hispano
landowners shortly after the 1848 Treaty of
Guadalupe Hidalgo, Tijerina formed the Alianza
Federal de los Pueblos Libres (Federal Alliance
of Free City States). In 1968 Tijerina
organized a political party, Partido Constitucional
del Pueblo (People's Constitutional
Party), which received several thousand votes
in that year's gubernatorial election. His bestknown
accomplishments were the 1966 occupation
of the Echo Amphitheater in the Kit
Carson National Forest and his 1967 raid on
the Rio Arriba County Courthouse in Tierra
Amarilla, New Mexico, an action aimed at arresting
the district attorney.

In 1969 Tijerina's movement came to an
abrupt end when U.S. Forest Rangers arrested
him and his wife for destroying U.S. forest
signs while attempting to occupy the Coyote
Campsite, again in the Kit Carson National
Forest. After 775 days of incarceration, Tijerina
came out of prison repudiating violence.
He found upon his release that his position
of leadership in the movement had waned.
Another activist from the Plains, Rodolfo
"Corky" Gonzalez, had simultaneously been
developing another strand of the Chicano
movement.

Gonzalez, a native of Denver, parlayed his
experiences as a professional boxer into a successful
political and business career. In the
mid-1960s, however, he changed from mainstream
politics to activism in an effort to address
issues specific to his community. Gonzalez
returned to the Denver barrio to organize
the Crusade for Justice, a movement for social
justice, and to lead protests such as the 1968
West Side High School walkout, which was
prompted by the killing of fifteen-year-old
Joseph Archuleta by a police officer. He also
published an epic poem, "I Am Joaquin," that
became the most inspirational piece of literature
in the Chicano movement.

In 1969 Gonzalez organized the Youth Leadership
Conference (YLC) in Denver. At this
event, he adopted the term "Chicano," meaning
a U.S.-born Mexican, and he introduced
Mexican Americans to the vision of Aztlán, the
mythical Chicano homeland. From that time
on, the term "Chicano" and the search to regain
Aztlán became the defining characteristics
of a movement for social and economic
justice among many Mexican Americans of the
Plains. A long-lasting legacy of the Crusade for
Justice in Denver is the Escuela Tlatelolco, a
community-controlled alternative school still
in operation three decades after its founding in
the late 1960s. In 1972, with a mandate from the
YLC, Gonzalez organized a Colorado chapter of
La Raza Unida, an independent Chicano political
party that had been founded in Texas two
years earlier.

La Raza Unida was founded in Texas by Jose
Angel Gutierrez, another important Chicano
leader. In 1967, while still a student at St.
Mary's University in San Antonio, Gutierrez
organized the Mexican American Youth Organization
(MAYO). In 1970, after failing to obtain
MAYO representation in city government,
Gutiérrez organized La Raza Unida.

La Raza achieved immediate success in the
small community of Crystal City in South
Texas, located just off the Plains. Here, within
one year, Gutierrez became president of the
Zavala County school board, and twentythree
of the twenty-four positions were filled
by Chicanos. In 1971 La Raza members moved
to expand the party's influence to a statewide
level by contesting seats on the Houston, Fort
Worth, Dallas, and San Antonio city councils
and school boards. In 1972 Ramsey Munoz ran
on the La Raza ticket as the party's Texas gubernatorial
candidate, and he experienced
greater success than anyone, including La
Raza leaders, had expected. That same year La
Raza voted to go national, at which time Gonzalez
organized the Colorado chapter.

At the beginning of the twenty-first century
Mexican Americans and Mexicans continued
to occupy many of the same niches in the
Great Plains labor market that they had occupied
for almost a century. Increasingly,
Central Americans joined them in these jobs.
Although it is difficult to assign numbers–
many are undocumented workers who moved
back and forth across the border–it is evident
that the majority worked in agriculture, manufacturing,
and construction. Meatpacking
drew thousands into the region each year. Nowhere
did this industry have a greater impact
than in Nebraska.

From 1980 to 1990 the number of Mexicans
and Central Americans in Nebraska more
than doubled. This increase was largely explained
by the opening of meatpacking plants
in Grand Island, Lexington, Omaha, and other
cities. Large companies such as Iowa Beef
Packers were attracted to the area by the promise
of tax cuts and other benefits. The meatpacking
companies relied on and recruited
nonunion immigrant labor, particularly Mexicans and other Latin Americans. In the 1970s
they paid most of these workers about $6 an
hour, substantially less than the $30,000 a year
made by unionized meatpackers, and this
trend continued into the 1980s and 1990s. Labor
recruiting focused on Texas border towns
and was so successful by the mid-1990s that 65
percent of all meatpacking workers in Nebraska
were of Mexican origin. In Lexington,
Nebraska, for example, the Mexican population
increased from 6 percent of the town in
1980 to 23 percent in 1993. But there was no job
security, the housing provided usually turned
out to be dilapidated, and the work itself was
grueling and hazardous.

Terrible working and living conditions led
to unionization drives in the late 1980s. Two
locals of the United Food and Commercial
Workers union were particularly active. In
1989 Local 271 attempted to organize the Millard
packing plant in Omaha, only to encounter
resistance from plant management. This
dispute reached the National Labor Relations
Board in 1995. Local 22 also attempted to organize
several plants, including an Iowa Beef
Packers plant in Fremont and a Monfort plant
in Omaha. The Monfort effort resulted in a
union contract in 1997. Meatpacking plants
often responded to union activity by increasing
their cooperation with ins officials searching
for undocumented workers. The result
was an increase in raids on the Mexican communities
in the area, and deportations were
frequent.

Exploitation of Mexican and Mexican
American meatpacking workers was not limited
to Nebraska. In Greeley, Colorado, similar
conditions existed. Following the temporary
shutdown of a Monfort meatpacking
plant there in 1980, the local meatpackers'
union disbanded, giving Monfort a free hand
in its treatment of the new workers the company
hired when it reopened in 1982. Monfort
started by filling its factories with Mexican
and Central and South American workers.
Working conditions were no better than at the
meatpacking plants in Nebraska, and Greeley
city officials were reluctant to take action
against Monfort's exploitation of its workers
because the local economy relied heavily on
the meatpacking industry.



The Hispanic Impact


Hispanic population in the U.S. Great Plains as a percentage of total population, by county, in 2000


At the beginning of the twenty-first century,
Mexicans and Mexican Americans maintained
a significant presence in the Southern
Plains. In a broad belt of counties reaching
along the western Great Plains from the Mexican
border to southern Colorado, "Persons of
Hispanic Origin," the designated census category
encompassing Mexican Americans, Mexicans,
and other Latin Americans, comprised
more than 25 percent of the total population.
In Texas, Hispanics comprised one-third of
the total state population: a number of counties
in the Panhandle saw their Hispanic population
grow by more than 10 percent from
1990 to 2000. In Colorado, Hispanics made up
13 percent of the total population. In Denver
alone there were more than 397,000 Hispanics
in the 2000 census, comprising almost 19 percent
of the city's total population.

These large populations have had an extensive
impact on the social, economic, and political
makeup of Plains communities. In Denver,
for instance, Hispanics have turned their
formidable numbers into political representation.
Federico Peña, secretary of transportation
in President Bill Clinton's first administration
and secretary of energy for two years
in Clinton's second administration, cut his
political teeth in Denver. Originally from
Texas, Peña served as Denver's mayor from
1983 until 1990, when he stepped down from
that position. As secretary of transportation,
Peña turned his position into positive gains
for Denver when he helped the city obtain
nearly $5 billion in federal funds for a new
Denver International Airport.

Other distinguished Mexican American
politicians from Colorado include Polly Baca
(born in 1943 in Greeley), the first minority
woman elected to the Colorado Senate, and
Linda Chavez (who was born in Albuquerque
in 1947 but grew up in Denver), the highest-ranking
woman in the Reagan administration
and a leading conservative figure.

In New Mexico, where in 2000 all the Plains
counties were more than 25 percent Hispanic,
political power for Mexican Americans is
deeply rooted. Miguel Antonio Otero (1829–
82) served in the territorial legislature, was appointed
as territorial district attorney, and was
elected New Mexico's delegate to Congress in
1855. The tradition continued: Mari-Luci Jaramillo
(born in 1928 in Las Vegas) was appointed
ambassador to Honduras by President
Jimmy Carter in 1976, the first Mexican
American woman to hold an ambassadorship.
Bill Richardson went from New Mexico congressman
to serving as ambassador to the
United Nations and as secretary of energy in
the second Clinton administration. In 2002 he
was elected governor of New Mexico.

Numbers and percentages of Hispanics decrease
northward up the Plains and eastward
away from the linear concentration running
from the Rio Grande to Colorado. Persons of
Hispanic origin comprise 7 percent of the total
Kansas population. Finney County, home
to meatpacking plants in Garden City, has
Kansas's highest concentration of Hispanics.
Voters in Hutchinson, in central Kansas, elected
the Great Plains' first Mexican American
woman mayor, Frances Garcia, in 1985. In Nebraska,
Hispanics constitute 5.5 percent of
the total population, but in the Panhandle,
the prime sugar-beet-growing region, and in
counties with meatpacking activities they are
a more significant presence. Moreover, Hispanics
are now Nebraska's largest minority
population and, with a 338 percent growth
from 1990 to 2000, its fastest-growing one. In
Oklahoma, Hispanics account for 5 percent of
the total population; their numbers are relatively few but the distribution is broad. In only
a handful of counties in Oklahoma is the population
less than 1 percent Hispanic.

The only other Plains state to have a sizable
Hispanic population is Wyoming. Along the
sugar beet belt of southern Wyoming, Hispanics
comprise between 5 and 25 percent of
the population in each county. In the Northern
Plains states, there are relatively few Hispanics.
Recent (1996) statistics of ethnic origin
for the Canadian Prairie Provinces show Alberta
with the largest concentration of Hispanics
(10,335), but this represents only 0.3
percent of the total population. Manitoba had
2,735 Hispanics in 1996 and Saskatchewan
1,229.

The impact of Mexicans and Mexican
Americans on the modernization of the Great
Plains has been invaluable. Without their labor
there is no doubt that this region would
not enjoy the farming and industrial prosperity
that it has achieved. One of Colorado's
preeminent labor leaders in the postwar era
was Mexican-born Tim Flores, who rose from
farm laborer in Greeley and brick mason in
the Pueblo steel mills to leadership positions
in the Colorado Labor Council before his
death in 1988.

Their cultural contributions also have enriched
the region. The poet Bernice Zamora
was born in 1938 in the small town of Aquilar
in south-central Colorado and grew up in
Pueblo and Denver. The greatest of all women
golfers, Nancy Lopez, grew up in Roswell,
New Mexico. Tejano music, originating in the
Rio Grande Valley at the southern edge of the
Plains, and a full range of social and political
programming are now widely broadcast on
more than forty full-time and scores of parttime
Spanish-language radio stations from
Texas to Nebraska and Wyoming. And wherever
there is a Mexican American population
of any significant size, there is a family Mexican
restaurant, perhaps the greatest addition
to Plains cuisine in the twentieth century.
These contributions have not always come
easily. Mexican Americans have often been rewarded
with racist treatment and second-class
citizenship. But like the Chicano activists of
the 1960s and 1970s, they will continue to
strive for a better life in this region.

The story of the Spanish, Mexicans, and
Mexican Americans in the Great Plains is one
that features great sacrifice and perseverance.
There were dramatic events that shaped migration
and settlement, such as the Narvñez
expedition crashing ashore in Texas, the opening
of the Santa Fe Trail, and the establishment
of the Bracero Program. There were collisions
of empires and economies, such as the
Mexican Revolution, the Texas Revolution,
the Mexican American War, and the Industrial
Revolution. There are cultural continuities,
built around faith, song, home, and word.
And there are the people–Francisco Vÿsquez
de Coronado and Pedro de Villazur; the traqueros
and betabeleros; Federico Peña and
Corky Gonzalez; pastores and vaqueros; and,
yes, recruited worker Damasso Armendñriz.

See also EUROPEAN AMERICANS: Coronado; Spaniards; Villasur, Pedro de / FOLKWAYS: Cowboy Crafts / IMAGES AND ICONS: Quivira / INDUSTRY: Meatpacking.


 

Malcolm Yeung
Evelyn Hu-DeHart
University of Colorado at Boulder



Almaráz, Félix D. Jr. "An Uninviting Wilderness: The
Plains of West Texas, 1534–1821." Great Plains Quarterly 12
(1992): 169–80. Andreas, Carol. Meatpackers and Beef Barons: Company Towns in a Global Economy. Niwot CO:
University Press of Colorado, 1994. Carranza, Miguel A.
"The Hispanic Presence on the Great Plains: An Introduction."
Great Plains Quarterly 10 (1990): 67–70. Castro,
Tony. Chicano Power: The Emergence of Mexican America.
New York: Saturday Review Press, 1974. Cooper, Marc.
"The Heartland's Raw Deal: How Meat Packing Is Creating
a New Immigrant Underclass." The Nation, February
1997: 11–17. De León, Arnoldo. Mexican Americans in Texas: A Brief History. Wheeling IL: Harlan Davidson,
Inc., 1999. Garcia, Juan R. Mexicans in the Midwest, 1900– 1932. Tucson: University of Arizona Press, 1996. González,
Nancie L. The Spanish-Americans of New Mexico: A Heritage of Pride. Albuquerque: University of New Mexico
Press, 1969. Haverlank, Terrence. "The Changing Geography
of U.S. Hispanics, 1850–1990." Journal of Geography 96
(1997): 134–45. Nostrand, Richard L. The Hispano Homeland.
Norman: University of Oklahoma Press. 1992. Oppenheimer,
Robert. "Acculturation or Assimilation: Mexican
Immigration in Kansas, 1900 to World War II." Western Historical Quarterly 16 (1995): 429–48. Simmons, Helen,
and Cathryn A. Hoyt, eds. Hispanic Texas: A Historical Guide. Austin: University of Texas Press. 1992. Smith, Michael.
"Beyond the Borderlands: Mexican Labor in the
Central Plains, 1900–1930." Great Plains Quarterly 1 (1981):
239–51. Weber, David J. The Spanish Frontier in North America. New Haven CT: Yale University Press, 1992.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>