<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pd.007</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Appeal to Reason</field>
      <field name="author">Dean, Virgil W.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




APPEAL TO REASON

First published by Julius A. Wayland at Kansas
City on August 31, 1895, Appeal to Reason was a
four-page socialist weekly. In February 1897
Wayland moved the paper to the southeast
Kansas coal-mining town of Girard. There,
drawing on the talents of some fine editors
and numerous nationally known socialist
thinkers and writers, the Appeal became the
leading socialist publication in the United
States, with a circulation of 760,000 at its peak
in 1913.

Throughout its history, the Appeal highlighted
the evils of capitalism and the promise
of a socialist society. It fashioned itself the
champion of a uniquely American brand of
socialism and was tremendously successful
because it combined this epigrammatic socialism
with the right amount of muckraking,
scandal, and circulation hustle. During the
first decade of the twentieth century, American
socialist leader Eugene Debs worked as a
staff writer for Appeal to Reason, and the paper
introduced its readers to Upton Sinclair's
attack on poor and unsanitary working conditions
in the meatpacking industry. A serialized
version of Sinclair's The Jungle first appeared
in Wayland's weekly, beginning on February
25, 1905.

Upon the death of J. A. Wayland by suicide
in November 1912, Fred D. Warren, who had
been working as editor for some years, continued
publishing the Appeal. He was succeeded
by Walter H. Wayland, son of the
founder, Louis Kopelin, and then Emmanuel
Haldeman-Julius. Appeal to Reason and its editors
came under frequent attack by federal
authorities during the years leading up to
World War I. Some detractors labeled it the
"Squeal for Treason," while Theodore Roosevelt
branded it a "vituperative organ of propaganda,
anarchy and bloodshed." Nevertheless,
to the chagrin of many socialists, Appeal to
Reason supported President Woodrow Wilson
and the crusade to "make the world safe for
democracy." It continued its advocacy of socialism
and the international movement but
changed its name to the New Appeal.

Soon after the war ended, the paper reverted
back to its old title. It had, however, lost
much of its zeal and readership and wilted
under the anti-Red reaction of the early twenties.
Appeal to Reason was discontinued in
1922, but its last editor, Haldeman-Julius, continued
the paper's long-standing effort to educate
the masses through his immensely popular
Little Blue Book series, which brought
quality literature to the public in inexpensive
pocket books.


Virgil W. Dean
Kansas State Historical Society




Appeal to Reason, Kansas City MO, Kansas City KS, and
Girard KS, 1895–1922, Library and Archives Division,
Kansas State Historical Society, Topeka KS. Shore, Elliott.
Talkin' Socialism: J. A. Wayland and the Role of the Press in
American Radicalism, 1890–1912. Lawrence: University
Press of Kansas, 1988. Wayland, Julius Augustus. Collection.
Pittsburg State University Library, Pittsburg KS.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>