<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ha.045</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Tafoya, José Piedad (c. 1830-?)</field>
      <field name="author">Ellis, Mark R.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




TAFOYA, JOSÉ PIEDAD (c. 1830-?)

Sometimes called the "Prince of the Comancheros,"
José Piedad Tafoya was born in northern
New Mexico around 1830. He was in the
Great Plains as early as 1859 with his father,
who was scouting for a survey party along the
Texas–New Mexico border. Although Tafoya
owned a large sheep ranch in San Miguel
County, New Mexico Territory, by the early
1860s he was heavily involved in the comanchero
trade on the Texas Llano Estacado–
comancheros traded livestock, horses, and
manufactured goods with Plains Indians, particularly
the Comanches. During the Civil War,
when the U.S. military and the Texas Rangers
had little control over the Southern Plains, Tafoya
operated a trading post in present-day
Briscoe County, Texas, where he traded stolen
Texas cattle and horses.

Comancheros began losing business during
the 1870s Plains Indian Wars. Because of their
knowledge of the Southern Plains and familiarity
with the Plains Indians, the military enlisted
or conscripted many comancheros as
guides, interpreters, and scouts. In 1874 Col.
Ranald S. Mackenzie allegedly forced Tafoya
to serve as a scout in the campaigns against the
Comanches. At the end of the Southern Plains
Indian Wars, Tafoya and other former comancheros,
such as Casimero Romero and Juan
Trujillo, herded sheep in the Texas Panhandle.
By the early 1880s, however, most had been
forced out by large cattlemen, and Tafoya
moved his wife and four children back to his
ranch in New Mexico. In 1893 the U.S. Court
of Claims subpoenaed Tafoya and several ex-comancheros
as witnesses for Indian depredation
cases. Based upon Tafoya's testimony,
Charles Goodnight and other Texas ranchers
were awarded $14,176. Tafoya probably spent
his remaining years on the family ranch and
died in obscurity sometime after 1893.


Mark R. Ellis
University of Nebraska at Kearney




Kenner, Charles Leroy. A History of New Mexico–Plains Indian Relations. Norman: University of Oklahoma Press,
1969. Rathjen, Frederick W. The Texas Panhandle Frontier.
Austin: University of Texas Press, 1973.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>