<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.arc.024</field>
      <field name="titleMain">German Architecture</field>
      <field name="author">Domer, Dennis</field>
      <field name="text">

 




GERMAN ARCHITECTURE

During the nineteenth century, particularly
after the Civil War, Germans in large numbers
streamed into the Great Plains from the eastern
United States, Canada, and Germany and
created a distinctive German American architecture
throughout the region. Although
modified significantly by dominating environmental,
cultural, social, technological, and
political influences and reduced in quantity
and distribution through use and obsolescence,
remnants of this architecture still exist
in thousands of churches, barns, houses, and
commercial buildings from Canada to Texas.

Whether in city or country, German immigrants
settled the Great Plains in Catholic and
Protestant enclaves, and, through the powerful
nexus of religion, language, and architecture,
their churches functioned as cultural
centers of German American life. The most
widely distributed German church architecture
in the Great Plains is Rundbogenstil,
a Romanesque Revival architecture that the
Bavarian architect Friederich von Gärtner
(1792–1847) used in the Ludwigskirche, the
Bavarian Court and State Library, and the
Ludwig Maximilian University in Munich.
Roman in origin, the Rundbogenstil church
featured the basilica plan with prominent
half-circle or segmented arches that form
doors, windows, and cornices on plain building
surfaces of brick or stone.

By the second half of the nineteenth century,
Rundbogenstil architecture in religious and
commercial buildings had spread throughout
Germany and widely throughout the Great
Plains. St. Bonaventure Catholic Church in
Raeville, Nebraska, constructed of brick by the
Omaha architect Jacob M. Nachtigall in 1917,
is a Rundbogenstil church with arcades of
arched openings on its towers and west entry
and along its aisled nave, transepts, and apse.
There is a series of corbeled arches on its cornice.
The twin, cross-gabled, polygonal spires
of this Nebraska church are characteristic of
many churches in Germany and the Great
Plains. A typical smaller variant is the Evangelische
Lutherische Dreieinigkeits Kirche, a
stone Rundbogenstil church with a single
tower built in the shape of a cross in Grand
Island, Nebraska, by German-born masons
William and Jacob Scheffel from 1894 to 1896.
These masons carved elaborate, half-round
arches over doors and windows that open into
an aisled church with a nave, transept, chancel,
and U-shaped balcony. Stained-glass windows
with German inscriptions also frequently
characterize Rundbogenstil churches
on the Plains. For example, St. Anthony of
Padua Catholic Church in Wichita, Kansas,
built in 1905 and called the "German Church,"
displays magnificent stained-glass religious
scenes that were designed in Germany, shipped
in pieces, and reassembled in grand windows
under round-arched openings of brick.

Unfortunately, many Plains Rundbogenstil
churches, built to symbolize a vibrant German
American culture and to last an eternity,
are being closed for lack of priests. Many other
distinctive examples of late-nineteenth- and
early-twentieth-century German Rundbogenstil
architecture survive in brick and stone industrial
and commercial buildings in a variety
of urban settings.

Germans who settled in rural areas expressed
their ethnic heritage in a rich vernacular
architecture consisting of barns and other
farm buildings such as springhouses, granaries,
and cribs. The German bank barn originated
in southern Germany and Switzerland
and was built extensively by Germans who migrated
west from the Middle Atlantic cultural
hearth into the northern half of the Great
Plains. This gabled barn is rectangular in
form, and one of its long sides is built into a
bank or earthen ramp that leads to the main
floor of the structure, consisting of a central
threshing bay, a hay-storage bay, and a grainstorage
bay. Openings placed strategically in
the storage bays allow feed to be dropped into
the lower story, which is usually divided into
numerous sections of various sizes to feed and
shelter different kinds of animals, especially
cattle, milk cows, and horses. The foundations
of these barns are often thick limestone walls
that enclose the lower story while supporting
the main floor. The expansive two-story space
of the main floor is usually formed by a massive
structure of hand-hewn or -sawn wooden
posts and beams; diagonally placed corner,
wall, and roof braces; and girts, purlins, and
rafters that have been mortised, tenoned, and
pegged together in a manner common for
centuries in Germany and Central Europe.
The exterior skin of these large barns is
usually vertical board nailed to structural
members, and roofs are board with wooden
shingles or metal sheathing. Sometimes the
German bank barn has a forebay that extends
the main upper floor in a cantilever over the
first-floor wall on the downside of the hill and
gives outside shelter to animals below.

Another German barn type is the double
crib barn, which originated in German
speaking areas of the Alps, was transported
almost without change by German speakers
into the Middle Atlantic and Upland South of
North America, and was diffused from there
throughout the South and into the Southern
Great Plains, especially Texas. This barn has
two square cribs separated by an open driveway
that runs transversely to the gable roof.
The doors to the cribs most often face the
interior driveway. The cribs are usually composed
of logs connected at the corners with
round or V notches, and the spaces between
the logs typically are not chinked.

Although more Germans immigrated to the
North American Plains than any other ethnic
group, the heritage of German house types
and domestic construction details is relatively
thin and often misunderstood. The most
widely built rural house type in Germany was
the Wohnstallhaus, or barn house, which sheltered
humans and animals under one roof.
Although there are rare examples of this house
type from the Canadian Prairie Provinces and
the Northern Plains, most Germans followed
English precedent in their new country by separating
their houses from their barns and
adopting house types of the dominant American
culture such as the symmetrically composed,
central hall, I house, or hall and parlor
house. Even then, however, German Americans
often expressed their own cultural preferences,
including their off-center doors, main
entries into kitchens, central chimneys with
stoves, half-timbered walls, V-notched or
dovetailed corners in log structures with hewn
stone chinking between the logs, casement
windows, and exterior plastering.

One descendant of the Wohnstallhaus that
frequently goes unrecognized and is confused
with similar house types among other ethnic
groups is the German American two-door
house. This type was common in rural Germany
from the seventeenth to the twentieth
century and can be found in significant numbers
nearly everywhere Germans settled, from
the eastern seaboard to the Plains. This rectangular,
gable-roof, balloon-frame house is
usually covered with clapboard, although the
oldest examples are sometimes half-timbered
structures filled with nogging. The house
varies from one and a half to two stories and
has two entries on the front long side, a front
porch, and a kitchen ell or shed addition in
the back with a porch. One entry led to a formal
parlor (seldom used except for special
family events), and the other entry led to a
much-used informal parlor or living room.
The living room had a stair to the second floor
and interior doors that opened to the formal
parlor and to the kitchen in the back.

See also EUROPEAN AMERICANS: Germans.


Dennis Domer
University of Kansas





Domer, Dennis. "Genesis Theories of the German-
American Two-Door House." Material Culture 26 (1994):
1–35. Leiding, Gerlinde. "Germans in Texas." In To Build in a New Land: Ethnic Landscapes in North America, ed.
Allen G. Noble. Baltimore md: Johns Hopkins University
Press, 1992: 362–78. Pierson, William H., Jr. "Richard Upjohn
and the American Rundbogenstil." Winterthur Portfolio
21 (1986): 223–42.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>