<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.082</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Texas Republic</field>
      <field name="author">Cuthbertson, Gilbert M.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




TEXAS REPUBLIC

The Great Plains was in politics before politics
was in the Great Plains. The Llano Estacado
and the tierras lejas (distant lands) of early
maps caused controversy during the Texas Republic,
the period of Texas's independent government
that lasted from its revolution against
Mexico in 1836 to its annexation by the United
States in 1845. Even later, some areas in the
Texas Plains prided themselves on only having
been crossed by Coronado, Comanches, or
Lipan Apaches before 1870. The power to ward
"hostiles" of the frontier still survives in Texas's
constitution.

Comanche raids, including the kidnapping
of Cynthia Ann Parker in 1836 and Matilda
Lockhart in 1838, necessitated the protection
of the western frontier during the Texas Republic
and the establishment of "ranging
companies" under Capt. John C. Hays. This
organization began the development of the
law enforcement officers known as the Texas
Rangers. One of the most significant episodes
of frontier violence was the Council
House Fight at San Antonio of March 19, 1840.
Representatives of the Comanche delegation
were arrested for failing to return all of their
captives.

President of the Texas Republic Mirabeau
Lamar viewed the Great Plains as part of Texas's
"manifest destiny." Imperial Texas extended
at least to Santa Fe. Lamar's Santa Fe
expedition in 1841 was arrested by Mexican
governor Manuel Armijo near Tucumcari on
October 5. A retaliatory expedition, led by
Jacob Snively in 1843, was halted by Capt.
Philip St. George Cooke of the U.S. Army. Part
of the Texas annexation settlement required
reparations of $10 million for the seizure of
the Snively expedition. The expedition's arrest
was made on the Arkansas River in an area
Texas claimed as its territory.

During the Texas Republic only a few small
forts were established west of San Antonio and
the Balcones Escarpment. Defense of the trade
routes against marauders and protection of
settlements west of Lamar's new capital at Austin
became major priorities after annexation.

See also LAW: Texas Rangers.


Gilbert M. Cuthbertson
Rice University




Fehrenbach, T. R. Lone Star. New York: Macmillan Publishing
Company, 1968. Webb, Walter Prescott. The Texas
Rangers. Austin: University of Texas Press, 1970.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>