<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ind.051</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Potash</field>
      <field name="author">Jackson, Grant D.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




POTASH

Potash refers to compounds containing the element
potassium such as potassium chloride,
potassium sulfate, potassium-magnesium sulfate,
potassium nitrate, and mixed sodiumpotassium
nitrate. The word "potash" comes
from an early settler term, "pot-ashes," referring
to potassium salts obtained by burning
wood in pots. It is called potassium oxide in
the ceramics industry.

Potassium is the seventh most abundant element
of the earth's crust and is found in all
plants and animals and in soils, rocks, minerals,
oceans, rivers, and lakes. Potassium is
essential for plant and animal growth; consequently,
95 percent of potash production is
used as fertilizer or plant food. The remaining
5 percent of potash production is consumed
by the chemical industry for a variety of products
such as glass, ceramics, soaps and detergents,
explosives, dyes, medicines, and alkaline
batteries.

Potash is usually mined from underground
bedded salt deposits. Shafts are sunk, and the
ore is dug out or pumped to the surface
through solution mining. Canada leads the
world in both production and reserves. The
bulk of Canada's potash production (about 9.3
million tons in 1997) and reserves are located
in the Great Plains. The potash industry is
focused in Saskatchewan, because there the
ore deposits are thick and relatively close to
the earth's surface; similar but more expensive
to mine ore deposits occur in Alberta, Manitoba,
North Dakota, and Montana. Currently,
about ten mines produce potash in
Saskatchewan. Most of the output is exported:
about 55 percent to the United States and
about 40 percent overseas via Vancouver. The
United States is a much smaller potash producer
(about 1.6 million tons in 1997), but
again, the Great Plains is the leading region.
About 80 percent of U.S. production comes
from the Carlsbad area of New Mexico.


Grant D. Jackson
Montana State University




The 2000–2005 Outlook for Potash, Soda, and Boratic Minerals in North America and the Caribbean. CD-ROM, Icon
Group International, 2001.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>