<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ct.030</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Lincoln, Nebraska</field>
      <field name="author">Mutunayagam, N. Brito Davis, Abigail Posie</field>
      <field name="text">

 




LINCOLN, NEBRASKA

In 1859 a group of settlers gathered in southeastern
Nebraska Territory on the banks of
Salt Creek and founded the hamlet of Lancaster.
They had aspirations that Lancaster would
grow into a manufacturing center based on
local salt deposits, aspirations that came to
nothing. But by 1866 the hamlet was named
the county seat, and a year later, when Nebraska
attained statehood, the site was formally
selected as the capital and renamed in
honor of President Abraham Lincoln. The settlement
was incorporated in 1869.

The city grew rapidly, attracting one railroad
by 1870 and seven by 1900. In addition
to its governmental function, Lincoln became
home to meatpacking, agricultural-processing,
and printing industries and the
first of many insurance companies by the
1880s. Diversity was recognized early on by
the Nebraska legislature's donation of a site
for the African American congregation of the
Quinn Chapel African Methodist Episcopal
Church, in 1873. The city's population grew
rapidly to 55,000 in 1890, then declined during
the depression of the 1890s. Recovery was slow
at first, but Lincoln's population then increased
during every decade of the twentieth
century, reflecting the diversified economic
base, which furnished jobs, and the attractive
living environment. By 2000 the city's population
had reached 209,192, having grown at an
annual rate of 1.6 percent over the previous
three decades.

As the seat of state, city, and county governments,
Lincoln remains a major administrative
city. It has a mayor-council form of
local government and the option of home rule
under the Nebraska constitution, which authorizes
the city to operate under its own charter.
The University of Nebraska, established
in 1869, Nebraska Wesleyan University, and
Union College give the city its identity as
a university town. A mix of manufacturing,
transportation, trade, commerce, insurance,
health, and other service industries characterize
the contemporary diversified economy of
the city.

The premier work of architecture in the city
is the Nebraska State Capitol, designed by architect
Bertram Grosvenor Goodhue. The
First Plymouth Congregational Church, the
old university library (Architectural Hall),
and the William Jennings Bryan House are
also noteworthy and among several buildings
listed on the National Register of Historic
Places. Distinguished architects Phillip Johnson
and I. M. Pei designed the Sheldon Memorial
Art Gallery and Sculpture Garden and
the National Bank of Commerce, respectively.
Another local point of interest, Pioneers Park,
designed by landscape architect Ernst H. Herminghaus
(who also laid out the state capitol
grounds), lies at the fringe of the city.

Prominent historical residents of Lincoln
include John J. Pershing, commander of
American forces in Europe during World
War I; William Jennings Bryan, orator, U.S.
congressman, and three-time Democratic
Party presidential candidate; Charles Dawes,
vice president under Calvin Coolidge in 1924;
Willa Cather, Nebraskan author and 1895 graduate
of the University of Nebraska–Lincoln;
George Beadle, Nobel Prize–winning biologist;
and Roscoe Pound, legal scholar, dean of
the University of Nebraska Law College, and
dean of Harvard Law School.
    
Gilded Age Plains City website.    

See also ARCHITECTURE: Herminghaus, Ernst; Nebraska State Capitol / LITERARY TRADITIONS:
Cather, Willa / POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT:
Bryan, William Jennings / WAR:
Pershing, John J.


N. Brito Mutunayagam
Abigail Posie Davis
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Clerk of the Legislature, ed. Nebraska Blue Book 1998.
1999. Lincoln NE: Unicameral Information Office, 1999.
Copple, Neal. Tower on the Plains: Lincoln's Centennial History, 1859-1959. Lincoln NE: Lincoln Centennial Commission
Publishers, 1959. McKee, James L. Lincoln, the Prairie Capital: An Illustrated History. Woodland Hills CA:
Windsor Publications, 1984.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>