<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.gen.036</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Stewart, Elinore Pruitt (1876-1933)</field>
      <field name="author">George, Susanne K.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




STEWART, ELINORE PRUITT (1876-1933)

Born in White Bead Hill in the Chickasaw Nation,
Indian Territory, on June 3, 1876, Elinore
Pruitt Stewart was no stranger to hardship. At
eighteen, with both parents dying within a
year of each other, Stewart became responsible
for six siblings. A few years later, she married
and presumably divorced Harry Rupert.
In 1906 she moved with her daughter, Jerrine,
and two sisters to Denver, where she told
everyone that she was a widow. A life of poverty
in Denver encouraged her to try homesteading,
so in 1909 she answered Clyde Stewart's
advertisement for a housekeeper in the
Denver Post. Stewart and her daughter arrived
in Burntfork, Wyoming, in April 1909. In May
she filed on 160 acres adjoining Clyde's homestead,
and within eight weeks, married her
employer. Stewart spent the rest of her life
on the ranch, except for a few years when
the family moved to Boulder, Colorado, for
the children's education. She died in a Rock
Springs hospital on October 8, 1933, at the age
of fifty-seven.

Stewart's life is not unique, for many women
homesteaded as well as became "mail-order
brides." However, her contributions to American
history and literature are the letters that
she wrote to a former employer in Denver,
Mrs. Juliet Coney, which were published serially
in the Atlantic Monthly and then in book
form by Houghton Mifflin Company as Letters of a Woman Homesteader (1914) and Letters on an Elk Hunt (1915). Stewart describes in detail
the joys and hardships of homesteading and
raising a family on the frontier. Each letter
is often a complete narrative in itself; however,
together they combine to create a type of
story cycle, with characters and themes recurring.
Although largely autobiographical, these
works were written for publication, and she
was known to have "never let the facts get in the
way of a good story."


Suanne K. George
University of Nebraska at Kearney




George, Susanne K. The Adventures of the Woman Homesteader: The Life and Letters of Elinore Pruitt Stewart. Lincoln:
University of Nebraska Press, 1992.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>