<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.med.018</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Emporia Gazette</field>
      <field name="author">Turner, Sally E.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




EMPORIA GAZETTE

For more than 100 years, the Emporia Gazette
has covered the city of Emporia, Kansas, its
joys, heartaches, and scandals, and surrounding
Lyon County, providing Kansas with news
and opinion that includes the state, nation,
and world. It has endured as one of the state's
strongest small dailies and has been a training
ground for some of the state's best journalists.

Emporia, from its very beginning, had a
strong tradition of newspapers, as did many
pioneer communities. Its first newspaper, the
Kanzas News, began just a few months after
the town was founded in 1857, when Senator
Preston Plumb started the newspaper to promote
development and the Republican Party.
A former owner of the News, J. R. Graham,
founded the Emporia Gazette in 1890 but sold
it to W. Y. Morgan during the 1893 depression.

Five years after its founding, when newspapers
and the country were struggling financially,
the Gazette was purchased for $3,000 by
William Allen White, a twenty-seven-year-old
Republican newspaperman ready to hone his
reporting and editing talents. After writing for
several Kansas publications, White considered
purchasing newspapers in several northeast
Kansas cities, including Lawrence, but decided
on Emporia, the town where he was born and
where he had attended college. White borrowed
the money to purchase the paper from
Governor E. N. Morrill, from the estate of
Senator Plumb, from Plumb's brother George,
and from Major Calvin Hood. All were paid
back quickly, mostly from money made from
the sale of White's books and stories, which
were gaining popularity.

White played the role of small-town country
editor, conscious of his role in bolstering
the community. His editorials, often in support
of small-town values, were frequently
printed in national newspapers and magazines,
bringing recognition to the Gazette.
With new and faster presses and more efficient
distribution, larger editions and wider circulation
became possible, and the increased
subscription rates and advertising revenue put
the paper on a sound financial footing.

In many respects, the Gazette is similar to
most local hometown newspapers. It covers
the local area; it reflects its community's tastes;
it records the town's history. Unlike most
dailies, however, the Gazette also gained national
prominence, as William Allen White
became well known through his political associations,
national writings, and Pulitzer Prize.
As its reputation grew, the newspaper began
to attract starstruck young journalists, who
were trained by various Gazette managing and
city editors. Many went on to become some of
the state's best journalists.

To this day, the Gazette, appearing six days a
week, maintains its roots in community coverage.
It has stayed in the White family, first with
his son and daughter-in-law, William Lindsay
and Kathrine White, then with his granddaughter
and her husband, Barbara and David
Walker, and now his grandson and his wife,
Chris and Ashley Walker. While the newspaper
remains a training ground for many novice
reporters, its editors help maintain continuity
with long careers in the newsroom.


Sally E. Turner
Emporia State University




The Emporia Gazette's Album of Memories. Emporia KS:
Emporia Gazette, 1976. Griffith, Sally Foreman. Hometown News: William Allen White and the "Emporia Gazette."
New York: Oxford University Press, 1998. White,
William Allen. The Autobiography of William Allen White.
New York: Macmillan Publishing Company, 1946.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>