<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pe.036</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Llano Estacado</field>
      <field name="author">Templer, Otis W.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




LLANO ESTACADO

The Llano Estacado is that part of the High
Plains south of the Canadian River in northwest
Texas and eastern New Mexico. Encompassing
more than 30,000 square miles, this
vast, semiarid tableland is one of the flattest
parts of the United States. Its surface
slopes gently toward the southeast at about
eight to ten feet per mile, and elevations range
from around 2,500 feet on the eastern and
southern margins to more than 4,200 feet in
the northwest.

The Llano is a coalescent alluvial plain
composed of Tertiary and Pleistocene deposits
carried east from the Rocky Mountains by
east.west trending streams. This alluvium
also forms the massive Ogallala Aquifer that
underlies the Llano and is the region's major
water source. Later the Llano was isolated hydrologically
from the rest of the High Plains
by the downcutting of the Canadian River and
was deprived of runoff from the Rockies by
the headward erosion and stream piracy of
the Pecos River. Distinct physical boundaries
mark three sides: the rugged valley of the Canadian
River in the north and the prominent
Caprock and Mescalero Escarpments on the
east and west respectively. To the south, the
Llano merges imperceptibly with the Edwards
Plateau. The surface of the Llano is covered
with widespread eolian deposits of sands,
marls, and loams. Sand sheets and dunes are
found in many places, with the largest dune
field extending across the New Mexican Llano
into Bailey and Lamb Counties, Texas. Among
the Llano's topographic features are numerous
playa basins and a few shallow draws that
drain southeastward and form the headwaters
of the Red, Brazos, and Colorado Rivers.
These intermittent streams have cut scenic
canyons into the eastern escarpment, most
notably Palo Duro Canyon. Nearly all runoff
on the Llano, however, accumulates in the
thousands of ephemeral, freshwater playa
lakes, which capture as much as two to three
million acre-feet of water annually, although
most of it soon evaporates.

Several theories explain the origin of the
name Llano Estacado, though none is universally
accepted. At present, a favored theory
is that "estacado" refers to the palisaded or
stockaded appearance of the caprock in many
places, especially the west-facing escarpment
in New Mexico.

See also WATER: Playa Lakes.


Otis W. Templer
Texas Tech University




Hunt, Charles B. Natural Regions of the United States and
Canada. San Francisco: W. H. Freeman and Company,
1974. Leatherwood, Art, and Otis W. Templer. "The Llano
Estacado: A Geographic Overview." In Land of the Underground
Rain: Water Usage on the High Plains, edited by
Donald W. Whisenhunt. Portales, NM: Eastern New Mexico
State University, 1974: 12–22.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>