<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fil.061</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Splendor in the Grass</field>
      <field name="author">Tibbetts, John C.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SPLENDOR IN THE GRASS

Splendor in the Grass DVD Cover
     

Based on an original screenplay by Kansas
playwright William Inge, Splendor in the Grass
(1961) reflects Inge's concerns with the problems
and frustrations of small-town life in the
Midwest. Determined to shake off his frustrations
over his first failure on Broadway, A Loss of Roses (1959), Inge went to Hollywood to
prepare Splendor for Elia Kazan, who had directed
Inge's Dark at the Top of the Stairs for
the stage two years before. Characteristically,
the setting is a small Kansas town in the late
1920s (obviously Inge's hometown of Independence,
Kansas) where two ill-fated young
lovers, Bud Stamper and Deanie Loomis,
struggle against the sexual inhibitions and
materialistic priorities of their parents. As a
result of their enforced separation, Bud goes
to Yale and marries someone else, and Deanie
goes insane and is confined to a mental hospital
after a suicide attempt. At the end, both are
forced to accept what has happened and find
consolation in poet William Wordsworth's
words, "We will grieve not, rather find /
Strength in what remains behind."

Although Kazan was anxious to capture the
look of Kansas, most of the film was shot on
Long Island and Staten Island and in Poughkeepsie
and the Filmways Studio in New York
City. The role of Deanie was played by a young
Natalie Wood, already an established actress.
Bud's oppressive oil-rich father was played by
Pat Hingle. Warren Beatty, a newcomer from
the cast of the failed A Loss of Roses, appeared
as Bud, and Inge appeared in a cameo role as
the Reverend Whiteman. Ironically, the film's
theme of the dangers of prudery and hypocrisy
led to the excision by the Production Code
censors of several scenes thought to be too
sexually explicit. Despite some critical cavils
(Dwight Macdonald scornfully suggested the
film was essentially "an Andy Hardy story with
glands"), the film opened to sensational box
office returns and earned Inge an Academy
Award for his screenplay.

See also LITERARY TRADITIONS: Inge, William.


John C. Tibbetts
University of Kansas




Ciment, Michel. Kazan on Kazan. New York: Viking Press,
1974. Inge, William. "A Level Land." In What Kansas Means to Me, edited by Thomas Fox Averill. Lawrence:
University Press of Kansas, 1991: 153–59. Voss, Ralph. A Life of William Inge. Lawrence: University Press of Kansas,
1989.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>