<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.art.027</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Gilpin, Laura (1891-1979)</field>
      <field name="author">Sandweiss, Martha A.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




GILPIN, LAURA (1891-1979)

Photographer Laura Gilpin was born on April
22, 1891, in Austin Bluffs, Colorado, just north
of Colorado Springs. She was given a Brownie
camera for her twelfth birthday, and by the
time she was seventeen she was experimenting
with Autochromes, an early form of color
photography. In 1916 she moved to New York
and, using money from her own Colorado
poultry business, enrolled in the Clarence H.
White School of Photography. There she acquired
her skills, but it was in the Southwest
and the southwestern Great Plains that she
found her subject.

Gilpin returned to her native Colorado
Springs, established a professional photographic
business, and began photographing
the prairies of eastern Colorado. She would
remain a landscape photographer for sixty
years, becoming the first American woman to
devote herself to that art. As her interest in
the cultural dimensions of the landscape grew,
Gilpin expanded her work to embrace prehistoric
sites, contemporary Native American
settlements, and the communities of people
living and working along the Rio Grande. She
addressed these topics in her four major
books (The Pueblos: A Camera Chronicle, 1941;
Temples in Yucatan: A Camera Chronicle of
Chichén Itzá, 1948; The Rio Grande: River of Destiny, 1949; and The Enduring Navaho,
1968), each of which explores the interactions
between people and their physical environment
and focuses on the ways in which the
landscape shapes cultural patterns even as
people reshape their physical surroundings.
Gilpin moved to Santa Fe, New Mexico, in
1945. In her later years, an emerging market
for fine art photography brought renewed attention
to her life's work. Gilpin died on November
30, 1979, in Santa Fe. She bequeathed
her photographic estate to the Amon Carter
Museum, Fort Worth, Texas.


Martha A. Sandweiss
Amherst College




Laura Gilpin Photographs and Papers, Amon Carter Museum,
Fort Worth. Sandweiss, Martha A. Laura Gilpin: An Enduring Grace. Fort Worth: Amon Carter Museum, 1986.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>