<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.law.001</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Law</field>
      <field name="author">Leyton-Brown, Kenneth</field>
      <field name="text">

 




LAW

A legal system is one of the forces that shapes
a society and gives it structure. This is true
whether one considers very informal legal systems,
typical of early tribal communities on
the Great Plains, or highly formal systems
characteristic of modern urban life. In every
case, legal systems have been put in place and
designed to preserve established values and
ways of behaving and also to achieve desired
changes in society.a transformative role too
often overlooked. One result of the imbedding
of legal systems within societies is that there
have been as many systems of law on the Great
Plains as there have been communities. This
great diversity reflects the richness of the history
on the region but has also meant that
significantly different legal systems have at
times had to coexist. This has not always been
easy to achieve, and on occasion it has not even
been possible. The result has sometimes been
disputes amounting to battles for supremacy
between systems and between the communities
of which they were a part, though on
other occasions mutual modification has provided
a more peaceful solution. What has
emerged in the modern period is to a great
extent a legacy from all that has gone before, a
legal system derived predominantly from England's
but preserving elements from other
European traditions and from Aboriginal systems.
It is a system that has been and continues
to be shaped by the unique experience and
diverse communities of the Great Plains.


Indigenous Law

The legal history of the Great Plains may be
said to begin with the first appearance of organized
communities in the region thousands of
years ago and long before the arrival of Europeans.
The very persistence of these communities
over time makes it obvious that they
possessed systems of law su.ciently flexible
and sophisticated to answer the needs of societies
ranging from sedentary agricultural
groups with comparatively large population
centers to scattered bands of nomads who depended
primarily on hunting and gathering
for their survival. To some extent they all possessed,
for example, rules governing interpersonal
relations and well-developed ideas
about property that regulated access to the resources
of the land. Archaeologists have demonstrated
that small groups (e.g., individual
families) frequently had exclusive or at least
first access to the resources in a defined locale.
Larger groups (e.g., tribes) likewise occupied
defined territories from which they endeavored
to exclude others. Unfortunately, little
except generalities can reliably be set forth in
outlining the finer points of this sort of early
legal history and the rules these societies developed
to give them structure and cohesion
because of the lack of accessible and reliable
evidence available to the historian. Unfortunately,
this problem is only somewhat abated
as we come to consider more recent times and
even approach the arrival of Europeans.

In some respects, of course, Native peoples
on the Great Plains began to feel the first effects
of European influence before.in some cases
long before–the actual arrival of the Europeans
themselves. The introduction of the
horse, new trade goods (notably, firearms),
and diseases to which they had little resistance
disrupted traditional ways of living and patterns
of trade and drastically altered power
relationships. The effects of these changes were
visible wherever Europeans established themselves,
but, like the ripples from a rock thrown
in a pond, they spread far and wide, affecting
Indigenous people far away from Europeans
themselves. Precisely how the societies of the
Great Plains adjusted their existing practices to
respond to the new realities–or even if they
did in every case–is very difficult to determine
in the light of existing evidence. There is a body
of oral tradition preserved among the various
peoples who populated the Great Plains in the
years before the arrival of the Europeans, but
for very early periods this is a difficult source
for historians to use, and it is not always seen as
reliable without corroboration.

Nor, it seems, can we say much with confidence
about the period when Europeans first
had a physical presence, in the form of missionaries,
traders, and explorers, on the Great
Plains. These harbingers of change produced
the first body of written material dealing with
the autochthonous population of the Great
Plains, but even with this often fascinating
body of work in hand the legal historian is too
often frustrated. The internal ordering of
Indigenous societies was not something in
which many of these early writers were interested,
and even when it was mentioned, the
observers were not always su.ciently sensitive
to or even capable of understanding what they
saw. With the arrival of larger European populations,
though, we are on firmer ground because
of the increased abundance of written
records and more useful oral accounts.

The latter in particular have proven a valuable
source for reconstructing the laws of a
number of Plains tribes during the nineteenth
century. Both tribes that had a long history
on the Plains such as the Blackfoot and those
that moved into the region only in the eighteenth
century such as the Lakota (Sioux) had
to adjust to new realities. The result was approaches
to law that share certain broad characteristics
such as an emphasis on consensus
and restitution. Among the Kiowas of the
Southern Plains, for example, there were few
conflicts over property, the main exception
being horses. Food was shared and stealing
was rare. Internal family conflicts were also
rare and likely to be settled by reason rather
than by law. Criminal actions were deterred by
the fear of supernatural reprisal (taido). Serious
crimes such as murder might result in
social ostracism or, if they threatened the integrity
of the tribe, in the imposition of the
death penalty, a killing "legalized" by the singing
of a song, which nullified any supernatural
penalty.

There were, however, considerable differences
in legal systems (as in most other aspects
of life) among Plains Indians. The Kiowas' legal
system and, even more so, the Comanches'
were rather informal, certainly when compared
to the Cheyennes, to whom Llewellyn
and Hoebel attributed a "legal genius." In
Cheyenne society, for example, the tribal
chiefs had exclusive jurisdiction over punishment
of a murderer. Punishment generally
meant banishment from the society, though
remission was possible after a number of years
if the perpetrator was penitent. The Cheyenne
legal system, it might be added, had a refined
classification system of what constituted murder
and what might be excused as a justified
killing.

The dynamic and varied Indigenous legal
systems held on to much that harked back to
traditional times but also demonstrated the
ability to respond to new needs. The jurisdiction
of the chiefs is a good example of the
former, and perhaps the best example of the
latter in most tribes, including the Cheyennes,
is the increasing power of the warrior societies
to make and enforce rules. However, the various
tribal systems were eventually to come
into conflict with ultimately more domineering
legal traditions brought to the region by
Europeans.



The Impact of European American Legal System

Spain was active in the southern and France
and England originally along the eastern and
northern parts of the Great Plains. At first directly
and later through colonial offshoots in
the Americas, these three European powers,
with very different legal cultures, began to
transform the region. In all cases it was at first
the policy of the European and later American
powers not to extend their laws to the Indigenous
population. In fact, it was recognized,
either explicitly or implicitly, that it was neither
desirable nor possible to expect the full
body of their national law to apply even to
those of European extraction. In theory, then,
Native peoples would continue to be governed
by their own laws, and Europeans and Americans
would be subject to "appropriate" European
law. In the United States, Indian Country
was territory that was outside the organized
territories and states. Settlers were forbidden
there, and traders could operate only under
license. A series of Intercourse Acts, including
the 1834 act, which applied to the Great Plains,
regulated trade and imposed fines on violations
of the rules governing interactions with
Native Americans.

This separation of legal domains was often
very difficult and sometimes impossible to apply.
Which European or American laws were in
effect and which were not? Which rules should
apply in disputes involving both Indigenous
peoples and European Americans? What was
to be done with the increasing numbers of
people with both European American and Native
ancestry? The result of this period of confusion
was twofold. In the first place, there
is clear evidence that in some cases contact
with European Americans and their ways of
doing things profoundly modified Indigenous
rules and ways of proceeding. For example,
alcohol, forbidden through the Intercourse
Acts, continued to flow into the Plains through
the fur trade and severely disrupted Native
American lives.

But it was the second development that was
ultimately to prove more significant. The law
of the more powerful party, the European
Americans, came to dominate, holding sway
in most of the region and over most matters.
Indigenous law was, by this steady process,
largely marginalized. (Marginalized does not,
however, mean exterminated. Indigenous law
not only survives but in some jurisdictions–
for example, rules concerning access to Native
American sacred sites–has been rejuvenated
and is even modifying the dominant
European-inspired legal system.)

It is difficult to overstate the impact on Indigenous
cultures and indeed on the entire
ecology of the Great Plains itself that was occasioned
by the arrival of large numbers of
European Americans coming not simply to
explore or trade but also to settle and to make
lives for themselves and their children in these
new lands. This process began in earnest during
the nineteenth century and filled the region
roughly from east to west. Friction was
often impossible to avoid as the new arrivals
sought to take control over the lands and water
they needed in order to survive and as a
result dispossessed the Native peoples. This
process, accomplished by a series of treaties
sanctioned by existing European and international
law, occasionally led to violence and
even wars, especially in the United States but
also during two brief episodes in Canada (the
Red River Resistance of 1869.70 and the 1885
Riel Rebellion). But these were only the most
visible evidences of a kind of low-grade battle
that had been in progress for some time as
European American and Indigenous ideas
about the ownership of property competed.

Traders had earlier confronted the fact that
Native peoples often had ideas about private
property quite different from their own. This
was dealt with in a variety of ways; the Hudson's
Bay Company's and American Fur Company's
practice of trading literally through a
hole in the wall so that their customers had no
direct access to the trade goods and could not
simply walk off with what they wanted is a
good example. This fundamentally different
view of property rights remained a source of
friction between European Americans and Native
peoples as the process of settlement continued
and affected everything from land to
movables. One particular focus was the horse,
which had spread rapidly throughout the
Great Plains region after the first Spanish
imports had been introduced in the south.
Horses became an integral part of the life of
many tribes, and possession of horses conferred
great status. The result of this was, eventually,
a period of near constant raiding.
which European Americans, as usual not
overly sensitive to Indigenous life and values,
termed simply "horse stealing"–during which
the aim was to control as many horses as possible.
Any and every horse was fair game in this
passionate activity, with the frequent result
that horses owned by European Americans
were run off by Indians. Unfortunately, what
was a serious though in some respects a sporting
activity for Native peoples was seen as a
very serious crime by European Americans,
and only the efforts of the military in the
United States and lawmen on both sides of the
Canadian-American border prevented more
serious problems from developing. They were
occasionally thwarted by knowledgeable raiders,
who knew they could not be chased across
the international boundary, sometimes referred
to as the "medicine line."

A second problem, related in the minds of
most European Americans but in fact quite
distinct, concerned the safety of cattle kept on
the open range. Native peoples in the Great
Plains depended to some extent on hunting
for their subsistence, and in the northern regions,
where huge herds of bison wandered
the prairies, they were almost entirely dependent
on this important source of food and its
secondary products. It was difficult to persuade
Indian hunters, especially after the destruction
of the great bison herds was well
advanced, that they should not take the cattle
that had replaced them, since hunger and even
starvation were often the only alternative to
killing cattle.

However, the picture so often presented, at
the time and since, of Indians as cattle killers
and horse thieves has been greatly overdrawn.
They did take both cattle and horses in some
numbers, but careful reading of the records of
the time makes it clear that European American
criminals often found it easy to blame Indians
for their own crimes and that many
complained of Indian depredations simply
because they hoped their respective governments
would make good their "losses." In fact,
members of the North-West Mounted Police
in Canada frequently complained in their annual
reports that settlers reported that their
animals had been stolen simply so that the
police would go out and round up their herds
for them in the fall free of charge. In the
United States Indian agents often noted that
"depredation claims" by settlers seemed to coincide
with the arrival of Native American annuity
payments.

From the point of view of many in the
dominant society, a solution to these and
other problems was finally arrived at in both
Canada and the United States when the various
tribes were confined to lands set aside for
them, called reserves in Canada and reservations
in the United States. In the United States
these areas have preserved an important legal
significance, stemming initially from the judgments
of Chief Justice John Marshall in the
famous Cherokee cases–Cherokee Nation v.
Georgia (1831) and Worcester v. Georgia (1832)
–that established the idea of tribes as "domestic
dependent nations" possessing limited sovereignty.
This sovereignty was further defined
by the U.S. Supreme Court in Ex Parte Crow
Dog (1883), where it was ruled that the United
States had no jurisdiction over crimes committed
by one Indian against another. Congress
subsequently acted to limit this sovereignty,
notably, in the Major Crimes Act of
1885, which determined that the United States
did have jurisdiction over Indians for seven
major crimes, including murder, but it remains
an important part of the legal apparatus
of the American Plains.

The "checkerboard" nature of landownership
patterns on Plains reservations, however
(a product of the 1887 Dawes Act, which imposed
allotments on the Indians and permitted
the sale of "surplus" reservation lands to
Americans), makes for extremely complicated
jurisdiction in Indian Country. On many
Plains reservations, non-Indians own most of
the land, the lines between tribal and federal
jurisdictions are blurred, and individual states
also try to assert their legal and political authority.
Landmark cases, including Montana
v. United States (1981), have revolved around
this complex geography and the extent of
tribal jurisdiction over nonmembers of the
tribe living on or, in that case, fishing and
hunting on the reservation. Recent Supreme
Court decisions have even led to the "diminishment"
of reservations, especially in South
Dakota.

In Canada, however, the approach has not
been to recognize group rights, and the various
tribes and bands have not had any formal
power to make and enforce law. This seems to
be changing, though, as a result of the current
strong movement toward First Nations self-government,
a movement at least partly informed
by the perception that the American
approach has its virtues. This movement was
born in the Prairie Provinces, where more
than half of Canada's Status Indians reside,
but opposition to Native self-government is
also greatest in that same region.



The American Legal Frontier

Neither the Spanish nor the French were willing
or able to support the large-scale presence
in the Great Plains proper that would have led
to the institutionalization of their laws there.
Texas did later follow some Spanish concepts
of family and property laws, including the legalization
of adoption and the recognition of
woman's rights to property acquired during
marriage, and there is a legacy of French civil
law, especially in Manitoba. But overwhelmingly,
it was English law that was brought to
the Plains. The United States, despite its violent
separation from England, essentially preserved
the English system of laws and extended
it to much of the Great Plains. To the
north, eventually north of the forty-ninth
parallel, the Hudson's Bay Company and later
Canada also introduced an English-inspired
legal regime.

People of European extraction came to the
Great Plains during the nineteenth century in
great numbers, and they did so, by and large,
to make lives for themselves in this land of
endless possibilities. Much has been made of
the wild frontier that greeted them, with its
violence, its lawlessness, and its "gun-totin'"
heroes. Recent scholarship suggests, however,
that at least as striking is the underlying "law-mindedness"
of its people. Even on the Oregon
Trail, cutting through the Central Plains
in the 1840s, conduct was regulated by respect
for lawful behavior. Constitutions were drawn
up to define the rules of traveling, and the
sanctity of private property was recognized,
even though there was no formal legal machinery
governing actions.

Later, during the settlement era, the Great
Plains became essentially a ranching and farming
frontier inhabited by three related but also
distinct groups–cattle ranchers, sheep ranchers,
and farmers–and the towns associated
with them. It is their often-different needs, and
the frequent friction between them, that provides
an important backdrop for understanding
much of the legal history of the Great
Plains during the nineteenth century.

All three systems needed access to land and
water. However, the different ways they needed
access caused problems that often proved intransigent.
The cattle ranchers, who were usually
the first on the scene, expected and in fact
needed free access to open rangeland and the
region's limited water resources. If they had
these, their often-huge herds could become the
basis of a way of life and also of huge fortunes
and great power. However, there were those
who threatened all this. Sheep, which cattlemen
believed cropped the land so thoroughly
that it could not support cattle, and farmers,
who plowed the prairie and fenced it in, were
perceived as threats to the very survival of cattle
ranching, and so the cattle ranchers resisted
them (and were in turn resisted by them), resorting
to both legal and extralegal means. The
legal means included an appeal to appropriate
political powers, seeking new laws and better
enforcement of existing ones. For one side or
the other, this could produce satisfaction or at
least livable results. The gradual development
of a body of law relating to water rights and
water use is the best example of this and a case
where the law continues to prove responsive to
the ever-changing needs of the region.

The doctrine of riparian rights, whereby
the owner of the land bordering a stream had
the right to use its water, came west with the
earliest settlers. This was, however, a thoroughly
inappropriate system in the arid and
semiarid lands of the Great Plains and was
eventually replaced by what is called the "appropriative
system." This system, which was
largely put in place by the courts of the western
states, protects users of water whether
they are located near the source of water or
not. The 1882 Colorado Supreme Court case,
Coffin v. Left Hand Ditch Company, was a key
decision in this transition. This approach to
water rights and use, modified somewhat in
the case of Native American water rights (see
the 1908 decision of the Supreme Court in
Winters v. United States, which reserved water
rights for reservations from the time of their
establishment), has also been adopted in Canada,
though the active and controlling role of
the provincial governments there has resulted
in its being termed an "allocative system."

The law did not always provide an acceptable
solution, however, and the sort of ranching
operations that developed during the middle
years of the nineteenth century had certain
characteristics that meant that problems associated
with lawlessness were virtually unavoidable.
The best example is rustling, a
problem that was met head-on by the ranchers.
They could not keep their cattle under
constant supervision (that was not compatible
with open-range grazing), but they did brand
them to establish ownership, and they could
see to it that they and the men they hired to
help manage their herds carried guns and
were prepared to use them. This resort to
"self-help" made sense in the absence of reliable
policing, as did its elaboration in the
form of vigilantism, a kind of cooperative self-help.
Such tactics no doubt produced good
results at times, but they also posed a danger,
since the "might is right" approach could easily
lead to excesses and abuses. A group of
citizens rounding up rustlers and robbers
seemed like a good thing, but without the protections
afforded by a fully developed legal
system mistakes were unavoidable, and sometimes
the innocent suffered, not the guilty.
And of course there was a dangerous seduction
about the whole process that made armed
men operating without the sanction of the law
seem an acceptable solution to other perceived
problems. The result at times was that
weaker groups such as farmers and Chinese
could also find themselves the targets of what
was sometimes referred to as "rough justice"–
something that usually had a lot of the former
and very little of the latter.

Another focus of lawlessness during this
period was the towns, especially those located
at the end of the trails used to bring cattle to
the railheads prior to shipping them to market.
The end of a long drive brought to these
towns a large number of men with money in
their pockets and guns at their hips, anxious
to blow off steam in the first saloon they'd
seen for weeks. The results were predictable
(though again, the lawlessness of the cattle
towns has been overblown) and, in the eyes of
the residents of such towns, highly undesirable.
County sheriffs were rare, and townspeople
could not rely on the comparatively
few federal marshals, so in many cases the solution
ultimately adopted was to hire a town
marshal. The names of many of these have
passed into history–and even into legend. In
fact, job mobility between outlaws and marshals
was high. Some men, like Wyatt Earp
and Bat Masterson, walked both sides of the
line. To be successful they had to be willing
and able to meet force with force, and since
they were usually paid, at least partially, according
to the number of arrests made or fines
levied, they tended to be extremely aggressive
in their work. Their results were often crude,
but the work of these men and of the few
corporate bodies such as the Texas Rangers
was all the more important in light of the virtual
absence of proper courts and even the
most rudimentary of prison facilities during
the early years of settlement.



The Canadian Legal Frontier

During the nineteenth century the lands that
were soon to form the Prairie Provinces began
to fill with settlers, though much later (mainly
after 1880) than was the case in the United
States. This timing was important insofar as
the legal history of the region is concerned,
but it is only one of several factors that explain
the significantly different legal culture of the
Canadian Plains.

The Hudson's Bay Company, whose charter
of 1670 granted the great trading company jurisdiction
over a huge area and which extended
a poorly defined body of England's
laws to North America, was not originally active
on the Great Plains. That region was at
first completely unknown to Europeans and
later was seen as little more than a hinterland
of the rich fur-trapping land to the north, but
as the trade progressed and as competition
with Canadian and later American traders became
progressively more fierce, the region was
divided up by the company into jurisdictional
units. The first rudiments of a justice system
were established, notably as a result of English
statutes of 1803 (the Canada Jurisdiction Act)
and 1821 (An Act for Regulating the Fur Trade)
and of the establishment of the Red River
Colony by Lord Selkirk in 1811. The forced
union of the English Hudson's Bay Company
and the Canadian North West Company in
1821–the result of a famous br each of the law,
the 1816 Seven Oaks Massacre–ended the
worst of the violence that had come to characterize
the trade and, more completely though
not unambiguously, extended English law and
legal institutions to the region. Even so, development
of the law was still halting. Something
approaching a full-fledged though very
poorly functioning justice system did develop
at Red River, which had been returned to the
control of the Hudson's Bay Company by Lord
Selkirk's heirs in 1834. But the Métis population
of the colony never really accepted Hudson's
Bay Company rule. Their open practice
of selling robes and furs to American traders
led to the Pierre-Guillaume Sayer trial in 1849.
Sayer was found guilty of illegal trading, but,
with 300 armed Métis protesting outside the
courthouse, he was set free. The Hudson's Bay
Company monopoly on trading was broken.

The antipathy of the company toward settlement,
its desire to keep all costs to a minimum,
and the sense that the days of the great
monopoly trading companies were numbered
all tended to prevent elaboration of the courts,
prison facilities, and other institutions of the
Red River Colony, with the result that when
the area passed from the company's control to
Canada in 1869, the new Dominion found itself
inheriting a justice system that existed
more in theory than in fact.

In taking up responsibility for these new
lands, Canadian authorities had to respond to
a number of needs: to avoid the mistakes of
American policies, which were seen to have
led to a great deal of violence and especially to
the Indian Wars; to assert sovereignty against
what was perceived to be an expansionist
United States; to keep control over a fractious
population, some of whom had recently taken
up arms in an effort to safeguard their rights
under the new political order; to prepare the
region for settlement; and to do all this as
cheaply as possible. The solution arrived at
in 1873 was the creation of the North-West
Mounted Police (NWMP), a body designed primarily
to act as a police force (but some of
whose members served as judges) and to provide
prison facilities. The NWMP juggled these
various roles effectively and ensured that a
comparatively well-developed legal apparatus
preceded settlement in most parts of the Canadian
Prairies. However, having members
perform every role from arresting officer, to
witness, prosecutor, and judge, to jailer unavoidably
left the NWMP open to accusations
of conflict of interest and improper conduct.
At times, especially when enforcing unpopular
laws such as prohibition, the criticism
could be fierce. Nonetheless, when the question
 of dissolving the NWMP was seriously
raised in 1905 (the achievement of provincial
status by Saskatchewan and Alberta meant
that it was questionable whether a federally
controlled police force could continue to operate
in the West), a constitutional amendment
was introduced to preserve what was,
after all, an extremely popular and successful
institution. And so the NWMP and the independent
courts and prisons that had gradually
appeared survived to become the basis of the
provincial justice systems of the Canadian
Prairies.



Twentieth-Century Development

In both the American and Canadian sections
of the Great Plains the late nineteenth century
witnessed dramatic increases in population,
the appearance of towns and cities, and the
maturing of economies and important social
institutions. These developments allowed the
transformation of what had been, in a constitutional
sense, territorial lands into states, in
the case of the United States, and, by the beginning
of the twentieth century, into provinces,
in the case of Canada. This change was
important in the legal sphere since it made the
people of the Great Plains responsible to a
much greater extent for their own legal institutions,
though they were, of course, constrained
in all cases by limits inherent in federal
statutes. To a large extent, the outlines
were already in place, and they were the base
on which the future was built. All Great Plains
jurisdictions inherited common-law traditions
and the broadly similar structures and
ways of proceeding those traditions implied.
Law was to be made by democratically elected
legislators and to a very limited extent by the
courts. Courts, both courts of first instance
and appeal courts, were to be presided over by
judges who were to be impartial and independent
and who were not to take a more active
role in proceedings than necessary. (There is,
however, an important difference between
Canada and the United States here, since in
Canada judges of all superior courts are appointed
by the federal government.) Prisons,
both local jails for those serving shorter sentences–
generally less than two years–and
penitentiaries for those serving longer terms,
were there to punish, rehabilitate, and deter,
and they operated along broadly similar lines.
Finally, in all states and provinces of the Great
Plains, a variety of police forces existed to
serve their communities.

These similarities have also extended to include
some of the most important uses of law.
One of the most long-lived examples of this
has been the use of law, albeit not always successful,
to protect the perceived collective interests
of the inhabitants of the Great Plains.
From the Progressives and others in the United
States who, beginning in the 1890s, tried to use
legal means to control the railways, financial
institutions, and other large businesses that
seemed to stand against the people's interest to
the governments, especially on the Canadian
Plains, that pursued some of these same or
similar goals during the twentieth century, the
Great Plains has produced some of the most
significant legal initiatives on the continent
(not the least of which is women's suffrage). It
should be noted, however, that efforts to use
the law to "protect" society have not always
been so commendable, and one of the blackest
marks on the record of the various Great Plains
jurisdictions is the use majorities have made of
the full apparatus of the law to deny equality to
groups who have at different times been identified
as posing a danger. Indigenous peoples
had already suffered in this way, but as the
nineteenth century came to an end and the
twentieth century began other groups–Chinese,
Germans, Japanese, and many others
besides–were similarly mistreated. For example,
all the American Plains states, except Colorado
and the Dakotas, introduced "alien land
laws" in the early 1920s directed at preventing
Japanese Americans from owning land. This is
a regrettable record for a region that in other
respects–the early achievement of women's
suffrage, for example–has been a leader in
modern legal development.

Within these broadly similar outlines, however,
there was still room for significant variation,
which has, in some cases, tended to increase
over time, especially when American
and Canadian jurisdictions are contrasted.
One good example of this is the generally different
handling of mineral rights in the two
countries. The origin of this difference is that
in Canada mineral rights over much of the
Great Plains region did not pass to settlers and
instead remained vested in the government.
This has meant that in Canada the provincial
governments (especially since 1930, when the
national government finally gave its remaining
crown lands to the western provinces)
have had a much more direct role to play in
the development of extractive industries than
is the case in the United States, and it is probably
safe to say that there are more differences
between Canadian and American law in this
area than there are similarities. Moreover, it
might be argued that this has contributed to
a significantly different perception of the
proper role for government in the economy
and in society generally and therefore of the
proper use of law.

Another instance where there is an apparent
difference is in the approach to public policing.
In the United States one encounters
forces that serve towns and cities, counties,
and states as well as various national bodies.
a complex system with many intricacies involving
separate and overlapping jurisdictions.
In the Prairie Provinces there are only
municipal police forces and the Royal Canadian
Mounted Police, which is rented by the
provinces and numerous smaller municipalities.
(Provincial police are allowed under
Canada's constitution but were found, after a
brief experiment, to be too expensive. Moreover,
their primary responsibility, enforcing
prohibition, did not ensure their credibility.)
However, any differences between Canada and
the United States with respect to policing
mask broad areas of agreement over questions
such as what police ought to do (and not do)
and what powers they need. It is probably also
accurate to say that citizens of both countries
share concerns about the limits that must be
placed on police in a free society.



Contemporary Issues

The existence of a generally satisfactory legal
system in the various jurisdictions of the Great
Plains has not meant the end of the development
of law or that no new challenges have
arisen. One of the most important has been
the question of individual rights and the limits
freedom must place on the coercive power of
the state. In the United States, individual rights
have been guaranteed under the Constitution
for more than two centuries, and the nature of
these rights has been developed and elaborated
by courts for most of that time. Such a
process has been much less apparent in Canada,
until comparatively recent times. But with
the enactment of Canada's Charter of Rights
and Freedoms in 1982 as well as provincial human
rights legislation, Canadian courts have
begun to develop an approach to individual
rights that is in some ways reminiscent of the
American model. Neither country, though,
has been completely successful in identifying
and protecting group rights, though things
like protection of identified groups in rights
legislation and in legal decisions, tribal control
of the administration of justice on reservations
in the United States, the move toward
First Nations self-government in Canada, and
the very recent innovation of sentencing circles
in western Canada seem to indicate that an
approach to law that recognizes that both individual
and group rights can be accommodated
within modern democratic states.


Sign behind bar in Birney, Montana, August 1941


A second area where both differences and
the beginnings of convergence can be detected
is in the methods used to choose important
officials in the justice system. The strongly
democratic character of American selection
procedures–either directly through such
mechanisms as the election of judges, prosecutors,
and high-ranking police officers or
more indirectly through public confirmation
hearings–has traditionally been rejected by
Canadians. Recently, however, a movement,
especially strong in western Canada, has begun
pushing for a more public appointment
process for Canada's judges. But while it seems
likely that Canada's traditionally secretive process
will soon undergo some reform, it is extremely
unlikely that the final result will be
closely modeled on American practices, nor
does there seem to be any move to "democratize"
other elements of the justice system. Instead,
there appears to be more support for
increasing the role of supervisory bodies such
as police commissions, which have mainly civilian
members, and corrective bodies, such as
royal commissions, which have, with increasing
frequency, been created to look at existing
and past problems.

One last trend we might note here is a result
of the popular perception of an increase in
violent crime, despite statistics that show a
steady decrease in such crimes over the last two
decades or more. In the United States the response
has been a huge increase in the prison
population, reflecting higher conviction rates,
a more frequent resort to prison time in sentencing,
and longer sentences. The prison population
in Canada has also increased recently,
though to nothing like the degree it has in the
United States. The fact that Canada has no
death penalty is also a significant difference
between the two countries. An important similarity,
though, and a very worrying one, is the
overrepresentation of minority groups in the
region's prisons, be they Latinos, Native Americans,
or African Americans in American prisons
or Natives in Canadian prisons. This reflects
the serious societal problems faced by
these groups as well as the unequal treatment
they receive from the justice system. Members
of such groups are more likely than others to be
charged, to be convicted, and to be sentenced
to time in prison. They also tend to receive
longer sentences. Addressing this problem will
be one of the most important challenges of the
twenty-first century on the Great Plains as in
other parts of the United States and Canada.

See also AGRICULTURE: Branding / ASIAN
AMERICANS: Asian Exclusion Legislation; Poison Porridge Case; Territory of New Mexico v.
Yee Shun / INDUSTRY: Hudson's Bay Company
/ NATIVE AMERICANS: Sovereignty / POLITICS
AND GOVERNMENT: Forty-ninth Parallel /
WATER: Appropriation Doctrine; Riparian Doctrine; Winters Doctrine.



Kenneth Leyton-Brown
University of Regina




Cutter, Charles R. The Legal Culture of Northern New Spain, 1700–1810. Albuquerque: University of New Mexico
Press, 1995. Knafla, Louis, ed. Law and Justice in a New Land: Essays in Western Canadian Legal History. Toronto:
Carswell, 1986. Llewellyn, K. N., and E. Adamson Hoebel.
The Cheyenne Way: Conflict and Case Law in Primitive Jurisprudence. Norman: University of Oklahoma Press,
1941. McLaren, John, et al., eds. Law for the Elephant, Law for the Beaver: Essays in the Legal History of the North American West. Regina: Canadian Plains Research Center,
1992. Reid, John Phillip. Law for the Elephant: Property and Social Behavior on the Overland Trail. San Marino CA:
Huntington Library, 1997. Richardson, June. Law and Status among the Kiowa Indians. Monographs of the American
Ethnological Society, vol. 1. New York: J. J. Augustin,
1941. Wunder, John, ed. Law and the Great Plains: Essays on the Legal History of the Heartland. Westport CT: Greenwood
Press, 1996.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>