<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.art.018</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Dust Bowl Photographers</field>
      <field name="author">Vollan, Charles</field>
      <field name="text">

 




DUST BOWL PHOTOGRAPHERS

On the Southern and Central Great Plains,
the Great Depression of the 1930s was compounded
by the Dust Bowl, a combination
that put great stress on the people of the region
as well as the federal government, which
sought to alleviate their suffering. Working
under Roy Stryker, primarily under the Farm
Security Administration (FSA), a small group
of talented photographers, including Walker
Evans, Dorothea Lange, Marion Post Wolcott,
John Vachon, Russell Lee, and Arthur Rothstein,
documented the human, natural, and
economic devastation of the region in photographs
printed in federal publications as well
as in a wide variety of newspapers and magazines.
Stryker explicitly directed his photographers
to document the tragedy and also
show the need for and effectiveness of expensive,
agriculturally oriented government relief
programs.

The most important Dust Bowl photographer,
both in terms of technical ability and
time spent in the region, was Arthur Rothstein.
Rothstein joined the project in 1935, immediately
following his graduation from Columbia
University. He traveled the Plains from
1936 to 1940. Rothstein's early role and technical
abilities gave him considerable influence
on the artistic direction of the federal program.
He was deeply influenced by the 1936
documentary The Plow That Broke the Plains
and adopted its visual perspective and persuasive
intent. His works were gritty, taking
advantage of the ability of black-and-white
film to capture the contrast between light and
dark. His realistic style, seemingly documentary,
was chosen to enhance the believability
of his work.

Under Stryker and Rothstein, government
photographers stressed images of poverty and
destruction from 1935 to 1937. Russell Lee
worked in Texas and Oklahoma, although he
concentrated on the Northern Great Plains.
His 1939 series, Part of Mays Avenue Camp, Oklahoma City, Oklahoma, reveals that even
late in the Depression poverty continued to
plague the region.

The work of government photographers
was sometimes controversial, which is hardly
surprising, given the persuasive intent of the
assignment. Arthur Rothstein's work proved
to be the most controversial. Rothstein was
involved in a political controversy during the
1936 presidential election when the conservative
Fargo Forum criticized him (and, by extension,
the Roosevelt administration) for his
repeated use of a cow skull to dramatize the
bleakness of the Plains. The story spread.
Many newspapers later retracted the story, following
Stryker's justification of the skull's artistic
use, but the reputation of the government
photographers suffered. Rothstein's
most famous image, Farmer and Sons Walking
in the Face of a Dust Storm, Cimarron County, Oklahoma (1936), showing a farmer and his
two young sons leaning into the wind as dust
swallows their outbuildings, has also proven
controversial. Other images taken on the same
day but with clear skies and an apparent absence
of dust belie Rothstein's claim that he
took the photograph without staging.

While most of the Dust Bowl photographers
worked for the federal government, others
worked for private publications. Dorothea
Lange worked sporadically for the federal government,
but only a small portion of her work
covers the region. Among these, produced independently
of federal efforts, was An American Exodus (1939), which includes bleak scenes
of life in the Southern Plains that explain why
people would travel great distances to California
to live in camps and work in such miserable
conditions. Margaret Bourke-White, also
considered to be a major Dust Bowl photographer,
worked for Fortune, which commissioned
her to photograph the Deep South. Her
most famous photographs, included in You Have Seen Their Faces (1937), were taken in the
American South but have often been perceived
as being set in the Dust Bowl.

Just as the Dust Bowl passed, so too did the
need to justify government programs or document
rural suffering in the region. After 1937
emphasis shifted to the more positive effects
of government relief efforts, with fewer scenes
of economic and environmental distress.

See also AGRICULTURE: Farm Security Administration / FILM: The Plow That Broke the Plains / PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT: Dust Bowl.


Charles Vollan
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Curtis, James. Mind's Eye, Mind's Truth: FSA Photography
Reconsidered. Philadelphia: Temple University Press, 1989.
Fleischhauer, Carl, and Beverly W. Brannon, eds. Documenting America, 1935–1943. Berkeley: University of California
Press, 1988.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>