<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ag.001</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Agriculture</field>
      <field name="author">Hudson, John C.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




AGRICULTURE

The Great Plains is an agricultural factory
of immense proportions. Between the yellow
canola fields of Canada's Parkland Belt and the
sheep and goat country of Texas's Edwards
Plateau, more than 2,000 miles to the south,
lie a succession of agricultural regions that
collectively produce dozens of food and fiber
products. The most important Great Plains
crop is wheat. Although the United States
and Canada together produce slightly less
wheat than China (the world's leading wheat
grower), the two North American countries
account for more than half of the world's
wheat exports. Barley, canola, corn, cotton,
sorghum, and soybeans grown in the Great
Plains also reach markets around the world.

Agriculture has long been the life force of
the Great Plains economy. Although manufacturing
employs more people than agriculture
in some parts of the Great Plains today,
many urban industries rely on the region's
farms and ranches for the raw materials they
process. One has to look back several thousand
years, to a time when plains inhabitants
were mainly nomadic hunters, to find an era
when agriculture did not figure prominently
in the region's pattern of human occupation.
Some Native North American groups depended
on agriculture as much as the European
Americans who displaced them.



Native American Agriculture

Cultivation of domesticated plants was a relatively
late innovation in the Great Plains compared
to the southeastern and southwestern
regions of North America. By A.D. 850, semisedentary
horticultural villages dotted the
banks of the Missouri River and its tributaries
as far north as the Knife River in present-day
North Dakota on the Northern Plains. These
settlements were a result of migration and diffusion
from the Mississippian cultural complex
to the east. However, agriculture in the
Great Plains has always been a risky business
threatened by drought, grasshoppers, and early
frosts. For that reason early farmers did not
depend entirely on the produce of their gardens;
rather, they hunted bison and other
game and supplemented their diets with meat
and diverse wild plants.

Villages were located on the bluffs and terraces
overlooking the gardens, which were
carved into the fertile floodplains below.
Maize was the most important food crop produced,
but gardens also included a wide variety
of beans and squash. Some of the earliest
domesticates on the Plains were amaranth,
chenopods, and sunflowers. Tobacco, central
to ritual life in many tribes, was a highly valued
crop and trade item as well. The annual
cycle of village life revolved around the planting,
hoeing, harvesting, and processing of
their crops. The architecture, implements,
and other technologies associated with this
early agricultural lifestyle in the Great Plains
were remarkably uniform: semisubterranean
earth lodge villages, bison scapula hoes, and
ceramic pots used to cook corn and beans.

One of the secrets of the longevity of this
lifestyle among Native groups was the sophisticated
risk-management strategies employed
by the farmers, who were mostly women. Archaeological
and ethnographic records reveal
careful development of a wide variety of
maize, beans, and squash, specifically selected
to produce under different conditions. The
Mandans, for example, planted at least thirteen
varieties of corn at the time of contact
with European Americans. In addition, their
gardens were widely dispersed geographically
and were intercropped. For example, beans
were planted among the corn because beans
returned essential nitrogen to soils depleted by
corn production.

The first harvest of the season was the green
corn harvest, which typically began in mid-August. The green corn was roasted or boiled,
shelled using clam shells, and spread out to
dry in the sun. Corn was used sparingly when
other foods were available. The dried corn
was usually boiled with beans, squash, or
dried meat. Occasionally, it was processed
with mortar and pestle to make cornmeal.
Particularly good ears were chosen carefully
and saved as seed corn for the following year's
gardens.

The major harvest of the season was the
ripe corn harvest in late September and October.
The corn was husked, and fifty or more
brightly colored ears were braided together
and hung on drying scaffolds in the villages.
After the corn was dried, it was stored either
in parfleches or in the numerous bell-shaped
cache pits located under the floors of the earth
lodges. The cache pits could hold twenty to
thirty bushels of corn, beans, sunflower seeds,
dried pumpkins, or squash. Yields varied from
year to year and from region to region, but
most fields produced an average of twenty
bushels per acre. A good harvest encouraged
mutually beneficial trading with the bisonhunting
nomads of the Plains.



Early Commercial Agriculture

Some crops perform better in one environment
than in another. This obvious fact was
learned early in the European American settlement
of the Great Plains, and it has been
relearned in various ways since. Not only is
the Plains region too dry on average for the
production of a number of crops, but it also
receives a highly variable amount of moisture
from year to year. Thus, even crops that do not
demand significant amounts of moisture may
wither in certain years when moisture is insufficient.
Corn became the staple crop of European
Americans who learned how to cultivate
it from the Native peoples along the Atlantic
seaboard. As migrants moved westward into
the Great Plains after 1854, they brought with
them familiar "American" practices such as
raising livestock, which also required that they
produce a corn crop for feed.

Corn and wheat became the most important
crops of the Plains, just as they had been
in the more humid eastern states. The importance
of hogs in the Middle West was paralleled
by beef cattle in the Great Plains, and
cattle typically were fattened for market on
corn just like hogs. Wheat was not grown for
consumption by farm animals, but rather as a
cash crop that would bring the farmer a sure
return at the market. Farming practices introduced
to the Great Plains by settlers coming
from the East thus involved no radical changes
in established patterns.

When new lands that had never been cultivated
were put into crops by homesteading
farmers, it was necessary to "break" the land
with a large plow that was capable of turning
over the thick prairie sod. Breaking the
land was demanding work that required many
teams of draft animals. Broken land often was
planted with sod corn, which tolerated weeds.
After a few years of cultivation, however, the
land surface was easily worked with smaller
farm implements, and a variety of food crops
including wheat, flax, and corn could be
planted.

Several traditions of wheat culture were
brought to the Great Plains. Early settlers from
Minnesota, Ontario, Wisconsin, and places
farther east brought spring wheat to the
Northern Great Plains and the Canadian Prairies,
where it was (and still is) the most common
variety grown. It is planted in the spring
as soon as fields are dry enough to work and
harvested in the fall before the weather turns
cold. In Canada, Marquis wheat, a hard northern
spring variety, became the preferred crop.

In the Central Great Plains the original
bread-grain crop was soft winter wheat, which
was brought to Kansas by migrants from
Pennsylvania, Ohio, and Missouri. Winter
wheat is sown in the fall, allowed to overwinter
in the ground, and then resumes its growth the
following spring. It is typically harvested in the
early or midsummer months.

A third type of wheat, Turkey Red wheat,
was brought to central Kansas in the early
1870s by German Mennonites who had recently
immigrated from southern Russia. This
was a hard winter wheat that produced a superior
bread grain, like the hard spring wheats
of the north. Turkey Red wheat eventually became
the favored variety in the Central and
Southern Great Plains.

The first cattle to graze the pastures of
the Great Plains were the mixed breeds that
were brought to the Americas by the Spanish.
These mixed-blood (or criollo) cattle were
a unique breed from the West Indies that
had evolved as the result of crossbreeding. Of
the criollo cattle, the best-known were the
semiwild Texas longhorns. Beginning in the
1860s longhorns were rounded up in Texas for
trail drives north to railheads in cities such
as Abilene and Dodge City, Kansas, and then
shipped east.

Although the longhorn's story forms a colorful
chapter in the history of the Great
Plains, they were not economically important
after the 1880s. Cattle and sheep breeds introduced
from England and Scotland were the
foundation stock of most herds from the middle
of the nineteenth century onward. Sheep
grazing was especially well suited to the shortgrass
prairies of Wyoming, Montana, and Alberta.
Cattle breeds, such as the Aberdeen Angus and Hereford ("whiteface"), were brought
to the Great Plains by cattlemen who in the
early years of settlement sought to establish
large herds on millions of grazing acres. The
ranching style they introduced was implemented
over much of the western shortgrass
Plains, especially in the Dakotas, Wyoming,
and Alberta.

Many of the early sheep ranchers and cattle
barons were from Scotland and Ireland where
pastures were far better suited to grazing animals
than to raising crops. Thus the Scots and
Irish continued a long-established tradition
by focusing on livestock rather than crop production
on the Plains. It was settlers from England,
Germany, and the agricultural lands
of central and eastern Europe who brought a
knowledge of crop farming with them, and it
was they who introduced most of the varieties
of wheat to the Great Plains. They continued
the tradition of agriculture they had practiced
in Europe.



Droughts

Livestock grazing is less affected by drought
than is crop farming, but it was farming that
inspired the large number of settlers to come
to the Great Plains during the second half of
the nineteenth century. The region's agricultural
history has frequently involved attempts
to cope with droughts. Unpredictable dry
years can lead to a series of crop failures and,
eventually, the failure of settlement itself.

Early farmers on the Plains had poor
weather records to guide them in choosing the
best crops to plant. They selected the crops
with which they had success elsewhere, but
their previous farming experience was not always
a reliable guide. For example, in the 1870s
and 1880s farmers in Kansas debated whether
to plant winter wheat or corn as their primary
crop. Wheat was harvested early in the season,
before summer droughts did their worst damage.
Corn was subject to summer drought but
was less affected by spring freezes because
it was planted later, after the ground was
warm. As a result, the best wheat crops frequently
came during years when corn suffered.
Droughts in the 1890s heralded a period
of decline in the number of acres devoted to
corn production in the Great Plains; the trend
was not reversed until irrigation became more
common in the 1960s.

The most drought-resistant crops often
have been the ones that have triumphed in the
Great Plains. Sorghum (or milo) was introduced
on the Plains because it produces grain
under the same drought conditions that cause
corn to wither. Sorghum became a major
source of cattle feed in the Southern Great
Plains after seed companies introduced it in
an improved, hybrid form in Texas and Oklahoma
in the 1950s. Most varieties of wheat
and barley are fairly drought tolerant; consequently
these crops are grown in the drier,
western plains. Corn, soybeans, cotton, and
sugar beets demand a great deal of moisture.
These crops are always irrigated when grown
in the drier, western parts of the region but are
grown frequently on the eastern Plains, where
irrigation is not a necessity.

The causes of prolonged drought are not
well understood. Wet and dry years often
come in series that span several seasons. Persistent
droughts occurred during the 1890s
and 1930s and in response both of those decades
witnessed an abrupt outward-migration
of people from the Plains. The most serious
problems developed in southwestern Kansas,
eastern Colorado, and the Oklahoma and
Texas Panhandles, an area that became known
as the Dust Bowl in the 1930s because the combination
of drought, overcultivation, and excessive
grazing had removed so much of the
plant cover that soil surfaces became completely
open to wind erosion.

Attempts to make rain by cloud seeding
were once seen as a means to combat drought,
but today the more common approach is
to use irrigation where possible. If water
resources are lacking, however, drought still
represents a major hazard to Great Plains
agriculture.



The importance of Great Plains agriculture



Agricultural Technology

Although the agriculture undertaken by European
American settlers involved little more
than the simple transfer of familiar practices
and cultures from one environment to another,
the special needs of farming in the
Plains soon became evident. New strategies
evolved to cope with the environment from
the 1860s onward.

Some innovations included new types of
farm implements. The self-scouring steel plow
was an invention demanded by the prairie because
the thick, black sod was too difficult to
turn with the smaller, cast-iron plows farmers
were accustomed to using. Steel plows were
invented in the Middle West just prior to the
European American settlement of the Great
Plains. The invention of barbed wire in the
1870s also took place outside the Great Plains,
but it similarly had an impact on the Plains
region because it made it possible to fence
millions of acres quickly and cheaply in areas
where timber or hedges for fencing were unavailable.

Other innovations involved new systems for
managing water resources. Windmills made it
possible to pump water at remote locations,
and thereby to control the grazing patterns
of large herds of cattle. The introduction of
steam threshing engines in the 1890s required
that a supply of fuel be available, but in the
Great Plains the firewood commonly found in
other regions was lacking. Coal was also often
unavailable. The solution was to build strawburning
steam engines that consumed the
wheat straw, the principal by-product of
threshing.

Still more specific innovations in crop
farming were made in the late nineteenth and
early twentieth centuries. Known under the
general heading of dry farming, these methods
involved a scientific approach to conserving
soil moisture in areas where, by then,
it was known that precipitation was often inadequate.
Included under the practices of
dry farming is the custom of "alternate fallow"–
leaving strips of land unused between
cultivated strips, or alternating fields and fallow
from year to year so that two years of
moisture are available for a single year's crop
demand. Cultivating to control moisturerobbing
weeds also proved beneficial. Deep
plowing, subsurface compaction, and a variety
of other methods were similarly introduced
to combat the negative effects of inadequate
moisture.

Dry farming is, in some respects, a passive
technology in terms of environmental adaptation.
Irrigation, however, is a much more direct
approach to overcoming environmental
limits. Irrigation was not widespread in the
Great Plains before the middle of the twentieth
century. What little irrigation there
was had to be located on gently sloping river
floodplains where water, diverted from a river
channel upstream, could flow across fields
and eventually drain back into the main channel
farther downstream. In the United States,
the federal government's policies related to
land and reclamation encouraged the construction
of dams and diversion projects on
smaller streams; in Canada, the Canadian Pacific
Railway promoted large river diversions
for irrigation in the early twentieth century.
But prior to the 1960s irrigation was limited
by the availability of streamside locations–
the only place irrigation was feasible so long
as dams, canals, and lateral channels were the
only means for distributing water.

New technology provided an economical
means for expanding irrigation after 1960.
Deep wells were drilled and powerful electric
pumps brought groundwater up to the surface.
The wells fed surface sprinkler systems
that moved across fields automatically. With
sprinkler irrigation, it became possible to raise
almost any feed grain. Once irrigation was in
place, corn, the most valuable grain on which
to fatten livestock, began to replace the more
drought-resistant grain sorghums, although
sorghum itself quickly became an irrigated
crop as well.

As a result of these developments it became
possible for Great Plains farmers to fatten
larger numbers of cattle with locally produced
feed grains. The typical pattern of shipping
young cattle from the Plains to midwestern
feedlots went into decline as more and more
cattle were born, raised, fed, and slaughtered
within the Great Plains itself. The result was a
westward pull on the beef packing industry.
About half of the major beef packing companies
in the United States relocated to the
Great Plains during the 1970s and 1980s.

In the 1930s farmers began to implement a
variety of techniques to control soil erosion.
Contour plowing was an early technique that
prevented gullying on steeper slopes. Even
seemingly small innovations helped, such
as the now-common practice of leaving crop
residues on fields after harvest to combat
blowing soil conditions. Windbreaks, whether
planted as rows of trees in shelterbelts or as
strips of perennial grasses along narrow paths
within fields, also curtail wind erosion. In
the Great Plains today farmers no longer plow
their fields annually. Rather, they disturb the
soil as little as possible from year to year
by working it with smaller cultivating implements
and controlling weeds with chemicals.



Contemporary Agricultural Problems

The public's concern with environmental issues
in recent years has led many to question
the nature of some common farm practices in
the Great Plains. Nitrification of groundwater
supplies is one such example. Nitrification results
from the continued application of nitrogen
fertilizers that are used to increase yields
of crops such as corn. With increased amounts
of fertilizers, pesticides, and herbicides in
the environment, some groundwater supplies
have become contaminated, especially in areas
where irrigation is in heavy use, such as the
Platte River Valley of Nebraska.

Animal manure was once spread over croplands
to increase soil fertility on the farms
where livestock were penned for feeding.
Large, modern Great Plains feedlots produce
far more animal wastes than local fields can
use, and this has created a serious problem in
waste disposal. Water pollution problems have
multiplied as a result of large feedlots and the
heavy use of chemical fertilizers.

Agricultural scientists have urged a return
to crop rotation practices, whereby a fixed sequence
of crops is grown on the same field
over a series of years. Some crops, such as
alfalfa, are planted to replenish soil fertility;
others such as corn, are planted for feed; and
still others, such as rye, are planted as a means
to "rest" the land between years of more
nutrient-demanding crops. But crop rotation
is uncommon on irrigated fields in the Central
Great Plains, most of which are used to
produce corn every year. It is also uncommon
in dryland wheat farming in the Prairie Provinces
of Canada.

Irrigated land is expensive, so a higher return
per acre is generally expected. The introduction
of less intensive means of production
is often resisted in areas that rely on irrigation.
If too much irrigation water is diverted from
streams, or if groundwater levels are lowered
to the point that subsurface streams cannot
feed ponds, streams, and rivers, then surface
wetlands will dry up and wildlife numbers will
decline.

One of the most difficult problems of Great
Plains agriculture has actually been its very
success. Since the 1930s national policies have
been enacted to regulate overabundant crops
that would depress the market and drive the
price down to a level below farmers' costs of
production. Both the Canadian and the U.S.
governments have experimented with ways to
increase grain exports overseas as one means
of coping with oversupplies at home. Other
government programs, such as the Soil Bank,
enacted in the United States in 1957, have
focused more on the conservation of land resources.
Under the Soil Bank, and the Conservation
Reserve Program that succeeded it,
marginal land, such as that most susceptible to
erosion, has been taken out of production by
paying farmers not to cultivate it.



Agricultural Regions of the Great Plains


Agricultural regions of the Great Plains


Great Plains agriculture varies throughout the
region according to the nature of the physical
environment, the demand for farm products,
and the crop and livestock preferences of local
ranchers and farmers. There are eleven major agricultural regions within the Great Plains. From north to south they are the (I) Parkland Belt, (II) Canadian Prairies, (III) Northern Spring Wheat Region, (IV) Unglaciated Missouri Plateau, (V) Sandhills, (VI) Eastern Feed Grains and Livestock Region, (VII) Winter Wheat Region, (VIII) Irrigated High Plains, (IX) Upland Cotton Region, (X) Irrigated Valleys, and (XI) Rangelands. Within these eleven
regions are numerous subregions that have
special defining characteristics as well.

The Parkland Belt (I) is the northern limit
of prairie vegetation and, except for the outlier
of the Peace River wheat country, is the northern
limit of successful agriculture in North
America. The term "parkland" suggests the
open nature of the landscape, which consists
of expanses of tall grass dotted with groves of
aspen and spruce trees. Soils of the Parkland
Belt are known as Luvisols in the Canadian
system of soil nomenclature. Luvisols are fertile
soils associated with broadleaf forests. Although
the Parkland's growing season is quite
short, the region normally receives more precipitation
than does the Canadian Prairie region
which forms the Parkland's southern
limit. Many portions of the Parkland were settled
ahead of the adjacent Canadian Prairie for
this reason, although the earliest settlements
were made along the line of the Canadian Pacific
Railway. European settlers (of whom the
Ukrainians are the best known) and the Métis
people from Manitoba established agriculture
in the Parkland zone at the end of the
nineteenth and beginning of the twentieth
centuries.

Canola, not wheat, is the crop favored to
advance the agricultural frontier northward in
Canada because it produces well in a short
season of long summer days. The oilseed produces
valuable forage and its seedpod yields
a highly unsaturated cooking oil. Canola, as
well as sunflower oil, is gaining great popularity
around the world, and Canada exports
large quantities of both to the United States,
Europe, and Asia.

The Canadian Prairies agricultural region
(II) consists of the large, triangular-shaped zone of grain production bounded roughly by Calgary, Edmonton, Saskatoon, Winnipeg, and the boundary with the United States (the
forty-ninth parallel). Hard, red spring wheat
is the most important crop here, followed by
barley, canola, oats, and a variety of other
small grains. Canadian Prairie wheat was traditionally
hauled by rail through Winnipeg
(the region's major wheat marketing and trading
center) to the Lake Superior port of
Thunder Bay (formerly, Port Arthur and Fort
William), loaded aboard ship, and sent to
Liverpool or to other European markets. Today
much of the wheat from the Prairie Provinces
moves westward to ocean ports in British
Columbia for shipment to Asia. Despite being
the world's largest wheat producer, China consumes
more than it can grow and greatly depends
on wheat from Canada to make up the
difference.

Chernozemic soils–deep, dark-colored,
and high in nutrients–are an important basis
for the wheat crop of the Prairie Provinces.
About one-half of Canada's total agricultural
land in the Prairie Provinces consists of chernozemic
soils. It is the same type of soil that
is found in the principal wheat-raising areas
of the Ukraine, an area that is climatically
similar to the southern portions of the Prairie
Provinces.

The Canadian Prairie region was less wooded
than the Parkland to the north, and the Canadian
Pacific Railway, linking the coasts after
its completion in 1885, channeled settlement
away from the Prairie and into the Parkland
Belt. The Prairie region had received unfavorable
comment in an early survey conducted by
John Palliser and Henry Hind between 1857
and 1860. Much of the prairie was described
by Palliser as "sterile with scanty pasturage."
The innermost portion of the Prairie region,
which thereby became known as Palliser's Triangle,
received little European settlement until
the first two decades of the twentieth century.
The European immigrants immediately began
producing wheat, and by 1930, Palliser's Triangle
was a significant wheat-growing region.
Today Canada's Prairie Provinces export
quantities of wheat not only to Europe and
Asia, but also to the United States. The North
American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) has
made it possible for the lowest cost producers
to capture markets on either side of the fortyninth
parallel.

The Northern Spring Wheat region (III) of
the United States is physically similar to the
Canadian Prairies. Spring wheat is the major
crop of North Dakota and much of Montana.
Barley, durum, flax, sunflowers, oats, and
other small grains are also produced.

U.S. breweries depend on the barley grown
in Montana and North Dakota just as U.S.
pasta manufacturers rely on the durum grown
in North Dakota's Durum Triangle in the central
and northeastern part of the state. The
Red River Valley of the North, along the
Minnesota–North Dakota border, also produces
wheat, but it is best known for its crops
of sugar beets and potatoes that grow on the
almost perfectly flat surface that once formed
the bed of glacial Lake Agassiz. Fargo, Grand
Forks, Minot, and Great Falls are the major
cities of the region; however Minneapolis has
long functioned as the control point of the
Northern Spring Wheat farming system. In
the nineteenth century super-sized farm units
known as "bonanza farms" were established
in the Red River Valley of the North, where
wheat monoculture was practiced on a large
scale.

The glaciated portion of the Missouri Plateau,
with its fertile soils and smooth topography,
is part of the Northern Spring Wheat region.
The broad platform of sedimentary rock
formation stretches hundreds of miles east
of the Rocky Mountains across the steppes
(grasslands) of Montana, Wyoming, and the
Dakotas. It is an eastward-sloping surface
of low relief that is covered, especially in
its northern sections, with a mantle of glacial
materials from which the deep, black, grainproducing
soils were formed. In the U.S. system
of soil nomenclature these soils are known
as Borolls (a type of Mollisol), the equivalent
of the chernozemic soils of Canada and the
Ukraine. Borolls provide an adequate supply
of nutrients for a variety of small grains
throughout the growing season.

Montana's Wheat Triangle, an area of particularly
productive grain crops bounded by
the cities of Shelby, Havre, and Great Falls, lies
at the edge of the glaciated Missouri Plateau
and the Northern Spring Wheat region. It was
one of the last portions of the Great Plains to
be settled, chiefly between 1910 and 1920. Like
the grain exports of the Canadian Prairies to
the north, most of Montana's wheat and barley
exports are directed toward Asia.

The Unglaciated Missouri Plateau (IV), in
contrast, is primarily a region of livestock
grazing. It has only limited areas suitable for
crop farming, and within these areas dry
farming is standard. The unglaciated plateau's
soils are of several types, but nearly all of them
are inferior to those that have developed on
the glaciated Missouri Plateau. The unglaciated
area's slopes are also steeper and more
easily eroded. North and South Dakota's badlands
are part of the Unglaciated Missouri
Plateau. Here, along the White River in South
Dakota and the Little Missouri River in North
Dakota, steep, easily eroded slopes preclude
agriculture, except in the broader valleys and
on the grass-covered tablelands where grazing
is possible.

The present course of the Missouri River
roughly marks the eastern limit of glaciated
topography. In South Dakota the portion of
the state west of the glacial border is known as
West River country and in North Dakota it
is referred to as the Missouri Slope. In both
states there is a markedly lower population
density on the unglaciated portions of the
Missouri Plateau, corresponding to a ranching
rather than farming economy. Much of
the Unglaciated Missouri Plateau was part
of the Great Sioux Reservation until it was
broken into six separate reservations in 1888.
The relinquished Native American lands were
opened to European American settlement.
Early homesteaders tried to raise crops on the
inferior West River and Missouri Slope soils,
but most of the area proved to be submarginal
for grain production.

A similar history of agricultural failure
is found in the Jordan Country (Garfield
County) of Montana, a largely unpopulated
stretch of rough rangeland that lies on the divide
between the Missouri and Yellowstone
Rivers north of Miles City. Attempts to raise
wheat in the Jordan Country, as in the West
River of South Dakota, were unsuccessful, and
the lands reverted to cattle and sheep range by
the 1950s. This was one of America's last agricultural
frontiers, one that had only a brief
"season of hope" before hard environmental
realities were understood.

Some parts of the Unglaciated Missouri
Plateau have better soils and are suitable for
dry-farmed grain crops. One of these districts
is the Judith Basin, a highland wheat- and
barley-growing region between Billings and
Great Falls that was settled during the decade
centered on World War I.

The Sandhills (V) is a 20-million-acre region
of grass-covered sand dunes in northcentral
Nebraska that is devoted almost entirely
to livestock grazing. Agricultural settlers
came to the Sandhills during the so-called
Kinkaid Era after 1904 when enlarged homesteads
(640 acres) were granted in the sandy
hill country. But wherever the land was broken
for planting, wind erosion soon deflated
the ground surface and new sand dunes began
to accumulate along fence lines. Cattle ranching,
which had traditionally been the major
land use, was quickly reestablished.

Today, the Sandhills region has some of the
largest cattle ranches in the United States.
Typical ranches are tens of thousands of acres
in size. The only crop of significance is hay,
baled from meadows–where it grows wild–
that surround the region's many east-flowing
streams or surface lakes, formed where the
water table intersects the surface. Sandhills
cattle ranching has the look of the open range,
even though most of the land is fenced and
privately owned. A mark of the sparse population
in this area is that signposts are to ranches
more often than to towns.

The Eastern Feed Grains and Livestock region
(VI) covers much of the eastern margins
of the Central Great Plains. It consists of several
important subregions, but throughout it
has a mixed farming system that emphasizes
both crop and livestock production.

From eastern South Dakota, across eastern
Nebraska, and south across Kansas to Oklahoma
and Texas, a version of Corn Belt agriculture
dominates the landscape. Beef cattle
feeding, hog raising, and corn, soybean, and
sorghum production are the backbone of the
farm economy. While irrigation is found in a
few areas within this region, the climate is
not dry enough to require irrigation in most
years. For that reason, paradoxically, agriculture
here remains vulnerable to drought, but
its mixed nature means that farmers have the
means to ride out some bad years because
their operations are comparatively diversified.

In Kansas this region is bordered on the
west by the Flint Hills where crop agriculture
is largely confined to valley bottoms while
livestock grazing occupies the uplands. Upland
soils are relatively thin and unsuited for
cultivation. For many years young cattle from
the dry, western ranges of the Great Plains
have been shipped to the Flint Hills for pasturing
on grass before being grain-fed for market.
Flint Hills pastures are burned regularly
to increase the nutritive value of grasses for
livestock.

In Kansas this region is bordered on the
west by the Flint Hills where crop agriculture
is largely confined to valley bottoms while
livestock grazing occupies the uplands. Upland
soils are relatively thin and unsuited for
cultivation. For many years young cattle from
the dry, western ranges of the Great Plains
have been shipped to the Flint Hills for pasturing
on grass before being grain-fed for market.
Flint Hills pastures are burned regularly
to increase the nutritive value of grasses for
livestock.

German Mennonites from southern Russia
introduced (probably unknowingly rather
than deliberately) most of the strains of hard
winter wheat to this area in the late 1870s.
Kansas, which had previously been known
as a corn state, soon became a major wheat
producer. Winter wheat production is concentrated
between Wichita and Dodge City,
Kansas, near Enid, Oklahoma, and north of
Amarillo, Texas, but large wheat fields are
ubiquitous from central Kansas to eastern
Colorado.

As a crop, wheat is not as profitable as feed
grains like corn or sorghum. For this reason,
and because it requires less water to produce,
it is rarely economical to irrigate wheat. So
where irrigation water is unavailable in the
Central Great Plains, wheat farming remains
the best option. In most respects soils of the
spring and winter wheat region are quite similar
and are associated with grassland vegetation.
Ustolls, a warm and dry variation of the
fertile Mollisol, are the typical soils of the winter
wheat region.

Because large acreages mean a sparse rural
population, many wheat farmers in the High
Plains prefer to live in town rather than on
their farms. "Suitcase farmers" or "sidewalk
farmers," as such absentee operators are
known, live on their farms only a few weeks
each season when work needs to be done. Suitcase
farming is especially characteristic of the
drier, high-drought-risk winter wheat areas of
eastern Colorado and western Kansas.

Also a producer of feed grains and livestock,
the Irrigated High Plains (VIII) is the
newest agricultural region of the Great Plains.
It is here that irrigated grain crops are raised
to supply local beef feedlots. Sprinkler irrigation
fed by deep-well pumps offers the means
to produce feed grains in a climate that, by
itself, could not sustain crops like corn more
than one year in five on average. Central
to southwestern Nebraska, western Kansas,
eastern Colorado, and the panhandles of
Oklahoma and Texas–all areas that had been
marginal even for wheat in some years–
experienced an intensification of agriculture
with the introduction of sprinkler irrigation
in the 1960s. Much of the nation's beef industry
is now concentrated in this region.

The Upland Cotton Region of the Southern
Plains (IX) consists of several separate areas of
cotton culture in Texas and Oklahoma. Shortstaple
upland cotton, the variety used for
making coarser cotton goods such as denim, is
grown both under irrigation and with dry-farming
techniques. Migrants from the southeastern
cotton districts of the United States
brought cotton farming to Texas and Oklahoma
early in the twentieth century.

The Texas High Plains has a long enough
growing season for cotton, but its precipitation
is insufficient to produce a crop in many
years. Especially after the Dust Bowl years,
and as pump irrigation was introduced, both
cotton and grain sorghum became irrigated
crops in this region. Plowed ground is especially
prone to soil erosion here, and soil conservation
measures, such as surface corrugation
to reduce wind speed at the ground, are a
common sight. Despite these problems, the
Texas Panhandle remains the single largest
concentration of cotton acreage in the United
States. Farmers began diversifying in the 1970s
with the development of viticulture.

Irrigated Valleys (X) comprise a discontinuous
but distinctive agricultural region within
the Great Plains. Unlike the Irrigated High
Plains, where pump irrigation feeds sprinklers
supplying water to feedgrain crops, the traditional
irrigated valleys of the Great Plains still
rely on ditch irrigation and produce a variety
of food and feed crops. Sugar beets are grown
in these older, valley-based irrigation districts.
While technically a food crop (from which
ordinary table sugar is refined), sugar beet
tops and waste also provide livestock feed.
Sugar beets are produced in nearly all of the
irrigation districts of the Great Plains and are
grown unirrigated in the Red River Valley of
North Dakota and Minnesota.

Crosscutting the Unglaciated Missouri Plateau
in Montana is the Yellowstone River Valley,
which, in its downstream portions, is a
corridor of irrigated agriculture dominated
by sugar beets and alfalfa. The Yellowstone
River has remained undammed, but smaller
dams constructed across numerous Yellowstone
tributaries channel water to streamside
fields. Irrigation provides its greatest benefit
to hot regions where water evaporates quickly,
however, and thus the Yellowstone irrigation
district has few counterparts located this far
north in latitude.

The most productive of the Great Plains irrigated
corridors is the Platte River Valley of
Nebraska, Wyoming, and Colorado. Downstream
from the city of North Platte, where
the South Platte and North Platte Rivers join,
ditch irrigation is practiced within a region
where pump irrigation is also available. Nebraska's
irrigated Platte River Valley is one
of the most productive feedgrain regions
of North America. Corn and sorghum crops
grown here are sold to local feedlots or are
exported from ports on the Pacific Coast.

The North Platte River Valley extends irrigated
agriculture into eastern Wyoming. The
most intensive irrigation district of the North
Platte River Valley is the Scottsbluff Lowland
near Scottsbluff and Gering, Nebraska,
where sugar beets and feedgrains are the principal
crops. Irrigation in the South Platte
River Valley is now functionally part of a
much larger scheme. Completed in the 1950s
the Colorado–Big Thompson project captures
water from the upper tributaries of the
Colorado River, sends it through a tunnel in
the Front Range of the Rocky Mountains, and
distributes it to farms in the Colorado Piedmont.
The South Platte River thus became the
principal drainage outlet for the irrigated Colorado
Piedmont.

The irrigated Piedmont is Colorado's most
important agricultural region. Irrigated crops
grown near Greeley and Fort Morgan, Colorado,
include onions, pinto beans, sugar beets,
corn, and alfalfa. Feedgrains and sugar beets
grown in the Piedmont are the basis for its
cattle feeding industry. Feedlots near Greeley
are often cited as the world's largest.

Smaller in area, but also productive, is
the Arkansas River Valley irrigation district
that stretches downstream from Colorado
into western Kansas. Grain sorghum, sugar
beets, onions, and cantaloupe are the principal
crops of this region. Water diverted from
the Arkansas River is the principal source of
irrigation, although underground wells supply
additional water as well.

Rangelands (XI) are found throughout the
Great Plains, primarily wherever rough, steep,
stony, or broken land predominates. Areas
with low mountains or rugged terrain include
the Cypress Hills in Alberta and Saskatchewan
and most of the Unglaciated Missouri Plateau.
Other areas, such as the Great Divide Basin of
Wyoming, are poorly drained and experience
high evaporation rates producing saline residues
in soils and making the ground surface
unsuited for raising crops even with irrigation.
Cattle and sheep grazing are the only
forms of agricultural activity associated with
these areas. Much of the land remains in the
public domain.

South of Colorado Springs, the Piedmont
lowland disappears at the eastern margin of
the Front Range and is replaced by rangelands
of comparatively high elevation. Across New
Mexico and into Texas, the western limit of
the Great Plains consists of dry, broken land
suitable only for grazing. Upstream tributaries
of the Canadian, Cimarron, Red, and Pecos
Rivers are, in places, incised hundreds of feet
into the High Plains rock formations.

South of the Pecos River in Texas is a large
limestone plateau, underlain by springs and
caverns, which is unsuitable for crop farming
but excellent for grazing. This is the Edwards
Plateau (sometimes designated as the Edwards
and Stockton Plateau). Soils are thin and the
vegetation cover has a subtropical, savannalike
appearance. The largest concentration of
sheep and goats in the United States is found
here. The Edwards Plateau is also the world's
leading center for the breeding of Angora
goats.

Despite the nearly ubiquitous importance
of grain crops in the Great Plains, variations
in the physical environment and the timing
and nature of human settlement activities
have created an ever-changing mosaic of agricultural
land use that today stretches from Alberta
to Texas. Some crops, such as corn, are
of native origin although they are grown today
on a vastly increased scale of production. Others,
such as sorghum and soybeans, have exotic
origins. Sorghums are native to Africa,
while soybeans originated in China. Great
Plains livestock herds are based on cattle and
sheep breeding efforts that trace back to England,
Scotland, and Ireland. And Great Plains
farm families have ethnic roots that extend to
many parts of Europe.

In this region were brought together, by
various groups of people at various times,
the successful ingredients of food and fiber
production that now provide a basis for the
United States' and Canada's great agricultural
abundance. The two countries' favorable balance
of trade in foodstuffs helps earn foreign
exchange that makes it possible to import
other goods from around the world. As a
world supplier, the Great Plains ships agricultural
products in all directions–south to the
Gulf of Mexico, west to the Pacific Ocean
ports, east via the Great Lakes to the Atlantic,
and even north through Hudson Bay. The region's
strategic importance will likely continue
well into the future. Agriculture, the
Great Plains' most important industry, will
continue to provide the basis for its economic
growth.

See also IMAGES AND ICONS: 
West River Country / INDUSTRY: Feedlots; 
International Trade; Meatpacking / 
PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT: Palliser's Triangle; Sandhills; Soils / WATER: Irrigation.


 

John C. Hudson
Northwestern University



Drache, Hiram. The Day of the Bonanza: A History of
Bonanza Farming in the Red River Valley of the North.
Fargo: North Dakota Institute for Regional Studies, 1964.
Foth, Henry D., and John W. Schafer. Soil Geography and
Land Use. New York: John Wiley, 1980. Green, Donald E.
Land of the Underground Rain: Irrigation on the Texas High
Plains, 1910-1970. Austin: University of Texas Press, 1973.
Hargreaves, Mary W. Dry Farming in the Northern Great
Plains, 1900-1925. Cambridge: Harvard University Press,
1957. Hewes, Leslie. The Suitcase Farming Frontier: A
Study in the Historical Geography of the Central Great
Plains. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1973. Hudson,
John C. Making the Corn Belt: A Geographical History
of Middle-Western Agriculture. Bloomington: Indiana
University Press, 1994. Jordan, Terry G. North American
Cattle Ranching Frontiers: Origins, Diffusion, and Differentiation.
Albuquerque: University of New Mexico Press,
1993. Kraenzel, Carl F. The Great Plains in Transition. Norman:
University of Oklahoma Press, 1957. Mackintosh, W.
A. Prairie Settlement: The Geographical Setting. Toronto:
Macmillan, 1934. Malin, James C. Winter Wheat in the
Golden Belt of Kansas. Lawrence: University Press of Kansas,
1944. Nelson, Paula M. The Prairie Winnows Out Its
Own: The West River Country of South Dakota in the Years
of Depression and Dust. Iowa City: University of Iowa
Press, 1995. Shannon, Fred A. The Farmer's Last Frontier:
Agriculture, 1860-1897. New York: Harper, 1968. Sherow,
James Earl. Watering the Valley: Development along the
High Plains Arkansas River, 1870-1950. Lawrence: University
Press of Kansas, 1999. Webb, Walter P. The Great
Plains. New York: Ginn &amp; Co., 1931. Worster, Donald E.
Dust Bowl: The Southern Plains in the 1930s. New York:
Oxford University Press, 1979.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>