<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.sr.036</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Maris, Roger (1934-1985)</field>
      <field name="author">Krause, Kent</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MARIS, ROGER (1934-1985)

In 1961 Roger Maris hit sixty-one home runs
and broke baseball's most-hallowed single season
record. He was born in Hibbing, Minnesota,
on September 10, 1934, but spent his
formative years in North Dakota. As a teenager
in Fargo, Maris excelled in football at
Shanley High School and also starred with the
town's American Legion baseball team. Although
the University of Oklahoma recruited
Maris to play football, he instead signed a contract
to play baseball for the Cleveland Indians
in 1953. Maris played for several Cleveland
farm teams, including their Class C club in
Fargo, before making his major-league debut
in 1957.

In 1958 Cleveland traded Maris to the Kansas
City Athletics, who then dealt the outfielder
to the New York Yankees in December
1959. In 1961, despite facing intense media
pressure as well as opposition from fans who
did not want him to pass Babe Ruth's single-season
mark of sixty home runs, Maris broke
the record on the last day of the season. While
this achievement made him famous, it proved
to be a mixed blessing for Maris, because
many never forgave him for surpassing the
legendary Ruth. Nevertheless, over the next
thirty-seven years Maris's mark was annually
the subject of intense media speculation and
fan excitement. This culminated in 1998, when
his record was finally surpassed by Mark
McGuire.

Maris's 1961 season overshadowed a very respectable
career in which he hit 275 home
runs, won two most valuable player awards as
well as a Gold Glove Award, and played in
seven World Series. Maris died on December
14, 1985, after a year-long battle with cancer.


Kent M. Krause
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Allen, Maury. Roger Maris: A Man for All Seasons. New
York: Donald I. Fine, Inc., 1986. Maris, Roger, and Jim
Ogle. Roger Maris at Bat. New York: Duell, Sloan and
Pearce, 1962.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>