<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.afam.007</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Baseball, Interracial</field>
      <field name="author">Pendleton, Jason</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BASEBALL, INTERRACIAL

A 1935 team photograph of the integrated Bismarck Churchills semi-professional baseball team.
   
Interracial baseball was prevalent in the Great
Plains at the same time that other social interaction
between African Americans and whites
was virtually nonexistent. While Jim Crow
segregation prevented African Americans
from fully enjoying their constitutional liberties,
black baseball players routinely experienced
equality on the baseball fields of the
Great Plains. It was common for all-black
teams such as the San Angelo Sheepherders or
Kansas City Colts to play against all-white
teams such as the Duncan (Oklahoma) Cementers
or the Arkansas City (Kansas) Dubbs.

Beginning around 1920, and increasingly
thereafter, residents of the Great Plains could
watch baseball contests between local all-black
teams as well as barnstorming (touring) black
teams that challenged local white teams. The
all-black Wichita Monrovians, who played
in the professional Colored Western League
(founded in 1922) along with all-black teams
from Oklahoma City, Omaha, Coffeyville,
Topeka, Independence, and Kansas City (Kansas),
often played white teams throughout the
Plains because additional games provided
players the opportunity to earn extra money.
Barnstorming tours were also common and
included many professional black teams, including
the Cuban All Stars and the Kansas
City Monarchs–the top team in the Negro
National League in the 1920s and 1930s. Despite
the segregation that isolated white and
black Americans in everyday life, the baseball
diamond proved to be a place where diverse
people could compete on an equal basis.

The extent of racial toleration on the baseball
field is evident from the game that took
place in 1925 between the all-black Wichita
Monrovians and the all-white Wichita Ku
Klux Klan Number 6 team. The game was
played without violence, and the Monrovians
prevailed ten to eight. Another sign of racial
toleration on the baseball fields of the Great
Plains was the existence of an entire racially
integrated league in North Dakota in the early
1930s. The league included many players from
the Negro National League, including Hall of
Famer Satchel Paige, who played for the integrated
Bismarcks and was paid $400 a month
and given a car by the team owner.

The expansion of integrated regional baseball
continued in 1934 when the organizers of
the Denver Post's semiprofessional baseball
tournament invited the Kansas City Monarchs
to be the first all-black team in the tournament's
nineteen-year history. The Monarchs
finished second and set the stage for future
black teams to participate in Plains baseball
tournaments. In 1935 the magnitude of racial
toleration in baseball in the Plains was displayed
in Wichita at the first National Semi-
Pro Baseball Tournament. Four different racial
groups competed among the thirty-two
teams in the tournament. The Memphis Red
Sox, San Angelo Sheepherders, Denver Stars,
Texas Centennials, and Monroe Monarchs
were all-black teams. The Nipponese Stars
from California were Japanese and the Stanolind
Indians from Oklahoma were Native
American. The most diverse team was the
tournament champion, the Bismarcks, who
featured five white players and six black players,
including Satchel Paige, who pitched in
the decisive championship game.

Despite the presence of interracial baseball,
the Great Plains was not a haven of racial tolerance
in the Jim Crow era. Racial toleration
in baseball in the Great Plains existed because
African Americans represented only a tiny
fragment of the total population and were
consequently not considered a threat to the
existing social order. Interracial and integrated
baseball flourished there because the
presence of black and white players together
did not challenge the racist segregation that
existed outside the lines of the ballfield.

See also SPORTS AND RECREATION: 
Baseball.


Jason Pendleton
Lawrence, Kansas




Bruce, Janet. The Kansas City Monarchs. Lawrence: University
Press of Kansas, 1985. Pendleton, Jason. "A Jim
Crow Strikes Out: Interracial Baseball in Wichita, Kansas
1920–1935." Kansas History 20 (1997): 86–101. Rogosin,
Donn. Invisible Men: Life in Baseball's Negro Leagues. New
York: Atheneum, 1983.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>