<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ct.006</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Billings, Montana</field>
      <field name="author">McCormack, J. Michael</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BISMARCK, NORTH DAKOTA

The capital of North Dakota and seat of Burleigh
County, Bismarck is located in the southcentral
part of the state on the eastern bank of
the Missouri River. Its sister city, Mandan, is
situated on the opposite western shore in Morton
County. Though originally a rich agricultural
center and regional river and railroad
transportation hub, during the last quarter of
the twentieth century Bismarck evolved into
a diversified regional medical, governmental,
industrial, and technological center.

Bismarck was founded in 1873, the child of
both Missouri River steamboat transportation
and late-nineteenth-century Great Plains railroad
expansion. Originally called The Crossing,
the town was a strategically located port
for steamboats, which carried upriver immigrants,
and military supplies. In 1872 Camp
Greeley (later Camp Hancock) was built by
the military as a warehouse and supply depot
for troops that were protecting the Northern
Pacific Railroad survey crews. Indeed, the
town was at one time named Edwinton after
the railroad's first chief engineer, Edwin Johnson.
However, the financially distressed railroad's
need to attract German bond investors
induced the railroad's board of directors in
1873 to rename the city Bismarck in honor
of Germany's "Iron Chancellor," Otto von
Bismarck-Schönhausen.

Bismarck was named the capital of Dakota
Territory in 1883, and when Congress passed
the 1889 Omnibus Bill, dividing the territory
into North and South Dakota, the city became
the capital of the new state. The city was officially
incorporated in 1875, adopted the commission
governing structure in 1913, and began
operating under a home rule charter in 1986.

Bismarck grew from a Dakota river town of
1,200 in 1874 to a metropolitan center with a
population of 55,532 in 2000. Much of the recent
growth has centered around the city's development
into a regional health center, with
two major hospitals, allied and independent
clinics, health-care services, and nursing and
elder-care facilities. The next largest employers
are federal, state, county, and city governments.
Bismarck also functions as a wholesale
and retail center, serving a trade area of a 100-
mile radius with more than 170,000 customers.
The city's growing technology and energy
industries are other major employers.

Bismarck has also become a regional education
center, with a comprehensive two-year
college, Bismarck State College, the Benedictine-
founded University of Mary, and an intertribal
United Tribes Technical College. In
addition to these institutions, there are two
colleges of nursing, a school of respiratory
care and radiological technology, a university
graduate center, and the Bismarck campus
of the University of North Dakota School of
Medicine.

Long the center of state politics, Bismarck
is home to the state's Heritage Center, the
law library, the penitentiary, and the Bank
of North Dakota. The bank, chartered in 1919
to promote the state's agriculture, commerce,
and industry, is the nation's only state-owned
bank. Bismarck's most recent national accomplishment
was being named an all-American
city in 1997.

Bismarck offers a wealth of cultural organizations
and activities for its citizens, including
an arts and galleries association, art
schools, summer musical productions, amateur
theater, a symphony orchestra, dance studios,
men's and women's choruses, and a national
tribal powwow. The city owns and
manages 2,525 acres of park facilities, including
forty-eight parks, thirty miles of recreational
trails, and one of the nation's fifty Millennium
Legacy Trails.

Bismarck's historical connections with the
Custer legacy center on its proximity to his
command post at Fort Abraham Lincoln and
its status as the port for the famous steamboat,
the Far West, whose epic journey to transport
the wounded from the Little Bighorn battlefield
in 1876, a distance of 900 miles in fiftyfour
hours, stands unrivaled in Missouri River
steamboating history.

See also MEDIA: 
Bismarck Tribune.


J. Michael McCormack
Bismarck State College




Bird, George F., and Edwin J. Taylor Jr. History of the City of Bismarck: The First 100 Years, 1872–1972. Bismarck ND: Bismarck Centennial Association, 1972. Bismarck-Mandan
North Dakota Community Profile. Bismarck: Bismarck-
Mandan Area Chamber of Commerce, 2000. Robinson,
Elwyn B. History of North Dakota. Lincoln: University of
Nebraska Press, 1966.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>