<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fol.015</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Folk Music</field>
      <field name="author">Lowe, Donna</field>
      <field name="text">

 




FOLK MUSIC

Folk music can be defined as music that is
perpetuated orally rather than by the use of
traditional notation, and whose subject matter
reflects the social community within which it
exists. The concept of marginalization also enters
into the definition of this art form, indicating
that some form of isolation from the
mainstream–by class, sex, age, race, language,
space, time, or religion–has historically influenced
the creation of much so-called folk
music. Within a climate of relative seclusion,
people necessarily create a common musical
currency. By this definition, the Great Plains
has afforded much opportunity for distinct
regional types of music, owing to its vast size
and geographical diversity, and indeed the folk
music tradition of this region is as varied as the
people who populate its prairie landscape. A
discussion of the art form is probably best attempted
within the context of some of the various
influential ethnic groups that originally
settled the region: the British settlers throughout
the Plains, the Scottish and French influence
on the Métis culture in Central Canada,
the Hispanic explorers in Texas to the south,
and the Ukrainian and Russian tradition in the
Prairie Provinces and Northern Plains states.

The British, the most prevalent ethnic group
in the Great Plains as a whole, brought with
them to North America a long legacy of narrative
song. In 1882 the historian and musicologist
Francis James Child published a collection
called English and Scottish Popular Ballads that
was revered throughout pioneer America as
the primary source of traditional music. Eventually
known simply as "Child's ballads," these
songs were typically narrative in nature and
concerned largely with love affairs and their
oft-tragic ends. Other forms of vocal music,
including part-songs known as broadside ballads,
supplemented this collection. Circulated
on large sheets of paper called broadsides,
these songs chronicled historical events and
described folk heroes such as Jesse James.
Dance traditions from the British Isles were
also revived, translating into "play-party"
songs and square dances, normally accompanied
by the guitar, banjo, mandolin, violin,
and mouth organ–the main instruments of
the American folk experience.

Scottish and Irish fur traders contributed to
the Aboriginal musical community in early
Canada, deepening its preexisting tradition of
balladic storytelling and combining with the
vocal and instrumental music of the French
voyageurs to create a unique hybrid of music
and song that chronicled the history of the
Red River Valley of the North region. These
traders introduced European fiddles and fiddle
music to the Plains in the early 1800s and,
when combined with the more organic song
tradition of the Native peoples, produced a
unique hybrid musical style incorporating elements
of both cultures. The fiddle music of
the Métis (who emerged from intermarriage
between French, Irish, and Scottish traders
and Native women) utilized Celtic or French
melodies reinterpreted through a distinctive
Native musical perspective–characterized by
irregular phrase lengths and/or overlapping
phrases, reiterated or embellished cadences,
variable formal structures, and rhythmic freedom–
resulting in the development of a new
musical form, specific to the region.

The Hispanic folk music tradition in the
Great Plains originated more than 400 years
ago when Spanish conquistadors, moving
northward from Mexico, explored the southwestern
part of the region. The prevalent song
forms in the Mexican region, the corrido and
the decima, became popular in southern Texas
during the nineteenth century. The corrido
typically related a story or event of local or
national interest–a natural disaster, the exploits
of a hero or villain–and usually adhered
to a conventional form, consisting of six
sections. The formal opening of the corrido,
in which the balladeer called upon the audience
to hear his tale, was followed by a section
that introduced the song's protagonist
and established its setting. The arguments of
the hero were then stated, followed by the
main plot of the tale. The corrido concluded
with the farewells of both the song's protagonist
and the balladeer himself. A history of
liturgical drama also exists in the Southwest
and Southern Plains, dating back to the mystery
and miracle plays of medieval Spain. Religious
folk plays called autos, based upon
both Old and New Testament texts and consisting
of spoken dialogues alternated with
sung portions, are still performed regularly in
many communities.

Also prevalent in the Prairie Provinces and
Northern Plains states is the heritage of the
Russian Doukhobor and of the Ukrainian settlers.
Doukhobor music (the word meaning
"spirit wrestler" to denote the sects' struggles
against the Russian Orthodox Church) is
largely choral in nature, passed down without
the aid of notation, and encompassing a variety
of musical styles from monody to counterpoint.
The Ukrainian community also values
choral singing in two and three parts, as well
as instrumental music played on the cembale,
bandura, and kobza.

The influx of diverse cultures to the Great
Plains of North America has been, and continues
to be, the greatest influence upon its
folk music. The ethnic groups discussed here
may be easily supplemented by countless
other nationalities, producing a truly varied
and colorful musical mosaic.

See also EUROPEAN AMERICANS: Ukrainians / 
MUSIC: Hispanic Music / NATIVE AMERICANS: 
Métis / RELIGION: Doukhobors.


Donna Lowe
Brandon Folk Music and Arts Festival




Nettl, Bruno. Folk Music in the United States. Detroit:
Wayne State University Press, 1976. Peacock, Kenneth. A Survey of Ethnic Folkmusic across Western Canada. Anthropology
Papers, no. 5. Ottawa: National Museums of
Canada, 1963. Tawa, Nicholas. A Sound of Strangers: Musical Culture, Acculturation, and the Post–Civil War Ethnic American. Metuchen NJ: Scarecrow Press, 1982.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>