<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ind.022</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Fur Trade</field>
      <field name="author">Wood, Raymond</field>
      <field name="text">

 




FUR TRADE

The historic fur trade in the Great Plains
spanned the midcontinent and involved three
separate systems: the French and, later, the
English fur trade in the Prairie Provinces and
on the Northern Plains; the successive French
and Spanish, then English and American, fur
trades of the Missouri River; and the fur, hide,
and skin trade on the Southern Plains. The
trade was fueled by businessmen who sought
to provide furs and hides necessary for the
fashionable clothing and accessories of eastern
North America and Europe.

While beaver pelts were generally the most
important single item, at least in the Far
North, the pelts and hides found in fort warehouses
were as diverse as the mammals living
on the Plains. They included bison, elk, wolf,
fox, rabbit, deer, bear, and, in the Southern
Plains, even hedgehog, although many of
these pelts were of little value. Goods traded to
Native American trappers and hunters were
equally varied, depending on wants, style, and
time period, but firearms, ammunition, metal
containers, glass beads, knives, blankets, and
cloth were universally important. Alcohol was
also an important trade item in many places.
Native Americans were not passive participants
in the business, for they had traded extensively
among themselves long before the
arrival of Europeans and Americans. They
were shrewd traders and demanded quality
goods.

Beginning in 1727, the Canadian fur trader
Pierre Gaultier de Varennes, sieur de La Vérendrye,
established a series of posts across
what is now south-central Canada, ultimately
building Fort La Reine in southern Manitoba.
From there he made an expedition to the
Mandans on the Missouri River in 1738. A few
years later his sons explored as far southwest
as the Black Hills of South Dakota. It was not
until late in the 1700s, however, that two rival
companies, the Hudson's Bay Company and
the North West Company, began competing
for the trade in the Prairie Provinces. Their
goods reached central Canada by canoe from
York Factory on Hudson Bay and from Montreal,
respectively. Between 1779 and 1821, these
companies established more than 100 posts
along the North and South Saskatchewan,
Qu'Appelle, Souris, and Red Rivers. Although
most posts were occupied for only a few years,
they linked the region's Native groups–Plains
Crees, Assiniboines, Blackfoot, Gros Ventres,
and Sarcees–firmly to international fur markets.
Beavers were the most lucrative items of
the trade. These companies, along with independent
traders, also crossed what is now the
Canada-U.S. boundary to trade with the Mandans,
Hidatsas, and others. The merger of the
two companies in 1821 led to domination by
the Hudson's Bay Company, which is still in
business.

The Missouri River fur trade was rudimentary
before 1806, although the lower parts of
the river had been explored and exploited by
French fur traders in the decades following the
discovery of its mouth by Jacques Marquette
and Louis Jolliet in 1673. French and, later,
Spanish traders penetrated as far north as the
Mandans by 1791. English traders also reached
the Missouri River tribes, such as the Omahas
and Poncas, by ascending the Des Moines
River and by traveling overland from Prairie
du Chien on the upper Mississippi River. It was
only after the return of the Lewis and Clark
expedition in 1806, however, that American
exploitation of the resources of the Missouri
basin began in earnest. In 1807 Manuel Lisa
established Fort Raymond at the mouth of the
Bighorn River in modern Montana. His enthusiasm
for that trade, albeit short-lived, led
to the formation by others of the Missouri Fur
Company in 1809, one of the first of many
successive and overlapping American companies
dedicated to the pursuit of furbearers in
the Central and Northern Plains. Dugout canoes
and keelboats carrying trade goods up the
Missouri were replaced after 1832 by steamboats,
beginning with the famous steamer Yellowstone,
which carried goods by the ton in
both directions.

The most important of the companies was
the American Fur Company founded by John
Jacob Astor in 1808. By the early 1830s, a string
of the company's posts and those of its competitors
lined the Missouri River and its tributaries,
the most important of which were Forts
Union, Clark, and Pierre. Although many
types of furs and skins were produced, bison
robes were the dominant product after 1830
on the American Plains. By 1867, with fur-bearers
depleted and the bison all but extinct,
even this trade was over. Traders and their kin
were replaced by settlers, and their forts were
abandoned.

The early trade on the Southern Plains was
closely linked to the lower Mississippi River
valley. From that center, French and later
American traders pushed up the Red and Arkansas
Rivers to barter for furs, hides, and
deerskins with Caddos, Wichitas, and Comanches.
From the late eighteenth century
on, Comancheros, Pueblo, and Spanish traders
from New Mexico journeyed to Comanche
camps to trade foodstuffs, tobacco, and manufactured
items for bison hides, deerskins,
horses, and captives. A new era in the region's
trade began in the early 1830s, when Charles
and William Bent and Ceran St. Vrain established
the prosperous Bent's Old Fort on the
upper Arkansas River. The success of Bent's
Fort enticed others, and by the early 1840s the
fringes of the Plains were dotted with numerous
posts operated by merchants from the
United States and Texas. The trade collapsed
in the early 1850s, when the combined effects
of commercial hunting, aridity, exotic bovine
diseases, and environmental degradation
pushed the massive bison herds into decline.

Although the days when the fur trade was
the dominant industry of the Great Plains are
long passed, there is still a fur industry in the
region, particularly on the Northern Great
Plains and in the Prairie Provinces. Trapping
is generally a part-time occupation of rural
Plains people. Beaver and muskrat are the
most important products of a trade that, in
the Prairie Provinces, was worth an average of
$15 million a year from 1976 to 1986.

See also EUROPEAN AMERICANS: Vérendrye Family / HISPANIC AMERICANS: Missouri Company.


Raymond Wood
University of Missouri-Columbia




Ray, Arthur. Indians in the Fur Trade: Their Role as Trappers, Hunters, and Middlemen in the Lands Southwest of Hudson Bay, 1660–1870. Toronto: University of Toronto
Press, 1974. Wishart, David J. The Fur Trade of the American West, 1807–1840. Lincoln: University of Nebraska
Press, 1979. Wood, W. Raymond, and Thomas D. Thiessen.
Early Fur Trade on the Northern Plains. Norman: University
of Oklahoma Press, 1980.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>