<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pd.057</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Winnipeg General Strike</field>
      <field name="author">Mitchell, Tom Naylor, Tom</field>
      <field name="text">

 




WINNIPEG GENERAL STRIKE


Winnipeg General Strike, June 21, 1919


For six weeks in the early summer of 1919,
Winnipeg, then the largest city in the Canadian Prairies, was shut down by a general
strike. More than 30,000 of the city's workers
walked off their jobs in a test of strength that
was to prove the focal point of a labor explosion
that was national and international in
scope. The strike was provoked by the refusal
of employers to recognize and bargain with
the metal and building trades federations
of unions. The Winnipeg Trades and Labor
Council organized a poll of its affiliates' members,
and a general strike was approved by a
vote of 11,112 to 524. The response to the strike
call on May 15 was overwhelming. Not only
did organized workers respond solidly, shutting
down factories, newspapers, telephones,
and streetcars, but thousands of unorganized
workers joined them. The city fell silent.

Longer and more disciplined than the Seattle
General Strike the previous February, the
Winnipeg confrontation remains without
precedent in the history of class confrontation
in North America. In the discourse of its opponents,
the strike was a drive for revolutionary
power by working-class militants. Workers,
perhaps too defensively, saw the strike as a
struggle for collective bargaining. Traditional
accounts of the strike have been shaped by
these conflicting narratives, with historians
siding with the strikers' portrayal of the strike.

Recent assessments of the strike have rejected
this dichotomy and now view the strike
as a complex social event with various meanings
rooted in the growing social crisis that
marked Canadian society in the last years of
World War I. Wartime inflation, the dramatic
growth in union membership, the movement
for industrial unionism, and the determination
of workers to press for a new postwar
order shaped an unprecedented threat to the
state and to business capital interests in 1919. A
Royal Commission on Industrial Relations,
appointed by the Canadian government to investigate
the labor revolt, encountered widespread
anger at "profiteering" and heard repeated
calls for "production for use and not
for profit." Across the country, workers debated
various tactics and increasingly adopted
the general strike as the best means of fostering
solidarity and furthering working-class interests
during postwar reconstruction. In 1918
the Winnipeg Trades and Labor Council had
debated calling a general strike on four different
occasions. When it finally occurred, old
animosities among workers, between central
and eastern European immigrants and Canadian
or British-born workers, and between
men and women workers, dissolved before the
logic of class unity. Even the swelling ranks of
returned war veterans rallied, for the most
part, to labor's cause, adding even greater volatility
to the developing crisis.

Revolutions in Russia and Germany no longer
seemed very remote in Winnipeg in 1919.
While trade unions tried to focus negotiations
on issues of collective bargaining, employers
and those in charge of the federal government
were deeply uneasy about the trajectory of this
unprecedented working-class mobilization.
Determined that the strike had to be crushed,
employers formed a "Citizens Committee of
One Thousand" to fight the strike and support
"established government." Despite the overwhelming
British-Canadian character of the
strike leadership, they denounced the general
strike as an attempt at revolution inspired by
"enemy aliens" and called for its immediate
suppression by the state. At the behest of the
Committee, Winnipeg's entire city police force
was dismissed when they refused, en masse, to
sign a loyalty oath; the force was replaced with
untrained, antistriker "specials."

While the federal government was committed
from the outset to the unconditional
defeat of the strike, it was determined to avoid
provoking a threatened walkout of the railway-running
trades across western Canada.
Such a development could easily have unified
the wave of local strikes in sympathy with
Winnipeg workers into a massive strike from
Lake Superior to the Pacific. By separate negotiations,
the Canadian minister of labor
managed to appease the leadership of the
railroad-running trade unions. Early in June,
the federal government prepared the legislative
groundwork for an assault on strike leadership
by amending the Immigration Act to
allow for the deportation from Canada of
British subjects and broadened the Criminal
Code definition of sedition. In late-night raids
on June 16–17, the strike leaders were arrested,
along with a group of eastern European immigrants,
who could serve as evidence of the
"alien" character of the struggle. On June 21–Bloody
Saturday–a demonstration of prostrike
returned-soldiers was brutally attacked
by the specials and the Royal North-West
Mounted Police, killing two men and injuring
at least two dozen. Following further repression
of the strikers' newspaper and the promise
of a provincial government inquiry, the
General Strike was ended on June 25.

The tide of postwar radicalism did not subside
with the state suppression of the strike.
Led by A. J. Andrews, members of the Citizens
Committee of One Thousand mobilized the
authority and resources of the federal Department
of Justice in legal and ideological assaults
designed to discredit and disperse proponents
of labor radicalism in Winnipeg and
elsewhere and to restore the legitimacy of the
existing order. Postwar radicalism was condemned
as a form of Bolshevism. The workers'
revolt of 1919 was portrayed as a criminal
enterprise and its radicals were jailed. Yet the
legal and ideological ascendancy of the Citizens
Committee and its allies in the government
was far from absolute. Rather than produce
mass adhesion to the established order,
the assault on radicalism generated workingclass
dissent and antagonism.

See also CITIES AND TOWNS: Winnipeg, Manitoba.


Tom Mitchell and James Naylor
Brandon University




Bercuson, David J. Confrontation at Winnipeg: Labour, Industrial
Relations, and the General Strike. Montreal: McGill-Queen's
University Press, 1990. Heron, Craig. The
Workers' Revolt in Canada, 1917–1925. Toronto: University
of Toronto Press, 1998. Penner, Norman, ed. Winnipeg
1919: The Strikers' Own History of the Winnipeg General
Strike. Toronto: James Lorimer, 1972.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>