<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pd.036</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Nation, Carry (1846-1911)</field>
      <field name="author">Kidd, Karen</field>
      <field name="text">

 




NATION, CARRY (1846-1911)

Carry Amelia Nation became famous for her
exploits as a direct-action prohibitionist in
Kansas. Her career began in 1900, when she
single-handedly demolished a number of saloons
in Kiowa and Wichita, and the notoriety
she cultivated during the next ten years made
her a catalyst for antiliquor sentiment throughout
the country. Always controversial, she was
vilified by some as a crank and lauded by others
as a saintly friend and benefactor; yet her
image as the woman with a hatchet in one
hand (commemorating one of the weapons
she wielded against saloons) and a Bible in the
other achieved iconographic status. At the beginning
of the twentieth century, she was arguably
the most notorious woman in America.

She was born Carry Moore in Garrard
County, Kentucky, on November 25, 1846. Her
father, a planter and stock trader, was frequently
away on business; her mother was periodically
delusional. Most of the nurture she
received as a child came from the family's
slaves. Her parents' entrepreneurial ambitions
made life peripatetic throughout Carry's
youth. After several relocations in Kentucky,
they moved to western Missouri in 1857. There,
sectional tensions along the Kansas-Missouri
border were on the rise. In 1860 they finally
put down roots in Cass County, just south of
Kansas City, but wartime hostilities forced
them to relocate several more times before it
was safe to stay there permanently. In 1864–65
Carry lived and studied at the Clay Seminary in
Liberty, Missouri. Then her mother's condition
worsened, and her father, without slaves,
needed her at home to care for her five younger
siblings.

Carry was desperately unhappy as the family
drudge, and when a young physician named
Charles Gloyd proposed marriage, she was eager
to accept. She married him on November
21, 1867, too headstrong to heed warnings
about his alcoholism. She soon acknowledged
the extent of his problem and left him after ten
months. She returned to her parents' home
and gave birth to her daughter, Charlien, on
September 27, 1868.

In 1871–72 Carry Gloyd attended the Missouri
State Normal School in Warrensburg
and earned a teaching certificate, then taught
school in Holden until she lost her position to
the niece of a school board member. Unemployed
and desperate, she fixed her sights on
David Nation, a widower with four children.
He was nineteen years her senior and generally
unpopular, but she married him anyway
on December 30, 1874. Carry later declared
that the chief benefit of their long, unhappy
marriage was that it had given her a new
name, one that prophetically declared her
mission to "Carry A. Nation" for the prohibitionist
cause.

The Nations lived in Warrensburg for two
years, then acquired a cotton plantation in
Brazoria County, Texas, where they moved in
January 1877. The cotton venture failed, but
the prospect of starvation prompted Carry to
rent a boardinghouse in nearby Columbia.
The business grew, and when they moved to
Richmond, Texas, in 1881, she was able to
buy a large hotel adjacent to the county courthouse.
They lived in Richmond for eight
years, with Carry as the family's breadwinner,
but they were run out of town for supporting
freedmen's voting rights.

Carry's life in the Great Plains began in
Medicine Lodge, Kansas, where David found
work as pastor of the Christian Church in
1889. With no hotel to keep her busy, and with
all five children grown and living elsewhere,
Carry channeled her energies into prohibitionism.
Kansas was a "dry" state, but liquor
flowed freely and public officials refused to
enforce the law. Carry founded a local chapter
of the Woman's Christian Temperance Union
(WCTU) in 1892 and spearheaded its successful
campaign to close the saloons of Medicine
Lodge. Her activism waned between 1894 and
1899, when she and David homesteaded in
Oklahoma Territory, but it returned with a
vengeance after they moved back to Medicine
Lodge. In June 1900 she dreamed that God
was commanding her to take violent action,
so she abandoned the WCTU's ladylike tactics
and launched the "hatchetation" crusade that
made her famous.

Carry moved to Topeka in January 1901 and
made it her base of operations until 1905,
when she shifted her headquarters to Guthrie,
Oklahoma Territory, to fight for a "dry" Oklahoma
statehood. In 1907 she moved to Washington
DC, and in 1908 and 1909 took her
crusade to Great Britain. She declared herself
semiretired in 1909 and settled in Eureka
Springs, Arkansas, but she continued her
efforts until paralyzed by a stroke in January
1911. She was hospitalized in Leavenworth,
Kansas, where she died on June 9, 1911.

Carry Nation was on the move throughout
her career and supported herself by lecturing
on the Lyceum, Chautauqua, and Vaudeville
circuits, speaking wherever she could find an
audience. She also sold souvenir hatchets and
copies of her autobiography. With her earnings,
she built a home for drunkards' wives in
Kansas City, launched a purity farm for boys
in Oklahoma, and gave to many causes. She
created disturbances wherever she went, was
jailed more than thirty times, and endured
several beatings at the hands of her opponents.
Noteworthy for her support of African
Americans, Catholics, and Jews, and for her
promotion of women's suffrage, sex education,
and public health, she is nevertheless
mainly remembered for the things that she
opposed–alcohol, tobacco, political corruption,
and fraternal organizations.


Karen Kidd
California State University, Fullerton




Nation, Carry A. Scrapbook and Diary. Topeka: Kansas
State Historical Society. Nation, Carry A. The Use and
Need of the Life of Carry A. Nation. Topeka: F. M. Steves
and Sons, 1909.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>