<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.med.036</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Peffer, William Alfred (1831-1912)</field>
      <field name="author">Argersinger, Peter H.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




PEFFER, WILLIAM ALFRED (1831-1912)

William Alfred Peffer was a prominent newspaper
editor who helped organize the People's
Party and became the first Populist U.S. senator.
Born in Cumberland County, Pennsylvania,
on September 10, 1831, Peffer farmed and
taught school in several states before settling
in Fredonia, Kansas, in 1870. There he purchased
a small newspaper that he renamed the
Fredonia Journal.

A Republican, Peffer was elected a state senator
in 1874 and a presidential elector in 1880,
but he was more involved in journalism than
politics. In 1875 he moved to Coffeyville, renamed
his newspaper the Coffeyville Journal,
and became active in the Kansas Editors Association.
In 1881, leaving a son to run the
Coffeyville Journal, Peffer moved to Topeka as
editor of the Kansas Farmer, the state's foremost
farm journal and most widely circulated
newspaper. He also became an associate editor
for the Topeka Capital, the state's leading Republican
daily. But he followed a nonpartisan
course in making the Kansas Farmer an influential
reform newspaper, advocating railroad
regulation, financial reform, antimonopolism,
and political democratization. He urged
farmers to organize, and the Farmers Alliance
made the Farmer its official state paper.

In 1890 Peffer's editorials and speeches
helped the alliance launch the People's Party
of Kansas, which defeated the Republicans
and in 1891 elected him senator. Resigning
from the Farmer, he became the major shareholder
of the Topeka Advocate, the leading
Populist newspaper, and organized and became
the first president of the Kansas Reform
Press Association. His books, The Way Out
(1890) and The Farmer's Side: His Troubles and Their Remedy (1891), were fundamental Populist
literature.

Peffer chaired the 1891 Cincinnati conference
that organized the national People's
Party, and he became the principal advocate of
Populist measures in Congress. He used his
official salary to help start the National Watchman
as a Populist newspaper in Washington
DC, and in 1895 he took control of the Advocate.
He consistently promoted a radical and
independent course for the Populist Party but
gradually lost influence as it turned to a policy
of fusion on the basis of free silver. He was not
reelected in 1897 and shortly thereafter sold
the Advocate. He continued to write for newspapers
and magazines on agricultural and
economic topics until his death in Grenola,
Kansas, on October 6, 1912.

See also POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT: Populists (People's Party).


Peter H. Argersinger
Southern Illinois University




Argersinger, Peter H. Populism and Politics: William Alfred Peffer and the People's Party. Lexington: University Press of
Kentucky, 1974. Peffer, William A. Populism, Its Rise and Fall, edited by Peter H. Argersinger. Lawrence: University
Press of Kansas, 1992.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>