<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ag.020</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Center for Rural Affairs</field>
      <field name="author">Powell, Marie</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CENTER FOR RURAL AFFAIRS

The Center for Rural Affairs, established
in 1973 in Walthill, Nebraska, was created
through the vision of two vista volunteers,
Don Ralston and Marty Strange. The center
established its reputation early as an agricultural
advocate with a conscience and a strong,
independent voice on agricultural matters
throughout the Great Plains and beyond.

The center immediately confronted several
agricultural issues with serious economic, social,
and environmental overtones. Taking issue
with irrigation in the fragile Nebraska
Sandhills, large-scale hog confinements, and
the decline of independent banking in rural
Nebraska, it earned a reputation for sound
research and honest, practical, and fair solutions.
Subsequently, research expanded into
global warming, rural economic development
policy, unfair livestock markets, and federal
farm policy. Most recently the center has examined
the structure of agriculture and new
marketing opportunities for family farmers.

Advocacy is equally important to the center's
history and character. Major policy
thrusts include tax reform and school finance
in Nebraska as well as conservation and fairness
in federal farm policy. The center has
worked alone and with others to invigorate
and broaden the meaning of sustainable agriculture
and to hasten its acceptance in the
agricultural community.

Engaging people to find their own solutions
has been another major thrust of its work.
When the energy crisis of the 1970s created an
opportunity for small farms to demonstrate
appropriate technology, the center created the
nation's first on-farm research program with
the Small Farm Energy Project. The Rural Enterprise
Assistance Project (REAP) builds on
the entrepreneurial assets of rural people and
helps communities to support them. And the
Land Link program connects retiring farmers
with beginning farmers, placing farmland in
the next generation's hands. The center sponsors
a total of eight such projects to help build
rural communities and family farms. Truly
one of a kind, the Center for Rural Affairs is a
leader in advocating social and environmental
justice in rural America.


Center for Rural Affairs website.


Marie Powell
Center for Rural Affairs





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>