<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.sr.023</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Gowdy, Curt (b. 1919)</field>
      <field name="author">Harper, Jim W.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




GOWDY, CURT (b. 1919)

Curtis Gowdy was a major figure in televised
sport during the 1960s and 1970s, coinciding
with that medium's increasing impact on American
society. Gowdy was born in Green River,
Wyoming, on July 31, 1919, and raised in Cheyenne.
He grew up loving team and outdoor
sports. He excelled in basketball and softball
during his high school years and at the University
of Wyoming from 1938 to 1942. After a back
injury ended his service in the Army Air Corps
in 1943, he began a career as a broadcaster in
Cheyenne and later Oklahoma City, Oklahoma.

Gowdy reached broadcasting's big markets
in 1949, starting a two-year tour as Mel Allen's
partner with the New York Yankees. This exposure
led to a job as the announcer for the
Boston Red Sox from 1951 to 1966. Gowdy
quickly became a popular figure with the large
New England audience. Like most broadcasters
he covered all major sports and hosted various
programs. He impressed network officials and
peers with his versatility, preparation, and good
humor.

Gowdy reached national prominence during
the 1960s as the play-by-play broadcaster of the
young American Football League. Teamed with
former Missouri quarterback Paul Christman
and backed by the managerial and technological
innovations of Roone Arledge, Gowdy attracted
listeners to the rival league with his enthusiasm,
knowledge, and fairness. When the National
Broadcasting Company took over the AFL rights
in 1966, the network hired Gowdy as its main
football and baseball announcer. He announced
every World Series and major afl telecast from
1966 through 1975. In addition, he broadcast
college football bowl games and basketball
championships. He described his life and announcing
philosophy in Cowboy at the Mike in
1966.

Gowdy's stature enabled him to launch the
American Sportsman series in 1967. The program
took celebrities on hunting, fishing, and
camera trips around the globe and introduced
millions of urbanites to the beauties of wilderness,
augmenting the fledgling environmental
movement. Gowdy received numerous accolades:
four Emmys; sportscaster of the year
recognitions in 1965 and 1967; a George Foster
Peabody Award in 1970; and membership in
the Sports Broadcasters, National Baseball,
and American Sportscasters Halls of Fame. He
served as president of the National Basketball
Hall of Fame, and that organization's media
award was named in his honor. The creation
of Curt Gowdy State Park in Cheyenne in 1971
was yet another recognition.

Gowdy's work on so many sportscasts led to
his overexposure in an industry that constantly
demanded new faces, and his network appearances
declined after 1975. He branched
into production and ownership and hosted a
critically acclaimed nostalgia series, The Way It
Was, on PBS during the 1980s. He wrote Seasons
to Remember: The Way It Was in American
Sports, 1945–1960 in 1993. Gowdy retired to
Palm Beach, Florida, in the 1990s. His son,
Curt Gowdy Jr., is an Emmy Award–winning
producer of sports programs.


Jim W. Harper
Texas Tech University




Smith, Curt. Of Mikes and Men: From Ray Scott to Curt
Gowdy: Broadcast Tales from the Pro Football Booth. South
Bend IN: Diamond Communications, 1998. Smith, Curt.
Voices of the Game. South Bend IN: Diamond Communications,
1987.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>