<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pe.043</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Niobrara Ecotone</field>
      <field name="author">Steuter, Allen A.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




NIOBRARA ECOTONE

The Niobrara ecotone, along the Niobrara
River in north-central Nebraska, is an area of
transition between habitats, plants, and animals
with more eastern, western, southern,
and northern distributions. The ecotone is
most dramatic from the mouth of Minnechaduza
Creek on the Fort Niobrara National
Wildlife Refuge to the mouth of Plum Creek
north of Ainsworth. In this fifty-mile stretch,
the Niobrara flows through a gently rolling
grassland in a wooded canyon nearly 400 feet
deep. The canyon has developed during the
last 20,000 years as local uplifting of the
earth's surface has been countered by the actively
downcutting Niobrara River. Several
geological formations are exposed, leading to
an array of soils, slopes, and sun angles. The
ecotone is a mosaic of habitats on wet-to-dry
and warm-to-cool sites, with shallow-to-deep
and fertile-to-sterile soils.

South of the river, paper birch (Betula papyrifera)
and aspen (Populus tremuloidesgrandidentata)
stands, with northern mannagrass
(Glyceria borealis) and green orchids
(Habenaria hyperborea) in the understory,
grade into eastern deciduous woodland featuring
basswood (Tilia americana), hop hornbeam
(Ostrya virginiana), and hazelnut (Corylus
americana). These woodlands are replaced
by mesic tallgrass prairie stands on subirrigated
low terraces, and bur oak (Quercus macrocarpa)–
ponderosa pine (Pinus ponderosa)
savanna and then Sandhills prairie on the dry
upper slopes. North of the river the ecotone is a
transition from western coniferous woodland
dominated by ponderosa pine to northern
mixed-grass prairie. Riparian woodlands,
shrub lands, wetlands, and riverine habitats
occur on the valley floor.

The Niobrara ecotone is particularly rich in
species because of the many transitions between
the distinct woodland, grassland, and
wetland habitats in a relatively small area. The
ecotone supports nearly two-thirds of the vascular
plant species, more than half of the
mammal and bird species, more than a third
of the butterfly species, and more than a quarter
of the fish species found in Nebraska.
Fifty-five moss and eighty-six lichen species
have been collected within the ecotone.

Whether on the canyon slopes and terraces
or in the valley bottom, the forces of moving
water, fire, and grazing continue to maintain
this dynamic mosaic. Interestingly a northwest
to southeast flowing river of the Miocene
epoch (5 to 24 million years ago) also supported
an impressive ecotone in what is now
the middle Niobrara Valley. The fossil remains
of a diverse group of browsers, grazers, predators,
and aquatic species are represented in
numerous quarries excavated in the contemporary
Niobrara ecotone.


Allen A. Steuter
The Nature Conservancy




Kaul, Robert B., Gail E. Kantak, and Steven P. Churchill.
"The Niobrara River Valley, a Postglacial Migration Corridor
and Refugium of Forest Plants and Animals in the
Grasslands of Central North America." The Botanical Review
54 (1988): 44–81. Steuter, Allen A., Bruce Jasch, Joel
Ihnen, and Larry L. Tieszen. "Woodland/Grassland
Boundary Changes in the Middle Niobrara Valley of Nebraska
Identified by Delta Carbon 13 Values of Soil Organic
Matter." American Midland Naturalist 124 (1990): 301–8.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>