<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ag.062</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Soybeans</field>
      <field name="author">Mason, Stephen C.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SOYBEANS

Soybean (Glycine max), native to China, is a
relatively new crop to the Great Plains, where
there was no appreciable production prior to
1950. Since 1950, the production area has increased
rapidly to more than 12 million acres
in the U.S. Great Plains in 1998, which is about
18 percent of the national production area.
The production is largely in the eastern Great
Plains, due to the higher annual precipitation
and the greater likelihood of rainfall during
the critical pod elongation stage, which occurs
in early August. Little soybean production occurs
in the western Great Plains and the Canadian Prairie Provinces because of the short
growing season (in the north), low annual
precipitation, and low probability of rainfall
during early August. Major production problems
are water and high-temperature stress
during the growing season. Only a few insect
and pest problems cause sporadic yield losses.
The most common pest problems are Phytophthora
root and stem rot, bean leaf beetle,
and soybean cyst nematode.

Since soybean is grown most widely in
the eastern Great Plains, it does not overlap
greatly with the region's large wheat acreage.
Soybean is most commonly grown as a rotational
dryland crop with corn, grain sorghum,
and winter wheat, and is the third most important
grain crop in the region, following
wheat and corn. Soybean is produced as a cash
crop, with the production being shipped by
rail or truck to crushing plants. The major
food end products are cooking oil, margarine,
shortening, and emulsifiers. Soybean is also
widely used as a high protein livestock feed
supplement. Nonfood end uses include plastics
and coatings, lubricants, diesel fuel substitute,
carrier for pesticides, dust suppressant
in grain handling, and printing ink.

The soybean production area within the
Great Plains is concentrated in Nebraska and
South Dakota, with 60 percent of the total,
while production in Oklahoma and Texas is
quite small. The highest yields–45 bushels per
acre in 1998–are in Nebraska, largely because
approximately one-third of the soybean production
area is irrigated. Yields of approximately
25 bushels per acre are common in
North Dakota, Oklahoma, and Texas. Soybean
yields in the Great Plains average approximately
10 percent less than in the Corn Belt
states, where higher, more uniformly distributed
annual precipitation occurs.

See also INDUSTRY: Oilseeds.


Stephen C. Mason
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Wilcox, J. R., ed. Soybeans: Improvement, Production, and Uses. Madison WI: American Society of Agronomy, 1987.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>