<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.tra.036</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Trans-Canada Highway</field>
      <field name="author">Horne, William R.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




TRANS-CANADA HIGHWAY

In 1949 the government of Canada passed an
Act to Encourage and to Assist in the Construction
of a Trans-Canada Highway. The act
specified a set of construction criteria for a
two-lane highway to connect Canada's east
and west coasts by the most direct route. The
federal government would pay 50 percent of
the construction costs. The highway was officially
opened in 1962, and the federal government
continued to make payments under the
act until 1971. The federal share was over $900
million, and the total cost was estimated at
$1.4 billion. At 4,860 miles, it is the longest
national highway in the world.

The highway crosses the Prairie Provinces
following the route of the transcontinental
railway built between 1881 and 1883, linking
together five of the eleven largest cities in the
region. Leaving the Canadian Shield country
of Ontario, it becomes the main street of Winnipeg,
Manitoba, then pushes west to the
province's second largest city, Brandon. Regina,
Saskatchewan, is the next city on the
highway, followed by Moose Jaw, Saskatchewan,
and Medicine Hat, Alberta. The highway
is a major expressway through Calgary, then,
heading west, it enters the Rockies via Banff
National Park. This route makes the highway
an important truck route for provincial and
interprovincial trade. Most of the highway
across the Prairie Provinces has now been
widened to four lanes, and the twinning process
continues.

Since the construction of the Trans-Canada
Highway, the social custom of gathering for
coffee has shifted from the centers of the small
towns near the highway to the restaurants and
service stations at highway intersections. Further,
improved transportation has led to the
loss of services and the economic decline of
some towns, while those towns near cities
have taken on a dormitory function.

Like the railway, the highway was also built
for symbolic reasons: to demonstrate Canadian
unity. The highway is designated Highway
1 and has the Canadian maple leaf signage.
During the summer months it is heavily
used by hitchhikers, cyclists, mobile homes,
and automobile tourists. Banff National Park
receives over five million visitors annually.

Many diaries and coffee-table books have
been published reflecting personal experiences
along the highway. It has been described
as "the artery through which the soul of the
nation pulses . . . dedicated to the freedom to
travel without restriction." Across the vastness
of the Prairie Provinces this is particularly noticeable.
In some ways it is the Canadian equivalent
of U.S. Route 66.

During the 1970s, a northern route through
the Parkland Belt was designated the Yellowhead
Highway. Following the Trans-Canada
Highway west from Winnipeg for fifty miles, it
turns northwest to Saskatoon, Saskatchewan,
and Edmonton, Alberta, and enters the Rockies
through Jasper National Park and the Yellowhead
Pass. It has also been designated as a
trans-Canada highway route, although the
Yellowhead name is still in more general use.


William R. Horne
University of Northern British Columbia




Howarth, William. Traveling the Trans-Canada. Washington
DC: National Geographic Society, 1987. Ratausky,
Wes. Silver Highway: A Celebration of the Trans-Canada
Highway. Markham, Ontario: Fitzhenry and Whiteside,
1988.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>