<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.rel.041</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Quakers</field>
      <field name="author">Brightup, Leroy</field>
      <field name="text">

 




QUAKERS

Quaker settlements began to appear in the
Great Plains in Kansas in the 1850s when families
moved together from Quaker communities
in Indiana and Iowa. Lured by the prospect
of choice land, they were also motivated
by benevolent concern for Native Americans
and the opportunity of voting against slavery
in this newly opened territory. Homes and
churches were constructed of logs and prairie
sod.

Historically, Quaker worship consisted of a
simple gathering in silence, without clergy,
planned program, or sacrament. Worshipers
prayed or spoke as they felt moved by God.
Influenced by frontier revivalism, many Quakers
in the latter third of the 1800s embraced the
evangelistic methods and pastoral leadership
characteristic of others. Thereafter, much of
the spread of Quakerism in rural Oklahoma
and Nebraska reflected this new development.

Maintaining the dignity and equality of all
persons and leadership by women as well as
men have been encouraged. Numerous Quaker
schools across Kansas, Oklahoma, and Nebraska
made education available before the advent
of public schools. Not limited to Quakers, Barclay
College (Haviland, Kansas) and Friends
University (Wichita, Kansas) continue to provide
education at the adult level. Work with
Native Americans, initiated in Kansas at Shawnee
Mission (1836), continued in Nebraska in
the late 1860s, when Quakers were appointed
as agents to the Pawnees, Omahas, and Otoe-
Missourias, and subsequently in Oklahoma and
New Mexico.

Approximately a dozen isolated Quaker
Meetings (worship groups) can be found in
Nebraska, and there is a small, unprogrammed
group in each of the five major cities of the
Prairie Provinces of Canada. The highest concentration
of Quakers in the Great Plains,
however, is found in southern Kansas, northern
Oklahoma, and southeastern Colorado,
where the pastoral leadership style of worship
tends to prevail. Membership among Quakers
within the Great Plains is approximately 6,000,
with about 75 percent located in Kansas and
Oklahoma.


Leroy Brightup
Friends University




Barbour, Hugh, and J. William Frost. The Quakers. Richmond
IN: Friends United Press, 1994. Dorland, Arthur
Garratt. The Quakers in Canada: A History. Toronto: Ryerson
Press, 1968. Elliott, Errol T. Quakers on the American
Frontier. Richmond IN: Friends United Press, 1969.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>