<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.tra.017</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Holliday, Cyrus K. (1826-1900)</field>
      <field name="author">Ward, Derrick S.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




HOLLIDAY, CYRUS K. (1826-1900)

Cyrus Kurtz Holliday, founder of the Atchison,
Topeka and Santa Fe Railroad, was born
April 3, 1826, in Carlisle, Pennsylvania. He became
a leading abolitionist in Kansas, established
a settlement at Topeka, and battled Missouri
border ru.ans before achieving lasting
fame and fortune as a railroad builder.

As a young man, Holliday dreamed of building
a railroad that would follow the old Santa
Fe Trail to the Southwest. His involvement in
the struggle over slavery in "Bleeding Kansas,"
however, put his railroading career on hold.
In 1854, when Congress passed the Kansas-Nebraska
Act, Holliday moved to Kansas,
joined the Free Soil Party, and resided briefly
in the small settlement of Lawrence. That fall,
he helped found the settlement of Topeka
and became that future state capital's first
mayor. Throughout the fall of 1855, Holliday,
an outspoken antislavery activist, wrote extensively
for the Kansas Freeman, an abolitionist
newspaper. As guerrilla warfare erupted
around him, he was named colonel and commanded
the Second Kansas Regiment at the
December siege of Lawrence. When proslavery
guerrillas renewed their incursions into Kansas
six weeks later, Colonel Holliday was promoted
to brigadier general, and he repulsed
the Missourians.

During the late 1850s, Holliday served in the
legislature and once again pursued his dream
of a career in railroad building. In 1859 the
Kansas Territorial Legislature granted him a
state charter for the Atchison and Topeka
Railroad, and in 1863 President Lincoln signed
an act granting Holliday's railroad 2,928,928
acres of land in Kansas and millions more
over time in states farther west. On November
24, 1863, the line was renamed the Atchison,
Topeka and Santa Fe Railway. Holliday spent
half a decade raising the funds needed to get
this railroad started. Finally, in 1868, ground
was broken at Topeka. The line was a success,
soon reaching Colorado and New Mexico and
eventually stretching on to Los Angeles.

In 1874, after saving the Atchison, Topeka
and Santa Fe from bankruptcy, Thomas Nickerson,
a Boston financier, replaced Holliday as
the company's president. Holliday returned to
serve as president of the reorganized Santa Fe
rail system from July 1, 1896, until his death on
March 29, 1900.

See also WAR: Bleeding Kansas.


Derrick S. Ward
Ventura, California




Marshall, James. Santa Fe: The Railroad That Built an Empire.
New York: Random House, 1945.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>