<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.arc.006</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Brick Masonry</field>
      <field name="author">Martens, Steve C.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BRICK MASONRY

Brick masonry–more precisely, construction
utilizing modular fired-clay products–is one
of many building technologies found in the
Great Plains. Bricks are the product of a complex
manufacturing process that converts naturally
occurring raw clay into an inert, vitrified
building material by baking it to very high
temperatures (kiln firing). The quality of the
finished product (in terms of hardness, uniformity,
and color) varies widely, based on the
raw clay "body," the method and conditions
under which the bricks are fired, and the
chemical or mineral impurities present in the
clay. Colors typically tend toward either a buff
tan color or a reddish color range. Masonry is
regarded as a highly desirable building material
in the Great Plains, as elsewhere, because
of its durability and fire resistance as well as
the expression of permanence it conveys.

Reasons for the prevalence of brick masonry
in the Great Plains include the time
frame of settlement, environmental requirements,
and the imported skills and traditions
of ethnic groups that settled on the Plains. In
many locations the earliest buildings were
constructed of other available materials, but
after settlements became better established the
second generation of buildings often included
brick masonry in combination with more
costly ornamental stone masonry. Masonry is
a relatively massive material with good thermal
performance where temperature varies
widely from day to night. Brick is inherently
fire resistant, a characteristic important in
both tightly grouped buildings in urban commercial
districts and isolated buildings in
the countryside. Many communities adopted
building codes mandating masonry construction
in downtown locations after disastrous
fires like the Great Fargo Fire of 1893 in North
Dakota.

The type of clay used to make bricks is present
in many Great Plains locations. Immigrants
to the Plains (particularly those from
northern Europe) were familiar with methods
necessary to make bricks and often selected
town sites where clay was available and where
there were suitable fuels for firing kilns. German
Americans in particular had a fondness
for brick masonry in buildings. Early brick
making sometimes entailed firing piles of
hand-molded bricks in the open, referred to
as a scove kiln or a clamp. This method was
soon supplanted by beehive-shaped kilns,
which were fired intermittently, and eventually
by industrialized tunnel kilns, which
were fired continuously. By 1900 there were
more than twenty brick manufacturers in
North Dakota alone. Now there are fewer than
a dozen manufacturers on the entire Northern
Plains.

Brick-making technology led to the design
and construction of many types of masonry
buildings, including civic and commercial
buildings, schools, churches, and a variety
of agricultural structures (structural claytile
silos, grain storage buildings, and rural
creameries). Use of brick to construct houses
in the Great Plains has been relatively uncommon,
but in certain localities significant concentrations
of brick residences do occur in
both towns and rural areas. Notable examples
include areas of German American settlement
in river valleys where brickyards are situated,
continuing a pattern found farther east in the
Minnesota River valley and along the Missouri
River near Hermann, Missouri. Similar patterns
of brick production, distribution, and
usage occur from the Prairie Provinces to the
Southern Plains, with the extent of brick masonry
diminishing as one moves farther westward
onto the Plains. Buildings that appear to
be of primarily brick masonry construction
were often actually constructed using a mixture
of available materials, commonly including
wood-floor framing. Brick buildings were
generally limited to about four stories in
height, which made them relatively well suited
to the scale of buildings in most Great Plains
cities and towns.

Brick masonry buildings range from the
vernacular to high-style buildings designed by
professionally trained architects like Frank
Lloyd Wright. Historically, ornamentation
tended to be accomplished less by molding
unique, individual pieces of brick than by the
patterns in which the bricks were assembled.
Detailed features of brick masonry buildings
thus reflect the skill of the masons who
erected them and the aesthetic judgment of
the architects who designed them.


Steve C. Martens
North Dakota State University




Foster, Joseph Arnold, ed. Accounts of Brick Making in
America Published between 1850 and 1900. Claremont CA:
Privately published, 1971. McKee, Harley. Introduction to
Early American Masonry. Washington DC: National Trust
for Historic Preservation, 1973. Noble, Allen G. Wood,
Brick, and Stone. Amherst: University of Massachusetts
Press, 1984.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>