<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.art.029</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Greener, Charles Theodore (1870-1935)</field>
      <field name="author">Miller, John E.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MILLER, JOHN E. (1870-1935)

Charles Theodore Greener's oil paintings of
the area surrounding his Redfield, South Dakota,
home made him a leading regional artist
during the early twentieth century. His realistic
prairie landscapes, painted in soft brush
strokes, capture the beauty of the region's
wide-open spaces, depict panoramic sunsets
and sunrises, and render ordinary scenes that
include geese, coyotes, hunting dogs, and
other inhabitants of the Plains.

Greener was born on March 16, 1870, in a
log house in Grant County, Wisconsin, the
second oldest of seven children of Christian
and Albina Greener. The family moved to
Hand County, Dakota Territory, in 1883 and
eight years later settled in Faulkton, which
Greener made his home for the rest of his life.
Largely self-taught as an artist, he received formal
training at the University of North Dakota
and at schools in Cincinnati, Minneapolis,
and Galesburg, Illinois. His work was
displayed at the World's Columbian Exposition
in Chicago in 1893. In 1906 Faulk County
commissioned him to paint the murals for its
new courthouse. He was one of two artists
representing South Dakota in 1915 at the St.
Paul Institute's first survey of northwestern
painting, and he gained national recognition
in 1932 by being selected for an exhibit entitled
The American Scene in Indianapolis.

Greener supplemented his small income
from commissions and sales of his paintings
through a variety of business ventures, including
a photo shop and a combined novelty and
grocery store. In 1900 he married W. Florence
Jones; they had one child, Dorothy. He engaged
actively in community affairs, serving as
a deacon in the Congregational church, singing
in the church choir, and joining the Masonic
Lodge. He was a member of the city
council at the time of his death on July 4, 1935.


John E. Miller
South Dakota State University




Lewis, Dale. "Early South Dakota Artist Is Regaining Popularity."
Dakota West 12 (1986): 20–22.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>