<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ha.027</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Meatpacking</field>
      <field name="author">Vargas, Zaragosa</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MEATPACKING


Armour Packing Plant in Kansas City, Kansas


The employment of Latinos in the meatpacking
industry of the Great Plains first took
place between 1900 and 1930. Many Mexicans
had entered the region to perform sugar beet
work for the Great Western Sugar Company.
Mexican communities formed near the refineries
at sugar-beet-producing centers like
Scotts Bluff County, Nebraska, and Weld
County, Colorado. By 1927 half of the 58,000
Mexicans employed by the sugar beet industry
worked in Wyoming, Colorado, Iowa, and
Nebraska. Other Mexican immigrants entered
the meatpacking industry after coming to the
region through Kansas City, Kansas, to work
for the Union Pacific, Burlington Northern,
Santa Fe, and other railroads. The Mexican
section hands settled in towns along the rail
lines like Lawrence, Garden City, and Kansas
City, Kansas, and Sidney, Ogallala, Grand Island,
and Omaha, Nebraska.

Mexican immigrants obtained work in the
slaughterhouses and meatpacking plants of
Wilson and Company, Swift and Company,
Cudahy, and the Omaha Company in Nebraska,
South Dakota, Kansas, and Iowa.
They established settlements near the packing
plants in Omaha, Kansas City, Sioux City, and
Sioux Falls. Many meatpackers and their families
became permanent residents of the Great
Plains, though large numbers were repatriated
to Mexico during the 1920–21 depression and
the Great Depression. During and after World
War II, Mexican meatpackers in Omaha, Kansas
City, and Fort Worth played an important
role in the unionizing drives of the Packing-house
Workers Organizing Committee.

The Great Plains meatpacking industry
continues to attract Mexicans and other Latinos
because of the labor needs of processing
plants that have moved from the big urban
centers to the Plains rural areas and small
towns like Lexington, Nebraska, and Emporia
and Garden City, Kansas. From 1980 to 1990
the beef, pork, and poultry processors in Nebraska,
Kansas, and Iowa recruited workers
from South Texas and California. The percentage
of Latinos throughout the meatpacking
industry continues to increase, representing
more than 20 percent of the workers in some
meat plants, like those in Emporia, to twothirds
in others, like those in Finney County,
Kansas. Most workers are young males born in
Mexico and in Guatemala. Fewer than half of
the Latino immigrant meatpackers have lived
in the United States for five years. More than
one-third are in the country legally through
provisions of the Immigration Reform and
Control Act of 1986, while more than onefourth
lack legal residence, resulting in frequent
arrests and deportations.

Illness, high injury rates, and stress caused
by repetitive work plague meatpackers, who
often quit after a few months or are forced off
the job by the company. More than two-thirds
leave because of poor working conditions. Low
wages, limited mobility and advancement, and
poor relations with management also account
for high turnover rates in this industry. Latino
meatpackers are burdened with housing shortages,
poor health care and other social services,
and racism and discrimination. The passage of
"English only" ordinances and other such laws
has been prompted by the increasing presence
of Latinos in the meatpacking centers of the
Great Plains. That presence, however, which is
only the latest wave of immigration to a region
populated by the descendants of immigrants,
is not likely to diminish in the foreseeable
future.


Zaragosa Vargas
University of California, Santa Barbara




Gouveia, Lourdes. "Global Strategies and Local Linkages:
The Case of the U.S. Meat Packing Industry." In From Columbus to ConAgra: The Globalization of Agriculture and Food, edited by Alessandro Bonanno, Lawrence Bush,
William Friedland, Lourdes Gouveia, and Enzo Mingione.
Lawrence: University Press of Kansas, 1994: 125–48. Lamphere,
Louise, Guillermo Grenier, and Alex Stepick, eds.
Newcomers in the Workplace: New Immigrants and the Restructuring of the U.S. Economy. Philadelphia: Temple
University Press, 1994.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>