<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pd.039</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Nonpartisan League</field>
      <field name="author">Porter, Kimberly K.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




NONPARTISAN LEAGUE

United by low commodity prices, high interest
rates, shady practices in the grain trade, and
thwarted political goals, farmers of North Dakota
gathered in the spring of 1915 to form the
Nonpartisan League (NPL). Coalescing behind
the impressive oratorical and organizational
skills of Arthur C. Townley, the NPL served the
state, and the nation, as a grand experiment in
socialist agrarian reform.

After failing as a farmer and as an organizer
for North Dakota's Socialist Party, Townley
drifted to Bismarck to observe the 1915 session
of the state legislature, where representatives
prepared to debate the creation of a stateowned
terminal elevator. The elevator was intended
to give North Dakota farmers a degree
of control over the marketing of their wheat.
In the heated debate, Fargo representative
Treadwell Twitchell allegedly told farmers
crowding the balcony that "running the state
was none of their business" and that they
should "go home and slop the hogs."

Rather than returning home, however,
Townley met with a number of McHenry
County farmers to discuss their growing resentment
and frustration with politics as dominated
by the grain trade and the railroads. Declaring
that the end had come for machine politics,
which left no role for farmers or laborers,
the assembled men declared the formation of
the Farmers Nonpartisan Political League, later
renamed the Nonpartisan League.

Familiar with the failure of third-party political
movements, Townley determined that
the NPL should use existing parties to implement
the organization's agenda. Accordingly,
the NPL sought to endorse candidates from
either of the major political parties in the
state's open primaries in order to form a
"nonpartisan" ticket that farmers could support
in the November election. To gain farmers'
support, candidates needed only to promise
to uphold the NPL's ever-growing list of
demands. By the primary of 1916, the League's
platform included state ownership of terminal
elevators, flour mills, cold storage plants, and
packing plants; formation of a state hail insurance
program; and establishment of stateowned
banks that would offer farmers lowinterest
loans. Additionally, the state would
inspect grain, exempt farm improvements
from taxation, and create a program of public
works for the unemployed.

Despite flooding on primary day that kept
significant numbers of farmers from the polls,
NPL-designated candidates carried all but one
state office in June 1916. In the November general
election, the NPL claimed control of the
governorship, cabinet, and state house of representatives.
Its failure to carry the state senate
stalled the effort to achieve state socialism, but
the organization's 40,000 members still held
the day. During the 1917 session, the legislature
passed into law much of the progressive
agenda called for by NPL members. It created a
much-improved grain grading system, established
a state highway commission, prohibited
rate discrimination by railroads, increased aid
to education, and proposed constitutional
amendments for female suffrage and the exemption
of farm improvements from taxation.

In 1918, claiming near total victory, the Nonpartisan
League began implementing what
Townley referred to as the "New Day for North
Dakota." Aided by constitutional amendments
sponsored by the League and interpreted by an
NPL-dominated state supreme court, the organization
set about its agenda. The NPL utilized
the 1919 legislative session to implement much
of its platform, creating the North Dakota Mill
and Elevator Association, the Home Building
Association, the Bank of North Dakota, a statesponsored
hail insurance program, and an industrial
commission to oversee the development
of further state businesses. The 1919 legislative
session also sponsored progressive
legislation to provide workman's compensation,
reduced hours of labor for working
women, the inspection of coal mines, and limited
the use of injunctions in labor disputes.

The party's appeal was not limited to North
Dakota, and over the course of 1918–19 the
movement expanded into the majority of
Great Plains and midwestern states. At the
height of its popularity, the NPL claimed more
than 200,000 members in twenty states. Although
the NPL never took control of the reins
of state power elsewhere as it did in North
Dakota, the political debate in many states
clearly felt the influence of the organization.

The work of the NPL did not go unchallenged.
Increasingly, the league's leadership
came under attack for malfeasance, socialist
inclination, and fraud. The primary opposition
came from a coalition of disaffected businessmen
and Republicans locked out of their
own party. Charges from the Independent Voters
Association, as well as the defection of major
NPL officeholders–Attorney General William
Langer, Secretary of State Thomas Hall,
and state auditor Carl Kozitsky–and the publication
of the salacious Red Flame, ultimately
brought the NPL era in North Dakota to a close.
Equally detrimental to the cause of continued
NPL control was the almost universally poor
management of the state's new businesses.

On October 28, 1921, npl governor Lynn J.
Frazier suffered the ignominy of being the first
state official removed from office under the
terms of an NPL-sponsored state constitutional
amendment. The same recall election witnessed
the removal of Attorney General William
Lemke and Commissioner of Agriculture
John Hagen. North Dakotans, however, voted
to uphold the principles of state-sponsored
business. Indeed, much of the program instigated
by the NPL remains in place in modernday
North Dakota.

See also POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT: Frazier, Lynn; Langer, William; Lemke, William; North Dakota.


Kimberly K. Porter
University of North Dakota




Coleman, Patrick K., and Charles R. Lamb, compilers. The
Nonpartisan League, 1915–1922: An Annotated Bibliography.
St. Paul: Minnesota Historical Society Press, 1985.
Morlan, Robert L. Political Prairie Fire: The Nonpartisan
League, 1915–1922. St. Paul: Minnesota Historical Society
Press, 1985. Robinson, Elwyn B. History of North Dakota.
Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1966.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>