<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.gen.027</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Peattie, Elia (1862-1935)</field>
      <field name="author">George, Susanne K.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




PEATTIE, ELIA (1862-1935)

Elia Wilkinson Peattie was born in Kalamazoo,
Michigan, on January 15, 1862, and later
moved to Chicago with her parents. In 1883
she married Robert Peattie, a Chicago newspaperman.
Later, she and her husband and
children moved to Omaha, where from 1889
to 1896 she was an editorial writer and columnist
for the Omaha World-Herald. While in
Omaha, Peattie participated in politics, especially
with William Jennings Bryan; hobnobbed
with Willa Cather and Hamlin Garland,
among other authors; helped organize
Women's Clubs across the state; and actively
supported hospitals for unwed mothers, orphanages,
relief for the poor and homeless,
and day-care centers for Nebraska women. As
one of the first western women to write editorial
columns that addressed public issues,
her outspoken and often irreverent remarks
show a side of the frontier often overlooked.
Not all pioneer women lived in sod houses
and spent their days gathering buffalo chips
for cooking. Many western pioneers, like Peattie,
lived in fledgling villages and booming
cities, and their influence impacted the course
of history, too.

Upon her return to Chicago, Peattie became
the literary critic for the Chicago Tribune,
a member of the exclusive literary club
Fortnightly, and one of the leaders of Chicago
Women's Clubs. She influenced the taste of a
wide-reading public until realists such as Theodore
Dreiser, whom she labeled a "literary
tomcat," rebelled against the prevailing romantics
and Victorian sentimentalists. Peattie
died on July 12, 1935, while visiting her grandchildren
in Wallingford, Vermont.

Throughout her life, Peattie penned hundreds
of stories, novels, children's books,
poems, essays, and book reviews. Torn between
the ideals of the self-sacrificing "True
Woman" of Victorian society and the emerging,
independent "New Woman" of the early
twentieth century, Peattie's life is representative
of the struggles of late-nineteenth-century
women authors to balance the demands of the
home with their careers as writers.

See also MEDIA: Omaha World-Herald.


Elia Peattie: An Uncommon Writer, An Uncommon Woman website.


Susanne K. George
University of Nebraska at Kearney




Falcone, Joan. The Bonds of Sisterhood in Chicago Women Writers: The Voice of Elia Wilkinson Peattie. Normal: Illinois
State University Press, 1992.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>