<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fol.035</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Play Party</field>
      <field name="author">Cunningham, Keith</field>
      <field name="text">

 




PLAY PARTY

The play party, a preplanned traditional dance
without instruments, was a recreational activity
of teenagers and young adults that was
once common across the Great Plains and the
entire United States. People attending play
parties played singing and action games such
as "musical chairs" and many other games in
volving male-female interactions, emphasizing
socialization and interpersonal relationships
rather than competition, while they
shared refreshments and conversation.

Early folklorists, including Ben Botkin,
Vance Randolf, and L. D. Ames, analyzed the
play party and concluded that it flourished in
Anglo-American culture on the western frontier
because of the repressive influence of the
puritan ethic, especially its opposition to musical
instruments. As early as 1949, folklorists
began to challenge this widely accepted description
by noting that the lack of instruments
at the play party might well have been
caused simply by a shortage of instruments.
Ben Botkin further maintains that the songs
of the play party came to the Great Plains with
the cattle drives through Texas and Oklahoma,
two states where the parties were very
popular. He also made the point that despite
the play party's Anglo-American origins, African
Americans and Native Americans participated
in them as well, particularly in the Southern
Great Plains. A 1972 article based on field
interviews conducted in the mid-1960s concluded
that the play party probably existed
across America, persisted after the passage of
the frontier, experienced revivals that often included
instruments, created a complex poetic,
and lived on as a substantial contribution to
American children's games and folk music.
Since that time, however, it seems that the tradition
of the play party has faded.


Keith Cunningham
Northern Arizona University




Ames, L. D. "The Missouri Play Party." Journal of American Folklore 24 (1911): 295-318. Cunningham, Keith. "Another
Look at the Play Party." Affword 2 (1972): 12-23.
Randolf, Vance. "The Ozark Play-Party." Journal of American Folklore 42 (1929): 201-32.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>