<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.077</field>
      <field name="titleMain">South Dakota</field>
      <field name="author">Burns, Robert V.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SOUTH DAKOTA

Government and politics of South Dakota are in
large measure a reflection of the state's past.
Home of the Arikaras, and later the Lakota-,
Nakota-, and Dakota-speaking Indians (Sioux),
the area that became South Dakota was penetrated
by French and Spanish explorers, traders,
and trappers before and after the Louisiana Purchase
of 1803. However, permanent European
American settlers did not begin to arrive in any
significant numbers until the establishment of
the Dakota Territory in 1861 and approval of the
Homestead Act in 1862. The two acts together
offered some promise of law and order and
economic livelihood through ownership and
productive use of the land for American-born,
German, Scandinavian, and Irish pioneers. Still,
the disruption of the Civil War, isolated Indian
outbreaks, and drought and other environmental
disasters kept the non-Indian population below
12,000 persons until the start of a population
spurt in 1878, following the discovery of
gold in the Black Hills and the completion of the
railroad to Sioux City, Iowa.

On November 2, 1889, the separate states of
North and South Dakota were proclaimed,
and the era of the Dakota Territory ended.
Rival factions fighting over whether the capital
city of the Dakota Territory should be located
in the southern territorial city of Yankton or
the northern territorial city of Bismarck had
much to do with the division of the Dakota
Territory into North and South Dakota. Pierre
was selected as the capital of South Dakota
upon statehood.

The Great Depression destroyed South Dakota's
agricultural economy and drove the
population down from a high of 697,000 in
1930 to 642,000 by 1940. South Dakota has not
experienced another economic or population
boom since the Depression, as evidenced by
the fact that the 1990 population of 724,000
was not far from the 1930 total. The population
according to the 2000 census only increased
to 755,000. Economically, the state
ranks near the bottom in nonfarm industrial
wages and continues to have one of our nation's
most rural economies. South Dakota's
per capita income ranks thirty-eighth among
the fifty states.

The beliefs of pioneer German, Scandinavian,
and Irish pioneers permeated the state
and continue to contribute to a strong moral
overtone in politics and governance that has
low tolerance for graft and corruption in public
affairs. The values and homeland experiences of German and Scandinavian pioneers
favored experimentation with public ownership
of economic enterprises and substantial
public sponsorship of education from the elementary
through postsecondary levels in all
corners of the state. The success of the Populist
Party in South Dakota in the 1890s and the
progressive movement that impacted both the
South Dakota Democratic and Republican
Parties in the early 1900s can be explained by
these immigrant values, as well as by farm
problems. Peter Norbeck championed the Republican
progressive era as governor from
1917 to 1921, and Tom Berry best represented
the Democratic progressive era as governor
from 1933 to 1937. Municipal-owned enterprises,
the South Dakota Cement Plant, more
than 170 public school districts, and six public
regional universities are contemporary examples
of the manifestation of those beliefs.

There is also a strong strain of fiscal conservatism
in South Dakota that emphasizes efficiency in government and limited public revenue
to support government. However, the
desire for many units of local government to
serve a sparse population spread out over a
large area contributes to many ine.ciencies.
Still, the emphasis on e.ciency is evident in
South Dakota's streamlined State Unified Judiciary,
the modern cabinet model of its executive
branch, and the part-time, nonprofessional
105-member legislature that meets only
seventy-five days during its two-year term.

Native Americans constitute approximately
8 percent of the state's population, including
those who reside on the nine reservations that
lie wholly or in part within South Dakota and
those who live in urban areas. Relations between
Indians and non-Indians continue to be
a source of conflict, most recently in the state's
attempt to disestablish the Yankton Reservation,
but otherwise, and despite the muchpublicized
East River (Missouri) and West
River differences and urban-rural disputes,
the relatively homogeneous character of the
population reduces political dispute in the
state. Recent exit polling conducted by Voter
News Service following the 1998 election revealed
that 40 percent of the South Dakota
voters identify themselves as conservatives, 50
percent as moderates, and only 10 percent as
liberals. Moderate conservatism is a suitable
ideological label for South Dakota.

The moderate conservatism of South Dakota
politics also leads to Republican Party
domination of state gubernatorial and legislative
elections. William Janklow's domination
of state politics as governor from 1979 to 1987
and congressman from 1995 to 2004 is an example
of Republican success in state elections.
Democrats have controlled the state senate for
only six years, the state house of representatives
for only two years, and the governorship
for only ten years since 1938. In fact, from 1889
to the present, Democrats have won only four
governorships (1926, 1932, 1958, and 1970).
Richard F. Kneip's three gubernatorial election
victories in 1970, 1972, and 1974 are the
most remembered by Democrats. Democrats
do fare much better in congressional races and
state constitutional office races when a vacancy
exists and an energetic, articulate Democrat
runs for election. Once elected, these
Democrats have been able to use the advantages
of the incumbency to be reelected. Former
U.S. senator and Democratic presidential
nominee George McGovern and U.S. Senate
minority (1995-2001 and again beginning
in 2003) and majority (2001-3) leader Tom
Daschle are obvious examples of Democratic
success stories. Former Republican U.S. representatives
and senators Karl Mundt, Francis
Case, and Larry Pressler and former Democratic
U.S. representative and current U.S.
senator Tim Johnson are other major political
figures in twentieth-century South Dakota
politics.

See also IMAGES AND ICONS: West River Country.


Robert V. Burns
South Dakota State University




Burns, Robert V., and Herbert E. Cheever. "South Dakota:
Conflict and Cooperation among Conservatives." In Interest
Group Politics in the Midwestern States, edited by Ronald
J. Hrebenar and Clive S. Thomas. Ames: Iowa State University
Press, 1993: 285–304. Farber, William O., Thomas C.
Geary, and Loren M. Carlson. Government of South Dakota.
Vermillion: Dakota Press, 1979. Schell, H. S. History of
South Dakota. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1975.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>