<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.arc.034</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Native American Contemporary Architecture</field>
      <field name="author">Krinsky, Carol Herselle</field>
      <field name="text">

 




NATIVE AMERICAN CONTEMPORARY ARCHITECTURE


Oglala Lakota College, Piya Wiconi Building, Pine Ridge Reservation, South Dakota. Hodne-Stageberg, architects


Before the 1960s and after the demise of traditional
architecture, little attention was paid
to cultural relevance when designing housing
and other structures on Indian reservations.
Assimilative pressures, financial exigencies,
and supposed efficiency led to reservation
housing that was built to resemble housing for
other groups, however different the cultural
contexts. The standardized buildings also ignored
differences in natural environments.
Reservation cultural centers and urban social
service centers, if built at all, were usually vernacular
structures with little indication of the
culture in question.

In the late 1960s and early 1970s Native
Americans and Canadian First Peoples began
to consider ways in which their cultural expressions
could help them overcome difficulties in their private and community lives.
Language revival, religious renewal, and other
recalled traditions were brought into service.
Economic development grants made it possible
to use the marketing of heritage to generate
employment on reservations in need of
jobs. Greater public awareness of past social
injustices and a new emphasis on group identity
rather than the "melting pot" ideology
created a favorable background for efforts to
make architecture, as the setting for life, more
relevant to the traditions of Native American
users. Not all Native American groups are
creating specifically Native American modern
architecture, but many are, and in increasing
numbers.

Cultural relevance can be suggested quickly
by adding ornament to a standard building,
for example. It can be achieved more substantially
by reproducing or paraphrasing building
types such as earth lodges and brush shelters
that predated the arrival of European
American settlers. Architects may use traditional
building materials and may align their
structures with the movements of the stars
and other natural forces. Douglas Cardinal, a
Canadian Métis, designs curvilinear forms for
both Indigenous and immigrant clients that
remind observers of the massive contours of
bison or eroded rocks. Some clients and architects
prefer to use symbolic forms, incorporating
numerological patterns or the shapes
of animals or medicine wheels, hoping that
the values inherent in the symbols can be
transferred to the users. Still others incorporate
traditional patterns of use into the building
plans, adding ceremonial rooms, central
gathering areas, and meditation chambers to
schools and hospitals. They may take into account
customary desires to observe events in
groups, standing, instead of in fixed rows
of seats. They may also accommodate Native
peoples' reticence when meeting strangers or
the need for storage of crafts and hunted food.
Some buildings have been designed by communal
processes rather than by standard European
American professional practices.

Some tribes restrict culturally appropriate
efforts to buildings erected for the direct benefit
of all tribal members, including schools,
clinics, tribal office buildings, cultural and religious
structures, and urban social and service
centers, while excluding casinos. Other
tribes include windows, trees, and other
plantings in casinos, suggesting links between
Native Americans and nature and implying
that a casino, the "new buffalo," benefits the
tribe and is therefore respectable.

In the past decade the United States Department
of Housing and Urban Development has
become more sensitive to the need for inexpensive
housing that also supports customary
patterns of Native American life. Multigenerational
families and issues of courtesy
and privacy are now taken into account. The
department has sponsored or encouraged
construction with natural materials and with
centralized and other unconventional plans
inspired by preference polls of prospective
residents. Not all tribes take advantage of the
department's initiatives, and the available
funds cannot meet the urgent need for lowincome
reservation housing units and the repair
of existing ones.

Museum buildings and tourist facilities are
especially likely to embody aspects of Native
American culture or tradition, because one
major aim is to celebrate the distinctiveness of
the historic cultures in question. Construction
of tribal museums has been stimulated
recently by the Native American Graves Protection
and Repatriation Act of 1990, which
provides for the return of artifacts and human
remains to descendants of their original owners.
There is no standard museum plan, so the
sponsors can build innovative forms or reproduce
older ones.

Ceremonial buildings, by contrast, must
adhere to certain physical patterns lest the ritual
action be hindered. Other religious buildings
too, such as the Native American Church
at Wounded Knee, South Dakota, are usually
traditional in form, though not always in materials.
Glass walls or steel beams, for instance,
may be used to enlarge such buildings, to
economize, or to improve safety.

One design problem is that many Plains
people traditionally lived in portable and temporary
structures that cannot easily be evoked
by fixed buildings made of permanent materials.
For this reason, Denby Deegan (Arikara-
Sioux) and Dennis Sun Rhodes (Arapaho)
have substituted symbolic forms such as
the medicine wheel at Deegan's Four Winds
School at the Fort Totten Reservation in North
Dakota or Sun Rhodes's prairie-side facade
(under Thomas Hodne's supervision) for the
Piya Wiconi Building at Oglala Lakota College
on the Pine Ridge Reservation in South Dakota.
Peter Kommers used the morning star to
generate a design for the Northern Cheyenne
Heritage Center in Lame Deer, Montana. A
design by Mark Hoistad for the Omaha interpretive
center in Macy, Nebraska, includes
totems evoking clan warriors and references to
the cosmos reflected in a camp circle as well as
a conical container for the sacred pole.

Problems connected to culturally appropriate
design include locating sensitive architects
(there are still few Native Americans in the
profession), securing funds, making decisions
by consensus, and devising forms that reflect
the cultures. Not all tribal members understand
the symbolism in proposed designs, but
most will respond favorably to buildings that
honor age-old customs and revere traditional
patterns of life.

See also CITIES AND TOWNS: 
Reservation Towns.


Carol Herselle Krinsky
New York University





American Indian Council of Architects and Engineers.
Our Home: A Design Guide for Indian Housing. Washington
DC: National Endowment for the Arts–Design Arts
Program, 1994. Krinsky, Carol Herselle. Contemporary Native American Architecture: Cultural Regeneration and Creativity. New York: Oxford University Press, 1996.
Landecker, Heidi. "Designing for American Indians." Architecture
82 (1993): 93–101.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>