<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pd.034</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Martison, Henry (1883-1981)</field>
      <field name="author">Terry L. Shoptaugh</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MARTISON, HENRY (1883-1981)

Born in Minneapolis, Minnesota, on March 6,
1883, Henry Martinson became one of the
most prominent figures in the North Dakota
labor movement. After trying to farm a homestead
in Minnesota, Martinson moved to
Minot, North Dakota, in 1907 and became a
painter. After reading several labor tracts, he
became a socialist and began to write for the
labor newspaper Iconoclast. He rose to become
its editor. He served as secretary of the state
Socialist Party until its collapse in 1918, then
recruited members for the Nonpartisan League.
He remained active in the labor movement and
in 1937 was appointed the deputy commissioner
of labor for North Dakota. He held the position
for twenty-eight years, fighting to improve labor
conditions.

After losing his state position in 1965, Martinson
remained active as secretary of the
Trades and Labor Assembly in Fargo, and he
began preserving the early history of labor in
the state. He wrote a brief History of North
Dakota Labor in 1970, expanding on this in
articles in North Dakota History and in contributions
to the film documentaries Prairie Fire
(1977) and Northern Lights (1978). He also
wrote and published poetry with regional
themes. In 1975 he was named poet laureate of
North Dakota. Martinson sought public offiqce
many times, always on a socialist platform. He
commented wryly late in life that while he
should have won these contests, he lacked the
votes. Active in the cause of labor to the last,
he died in Fargo on November 20, 1981.

See also FILM: Northern Lights.


Terry L. Shoptaugh
Moorhead State University




Martinson, Henry. Comes the Revolution: A Personal
Memoir of the Socialist Movement in North Dakota. Fargo:
n.p., 1969. Martinson, Henry. Papers. University of North
Dakota Library, Grand Forks ND. Martinson, Henry. Village
Commune Barefoot Boy. Fargo ND: n.p., 1976.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>