<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ag.066</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Sunflowers</field>
      <field name="author">Schild, James</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SUNFLOWERS

Native Americans domesticated the sunflower,
a native of the Great Plains. They used
the seed for food, extracted oil from them for
paints, and used bloom petals for dye. The
wild form, Helianthus annuus L., is still common
throughout the Great Plains in cultivated
fields, pastures, gardens, roadsides, and other
disturbed sites. The plants provide cover, and
the seeds furnish energy and protein for a
wide range of wildlife species, but they are
considered weeds because they compete with
cultivated crops.

Cultivated sunflowers are grown as either
an ornamental plant in the landscape or as
an agronomic crop used for its edible seed or
extractable oil. Ornamental sunflowers have
been developed to produce blooms of magenta,
white, and orange and to reach heights
of one to fifteen feet. They are commonly used
in the back of garden beds for height, color,
and texture, or as screens and alongside fences.
Kansas, the Sunflower State, has adopted it as
its state flower.

Agronomic sunflower production is divided
into two market classes, oil and confectionery.
Most of the acreage in the Great
Plains is planted with the oil type. The oil is
used primarily in cooking and baking. Confectionary
types are grown for the edible
roasted seed. Acreage in confectionary sunflowers
is contracted with processing companies
and is subject to strict guidelines. Confectionery
seeds not meeting the guidelines go
into birdseed markets. Recently, a third market
class has developed based on specialty
cooking oil markets.

Sunflowers in the Great Plains are grown
under both irrigation and dryland-farming
methods but mainly under dryland farming.
Yields under irrigation are typically double
those of dryland. Although sunflowers are
cultivated in significant amounts in western
Kansas and Nebraska, eastern Colorado, and
parts of the Texas Panhandle, U.S. production
is dominated by South Dakota and, especially,
North Dakota. In Canada, fully 90 percent
of national production comes from central
Manitoba.

Sunflowers work well in rotation with winter
wheat, as a wheat-fallow-sunflower rotation.
In this system two crops are harvested in
a three-year period. They are sown in May and
harvested in late September or October. Sunflowers
should be planted into a firm seedbed
when soil temperatures are above 50ºF. They
grow best on medium-textured soils, such
as loams. Planting is done with a row crop
planter equipped with special plates or with a
grain drill. Seeding rates are 14,000 to 21,000
plants per acre under dryland conditions and
20,000 to 25,000 plants per acre under irrigation.
Sunflowers are harvested with the use of
a combine with special extensions (sunflower
pans) in front of the cutter bar.

The sunflower, being native to the region, is
vulnerable to a wide array of insects and diseases
that can cause serious economic yield
reductions. Common insect pests are the sunflower
seed weevil, sunflower moth, grasshoppers,
and the sunflower head clipper weevil.
Common diseases are stalk and head rot, rust,
Phoma black stem, and downy mildew.

See also INDUSTRY: Oilseeds


James Schild
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Schild, Jim, Dave Baltensperger, Drew Lyon, Gary Hein,
and Eric Kerr. "Sunflower Production in Nebraska." G91–
1026, University of Nebraska, 1991. McMullen, Marcia P.
"Sunflower Production and Pest Management." Extension Bulletin 25. North Dakota State University, 1985.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>