<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.med.015</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Denver Post</field>
      <field name="author">Kodrich, Kris</field>
      <field name="text">

 




DENVER POST

An integral ingredient in Colorado lore and
pride, the Denver Post entered unfamiliar
peaceful territory in 2001, when the 108-year-old
daily newspaper ended a bitter feud with
the Rocky Mountain News and began working
with its former crosstown rival and new business
partner. A joint operating agreement effectively
ended one of the longest, most ruthless
newspaper wars in the country. In its early
years, the battle between the Post and the News
included name calling, sensationalism, editorial
crusades, and promotional stunts. In
the spirit of a Wild West duel, the fight even
spilled out into the streets near the state capitol
in 1907, when Post owner Frederick Bonfils
attacked and beat News owner Thomas
Patterson, who had called Bonfils a "blackmailer"
in a cartoon.

The Denver Post was founded in August
1892 as a weekly. Three years later, Harry Tammen
and Frederick Bonfils purchased the
then-daily Evening Post for $12,500 and began
an all-out war against its four rival dailies,
turning Denver's journalism scene into what
one historian called "a three-ring circus." (The
Post, in fact, even owned a circus in the early
1900s.) With its use of red headlines and lurid
stories, the Post was proud of its yellow journalism.
The other newspapers soon died or
were merged. In 1926 Scripps-Howard Newspapers
bought the News and merged it with
the Express, leaving only the morning News
and afternoon Post. Each newspaper tried
furiously to put the other out of business and
in the process lost millions of dollars. The
News, which had been founded in 1859 by
William Byers, almost perished around the
time of World War II. It then switched to a
tabloid format. But for forty years the Post,
declaring itself "The Voice of the Rocky Mountain
Empire," held the dominant position in
the market.

The Post was sold in 1980 to the Times Mirror
Company for $95 million and became a
morning newspaper the following year. But
its circulation declined until William Dean
Singleton's MediaNews Group bought it in
1987, also for $95 million. The circulation war
heated up, and both newspapers remained
neck and neck in their race to gain the most
subscribers. Nevertheless, when the joint operating
agreement was announced in May 2000,
the E. W. Scripps Company admitted the Rocky Mountain News had lost $123 million in the
past decade. The Post meanwhile reported
profits of $192 million in the same period. Both
papers had ridiculously low penny-a-day subscription
rates to attract readers, and both
claimed the largest circulation gains in the
country in 2000. The Post reported a daily circulation
of 420,033 and Sunday circulation of
586,485, while the News had a daily circulation
of 426,465 and Sunday circulation of 529,681.

The joint operating agreement, which
merged business operations such as advertising
and circulation under the Denver Newspaper
Agency, was approved by U.S. Attorney
General Janet Reno in January 2001 in record
time. Both companies agreed to split the
profits fifty-fifty, but the E. W. Scripps Company
and the News had to pay $60 million to
MediaNews and the Post to enter the arrangement.
The editorial departments of the two
newspapers remained independent, keeping
Denver one of the dwindling number of twonewspaper
towns (in 2001, fewer than twenty
remained in the United States). In 2001 the
two newspapers continued to publish competing
newspapers Monday through Friday,
but the News oversaw publication of a single
newspaper on Saturdays, and the Post oversaw
a single Sunday edition. The staffs of both
newspapers vowed to continue the journalistic
rivalry that has provided more than a century
of interesting and colorful reporting to the
people of Colorado. In 2000 both newspapers
won Pulitzer Prizes for their coverage of the
shootings at Columbine High School, the Post
for reporting and the News for photography.

See also ASIAN AMERICANS: Hosokawa, William / CITIES AND TOWNS: Denver, Colorado.


Kris Kodrich
Colorado State University




Anton, Mike. "Battle of Wits, Words Made History." Rocky Mountain News, May 12, 2000: A5. Hosokawa, Bill. Thunder in the Rockies: The Incredible Denver Post. New York:
William Morrow, 1976. Kreck, Dick. "A 108-Year-Old
Street Fight: Newspapers Share a Long, Colorful History."
Denver Post, May 12, 2000: A16.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>