<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.afam.029</field>
      <field name="titleMain">McDaniel, Hattie (1895-1952)</field>
      <field name="author">Jackson, Carlton</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MCDANIEL, HATTIE (1895-1952)


Hattie McDaniel, 1939


In the post–Civil War period, Kansas became
the new promised land for recently freed
slaves. This was John Brown country, and African
Americans believed they would be treated
more fairly here than in the South. They traveled
by railroads, rivers, and on foot. The Missouri,
Kansas, and Texas Railroad ran through
Emporia, with easy transfers to the Atchison,
Topeka, and Santa Fe Railroad for points west,
including Wichita and Fort Collins. Two of the
black settlers who came to Wichita, Kansas,
were Mr. and Mrs. Henry McDaniel. Henry,
originally from Virginia, and Susan (nee Holbrook),
from Tennessee, ultimately had a family
of thirteen children, most of whom died at
birth or shortly thereafter. Their youngest,
Hattie, was born on June 10, 1895. The family
moved to other places in the Great Plains: first
to Fort Collins, Colorado, and then to Denver,
the city Hattie McDaniel always considered to
be her hometown.

Hattie became an internationally known
movie star. She began her professional career
in a band; she was the first African American
woman to sing on the radio. She started appearing
in movies in the early 1930s. Her
greatest film achievement was her role as
Mammy in Gone with the Wind (1939), for
which she won an Academy Award for best
supporting actor. This was the first time an
African American had won an Oscar. Altogether,
she played in about 100 films, with
only half of them attributed. After Gone with the Wind, Hattie was much in demand, and she made at least one movie a year during the
1940s (except 1945), including In This Our Life
(1942) and Since You Went Away (1944).

In 1947 she began starring in Beulah, which
became the most popular radio program in
the United States. She was scheduled for a television
version of Beulah but fell ill with breast
cancer. Hattie McDaniel died on October 26,
1952, and was buried in Rosedale Cemetery in
Los Angeles.



Carlton Jackson
Western Kentucky University




Jackson, Carlton. Hattie: The Life of Hattie McDaniel. Lanham
MD: Madison Books, 1990.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>