<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pe.024</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Endangered Species</field>
      <field name="author">Genoways, Hugh H. Bolick, Margaret R.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ENDANGERED SPECIES

Endangered species of fauna and flora are
those species in imminent danger of becoming
extinct unless mitigating actions are taken,
particularly in saving critical habitats. The list
of endangered species in the Great Plains was
developed using the official list of the Division
of Endangered Species of the U.S. Fish and
Wildlife Service and provincial lists for Alberta,
Manitoba, and Saskatchewan prepared
by the World Wildlife Fund. The list is dominated
by vertebrate species, with six species of
mammals, thirteen birds, one amphibian, and
six fishes. The only invertebrate is an insect, the
American burying beetle, and there are ten
species and two varieties of vascular plants.

The most noticeable characteristic of this
list is how short it is. There are only thirty-nine endangered species in the entire Great
Plains. There are no reptiles on the list, and
the only amphibian on the list is the Houston
toad, which only marginally enters the Great
Plains in central Texas. If all the species that
only marginally enter the Great Plains are
eliminated, the list would be significantly reduced.
Among mammals, the gray bat and the
Indiana bat reach the Great Plains only in extreme
eastern Kansas, and the ocelot reaches
the Great Plains only in south Texas. The grizzly
bear and gray wolf may well be extirpated
from the Great Plains, although grizzly bears
may still be extant along the front of the Rocky
Mountains west of Calgary and gray wolves
may be found in the Parkland Belt at the
northern edge of the region in the Canadian
provinces.

Six species of birds on the list–burrowing
owl, greater prairie-chicken, loggerhead shrike,
mountain plover, piping plover, and sage
thrasher–appear in the Great Plains list only
because they are on one or more of the Canadian
provincial lists of endangered species. The
whooping crane and Eskimo curlew only migrate
through the Great Plains and do not
breed or reside for very long in the region. Five
of the six species of fishes (the pallid sturgeon
being the exception) are from restricted habitats
at the southwestern edge of the Great
Plains in Texas. Among the vascular plants,
there are four types of cacti that enter the Great
Plains in the desert grasslands along the southwestern
edge of the region.

The American burying beetle has an extensive
geographic range in the eastern United
States, but some of the largest and best-studied
populations are in Nebraska. The pallid sturgeon
is found in the Missouri River and its tributaries.
This leaves very few species on the list
that have a broad geographic range in the Great
Plains, including the black-footed ferret, swift
fox, American peregrine falcon, loggerhead
shrike, least tern, piping plover, western prairie
fringed orchid, small white lady's slipper orchid,
and Mead's milkweed.

Endangered status results from complex
changes in habitats. The black-footed ferret,
for example, has been taken to the brink of
extinction because of the decline of its main
food source, the black-tailed prairie dog,
which now occupies only 2 percent of its former
range. The presence of the burrowing owl
on the endangered lists of three Canadian
Prairie Provinces may be linked to the same
cause.

Why does an extensive phytogeographic region
such as the Great Plains have so few endangered
species? There are at least two answers to
this question. First, habitats in the Great Plains
cover extensive areas and the phytogeographic
regions flow almost imperceptibly from the
shortgrass prairie in the west through the midgrasses
to the tallgrass prairies of the east. Consequently,
there are few habitats in which species
can become isolated and vulnerable. Species
that do become endangered tend to occupy limited
geographic ranges or live in very specialized
ecological niches, such as caves, hot springs, or
gypsum outcrops. Second, the species that do
occur in the Great Plains have broad geographic
distributions and broad ecological resource
limits. Species with these characteristics are generally
not those that reach endangered status.


&gt;Endangered Fauna and FLora of the Great Plains (2001)

FAUNA


Mammals (7)
Canis lupusgray wolf
Felis pardalisocelot
Mustela nigripesblack-footed ferret
Myotis grisescensgray bat
Myotis sodalisIndiana bat
Ursus arctosgrizzly bear
Vulpes veloxswift fox



Birds (13)
Charadrius meloduspiping plover
Dedroica chrysopariagolden-cheeked warbler
Empidonax traillii extimussouthwestern willow flycatcher
Eupoda montanamountain plover
Falco peregrinus anatumAmerican peregrine falcon
Grus americanawhooping crane
Lanius ludovicianusloggerhead shrike
Numenius borealisEskimo curlew
Oreoscoptes montanussage thrasher
Speotyto cuniculariaburrowing owl
Sterna antillarumleast tern
Tympanuchus cupidogreater prairie-chicken
Vireo atricapellusblack-capped vireo



Amphibian (1)
Bufo houstonensisHouston toad



Fishes (6)
Cyprinodon bovinusLeon Springs pupfish
Cyprinodon elegansComanche Springs pupfish
Gambusia heterochirClear Creek gambusia
Gambusia nobilisPecos gambusia
Hybognathus amarusRio Grande silvery minnow
Scaphirhychus albuspallid sturgeon



Insect (1)
Nicrophorus americanusAmerican burying beetle




FLORA


Vascular Plans (11)
Asclepias meadiiMead's milkweed
Callirhoe scabriusculaTexas poppy-mallow
Coryphantha minimaNellie cory cactus
Coryphantha sneedii var. leeiLee pincushion cactus
Coryphantha sneedii var. sneediiSneed pincushion cactus
Cypripedium candidumsmall white lady's slipper orchid
Echinocereus fendleri var. kuenzleriKuenzler hedgehog cactus
Erigonum gypsophilumGypsum wild-buckwheat
Frankenia johnstoniiJohnston's frankenia
Penstemon haydeniiblowout penstemon
Platanthera praeclarawestern prairie fringed orchid




Hugh H. Genoways
University of Nebraska-Lincoln
Margaret R. Bolick
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Benedict, Russell A., Patricia W. Freeman, and Hugh H.
Genoways. "Prairie Legacies—Mammals." In Prairie Conservation,
edited by Fred B. Samson and Fritz L. Knopf.
Washington DC: Island Press, 1996: 149–68. Bragg, Thomas
B., and Allen A. Steuter. "Prairie Ecology–The Mixed
Prairie." In Prairie Conservation, edited by Fred B. Samson
and Fritz L. Knopf. Washington DC: Island Press, 1996, 53–
66. Knopf, Fritz L. "Prairie Legacies–Birds." In Prairie
Conservation, edited by Fred B. Samson and Fritz L. Knopf.
Washington DC: Island Press, 1996: 135–48.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>