<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.023</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Grove, Frederick Philip (1879-1948)</field>
      <field name="author">Divay, Gaby</field>
      <field name="text">

 




GROVE, FREDERICK PHILIP (1879-1948)

Frederick Philip Grove was born Felix Paul
Greve in Radomno, East Prussia, on February
14, 1879. As a young adult he earned a meager
living translating novels and publishing poetry
under various names. He incurred large
debts and was jailed in 1903 for defrauding a
fellow student. Greve left Germany in 1909,
covering his tracks with a fake suicide, and
spent three poorly documented years in the
United States. He surfaced in Manitoba in
September 1912 as Frederick Philip Grove and
started teaching first in the predominantly
German-speaking Mennonite regions south
of Winnipeg and then later in even more remote
rural districts. In August 1914 he married
Catherine Wiens (1892–1972), and a year later,
while in Virden, Manitoba, the couple had a
daughter, Phyllis May (1915–27). He graduated
with a bachelor of arts degree in French
and German from the University of Manitoba
in 1922, and he and his wife accepted teaching
assignments in Rapid City, Manitoba, where
they remained until 1929.

After Phyllis May Grove's tragic death during
an appendicitis operation in Minnedosa
in 1927, the Groves longed for different surroundings
and moved to Ontario. In October
1931 Grove settled on an estate in Simcoe, Ontario,
where he hoped to fulfill his dream of
living like a gentleman farmer. Despite unfavorable
conditions during the Depression
and World War II and increasingly poor
health, Grove managed to publish almost to
the end of his life.

His first novel, Settlers of the Marsh (1925),
a story of love, murder, and redemption on
the Manitoba Prairie (a thinly veiled account
of Grove's own affair in Kentucky in 1911
with Else Ploetz, later Baroness von Freytag-
Loringhoven), was critically praised but commercially
unsuccessful. It was followed in 1927
by the partly autobiographical and partly allegorical
novel A Search for America, the story of
a young European immigrant's settlement in
Canada, which earned him both critical acclaim
and some prosperity. His later novels,
essays, and partly fictional autobiography, In Search of Myself (1946), failed to achieve the
popular success of A Search for America.

Grove always felt underappreciated, although
he was the recipient of many honors
and his work was taught in schools and universities.
The Royal Society of Canada awarded
him the Lorne Pierce Medal for literary achievement
in 1934 and elected him a fellow in 1941,
and Grove obtained honorary doctorates from
the University of Manitoba and Mount Allison
University, New Brunswick, in 1944.

In May 1946 Grove suffered a debilitating
stroke that left him crippled. He died on August
19, 1948. Grove's complicated biography,
with its blending of fact and fiction in both his
life and his works, was not worked out until
1971, when Douglas O. Spettigue traced the
Canadian author back to the minor German
literary figure, Felix Paul Greve.


Gaby Divay
University of Manitoba




Frederick Philip Grove Papers, Archives and Special Collections,
University of Manitoba Libraries, Winnipeg.
Spettigue, Douglas O. FPG: The European Years. Ottawa:
Oberon Press, 1973.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>