<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.gen.022</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Mail-Order Brides</field>
      <field name="author">Checkoway, Julie</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MAIL-ORDER BRIDES

The term "mail-order bride," as it applies to a
marriage arranged via correspondence between
American men and women in the Great
Plains in the nineteenth century, is largely a
misnomer. Twentieth-century folklore has it
that a homesteader could peruse the Sears and
Roebuck or Montgomery Ward catalogs and
order a wife to be delivered to his dusty doorstep
just as easily as he could order a rifle,
stove, or stomach cure, but the truth is far
more interesting. Arranged long-distance
marriage existed in the Plains in a range of
communities, took a number of forms, and
grew out of a variety of social, economic, and
cultural phenomena, but never involved the
literal sale, purchase, or ownership of women,
as the term "mail-order bride" suggests.

Among Plains Indians, sight-unseen marriage
was frequently arranged with the help of
a middleman and could involve the payment
of a "bride price," intended to compensate the
woman's family for the impending loss of her
labor. But intercultural marriage was rare. In
1854, at a peace conference at Fort Laramie, a
prominent Cheyenne chief requested of the
U.S. Army the gift of 100 white women as
brides, but the army refused. Russian immigrants
brought with them the tradition of
koopla, whereby marriage brokers were paid a
fee to pair men with potential spouses from
the Old Country. Similarly, Chinese and Japanese
obtained "picture brides" from their
homelands, women whom they had come to
know only through grainy photographs.
According to historian Glenda Riley, Asian
women entered such relationships because of
parental pressure, to escape poverty, or to hide
a sullied reputation. It was customary for the
men to bear all costs, including the woman's
passage and any wedding expenses incurred.

During the peak years of overland migration,
hundreds of thousands of white women
traveled west, but the majority were already
married, and it was thought that "suitable"
single women did not go west alone. While
many cowboys eschewed marriage for perpetual
bachelorhood, homesteaders believed
that married men made better farmers.

From the 1830s until the turn of the twentieth
century, settlers pined for "that useful
and essential article of household furniture–a
wife." So severe was the shortage of single
white women of marriageable age in Nebraska,
recounts Mari Sandoz in Old Jules
(1935), her classic portrait of Plains homesteading,
"a man had to marry anything that
got off the train."

By 1865 it was estimated that there were as
many as 30,000 single women back east, a
number augmented by the Civil War widows.
The plentitude of bachelors in the Plains–and
hence the chance for greater social and economic
freedom away from home–beckoned
women. Newspapers from Nebraska to Kansas
and Wyoming (a state the Ladies Home Journal in 1899 declared a heaven for spinsters
and widows) began to serve as forums for
matchmaking, running regular "matrimonial
columns" of paid advertisements, frequently
with accompanying photographs, for example:
"A young lady residing in one of the small
towns in Central New York is desirous of
opening a correspondence with some young
man in the West, with a view to a matrimonial
engagement. . . . she is about 24 years of age,
possesses a good moral character . . . is tolerably
well-educated, and thoroughly versed in
the mysteries of housekeeping"; or more commonly,
"A Bachelor of 40, good appearance
and substantial means, wants a wife. She must
be under 30, amiable, and musical." Across the
Plains there arose a cottage industry of "heart
and hand" catalogs, folded double sheets and
broadsides devoted entirely to the matrimonial
prospects.

Letters were the only means of courtship
between potential mates separated by thousands
of miles. According to one bride, the
Pony Express "took about four weeks to go
from east to west," and letters "often came in
bundles." Language was a means of persuasion.
Illiterate men could dictate their letters
to typists who, for a fee, would doctor their
sentiments on Remington Standards. Dishonesty
was a risk. Men and women could easily
misrepresent their physical attributes, their
station, or finances. A homesteader who sent
his betrothed a train ticket might find that she
had turned it in for cash. A 1911 Wahpeton Times article tells of a New York girl for
whom, upon arrival in Buford, North Dakota,
"the spell was immediately broken" when she
saw the face of her intended.

The railroad also played an important role
in the western diaspora of single women. In
1882 businessman Fred Harvey sought young
rural women "of good character, attractive
and intelligent" as waitresses in whistlestop
cafés along the Santa Fe rail line. Harvey required
that they remain single for a year, live
in chaperoned dormitories, and entertain
callers in "courting parlors." By the turn of the
century, he had married off nearly 5,000 socalled
Harvey Girls.

By the early twenty-first century, matchmaking
not only in the Plains but across the
globe had become technically sophisticated.
More than 200 so-called mail-order bride
companies are available on the Internet, providing,
for a fee, pictures of, or arranged
meetings with, women from impoverished
third world countries. At the millennium, the
U.S. Immigration and Naturalization Service
estimated that there were 10,000 such marriages
per year, although specific numbers for
the Great Plains are not available. The contemporary
mail-order bride business, with its
roots in benign nineteenth-century customs,
has been called the "trafficking" and "enslavement"
of women, but no clear evidence exists
that the contemporary incarnation is different
from its antecedents, except that profits from
a single business can exceed $500,000 per year
and a greater economic, social, and linguistic
divide exists between the men and the women
they marry.


Julie Checkoway
University of Georgia




Luchetti, Cathy. "I Do!": Courtship, Love, and Marriage on the American Frontier: A Glimpse at America's Romantic Past through Photographs, Diaries, and Journals, 1715–1915.
New York: Crown Trade Paperbacks, 1996. Makabe, Tomoko.
Picture Brides: Japanese Women in Canada. Toronto:
University of Toronto Press, 1995. Riley, Glenda. Building and Breaking Families in the American West. Albuquerque:
University of New Mexico Press, 1996.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>