<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.war.011</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Civil War</field>
      <field name="author">Winkle, Kenneth J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CIVIL WAR

The Civil War, from 1861 to 1865, focused on
Northern efforts to prohibit slavery in western
territories, including the Great Plains. Most
battles occurred east of the Mississippi River.
Federal officials considered the western theater
secondary. They withdrew regular troops
from the Great Plains and recruited volunteers,
most of whom served in militias, to stay
in the West and fight Native Americans. Partisans
waged a guerrilla war, especially in eastern
Kansas and western Missouri. In the long
run, the war intensified federal authority in
the Plains, speeding the dispossession of Native
Americans, consolidating the reservation
system, and escalating the Plains Indian Wars.

In the Southern Plains, the war divided the
Five "Civilized" Tribes, who had been removed
from the Southeast to Indian Territory during
the 1830s. All five signed treaties with the Confederacy
but provided troops to both armies
and fought an internal civil war. In reprisal, the
Union recruited Native "home guards," invaded
Indian Territory, and seized one-half of
tribal lands to create reservations for Native
Americans removed from Kansas. On the
western Plains, Colorado militias warred
against Cheyennes and Arapahos, massacring
150 at Sand Creek. In the Northern Plains, the
United States forced the Sioux out of eastern
Dakota Territory after the Santee Sioux Uprising
of 1862 in Minnesota. Congressional initiatives,
including the Homestead Act, transcontinental
railroad land grants, the Land Grant
College Act (Morrill Act), and the Department
of Agriculture, encouraged rapid agricultural
settlement of the Plains. The Civil War intensified
westward expansion, dispossession, the
reservation system, and the military subjugation
of the Plains Indians.


Kenneth J. Winkle
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Josephy, Alvin M. The Civil War in the American West.
New York: Random House, 1991.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>