<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ag.026</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Draft Animals</field>
      <field name="author">Kauffman, Kyle D.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




DRAFT ANIMALS

Draft animals were the most important piece
of farm capital and motive power for transportation
in the Great Plains in the premechanization
period. These work animals–principally
horses, oxen, and mules–were used
initially to pull wagons to the Plains and then
to pull plows and other farm equipment once
the settlers arrived.

Many factors came into play when deciding
which type of draft animal to use for the westward
trek. Oxen were used most often because
they were relatively inexpensive to purchase
and could be easily sold or used for food at the
final destination, thus serving as a "store of
value" for the family's wealth. This final attribute
was important because an enormous
amount of a family's total wealth, in many
cases up to 50 percent, was tied up in the value
of the draft animals. If on the trek west a horse
broke its leg, an extremely large proportion of
a family's wealth would be lost. However, if an
ox broke its leg much of the value could be
salvaged in the form of meat, either for personal
consumption or through sale.

Once at the final destination oxen were then
used to plow the prairie sod. This task was one
where the ox had a distinct advantage over
both the horse and the mule because of its
greater strength and torque power. However,
after the sod had been turned settlers usually
sold or consumed their oxen. From that point
on they relied on either horses or mules for
their motive power. Both of these animals were
better suited to the daily farming chores of the
Great Plains, but because horses were less
costly than mules they were overwhelmingly
preferred on Plains family farms. The more
expensive and more resilient mule tended to
be used on farms where there were large numbers
of hired hands who had less incentive to
care for the owner's work stock.

Oxen were used predominately in the early
years of Plains settlement, comprising about
one-third of all draft animals in 1860. Their
numbers declined rapidly thereafter, and they
accounted for only about 3 percent of Plains
draft animals by 1890. Horses took their place,
increasing from 59 percent of all draft animals
in 1860 to 89 percent in 1890. The number of
mules remained consistently small, varying
from 7 to 10 percent between 1860 and 1890. In
the early years of the twentieth century, the
internal combustion engine signaled the end
of the draft animal era on the Plains, though
horses are still used extensively in modern-day
ranching.


Kyle D. Kauffman
Wellesley College




Kauffman, Kyle D. "Why Was the Mule Used in Southern
Agriculture? Empirical Evidence of Principal-Agent Solutions."
Explorations in Economic History 30 (1993): 336-51.
Kaufman, Kyle D., and Jonathan J. Liebowitz. "Draft Animals
on the United States Frontier." Overland Journal 15
(1997): 13-26.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>