<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.art.011</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Cameron, Evelyn (1868-1928)</field>
      <field name="author">Shirley, Gayle</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CAMERON, EVELYN (1868-1928)

An English aristocrat who settled in Montana
in 1889, Evelyn Cameron spent more than
three decades documenting the settlement of
the Great Plains with arresting photographs
and diaries. Cameron was born Evelyn Jephson
Flower on August 26, 1868, near London.
She married Scotsman Ewen Cameron, and
they honeymooned in 1889 in the United
States, hunting in the Great Plains. The Camerons
were smitten by the badlands and undulating
prairies of southeastern Montana. They
decided to stay and raise polo ponies for export
to Great Britain, eventually settling on a
spread near Terry, a rough-and-tumble town
that Evelyn described in her diary as "rather
lively of late, cowboys shooting here, there &amp;
everywhere."

Making a living was tough in the hardscrabble
hills. The Camerons' polo-pony enterprise
failed, and they lost the rest of their money
during the Panic of 1893. To make ends meet,
Evelyn sold vegetables and took in boarders.
She did all the domestic chores as well as
jobs considered "man's work": branding cattle,
breaking horses, chopping wood, and
cleaning stables. Ewen had persistent health
problems and was of little help. He spent most
his time observing and writing about wildlife.

Despite the hardships, Evelyn loved ranch
life. Photography, which she learned from one
of her boarders, became a passion. Soon she
was focusing her camera, a plate Kodet, on the
sweeping Plains and its inhabitants, including
wildlife. She had no telephoto lens, so she
had to sneak up on many of the wild animals
she photographed. Ewen used her photographs
to illustrate his articles. Evelyn's great
achievement, however, was to capture the immensity
of Montana's space in a small photographic
print. She would use a line of cattle
or a string of horses on the horizon to measure
the vastness, or she would let a small
scene in the foreground, like a corral, contrast
with the openness beyond. Evelyn also recorded
the hardness of pioneer life on this
twentieth-century frontier, the settlers' small
plain shacks dwarfed by the surrounding
landscape.

As the Camerons' financial situation worsened,
they relied increasingly on income from
Evelyn's photography. She charged a quarter
apiece for pictures or three dollars for a dozen.
Using a new Graflex camera with a nine-inch
Goerz lens, which she bought in 1905 for the
princely sum of $225.50, Evelyn worked on
commission for the Chicago, Milwaukee, St.
Paul and Pacific Railroad, making the harsh
land of eastern Montana look seductive to
homesteaders.

The Camerons moved to several different
ranches in search of more bountiful land.
They started their fourth and last ranch in
1907 within sight of the Yellowstone River.
Ewen's condition grew worse, despite Evelyn's
patient care, and he died of cancer in 1915.
Evelyn continued on alone, "as busy as a one-armed
man with hives," as she put it. Her fortitude,
resourcefulness, and independence
were widely admired. An Englishwoman who
met Evelyn described her as the "most respected,
most talked of" woman in Montana.
Evelyn became a U.S. citizen in 1918. Ten years
later, on the day after Christmas, she died of
heart failure.

Evelyn might have faded into the mists of
history had not Donna Lucey, a New York editor
who visited Montana in 1978 in search of
photographs for a book on pioneer women,
discovered a huge stash of Cameron's negatives
and diaries in the basement of a neighbor
of the photographer. Evelyn's photographs,
negatives, diaries, and other personal
effects were donated to the Montana Historical
Society in Helena. The Prairie County Museum
in Terry, Montana, also has a gallery of
Evelyn's photographs.


Gayle Shirley
Montana Secretary of State's Office




Lucey, Donna. Photographing Montana, 1894–1928: The Life and Work of Evelyn Cameron. New York: Alfred A.
Knopf, Inc., 1990. Raban, Jonathan. Bad Land: An American Romance. New York: Vintage Books, 1996. Shirley,
Gayle. "Evelyn Cameron, Frontier Photographer." In More Than Petticoats: Remarkable Montana Women. Helena MT:
Falcon Publishing, 1995: 74–83.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>