<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.art.035</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Howling Wolf (1849-1927)</field>
      <field name="author">Szabo, Joyce M.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




HOWLING WOLF (1849-1927)

"Howling Wolf, Southern Cheyenne, picture taken while imprisoned at Fort Marion in Florida, circa 1876"


Active in the Southern Plains wars, then incarcerated
at Fort Marion in St. Augustine, Florida,
between 1875 and 1878, Howling Wolf was
a Southern Cheyenne warrior and noted artist
who was born in 1849. He and his father, Eagle
Head, were undoubtedly at the Sand Creek
Massacre in 1864, and Howling Wolf subsequently
engaged in various battles, successfully
counting coup or completing his first
culturally recognized brave action on a war
party led by the Bowstring warrior Lame Bull
in May 1867. Howling Wolf became a secondary
Bowstring leader before being selected,
together with seventy-one other Southern
Plains warriors and chiefs, for exile to Fort
Marion, Florida.

Arguably the single most important Plains
artist who worked on paper during the late
nineteenth century, Howling Wolf is the only
artist known to have created drawings during
the prereservation era, on the reservation, and
at Fort Marion. Using available paper, often
lined accountants' ledgers, Plains men drew
images of their battles and horse raids in
much the same manner they did on hide
robes. Howling Wolf 's drawings from the first
half of the 1870s not only reflect Plains systems
of representation, with emphasis on the identity
of protagonists and important actions,
but also demonstrate experimental creativity
and great skill. At Fort Marion he, like many
of the younger prisoners, made drawings for
various reasons, including to sell to tourists.
His Florida drawings are generally nostalgic
views of home or records of the men's new
experiences rather than battle images. The few
drawings he made following his release in
mid-1878 demonstrate additional changes in
subject and style that may be attributed to
the vastly different life of the reservation and
to many of the unique experiences he had in
the East. Howling Wolf died in Oklahoma on
July 5, 1927.

See also WAR: Sand Creek Massacre.



Joyce M. Szabo
University of New Mexico




Petersen, Karen Daniels. Howling Wolf: A Cheyenne Warrior's Graphic Interpretation of His People. Palo Alto CA:
American West Publishing Company, 1968. Szabo, Joyce
M. Howling Wolf and the History of Ledger Art. Albuquerque:
University of New Mexico Press, 1994.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>