<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fol.041</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Siringo, Charles (1855-1928)</field>
      <field name="author">Ellis, Mark R.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SIRINGO, CHARLES (1855-1928)

Charles A. Siringo
        

Cowboy, Pinkerton detective, and western author,
Charles Angelo Siringo was the first authentic
cowboy autobiographer. His books
helped popularize the romantic image of the
American cowboy. Born on February 7, 1855,
in Matagorda County, Texas, Siringo was introduced
to the life of a cowboy at a young
age. By the age of eleven he was working on
Texas ranches, and during the 1870s he drove
cattle north on the Chisholm Trail to the
Kansas cattle towns of Abilene and Dodge
City. During the late 1870s he helped establish
the LX Ranch, a large cattle-ranching operation
in the Texas Panhandle. While in West
Texas, Siringo reportedly met Billy the Kid,
and later he led a posse in search of the outlaw.
In 1884 Siringo left the LX Ranch and moved to
Caldwell, Kansas, where he opened a general
merchandise store. With more time on his
hands, he began writing about his experiences
as a cowboy. Published in 1885, A Texas Cowboy; or, Fifteen Years on the Hurricane Deck of a Spanish Pony was the first cowboy autobiography
and a best-seller. Historian J. Frank Dobie
called it the most widely read book on cowboy
life. In 1886 Siringo went to work for the Pinkerton
Detective Agency. For the next twenty-two
years he lived an adventurous life, chasing
criminals across the West, infiltrating outlaw
gangs and labor unions, and serving as a
bodyguard for high-profile clients such as
"Big Bill" Haywood.

Siringo resigned from the Pinkerton Agency
in 1907, returned to his ranch near Santa Fe,
New Mexico, and began writing books about
his career as a western cowboy and detective. A Cowboy Detective (1912), his second book, was
originally titled "Pinkerton's Cowboy Detective."
Siringo dropped the word Pinkerton
from the title and throughout the text after the
agency blocked its publication through legal
action. Angered by the Pinkerton's legal attack,
Siringo lashed out at the company in his third
book, Two Evil Isms, Pinkertonism and Anarchism
(1915). The book was highly critical of
methods used by the Pinkertons, accusing the
agency of buying off policemen and politicians,
bribing juries, intimidating witnesses,
and murder. Once again the agency went to
court to block the sale and publication of the
book. Frustrated with such legal wrangling,
Siringo briefly retired from writing in 1916 and
took an assignment as a New Mexico Ranger.

Two years of chasing cattle rustlers and
horse thieves across the Southwest, however,
was enough to convince the aging Siringo to
return to writing. In 1919 he published A Lone Star Cowboy, and the following year his History of Billy the Kid appeared. In 1922 failing
health and financial problems forced Siringo
to leave his Santa Fe ranch and move to California,
where his children lived. Siringo eventually
landed in Hollywood, where he had several
small roles in Western movies and served
as a consultant for Western actor William S.
Hart. Siringo's final book, Riata and Spurs,
was published in 1927.

Siringo had a difficult married life. His
first wife died in 1889, leaving him with a
young daughter to raise. A second marriage in
1893 to Lillie Thomas ended in divorce after
three years (the couple had a son). Two other
marriages each lasted only a few months. Siringo
died on October 28, 1928, in Altadena,
California.



Mark R. Ellis
University of Nebraska at Kearney




Peavy, Charles D. Charles A. Siringo: A Texas Picaro. Austin:
Steck-Vaughn Co., 1967. Pingenot, Ben E. Siringo: The True Story of Charles A. Siringo. College Station: Texas
A&amp;M University Press, 1989.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>