<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ind.001</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Industry</field>
      <field name="author">Regehr, Ted D.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




INDUSTRY

On a lonely stretch of the Trans-Canada Highway,
in the heart of what local radio announcers
call the "Wheat Belt," a large sign advises
motorists that the next turn to the left will
take them to the Great Plains Industrial Drive.
The sign, on the flat, dusty, and seemingly
empty Saskatchewan landscape, looks like a
statement of hope rather than of economic
developments already realized.

In the popular mind, the Great Plains of
North America consists of vast open spaces inhabited
by cowboys, wheat farmers, oil-patch
wildcatters, and roughnecks. The huge smokebelching
factories and blast furnaces of industrial
America and the microchip valleys of
modern technology are located elsewhere. The
perception is that people living on the Plains
produce only raw materials, mainly agricultural,
that are shipped in a raw or semiprocessed
state to major industrial, manufacturing,
and processing centers outside the region.

There is, nonetheless, a great deal of industrial
activity in the region if one considers not
only the primary and secondary processing
and manufacturing, whereby raw materials
are converted into finished consumer products,
but also the extraction, handling, and
marketing of the region's resources and the
numerous regional service industries. Developments
in the various resource industries
are similar in some respects, but there are also
important differences, making it necessary to
examine them separately.


The Fur Trade

The first major natural resources extracted
and exported from large portions of the Canadian
Prairies and Northern Great Plains were
bison meat and the skins of fur-bearing animals.
Furs and later bison robes were exported
raw, with only basic processing being done by
the Native producers or traders. Final processing
and use of the resource occurred mainly
outside the Great Plains, while most of the
supplies were imported.

The fur and meat trade in the Great Plains
began in the 1780s, when the Prairie Provinces
became a scene of intense rivalry between the
Hudson's Bay and North West Companies. Between
1780 and 1821 both companies established
numerous trading posts along the North
and South Saskatchewan, Souris, Qu'Appelle,
and Red Rivers. These posts furnished sizable
amounts of beaver, muskrat, marten, and
other skins, but their main function was to
procure provisions, primarily pemmican, for
trading posts located to the north in the Canadian
boreal forests. The traders at these northern
posts used the pemmican during their long
trips to the primary fur distribution centers on
Hudson Bay and in Montreal.

This pattern changed dramatically in the
1820s and 1830s. In 1821 the two rival companies
united, making it possible for the reorganized
Hudson's Bay Company to establish a
monopoly over the fur trade in the Canadian
Prairies. The Hudson's Bay Company attempted
to take advantage of its monopoly by
reducing the number of trading posts and
placing the fur production on a more sustained
ecological basis. Unfortunately, the attempt
came too late. By the 1820s, beaver, the
primary hunted animal of the fur trade, had
already become virtually extinct in many areas
of the Canadian boreal forest and Prairie
Provinces. The final blow to the beaver trade
came in the 1830s, when European demand
for beaver abruptly collapsed due to a change
in fashion. To overcome these difficulties, the
Hudson's Bay Company shifted its production
in the Prairie Provinces from pelts to bison
robes, which were in great demand in the
rapidly growing industrial centers of eastern
North America.

The 1830s also saw an expansion of the
American fur trade onto the Northern Plains
south of the forty-ninth parallel. American
traders had attempted to advance onto the
Northern Plains ever since Lewis and Clark
had praised the region's rich animal resources,
but it was not until after the introduction of
steamboat transportation on the Missouri
River in the early 1830s that a large-scale U.S.
trade in the area became possible. The American
fur trade on the Northern Plains was controlled
from St. Louis, the artery of the trade
was the Missouri, and its main product was
bison robes. By the mid-1830s the American
Fur Company had established a virtual monopoly
over this trade, a position it and its
direct successors held until the 1860s. The
trade in furs was never a major economic activity
on the Southern Plains, where the rivers
did not provide reliable year-round navigation
and there were fewer animals with rich
and thick winter furs.



Ranching

After the demise of the fur trade, a series of
developments made possible the emergence of
new economic undertakings that exploited
other major resources of the region. The new
developments making such initiatives possible
included the earlier purchase by the United
States of the Louisiana Territory from France
in 1803, the drawing of the boundary between
British and U.S. territory at the forty-ninth
parallel in 1818, the acquisition through conquest
of northern New Spain by the United
States in 1848, the military resolution of the
quarrel between the northern and southern
states in 1865, the acquisition by Canada of
Rupert's Land in 1869, and the military or negotiated
subjugation of the Native peoples by
1890. These developments opened the Great
Plains to whatever new economic initiatives
U.S. and Canadian governments and businessmen
thought appropriate.

When they first came into possession of the
Plains neither Americans nor Canadians were
quite sure what to make of the vast, semiarid
lands. Many regarded the Plains, described by
Edwin James, chronicler of Stephen Long's
1820 expedition, as the "Great American Desert,"
as little more than an impediment to national
expansion and occupation of the more
promising lands on the Pacific slope of the
continent. Many early Plains settlers who tried
to apply farming methods common in more
humid areas failed or paid a very high price
for limited success. As a result, the settlement
frontier jumped across the Great Plains to the
Pacific slope and then worked its way onto the
Plains from both east and west. That was followed
after the mid-1890s by a massive northward
thrust from the United States, augmenting
the settlement of the Canadian prairies.

The Plains were very rich in one important
resource: there was an abundance of grass,
which had sustained enormous buffalo herds
for hundreds of years. The destruction of these
great herds by the 1880s made possible the raising
of domestic cattle on the great open ranges.
While there is some disagreement, most historians
trace the immediate origins of the Great
Plains range cattle industry to the Nueces River
valley of southern Texas. That valley is not part
of the Great Plains, but, beginning in the 1860s,
significant numbers of cattle were driven
northward from the Nueces Valley onto the
open plains. There the animals mingled with
livestock brought in by early settlers and with
some of the stock from former Spanish encomiendas,
or estates. As demand for meat increased
with the construction of numerous
military posts, the opening up of mining developments
in adjacent mountain regions, and
the construction of railroads, the size of the
herds also increased, and cattlemen extended
their operations northward.

Transcontinental railways across the Plains
also provided the means to take the cattle to
eastern markets, and major cattle drives to rail
towns became a much-celebrated aspect of regional
life. There was rapid expansion throughout
the 1860s and 1870s, and by 1885 some of the
ranchers from the Powder River territory of Wyoming
began to drive their cattle northward to
the summer grazing grounds of the Cypress
Hills and the foothills of the Canadian Rockies.

Open range ranching, in spite of the longevity
of cowboy myths in Hollywood movies
and at regional stampedes and rodeos, remained
the primary industry of most of the
Great Plains for only two or three decades.
And the popular image of the stalwart individualism
of the cowboy at one end of the
business should not obscure the fact that at
the other end ranching was dominated by a
few large companies. Closed range ranching,
of course, remains an important economic activity
in many parts of the region.

Natural and human-made disasters and a
growing demand that the cattle ranges be
opened to farmers broke up the large operations.
Serious overgrazing, combined with a
harsh winter in 1885–86, destroyed the herds
in Colorado, Kansas, and the Texas Panhandle,
with some operators reporting losses of
up to 85 percent of their animals. The next
winter a similar disaster overtook the ranchers
of Wyoming, Montana, and the Dakotas, accounting
in part for the driving of cattle from
Wyoming into the new ranching frontier of
southern Alberta and Saskatchewan. The industry
prospered there for a time, but all the
remaining large-scale operators in Canada
and adjacent U.S. territories faced economic
ruin in 1906–7, when an unusually severe winter
destroyed their herds.

On some southern ranges sheep replaced
the cattle herds, but all grazing operations
came under increasing pressure with the arrival
of the farmers. Homesteaders and settlers
were eager to transform the open cattle ranges
into an agricultural garden. In the United
States they began to encroach on the grazing
lands of the Plains as early as the 1860s, while
in Canada the major influx of homesteaders
only began in the mid-1890s.

In the contest between ranchers and farmers
the operations of the former were relegated
to the semiarid High Plains, hilly lands,
and other tracts of land not well suited to the
cultivation of cereal grains. Later disasters
would show that farmers broke vast tracts of
marginal land that had to be returned to grazing
during the disastrous droughts that periodically
aÄict the region. During the settlement
booms, however, farmers usually had
their way, sometimes causing terrible environmental
damage that could have been minimized
if land best suited for grazing had been
left to the ranchers.

Cattle ranching promoted some related
business undertakings, most notably meatpacking
plants. In the United States the beefpacking
industry in the late nineteenth century
was dominated by the "Big Five": Swift and
Company, Armour and Company, Wilson
Packing Company, Morris Packing Company,
and Cudahy Packing Company. Kansas City
and Fort Worth were the main centers of the
industry. In 1903 these companies joined to
form the National Packing Company, which
controlled the industry until it was dissolved in
1920. Thereafter, the location of packing plants
became more diffuse throughout the Great
Plains, but these five companies were still in
control. Most of the equipment and supplies
needed by ranchers and later by the packers
and processors were shipped in from outside.

In Canada ranchers supplied meat in the
1880s to railway construction contractors and
the federal Department of Indian Affairs. In
the late 1890s the Yukon gold rush absorbed
much of their produce, but surplus supplies
were sent east, either to Toronto or Chicago,
until Patrick Burns established meatpacking
plants first in Calgary and then in Edmonton
and Prince Albert. Burns, however, was more
interested in ranching than in meatpacking.
Together with fellow ranchers George Lane, A.
E. Cross, and Archie McLean, Burns was one
of the "Big Four" who created the worldfamous
Calgary Stampede in 1912. The Burns
meatpacking operations were sold in 1928 to
the Toronto-based Dominion Securities Corporation.
As is the case in the United States,
the meatpacking industry in Canada has become
more diverse, with strong local companies
such as Olympic Meats in Saskatoon
and Gainers in Edmonton competing with
U.S.-based international companies.

Cattle were significant as a revenue-producing
freight for the new railroads. Rail construction
and operating crews consumed much
of the meat produced by the ranchers, but the
railroads, the men who built and financed
them, and the construction supplies all came
from outside the region. Cattle ranchers, like
the fur traders before them and grain farmers
later, sold an essentially unprocessed staple
commodity in volatile outside markets over
which they had little or no control.

On the High Plains, in the interior valleys
of the mountain ranges, in the driest regions
of the open Plains, and rough country such
as the Flint Hills of Kansas, ranching has
remained an important industry. Taken together,
West Texas, Kansas, and Nebraska remain
the largest cattle-producing region in
the world, and the industry still exerts a powerful
economic and political influence in
many parts of the Plains. In most areas it has,
nevertheless, yielded its place of economic
primacy to cereal agriculture after only two or
at most three decades during which the large
cattle companies and their individualistic
hired cowboys dominated not only the economy
but also an entire way of life on the
Plains.



Precious Metals


The Ellison shaft group, cyanide plants, and the open cut at the Homestake Mine, Lead, South Dakota, between 1940 and 1950


Major mining developments on the Plains and
in adjacent territories coincided with the expansion
of ranching and provided important
markets for the beef raised by the ranchers.
The most important discoveries of precious
metals in the second half of the nineteenth
century, however, occurred in the Rocky
Mountains to the west of the Great Plains.
There was only one spectacular gold field on
the Plains, and that was in the Black Hills of
South Dakota, where old Indian legends of
important gold deposits were confirmed in
1874. A discovery that year near present-day
Custer and others at Deadwood Gulch and
Gold Run Gulch in 1876 brought in swarms of
prospectors. The Homestake Mine at Lead,
South Dakota, employed as many as 500 men
in the 1880s and remained until recently one
of the most productive gold mines in the
United States.

Placer mining was possible for individual
prospectors, but the extraction of gold imbedded
in rock required expensive crushing,
smelting, and refining equipment that only
wealthy individuals and large corporations
could afford. As a result, gold prospecting,
which at midcentury was undertaken by thousands
of independent amateurs, became the
preserve of large and wealthy corporations.
Independents, however, were never entirely
driven from the field.

The Great Plains yielded few other precious
metals. The great silver discoveries in the
mountain states and the contentious "Free Silver"
campaigns of Great Plains politicians
(which proposed the unlimited coinage of silver
in the 1890s) gave that metal a prominence
not matched by the actual silver-mining developments
in the region. Some rich zinc and
pumice deposits were discovered and developed
in Kansas, while several Plains states
have commercially viable bentonite and other
clay product developments. Traces of other
precious metals and minerals can be found in
a few places, most notably in the Black Hills.
The search for precious metals on the Plains
resulted in few major discoveries, but it was
important because it brought in many wouldbe
miners who took up farming when their
dreams of a new bonanza faded. Mining developments
in adjacent mountain states also
created lucrative markets for the agricultural
products of the Plains.



Agriculture

Agriculture became the dominant industry of
the American Great Plains and Canadian
Prairies during the second half of the nineteenth
century and the early decades of the
twentieth century. Farming operations had, of
course, been carried on in some parts of the
Plains for many years. The Indigenous people
of the Central Plains, for example, had developed
agriculture long before the coming of
European settlers. Early European American
settlers on the Plains often had difficulty making
a living from the soil. Coming from more
humid and temperate climates, they found it
difficult to cope with the drought and heat in
the South and with the short frost-free growing
season in the North. As a result, subsistence
agriculture was all but impossible for
non-Native people, while lack of suitable
products and the means to bring them to market
militated against the development of any
form of commercial agriculture, at least until
military, mining, and railroad developments
provided the needed markets and transportation
facilities.

The transcontinental railroads were critically
important in the development of Plains
agriculture. The Union Pacific Railroad, completed
in 1869, was the first to cross the region
from east to west. Its construction crews
provided lucrative but transitory markets for
local farm products. Once built, the railroads
provided the necessary means to carry
grain grown on the Plains to eastern markets.
Thanks to their land grants, the railroads also
had a direct interest in bringing in as many
new settlers as possible and to see them established
so that more traffic could be generated.
At least six additional transcontinental railroad
lines were built across the Prairies and
Plains between 1880 and 1915, while other major
railroads provided branch-line facilities
and important north-south linkages. The
railroads provided the necessary transportation
services that made possible the export of
wheat from the region and the importation of
the needed equipment and supplies that were
not produced within the region.

Major grain-handling, milling, and marketing
facilities were also needed. Most facilities
were established by large corporate interests
whose headquarters were located in large
urban centers outside the region such as Minneapolis,
Milwaukee, and Chicago. Winnipeg
was one Plains city that did provide more
grain-marketing, wholesaling, and other intermediate
economic services. Many of the
large grain handling, milling, and marketing
companies, whether located within or outside
the region, had close financial links with the
large and powerful railroad and financial corporations
and were consequently often regarded
as agents of outside interests.

Successful Plains farming depended on the
production and export of wheat. The fortunes
of Plains farmers fluctuated with the weather
and the price of wheat delivered at Liverpool
for distribution throughout the British Isles
and northern Europe. Exceptionally strong
demand during World War I gave wheat virtually
complete dominance of the Plains
farming economy. But the wartime bonanza
was followed by great market instability in the
1920s, when, twice, the average price of wheat
in one year fell to less than half that obtained
the previous year. This was followed in the
1930s by the disastrous collapse of world markets
when wheat prices fell to a 400-year low
and to one-tenth of the record high prices
paid in 1919.

These developments demonstrated that
what happened beyond the farm gate was
often far more important to the success and
prosperity of the farm than anything done on
the farm. Beyond the farm gate, large impersonal
corporations, institutions, and interest
groups manipulated market conditions in
their own interest, making a mockery of the
alleged independence of the individual producers
and of the myth that rewards were directly
linked to hard work and intelligent
management.

The market instability of the 1920s and the
disasters of the 1930s convinced many Plains
farmers that they had become too dependent
on a single export commodity and that they
should diversify their economy. In areas where
there was sufficient precipitation, most notably
in the Red River Valley of the North, sugar
beets, oilseeds, vegetables, animal fodder
crops, and truck farming supplemented or replaced
cereal grains. Irrigation, either through
stream diversions, particularly in southern Alberta,
or the pumping of groundwater in Kansas,
Nebraska, and Texas, made the planting of
vast areas of similar crops possible. Elsewhere,
poultry, dairy, hog and beef operations, including
large feedlot operations in which
range cattle were prepared for market, sprang
up. In Kansas and Nebraska the decline of
wheat as the primary agricultural export commodity
led to a revival of corn. Farther south
in Texas and New Mexico irrigated cotton,
which had gained a hold during World War I,
became very important.

A second aspect of regional economic diversification
involved the processing of agricultural
products grown on the Plains. Instead
of sending the produce out in its raw state,
efforts were made to do more of the processing
in the region. The big slaughterhouses in
Chicago and Toronto faced increased competition
as new packing plants were built in several
of the larger Plains urban centers, often
with provincial or state subsidies and tax concessions.
Similarly, numerous sugar refineries
were built to process locally grown sugar
beets. Oilseed-crushing plants and refineries
transformed the economies of several communities,
and vegetable dehydration plants,
particularly those specializing in the manufacture
of potato chips, became the economic
mainstay of Prairie and Plains towns such as
Winkler and Steinbach in Manitoba and Clark
in South Dakota. Specialized milling operations
facilitated processing of cereal products,
while new pelletizing technology created new
markets, most notably in Japan, for hay and
grass grown on the Plains. Discoveries of huge
potash deposits in Saskatchewan and New
Mexico provided a new staple export commodity
but also facilitated the establishment
of chemical fertilizer-manufacturing plants
near the mines.

Economic diversification also extended to
the establishment of numerous agricultural
service industries. Transportation was probably
the most important. The railroads provided
a wide array of economic services, although
their primacy as carriers of goods and
products being shipped into or out of the region
declined after World War II, when automotive
forms of transportation, supported by
massive government highway construction
programs, became more important.

Wholesalers and jobbers of all kinds provided
other vital economic services for people
living on the Plains. These services related to
both the assembling and handling of products
destined for export and the making of all the
arrangements necessary for the importation
and distribution of the great variety of supplies
needed but not produced by the region's
residents. Winnipeg was, for many years, the
most important regional wholesale, jobbing,
grain-handling, and marketing center in the
Prairie Provinces. Later, with the growth of
other resource industries, businesses in other
Prairie cities such as Calgary and Edmonton
provided similar services. In the United States,
by contrast, many of these intermediate economic
services were provided by businesses in
cities such as Denver, Dallas–Fort Worth,
Minneapolis, and Chicago, all marginal to or
outside of the Great Plains region. In that respect,
then, the Canadian Prairie economy became
more diversified than the adjoining
Plains economy in the United States.

Another important agriculturally related
industry is the manufacture and, more importantly,
the modification and adaptation of assembly
line–produced machines to meet local
requirements. A few so-called full-line farm
machinery manufacturers located their factories
on the Plains, providing an industrial base
for places such as Hesston, Kansas, Hastings,
Nebraska, and Yorkton, Saskatchewan. Most
of the big farm machinery factories remain
outside the region. Many mass-produced farm
machines, however, require modifications and
adaptations to make them suitable for local
conditions or specialty crops. As a result,
short-line agricultural implement manufacturers
have prospered on the Plains, as have
small factories manufacturing or adapting
other equipment and machinery needed by
Plains farmers.

The modification of large assembly line–
produced machines has also given a number
of Plains industries a profitable niche in the
automotive industry, where modifications of
trucks and vans for specialized farm, recreational,
and other domestic uses are needed.
The major factories are located elsewhere, but
shops adapting the products of those factories
to meet local requirements or to take advantage
of reliable and inexpensive regional labor
resources have created employment and revenue
for many Plains residents.

Agricultural diversification in its various
forms has helped to stabilize the Plains economy,
but the region remains heavily dependent
on the export of agricultural products,
and international marketing crises quickly engulf
not only the primary producers but also
those who serve those producers or process
what has been produced. Diversification into
nonagricultural products, most notably fossil
fuels, has, however, reduced regional economic
dependence on agriculture.



Fossil Fuels

The American Great Plains and the Canadian
Prairies have exceptionally rich deposits of
fossil fuels. The most abundant of these are the
coal deposits along the entire eastern slope of
the Rockies and in numerous large pockets
farther east. Most of the coal found on the
Plains, however, is lignite or brown wood coal
that has been fossilized to some extent but retains
its distinctly wooden texture. It is inferior
to anthracite and bituminous coal for heating
purposes. The fact that it expands when burning
rather than simply burning down evenly
increases the risk of explosions when such coal
is used to fire steam engines and locomotives.
Because of its high sulfur content, lignite coal
also produces more pollution than the superior
coals. As a result, although substantial income
has been derived from the lignite coal
mined on the Plains, the availability of superior
coals elsewhere has prevented the exploitation
of this resource to its full potential.
Some of the lignite deposits are su.ciently
close to the surface so that strip mining is possible,
but there are also deep-seam lignite coal
mines on the Plains. Some, most notably those
in the Black Hills of South Dakota, produce
a much higher quality coal than the stripmining
operations on the Missouri Escarpment.
The resource is abundant, but discoveries
of huge oil and natural gas deposits, particularly
at the northern and southern ends of
the Great Plains, have limited the exploitation
of the coal resources of the region.

The economies and cultures of Texas, Oklahoma,
Alberta, and parts of other Plains states
and provinces have been radically altered by
the discovery and extraction of these fossil
fuels. In the south, the Texas cities of Dallas
and Houston, both outside the Great Plains
region, have been major beneficiaries of oil
developments, but several cities on the Southern
Plains, most notably the Texas cities of
Midland and Odessa as well as Tulsa and Oklahoma
City, owe much of their growth to oil.
The boom in Midland and Odessa began in
the 1920s with numerous local oil discoveries.
Odessa became one of the world's largest inland
petrochemical centers during World War
II, while Midland became a major administrative
center, housing offices of more than 200
oil companies by the 1950s. Although both
cities have suffered from fluctuations in the oil
industry, they remain important oil centers.

In the north, Calgary and Edmonton, both
clearly on the Prairies, became major oil capitals
following discovery of the huge Leduc
field near Edmonton in 1947. There had, however,
been earlier natural gas and oil discoveries
near Calgary, which became the site of
major head or branch offices, while the major
cracking plants and oil-related petrochemical
industries (the blue-collar oil businesses) located
in Edmonton. Oil has become the single
most important source of revenue in Texas
and Alberta and has spawned numerous related
economic activities. Primary processing
is done within the region. Efforts have been
made to establish major petrochemical industries
in the region, but most are still located
elsewhere.



Potash

The discovery of massive deposits of potash,
used mainly in the manufacture of fertilizers,
has given several regions, most notably Saskatchewan
and New Mexico, an important
new source of economic activity. Technological
difficulties, mainly in the sinking, stabilizing,
and waterproofing of shafts through the
water-bearing layers of gravel that overlie the
potash deposits, created major difficulties in
the industry immediately after the discovery
of marketable quantities of the mineral. Then
the industry was beset for a time in the 1960s
and 1970s with serious problems of overcapacity
in which the less-efficient New Mexico
operators sought to protect domestic
American markets from Canadian competition.
These problems have, however, been
largely resolved as international demand for
fertilizer increased and trade barriers were
lowered or removed. Most of the product undergoes
only primary processing before being
exported. There are, however, some attempts
to promote further processing of potash and
many other staple products of the Plains locally.



Health-Care and Service Industries

The relative isolation of most rural people living
on the Plains and their remoteness from
many essential services resulted in much unnecessary
suffering. Nineteenth-century epidemics
that decimated the Native peoples
were attributable to diseases against which
these peoples could offer little resistance.
Later, among the homesteaders, lack of the
best available health care made women, children,
and the elderly particularly vulnerable,
and many an old rural cemetery bears mute
witness to these tragedies. It was, therefore,
not surprising that Plains and Prairie people
became particularly concerned about and demanded
improved hospital and medical care.

The desperate conditions during the Great
Depression of the 1930s gave a particularly
strong impetus to the development of government-
supported and -sponsored medical care
facilities. The first socialist government elected
anywhere in North America, the socialist Cooperative
Commonwealth Federation government,
which came to office in Saskatchewan in
1944, made improved medical care its most
important and controversial priority. It, like
other provincial and state governments, supported
community-based hospital and healthcare
organizations and facilities. Then in 1961
the Saskatchewan government introduced a
comprehensive government-sponsored medical-
care program. Socialized medicine became
a very controversial issue in Canada, but before
the end of the 1960s the federal government
had adopted the main features of the Saskatchewan
plan, giving Canada a medical-care system
that differed sharply from the one previously
in force everywhere in North America
and continuing in force in the United States.
But even where private medicine remained the
norm, governments took measures to assist
private and community initiatives and to provide
basic health-care services for those most
in need.

Health care, including medical research,
has become a major industry in all parts of
North America. In Canada it is the largest single
expenditure in the budgets of both provincial
and federal governments, while the privately
operated systems in the United States
absorb a higher percentage of the gross national
product than anywhere else in the
world.

Rapidly rising health-care costs associated
with new and expensive technological and
pharmaceutical developments and changing
demographics as young people in large numbers
migrate from rural to urban areas, together
with growing concern about deficit
spending by all levels of government, created a
health-care crisis in the 1990s. In the ensuing
debates tensions between sparsely settled parts
of the country and the larger urban centers
and between areas with an aging and declining
population and new growth centers have become
more intense. The health-care industry
will certainly continue to expand, but its
development on different sides of the forty-ninth
parallel and in lightly settled rural areas
compared to larger urban centers may well
follow divergent patterns.



Tourism

The Great Plains, with their windswept open
spaces, have not benefited as much from the
post.World War II development of tourism as
have the adjacent mountain states and other
regions of more conventional natural beauty.
The scenic Black Hills of South Dakota, the
rich heritage of Native peoples, the pioneer
past, the splendid desert and winter resort
country of the southwestern Plains, and the
hunting and fishing opportunities of the
northern parklands and other fish and game
habitats have, however, contributed greatly to
a growing Great Plains tourist industry. The
great mountain parks and resorts, while outside
the Plains region, attract millions of tourists
every year, many of whom cross the Plains.
And every major city, town, and village along
the major freeways in the United States and
the Trans-Canada and Yellowhead Highways
in Canada offers basic services to tired, hungry,
thirsty, or, alas, mechanically disabled
tourists. Most of the major tourist routes run
in an east-west direction, but Alberta has also
become a beneficiary of a strong northward
pull as tourists point their horseless carriages
and truckers their burdened tractor-trailers
toward the glories of that enormous wartime
construction project–the Alaska Highway.



Defense Industries

Military activity supported large sectors of the
Great Plains economy during the major U.S.–
Native American wars. The subjugation of the
Native peoples after about 1890 sharply reduced
the need for a strong military presence
during the mining and agricultural phase of
Great Plains development. During and after
World War II, however, the strategic location
of the region resulted once again in a sharply
increased military presence.

American military expenditures in the Pacific Northwest during the war created a major
economic boom for Edmonton, the jumping
off point for the North, and for major sectors
of the Canadian agricultural community,
which supplied much of the food required by
the incoming American construction workers.
The Canadian Prairies also became the primary
training ground for the Commonwealth
Air Training Program, under which thousands
of British, Canadian, Australian, and other
prospective military pilots obtained their basic
training on the relatively flat terrain. During
the cold war numerous electronic surveillance
and antiballistic missile sites were
built on the American Great Plains. Also in
the United States, major defense contractors,
often prompted by government incentives to
create jobs in economically depressed areas,
have established manufacturing, training, and
testing facilities in the region. Boeing, for example,
has established a major aircraft assembly
plant and related facilities in Wichita,
Kansas, serving both military and civilian
markets.

The end of the cold war and political pressures
to reduce government spending have resulted
in cutbacks in the defense industry that
have had a major impact on those towns and
cities such as Lubbock, Texas, and Rapid City,
South Dakota, with large military defense industries
or nearby major military bases.



New Footloose Industries

Defense industries were only the most notable
of many industries that were established wherever
they could take advantage of the largest
federal, state, provincial, or municipal grants,
tax concessions, the provision at public expense
of needed economic infrastructure, the
availability of cheap or better-qualified workers,
and lower costs of living. Modern computer
and electronic technology help industries
to overcome many of the disadvantages of
geographical remoteness. Omaha, Nebraska,
for example, is a major telemarketing center.

Efforts to attract major electronic industries,
often in close cooperation with local
university and research facilities, have given
those Plains cities with large university graduate
schools, research institutes, or research-oriented
military and transportation industries
an advantage over other centers lacking
these facilities. Thus, for example, Saskatoon,
Saskatchewan, has overtaken its rival, Regina,
thanks largely to its ability to attract new electronic
industries whose research interests are
enriched by work done at the well-established
University of Saskatchewan and the large "Innovation
Place" research park on the sprawling
university campus. In Calgary, Alberta, by
contrast, the presence of a rapidly increasing
number of company head offices has lured key
financial, legal, and taxation specialists to the
city, which in turn makes the city more attractive
to other industries contemplating a move.
The premier of Alberta also places much stock
in what he calls the "Alberta Advantage." Alberta
is the only Canadian province that does
not have a provincial sales tax. Neighboring
Saskatchewan, where taxes are higher but the
cost of living is lower, in part because of the
wider array of services offered by the government,
promotes those services in efforts to attract
"footloose" industries.

The North American Free Trade Agreement
has increased competition between Canadian
and American states and provinces trying to
attract new industries. The United States frequently
cites the higher tax burdens in Canada.
Canada promotes the public funding of
services such as health care, which saves employers
from having to provide expensive private
health-insurance plans for their employees.
Every state and province and most
municipalities are eager to attract footloose
industries, but the inducements differ widely.
Some, for example, stress the better quality of
life available because of low pollution levels;
others regard the absence of effective environmental
legislation as an advantage in the quest
for economic diversification and industrialization.



Conclusion

Industrial activity in the Great Plains is mainly
concentrated in the extraction, handling, partial
processing, and export of a few staple
products. Beginning with the fur trade in the
North and on through ranching, grain farming,
and gas, oil, and other natural resource
developments, the region is an economic hinterland
that sells its products in outside markets
and is dependent on outside suppliers for
most manufactured goods and centralized
services.

There have been numerous attempts to diversify
the regional economy and to establish a
broader industrial base, as the numerous sites
set aside for such economic development affirm.
Those efforts have been most successful
in the early processing of locally extracted natural
resources and in a variety of businesses
that, directly or indirectly, serve the needs
of the basic commodity producers. In recent
years, more broadly based service industries,
most notably tourism and in some places defense,
health-care, and electronics establishments,
have contributed to regional economic
diversification.

The region has a relatively small population.
The extractive and primary processing
industries, particularly farming, were at one
time quite labor-intensive, but mechanization
has reduced the number of people needed to
sustain the basic regional industries. Regions
with small populations tend to be politically
weak in countries where political representation
and influence are largely based on population.
This has fostered periodic populist political
protests and revolts against outside
influences, particularly against the "big interests,"
almost all of which have their power
bases outside the region. When William Jennings
Bryan made his famous "Cross of Gold"
speech in the difficult economic years of the
1890s and William Aberhart vehemently denounced
the "Fifty Big Shots" during the
worst years of the Great Depression, they provided
few clear definitions of exactly who
those big shots were. It was enough that they
and their listeners believed that there were
powerful interests that thwarted their region's
economic aspirations.

Such sentiments were reinforced by important
class differences. The major extractive industries
were dependent on the economic services
of large corporations, almost all of which
had their headquarters outside the region. Local
economic activities, however, were dominated
by large numbers of small independent
operators. Clashes between farmers and transcontinental
railroads, between grain handlers,
marketers, millers, and brewers, or between
the wildcatters and the major oil companies
were often a product of divergent interests of
regionally based small independent operators
and large international capitalist corporations.
Small independent operators rarely
think of themselves or their economic activities
in terms of "class," but in their hostility
and suspicion of big business, big government,
and big labor they manifest not only
regional but also class characteristics.

Industrial development and the attitudes
associated with it evolved rather differently in
Canada than in the United States. Seymour
Lipset, in his book Continental Divide, argues
that the values and institutions of the two
countries are, in some respects, fundamentally
different. Both countries, he argues, were
products of the American Revolution, but one
adopted classical liberal or Whig values and
institutions, while the other adhered to classical
conservative or Tory traditions. Other
writers have challenged such neat dichotomies,
but it must be admitted that government
involvement in industrial policies, particularly
in the promotion and ownership of
key economic infrastructures, is more pronounced
in Canada than in the United States.

Differences between the regional economies
north and south of the forty-ninth parallel
may also be due to the major urban centers
that were established within the region in
Canada but mainly beyond the peripheries of
the region in the United States. Both regions
depend on large eastern metropolitan centers
to meet their major financial, trade, transportation,
and manufacturing needs, but on the
American Plains the intermediate economic
services are provided by cities such as Minneapolis.
St. Paul, Chicago, Kansas City, St.
Louis, Dallas, Salt Lake City, and Denver, all of
which are on the periphery or outside of the
Great Plains. In Canada the areas surrounding
the Prairies are not suitable for urban development.
The Laurentian Shield to the east,
boreal forests and tundra to the north, the
Rocky Mountains to the west, and the international
boundary to the south made it necessary
to establish the major intermediate economic
urban centers, notably Winnipeg,
Edmonton, Calgary, Saskatoon, and Regina,
on the Prairies. Consequently, Canadian Prairie
cities have become an integral part of the
regional economy and identity, while American
cities on the periphery of the Plains seem
to be more closely integrated into and responsive
to national and international economies.

There are thus some differences between
the economies of the two regions. These differences
should not, however, obscure the important
structural similarities in the regional
economies. The most important of those similarities
is the reliance on the extraction, partial
processing, and export of natural resources
and a dependence on outside sources
for most manufactured goods. As a result, the
motorist who is diverted onto a Great Plains
Industrial Drive will find numerous farm and
automotive service, machinery, and agricultural
processing industries but few of the large
factories normally associated with industrialization.

See also AGRICULTURE: Cattle Ranching;
Wheat / IMAGES AND ICONS: Colony of the East / POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT: Bryan, William Jennings; Cooperative Commonwealth Federation / PROTEST AND DISSENT:
Aberhart, William / TRANSPORTATION: Railroads, United States; Railways, Canada / WAR:
British Commonwealth Air Training Plan.



Ted D. Regehr
University of Saskatchewan and University of Calgary




Eagle, John A. The Canadian Pacific Railway and the Development of Western Canada, 1896-1914. Montreal: Mc-
Gill-Queen's University Press, 1989. Fowke, V. C. The National Policy and the Wheat Economy. Toronto: University
of Toronto Press, 1957. Lipset, Seymour Martin. Continental Divide: The Values and Institutions of the United States and Canada. New York: Routledge, 1990. Nash,
Gerald D. The American West in the Twentieth Century.
Albuquerque: University of New Mexico Press, 1977. Perloff,
Harvey, et al. Regions, Resources, and Economic Growth. Baltimore MD: Johns Hopkins University Press,
1960. Richards, John, and Larry Pratt. Prairie Capitalism: Power and Influence in the New West. Toronto: McClelland
and Stewart Ltd., 1972. Robbins, William G. Colony and Empire: The Capitalist Transformation of the American West. Lawrence: University Press of Kansas, 1994.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>