<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.art.056</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Sandzén, Sven Birger (1871-1954)</field>
      <field name="author">Kahler, Bruce R.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SANDZÉN, SVEN BIRGER (1871-1954)

Sven Birger Sandzén was one of the premier
landscape painters of the Great Plains during
the first half of the twentieth century. Born
in Blidsberg, Sweden, on February 5, 1871,
Sandzén left in 1894 for the small town of
Lindsborg, Kansas, founded twenty-five years
earlier by Swedish Lutherans. There he intended
to teach at Bethany College and pursue
his art in the American West. As a student of
drawing and painting in Stockholm and Paris,
Sandzén valued the European tradition, but
he was also eager to experience the liberating
influence of the open prairies. Over the next
sixty years he produced an estimated 2,800 oil
paintings, 400 watercolors, 330 prints, and
5,600 sketches.

Best known are the landscapes, whose thick,
vigorously applied paint in vivid colors reveal
Sandzén's passionate response to nature. He
was thrilled by the clear atmosphere and "glorious
scenery" he found in Kansas, particularly
the Smoky Hill River valley, where he lived,
and farther west in Graham County. Sandzén
was deeply impressed by rolling hills and ravines,
and he cherished other commonplace
features of the region such as cottonwood
trees, sandstone boulders, and pioneer homes.
He was also a consummate professional with a
strong sense of civic responsibility. He taught
art at Bethany College for over half a century,
wrote articles for newspapers and magazines,
and helped establish numerous organizations
such as the Kansas Federation of Art and the
Prairie Print Makers. Sandzén's legacy in
Lindsborg lives on through the art department
at Bethany College, his recently restored house
and studio, and the Birger Sandzén Memorial
Gallery, opened in 1957. Sandzén died in
Lindsborg on June 22, 1954.



Bruce R. Kahler
Bethany College




Diffily, John. "Birger Sandzén 1871-1954: Through the
Corridor of Nature." Southwest Art 13 (1983): 42-51. Lindquist,
Emory. Birger Sandzén: An Illustrated Biography.
Lawrence: University Press of Kansas, 1993. Birger Sandzén
Papers, Birger Sandzén Memorial Gallery Archives,
Lindsborg KS.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>