<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.045</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Memoirs</field>
      <field name="author">Thacker, Robert</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MEMOIRS

From the very first incursion of European
Americans into the Great Plains (the Spaniard
Cabeza de Vaca, about 1534), the memoir has
been a preeminent form for the region's writers.
Confronted with an unfamiliar and treeless
landscape peopled by culturally alien Natives
and roamed over by buffalo (an animal he
was the first recorded European to have seen),
Cabeza de Vaca recalled his experiences and
then wrote and published his Relación (1542).
It began an autobiographical memoir tradition
that continues today through volumes
such as Ian Frazier's Great Plains (1989), William
Least Heat-Moon's PrairyErth (1991), and
Sharon Butala's The Perfection of the Morning
(1994). So pervasive is the form that two of the
region's best-known novels–Willa Cather's
My Ántonia (1918) and Sinclair Ross's As for Me and My House (1941)–adopt the illusion of
memoir for fictional purposes. This was nothing
new: when James Fenimore Cooper first
used the Great Plains as the fictional setting in
his The Prairie (1823), his primary source for
landscape description was Edwin James's
memoir of Major Stephen Long's 1819-20 expedition
to the Rocky Mountains.

Cabeza de Vaca's account was followed by
Pedro de Castañeda's Narrative (1896) of the
Coronado expedition of 1540–42, and, as the
Great Plains was visited by other explorers
through the early nineteenth century, numerous
other accounts were written and published.
On the Canadian Plains the British furtrading
companies sponsored the explorations
–and ultimately the writing–of early figures
such as Henry Kelsey (c. 1667–1724), Anthony
Henday (who journeyed through the Plains in
the mid-1700s), and David Thompson (1770–
1857); of these, Thompson's Narrative is the
best known and most detailed.

As the United States expanded onto the
Great Plains before the Civil War, several aesthetically
shaped memoirs appeared: Washington
Irving's account of his trip to the Indian
Territory, A Tour on the Prairies (1835),
was but one of three western books published
by America's then most acknowledged man of
letters. This period also saw Josiah Gregg's
Commerce of the Prairies (1844) and painter
George Catlin's Letters and Notes (1841). (Catlin's
Canadian counterpart, Paul Kane, published
Wanderings of an Artist in 1859.) The
single most significant memoir of the prewar
period, however, is Francis Parkman's The Oregon Trail (1849). The young historian was
determined, during his overland trip to the
Rockies in the summer of 1846, to see and
describe Native Americans, their landscapes,
and their ways of life.

After the war, as exploration gave way to
settlement, pioneering memoirs–both unpublished
and published–supplanted travelers'
accounts. Of these, Hamlin Garland's
various autobiographical memoirs–especially
A Son of the Middle Border (1917) and A Daughter of the Middle Border (1921)–are representative
and may be read within the contexts
of Garland's fiction. Like such fiction–
and that by Cather, Wallace Stegner, Wright
Morris, Robert Kroetsch, and others–the
Great Plains memoir since settlement has focused
on understanding the region–in Morris's
phrase–as "home place." Of these, three
autobiographical memoirs stand out particularly.
Frederick Philip Grove's Over Prairie Trails (1922) recounts the author's weekly
struggle traveling through the Manitoba bush
to reach his family, who lived some distance
away. The other two, Mari Sandoz's Love Song to the Plains (1961) and Wallace Stegner's Wolf Willow (1962), marry each author's personal
feelings for the Plains with a recounted history
of the region. Wolf Willow, the most sustained
and complex Great Plains autobiographical
memoir, is a profound articulation of the recalled
meanings made and found in a single
landscape, felt by a single person: "If I am
native to anything," Stegner sees at one point,
"I am native to this." And, because the Iowaborn
Stegner wrote about the Plains borderland
region of south Saskatchewan where he
grew up, Wolf Willow remains better regarded
in Canada than in the United States. It need
not be, for the book is a paradigm of the Great
Plains autobiographical memoir, capturing its
most frequently seen characteristics.


Robert Thacker
St. Lawrence University




Grove, Frederick Philip. Over Prairie Trails. Toronto: Mc-
Clelland and Stewart, 1991. Parkman, Francis. The Oregon Trail. 1849. Edited by E. N. Feltskog. Lincoln: University of
Nebraska Press, 1994. Stegner, Wallace. Wolf Willow: A History, a Story, and a Memory of the Last Plains Frontier.
New York: Viking Press, 1962.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>