<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.na.124</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Veterans</field>
      <field name="author">Holm, Tom</field>
      <field name="text">

 




VETERANS

Native Americans have served with the U.S.
armed forces as auxiliaries, allies, scouts, volunteers,
and conscripts since the Revolutionary
War, and Canadian First Peoples fought for
Great Britain as early as the mid–eighteenth
century. During both world wars, Native Americans
and First Peoples served (and died) in
numbers exceeding their relative populations
and distinguished themselves on battlefields
from the Argonne Forest to Iwo Jima. For example,
more than 4,000 First Peoples enlisted in
World War I, including every eligible man in
Saskatchewan's File Hill community. Native
North Americans' record of service extended to
the hills of Korea, the rain forests of Vietnam,
and the deserts of Saudi Arabia and Iraq during
the Gulf War of 1991 and 2003 invasion of Iraq.

The reasons why Native North Americans
enter the armed forces are many and complex.
They serve to earn a guaranteed wage or perhaps
because they believe that tribal treaty
agreements obligate them to volunteer for
military duty. For some, military service was
a natural step from militarized Indian boarding
schools. For Mike Mountain Horse of the
Blood Band of Alberta, and no doubt many
others, fighting in World War I was proof that
the warrior tradition had not been suppressed
by reservation life.

Whatever their reasons for entering the
military, those who returned had to face challenging
problems of readjustment to civilian
life. Information from the U.S. Department of
Veterans Affairs and statistical data from the
Bureau of the Census reveal that by 1980 there
were more than 159,000 Native Americans eligible
to receive veteran's benefits. The majority
of these veterans came from the Great
Plains. Many of them rarely used their hardearned
benefits because of the distances involved
in traveling from reservations to va
hospitals, benefits offices, and veterans' outreach
clinics.

Adjustment to civilian life was much more
than taking advantage of veteran's benefits,
however. Returning veterans had to readjust
emotionally, economically, and culturally. The
adjustment was eased for some by strong family
relationships and by ceremonies designed
to cleanse the veteran of his or her war-related
trauma or to honor their sacrifices. Economic
adjustment was difficult. Many veterans of the
wars of the twentieth century returned to
Plains communities, whether urban or reservation,
that were among the poorest in the
nation, with few opportunities for work. Still,
these veterans revived warrior societies, took
part in time-honored ceremonies related to
warfare, and founded all-Indian vfw and
American Legion posts.

Nowhere were these revivals, ceremonies,
and organizations as important as in the Great
Plains. The Kiowas, for example, rejuvenated
the Gourd Dance, a warriors' society ceremony, and the Black Leggings, another warrior
sodality, following World War II. Several
other societies were revived among the
Cheyennes, Lakotas, Arapahos, Pawnees, and
Osages. These revivals, initiated and kept alive
largely by veterans, have become an important
part of the post–World War II movement to
preserve tribal cultures.

Militarization quite often has an effect of
democratizing societies. It was clear, for example,
that after World Wars I and II Native
North American veterans were prepared to
demand their full rights of citizenship. Their
service in the military had, in effect, legitimized
their quest for better treatment. A
great number of veterans of World War II became
tribal officials almost immediately following
the conflict. One, a Lakota from the
Lower Brule Agency of South Dakota, was
elected tribal chairman at the young age of
nineteen. In 1945, all the tribal council members
of Crow Creek Reservation (also in South
Dakota) were veterans. By 1946 more than
one-third of all tribes in the United States had
veterans serving as tribal council members.
Numerous others went on to lead the fight
against the federal policy of termination and
later to promote self-determination and tribal
self-sufficiency.


Tom Holm
University of Arizona



Bernstein, Alison R. American Indians and World War II.
Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1991. Gaffen, Fred.
Forgotten Soldiers. Penticton, British Columbia: Theytus
Books Ltd., 1985. Holm, Tom. Strong Hearts, Wounded
Souls: Native American Veterans of the Vietnam War. Austin:
University of Texas Press, 1996.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>