<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.med.047</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Trillin, Calvin (b. 1935)</field>
      <field name="author">Wishart, David J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




TRILLIN, CALVIN (b. 1935)

Journalist, critic, and novelist Calvin Trillin
was born on December 5, 1935, and raised in a
middle-class neighborhood in Kansas City,
Missouri. Even now, after decades of living in
Greenwich Village in New York City, he still
regards Kansas City as his primary point of
reference.

Trillin's mother and father (so tenderly recollected
in his 1996 book, Messages from My Father) were second-generation grocers whose
own parents had immigrated from Lithuania
and the Ukraine, respectively. Trillin's father
brought him up to aspire to greater things than
being a grocer, yet it was his father's quiet messages
and example that had the greatest effect
on Trillin.

In 1953 Trillin did what his father had always
planned for him and left for Yale, where
he edited the Yale Daily News. He graduated in
1957. Trillin's first job was as a "floating" journalist
with Time, writing on subjects as diverse
as medicine and religion. In 1963 he
moved to the New Yorker as a staff writer, and
there he quickly established his reputation as a
first-rate essayist and journalist. In 1978 he
joined the Nation as a columnist; since 1990 he
has also contributed light but scathing political
verse to that magazine.

Trillin has written on a wide range of subjects
in his columns, novels, plays, and poems:
politics, murder, growing up, food, and American
places. Some of his pieces in the Great
Plains, for example, his essay on the small
town of Protection, Kansas, which for a brief
time flourished on the manufacture of concertina
barbed wire for use in Vietnam and
then reverted to its normal state of barely
"holding its own" (U.S. Journal, 1971), are
filled with Trillin's empathy for ordinary people.
Others, like his explication of the sordid
relationships behind brutal murders in Emporia,
Kansas, in 1983, undermining its "frontporch"
image (American Stories, 1991), are
prime examples of tough investigative reporting.
But Trillin is perhaps best known for his
political commentary, which generally employs
understated humor to lay bare hypocrisies
and injustices and to bring inflated egos
down to size. Like his father before him, Calvin
Trillin has always "given good weight."


David J. Wishart
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




"Trillin, Calvin (Marshall)." In Contemporary Authors,
New Revision series, 67: 349–53. Detroit: Gale Research.
1981. Trillin, Calvin. Messages from My Father. New York:
Farrar, Straus, and Giroux, 1996.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>