<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.afam.047</field>
      <field name="titleMain">York (ca. 1770s–ca. 1815/1832)</field>
      <field name="author">Buckley, Jay H.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




YORK (ca. 1770s–ca. 1815/1832)

Statue depicting York during the Lewis and Clark expedition

    
    
Born into slavery in the 1770s, York achieved
fame as the sole African American member of
the Lewis and Clark expedition. Virginia plantation
owner John Clark selected young York
as his son William's body servant, a position
of status and privilege, around 1784 when the
Clark family moved to the Falls of the Ohio
River (Louisville) where they established the
Mulberry Hill plantation. William Clark inherited
the Clark estate, including York, in
1799. Meanwhile, York married a slave on a
nearby plantation.

From 1804 to 1806 York joined his master as
a member of the Lewis and Clark expedition.
Presumably, York was the first African American
to travel through the Northern Plains. He
enjoyed the same freedoms as the other men,
which enabled him to make considerable contributions
to the success of the expedition.
York carried a rifle for hunting and protection,
went on reconnaissance missions, and
cast his vote on selecting a winter campsite
near the Pacific Ocean.

When the expedition returned, York did
not want to go back to the confines of slavery,
nor did he want to be separated from his family
in Kentucky by moving with Clark to St.
Louis. Clark considered selling York, but decided
to discipline him through beating, confinement,
hiring him out, and lending him to
his family in Kentucky. Sometime after 1815,
Clark either had a change of heart or simply
relented to York's demands for freedom. Clark
manumitted York, providing him with six
horses and a wagon to operate a freighting
service between Nashville, Tennessee, and
Richmond, Kentucky. York struggled to survive,
a free man in the slaveholding South,
before presumably dying of cholera in Tennessee
sometime between 1815 and 1832. The
Lewis and Clark Bicentennial Commission
plans to confer enlisted man status posthumously
on York.

See also EUROPEAN AMERICANS: Lewis and Clark.


Jay H. Buckley
Brigham Young University




Betts, Robert B. In Search of York: The Slave Who Went to
the Pacific with Lewis and Clark. Boulder: Colorado Associated
University Press, 1985.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>