<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ct.014</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Colorado Springs, Colorado</field>
      <field name="author">Jennings, Steven Larkin, Robert P.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




COLORADO SPRINGS, COLORADO


Colorado Springs, Colorado, between 1880 and 1910


Colorado Springs, although dominated by
and identified with Pikes Peak, is located on
the western edge of the Great Plains. The city
was founded in 1871 by a consortium of investors
led by William Jackson Palmer, a Civil
War hero and railroad builder. Since then Colorado
Springs has grown from a small tourist
town to a metropolitan area of over half a
million people.

Prior to the 1850s the area was traversed by
Native Americans, fur trappers, and Spanish
military expeditions. Zebulon Pike led the
first U.S. government exploration to this region in 1806. Later explorers included Stephen
Long in 1820 and Kit Carson and John Charles
Frémont in the 1840s. Anglo-American ranchers
and a few merchants settled in the area
after the discovery of gold to the north in 1859.

Colorado Springs was the crown jewel of
Palmer's north–south railroad, the Denver
and Rio Grande. He oversaw the development
of the initial 2,000-acre plat and championed
Colorado Springs as a well-planned community.
The town's treeless prairie environment
was modified through an active tree-planting
program that transformed the appearance of
its wide thoroughfares. An extensive irrigation
works was constructed, and large tracts of
land were donated for city parks and Colorado
College. As the city grew steadily in its
first two decades, Palmer invested in opulent
hotels and sanitariums.

In the early 1890s gold was discovered at
Cripple Creek to the west of Pikes Peak. Colorado
Springs was transformed, as it provided
transportation, milling services, and coal for
the gold mines. During a thirty-year mining
boom the city, home to fifty millionaires by
1900, became an internationally known health
resort, playground, and elite enclave. Philanthropic
millionaires such as Spencer Penrose
and Winfield Scott Stratton established institutions
that are still important today. Penrose,
for example, was instrumental in forming
the Cheyenne Mountain Zoo and the Fine
Arts Center, and Stratton founded the Myron
Stratton Home for orphaned children. New
elite neighborhoods such as the upscale suburb
of Broadmoor, which included a lavish
casino and recreation complex, were developed.
Tourism continued to be an important
part of the economy. The health benefits of
the climate were extolled for victims of tuberculosis,
leading to the development of several
tuberculosis sanitariums. During the Great
Depression the so-called lungers were an essential
part of the city's economic base.

World War II signaled another change in
the city's economy with the establishment of
Camp Carson, later Fort Carson, as an army
training center, bringing almost 30,000 soldiers
into the area. The military fueled much
of the economic and population growth for
the remainder of the twentieth century. Two
U.S. Air Force bases, the North American Air
Defense Command, and the United States Air
Force Academy became the engine of the regional
economy and infused millions of dollars
into the local economy annually. The
growth and development of the community
thus became linked to national policy and
government largesse. In addition, high-tech
firms associated with the military/industrial
complex were attracted to the city by billions
of Defense Department contract dollars. The
rapid population growth of the city has led
to the development of low-density suburbs,
spreading eastward on the Plains. Consequently,
infrastructure problems, especially
transportation issues, and associated air pollution
problems are important issues today.

See also EDUCATION: 
United States Air Force Academy.


Steven Jennings
Robert P. Larkin
University of Colorado at Colorado Springs




Huber, Thomas P. Colorado: The Place of Nature, the Nature of Place. Niwot: University Press of Colorado, 1993.
Sprague, Marshall. Newport in the Rockies: The Life and Good Times of Colorado Springs. Athens: Ohio University
Press/Swallow Press, 1987. Wyckoff, William. Creating Colorado: The Making of a Western American Landscape 1860-1940. New Haven CT: Yale University Press, 1999.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>