<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pd.047</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Riel, Louis (1844-1885)</field>
      <field name="author">Huel, James J. A.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




RIEL, LOUIS (1844-1885)


Hanging of Louis Riel in effigy, July 1885


Born on October 22 or 23, 1844, in Red River
Colony (Manitoba), Riel was educated in St.
Boniface before being sent by Bishop Alexandre
Taché to attend the Sulpician College in
Montreal in the hope that he would become a
priest. Riel was expelled from the college in
1865, after which he wrote poetry, read law,
and spent time in the United States.

Returning to Red River in July 1868, Riel
quickly became a leader in the agitation that
was developing over the annexation of the
Northwest. At his urging, the Métis established
a provisional government on December
8, 1869, to force Canada to negotiate the entry
of the Northwest into Confederation, and he
was elected president. In the events that followed,
a young Ontario Orangeman, Thomas
Scott, was executed by a Métis firing squad,
an act that enraged the people of Ontario. To
avoid reprisals, Riel fled Red River prior to the
arrival of a military expedition, and when the
Ontario provincial government posted a fivethousand-
dollar reward for the capture of
those involved in Scott's death, he sought refuge
in the United States.

Riel was elected three times as a member of
Parliament for the constituency of Provencher,
but he never took his seat and was subsequently
expelled from the House of Commons.
In December 1875 he underwent a deep
religious experience that convinced him he
had a special mission to fulfill. Riel's outward
manifestations of religiosity resulted in his
confinement in asylums in Quebec. Upon his
release in January 1878, Riel went to the United
States, where he lived with friends. He arrived
in Montana in 1880, married a Métis woman,
Marguerite Monet dit Bellehumeur, acquired
U.S. citizenship in 1883, and taught school at
Saint Peter's Mission on the Sun River.

On June 4, 1884, a delegation of Métis from
the territorial district of Saskatchewan arrived
at the mission to ask Riel to return with them
and champion the cause of the people of the
Northwest. Riel accepted the invitation and
returned to Saskatchewan, where he organized
a movement to pressure the Canadian
government to redress the grievances of the
Northwest.

In the meantime, Riel had religious revelations
and claimed to be a prophet with a mission
to create a new social order in the Canadian
Northwest. On March 19, 1885, Riel
formed a provisional government known as
the Exovedate, and hostilities broke out a few
days later. The Métis eventually were defeated
at the village of Batoche, and Riel surrendered
on May 15. He was taken to Regina, where he
was charged with high treason. He was tried,
found guilty, and sentenced to death, despite
the jury's recommendation for clemency. Riel
was hanged in Regina on November 16, 1885.

His execution contributed to a political revolution
in Quebec, strained dominion-provincial
relationships, and furthered the division between
French and English in Canada. The condemnation
of Riel's actions by the Catholic
clergy disappointed the Métis and contributed
to the emergence of a distinct Métis national
consciousness.

See also NATIVE AMERICANS: Métis / WAR: North-West Rebellion; Red River Resistance.


Raymond J. A. Huel
University of Lethbridge




Flanagan, Thomas. Louis "David" Riel: "Prophet of the
New World." Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 1996.
Stanley, G. F. G., ed. The Collected Writings of Louis Riel/
Les écrits complets de Louis Riel. Edmonton: University of
Alberta Press, 1985.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>