<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pe.018</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Chinooks</field>
      <field name="author">Palecki, Michael A.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CHINOOKS

Chinooks are warm and dry winds that descend
the eastern slopes of the Rocky Mountains
and dramatically affect the cold-season
weather of the western Great Plains. This term
is derived from the Chinook Indians of Oregon,
who originally identified a local unseasonably
warm wind as a "snow-eater." Air
from a mild source region over the Pacific
Ocean is further warmed by compression as it
descends downslope and replaces a shallow
cold air mass. Chinooks are capable of warming
regions near the mountains by 50ºF to
68\F in time periods as brief as fifteen minutes,
leading to a rapid melting of any snow
cover that is present. Some of the greatest extremes
of temperature change in U.S. history
have occurred in the Great Plains due to chinooks,
including a warming of 81ºF in two
minutes in Spearfish, South Dakota, on January
22, 1943.

While chinooks have beneficial temperature
effects during the cold season, they may
also be accompanied by severe windstorms,
especially east of the Front Range of the Colorado
Rockies. A stable layer in the atmosphere
just above the mountains and a low-pressure
trough to the east of the mountains cause
westerly winds to accelerate over the Front
Range. In this situation, a mountain wave can
develop that forces the air above the mountain
upward followed by a severe downslope acceleration.
In one instance, a chinook windstorm
struck Boulder, Colorado, on January 17, 1982,
with winds in excess of 200 feet per second,
resulting in more than $17 million in damage.

See also FOLKWAYS: Chinook Stories.


Michael A. Palecki
Midwestern Regional Climate Center




Barry, Roger G. Mountain Weather and Climate. New
York: Methuen &amp; Co., 1981. Geer, I. A., ed. Glossary of
Weather and Climate. Boston: American Meteorological
Society, 1996. Keen, R. A. Skywatch: The Western Weather
Guide. Golden, CO: Fulcrum, Inc., 1987.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>