<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ea.013</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Germans</field>
      <field name="author">Anderson, Timothy G.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




GERMANS


Burlington and Missouri Railroad lands advertisement in German


Immigrants from the German-speaking areas
of Europe (the various German states were
united politically only after 1871) comprise
one of the most significant elements of the
population of both the United States and Canada.
Germans began to arrive in North America
as early as the late seventeenth century,
but the overwhelming majority came between
1840 and 1890, "pushed" out of mainly northwestern
Germany because of the disruption of
traditional ways of life by the advent of factory
modes of production, and "pulled" to
North America (especially the American Midwest
and the Great Plains during this period)
by both real and perceived opportunities for
economic betterment, due in large part to the
prospects presented by landownership.

Immigrants from the German lands accounted
for at least six million of those who
entered the United States between 1830 and
World War II, or about one in five. During
most of this period Germans outnumbered
any other single immigrant ethnic group, and
their share of the total foreign-born in the
country was never less than one-quarter. The
influence of such a large immigration on
the ancestral makeup of the United States is
clearly reflected in late-twentieth-century census
data. In 1980, for example, just over 26
percent of those sampled in the long form
reported German ancestry, the largest of any
single ancestral group. The number of Germans
who immigrated to Canada is much
smaller, and they mainly arrived between 1870
and 1935, with an interruption during World
War I when Germans were barred from entry
into the country. Returns from the 1996 census
reveal that about 10 percent of the Canadian
population claims German ethnic origin,
but the numbers are much higher in the
Prairie Provinces of Saskatchewan, Alberta,
and Manitoba (29, 23, and 19 percent, respectively).
In these provinces most "German" immigrants,
however, were in fact German Russians
who emigrated primarily from southern
areas of the Ukraine.

One of the distinguishing characteristics
of the German population in North America
(especially in comparison to other immigrant
groups) has been its relative degree of cultural
diversity, reflected especially in the number of
Christian denominations to which Germans
belonged. In part this reflects patterns that had
developed over centuries in Germany, whose
population came to include nearly every variety
of Christianity–from Catholics, Lutherans,
and Reformed groups to more radical Anabaptist
pietistic movements such as Amish,
Mennonites, Schwenkfelders, and the Moravian
church. It is not surprising, then, that
nearly all of these denominations were represented
among the German immigrant population
in North America. The occupational profile
of German immigrants was diverse, but
like those of other western and northern
European immigrants, it was dominated by
farmers. This is largely because the process
of immigration tended to be highly selective,
drawing from specific socioeconomic strata.
Those Germans who immigrated to North
America during the nineteenth century, as revealed
in recent detailed studies of German
transatlantic migrations, mainly were smalltime
farmers, landless sharecroppers, and servants
(maids and farmhands), all of whom
had been negatively affected by the social
and economic disruptions that accompanied
industrialization. While many came over
in small family groups, a good number were
young, single men and women traveling
alone. A common theme underlying German
immigration to North America was chain migration,
the process by which generations of
immigrants moved between two locales over a
period of decades, creating transatlantic kinship
and place-specific linkages, which often
resulted in the transplantation of whole communities
overseas.

German immigrants participated in the settlement
and expansion of the agricultural
frontier in the American Great Plains from the
second half of the nineteenth century on, but
their numerical presence in this frontier was
not nearly as large as in the midwestern one
that had come before it. Their presence in the
region during the early phases of frontier expansion
immediately after the Civil War was
limited largely to the prairies of eastern Dakota
Territory, Nebraska, and Kansas, as well
as parts of central Texas. With the exception of
Volga Germans (who came from a physical
environment similar to the Plains), the semiarid
steppe grasslands in the western Great
Plains were much less attractive to most German
immigrant farmers, whether migrating
from the Midwest or Germany.

At the regional level, Germans, like other
population groups, were attracted to the lure
of free or cheap land in the Plains, largely as a
result of the Homestead Act of 1862. At the
local level, however, settlement patterns reflected
the influence of such processes as chain
migration and boosterism on the part of railroad
agents and land speculators. These processes
tended to direct migrants and immigrants
to specific locales and resulted in
literally hundreds of German ethnic "islands,"
particularly in the eastern Great Plains. Once a
community nucleus had been established by
the first generation of frontier settlers (often
centered around an ethnic church), subsequent
generations of migrants and immigrants,
attracted to a place inhabited by those
speaking a similar language or dialect, practicing
a specific faith, or even hailing from
the same region or village in Germany, filled
in surrounding areas until an ethnic community–
perhaps several townships or even
a county in size–had been established. By
1910 German-born immigrants comprised an
average of about 9 percent of the total population
in the Great Plains states, with North
Dakota registering the highest number (18 percent)
and Oklahoma and Texas the fewest
(5 percent).

The settlement of German immigrants in
the Hill Country of central Texas differed significantly
from that in the Midwest and elsewhere
in the Great Plains proper. There, immigrants
were participants in a short-lived
but nevertheless highly influential planned
settlement venture founded in 1842 in Hessen-
Nassau by members of the nobility as a private
joint-stock company. Among the goals of this
so-called Adelsverein (union of nobles) were
the alleviation of poverty and overpopulation
among German peasants on the nobles' lands
and the creation of new markets for goods by
transplanting Germans to south Texas. The
company obtained from the Republic of Mexico
a two-million-acre grant situated in the
Southern Plains of West Texas, and between
1844 and 1846 shipped about 10,000 Germans
from many areas of central and northern Germany
to Galveston through the port of Bremerhaven.
Unfortunately, the company went
bankrupt in 1846 before most had even arrived
in the proposed area of settlement.
Many became stranded along the way and settled
in present-day Mason, Gillespie, Kendall,
and Comal Counties at the edge of the Southern
Plains, where most became successful
farmers. Despite this setback, individuals and
families continued to migrate to the German
Hill Country on their own throughout the
1850s and 1860s. By 1857 it was estimated that
35,000 to 40,000 German-born immigrants
lived in Texas; in 1850 they comprised between
60 and 80 percent of the total population in
the four counties mentioned above.

In Canada, the Canadian Homestead Law
of 1872 (which offered 160 acres of land for
only $10) succeeded in attracting thousands
of German immigrant farmers to the Prairie
Provinces of Alberta, Saskatchewan, and
Manitoba. Overwhelmingly, these Germanic
immigrants were German Mennonites from
eastern Europe and southern Russia. In 1874
alone, 7,000 German Mennonites established
several villages near Winnipeg along the Red
River. But starting in the late 1880s thousands
of ethnic Germans who belonged to traditional
religions such as Lutheranism and Catholicism
began to immigrate to the Prairies
from parts of eastern and central Europe and
Russia, where they had been colonists in the
early and middle decades of the nineteenth
century. A smaller number came directly from
Germany or migrated from Ontario or the
United States. By 1911, 14 percent of Saskatchewan's
population was German-born. Interrupted
by World War I, immigration from
Germany resumed after the war, and between
1919 and 1935 more than 90,000 Germanspeaking
persons arrived in Canada. Fifty percent
again came from eastern Europe and Russia,
half came directly from Germany, and
seven of every ten were farmers. German settlement
processes in the Canadian Prairie
Provinces tended to mirror those in the American
Great Plains, with chain migration working
to direct immigrants to specific small ethnic
communities populated by those with
similar religious and linguistic backgrounds,
as well as similar geographic origins in Europe.

See also ARCHITECTURE: German Architecture.


Timothy G. Anderson
Ohio University




Conzen, Kathleen Neils. "Germans." In Harvard Encyclopedia of American Ethnic Groups, edited by Stephan
Thernstrom. Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1980:
405–25. Jordan, Terry G. German Seed in Texas Soil: Immigrant Farmers in Nineteenth-Century Texas. Austin: University
of Texas Press, 1966. McLaughlin, K. M. The Germans in Canada. Ottawa: Canadian Historical Association,
1985.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>