<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ha.025</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Lopez, Nancy (b. 1957)</field>
      <field name="author">Becker, Carl M.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




LOPEZ, NANCY (b. 1957)

Born on January 6, 1957, in Torrance, California,
Nancy Lopez, the daughter of Domingo
and Marina Lopez, was a "wunderkind" of
golf. When she was very young the family
moved to Roswell, New Mexico, where Domingo
ran an automobile repair shop. At age
eight, Nancy learned the game of golf, carrying
her mother's 4-wood and trailing her father
as he played the arid municipal course.
She developed an unorthodox swing, taking
her club back slowly with her arms stretched
high over her head, pausing, and then unleashing
a powerful downswing.

Lopez won a Peewee League girls' tournament
by 110 strokes at age nine (the prize was a
Barbie doll), the New Mexico Women's Amateur
Tournament at age twelve, and five national
and regional junior championships as a
teenager. As an amateur, she placed second
in the United States Women's Open in 1975
and, while attending the University of Tulsa,
captured five collegiate titles. She turned professional
in 1977 and in 1978 won nine tournaments,
a record-setting five in a row, including
the Ladies Professional Golf Association
Championship (LPGA). That year she was the
leading money-winner, won the Vare Trophy
for low scoring average, and was named both
Player of the Year and Rookie of the Year.

Ever flashing a telegenic smile, Lopez infused
women's golf with an expansive spirit;
she became, said one observer, "the whole
sport of women's golf." More women took up
the game, the media gave increasing coverage
to the lpga tour, and galleries at lpga events
multiplied. Heretofore eclipsed by women's
tennis, gymnastics, and running, women's
golf was soon equally popular.

Lopez won eight tour events in 1979 but
slipped comparatively from 1980 through
1984, claiming two to three titles each year.
Contributing factors were a failed marriage to
Tim Melton, her pregnancy following her
marriage to Ray Knight, a major league baseball
player, the flattening of her swing, and
stiffer competition on the tour. She returned
to preeminence in 1985 when she won five
tournaments. She attributed her renewed success
in part to Knight, who, understanding the
demands facing professional athletes, gave her
"peace of mind."

Lopez won thirteen championships from
1986 through 1993 despite cutting her play because
of two pregnancies and the demands of
domestic life. After 1993 her scoring average
remained nearly at old levels, but she did not
claim another title until 1997. She has been
named Player of the Year four times and was
elected to the lpga Hall of Fame in 1987.


Carl M. Becker
Wright State University




Deford, Frank. "Nancy with the Laughing Face." Sports Illustrated, July 10, 1978: 24. Lopez, Nancy, with Peter
Schwed. The Education of a Woman Golfer. New York:
Simon and Schuster, 1979.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>