<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.rel.004</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Baptists</field>
      <field name="author">Faught, II, Jerry L.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BAPTISTS

The people called Baptists represent the largest
Protestant religious tradition in the United
States, claiming more than 30 million members.
The Southern Baptist Convention, with
its 16 million members, is the largest Baptist
denomination, yet there are more than eighty
other groups in the United States that claim the
appellation "Baptist." Baptists span the theological
spectrum from Calvinist to Arminian,
from liberal to conservative to fundamentalist,
and are deeply divided into three major parties
–mainline ecumenical, conservative evangelical,
and separatist fundamental–a division
found within the Baptist family around the
world. There are approximately two million
Baptists in the Great Plains, mostly located in
Texas, Oklahoma, and Kansas. There are relatively
few Baptists in North and South Dakota,
Nebraska, Wyoming, Montana, and in the
Prairie Provinces. In these areas combined,
there are only about 140,000 total adherents.
Southern Baptists are by far the strongest Baptist
body in the Great Plains.

Despite the differences and disputes that
have created numerous variations, the Baptist
faith remains an experiential religion, embracing
differing ethical, cultural, and doctrinal
tenets. Nevertheless, throughout their history
Baptists have held to a number of basic
principles that set them apart from other
Christian bodies. Commonly held Baptist beliefs
and doctrines include the following:
scripture alone as the authoritative guide for
life; church membership that is predicated
upon personal faith in Jesus Christ as Savior
and Lord; baptism by immersion and the
Lord's Supper as the ordinances of the church;
the autonomy of each local congregation in its
decision making; congregational church government;
the priesthood of the believer, or
soul competency; and religious liberty and the
separation of church and state.

Baptists have long been concerned with
bringing persons to faith in Jesus Christ. Thus,
Baptists have tended to view the Central and
Northern Plains region as a mission field.
Originally, Baptists targeted Native Americans
and new settlers. In 1842 the Baptist missionary
Isaac McCoy founded the American Indian
Mission Association in Kansas. Through
this organization, which later came under the
direction of the Southern Baptist Convention,
McCoy worked to see that Native Americans
were fairly treated by the government. He also
defined areas for relocation of tribes, laid
out plans for cities, and initiated Baptist missions
at Topeka and Paaoli. The first Baptist
work in Nebraska was begun in 1833 by Moses
Merrill and his wife when the two started a
mission with the Otoe-Missouria Indians.
Merrill published a book of hymns in the
Otoe language.

The first known Baptists in Dakota Territory,
Elijah Terry and James Tanner, arrived in 1852
at Walhalla, in present-day North Dakota, and
started a church there. By 1881 the American
Baptist Home Mission Society had appointed
forty-eight missionaries in the territory who
helped establish various foreign-language
churches among Swedes, Germans, Norwegians,
and Danes. In Canada, Alexander Mc-Donald was sent by Ontario Baptists to Manitoba
in 1873; in 1875 he formed a church of
seven members. By 1900 there were ninety-nine
churches and 170 preaching stations in the
Prairie Provinces. As Native Americans and
ethnic populations became Americanized and
adopted English for their worship services, the
bilingual witness of Baptists in the Plains diminished.
Church planting continues as the
most significant feature of Baptist mission activity
in the Great Plains.

Theological education has also been an important
facet of Baptist endeavors in the Great
Plains. The Central Baptist Theological Seminary
in Kansas City, founded in 1901, was
jointly sponsored by Southern and Northern
(American) Baptist Conventions until Southern
Baptists started their own school across
the river in Missouri in 1957. The library at
Central contains materials related to Native
American missions, including a collection related
to Charles Journeycake, a Baptist minister
who was the last chief of the Delawares.
The North American Baptist Conference, the
only surviving transborder union of Baptists
and the leading Baptist group in the Prairie
Provinces, supports the North American Baptist
Seminary in Sioux Falls, South Dakota,
and Edmonton Baptist Seminary in Edmonton,
Alberta. The Canadian Convention of
Southern Baptists, which was organized in
1985, supports the Canadian Southern Baptist
Theological Seminary at Cochrane, Alberta.
While neither a college nor seminary, the Baptist
Leadership Training School, located in
Calgary, has provided basic training in biblical
and pastoral studies since 1949. The institute
operates under the auspices of the Baptist
Union of Western Canada.


Jerry L. Faught II
Oklahoma Baptist University




McBeth, H. Leon. The Baptist Heritage. Nashville: Broadman
Press, 1987. Thompson, Margaret E. The Baptist Story
in Western Canada. Calgary: Baptist Union of Western
Canada, 1974. Wardin, Albert W., ed. Baptists around the
World. Nashville: Broadman and Holman, 1995.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>