<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.war.005</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Army Topographical Engineers</field>
      <field name="author">Bartlett, Richard A.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ARMY TOPOGRAPHICAL ENGINEERS

From 1777 until 1863 the U.S. Army included
topographical engineers among its professional
officers. The Topographical Bureau was
created as a branch of the U.S. Army Corps
of Engineers on March 3, 1813, and remained
only a small, elite corps until John James
Abert, a graduate of the U.S. Military Academy
at West Point, became its head in 1829. A
good politician as well as a capable engineer,
Abert succeeded in getting the Corps of Topographical
Engineers created in 1838 as an
independent army unit separate from the U.S.
Army Corps of Engineers. Sixty-four of its
seventy-two officers were West Point men, testifying
to the unit's superior composition. The
Corps was in tune with the romantic interests
of a nation curious about the West and anxious
to unlock its secrets. On March 3, 1863,
Congress eliminated the independent unit,
merging it with the Army Engineers.

One of the first six officers in the Corps,
Stephen H. Long explored along the Platte,
Arkansas, and Red Rivers in 1820. His report
included a map of the Great Plains across
which was printed "Great American Desert."
Although the description is today considered
incorrect, Long (and Zebulon Pike before
him), in their pessimistic forecasts denying
the possibility of white settlement, were accurate
within the context of the technology of
the times.

The Topographical Engineers were most
active in the 1840s and 1850s. John C. Frémont's
western explorations began in 1841
with an exploration of the North Platte River.
Frémont's next exploration took him west to
present Pueblo, Colorado, then north to the
Laramie Plains. Returning east a year later,
Frémont took a southerly route via Bent's Fort
on the Arkansas River. His report of this twoyear
reconnaissance (1843–44) greatly expanded
the geographical knowledge of the
Great Plains.

The Southern Plains gained o.cial attention
with the advent of the Mexican War. Topographical
engineers accompanied military
forays searching out the best routes, and sites
for artesian wells, into New Mexico and California.
They were involved in the running
of the Mexican American boundary. Colonel
Abert's son, Lt. James W. Abert, Bvt. Maj. William
Hemsley Emory, Lt. Amiel Weeks Whipple,
and Lt. James H. Simpson are but four of
the many topographical engineers whose activities
added further to the knowledge of the
Southern Plains.

The Topographical Engineers were deeply
involved in the Pacific Railroad surveys. These
explorations resulted in the delineation of several
viable railroad routes ranging, in the
north, from St. Paul, Minnesota, to Oregon
and, in the south, from Vicksburg to southern
California. Lt. Gov. K. Warren, Capt. John W.
Gunnison, Isaac I. Stevens, and Capt. William
F. Raynolds were among the engineers who
traversed the Great Plains in the course of
their assignments. In addition, scientists accompanied
the surveys, and their Pacific Railroad
reports–magnificent volumes gathering
dust in research libraries–offer a proud beginning
to the scientific investigation of the
entire West, including the Great Plains.


Richard A. Bartlett
Florida State University




Goetzmann, William H. Army Exploration of the American
West, 1803–1863. New Haven CT: Yale University Press,
1959. Goetzmann, William H. Exploration and Empire.
New York: Alfred A. Knopf, Inc. 1966. Wallace, Edward S.
The Great Reconnaissance. Boston: Little, Brown and Co.,
1955.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>