<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.gen.005</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Binnie-Clark, Georgina (1871-1947)</field>
      <field name="author">Marshall, David B.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BINNIE-CLARK, GEORGINA (1871-1947)

Born at Dorset, England, on April 25, 1871,
Georgina Binnie-Clark was a journalist who
migrated to Canada in 1905 to become an independent
farmer. She "caused quite a sensation"
in the Qu'Appelle Valley of southern
Saskatchewan when she purchased a quartersection
of land. Single, independent women
farmers were rare in Prairie Canada. Under
the Dominion Lands Act (1872), single women
were not eligible for a quarter-section, or
160 acres, of free land from the Canadian
government.

Binnie-Clark was determined to make her
farm a successful revenue-producing investment
so that she could secure independence.
Without the free quarter-section of land, she
was under a greater financial burden than her
male counterparts. She had access to some
funds enabling her to buy necessary supplies,
farm equipment, and livestock, and to hire
labor. But purchasing land forced her to deplete
limited capital and make added interest
payments. The harvests were also disappointing,
making it increasingly difficult for her to
cover mortgage costs or meet growing debt
payments.

As a result of her experiences selling grain
in the open market, Binnie-Clark became a
sharp critic of the privately controlled grain-marketing
system. In her view the Prairie
farmer was not su.ciently aided by either
financial institutions or governments. She advocated
government regulation of grain marketing
and the establishment of governmentrun
experimental farms to serve as models for
Prairie women farmers. After the 1908 harvest,
Binnie-Clark traveled to Ottawa to discuss
with government officials the "claim of
women to her fair share" in the homestead
lands of Canada. She helped to spearhead the
movement calling for application of the freeland
provisions of the Dominion Lands Act to
women, which converged with other Prairie
women's crusades for equal rights before the
law, such as the campaigns for dower rights
and the voting franchise. The homestead land
provision was not open to single women until
the lands of the Canadian Prairie were transferred
from the federal government to provincial
jurisdiction in 1930.

Binnie-Clark wrote many articles in British
and American publications. Their purpose
was to outline the difficulties and provide
guidance through her experiences to other
women contemplating owning and operating
a farm on the prairie. She was a keen observer
of Saskatchewan rural life. Her autobiographical
books contain rich detail about the social
life and customs, material culture, local politics,
and the rhythm of daily farm life. She
died in England on April 22, 1947.


David B. Marshall
University of Calgary




Binnie-Clark, Georgina. A Summer on the Canadian Prairie. London: Edward Arnold, 1910. Binnie-Clark,
Georgina. Wheat and Women. Toronto: Bell and Cockburn,
1914. Jackel, Susan. A Flannel Shirt and Liberty: British Emigrant Gentlewomen in the Canadian North West, 1880–1914. Vancouver: University of British Columbia
Press, 1982.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>