<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.mus.036</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Opera</field>
      <field name="author">Lobaugh, H. Bruce</field>
      <field name="text">

 




OPERA

Professional opera in the Great Plains began
in Denver in 1864 and then was established in
Lawrence, Kansas (1869), Kansas City, Missouri
(1870), Lincoln, Nebraska (1874), Fort
Worth, Texas (1878), Winnipeg, Manitoba
(1883), Huron, South Dakota (1885), and various
other locations. Its appearance depended
on the size and wealth of the community
and/or the arrival of the railroad. It was presented
largely by touring companies such as
those of the soprano Emma Abbott and the
British impresario James Mapleson. Amateur
local companies specialized in lighter opera.
The abbreviated productions of the day often
had extraneous selections introduced into
them. In the United States, each Plains state
boasted as many as several hundred "opera
houses," but operas were performed only in a
small percentage of them.

Interest in opera had waned by the turn of
the century, but the Metropolitan Opera of
New York appeared at Omaha in 1890 and intermittently
elsewhere in the region through
the 1950s. After the turn of the century, touring
companies declined when economic conditions
worked against their success. Local societies
continued, one even presenting Verdi's
Aïda in Regina in 1932.

Through the 1940s, 1950s, and 1960s, permanent
professional opera companies with
seasons of varying lengths were formed. They
now number nearly ten, the more impressive
ones being those in Edmonton, Tulsa, and
Kansas City, Missouri. More than twenty universities
and colleges of the region maintain
opera activities of varying degrees of intensity
and scope. Outstanding singers from the region
include John Vickers, tenor, and Samuel
Ramey, bass. The career of White Eagle, tenor,
a Native American from South Dakota who
trained in opera in San Francisco, never fully
developed before his illness and death in 1995.
Opera plots set in the region include Charles
Wakefield Cadman's Shanewis (1918) as well as
Libby Larsen's Eric Hermannson's Soul (1998),
based on a story by Willa Cather.


H. Bruce Lobaugh
Omaha, Nebraska




Jennings, Harlan F. "Grand Opera in Kansas in the 1880's."
Ph.D. diss., University of Cincinnati, 1978. Musical America International Directory of the Performing Arts. Hightstown
NJ: Primedia Information, 1999. Sadie, Stanley, ed.
The New Grove Dictionary of Opera. London: Macmillan
Publishing Company, 1992.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>