<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.art.001</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Art</field>
      <field name="author">Kinsey, Joni L.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ART

The Great Plains has presented artists with
challenges unlike those of most other regions.
Lacking most of the visual elements that traditionally
comprise landscape compositions,
the terrain can seem utterly devoid of artistic
subject matter, empty and uninspiring to
those who attempt to portray it. Over time,
however, artists have adapted to the Plains'
unique qualities in a wide array of interesting
ways that offer insights into both the development
of the area and its peoples and the special
character of the place. And even though
the region's sheer extent and distance from
major urban centers have tended to relegate it
to the "margins" of the art world, artists in
the Plains have established a strong visual
heritage through other subjects and activities
in addition to depictions of their region's
landscape. The Great Plains is not often acknowledged
for its aesthetic achievements,
but it has a rich artistic history that deserves to
be better known.



Cultural Contrasts

In visual art Native American and European
American traditions differ to such a degree
that their imagery is usually considered separately;
they are often studied as two distinct
specialties within the history of art. These cultures,
with very different notions of vision,
representation, and relationships to the land,
have responded to the world in accordance
with their own conceptions of space and humanity's
place within it. As a result, each
group's art remained distinctive until the mid.
twentieth century, when cross-cultural influences
began to have an impact. The differences
between Native American and European
American art, which range from the most basic
qualities to the most profound aesthetic
issues, compromise comparisons and even
parallel discussions of the two to the point of
diminishing the integrity of both. This is nowhere
more apparent than in the art of the
Great Plains, where contrasts of media, styles,
subject matter, and perceptions of the land
between the two groups have been as polarized
as their different value systems and traditional
ways of life.

Native Plains art differs from European
American imagery stylistically, functionally,
and conceptually. Pictorially representing ideas
and visual surroundings symbolically rather
than literally or "naturalistically," Native Plains
artists did not attempt to directly transcribe
the appearance of the natural world according
to European techniques of perspective. Also,
rather than being separated from everyday life
within a hierarchical value system that creates
artificial divisions between "high art" and
lesser manifestations, art within Native traditions
is an integral part of societal activities,
both everyday and ceremonial.

Plains imagery that precedes European
American contact is today extremely rare; it
was usually constructed of organic materials
that were not long lasting, and it was not considered
"art" in the same sense that Europeans
conceive the term. Until almost this century it
has not been considered unique or valuable
apart from its ritualistic or functional purpose
and was therefore not usually preserved and
revered as collectible. Some European and
American visitors to the Plains region in the
mid-nineteenth century did collect artifacts
of various sorts from the Native peoples, and
while those activities were not comprehensive
and systematic and were often for anthropological
or scientific purposes rather than aesthetic
ones, their efforts, and those since,
have preserved a variety of objects that give a
glimpse into traditional Native Plains imagery.

Prehistoric rock carvings and paintings
(petroglyphs and pictographs) also survive at
several sites throughout the Plains, although
very little is known of their origins or intended
meanings. Efforts to understand the
significance of art in Native American life have
been hampered by this scarcity of early examples
as well as by the extreme differences between
European and Native American concepts
of art.

 Although the impulse behind
creating imagery in Native cultures was undeniably
inspired by aesthetic considerations
as well as by symbolic and ritualistic ones (all
of which offer important insights into their
artistic and cultural significance), the later exhibition
of these objects as museum collections
of "art" tends to remove them from their
original contexts and can misleadingly present
them within a foreign value system, one that
considers art primarily something to be looked
at rather than integrated into the daily activities
of its creators, as was originally intended.
At the same time, however, the art
establishment and its marketplace have provided
Native American artists an important
outlet for the expression and preservation
of their traditions, a means by which their
cultures can be understood and appreciated
by a wider public. They have also provided
some economic support, which in turn encourages
additional creative activities within
tribal communities.

Native American and European American
art forms do share at least one important
characteristic that is integral to understanding
the significance of their creation in the Plains
region. Both cultures created and used imagery,
although not exclusively in either case, to
document life experiences. Because the land
was fundamental to these experiences in both
cultures, this basic relationship can serve as a
touchstone for discussions of their art.



Plains Indian Art
Plains Indians were, of course, not a single
group but rather many different peoples who
inhabited an extremely large territory. While
they shared certain aspects of lifestyle, their
visual imagery, its specific symbolism, meaning,
and function, differed according to tribe
and even according to individual artists in
the same tribe. Comprehensive accountings of
their histories and the myriad of specific objects
would require separate studies for each
group, but because they all had their origin
in the same region some generalities can be
made.

Plains bison hunters moved frequently;
therefore, other than the petroglyphs and pictographs
inscribed on rocky outcroppings,
their art was necessarily portable. Ranging
from large painted tipis to small personal
amulets, decorated clothing, shields, and even
horses and their own bodies, their media and
the uses to which they were put were extremely
varied, a diversity demonstrating the richness
of the people's creative responses to their environments
and experiences.

A large percentage of Native Plains imagery
was and continues to be symbolic of sacred
events, rituals, and natural forces, which
could include everything from celestial bodies
and weather to the indigenous animals of the
region. Often stylized into schematic diagrams,
the representation of these objects
on personal and communal belongings could,
it was believed, transfer the power of these
forces into forms that would protect the user
from harm, bring health and prosperity, or
appease the spirits and encourage them to
provide for the people of the tribe. Some symbols
and their subjects or referents were ubiquitous
and relatively unchanging; others were
highly specialized and designed for specific
events or for particular uses. 

Common among Plains cultures are animal symbols 
and representations, especially those of the bison,
which was a staple of their lives. Other animals
were also revered for their special traits. Birds,
for example, with their ability to fly, were considered
especially powerful since they could
transcend the earth, and among these the eagle,
with its majestic size and fierceness, was
held in highest regard. These and other animals
were not only represented in Plains art in
pictures and sculptured e.gies; their hides
and feathers were used as functional and ritual
objects as well. In this way the elements of the
natural world were both depicted in and part
of Native American art, a duality that was
both symbolic and practical in the people's
creative expression of life and their understanding
of it.

Unlike the European tradition, in which the
making of art is mainly reserved for a gifted
few, most if not all members of Plains tribes
incorporated art into their daily tasks and became
artists in various ways. Women adorned
clothing, baskets, and other personal and
household objects with symbolic and decorative
imagery made from quills, beads, hides,
and other elements that were often dyed with
natural colors, and men were responsible for a
wide variety of artistic creations, from objects
for ritualistic purposes and the painting of
their own bodies for ceremonies, hunts, and
battles to the inscription of tipis and hides
with diagrams and narratives of important
events in their lives and those of their tribes.
Objects for particularly important purposes
would be made by shamans, who were endowed
with special gifts of wisdom or healing
abilities, but even children were sometimes invited
to sculpt small clay animal figures, which
would be used in ceremonials. All were taught
to understand the relationship between the
natural world and the artistic interpretation
of it.



Oscar Howe. Calling on Wakan Tanka, 1967. Casein on paper.



Although nothing was ever entirely removed
from its spiritual dimension in Native
life, actual events were also recorded in pictorial
imagery through a more purely narrative
format. Calendar hides painted by elders,
for example, documented years of history, and
although these were not designed according
to a standardized hieroglyphic system, they
could be read almost as written chapters of
tribal life over the course of time. Important
ceremonies, battles, hunts, tragedies, storms,
and other notable events were the main subjects
of these paintings, which augmented the
oral tradition of passing stories and communal
history from one generation to the next.
Individual warriors might also record especially
notable encounters, gatherings, and
conflicts in paintings, creating a visual document
of personally significant occurrences
that were used not simply as memory "books"
but for important ceremonials.

 When Native Americans were incarcerated toward the
end of the nineteenth century, this tradition
served as the basis for smaller ledger drawings
that depicted battles between various Plains
tribes and the U.S. Army. Named for the paper
upon which they were drawn, which was
taken from ledgers at the prisons or reservation
schools, these drawings form an important
record of Native Americans' reactions to
the violent disruption of their traditional ways
of life.

While the natural world was always the
most important subject for Native American
art, representations of landscape in the European
sense did not exist until late in the nineteenth
century and after prolonged contact
between the two cultures. The Native concept
of nature was not human centered, and thus
the tradition of portraying a landscape from a
fixed, individual point of view, looking across
a scene toward the horizon, was foreign and
inconceivable. In place of this "magisterial
gaze," a socially constructed concept that has
contributed much to the development of Europe
and the United States and from which
the artistic technique of linear perspective
evolved, Native Americans held the idea of the
sacred wheel, a cosmic view in which all of
nature is integrated and humans are merely
one part of a living entity, no more powerful
or significant than other things in the world.

 Because of this philosophy, in traditional Native
American representations of nature horizon
lines are rarely if ever found; more often,
symbols and representations of humans and
animals appear to float without a sense of specific
location, as if the entire universe is their
home. Within the epic expanse of the Great
Plains, where the horizon seems to merge with
the sky in all directions, this conjoining of
land with the cosmos must have seemed an
especially appropriate and true representation
of the place, even if it does not coincide with
the more familiar modern conception of the
Plains as an expansive terrain represented by a
line running horizontally across a picture.

Since their relegation to reservations, Plains
Indians have had to accommodate extraordinary
disruptions of their way of life, assimilate
vastly different worldviews and patterns of behavior,
and endure the loss of both physical
and psychological links to the past. While this
has altered their art profoundly (including
its increasing commercialization), Native
American artists have continued to draw
upon their traditional cultures for inspiration
even as they have incorporated a new array of
materials, subjects, and visual vocabularies
into their work. First encouraged in mission
schools to learn drawing and later trained
in art schools, they have become increasingly
familiar with modern artistic concepts and
methods. But they continue as well to utilize
imagery that links them with their historic
traditions and spiritual values. Their work today
is a blending of cultures, both visual and
social, but, no less than the art of their forebears,
it is a unique expression of their identity
as artists of the Great Plains.



European Encounters
Although Europeans encountered the Great
Plains as early as the 1540s, the first non-
Native artists (if early cartographers are not
counted) did not arrive until the 1830s. Intent
on documenting the appearance of the landscape
and its inhabitants for distant audiences
rather than incorporating it into an Indigenous
society, they worked within a set of
values, aspirations, and media entirely different
from that of their Native American
contemporaries. Their reactions to the terrain
were conditioned both by their previous experiences
and by their aesthetic preconceptions,
and thus they were ill-prepared for the Great
Plains landscape. Nothing, except perhaps the
boundless ocean, to which the land was often
likened, was familiar about the endless treeless
vistas that stretched from horizon to horizon,
and since their artistic training had taken
place in regions that were more visually varied,
many early artists in the Plains despaired
at the grassland's lack of subject matter for
pictures. The Great Plains, labeled the "Great
American Desert" in 1820 by Stephen Long's
government-sponsored expedition, seemed to
many an aesthetic desert that offered little
to artists.

The standard reference for nineteenthcentury
European American artists who traveled
West was the European landscape tradition
and its accompanying art theory. These
theories and practices had been conceived,
of course, for European terrain, which has
nothing in common with the Great Plains.
This pictorial tradition was premised on the
notion of prospect, a concept with multiple
meanings, both physical and philosophical. At
its most basic, referring to a point of view
(usually elevated) from which a landscape is
viewed, the term implies a human-centered
universe, a fixed point of reference that endows
the individual with essential power to
envision, imagine, and even create the scene
that lies ahead. Derived from this fundamental
concept are additional connotations that include,
among other things, the idea of futurity
or potential as well as specific artistic interpretations:
"prospect pictures" standardized
the representation of terrain into balanced
compositions framed with trees and rocks and
guided by meandering paths or streams, a
gradual movement toward a horizon that was
pleasantly glowing with the promise of opportunity.
As "prospects," these views offered to
audiences a carefully conceived version of visual
ownership, a psychological claiming of
the land's future and their role within it.

All these issues and traditions directly affected
the ability of artists to creatively respond
to the Great Plains landscape. Simply
stated, the grasslands of central North America
seemed to have no prospects. They had
no elevated vantage points from which to survey
a scene, no variegated vistas that would
charmingly direct the gaze through space, and,
just as important, they seemed to have no obvious
economic potential for a people more
accustomed to forestlands linked by navigable
waterways. Artists were at a loss both because
they had so little with which to fill their canvases
and because they knew that viewers expected
landscape paintings to imply the promise
of the American continent. The Great
Plains seemed empty and desolate, hardly the
sort of landscape that would fulfill the desires
of an eager nation looking west for its future.

This perception of vacancy was, of course,
misguided. A region of tremendous variety of
many sorts–culturally in its human diversity,
zoologically in its animal populations, climatologically
with its extremes of weather
and dramatic storms, and botanically with its
infinitude of grasses–the Plains offer both
great expanse and extraordinary subtlety, a
combination that is exceptionally difficult
to appreciate without long and thoughtful exposure.
And to artists intent on finding compositional
subject matters that would intrigue
their eastern audiences before they themselves
returned home, the special aesthetics of the
place more often than not went undiscovered
and undocumented. Almost none of the sizable
number of paintings of the grasslands
produced in the nineteenth century depict the
expansive landscape without including something
to break the monotony of the expanse.

Only in recent years, with the advent of
modernist abstraction, which suits the terrain's
minimal offerings, coupled with the increasing
appreciation of the region's ecosystem
and its relative solitude, have painters and
viewers begun to appreciate the Great Plains
for their own special characteristics. Until
then most artists felt compelled to fill the region's
emptiness or, alternately, transform it
into an idealized vision of their own making.



Expeditions and Excursions
The first European American artists to travel
through the Great Plains did so in the company
of expeditions, either government or
private, and this trend continued until well
after the Civil War. Federally sponsored artists
were charged in their commission with portraying
the scenery and its inhabitants for official
reports to be used in policy decisions that
would determine the future development of
the region. But artists who traveled privately
did so for a number of purposes. Most famous
of these, both for his expansive route and for
his dedication to his subject matter, was Pennsylvanian
George Catlin (1796-1872), who
journeyed throughout the Plains in 1832 and
1834 on a personal mission to visit and visually
document as many of the Native American
peoples as possible before, as he foresaw, their
way of life was destroyed. To the north, Paul
Kane (1810-71) followed Catlin's example
by creating an "Indian Gallery" of portraits
and landscapes from the Prairie Provinces. In
1833-34 Karl Bodmer (1809-93), a Swiss artist,
made his only visit to America in the company
of Prince Maximilian of Wied-Neuwied, an
ethnographer studying Native cultures who
needed paintings to illustrate the book he
would write upon his return. Bodmer's beautiful
watercolors, mostly Indian portraits and
river views, established a standard for all artists
who would follow. In 1837 Alfred Jacob
Miller (1810–74) accompanied Scottish nobleman
Sir William Drummond Stewart across
the Central Plains to the Rocky Mountains.
Stewart wanted souvenirs to decorate his castle
back home, and Miller's work is correspondingly
romantic, both stylistically and
thematically.

Other than Catlin, who had relatively little
artistic training and was thus less hampered
by aesthetic theory and precedents, none of
these artists, even Bodmer and Miller, who
produced a large number of evocative paintings
of the region, portrayed the landscape in
its pristine form without something in the
composition to provide it with visual interest.
This would be the norm for more than 100
years, as artists struggled to enliven their views
and to endow the seemingly empty Plains
with prospects, even if they were of the artists'
own making.

Animals, Indians, and the travelers themselves
formed important early subjects. Bison
were especially exotic and appealing, and
one of the most frequent subjects was the
bison hunt, with Indian horsemen engaged in
the chase. Prairie fires were another popular
theme, often filled with running animals
chased by flames and smoke, an eerie and dramatic
sight that never failed to evoke awe in
those who witnessed those events. Increasingly,
scenes of frontier life, usually highly
contrived, dominated the images and appealed
especially to eastern audiences, as the
paintings were exhibited widely and reproduced
in readily available publications and
prints by lithographic firms such as Currier
and Ives. Guidebooks also became immensely
popular, as much for their illustrations as for
their text, and, especially after the completion
of the transcontinental railroad in 1869, these
helped shape the expectations of thousands of
immigrants who moved into the Plains after
the Civil War. Artists often worked on commission
for these publishers, and, in the days
before copyright enforcement, their work was
also frequently shared among publishers or
redrawn by other artists in a variety of formats
for reprinting.



The Settlement Period
A major change in the portrayal of the Great
Plains occurred with the arrival of the settlers,
who dramatically altered the landscape and its
prospects. With the advent of overland routes
such as the Oregon Trail in the 1840s and then
with railroads in the 1860s, coupled with the
1862 Homestead Act, which made landownership
available to a wide populace, the influx of
Europeans and Americans into the region that
had first been a trickle became a virtual flood.
The prospects of the Great Plains began to
improve, and their image evolved from the
"Great American Desert" into the "Breadbasket
of America." For the Native peoples it
was a harrowing period of loss and despair as
their homelands were even more conclusively
encroached upon, their livelihoods destroyed,
and their ways of life irrevocably altered.

For artists, however, these events meant
new subjects and new audiences. Photographers
like Solomon Butcher (1856-1927) in
Nebraska in the 1880s recognized an opportunity
in the new settlers, and his work
appealed to people's fascination with his stillnew
medium that could in a matter of minutes
capture both a likeness and their pride in
home ownership. He and other entrepreneurs
traveled throughout the Plains photographing
the homesteaders and their farms. Occasionally,
they established studios in the burgeoning
towns in the region. Their work has become
a valuable historical record of the early
American settlement period. In their photographs
we see the range of pioneer living conditions
in the Plains, from the sod houses
of the new arrivals to the frame dwellings of
those more established. We also witness the
diversity of the people, from newly freed slaves
who claimed their own land to European immigrants
only recently off the boat. Meanwhile,
William Henry Jackson's (1843-1942)
photographs of Plains Indians depict the twilight
of a way of life that was being effaced.
In all these views the sense of place is almost
palpable, with the settlements perched tenuously
on the expansive Plains, but the insights
into the individuals are equally compelling,
whether it is hope on the faces of the new
landowners or despair on the faces of those
dispossessed.

Painters were also inspired by the settlers
and gratified by their ability to transform
the terrain into scenes not unlike those of
more traditional landscape art; at last the
artistic prospects of the land and its economic
potential were improving. Scenes of verdant
fields, locomotives, and farmers at work
helped convey these developments to eastern
audiences and satisfied the local inhabitants
that their efforts were indeed contributing to
the progress of the country. The land was taking
shape–literally–as what had previously
been seamless prairie was conformed to section
lines and plowed fields, creating the first
blocks of what now appears from the sky to be
an earthly quilt.

Although turn-of-the-century viewers did
not have the benefit of airplanes, of course,
aerial portraits of the landscape were available
to Plains audiences through artistic renderings.
Throughout the settlement period
bird's-eye town views drawn from maps, with
careful perspective manipulations to enhance
the appearance of each building, were extremely
popular and were used as promotional
objects by ambitious city planners, civic
organizations, and entrepreneurs. A clever adaptation
of the eighteenth-century English
prospect pictures, which were essentially estate
portraits for wealthy landowners, these
town views, with their clear delineations of
streets, homes, businesses, and surrounding
territory, offered a unique sense of ownership
to the inhabitants, a feeling of civic pride as
they witnessed the expanse of their towns. The
surrounding land beyond the last homes not
only suggested the local terrain but also implied
a stake in the future potential of the
community's growth. This innovative form of
depicting the Plains persists to this day in
an updated version; contemporary farms are
routinely photographed from the air, and
landowners regard the framed prints as prized
possessions.



Cowboy Art and the Great Plains


Charles M. Russell. Smoking Up, 1904. Bronze.


Even more than the landscape and its cultivation,
the most enduring visual image of the
Great Plains remains the western ideal of cowboys,
Indians, and cavalry. Although precedents
had been established for these themes in
the 1840s and 1850s, mostly by eastern artists,
the "golden age" of western art that codified
these indelible symbols actually occurred during
a relatively brief period, from the late 1880s
through the turn of the century, after the
Plains had been essentially fenced and domesticated
and its Indigenous populations reduced
and relegated to ever-shrinking reservations.
Inspired by the rapidly disappearing
ways of life, as the cattle drives were replaced
by railroad shipping, the cavalry campaigns
disappeared, and the tribes were subdued, artists
such as Frederic Remington (1861–1909)
and Charles M. Russell (1864–1926), among
others, dedicated their art to heroic masculine
action in the Plains, struggles between humans
and animals, and the conflict of cultures.

 The compelling power of this subject
matter, enhanced by their dramatic representations
of it, established a standard to which
all subsequent art of the region would be compared.
Russell had been a working cowboy
and lived in Montana, but Remington and
many of his colleagues such as Charles Schreyvogel
(1861–1912) were easterners, and their
work, produced in New Jersey and New York
studios, ignored the rapid industrialization
that much of the terrain they were portraying
was actually experiencing. While they were
careful to be accurate with details such as
clothing and movement, the histrionic compositions
of these artists were largely invented
and thus portrayed a mythic region that relied
as much on romance and nostalgia for its appeal
as on fact. Their legacy, however, has been
so profound that most Western movies have
ascribed to their model, sometimes quite directly,
and these representations have determined
the identity of the West and the Great
Plains for a large viewing audience. Today
their emulators are numerous, most notably
in the organization known as the Cowboy
Artists of America, whose members continue
to propagate the ideal of the cowboy and the
heroic battles of the Plains tribes through representational
imagery.

By the end of the nineteenth century, artists
in the Great Plains knew that a new era
was upon them. As the focus of the region
changed from establishing communities to
sustaining them, it became clear that the region
would once again be redefined in a new,
more modern image. The emphasis, by necessity, would have to be on connections with the
nation and the world as a whole—for trade,
for culture, and for identity itself. While this
promised to bring even greater bounty to the
region as it positioned itself as the country's
agricultural heartland, the transition also
posed risks, as dependence upon distant regions
became ever more important. This was
no less true for artists in the Great Plains as
they worked to strengthen their own connections
with the larger art world and position
their work within it.



Art Culture in the Great Plains

As one of the last major areas of the United
States to be settled, the Great Plains was correspondingly
slow in developing the trappings
of cultivated society, including artistic organizations
such as museums, galleries, and
societies to support and encourage the development
of artists and their work. As soon
as statehood was granted, however, which occurred
at different times in different parts of
the Great Plains, efforts were initiated to establish
institutions that would substantially
contribute to the region's cultural future. Art
museums took time, but private collections
were assembled in some places such as Omaha
and Winnipeg relatively early, and these as
well as public collections supported by civic
groups and wealthy philanthropists evolved
into today's museums.

Colleges and universities, many of which
were founded through federal land grants at
the time of statehood, however, offered art departments
very early and were an important
catalyst for the production of paintings and
sculptures as well as for the training of local
artists. Their dominance as centers of
art activities in the Plains has remained, even
as museums, galleries, and specialized art
schools have become more common throughout
the region.

Women were especially prominent in these
developments and, surprisingly perhaps,
formed the majority of the art faculties of state
universities in the Plains in the early years.
The University of Nebraska, for example, had
a strong art program as early as the 1880s, and
it was dominated by women, both in the professoriat
and the student ranks. This was true
as well throughout the Plains, although as the
schools developed and grew, men would increasingly
take the women's places on the faculty
by the 1920s. Far from being amateurs,
many of the early female artists in the Plains
came from or went on to study at prestigious
schools such as the Chicago Art Institute, the
New York Art Students League, and in Paris,
especially at the Académie Julian, which admitted
women beginning in the 1860s. Their
high level of expertise established a strong
foundation for the growth of art within their
home region. Characteristically, the careers
of these women have been overshadowed by
those of their male colleagues, but recent
studies have begun to recognize their achievements
and abilities.

Women contributed to the growth of art in
the Plains in other ways as well. They organized
art societies, art clubs, and exhibitions
of art from national collections as well as from
local artists and frequently were the guiding
forces behind the establishment of the region's
major museums. For example, a well-known
painter in Oklahoma, Nan Jane Sheets (1889–
1976), served as cosupervisor and then supervisor
of Oklahoma's Works Progress Administration
(WPA) art program during the Great
Depression. She also established an art gallery
in Oklahoma City with federal funding in
1935. Even after losing funding with the termination
of the program in 1942, she managed
to keep it open as the Oklahoma City Art Center,
the forerunner of the Oklahoma City Art
Museum.

While women worked in similar capacities
nationwide, their prominence in the Plains
states seems to have been especially significant.
They may have had a longer and consequently
greater impact in the Great Plains
because the cultural institutions there were
slower to mature than on the coasts, providing
the women with more time before men recognized
the importance of their activities and
moved into positions of authority, but much
research remains to determine this. Lack of
male competition may have also been a factor
in women's abilities to become cultural entrepreneurs
and successful artists, perhaps because
of a gender bias against artistic culture
in these frontier states that would have relegated
it primarily to the women's sphere. Nevertheless,
the status of art within the Great
Plains today–its prominent art academies
and university programs and museums that
rank among the country's finest–is certainly
due to a large degree to the farsighted early
women artists and philanthropists who made
the region their home.



Canadian Art of the Plains

Canadian art of the Plains has a history similar
to its counterpart in the United Sates, albeit,
of course, with its own unique circumstances
and character. First portrayed relatively sporadically
by a few intrepid individuals such as
Peter Rindisbacher (1806-34), who settled
briefly near the Red River in Manitoba, or artists
who accompanied exploring expeditions
such as W. G. R. Hind (1833-89), the landscape
became a major component of a few artists'
work such as that of Paul Kane, who, after
meeting George Catlin in London in 1843, followed
the elder artist's example and made extensive
travels through the Canadian Prairies,
creating both a visual and a written record.
Despite these efforts, however, the northern
grasslands did not receive significant attention
until the Canadian Pacific Railway began
providing a means of easy access to the Plains
in the 1870s and 1880s. To promote the line the
company provided artists with free passes to
travel its route, and this benefit, coupled with
the patronage of a burgeoning popular press, a
government eager to promote settlement in
the western provinces, and a growing nationalism
in the wake of the 1867 confederation
that declared Canada a unified commonwealth
of the United Kingdom, encouraged
Canadian artists to look to their own landscape
for pictorial inspiration. A number of
them, including Sydney P. Hall (1842-1922),
Frederick Verner (1836-1928), Edward Roper
(1857-91), and Augustus Kenderdine (1870-
1947), are known for their portrayals of northern
grasslands. A particular standout is Toronto
artist Charles W. Jefferys (1869-1951),
who not only devoted a number of his important
canvases to the Plains in the 1910s but also
wrote compellingly of the terrain's innate challenges
and its significance to a national art,
inspiring many younger artists to explore the
region's visual potential.

By the early part of the twentieth century,
especially through the work of the Group
of Seven, members of which first exhibited
together in 1920, Canadian painting became
noted for its landscape imagery. With a few
exceptions, such as some of the canvases
of A. Y. Jackson (1882–1976), these artists
focused their work on the rocky, northern Canadian
Shield region rather than on the
Plains. However, other painters increasingly
realized the visual power of the Prairie Provinces;
an increasing number of artists embraced
modernism's minimalist aesthetic and
followed the lead of Robert Hurley (1894–
1980), who devoted thousands of images to
the flat land of Saskatchewan after the 1930s.



The Dust Bowl


John Steuart Curry. Spring Shower; Western Kansas Landscape, 1931. Oil on canvas.


Apart from the nineteenth century and its
dramatic scenes of cowboys, Indians, and
bison, no other period has left as enduring
a characterization of the Great Plains as
the Great Depression, when years of drought
and poor land management turned the western
grasslands into the Dust Bowl. Farmers
throughout the Plains were forced off their
land by the thousands, and workers of all sorts
faced unemployment. Along with this widespread
suffering, however, art actually flourished,
drawing new attention to the central
states and developing cultural institutions
within them. Regional subjects were accorded
new appreciation: gripping depictions of the
difficult conditions throughout the Middle
West and South in paintings and photographs
captivated American audiences, and federal
relief programs brought new attention to the
region's communities through special programs
and investments that, among other
things, fostered the production of art and encouraged
related activities. Just as important,
many of the works produced in the Great
Plains or by artists from the area during this
period have become the archetypal images of
the period and a testament to the region's enduring
significance to the nation.

The artistic style known as regionalism was
not limited to the central states, and indeed
it had urban and coastal practitioners who
portrayed their own locales, but much attention
in both the art community and the country
as a whole became focused on the Midwest
and the Plains through the art of Kansan
John Steuart Curry (1897-1946), Missourian
Thomas Hart Benton (1889-1975), and Iowan
Grant Wood (1882-1942). Their work, which
usually depicted down-home themes and idealized
landscapes in an accessible, representational
style, seemed wholly American in style
and sentiment and indicative of the core of
national life, even if it did not usually portray
the difficulties of the time.
 Although only a few artists held the spotlight, 
regionalism was widespread, and many artists 
throughout thePlains states adopted it during the 1930s and
1940s. It suited the temper of the time well
with its dedication to local subjects and its
ability to simultaneously meld the ideal and
the real in ways that seemed to many to be
more relevant than modernist abstraction.
While the emphases of artists varied, from
idyllic, pastoral scenes of bounty to harsher
realities, some of the most effective works
concerned the effects of the Dust Bowl. As
much as any other subject since the days of the
bison, the widespread devastation peculiar to
the Great Plains ordered artists in the region
a new subject matter that could define their
sense of place and convey to others the power
of the landscape within which they lived.

Many of these images were produced independently,
without federal assistance, but the
wpa began an aggressive campaign in 1933 for
reemployment and revitalization throughout
the United States. Programs for artists were
included among these efforts. Most famous
was the Treasury Department's mural project,
which decorated post offices and other official
buildings throughout the country, but other
opportunities were equally exciting, offering
painters, sculptors, photographers, graphic
designers, and other artists the means for income
and the promise of commissions they
would never have received otherwise. The
programs also brought an unprecedented
viability to regional art, including that of the
Plains. Federal funding, for example, sponsored
traveling exhibitions and established
galleries where none had previously existed,
introducing original art to a wide spectrum of
the populace. Art education programs offered
jobs for artists and encouraged creative activities
among many, both children and adults,
who had never attempted them before. Some
of these programs, such as the Oklahoma
City Art Center (now the Oklahoma City Art
Museum), were maintained after the federal
subsidies were discontinued and have become
the principal art institutions in their
communities.

In what became one of the most familiar
programs of the New Deal art initiatives, the
Farm Security Administration (FSA) enlisted
corps of photographers to travel throughout
the hardest hit agricultural areas to document
local conditions. From their work emerged
some of the most memorable images of the
Plains. Dorothea Lange's (1895–1965) Tractored Out (1938) and Arthur Rothstein's (1915–
1985) gripping image of a farmer and his son
running to their house, half buried beneath a
sea of dust (1936), for example, are just two of
the most famous of the thousands of images
produced by this program. These evocative
depictions of the Great Plains are today still
widely recognized and not only stand as testimony
to the most desolate period in the region's
history but also attest to the enduring
ability of the art of the region to symbolize the
state of the country.



Contemporary Art in the Great Plains


Keith Jacobshagen. Havelock Elevator, Evening of Ash Wednesday, 1993. Oil on canvas.


Although diversity of artistic subject matter
has existed since artists began living in the
Great Plains, as life there has become more
cosmopolitan, art there has correspondingly
grown and developed. With increased ease of
travel, the publication of excellent art books
and catalogs, the prevalence of television and
increasingly the Internet, the growth of art
schools and university programs, and the development
of active museums, artists and the
public today have easy access to art of other
regions and countries, and the Great Plains
has become no less central to the development
of visual culture in the United States and Canada
than any other area.

The notion of regionalism in art, which was
never an insular concept, is more than ever a
matter of choice. As the world becomes more
culturally connected and increasingly homogenized,
however, the appeal of local identity,
artistic and otherwise, becomes more powerful.
Increasingly, a number of artists, museums,
and galleries in the Great Plains are
recognizing this potential and focusing their
attention on art of their own region. Institutions
such as the Museum of Nebraska Art in
Kearney, the National Cowboy Hall of Fame
in Oklahoma City, the Center for Great Plains
Studies at the University of Nebraska, and
others are demonstrating the vitality and richness
of the local landscape and its inhabitants
and history through art and scholarship.

Artists too, now freed from the constrictions
of European theory and the prejudices it
carried against planar terrain, are recognizing
the visual power of the Great Plains in new
ways. With the advent of minimalist abstraction
and the more recent return to figurative
representation, the art world can finally accept
the openness of the landscape and recognize
the sublimity it has always offered.

In the final decades of the twentieth century
a host of artists, working in a range of media
from traditional painting and photography to
installations, rediscovered the region and provided
new insights into its visual, environmental,
and cultural complexity. Their work
sometimes celebrates its visual breadth in
spectacular dimensions and panoramic scope,
as in the work of Nebraska painter Keith
Jacobshagen (b. 1941) and the 360-degree photographs
of Gus Foster (b. 1940), in which the
epic sweep of the horizon and the dominance
of the sky overwhelm human scale. In other
instances the land's ecological richness is the
subject, as artists such as Terry Evans (b. 1944)
explore the fragile relationship of the densely
integrated foliage and its substructure to the
health of the land and its inhabitants.

There is also a new appreciation of the epic
poetry of fire as it rages through the grasses or
the peacefulness of different times of day, but
just as significant in contemporary Plains art is
the human presence, which increasingly dominates
the landscape in so many ways. Photographers
Robert Adams (b. 1937) and Frank
Gohlke (b. 1942) and painter Harold Gregor
(b. 1929), for example, draw our attention to
the often unsettling relationship between people
and nature in the Plains through images of
suburban sprawl, abandoned towns, and endless
views of pristine farm fields where prairie
grasses once grew. In their work, as in most
recent art of the region, the real and the ideal,
the Plains and the spectacular, are conjoined in
ways that are often unsettling, provoking a reconsideration
of the land and its vulnerability
and our ability to inhabit it in sustainable ways.

Finally, environmental art is also emerging
as a new art form in the Plains, which now, as
every air traveler recognizes, appears as a giant
patchwork quilt. Some farmers, ranchers, and
"earth artists" such as Stan Herd (b. 1950) are
emulating this effect in giant multiacre portraits
and plowed pictures. The pictorial prospects
of the region have multiplied beyond
anything early artists could have imagined. As
those who live in the Great Plains have always
known, the region of waving grasses and endless
horizons is hardly a vacant plain. It is a
vibrant place of many visions.



See alsoEDUCATION: Museums 
National Cowboy Hall of Fame and Western Heritage Center / 
IMAGES AND ICONS: Emptiness; Flatness;
Remington, Frederic / NATIVE AMERICANS:
Astronomy / PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT: Dust Bowl / 
POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT: New Deal.


 

Joni L. Kinsey
University of Iowa



Kinsey, Joni L. "Cultivating the Grasslands: Women
Painters in the Great Plains." In Independent Spirits: Women Painters of the American West, 1890–1945, edited
by Patricia Trenton. Berkeley: University of California
Press and the Autry Museum of Western Heritage, 1995:
242–73, 289–92. Kinsey, Joni L. "Not So Plain: Art of the
American Prairies." Great Plains Quarterly 15 (1995): 185–
200. Kinsey, Joni L. Plains Pictures: Images of the American Prairie. Washington DC: Smithsonian Institution Press,
1996. Kinsey, Joni L., Rebecca Roberts, and Robert Sayre.
"Prairie Prospects: The Aesthetics of Plainness." Prospects: An Annual of American Studies 21 (1996): 261–97. Lamar,
Howard. "Seeing More Than Earth and Sky: The Rise of a
Great Plains Aesthetic." Great Plains Quarterly 9 (1989):
69–77. Maurer, Evan M., ed. Visions of the People: A Pictorial History of Plains Indian Life. Minneapolis: Minneapolis Institute of Arts, 1993. Nottage, James. Prairie Visions: Art of the American West. Topeka: Kansas State Historical
Society, 1984. Rees, Ronald. Land of Earth and Sky: Landscape Painting of Western Canada. Saskatoon, Saskatchewan:
Western Producer Prairie Books, 1984. Stein, Roger.
"Packaging the Great Plains: The Role of the Visual Arts."
Great Plains Quarterly 5 (1985): 5–23. Thacker, Robert. The Great Prairie Fact and Literary Imagination. Albuquerque:
University of New Mexico Press, 1986.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>