<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.art.062</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Wimar, Carl (1828-1862)</field>
      <field name="author">Vollan, Charles</field>
      <field name="text">

 




WIMAR, CARL (1828-1862)

Charles "Carl" Wimar was born on February
19, 1828, in Siegburg, near modern-day Bonn,
Germany. He came to St. Louis in 1843, studying
there under Leon de Pomarede. His early
paintings of Native Americans were based on
images from popular literature rather than
firsthand knowledge. He earned his first public
notice after returning to Germany to study
at the Kunstakademie in Düsseldorf. Returning
to the United States in 1856, he decided to
gain a more authentic knowledge of the country
and of Native Americans. Like John Mix
Stanley, Wimar relied on his own photographs
as the basis of his paintings. From 1858
to 1860 Wimar traveled with parties of the
American Fur Trading Company up the Mississippi, Missouri, and Yellowstone Rivers. He
also accompanied shipments of annuities to
tribes along the Missouri River. He used these
experiences as the basis for a more realistic
approach to tribal subjects.

As he came in contact with Native Americans
his subject matter grew less romantic,
shifting from themes of tribal war, buffalo
hunting, and conflict with European Americans
to the changing western landscape and
the decline of tribal peoples and cultures in
the face of European American expansion. In
these years Wimar also painted several detailed
panoramas of the Missouri River and the tribes
living along its banks, the last large-scale works
completed before European American colonization
permanently altered tribal life there. Although
known for his accurate portrayal of
costumes and gestures, Wimar remained a romantic
in his choice of themes. His most famous
works include Indian Approaching Fort Benton (1859) and the important Attack on an Emigrant Train (1856), considered to be a prototype
of the wagon train attack painting.

Wimar was commissioned by the city of St.
Louis to paint murals for the city courthouse
with western themes, all of which have since
been destroyed. He died of tuberculosis in
St. Louis, Missouri, on November 28, 1862.


Charles Vollan
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Stewart, Rick, Joseph D. Ketner II, and Angela L. Miller.
Carl Wimar: Chronicler of the Missouri River Frontier. New
York: Harry N. Abrams, 1991.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>