<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.mus.028</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Lee, Peggy (1920-2002)</field>
      <field name="author">Stevenson, Kate</field>
      <field name="text">

 




LEE, PEGGY (1920-2002)


Peggy Lee


Peggy Lee was born Norma Deloris Egstrom
on May 26, 1920, in Jamestown, North Dakota.
Her love of singing pulled her out of an
abusive home and onto local radio by the age
of fourteen. After high school she performed
throughout the Midwest. She was discovered
by Benny Goodman in Chicago in 1941 and
recorded her first hits with the Benny Goodman
Orchestra. Lee and her husband, guitarist
Dave Barbour, left Goodman in 1943 to
write and record their own hits, including
"It's a Good Day" and "Mañana." The latter
marked the start of Lee's lifelong fascination
with Latin rhythms. The collaboration and
marriage ended in 1951.

Lee's solo career featured recording successes,
live concerts, and television appearances.
She also appeared in The Jazz Singer
(1953) and Pete Kelly's Blues, which garnered
her an Oscar nomination for best supporting
actress in 1955. In the same year, she wrote
songs for Disney's Lady and the Tramp and
provided voices for the film. Recording highlights
of Lee's career include the 1958 release
of "Fever," a million-seller that earned two
Grammy nominations and "Is That All There
Is," which earned her the 1969 Grammy award
for best contemporary vocal performance by a
female artist.

During a career that spanned six decades
and defies categorization by genre, Peggy Lee
recorded more than 60 albums and more than
700 individual songs. She wrote more than
75 songs and published poetry and an autobiography.
She was honored by fans and peers
for her uniquely sensuous vocal quality, her
flawless musicality, and her riveting stage
presence. Peggy Lee died of a heart attack at
her home in Bel Air, California, on January 21,
2002.


Kate Stevenson
Jamestown College




Lee, Peggy. Miss Peggy Lee: An Autobiography. New York:
Donald I. Fine, Inc., 1989. Lees, Gene. Singers and the Song II. New York: Oxford University Press, 1998. Reich, Howard.
"Peggy Lee: A Sensual American Classic, through Illness
and Injury, the Amazing Performer Has Managed to
Survive." San Francisco Examiner, September 5, 1993: D2.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>