<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.art.036</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Jackson, William Henry (1843-1942)</field>
      <field name="author">Zaruba, Gary</field>
      <field name="text">

 




JACKSON, WILLIAM HENRY (1843-1942)

William Henry Jackson, 1924


William Henry Jackson's career as a photographer
and painter spanned more than
seventy years, during which he recorded the
vast beauty of the western landscape, Native
American life, and the expansion of European
Americans into the Great Plains and the West.
According to the family Bible, Jackson was
born in Keeseville, New York, on April 14,
1843. He inherited his rootlessness from his
father, who moved the family six times before
William Henry was ten. After serving in the
Civil War with the Twelfth Vermont Volunteers,
he went to the Great Plains in 1866 and
worked as a teamster hauling freight out of
Nebraska City. Jackson made many sketches
of his early travels in the Great Plains that
would later serve as references for his paintings.
With his brother he bought a photography
studio in Omaha in 1867 and spent the
next few years photographing local residents,
the Indigenous peoples, the construction of
the Union Pacific Railroad, and the settlement
of the Great Plains. His photographs of the
Pawnee villages and people around 1870, during
their final years in Nebraska, are especially
evocative.

In 1870 he joined the Hayden Geological
Survey as its official photographer and
worked for the next eight years documenting
the West and Southwest. His photographs of
the Yellowstone area influenced Congress's decision
to designate the nation's first national
park in 1872, and his widely distributed photographs
gave Americans a visual knowledge of
the Great Plains and West. The quality of
his work, considering the equipment and glass
plate developing process of Jackson's time, is
noteworthy.

From 1879 to the mid-1920s, Jackson devoted
his career to commercial photography:
he opened a photography studio in Denver,
made a photographic survey of railroads
around the world, contributed frequently to
Harper's Weekly, served as photographer for
the World's Columbian Exposition in Chicago,
and made photographic prints and postcards
for the Detroit Publishing Company.

After his retirement in 1924, Jackson painted
numerous watercolors and oil paintings, some
of which were based on his experiences in the
Great Plains and West. The oil painting Pawnee Indian Village (1930) is representative. Many
others were scenes from the Oregon Trail,
which preceded his own time on the Plains. He
was mainly self-taught as a painter, although
his photography experience gave him compositional
skills, and he had become a close
associate of the artist Thomas Moran while
working on the Hayden survey. Jackson's watercolor
paintings have a singular appearance.
They are typically small and packed full of
subject matter, and they have a pale pastel appearance
created by adding white to the transparent
medium. He continued painting and
writing until his death in New York City on
June 30, 1942.



Gary Zaruba
University of Nebraska at Kearney




Hales, Peter B. William Henry Jackson and the Transformation of the American Landscape. Philadelphia: Temple University
Press, 1988. Jackson, William Henry. Time Exposure: The Autobiography of William Henry Jackson. New
York: Putnam's Sons, 1940.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>