<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fol.017</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Folk Speech</field>
      <field name="author">Wikle, Thomas A. Bays, Brad A.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




FOLK SPEECH

Folk speech refers to the dialect, or style of
speaking, unique to people living within a
geographic area. The folk speech of an area
may be differentiated from other regions by
variation in grammatical, phonetic (pronunciation),
and lexical (word usage) features.
Along with other forms of traditional culture,
such as music, dance, and folklore, folk speech
plays a role in the conservation and perpetuation
of Great Plains culture.

In his book The Great Plains (1931), Walter
Prescott Webb noted that sign language was
an essential early form of communication in
the Great Plains. Using hand and arm gestures,
sign language made intertribal communication
possible among Plains Indians.
Subsequently, the westward movement of European
Americans during the nineteenth century
established the basic geographical patterns
of speech within the Great Plains that
persist to this day. Because of the area's relatively
recent settlement (by non-Indians), migration
patterns played a more immediate
role in influencing contemporary patterns of
speech within the Great Plains than in many
other parts of North America.

Characterizing the folk speech of the Great
Plains presents a significant challenge because
the region is a meeting place of several migration
streams. Another difficulty is determining
what set of words, pronunciations, and
grammatical forms are specific to the region.
Beginning in the 1940s several regional atlas
projects were implemented by dialect geographers
and linguists in an attempt to form a
baseline of language patterns in the United
States. In part because of these efforts, most
linguists now recognize North Central, Midland,
Southern, and Western dialect areas
converging in the Great Plains.

The North Central area extends from the
western boundary of North Dakota southward
to Sioux Falls, South Dakota. Examples
of terms common to the Northern Plains include
"soddy" for a house constructed of
tough prairie sod and "sodbuster" for the one
who breaks the sod. The need for trees in
some Northern Plains areas during their settlement
years brought legislation to encourage
tree planting on "tree claims," a term that persists
in the eastern Dakotas to describe woodlots.
Another example can be seen in the use
of "borrow pit" or "bar pit" as a road-building
term that describes a place where earthen material
has been removed.

The Midland area, extending westward
from Philadelphia and represented in the
Great Plains in a zone from Lincoln, Nebraska,
southwest toward Amarillo, Texas, is
widely considered to be the most important
dialect region. This area forms a transition
zone between the north dialect stream and the
region dominated by southern speech forms.
Because it is a transition zone in terms of language
features, the Midland region is difficult
to distinguish and may be the most unmarked
in terms of a unique dialect.

Extending into southern Oklahoma and
most of Texas south of Amarillo, the Southern
dialect region is the speech region most easily
identified by the American public. The vocabulary
of this area includes the word "blinky"
as an adjective to describe milk that has begun
to sour. Another colorful term, "gully washer,"
refers to an exceptional amount of rainfall,
and in Texas a compliment might be paid to
someone who was said to be as "handy as hip
pockets on a hog." The Spanish language has
also had a profound impact on folk speech in
this part of the Plains, as represented in terms
such as "arroyo," meaning a dry gulch or deep
gully cut by an intermittent stream.

The Northern, Midland, and Southern dialect
areas merge with Western dialect forms
in the western reaches of the Plains. Western
dialect terms that mingle within the Great
Plains include "corral," "bull snake," and
"jerky." Slang terms are also an important part
of folk speech, as represented by "Wyoming
wind gauge," used for a logging chain on a
fence post. Native American and First Nation
languages have also influenced Plains folk
speech: in the Prairie Provinces, for example,
the verb "ponask" has been borrowed from
the Cree language to describe the practice of
splitting a piece of meat, putting it on a stick,
and roasting it over an open fire.

Distinctive folk speech of the Great Plains
can also be found within enclaves or ethnic
islands. These include places settled by European
immigrants who have retained distinctive,
yet not necessarily foreign-sounding, elements
in their speech. Language retention is
important, for example, to many ethnic Ukrainians whose ancestors migrated to Manitoba
beginning in the 1890s. In some cases the
Ukrainian language has blended with English,
as represented in words such as drúgshtor
(drugstore).

In many cases, unique forms of folk speech
in a particular area may have grown out of
isolation from mainstream society. During the
early years of settlement, particular forms of
grammar, word usage, and pronunciations
were also born out of necessity or emerged
from the imagination of settlers. For example,
a tree common to the Plains, the "bois d'arc"
(Maclura pomifera), was named by the French
for the Indian use of bois for the wood used
to construct the bow (arc). Americanization
replaced bois d'arc with "bowdark" and added
the term "horse apples" for the bowdark's
fruit.


Thomas A. Wikle
Brad A. Bays
Oklahoma State University




Allen, Harold, B. The Linguistic Atlas of the Upper Midwest.
Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 1976.
Bailey, Guy, Tom Wikle, and Lori Sand. "The Focus of
Linguistic Innovation in Texas." English Worldwide 12
(1991): 195–214. Cassidy, Federic G., ed. Dictionary of American Regional English. Cambridge MA: Belknap Press,
1985.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>