<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.gen.017</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Hayes, Kate Simpson (1856-1945)</field>
      <field name="author">Maguire, Constance A.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




HAYES, KATE SIMPSON (1856-1945)

Portrait photograph of Kate Simpson Hayes (University of Saskatchewan-Regina)
    

Kate Simpson Hayes, one of the earliest woman
authors and journalists in western Canada,
was born in Dalhousie, New Brunswick, in
1856 and died on January 15, 1945, in Victoria,
British Columbia. Hayes arrived at Prince Albert
in 1879. In the mid-1880s, after her marriage
failed, she took her two young children
and moved to the small Canadian Prairie town
of Regina. There she met Nicholas Flood
Davin, and their nine-year intimate relationship
resulted in the birth of two children out of
wedlock.

Following a brief period as proprietress of
her own millinery shop, Hayes worked as librarian
for the territorial legislature and wrote
for the Regina Leader newspaper. Much of her
work was written under the pseudonym "Mary
Markwell." In 1889 she spent several months in
North Dakota, reporting on fairs, harvest conditions,
and fashion trends. Hayes also wrote
plays and comedic sketches, which were performed
in a number of prairie communities.
Her first book, Prairie Pot-Pourri, a collection
of poems, stories, and a children's play, was
published in 1895. In 1900 Hayes moved to
Winnipeg, where she edited the women's page
of the Manitoba Free Press (later Winnipeg Free Press) until 1906. She then traveled to Britain,
where she worked for the Canadian Pacific
Railway, promoting the emigration of women
to western Canada. Kate Hayes was a charter
member of the Canadian Women's Press Club
in 1904 and served as club president in 1906-7.
Her newspaper columns reveal her conservative
social views, including her opposition to
women's suffrage. Hayes contributed to the
Manitoba Free Press until 1909, and during
1910-11 was women's editor of the Ottawa Free Press. For the remainder of her life Kate Hayes
continued to write, supporting herself with her
pen until well into her senior years.

See also MEDIA: Winnipeg Free Press.


Constance A. Maguire
Regina, Saskatchewan




Hayes, Catherine Simpson. Papers. r-215. Saskatchewan
Archives Board, Regina, Saskatchewan, Canada. Maguire,
Constance A. "Kate Simpson Hayes, Agnes Agatha Hammell,
and the ‘Slur of Illegiimacy.'" Saskatchewan History
50 (1998): 7–23. Maguire, Constance A. "'Leaving the
Hearth Fire Untended': Women and Public Pursuits in the
Journalism of Kate Simpson Hayes." Prairie Forum 23
(1998): 67–92.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>