<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.arc.040</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Religious Architecture</field>
      <field name="author">Sawyers, Keith</field>
      <field name="text">

 




RELIGIOUS ARCHITECTURE

The practice of religion in the Great Plains has
been diverse, and the historical evidence of
worship displays a rich variety of physical expression.
Among the Native inhabitants of the
Great Plains, religion was intertwined with
nature. Prominent landscape features such as
mountains and buttes were venerated as sites
possessing spiritual significance. An e.cient
form of mobile architecture was devised by
the Omahas, who created a special tent for
housing their Sacred Pole. Permanent structures
for the practice of religious ceremonies
were also erected by Plains Indians such as
the willow sweat lodge of the Lakotas. Indian
settlements attracted Christian missions as
European immigrants pushed into the Great
Plains. For the most part, the rude structures
associated with these religious activities
were short-lived. Notable exceptions were the
Spanish Colonial missions, which continue to
grace the southern fringes of the Great Plains
in Texas and New Mexico.

The influx of immigrants into the Great
Plains of Canada and the United States during
the nineteenth century resulted in the creation
of numerous local church organizations, and
buildings to accommodate worship soon followed.
The character of many of these early
churches, regardless of denomination, was
similar–a rectangular, one-room wooden
building capped with a gable roof. A slightly
more elaborate version included a central bell
tower, the lower portion of which served as an
entrance vestibule. Modesty of means and the
use of pattern books contributed to a significant
degree of homogeneity in the general appearance
of the building type during this period.
The style preferred for these structures
was Gothic Revival, an imagery associated
with European Christianity, but most attempts
to acknowledge this precedent were
pale imitations of the style as practiced in the
older metropolitan areas of North America.
Scarce resources limited use of the Gothic design
vocabulary; for example, the pointed
arch above door and window openings might
appear only on the front elevation. The interiors
of these early churches were generally
lacking in spatial development and ornamentation.
Furthermore, the functional anonymity
of the room and the mobility of the
sparse furnishings allowed some fledgling
frontier communities to temporarily utilize
the building for the secular activities associated
with a municipal hall, courtroom, or
school until resources allowed for the construction
of these special-use facilities.

By the end of the nineteenth century many
former frontier communities had grown in
both population and financial resources. Consequently,
attention was directed toward the
design and construction of more sophisticated
houses of worship. Congregations erected
churches that reflected both their wealth and
the history of their beliefs. Guided by the romantic
influences of the era, the more conformist
denominations such as Roman Catholic,
Lutheran, Episcopalian, and Canadian
Anglican favored the Gothic Revival, Romanesque
Revival, and occasionally the neoclassical
Revival styles that were associated with the
rituals and rich historical traditions of the European
Christian church. Methodists, Presbyterians,
Baptists, Congregationalists, and
some of the newer denominations frequently
took liberties with their interpretations of
the traditional Gothic, Romanesque, and
Classical styles as well as employing more original
nineteenth-century styles such as the High
Victorian, Gothic, and Queen Anne. In the
process they generated diverse and less historically
accurate versions of the precedents, the
latter modified to express more contemporary
values.

Noteworthy deviations from the popular
revival styles of the period were to be found in
the interpretations of the Byzantine style employed
in Jewish synagogues and the churches
built by both Eastern Catholic and Orthodox
congregations. Predominantly located in the
Northern Great Plains and Prairie Provinces,
Eastern Catholic and Orthodox churches in
particular were characterized by impressively
crafted wood construction, complex massing,
and picturesque domes crowning the roofs
above the nave and chancel.

More specific distinctions in the architecture
of the various denominations resulted
from their differing beliefs and rituals of worship.
These differences were especially evident
in the design of church interiors, the two basic
concerns being a recognition of those emotive
factors that influenced the worshipers' feelings
such as illumination, color, and proportions,
especially height, and liturgical factors
related to the actions, symbols, and furnishings
that defined and facilitated the process
of worship.

Prior to the 1960s the plan and spatial configuration
of conformist churches placed emphasis
upon a celebration of the sacraments
in an environment designed to enhance the
sense of mystery accompanying rituals and
the hierarchical separation between the clergy
and laity. Two traditional configurations were
most commonly employed. The basilican plan
consisted of a rectangular nave, which accommodated
seating for the congregation, and a
chancel, which was separated from the nave
by an arched opening and raised floor. Approached
by steps, the chancel was reserved
for the clergy and contained the high altar
against the rear wall. In the cruciform plan the
longer portion contained the nave, the short
projection at the top of the cross contained
the chancel, and the projections to the left and
right, the transepts, held secondary altars.

The spatial complexity and opulence of
these interiors could be enhanced by the addition
of side aisles, a tall nave illuminated by
clerestory windows, stained glass, liberal use
of three-dimensional detailing, elegant furnishings,
and decorative ceiling and wall surfaces.
A characterizing feature of Episcopal
and Canadian Anglican churches was the extended
length of the chancel. This space accommodated
a choir, the seating of which was
split into two segments facing one another
across an aisle that terminated at the altar. The
interiors of Eastern Catholic and Orthodox
churches were distinguished by domes that
spatially defined the nave and chancel. Typically,
the chancel was separated from the nave
by an elaborately decorated icon screen that
obscured the congregation's view of the altar.

The layout and spatial design of nonconformist
churches such as Methodist, Baptist,
Presbyterian, and Congregationalist placed
emphasis upon the spoken word. This led to
the abandonment of traditional elongated
plans in favor of a square auditorium configuration
that greatly enhanced acoustics and
sight lines. Other features borrowed from auditorium
design included a gently sloping
floor and a fan-shaped seating arrangement
that focused attention upon a raised platform
containing the pulpit and choir. All these features
were ideally suited to a room created for
preaching.

During the last half of the nineteenth century
a design scheme called the Akron plan
was widely used by many Protestant congregations. It typically consisted of the auditorium
arrangement of seating and platform plus a
large adjacent room separated from the main
meeting hall by a moveable partition. This
multipurpose room served several functions.
When the dividing partition was opened the
room could accommodate overflow seating
for the auditorium. When closed the partition
defined a space used for Sunday school classes.
The appearance of a church utilizing the
Akron plan was distinctive and usually asymmetrical.
The main entrance to the auditorium
was typically through a tall corner
tower. This arrangement was particularly appropriate
for a corner lot and invited direct
access from both streets. A secondary entrance
was marked by a shorter tower positioned
between the auditorium and the Sunday
school.

In the years following World War II the superiority
of historical precedents influencing
both style and hierarchical organization in
the design of conformist churches was questioned.
Modernization of Roman Catholic
churches was accelerated following the Vatican
Council II in the early 1960s. The latter
resulted in a massive program of remodeling
existing churches and rethinking the design
of new churches. Interior design changes included
reducing the dominance of the high
altar in favor of a more communal altar or
table situated at the front of the chancel or in
the midst of the seating area. Further diminishing
of the hierarchical separation of clergy
and laity was reinforced by utilization of the
auditorium seating plan. This has produced a
blurring of the historical distinctions between
conformist and nonconformist church interior
layout and exterior massing.

Recent trends in the design of religious architecture
in the Great Plains reveal a movement
away from the conservatism of the past
and toward a search for spatial and liturgical
compositions compatible with the evolving
views of contemporary religious worship.
Meanwhile, significant shifts in population
linked to social and economic changes resulted
in the abandonment of many older
churches throughout the Great Plains during
the last half of the twentieth century. Finding
new uses for these redundant but culturally
significant buildings presents a challenge to
the communities in which they are located.

See also RELIGION: 
Distribution of Religions.


Keith Sawyers
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Kalman, Harold D. A History of Canadian Architecture.
Toronto: Oxford University Press, 1996. Maddex, Diane,
ed. Built in the U.S.A.: American Buildings from Airports to Zoos. Washington DC: Preservation Press, 1985.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>