<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.tra.016</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Holladay, Ben (1820-1887)</field>
      <field name="author">Ward, Derrick S.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




HOLLADAY, BEN (1820-1887)

A giant in the history of transportation in the
United States, Ben Holladay was born into a
poor Kentucky family in 1820. In 1836 he moved
to St. Louis, Missouri, where he gained practical
business experience working as a store clerk,
liquor salesman, and tavern keeper. Holladay
became seriously involved in the transportation
business during the Mexican War in 1846, when
he contracted with Gen. Stephen W. Kearny to
supply wagons and provisions to the U.S. Army.
After the war, he formed a partnership with
Theodore W. Warner for transporting supplies
to Salt Lake City, where they were sold to westbound
emigrants. Holladay prospered greatly
through his trade with Brigham Young and the
Mormons.

Following the 1857 Mormon War, Holladay
capitalized on the Pikes Peak gold rush by associating
with the staging firm of Russell, Majors
and Waddell. The disruption of the Butterfield
Overland Mail during the Civil War
provided another business opportunity. In
March 1862 he gained control of the Central
Overland California and Pikes Peak Express
Company and its 1,200 miles of stage lines.
Holladay improved and expanded the company,
increasing the number of stations, obtaining
a fleet of new Concord stages, and updating
the numerous routes. He also secured
government mail contracts amounting to
$650,000 annually. By 1866 the Holladay Overland
Mail and Express Company extended
from Atchison to Denver and Salt Lake City.
Nonetheless, Holladay, tired of increasing
conflicts with Native Americans and aware
that rail transport would soon supplant his
stage lines, sold out to Wells, Fargo and Company
on November 1, 1866, for $1.5 million
cash, $300,000 worth of Wells, Fargo and
Company stock, and numerous other perks.

Ben Holladay played a major role in opening
up the Great Plains and the West to trade and
settlement. While remembered primarily for
his success in staging, Holladay held interests
in steamships bound for Asia, river-bound
stern-wheelers, and numerous western railroads.
He also helped establish the Pony Express.
Ben Holladay, the flamboyant Stagecoach
King, died in Portland, Oregon, on July
8, 1887.


Derrick S. Ward
Ventura, California




Frederick, James V. Ben Holladay, the Stagecoach King: A
Chapter in the Development of Transcontinental Transportation.
Glendale CA: Arthur H. Clark, 1940.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>