<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.med.029</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Leader-Post (Regina)</field>
      <field name="author">Mayeux, Peter E.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MILITARY POST PUBLICATIONS

U.S. troop newspapers in both Spanish and
English appeared in the Great Plains soon after
the Mexican War (1846–48). These soldier
newspapers included the Anglo-Saxon, the
Santa Fe Republican, the Flag of Freedom, and
the Picket Guard–one of the first substantial
troop papers of the U.S. Army. The papers
included items on American troop victories,
the preparedness of Mexican troops, the need
for accurate reporting, the rivalry between
regular and volunteer troops, and the need to
keep enlisted men's morale high. Although
they generally lasted a short time, these small,
letter-size sheets accustomed troops to having
their own papers, even in combat zones.

In 1864, during the American Civil War, the
Frontier Scout, a four-page, three-column
weekly, appeared at Fort Union, Dakota Territory.
The same name was used for a paper
started in 1865 farther down the Missouri
River at Fort Rice, Dakota Territory. It is likely
that the same printing office produced both
papers. Prisoner-of-war publications were not
uncommon. On a sheet of unruled letter paper,
a captain in the Connecticut Volunteers
produced a handwritten publication, the Old Flag, at Camp Ford, Texas. Each single copy
was read aloud to prisoners.

Post publications reflected the military's
growing professionalism between the Civil
War and the beginning of World War I. Weekly
newspapers were established at several Plains
military installations to help relieve boredom,
inform troops, and recount life on the frontier.
In articles, poems, drawings, cartoons, and editorials,
readers learned about military policies
and were informed about life at the post. Great
Plains newspapers included the Chugg Water Journal, Fort Laramie; the Phil Kearny Scout,
Fort Philip Kearny, Dakota Territory; the Daily Telegraph, Fort Bridger, Wyoming; and the
Plains, Fort Larned, Kansas. The frontier soldier
papers resembled their civilian counterparts
with their mixture of wit and satire and
their boosterism.

Publications were also established by veterans
and other military groups. In 1888, for
example, the United States Cavalry Association
issued the U.S. Cavalry Journal from
Leavenworth, Kansas, and after 1910 the Artillery
Association published the Field Artillery Journal from Washington DC and Fort Sill,
Oklahoma.

During World War I, camp newspapers
typically were seven-column, four-page papers
costing two cents a copy. Weekly issues
aimed to boost troop morale and promote
high moral standards. Many soldier papers
were launched following the Armistice, including
the Jayhawker in France, the "Unofficial
Organ of the 137th Infantry," a unit with
Kansas connections. A hospital paper, the Fort Bayard News, was published near Silver City,
New Mexico, by the U.S. Army General Hospital.
And in 1922 the first monthly issue of the
Military Review was published at the Command
and General Staff College at Fort Leavenworth,
Kansas. The Review has been labeled
the "Professional Journal of the U.S. Army"
because of its articles on military philosophy
and tactics and its influence on army doctrine.

Long before Pearl Harbor, GI papers were
started to help train draftees. Two of these papers
were the Camp Wolters Longhorn, published
near Mineral Wells, Texas, and the
Rainbow Reveille at Camp Gruber, Oklahoma.
During the war, other troop newspapers
emerged, including BAM, published in
1943 at the Naval Air Gunner's School, Purcell,
Oklahoma. World War II military publications
observed tight editorial controls that
produced items that were bland, traditional,
and predictable. Most were weeklies printed
by letterpress or offset, although several were
mimeographed issues. Writers with little or
no actual journalism experience produced
many of the camp papers.

Several Great Plains military post publications
continue journalistic traditions that began
in the nineteenth century. Some of these
are the Field Artillery Journal (a magazine)
and Military Review.

See also WAR: Military Bases.


Peter E. Mayeux
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Cornebise, Alfred Emile. Ranks and Columns: Armed Forces Newspapers in American Wars. Westport CT: Greenwood
Press, 1993.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>