<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.war.054</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Washita, Battle of the</field>
      <field name="author">Corbett, William</field>
      <field name="text">

 




WASHITA, BATTLE OF THE

Caption: "The seventh U. S. Cavalry charging into Black Kettle's Village at Daylight, November 27, 1868" (Harper's Weekly) (Library of Congress)
 

The Battle of the Washita occurred on November
17, 1868, in western Indian Territory, about
one mile west of present-day Cheyenne, Oklahoma.
Before dawn, Lt. Col. George Armstrong
Custer peered over a snow-encrusted ridge into
the valley of the Washita River. There he saw a
large Cheyenne village in a wooded bottom on
the south side of the stream. At daybreak, 700
men of the Seventh U.S. Cavalry struck the village
of Black Kettle, a Cheyenne peace chief.
Completely surprised, the warriors offered only
token resistance as women and children fled to
the surrounding woodlot and hills. Troopers
occupying the village began burning its fifty
lodges, killing approximately 800 horses and
destroying supplies. Throughout the day, soldiers
skirmished with a growing number of warriors
from camps downstream who converged
on the smoldering village. In late afternoon,
Custer assembled his troops and withdrew, with
fifty-three captives. Cavalry casualties included
twenty-two men killed and thirteen wounded.
Also, Indians murdered Clara Blinn, a white
captive, and her young son during the attack.
Precise Native losses are unknown. Some estimates
placed the dead at nine to twenty men,
including Black Kettle, and eighteen to forty
women and children, while others suggest that
as many as 103 were killed in total.

The Battle of the Washita emerged as the
only significant engagement of the winter
campaign of 1868–69. Frustrated by elusive
Cheyenne and Arapaho warriors who raided
the Central Plains frontier the previous summer,
Gen. Philip H. Sheridan had organized
the expedition to chastise the Indians. He also
hoped a show of force would coerce the Cheyennes
and Arapahos onto a reservation created
for them by the 1867 Treaty of Medicine
Lodge Creek. Custer's attack on Black Kettle's
village, some of whose warriors participated
in the summer raids, accomplished both of
Sheridan's objectives. In 1997 the battlefield
was designated a National Historic Site by the
National Park Service.


William Corbett
Northeastern State University




Hoig, Stan. The Battle of the Washita: The Sheridan-Custer
Indian Campaign of 1867–1869. Garden City NY: Doubleday
and Co., 1976. Utley, Robert M. Cavalier in Buckskin:
George Armstrong Custer and the Western Military Frontier.
Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1988.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>