<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.rel.029</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Jones, Harold (1909-2002)</field>
      <field name="author">Cochran, Mary E.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




JONES, HAROLD (1909-2002)

Harold Stephen Jones, a Santee Sioux, was the
first Native American to be elected bishop of
any major denomination. Born in Mitchell,
South Dakota, on December 14, 1909, Jones
was raised by his grandparents, the Reverend
William Holmes, an early Indian Episcopal
priest, and his wife, Rebecca, a Caucasian.
This dual heritage fostered his eventual ability
to serve successfully in a racially conflicted
church and society.

Jones's childhood was spent in Niobrara,
Nebraska, and Wakpala, South Dakota, where
his grandfather served mission churches. His
grandfather died while Jones was in his teens.
Then came a struggle with discrimination and
poverty as he helped support his grandmother
and continued his education. He graduated
from Northern State College in 1935 and received
a licentiate in theology from Seabury-Western
Theological Seminary, Evanston, Illinois,
in 1938. He married Blossom Steele, a
Lakota, in December of 1938, a week after his
ordination as deacon.

Beginning with Messiah Chapel in Wounded
Knee, Jones was assigned in rapid succession to
four small chapels on the Pine Ridge Reservation.
There was never adequate compensation,
which led to mounting debts on top of unpaid
college loans. Three children were born into the
Jones family, with only the daughter, Norma,
surviving. Moves to the Cheyenne River Reservation
in 1947 and back to Pine Ridge in 1952
brought added responsibilities but no financial
relief. That finally came when he was called in
1956 to serve a white congregation in Wahpeton,
North Dakota.

In 1968 the national Episcopal Church
called him to take over the Navajo mission
field in Arizona, where he had to adapt to a
different language and culture. While there he
was elected suffragan (assistant) bishop of
South Dakota and was consecrated in a great
multiracial service in Sioux Falls on January
11, 1972. His ministry as bishop was severely
limited by a stroke after less than a year of
service to both white and Indian congregations,
and he had to take an early retirement in
1976. Subsequently, the Rt. Rev. Harold Jones
lived with his daughter in Chandler, Arizona,
and died there on November 12, 2002.


Mary E. Cochran
Tacoma, Washington




Anderson, Owannah. Four Hundred Years: Anglican/Episcopal
Mission among American Indians. Cincinnati: Forward
Movement Publications, 1997. Cochran, Mary E.
Dakota Cross-Bearer: The Life and World of a Native American
Bishop. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 2000.
Sneve, Virginia Driving Hawk. That They May Have Life:
The Episcopal Church in South Dakota. New York: Seabury
Press, 1977.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>