<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.asam.003</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Asian Canadians</field>
      <field name="author">Regehr, Ted D.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ASIAN CANADIANS

People of Asian Ethnic Origin
Living in Canadian Metropolitan Centers, 1991

CalgaryEdmontonReginaSaskatoonWinnipeg
Chinese32,51532,9602,4903,15510,445
Japanese1,8801,090100175980
East Indians14,94515,1201,0508356,130
Filipino7,8057,05555576521,720
Total Asian77,14578,6906,4406,53048,815


People of Asian origin comprise a small but
notable and increasingly important segment
of the population in the three Canadian Prairie
Provinces. Before 1951 the Canadian government
sought to restrict Asian immigrants. The
first Chinese and Japanese immigrants to Canada
were almost all laborers building the railways
or working in the mines. Many returned
home after the transcontinental railways were
built, but others stayed. The majority tried to
establish themselves in British Columbia or
Ontario. Some, however, remained in the
cities, towns, and villages on the prairies. Most
Chinese and Japanese in the Prairie Provinces
before World War II established or worked in
laundries, restaurants, market gardens, and
confectioneries. They faced systemic and persistent
discrimination and kept to themselves
as much as possible, living mainly in segregated
areas of the larger urban centers or in
their places of business in the smaller rural
towns and villages.World War II marked a decisive
turning point for Japanese Canadians.
In 1941 the Canadian government decided to
remove all those of Japanese origin from a socalled
security zone in western British Columbia.
These people were first placed in internment
camps in the British Columbia interior
and in other camps established during the
1930s for single, unemployed men. Labor
shortages, particularly in the labor-intensive
sugar beet industry on irrigated land in southern
Alberta, resulted in a relocation of many
Japanese internees to assist in farmwork. Several
Japanese Canadian authors, most notably
historians Ken Adachi and Ann Gover Sunahara
and novelist Joy Kogowa, have documented
that sad chapter in the history of their
people. A few Japanese farmers began cultivating
sugar beets in southern Alberta even before
the war, and others found opportunities to
enter that branch of farming as a result of their
wartime experience as farm laborers.

The reluctance of the federal government to
allow the Japanese to return to their prewar
homes in British Columbia persuaded many
to remain in Alberta, where they established
a good reputation and achieved moderate
success as farmers. Others entered the professions.
A strong Japanese community remained,
particularly in the Lethbridge area.
After the war the Japanese Canadians expressed
their appreciation for the opportunities
afforded them in southern Alberta by
creating and opening to the public a beautiful
Japanese garden and park in the city of
Lethbridge.

The postwar economic boom, chronic labor
and capital shortages, and changing attitudes
resulted in dramatic changes in Canadian immigration
policy after 1951. Specifically, immigration
restrictions against immigrants from
Asian countries were eased. The majority of
these new immigrants established themselves
in Vancouver, Toronto, and Montreal, but
some also found their way to cities on the Prairies.
There the new Chinese and Japanese
immigrants revitalized, not always without
conflict, old, established ethnic communities
while East Indian and Vietnamese immigrants
created new ones.

The more recent immigrants have found
integration into Canadian society easier than
did their predecessors, but in all the Prairie
cities, and in many of the towns and villages,
distinctive Asian restaurants as well
as cultural, social, and religious organizations
enhance the richness and diversity of prairie
society.


Ted D. Reghr
University of Saskatchewan and University of Calgary




Adachi, Ken. The Enemy That Never Was: A History of the Japanese Canadians. Toronto: McClelland and Stewart,
1976. Buchignani, Norman, and Doreen M. Indra. Continuous Journey: A Social History of South Asians in Canada&gt;.
Toronto: McClelland and Stewart, 1985. Li, Peter. The Chinese in Canada. Toronto: Oxford University Press, 1988.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>