<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.war.020</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Harney, William (1800-1889)</field>
      <field name="author">Chow, Richmond L.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




HARNEY, WILLIAM (1800-1889)

Gen. William S. Harney was born in Haysboro,
Tennessee, on August 22, 1800. He first visited
the Great Plains in 1825, when he accompanied
the Col. Henry Atkinson and Benjamin O'Fallon
expedition to sign treaties with the upper
Missouri tribes. Harney fought in the Sauk and
Fox wars in 1832, serving as Gen. Zachary Taylor's
assistant inspector. In 1837 he participated
in the Second Seminole War. Harney left Florida
with a reputation as an Indian fighter, having
performed several daring, and sometimes
ruthless, actions against the Seminoles.

Between 1846 and 1848 Harney fought in
the U.S.-Mexican War. After the war, Harney
was assigned to inspect military posts and
control Indian raids in Texas. In 1855 he assumed
command of a campaign against the
Brulés, who were involved in conflicts with
immigrant travelers on the overland trails. On
September 3, Harney's troops routed Little
Thunder's village at Blue Water Creek (Ash
Hollow) in western Nebraska, killing about a
half of the 250 band members. The Lakotas
named Harney "Mad Bear" because, following
the attack on their village, he marched
across the Badlands to Fort Pierre, Dakota
Territory, challenging the Lakotas to a winter
fight. The success of his campaign encouraged
Harney to suggest that mobile units might replace
permanent posts.

Harney was promoted to brigadier general
in 1858, and in 1863 he retired to St. Louis. He
returned to the Great Plains as a member of
the 1865 and 1867 peace commissions to negotiate
treaties with tribal leaders. In 1868 he also
received a temporary assignment to establish
three Sioux agencies on the Missouri River–at
Whetstone Creek, Cheyenne River, and
Grand River. Harney died in Orlando, Florida,
on May 9, 1889.


Richmond L. Clow
University of Montana




Clow, Richmond L. "General William Harney on the
Northern Plains." South Dakota History 16 (1986): 229–48.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>