<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.mus.005</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Border Radio</field>
      <field name="author">Reinhardt, Akim D.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BORDER RADIO

XERA, one of the border blasters near Del Rio, Texas. (www.modestoradiomuseum.org) 
    

In 1931 Kansas-native "Doctor" J. R. Brinkley
founded radio station XERA (later XERF)
in Villa Acuna, Coahuila, Mexico, due south
of San Angelo, Texas. It was the first border
radio station, positioned just over the Rio
Grande and aimed northward at the American
audience.

In Mexico, where wildcat station owners
were unfettered by the Federal Communication
Commission's regulations on wattage
output, stations like XERA could transmit in
excess of 500,000 watts. In the Great Plains,
where the level topography of the land means
that radio waves are usually obstructed only
by the curvature of the earth, signals (particularly
AM frequencies) can travel hundreds,
sometimes thousands of miles before fading
out. The result was a string of stations just
across the Mexican border that garnered massive
audiences.

Border radio stations were huge moneymakers
for station owners who sold programming
time, fundamental evangelists, and a
stunning array of entrepreneurs who used the
airwaves to run mail-order businesses. On the
artistic side, music ranged from country and
gospel to conjunto and rhythm and blues, and
musicians like Bob Wills used border radio to
widen their audiences. From 1938 to 1939 the
Carter family actually lived in Mexico and
broadcast live on border radio stations. The
stations' massive radius of air coverage also
allowed them to serve as a platform for numerous
self-made celebrities. Flour salesman
Wilbert Lee "Pappy" O'Daniel used border radio
to become a western swing music impresario
and later governor of Texas. A young
disc jockey named Bobby Smith created the
persona of Wolfman Jack in the mid-1960s on
XERF, where he also served as station manager.
He soon parlayed this into national success.

A 1968 Mexico-U.S. treaty finally put a cap
on border station wattage. However, nostalgia
over these stations has been celebrated in song
by the likes of zz Top ("Heard It on the X"),
John Hiatt ("Pirate Radio"), and Dave Alvin
("Border Radio").

See also MEDIA: Brinkley, John Richard.


Akim D. Reinhardt
Towson University




Fowler, Gene, and Bill Crawford. Border Radio: Quacks, Yodelers, Pitchmen, and Other Amazing Broadcasters of the American Airwaves. Austin: Texas Monthly Press, 1987.
Jack, Wolfman, with Byron Laursen. Have Mercy! Confessions of the Original Rock 'n' Roll Animal. New York:
Warner Books, 1995.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>