<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pe.011</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Black Hills</field>
      <field name="author">Reider, Richard G.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BLACK HILLS


Black Hills diagram


The Black Hills is an eroded structural dome
in northwestern South Dakota and adjacent
northeastern Wyoming. Elevations range from
about 3,500 feet along its margins to 7,242 feet
on Harney Peak near the center. The dome has
eroded Precambrian crystalline rocks (granite
and schist) exposed near its center, as at Harney
Peak and Mount Rushmore National Memorial.
Younger rocks lie outward from these.
Among them, soft shales form valleys, whereas
resistant rocks, such as sandstones and limestones,
form plateaus, hogbacks, or homoclines.
Paleozoic limestones, principally the
Minnekahta limestone (Permian), overlie the
crystalline units and form the Limestone
Plateau that covers much of the western half of
the uplift. Outward from the Paleozoic beds is
the Spearfish Formation (Triassic) that forms
the Red Valley (or Racetrack) that entirely rims
the edges of the Black Hills. Next, the Dakota
Sandstone (Cretaceous) forms a prominent
hogback encircling the uplift. Late Mesozoic
and Tertiary beds comprise the plains beyond
the hogback.

Limestone caverns are common on the
Limestone Plateau, as at Jewel Cave National
Monument and Wind Cave National Park.
Hot springs occasionally occur along the margins
of the uplift, as at the town of Hot Springs,
South Dakota. Numerous laccolithic peaks
(caused by volcanic intrusions) lie north and
west of the uplift in South Dakota and Wyoming,
including Elkhorn Peak, Crow Peak,
Crook Mountain, and Citadel Rock. Devils
Tower in Wyoming (a national monument) is
a volcanic neck and Bear Butte in South Dakota
is an igneous plug. All these volcanic features
are Tertiary in age. Gold deposits in the
Black Hills are associated with the Tertiary
volcanism.

The Black Hills is dominated by ponderosa
pine (Pinus ponderosa) with open parklands
and valleys covered by grasses. Birch (Betula
sp.) and aspen (Populus tremuloides) are also
common in higher elevations.

See also LAW: United States v. Sioux Tribe of Indians / SPORTS AND RECREATION: National Parks.


Richard G. Reider
University of Wyoming




Fenneman, Nevin M. Physiography of Western United
States. New York: McGraw-Hill Book Company, 1931.
Thornbury, W. D. Regional Geomorphology of the United
States. New York: John Wiley &amp; Sons, 1965.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>