<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.war.042</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Sheridan, Philip (1831-1888)</field>
      <field name="author">Trogdon, Gary</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SHERIDAN, PHILIP (1831-1888)

Portrait photograph of Philip Sheridan
 

Philip Henry Sheridan, five feet five inches tall
and unimpressive looking, was commander of
the Military Division of the Missouri during
controversial stages of Native American conflict
with post–Civil War westward expansion.
Sheridan was born on March 6, 1831, in (probably)
Albany, New York, and grew up in Ohio.
A rather undistinguished student, Sheridan
graduated from the U.S. Military Academy at
West Point in 1853 and served in Texas and the
Pacific Northwest. He rose to the rank of major
general by serving with distinction during
the Civil War as commander of the Army of
the Potomac's cavalry division. After the Civil
War, Sheridan performed short stints in
Reconstruction-era Texas and Louisiana before
going to Fort Leavenworth, Kansas, in the
spring of 1868. He was given command of the
Military Division of the Missouri in 1869 and
promoted to lieutenant general. In 1875 he
would marry Irene Rucker, his quartermaster's
daughter, and together they had four
children.

Too few soldiers, many with less than desirable
attitudes and character, too many forts to
garrison, and too large an area to defend were
just some of the problems confronted by the
careful and deliberative commander. Directed
by the "epeace policy" of the politicians, eastern
philanthropists, and social reformers, Sheridan
soon developed his strategy. He had two
main principles for dealing with Native Americans,
for whom he showed little sympathy. The
first was to place all Indians on well-guarded
reservations and have the U.S. government
feed and clothe them. The second was to capture
and punish any Indians found off their
reservation. To institute this policy, Sheridan
ordered a new type of warfare against Native
Americans.winter campaigning. His offensive
efforts, typified by Lt. Col. George Armstrong
Custer's winter battle at the Washita
River against the Cheyennes (November 17,
1868), proved successful. Columns of lightly
supplied cavalry troops converged on the Indians
in winter quarters, where they were immobile
because of women, children, and weakened
ponies.

Sheridan campaigned widely in the Plains
in the 1870s, against the Lakotas in the Sioux
War and against the Comanches, Kiowas,
Southern Cheyennes, and Southern Arapahos
in the Red River War. He was promoted to
general in chief of the army in 1883 and general
of the army in 1888. That same year, on
August 5, he fell victim to a fatal heart attack at
Nonquitt, Massachusetts.


Gary Trogdon
Lincoln, Nebraska




Hutton, Paul. Phil Sheridan and His Army. Lincoln: University
of Nebraska Press, 1985. Morris, Roy, Jr. Sheridan:
The Life and Wars of General Phil Sheridan. New York:
Crown Publishers, Inc., 1992.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>