<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.law.029</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Macleod, James (1836-1894)</field>
      <field name="author">Waiser, Bill</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MACLEOD, JAMES (1836-1894)

Col. James Farquharson Macleod, the second
commissioner of the North-West Mounted
Police (NWMP), worked tirelessly to establish
harmonious relations with the Indian nations
of the Canadian Prairie West, only to see his
efforts frustrated by a federal Indian policy
based on coercion, control, and parsimony.

Born on the Isle of Skye in Scotland on September
25, 1836, Macleod was nine years old
when his family moved to a farm north of
Toronto in present-day southern Ontario. Although
Macleod earned degrees in classics
and philosophy and then law, he preferred life
in the militia–a passion that was reinforced
in 1870, when he was sent west as a member of
the Wolseley Expedition to quell the Métis resistance
at Red River.

Thanks to his political connections, Macleod
secured a commission as superintendent
with the fledgling nwmp in May 1873. The following
July he was one of 300 Mounties on the
so-called Great March from Dufferin, Manitoba,
west along the international boundary
to southern Alberta. The police had been sent
into the western interior to suppress the American
whiskey trade on Canadian soil but barely
survived the trek across the open, unfamiliar
prairie; fortunately, neither the whiskey traders
nor the Indians offered any resistance.

Macleod, in command of the force in the
absence of the commissioner, lost little time in
establishing a police presence in the region; he
built posts on the Oldman River (Fort Macleod)
in 1874 and in the Cypress Hills (Fort
Walsh) and on the Bow River (Fort Calgary)
the following summer. He also initiated important
contacts with the leading Indians of
the area, in particular Chiefs Crowfoot (Blackfoot)
and Red Crow (Blood), and secured their
support in ending the debilitating whiskey
trade. Macleod's attempt to extradite several
Americans implicated in the 1873 Cypress Hills
massacre, however, ended in failure.

Macleod was appointed NWMP commissioner
in July 1876. He was a popular choice
because of his Canadian background, and his
tenure at the helm of the force was largely
preoccupied with First Nations issues. He participated
in the signing of the last two major
treaties in western Canada: Treaty Six with the
Plains Cree at Fort Carlton in August 1876 and
Treaty Seven with the Blackfoot Confederacy
at Blackfoot Crossing in September 1877. Both
Crowfoot and Red Crow attributed their willingness
to enter into treaties with the queen's
representatives to their friendship with Macleod.
The new commissioner also met with
Sitting Bull at Fort Walsh in September 1877;
he assured the refugee Lakota leader that his
people would find sanctuary there but that
there would be no government assistance. Finally,
as a member of the appointed Northwest
Territories council, Macleod sponsored
legislation to conserve the dwindling bison
herds in order to head off Indian starvation.
But the measure came too late, and his visits
to Indian agencies throughout the region in
1879–he traveled over 2,000 miles on horseback–
confirmed his worst fears.

By 1880 Macleod had become disillusioned
with the failure of the Canadian government
to honor its treaty obligations. Ottawa, in
turn, began to ask questions about his poor
management of police funds. Macleod consequently
resigned as commissioner that September
and devoted his energies to his other
major role as stipendiary magistrate. His earlier
legal training served him well, for he was
appointed to the first territorial supreme
court in 1887. But his arduous days on the trail
had taken a toll on his health, and Judge Macleod
died in Calgary on September 5, 1894.

See also NATIVE AMERICANS: Crowfoot / WAR: Red River Resistance.


Bill Waiser
University of Saskatchewan




Baker, William, ed. The Mounted Police and Prairie Society.
Regina: Canadian Plains Research Center, 1998.
Beahen, William, and Stan Horrall. Redcoats on the Prairies.
Regina: Centax Books, 1998. Col. J. F. Macleod Papers,
Glenbow Archives, Calgary.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>