<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.edu.016</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Eastman, Charles (1858-1939)</field>
      <field name="author">Wilson, Raymond</field>
      <field name="text">

 




EASTMAN, CHARLES (1858-1939)

Dr. Charles Alexander Eastman (Ohiyesa) devoted
his entire life to helping Native Americans.
He believed that Indians could retain
their beliefs, but they also needed to selectively
adopt non-Indian ways in order to function in
the dominant culture. This was the message
he often presented in his lecturers and his
eleven books and numerous articles. Elaine
Goodale Eastman, his non-Indian wife, assisted
him in his publications.

Eastman was born near Redwood Falls,
Minnesota, on February 19, 1858, and raised
in the traditional manner of a Santee Sioux
hunter and warrior. His life drastically
changed at age fifteen, when his recently
Christianized father convinced Eastman to
join him at Flandreau, Dakota Territory, and
enroll in Flandreau Mission School. For the
next seventeen years Eastman attended a number
of schools, including Santee Normal
Training School and Dartmouth College, ultimately
receiving his medical degree from
Boston University School of Medicine in 1890.

His first of several government appointments
was as Indian physician at Pine Ridge
Agency, South Dakota (1890–93), where he
witnessed the massacre at Wounded Knee.
Other government positions were outing
agent at Carlisle Indian Industrial School,
Pennsylvania (1899), Indian physician at Crow
Creek Agency, South Dakota (1900–1903),
head of the project to revise the Sioux allotment
rolls (1903–9), and Indian inspector
(1923–25). At times, he clashed with his white
superiors regarding policies. His nongovernment
work included a brief medical practice in
St. Paul, Minnesota (1893), serving as Indian
secretary of the International Committee of
the YMCA (1894–98), and representing Santee
Sioux claims in Washington DC. For several
years, the Eastman family ran a summer camp
near Munsonville, New Hampshire.

As an active Indian reformer, Eastman
helped found and later served as president
of the Society of American Indians. He condemned
reservation conditions, supported
Indian citizenship, and called for the abolition
of the Bureau of Indian Affairs. In his final
years, Eastman continued to present lectures
and worked with the ymca and Boy Scouts of
America and on several research projects. In
1933 he was awarded the first Indian Council
Fire Medal for his lifelong work in addressing
Indian and white relations. Eastman died in
Detroit, Michigan, on January 8, 1939.

See also GENDEREastman, Elaine Goodale 


Raymond Wilson
Fort Hays State University





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>