<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ea.039</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Vérendrye Family</field>
      <field name="author">Wood, W. Raymond</field>
      <field name="text">

 




VÉRENDRYE FAMILY

Pierre Gaultier de Varennes, the Sieur de la
Vérendrye, was born in Trois Rivières, Canada,
on November 16, 1685. He served briefly
in the army, married in Quebec in 1712, and
fathered four sons and a daughter. The rest of
his life was devoted to the western fur trade
and exploration. In 1727 he was appointed
commandant of the Posts of the North, which
then consisted of three forts on the west side
of Lake Superior. From that beginning, he established
a string of small forts that extended
deep into the Plains north and west of Lake
Superior in what is now southern Ontario and
Manitoba. These forts established the claim of
New France to this western country and challenged
the English fur traders based at Hudson
Bay. He and his sons went on to be the
first Europeans to explore what is now southern
Manitoba and western North and South
Dakota.

La Vérendrye and his sons established Fort
St. Pierre in 1727, Fort St. Charles in 1732, Fort
Maurepas in 1734, Fort Dauphin about 1741,
and finally, Fort La Reine on October 3, 1738.
Fort La Reine was on the Assiniboine River
directly south of Lake Manitoba. On October
18, 1738, La Vérendrye, two of his sons, and
a party of about fifty men moved southwest
from Fort La Reine. Accompanied by Assiniboine
Indians who joined them on the march,
they reached the Mandan villages near the
junction of the Heart and Missouri Rivers on
December 3. After a brief trading session, he
left two men there to learn the Mandan language
and, seriously ill, departed on the 13th.

In 1742 his two younger sons, François and
Louis-Joseph, returned to the Mandan villages,
and on July 23 they struck out to the
southwest, eventually approaching some high,
wooded mountains. Most historians believe
these mountains were the Black Hills of South
Dakota, although they may have been the Big
Horn Mountains of northern Wyoming. Because
of the generalized nature of their narrative
it is impossible to be certain either of
their destination or the identity of most of the
Indian tribes they met during their travels.
Whatever their route, it is certain that they
returned to the Mandans by way of the mouth
of the Bad River, near what is now Pierre,
South Dakota, for the discovery there in 1913
of a lead plate left by their party provides the
only indisputable point of reference for their
eleven-month expedition from the Mandan
villages.

The brothers had hoped to discover the
"Western Sea," and their long search was a
disappointment both for their father and his
superiors. La Vérendrye was recalled and replaced
as commandant in 1744. Much of his
exploration had been done at his own expense,
and he was deeply in debt. When his
successor left the post two years later, La Vérendrye
resumed his former position, but his
explorations were over. Before his death on
December 6, 1749, La Vérendrye was awarded
the coveted Cross of St. Louis. He had opened
the Canadian West for the French but they
ignored his explorations, and it was left to
the British to occupy the Prairie Provinces
of Canada. His trials, expenditures, and sacrifices
for New France had been in vain.


W. Raymond Wood
University of Missouri-Columbia




Burpee, Lawrence J. Journals and Letters of Pierre Gaultier
de Varennes de la Vérendrye and His Sons. Publications of
the Champlain Society, vol. 16. Toronto: Ballantyne Press,
1927. Smith, G. Hubert. Explorations of the La Vérendryes
in the Northern Plains. 1738–1743, edited by W. Raymond
Wood. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1980.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>