<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ha.040</field>
      <field name="titleMain">South Americans</field>
      <field name="author">Davis, Roger P.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SOUTH AMERICANS

Hispanics of South American origin, foreign
born or of foreign stock, appear in census figures
for the Great Plains from the late nineteenth
century on, but their numbers take on
significance only in the latter half of the twentieth
century.

In general, the South American population
in North America has never been substantial.
Canadian censuses do not distinguish ethnic
categories prior to 1941, and following that
date numbers of South Americans are consistently
below 1 percent of Canada's total population.
From 1890 through 1930 South Americans
accounted for an average of only 3.6 percent
of the entire Hispanic population of the
United States. Census figures range from a low
of 4,733 in 1900 to a high of 33,623 in 1930. Of
this population during those years, fewer than
1,000 ever settled in the Great Plains. As represented
in the 1900 and 1930 census, South
Americans on the Plains ranged from 279 to
853 individuals. However, while the numbers
are few, the geographic pattern they formed
represented a template for the future. Of the
ten states and three provinces of the Great
Plains, Texas and Colorado consistently accounted
for half, or nearly half, of the South
American population, with Kansas and Oklahoma
trading off as the third most popular
destination. The population of New Mexico,
while significantly Hispanic, was predominantly
Mexican and attracted relatively few
South Americans from 1890 to 1930.

The presence of South Americans in the
Great Plains increased markedly from 1960 to
the present. For the United States as a whole,
the number of South Americans increased
from 89,000 to more than 1 million persons.
For the Great Plains specifically, the relative
share of the national total remained nearly
constant at 5 to 6 percent, while numbers grew
from just over 9,000 to nearly 53,000 persons.
The most significant spatial aspect of this population
growth is the continuation of the earlier
pattern of settlement, but with an even
greater concentration in Texas.

As in the earlier census, Texas and Colorado
account for the majority of the South Americans
in the Plains. From 1960 through 1990
they claimed from 63 percent to just over 85
percent of the Plains total. Again, New Mexico,
with only 2 to 4 percent of the Plains total
during these decades, is not a significant location
for South Americans. A new variant that
has emerged in this time frame is the sharp
increase in the concentration of South Americans
in Texas. In 1960 Texas, Colorado, and
Oklahoma combined claimed 75 percent of
the South Americans in the Great Plains. By
1990 Texas alone was home to more than 76
percent of the total, and Texas and Colorado
together represented over 90 percent of the
Plains total.

While actual numbers for some other Plains
states increased–in Oklahoma from 1,098 to
2,477; in Nebraska from 307 to 783; in New
Mexico from 439 to 1,357; and in South Dakota
from 94 to 217–their relative share of Plains
South Americans fell as the Texas population
surged from 4,374 to 40,521.

What accounts for these geographic patterns
is unclear, but statistics on education and
occupation suggest some possible answers. Research
on Hispanics in the United States by
categories indicates that South Americans are
much more likely to have a college degree or
some education beyond high school than most
other Hispanic groups. South Americans are
also distinguished by their occupational profile:
they are twice as likely to report employment
in the managerial, professional, technical,
administrative, and sales areas than other
Hispanic groups. They are generally not associated with the service area categories of private
household occupations or farming, or
with other categories of general labor. The demographic
data suggest that because Texas and
Colorado represent expanding regional hubs
of technology, education, and professional occupations,
they offer the best prospects for
South Americans in the Great Plains.


Roger P. Davis
University of Nebraska at Kearney




Aponte, Robert, and Marcelo E. Siles. "Latinos in the
Heartland: The Browning of the Midwest." JSRI Research
Report no. 5. East Lansing MI: Julian Samora Research
Institute, Michigan State University, 1994. Moreno, Susan
E. "U.S. Latinos and Higher Education." IUPLR Briefing
Papers, no. 1: 6. Austin TX: Inter-University Program for
Latino Research, 1999. Pinal, Jorge del, et al. "We the
Americans . . . Hispanics." Washington DC: U.S. Department
of Commerce, Economics and Statistics Division,
Bureau of the Census, September 1993.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>