<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.art.059</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Thompson, Bradbury (1911-1995)</field>
      <field name="author">Bartels, Ron</field>
      <field name="text">

 



Washburn Bible





THOMPSON, BRADBURY (1911-1995)

Bradbury Thompson, the eminent American
graphic designer, was born in Topeka, Kansas,
on March 25, 1911. In 1934 he graduated from
Washburn College, where he served as the
graphic designer and editor of the college
publication. His major was in economics, but
his editorial design work presaged his brilliant
career in visual communications design. He
also developed his visual discipline during
these years by working as a draftsman for
roads and bridges.

From 1938 to 1962 Thompson designed
Westvaco Inspirations for Printers, the innovative
arts journal of the West Virginia Pulp and
Paper Company (Westvaco). It was at this time
that he developed his unique style of visual
graphic design, which included the experimental
use of four-color printing, typography,
and photo reproduction. Westvaco provided
him with unlimited paper stocks and advanced
printing processes; however, the company's
budget for illustration was nonexistent.
Thompson creatively solved this problem by
adapting engravings, photographs, and artwork
from advertising agencies, museums,
and magazines.

After World War II Thompson worked as a
freelance designer in New York. He was art
director of Mademoiselle magazine and design
director of Art News from 1945 to 1972. He also
designed the format of various publications,
including the Smithsonian Magazine. Another
accomplishment was his design of more than
ninety U.S. postal stamps.

In 1979, drawing from the experience he
had accumulated at Westvaco and in the magazine
trade, Thompson completed the design
of the Washburn College Bible in 1979.
He used the flush-left, ragged-right style of
modern typesetting, and the lines of text are
broken into individual phrases according to
speech cadences, making reading easier while
also providing a clearer meaning. His significant
contribution to this project was to follow
historical typographic traditions while
also advancing typographic standards and incorporating
them into modern visual themes.
Thompson died on November 1, 1995.


Ron Bartels
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Carter, Rob. American Typography Today. New York: Van
Nostrand Reinhold Company, 1989. Meggs, Philip B. A History of Graphic Design. New York: Van Nostrand Reinhold
Company, 1983. Thompson, Bradbury. Bradbury Thompson: The Art of Graphic Design. New Haven CT: Yale
University Press, 1988.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>