<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.wat.019</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Pick-Sloan Plan</field>
      <field name="author">Knutson, Cody L.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




PICK-SLOAN PLAN

Also known as "Big Muddy," the Missouri
River meanders 2,341 miles from its origins in
the Rocky Mountains of Montana before joining
the Mississippi River at St. Louis, Missouri.
The river drains roughly one-sixth of
the United States, including portions of ten
states, the homelands of twenty-eight Native
American tribes, and a small portion of Canada.
Before 1940 this great river was almost
completely uncontrolled.

A series of extreme droughts during the
1930s and severe flooding in 1943 that covered
many areas along the Missouri River, including
much of Omaha and Kansas City, prompted a
surge of interest in water planning for the Missouri
River basin. Planners felt that increased
management of the river and its tributaries
would not only reduce future flooding, but
also benefit the region’s economy through increased
irrigation and hydropower production,
enhanced navigation, and job opportunities
for veterans returning from World War II.
Two federal agencies, the U.S. Bureau of Reclamation
and the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers,
were the leading water development agencies
at the time, and both were called on by Congress
to compose plans to harness the unruly
river. The Bureau of Reclamation’s subsequent
plan, sponsored by William G. Sloan, focused
on increasing irrigation for agricultural stability
and hydropower production for regional
economic growth. The Corps of Engineers's
plan, sponsored by Col. Lewis A. Pick, concentrated
primarily on reducing floods and increasing
navigation within the basin. The two
plans were eventually merged into the Missouri
River Basin Development Project, commonly
known as the Pick-Sloan Plan, during a
conference in Omaha, Nebraska, on October
17, 1944. The combined plan was submitted to
Congress and enacted on December 22 as part
of the Flood Control Act of 1944. In appreciation
of Colonel Pick and William Sloan's
efforts in the development of the plan, the
project was officially dedicated as the Pick-Sloan
Missouri Basin Program in 1970.

Under the initial $1.9 billion plan, 316 separate
projects were authorized, aiming to create
112 dams, 4.3 million acres of irrigation, 2.6
million kilowatts of hydroelectric generating
capacity, and hundreds of miles of levees and
other flood protection structures. The highlight
of the plan was to be the construction of
five, large multipurpose dams along the upper
main stem of the Missouri River: Garrison,
Oahe, Big Bend, Fort Randall, and Gavins
Point, along with improvements to the previously
constructed Fort Peck Dam in Montana.
Under the compromise, the Corps of
Engineers would determine reservoir capacities
for flood control and navigation and the
Bureau of Reclamation would determine capacities
for irrigation. The following year,
Congress also authorized the Missouri River
Bank Stabilization and Navigation Project under
the 1945 Rivers and Harbor Act, which
allowed for a nine-foot-deep navigation channel
to be created on the Missouri River downstream
from Sioux City, Iowa. Together, these
projects constitute the majority of engineering
works on the Missouri River.

To assist in the cooperative management of
these projects, Congress authorized the establishment
of the Missouri Basin Inter-Agency
Committee in 1945, consisting of various federal
and state members. The name and structure
of this committee has changed several times
over the years. In 2001 it was known as the
Missouri River Basin Association to reflect the
addition of tribal and other interest groups.
Through these cooperative efforts, the region
was to receive a fair allocation of flood control,
enhanced navigation, cheap hydroelectric
power, irrigation, and programs to increase
public recreation facilities, municipal and industrial
water supplies, and fish and wildlife
populations. However, since the inception of
the Pick-Sloan Plan, many environmental, water
rights, and cost-benefit issues have arisen
that have forced planners to revise the design
and operation of projects. So many concerns
surfaced that in 1964 Congress mandated that
any Pick-Sloan project not yet initiated would
have to be authorized by Congress. Although
most of the primary projects have been completed,
many other works have been modified,
are still under review, or have been eliminated.

The region has received many significant
benefits from the Pick-Sloan Plan. Farms, residences,
and businesses worth approximately
$17.6 billion benefit from flood control measures
provided by the mainstem reservoir system.
Generated hydropower provides more
than 9 percent of the energy use in Iowa, Minnesota,
Nebraska, North Dakota, and parts of
Illinois, Montana, and Wisconsin. Many irrigation
projects were eventually scaled down
or eliminated because of inappropriate soil
types or lack of interest, but there are approximately
1,600 water intakes on the mainstem
reservoir system, supplying much-needed water
for municipal, agricultural, industrial, and
domestic water uses. In addition, the river and
its lakes provide recreational opportunities
that contribute $87.1 billion annually to basin
states as well as benefiting navigation on the
lower river.

Although these and other benefits have
been derived from the Pick-Sloan Plan, the
project has also caused significant problems
for many local people and the natural river
ecosystem. Filling the dams involved flooding
approximately 1.6 million acres of fertile bottomlands
along the river and the voluntary or
forced relocation of thousands of people, including
more than 900 Native American families.
Damming of the upper portions of the
river and channelization of the lower reaches
have also created new ecosystems to which
plants and animals have been forced to adapt.
On the upper reaches, lake environments have
replaced much of the free-flowing river, and
interlake reaches are affected by lower water
temperatures and reduced sediment loads. On
the lower river, channelization has reduced
river depth diversity and eliminated sandbars
and river connections with side channels and
backwaters. Natural river flows have also been
transformed, with high spring flows now captured
in reservoirs and low summer and fall
flows supplemented with reservoir releases.
These modifications have caused significant
changes to the habitats and populations of
many river fish and bird species, some to the
extent that they are now federal- or state-listed
as endangered or threatened species or species
of special concern.

Overall, the Pick-Sloan Plan has provided
local states and tribes with significant benefits.
The project has brought much-needed revenue,
employment, flood control, cheap hydroelectric
power (to some portions of the
region), enhanced navigation, recreation, water
supply, and a host of other benefits to an
economically depressed area. However, this
development comes at a great cost. Besides the
ever-increasing amounts of money spent on
construction and management of the project,
other losses have been incurred that cannot be
calculated. The cultures and livelihoods of
people relocated by the projects were often
severely disrupted, and the natural ecosystem
of the river has been forever altered. Because
of such concerns, attempts are now being
made to take a more balanced approach to
water management within the Missouri River
Basin.


Cody L. Knutson
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Ferrell, John R. Big Dam Era: A Legislative and Institutional
History of the Pick-Sloan Missouri Basin Program.
Omaha: U.S. Army Corp of Engineers, 1993. Lawson, Michael
L. Dammed Indians: The Pick-Sloan Plan and the
Missouri River Sioux, 1944–1980. Norman: University of
Oklahoma Press, 1982.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>