<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.wat.009</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Floods</field>
      <field name="author">Guthrie, Will</field>
      <field name="text">

 




FLOODS

The history of flooding in the Great Plains displays
a marked diversity of types. Most common
are short-lived flash floods on small watersheds
following intense cloudburst storms. Less common,
but usually more destructive, are longerlived
main-stem river floods. These result from
heavy rains dispersed over a wide area, fast ice
and snowmelt, or a combination of both. On
Northern Great Plains streams, ice dams during
the spring runoff also lead to flooding. No
stream escapes flooding. It is part of a river's
natural processes. The primary response of
humans to these floods has been through engineering:
dams, levees, drainage channels, and
land-use modification. Yet the underlying reason
humans in the Great Plains have repeatedly
suffered from floods is their tendency to
occupy floodplains.

Three of the most dramatic and devastating
flash floods in the Plains were those of June
1921 on the upper Arkansas; May 1951 on the
Little Nemaha at Syracuse, Nebraska; and June
1972 at Rapid City, South Dakota. In the first
case, moisture-laden winds blowing westward
created a swirling vortex against the Front
Range above Pueblo, Colorado, on June 3,
1921. Torrential rains fell from orographic
cooling, producing flash floods on the upper
Arkansas during the next two days. Pueblo residents
stood on the town's levees to watch the
flood along the straightened and channeled
river that ran through the business district. An
unknown number of people lost their lives
when flood crests topped the levees; seventyeight
bodies were eventually recovered.

Another example of a cloudburst flood was
the record-breaking (in terms of discharge per
drainage area) flood on Nebraska's Little Nemaha
River at Syracuse on May 8-9, 1951. It
was caused by runoff arriving together from
two intense thunderstorms over separate watersheds.
The flood flow from this event was
225,000 cubic feet per second from a watershed
of 218 square miles. Twenty-three people
died, and among other damages, sloping fields
on uplands lost topsoil in depths "up to the
plow sole," while fields at places down on the
floodplain were covered by five feet of that
topsoil.

A historical benchmark of flood devastation
in the Plains was the flood of June 9, 1972, at
Rapid City, South Dakota. An intense stationary
supercell thunderstorm in the Black Hills
dropped up to 15.5 inches of rain–close to
the average annual amount–in six hours in
the hills to the west of Rapid City. Failure of a
dam brought a flood crest on Rapid Creek
through town near midnight. Its flood flow
was ten times the previous flood record.
Homes, businesses, and 5,000 automobiles
were destroyed, more than 3,000 people were
injured, and 237 died.

Wider areal precipitation produced two of
the most devastating floods in the Central
Plains. Following a month of above-average
rainfall in the watershed, extremely heavy
rains fell–up to twenty inches in places–on
the south fork of the Republican River in eastern
Colorado and western Kansas during the
night of May 30–31, 1935. More than 100 people
lost their lives, 20,000 head of livestock
drowned, and massive destruction of railroad
tracks, bridges, and levees occurred. The high
loss of life in the upper valley resulted from
the arrival of the flood in the middle of the
night, with little or no warning. After daylight,
many others died when they refused to heed
warnings and tried to save livestock and personal
belongings.

The 1951 flood of the Kansas and Missouri
Rivers at Kansas City followed intense widespread
rainfall in the Kansas River basin. The
watercourse through Kansas City was notoriously
constricted, with much of the industrial
district protected behind twenty-foot levees.
At the time much of the flood protection work
authorized under the Pick-Sloan Plan remained
incomplete. After floodwaters topped
the levees, nearly $1 billion in damages was
sustained. The Missouri at Kansas City also
flooded in 1993 when heavy summer rains
over much of the Midwest caused the most
devastating flood in U.S. history to the Mississippi
River basin. Part of this extraordinary
event was the particularly severe flooding on
the lower Missouri, which brought a river
crest at Kansas City on July 27 at nearly three
feet above the devastating 1951 flood level.

The Red River of the North holds a special
place in the history of Great Plains flooding.
As the major northward-flowing river in the
United States, it is subject to a distinctive flood
potential. Spring floods occur as snow at the
headwaters to the south begins to melt. These
waters pool behind ice dams to the north. Because
the river flows in a relatively flat valley
(the bed of ancient glacial Lake Agassiz), the
waters rise gradually. A great flood in 1897 followed
this pattern, and repeatedly damaging
floods have occurred in the cities of Grand
Forks, Fargo-Moorhead, and Winnipeg. Movie
newsreels in 1950 followed the slowly rising waters,
sandbagging efforts, and flooding that went
on for weeks across Manitoba in the Red and
Assiniboine River valleys. Provincial and dominion
governments wrestled with responsibility
and assistance in the face of the unprecedented
disaster. Southern Manitoba had 530
square miles inundated. Television news in 1997
showed the dramatic burning of Grand Forks's
flooded downtown when the Red River flooded
on both sides of the border. This flood produced
a "Red Sea" in Canada nearly as large as Lake
Manitoba. Canadians responded with the enormous
engineering project of the Greater Winnipeg
Floodway, a twenty-six-mile diversion
ditch. Its construction required moving an
amount of dirt equal to that of the Panama
Canal.

See also CITIES AND TOWNS: Fargo, North Dakota; Grand Forks, North Dakota; Winnipeg, Manitoba / PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT: Climate.


Will Guthrie
University of Kansas




Bumsted, J. M. Floods of the Centuries: A History of Flood
Disasters in the Red River Valley, 1776–1997. Winnipeg:
Great Plains Publications, 1997. Hoyt, William G., and
Walter B. Langbein. Floods. Princeton: Princeton University
Press, 1954. Smith, Keith, and Roy Ward. Floods: Physical
Processes and Human Impacts. Chichester, England:
John Wiley &amp; Sons, 1998.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>