<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fil.025</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Giant</field>
      <field name="author">Wright-Peterson, Virginia M.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




GIANT


James Dean in Giant


Edna Ferber's best-selling novel Giant (1952)
provides the basis for this 1956 film set in
Texas and directed by George Stevens. Stevens,
who won an Academy Award for best director
for Giant, was especially lauded for his ability
to juxtapose the vast Texas landscape with the
narrow-mindedness of the people who lived
there. The film's star-studded cast includes
Elizabeth Taylor, Rock Hudson, and James
Dean. Giant was Dean's last film before his
fatal car accident, which occurred two weeks
after shooting the final scene.

Ferber based the opulent lifestyle portrayed
by Bick and Leslie Benedict (Hudson and Taylor)
on wealthy Texas ranch owners and oil
developers like Bob Kleberg and Glenn Mc-
Carthy, who received significant media attention
in the 1940s and 1950s, including representation
on the cover of Time magazine. Giant
contrasts a materialistic life of lavish dinners,
fine clothes, and automobiles with the exploitation
of Mexican Americans, whose labor was
a significant commodity in the Texas economy.
Mexican Americans were still being referred to
as "wetbacks" in the U.S. government documents
and academic reports that Ferber used
as sources in the late 1940s. In addition to the
politics of materialism, the film addresses racial
and class prejudices directly when the Benedicts'
son (played by Dennis Hopper) marries
a Mexican woman. The novel and film caused
considerable controversy. Articles in newspapers
and magazines, including the Dallas Morning News and the Houston Press, protested
what they considered a stereotypical
and exaggerated representation of the Texas
culture.


Virginia M. Wright-Peterson
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Ferber, Edna. A Kind of Magic. New York: Doubleday,
1963. Edna Ferber Papers, Wisconsin State Historical Society
Archives, Madison. Richie, Donald. George Stevens: An American Romantic. New York: Museum of Modern
Art, 1970.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>