<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.009</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Bush, George W. (b. 1946)</field>
      <field name="author">Shelley, Fred M.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BUSH, GEORGE W. (b. 1946)

In 2000 George Walker Bush was elected the
forty-third president of the United States. He
and John Quincy Adams are the only U.S.
presidents whose fathers also achieved that
high office.

Bush was born on July 6, 1946, in New
Haven, Connecticut, the son of George Herbert
Walker and Barbara Pierce Bush. At
the age of two, he moved with his family to
Odessa, Texas, and shortly thereafter to Midland.
Following in his father's footsteps, he
attended Yale University, graduating in 1968.
He later earned a master of business administration
degree from Harvard University in
1975. He served as a pilot in the Texas Air National
Guard between 1968 and 1973, and married
Laura Welch of Midland in 1977.

Bush spent much of his early career in the
oil and gas industry in Texas, although he
ran unsuccessfully for a seat in the House of
Representatives in 1978. In the late 1980s he
worked as an adviser and speechwriter in
his father's presidential campaign. After his
father won the election, the younger Bush
purchased the Texas Rangers professional
baseball team.

In 1994 Bush ran for governor of Texas. He
won the Republican nomination and defeated a
popular incumbent, Democrat Ann Richards,
in the general election. Bush was a popular governor,
emphasizing welfare and education reform
along with strong anticrime measures. He
was easily reelected in 1998.

In the spring of 2000 Bush began campaigning
for the Republican presidential nomination.
Turning back a strong challenge by Sen.
John McCain of Arizona, Bush won his party's
nomination. He selected Richard Cheney, former
Wyoming representative and U.S. secretary
of defense, as his running mate. In one of
the closest and most hotly contested presidential
elections in history, Bush and Cheney defeated
their Democratic opponents, Vice President
Al Gore and Sen. Joseph Lieberman. For
five weeks after Election Day, the outcome
hung in the balance while allegations of ballot
irregularities and flawed voting procedures
were investigated in Florida, whose twenty-five
electoral votes would determine the outcome.
Eventually, the U.S. Supreme Court
ruled in Bush's favor, and the Bush-Cheney
ticket was elected with a margin of 271 to 266 in
the Electoral College, despite the fact that
Gore won approximately half a million more
popular votes than Bush.

Bush was inaugurated in January 2001. The
September 11, 2001, terrorist attacks on the
World Trade Center and the Pentagon soon
provided a test of Bush's leadership. The administration's
response to global terrorism,
including military action in 2001 against the
al-Qaida network in Afghanistan and the 2003
invasion of Iraq, proved highly popular, and
Bush's approval rating remained very high
into 2003.


Fred M. Shelley
Southwest Texas State University




Bruni, Frank. Ambling into History: The Unlikely Odyssey
of George W. Bush. New York: HarperCollins, 2001. Hatfield,
James. Fortunate Son: George W. Bush and the Making
of an American President. New York: Times Books,
1999. Toobin, Jeffrey. Too Close to Call: The Thirty-six-Day
Battle to Decide the 2000 Election. New York: Random
House, 2001.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>