<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.sr.037</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Mills, Billy (b. 1938)</field>
      <field name="author">Hornbuckle, Adam R.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MILLS, BILLY (b. 1938)

"Billy Mills winning the 10,000m in the 1964 Olympics"
 

Billy Mills, an Oglala Sioux, achieved one of
the Olympic Games' most astonishing upsets
by winning the gold medal in the 10,000 meters
in Tokyo, Japan, in 1964. William Mervin
Mills was born on June 30, 1938, on the Pine
Ridge Reservation in South Dakota. He entered
Haskell Institute, an Indian school in
Lawrence, Kansas, after being orphaned at age
twelve. Active in various sports, he discovered
a penchant for distance running and, in 1957,
obtained an athletic scholarship to the University
of Kansas.

Mills won several Big 8 Conference crosscountry
and indoor and outdoor track titles
before graduating from the University of
Kansas in 1962. He joined the U.S. Marine
Corps and, after a two-year break from competitive
running, qualified for the 1964 U.S.
Olympic team in the 10,000 meters and the
marathon. A relative unknown in the 10,000
meters, Mills outran favorites Ron Clarke of
Australia and Mohamed Gammoudi of Tunisia
in the final few meters, establishing an
Olympic record of 28:24.4. He joined Louis
Tewanima, another Native American who had
won the silver medal in the 10,000 meters in
1912, as the only Americans to garner medals
in the event. Mills also won national Amateur
Athletic Union (AAU) titles at three miles indoors
and six miles outdoors in 1965.

After retiring from running, Mills established
insurance and public relations firms in
California. From 1971 to 1974 he served as an
assistant commissioner of Indian affairs in the
Office of Recreation and Physical Fitness. In
that role, Mills revived the National Track and
Field Hall of Fame and the American Indian
Athletic Hall of Fame. In 1980 he founded the
Billy Mills Leadership Institute to improve social
and economic conditions of Native Americans.
The 1984 film, Running Brave, depicted
his rise to Olympic success.


Adam R. Hornbuckle
Alexandria, Virginia




Mills, Billy. Wokini: A Lakota Journey to Happiness and Self
Understanding. New York: Crown, 1994.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>