<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.081</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Texas</field>
      <field name="author">Prindle, David F.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




TEXAS

Although Texas includes a significant portion
of the Great Plains, its politics and government
have been far more heavily influenced
by two other geographic factors: its proximity
to Mexico and its situation in the southern
United States.

Texas was originally a northern province of
Spanish Mexico. After winning their independence
in 1821, Mexicans encouraged immigration
from the adjacent United States. This policy
backfired in 1836, however, when an army
of "Texian" Americans under the command of
Sam Houston vanquished a Mexican army
under General Santa Anna and achieved independence.
From that year to the modern era,
persons of Mexican descent have been at an
economic and political disadvantage in Texas.
Their increasing numbers, plus other historical
changes, however, have guaranteed their
continuing, and growing, importance in the
state.

From the revolution of 1836, when Texas
declared itself a republic, through 1845 when it
entered the United States, to the end of the
Civil War in 1865, the state experienced immigration
largely from other Southern states.
Southern white farmers, moving west, brought
their slaves and the economic, political, and
social institutions of slavery with them. Texas,
like the other Confederate states, was defeated
in the war and occupied in a humiliating fashion
by victorious Union troops during Reconstruction,
which in Texas lasted until 1874. As
with the other Southern states, this searing
historical experience exercised a dominating
influence over Texas society and institutions
for well over a century after the end of the war.

The Southern political culture that dominates
Texas even today can best be summarized
as "conservatism." With some noteworthy
exceptions, such as Lyndon Johnson,
Anglo-Texans have opposed an active government,
especially on behalf of the disadvantaged.
They have defined good government
largely in terms of low taxes; when taxes are
necessary they prefer the regressive variety,
such as sales taxes. Anglo-Texans have also
been extremely conservative on social issues.
Contemporary public opinion surveys reveal
that they oppose affirmative action and gay
rights, and support prayer in schools and the
death penalty, by wide margins.

As in the other Southern states, after the
Civil War Anglo-Texans prevented African
Americans from voting by statutes, customs,
and violence. The schemes created to prevent
black political participation also worked to
keep ballots out of the hands of Mexican
Americans and poor Anglos. The federal government
forced Texas to admit all of its adult
citizens to the franchise in the 1960s and 1970s,
but the legacy of the suppression of voting
rights lives on in the extremely low turnout of
the state's minority citizens.

The great Spindletop oil strike near Galveston
in 1901 inaugurated a period in which
Texas became one of the world's important
petroleum-producing provinces and the nation's
dominant producer. Production taxes
on oil and gas, in many years supplying a third
of state government revenue, reinforced the
resistance of the population to more direct
taxes.

The general conservatism of the dominant
Anglo population found further expression in
two institutional arrangements. First, Texas
was a one-party Democratic state until well
into the 1970s. Since the Texas Democratic
Party was usually dominated by reactionaries,
the one-party system served to reinforce the
control of dominant ethnic and economic interests.
Second, the state constitution of 1876,
written by white farmers nursing grievances
against the perceived tyranny of the justdeparted
Reconstruction regime, "disintegrates"
the executive, parceling out legislative
and administrative power among several independently
elected o.cials. The governor is
weak. Moreover, in seeking to foresee and prohibit
every possible misbehavior by state government,
the authors wrote in specifically circumscribed
grants of power and forbade
almost everything not mentioned in the document.
The result of this specificity has been
both a state government that does comparatively
little, and one that must amend the constitution
to meet every new contingency. As a
consequence, by the late 1990s the constitution,
at over 80,000 words, was the second longest
among the states and had been amended
more than 360 times.

At the turn of the twenty-first century,
Texas had a population of about twenty million,
making it the second most populous
state in the country. Its economy was robust
and diverse. The modernity and prosperity of
the state, however, existed alongside political
institutions and behaviors that exhibited
more apparent than real change.

Texas's petroleum production, the foundation
of its economy for most of the twentieth
century, declined steadily after the 1960s. By
the mid-1980s production taxes were supplying
less than 5 percent of state government
revenue. The legislature responded by raising
the sales tax, whose regressive impact fell most
heavily on the poor. Texas remained the only
large industrial state without an income tax.

When the national Democratic Party became
dominated by liberals in the 1960s, it set
in motion a slow party realignment among
the state's conservative Anglo population. Minority
citizens, now fully enfranchised, tended
to vote overwhelmingly Democratic, but they
still went to the polls in very low percentages.
This voluntary abstention meant that the generally
greater liberalism of African Americans
and Mexican Americans had little impact on
elections, and state government remained
conservative. By the mid-1990s Republicans
filled most state offices.

Nevertheless, the Mexican American portion
of Texas's population continues to grow
rapidly. If Mexican Americans and African
Americans ever began to go to the polls in
significant numbers, they could join with the
few liberal Anglos in a "rainbow coalition"
that might transform the state's politics. At
this writing, however, there is no sign that
such a transformation is imminent.

See also INDUSTRY: Petroleum, United States.


David F. Prindle
University of Texas at Austin




Barr, Alwyn. Black Texans: A History of African Americans
in Texas, 1528–1995. Norman: University of Oklahoma
Press, 1996. Kraemer, Richard H., Charldean Newell, and
David F. Prindle. Texas Politics. 8th ed. Belmont CA: West/
Wadsworth, 1999. Montejano, David. Anglos and Mexicans
in the Making of Texas, 1836–1986. Austin: University of
Texas Press, 1987.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>