<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.053</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Nebraska</field>
      <field name="author">Sittig, Robert</field>
      <field name="text">

 




NEBRASKA

The politics and government of Nebraska have
been inextricably linked to national events and
developments. Statehood was achieved on
March 1, 1867, after a decade of political tumult.
The major factor influencing the extended
debate over statehood was the heightening
slavery issue. Once the Civil War settled
the slavery argument, Nebraska moved from
territorial status, which it had gained with the
Louisiana Purchase in 1803, to full statehood,
and its governance became primarily a state
matter.

The original constitution, which had been
hastily drafted and adopted in 1866, proved
inadequate for the state, and it was replaced in
1875 with a more relevant document. This revision
proved satisfactory until events late in the
century, such as rapid population growth fueled
by immigration and widespread economic
deprivation in the agrarian sector,
strained the political system, and another major
constitutional update was approved in
1920. Finally, numerous piecemeal amendments
proposed by the legislature and the populace,
as well as two constitutional revision
commissions in the 1970s and 1990s, have kept
the structure and powers of state government
in step with changing political conditions.

The most distinguishing aspect of Nebraska's
governmental structure is the nonpartisan,
single-chamber legislature, adopted in
1934 via a popularly initiated constitutional
amendment. Its legacy stems from the progressive
and populist movements, which succeeded
in adopting numerous major policy innovations
around the turn of the twentieth
century. The unicameral campaign lagged until
it was taken up by U.S. senator George W.
Norris. Norris also logged an unmatched Nebraska
record of political achievement in the
national capitol, which included the legal recognition
of labor unions, rural electrification,
and regional riverbed development. The unicameral
legislature system, although widely
accepted in Nebraska and generally lauded by
political reformers, has not been adoptable in
the many states that have reviewed it recently.
The nonpartisan feature is less popular, but
numerous constitutional amendment attempts
to abolish it and revert to a partisan
arrangement have fallen short.

Nebraska's executive and judicial branches
currently reflect political reform trends evident
throughout state government. The governor's
office was very restricted prior to the
1920 constitutional changes that lifted the ban
on the creation of additional executive agencies,
and since the 1950s additional budgetary,
appointive, and veto powers have been implemented.
The effect of these changes has allowed
the governor to contend for leadership
in setting state policy. The major areas of judicial
improvement involve the selection of
judges through a three-stage state system of
peer nomination, governor appointment, and
voter retention, plus a centralization for administrative
purposes of all state and local
courts under the chief justice of the state supreme
court. Both of these changes came in
the 1970s. A major structural change to the
Nebraska courts occurred in 1991 after a constitutional
amendment was adopted that authorized
creation of an appeals court.

Nebraska's political culture instills in its citizenry
a mixed set of goals and expectations.
Normally the populace abides by a conservatism
that sustains long periods of public support
for existing political institutions, procedures,
and officialdoms. The calm is altered,
however, by occasional interruptions fueled
by deteriorating economic conditions, especially
in the farm sector. This accounts for the
long electoral sway the Republican Party has
enjoyed in the state's history, but there have
been intervals of Democratic preponderance,
most notably in the 1910s, 1930s, and again in
the 1970s and 1980s. Nebraskans espouse their
party membership (or lack thereof ) at voter
registration time, and in 1998 the tally found
the Republicans well ahead with 49 percent,
Democrats with 37 percent, and Independents
with 14 percent of the registered voters.

The state's population base has been nearly
flat for the past half-century and it currently
numbers about 1,711,000; this ranks it thirty-seventh
most populous among the states. Nebraska
was rapidly populated by immigrants
after the Civil War and was sustained by economic
largess until the Great Depression.
Since then, the combined effect of plentiful
underground water resources for the agricultural
sector and beneficial tax incentives
proffered by state and city governments for
businesses making capital investments has resulted
in a slightly upward movement in both
population and economic growth.

See also ARCHITECTURE: Nebraska State Capitol.


Robert Sittig
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Breckenridge, Adam C. One House for Two: Nebraska's
Unicameral Legislature. Washington DC: Public Affairs
Press, 1957. Miewald, Robert D., ed. Nebraska Government
and Politics. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1984.
Pedersen, James F., and Kenneth D. Wald. Shall the People
Rule? A History of the Democratic Party in Nebraska Politics,
1854-1972. Lincoln NE: J. North, 1973.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>