<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.law.023</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Jim Crow Laws</field>
      <field name="author">Barr, Alwyn Hales, Douglas</field>
      <field name="text">

 




JIM CROW LAWS


Drinking at a "colored" water cooler in a streetcar terminal, Oklahoma City, Oklahoma, July 1939


Elaborate discriminatory laws existed in Great
Plains states with large African American populations
such as Texas, Oklahoma, and Kansas, while Nebraska, Colorado, Wyoming, and
Montana, with smaller minority populations,
created limited and often unenforced segregation
laws. Because of small African American
populations, North and South Dakota created
no such laws. Except for Texas and Oklahoma,
with their large rural African American populations
and Southern views of race relations,
Plains states applied segregation laws almost
entirely in towns. Other forms of segregation
in these states existed as a matter of custom.
Hispanic Americans and Native Americans
also faced discriminatory laws.

Texas adopted a state constitution in 1876
that required segregated schools for African
Americans. Some local school districts also segregated
Hispanic students. The legislature in
1876 allowed jury commissions that could eliminate
African American jurors. In 1891 the legislature
allowed segregated railroad cars. Six
years later it outlawed interracial sexual relations.
Texas added a constitutional amendment
in 1902 requiring a poll tax for voting that fell
primarily on working-class African Americans
and Hispanics. In 1903 a new election law allowed
political parties to exclude minorities
from white primaries. Texas strengthened that
law in 1923. Several towns segregated public accommodations
and transportation. Some West
Texas counties excluded African American settlers
by customs known as "sundown laws."

The first Oklahoma state constitution in
1907 segregated public schools. The legislature
added laws segregating transportation and
forbidding intermarriage. Oklahoma later
segregated various public accommodations,
while some towns segregated residential areas.
In 1910 the state adopted a literacy test and
a grandfather clause to disfranchise African
Americans. Both measures were declared unconstitutional
by the U.S. Supreme Court in
1915 in Guinn and Beal v. United States.

Segregation laws in Kansas dealt primarily
with education. The state constitution of 1859
specified separate African American schools.

Soon the Kansas legislature created county
school districts in which African Americans
could attend white schools if no separate institution
existed. In 1874 the state passed a civil
rights law that forbade segregated schools.
Five years later the legislature revised the
school code to allow towns of 15,000 population
to establish separate primary schools for
African Americans. Secondary schools were
segregated only in Wyandotte County. African
Americans challenged segregated schools, but
the Kansas Supreme Court upheld the segregation
statute.

Wyoming passed a law allowing a school
segregation law in 1899. In 1913 the state made
miscegenation a misdemeanor. Nebraska
passed a similar law against miscegenation in
1911. While some de facto segregation existed
in the state, no other Jim Crow measures became
law in Nebraska.

Montana, with its large Native American
population, denied voting rights to persons
under federal "guardianship" in 1871 and forbade
voter precincts on reservations. In 1889
the state opened voting to all male persons
except Native Americans. After the federal Indian
Citizenship Act of 1924, Montana divided
counties into at-large districts to dilute the
impact of Native American voters. In 1937 the
state ruled that all deputy voter registrars
must be taxpaying residents of their precincts.
Since Native Americans were exempt from
some local taxes, they could not act as voter
registrars, and tribal voter registration was effectively
limited.

In the early twentieth century Jim Crow
laws on the Plains began to face challenges.
Important court cases included those in Texas
that outlawed the white primary by the early
1940s. After earlier court cases in Texas eliminated
Hispanic school segregation and Texas
and Oklahoma cases outlawed segregation at
the law school/graduate school level, the U.S.
Supreme Court in Brown v. The Board of Education
of Topeka ruled against legal school segregation
on the basis of race in 1954.

See also AFRICAN AMERICANS: Civil Rights.


Alwyn Barr
Douglas Hales
Texas Tech University




Barr, Alwyn. Black Texans: A History of African Americans in Texas, 1528–1995. Norman: University of Oklahoma
Press, 1996. Svingen, Orlan J. "Jim Crow, Indian Style,
1980s." In Peoples of Color in the American West, edited by
Sucheng Chan, Douglas Daniels, Mario T. Garcia, and
Terry P. Wilson. Lexington KY: D. C. Heath and Company,
1994: 352–63. Taylor, Quintard. In Search of the Racial Frontier: African Americans in the American West, 1528– 1990. New York: W. W. Norton, 1998.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>