<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pd.053</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Trial of Standing Bear</field>
      <field name="author">Smith, Dennis J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




TRIAL OF STANDING BEAR

On May 12, 1879, in Omaha, Nebraska, in the
U.S. Circuit Court for the District of Nebraska,
Judge Elmer Dundy ruled that noncitizen
Indians–in this case, a group of Poncas
led by Chief Standing Bear–were defined
as persons in terms of federal law and entitled
to review under habeas corpus protections (a
constitutionally based appeal used to determine
whether a person is restrained or imprisoned
without due process). The writ of
habeas corpus specifically stated that Standing
Bear and his followers had withdrawn from
the Ponca tribe. Standing Bear's case not only
played a central role in four crucial decades of
Ponca-federal relations, but it also directly influenced
landmark Indian policy changes of
the 1880s.

In an 1858 treaty, the Poncas ceded all their
lands except for a small reservation (in presentday
northeastern Nebraska) on the lower Niobrara
River. Dutifully taking up farming the
white man's way, the Poncas endured terrible
hardships when their crops regularly failed and
Indian agency supplies remained woefully inadequate.
Yet their long-standing friendship
with the United States failed to prevent their
forced removal to Indian Territory in the
spring of 1877. The Poncas' conditions worsened
due to the Office of Indian Affairs' complete
lack of preparation for their arrival–no
lands had been reserved and no appropriation
secured to provide food, clothing, and housing.
As many as 200 Poncas died from related
hardships. In January 1879 Standing Bear and
twenty-nine others fled back to their Nebraska
homeland. When they reached the Omaha reservation
in March, the U.S. Army arrested
them and escorted them to Fort Omaha (located
four miles north of Omaha, Nebraska).

On March 30 Omaha Daily Herald assistant
editor Thomas Henry Tibbles interviewed
Standing Bear and dispatched a stream of features
to newspapers in Chicago, New York,
and other eastern cities. Tibbles also inaugurated
a legal challenge against Standing Bear's
arrest, obtaining the services of two prominent
Omaha attorneys, John Lee Webster and
A. J. Poppleton. In May, Judge Dundy delivered
his extraordinary ruling that habeas corpus
safeguards applied to Standing Bear, even
though as a Native American he was a noncitizen
and in spite of the fact that for all practical
purposes he had renounced his Ponca
tribal affiliation. Moreover, because federal
statutes authorized the army to deliver prisoners
only to civil authorities, making the
Ponca detainment at Fort Omaha illegal,
Dundy ordered Standing Bear and the Poncas
released and directed that there would be no
appeals to a higher court.

Judge Dundy's bold decision protected
Standing Bear's Poncas from being returned
to Indian Territory, but it provided no lands
for them. In 1890 they finally secured allotments
on their former reservation. Equally
important, Standing Bear's struggle for justice
significantly influenced the national movement
to reform Indian policy. In the fall of
1879 Tibbles featured Standing Bear on a
highly successful Indian reform tour that included
Chicago, Boston, New York, Philadelphia,
and Washington. In Boston, Standing
Bear's eloquence so impressed Massachusetts
senator Henry L. Dawes that he plunged into
the Indian reform movement. He joined the
Senate Indian Affairs Committee, and his
leadership on Indian issues and prominence
on the popular issue of Indian assimilation led
directly to passage of the 1887 General Allotment
(or Dawes) Act. Standing Bear lived on
his family allotment on the Niobrara until his
death in 1908.

See also NATIVE AMERICANS: Poncas; Standing Bear.


Dennis J. Smith
Morningside College




Hoxie, Frederick E. A Final Promise: The Campaign to
Assimilate the Indians, 1880–1920. Lincoln: University of
Nebraska Press, 1984. Lake, James A., Sr. "Standing Bear,
Who?" Nebraska Law Review 60 (1981): 451–503. Tibbles,
Thomas Henry. The Ponca Chiefs: An Account of the Trial
of Standing Bear, edited by Kay Graber. Lincoln: University
of Nebraska Press, 1972.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>