<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.071</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Small Presses</field>
      <field name="author">Kooser, Ted</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SMALL PRESSES

Small, independent publishers have been an
important presence in the Great Plains since
the mid–nineteenth century. During the early
days of settlement, nearly every small town
had its independent publisher, putting out
community newspapers, political pamphlets,
collections of sermons, church circle cookbooks,
and, occasionally, for a price, a slim
volume of poetry.

The principal difference today is that printing.
or, better, reproduced writing.has become
much less costly and more accessible to
people who want to publish their own writing
or the work of authors they admire. Until the
early to middle years of the twentieth century,
aspiring independent publishers had nothing
to work with but time-devouring, hand-set
lead type and manually operated, sheet-fed
printing presses. Offset lithography eventually
became the preferable option, but it was coste.
cient only when large numbers of printed
materials were ordered, and most small press
entrepreneurs did not have the wherewithal to
distribute large press runs.

In recent years, inexpensive typesetting
programs for home computers and a proliferation
of neighborhood copy centers have
made an enormous difference to aspiring
publishers. Len Fulton, longtime publisher
of the annual directory of small presses published
by Dustbooks, reports that at the end of
1997 his database showed 195 independent
publishers and 73 self-publishers located in
the American Plains states. A few of these
publishers adhere for aesthetic reasons to
original printing technology, creating beautiful
limited editions using hand-set type and
even handmade paper. These presses, which
might publish editions of, for example, 200
stapled chapbooks or 2,000 perfect-bound
books, have traditionally specialized in the
noncommercial market, offering writing of
high literary quality that may be too esoteric
for established publishers.

The quality of writing published by small,
independent publishers varies greatly, but
many noted writers got their start in Great
Plains literary magazines such as Cutbank
(Montana) and the Cottonwood Review (Kansas).
Native American writers such as James
Welch, Diane Glancy, Elizabeth Cook-Lynn,
and others appeared in Great Plains small
presses long before it became fashionable for
eastern literary houses to publish them. As a
young, aspiring writer, the important Native
American writer Louise Erdrich worked for a
time for Plains Distribution Service, a group
of small press people dedicated to getting the
publications of small, independent presses
and authors into bookstores and the hands of
readers.

In Canada, small independent presses have
also allowed writers to have their say. Perhaps
more important are the independent presses,
small by U.S. standards but midsize for Canada,
that, with the support of Canada Council
and provincial writers guilds, publish much of
the innovative writing of the Prairies. These
include Edmonton's NeWest, Saskatoon's Fifth
House, Winnipeg's Peguis and Turnstone, and
Regina's Coteau.


Ted Kooser
Garland, Nebraska





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>