<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.war.037</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Red River Resistance</field>
      <field name="author">Ens, Gerhard J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




RED RIVER RESISTANCE

In 1869 the Métis of Red River, led by Louis
Riel, formed a provisional government to stop
the Canadian annexation of Rupert's Land.
This territory, encompassing most of today's
Prairie Provinces, was under Hudson's Bay
Company rule and was scheduled to be transferred
to Canada in 1869. During the negotiations
between the company, the British government,
and the Canadian government for
the transfer of sovereignty, no one consulted
the Métis, who were the vast majority of the
12,000 residents in the Red River Settlement in
the present-day province of Manitoba. Worried
about their status in the new Dominion,
the Métis took matters into their own hands.

During the summer of 1869, the Métis,
comprised of English-speaking Protestant
"mixed-bloods" and French-speaking Catholic
Métis, held several public meetings to
determine how to respond to the proposed
transfer. Two competing factions emerged.
One, led by William Dease, argued that the
Métis should form a provisional government
and negotiate with Canada on the basis of
their Aboriginal rights. Louis Riel and the
Catholic clergy led a second faction, who argued
that the transfer represented the annexation
of Red River Settlement by Protestant
Ontario and threatened the religious rights of
the Catholic Métis. Controlling the largest
army, and having the Catholic Church on his
side, Riel triumphed in this power struggle. In
early November 1869 he seized Upper Fort
Garry and effective control of the settlement.

Riel and his Métis supporters suppressed
internal dissension in the settlement by imprisoning
dozens of Métis opponents and Canadians,
and then forged a consensus by calling
a number of representative conventions.
In January 1870 Red River residents elected a
representative provisional government to negotiate
the terms of their entry into the Dominion.
The resulting Manitoba Act of 1870
created the province of Manitoba, guaranteed
the property rights of the Métis, provided for
bilingual institutions and denominational
schools to protect the interests of the Catholic
Church, and granted 1.4 million acres of land
to Métis children.

The Manitoba Act and Manitoba's entry
into the Dominion was a victory for the Red
River Métis that Riel was unable to enjoy. During
the Resistance, which lasted from October
1869 until August of 1870, Riel's provisional
government had executed an Ontario Orangeman
by the name of Thomas Scott. This act
made it politically impossible for the Canadian
government to grant Riel's government
an unconditional amnesty for actions taken
during the Resistance. Riel fled to the United
States in August 1870 when Canadian troops
arrived in Manitoba.

See also POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT: Manitoba / PROTEST AND DISSENT: Riel, Louis.


Gerhard J. Ens
University of Alberta




Ens, Gerhard J. "Prologue to the Red River Resistance:
Pre-liminal Politics and the Triumph of Riel." Journal of
the Canadian Historical Association 5 (1994): 111–23. Stanley,
George F. G. Louis Riel. Toronto: Ryerson Press, 1963.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>