<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.rel.014</field>
      <field name="titleMain">De Smet, Pierre-Jean (1801-1873)</field>
      <field name="author">Carriker, Robert C.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




DE SMET, PIERRE-JEAN (1801-1873)


Pierre-Jean De Smet, ca. 1864


As a missionary to the West, Pierre-Jean De
Smet, S.J., had no equal among nineteenthcentury
Catholics. Born on January 30, 1801,
to a wealthy family in East Flanders (Belgium),
De Smet journeyed to America in 1821
to join the Society of Jesus, or Jesuits, an order
of Catholic men with a special interest in missions
and education. Following more than a
decade of religious formation, De Smet began
his missionary career in 1838 when he established
Saint Joseph's Mission for members of
the Potawatomi tribe at Council Bluffs. From
that date until his death, De Smet baptized
many thousands of Native Americans in more
than thirty tribes. He traveled some 180,000
miles, including seventeen trips across the Atlantic
Ocean, in his efforts to educate others
about the spiritual condition of Native Americans,
and he ultimately raised more than a half
million dollars on their behalf.

For thirty years, in nineteen journeys taken
between 1838 and 1868, De Smet traversed the
Great Plains from all points of the compass
and during all seasons of the year. Intimately
familiar with the drainage basins of both the
Missouri and Columbia Rivers, De Smet favored
the Great Plains because he believed
that the natural environment offered exceptional
advantages to potential settlers. He used
terms like "superb" and "smiling and beautiful" to describe the richness of the environment
in letters to his family and others in Europe.
De Smet encountered the Niobrara,
White Earth, and Little Medicine Rivers in his
travels in the Great Plains, but it was the attributes
of the Missouri and the Platte that
received most of the attention in his extensive
journals. An avid amateur scientist, De Smet
was also a close observer of the region's flora,
fauna, and geology.

After 1851 the question of how to reconcile
the needs of white pioneers with the rights of
Native Americans vexed De Smet. The key to
his solution, which he offered several times to
high government officials, including President
Abraham Lincoln, centered on isolating tribes
for a minimum of twenty years while missionaries
added elements of "practical civilization"
to their already crowded workload of spiritual
salvation.

De Smet passed away at his room in the
Jesuit community at St. Louis University on
May 23, 1873. His ideas, observations, and predictions
about the trans-Mississippi western
frontier survive in four published books and
hundreds of personal letters preserved in archives
in Belgium, St. Louis, Missouri, and
Pullman, Washington.


Robert C. Carriker
Gonzaga University




Carriker, Robert. "Admiring Advocate of the Great Plains:
Father Pierre-Jean De Smet, S.J., on the Middle Missouri."
Great Plains Quarterly 14 (1994): 243–56. Carriker, Robert
C. Father Peter John De Smet, S.J.: Jesuit in the West.
Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1995. Chittenden,
Hiram Martin, and Alfred Talbot Richardson, eds. Life,
Letters and Travels of Father Pierre-Jean De Smet, S.J., 1801–1873.
New York: Francis P. Harper, 1905.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>