<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.war.002</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Adobe Walls, Battle of</field>
      <field name="author">Tate, Michael L.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ADOBE WALLS, BATTLE OF

Photograph caption: "No. 1 Ranch road leading down into Adobe Walls Creek valley on north side of spur"


This battle between buffalo hunters and
approximately 700 Comanche, Kiowa, and
Southern Cheyenne warriors resulted in an Indian
defeat, one among several during the
course of the large-scale military operation
known as the Red River War of 1874-75. Inspired
by a recent Sun Dance and Comanche
medicine man Isatai's promise of easy victory,
the warriors sought to inflict a mortal blow
against the hated buffalo hunters who were
destroying the vast southern herds in the Texas
Panhandle. The young Comanche Quanah
Parker joined Isatai as nominal leaders of the
raid against the twenty-eight men and one
woman residing in Adobe Walls, a small complex
of trading stores and a saloon in presentday
Hutchinson County, Texas.

During the early dawn hours of June 27,
1874, the Indians attacked the residents,
quickly killing two hunters who were sleeping
in a wagon. The others were alerted immediately
because they had remained awake during
the night while repairing a broken beam in
the saloon. They held off several assaults, losing
only two other defenders–one to Indian
gunfire and one to the accidental discharge of a
rifle. The siege continued for five days. Indian
casualties mounted to several dozen, and faith
in Isatai's power faded. On the second day of
the siege, Billy Dixon fired his fabled shot, hitting
a mounted warrior fully eight-tenths of
a mile away. Following abandonment of the
Adobe Walls settlement six weeks later, the Indians
burned it to the ground. Yet the battle
had been a bitter setback for them, and it presaged
the larger defeat that would soon follow
at the hands of the army.

See also NATIVE AMERICANS: Parker, Quanah.


Michael L. Tate
University of Nebraska at Omaha




Dixon, Olive K. Life of "Billy" Dixon. Dallas: P. L. Turner
Co., 1927. Gard, Wayne. The Great Buffalo Hunt. New
York: Alfred A. Knopf, Inc., 1959. Haley, James L. The
Buffalo War. New York: Doubleday and Co., 1976.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>