<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fol.016</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Folk Songs</field>
      <field name="author">Logsdon, Guy</field>
      <field name="text">

 




FOLK SONGS

Folk songs are words and music transmitted
orally from one generation to another within
particular groups; usually there are musical
and textual variants of the songs. However, in
the twentieth century, recorded sound and the
printed word made it possible for folk songs
to be learned outside the traditional group experiences,
and they also reduced the number
of variants that accompanied the oral transmission
process. Folk songs can be ballads–
songs that tell a story; folk songs can be lyrical–
songs that communicate an emotion
without necessarily telling a story; and folk
songs can be functional–lullabies, songs for
dancing, play-party songs, work songs, and
songs that enhance other human activities.
For many decades it was a common belief that
folk songs were perpetuated and sung only by
the illiterate and that only art and popular
songs had cultural merit. That uninformed
criticism has been slow in disappearing.

The groups in which traditional songs
evolve are families, communities, churches,
occupations, ethnic, regional, and many others.
Great Plains folk songs, therefore, are
diverse, including a wide variety of Native
American songs that were inspired by musical
sounds in nature. Other traditional songs,
mostly of western European origin, came with
the expansion of the western frontier. They
include those from Spanish traditions that initially
dominated the Southern Plains, but
which by the twenty-first century had moved
into the central and northern portions of the
region. Mexican corridos (ballads) and other
Hispanic songs are now heard throughout the
Great Plains along with Anglo-American and
African American spirituals, Czech polkas,
Germanic or Scandinavian songs and schottisches,
a wide variety of fiddling tunes and
styles, blues, Southeast Asian music, klezmer
(Jewish) music, and the music of numerous
other ethnic and immigrant groups. However,
the most widely known or recognized folk
songs are those that have their origins in English,
Scottish, and Irish song.

Folk songs also can be associated with singing
styles, influenced by the openness of the
Great Plains–no tight throat sounds emerged
here–in contrast to the vocals from the mountain
regions of the South. Even ethnic groups
modified singing styles to the expanses of the
Plains by adopting open vocals.

By the 1960s folk songs had acquired a
broader definition and included songs that
had not gone through the long oral transmission
process but were written and/or sung by
individuals who referred to themselves as
folksingers. A musician with a guitar or at
least a banjo singing a ballad was a "folksinger";
often social protest songs were defined
as folk songs, even though their life expectancy
was sometimes no longer than the
duration of the topic being protested. Long
before this popular interpretation evolved,
however, two specific folk-song groups had
emerged from specific Great Plains experiences:
cowboy and western songs and songs
about the dust storms.

The cattle industry is one of the oldest European
American commercial ventures in the
Plains, dating back to early Spanish explorations when cattle and horses were brought to
the North American continent. The romanticized
American cowboy who emerged after
the Civil War capitalized on the traditions of
the Hispanic industry, using their tools, techniques,
and vocabulary. However, cowboy
songs came from southern traditions and
were based on the old English, Scottish, and
Irish songs sung throughout the South. In recent
decades, historians and pop culturalists
have shown African American influences on
traditional cowboy songs, but the western European
song style had greater influence on African
American song during the late nineteenth
century than did African American
song style on cowboy songs.

The cowboy idiom did not mature until the
early 1870s, at which time songs with a cowboy
theme appeared. Cowboys had been singing
the popular parlor and folk songs of the day, as
well as hymns; in short, a cowboy song was
anything a cowboy wanted to sing. The most
popular was "The Old Chisholm Trail," an English
lyrical song that dates to as early as 1640
and was modified by the cowboy idiom. Most
of the songs that came from the post.Civil
War trail-drive days were either tragedy or
humor, the two faces of drama; there were very
few lyrical songs, and most of those were written
by unknown poets. However, Montana
poet D. J. O'Malley wrote a few poems in the
1880s and 1890s, such as "When the Work's All
Done This Fall," that were set to music by unknown
musicians. In the early 1900s South Dakota
poet Charles Badger Clark Jr. wrote "Border
Affair," which was later adapted to a folk
song, and New Mexico cowboy N. Howard
"Jack" Thorp wrote "Little Joe, the Wrangler"
in 1898, which also was adapted to a folk song.
Some cowboy folk songs were bawdy, and most
working cowboys did not (and do not) have
outstanding singing voices. Some of their singing
would start a stampede, not settle down the
cattle.

The cowboy became the folk hero of the
nation, and a romanticized singing cowboy
enhanced the image. In the mid-1930s Hollywood
developed the singing-cowboy movie
genre for Gene Autry, who started his career
as the "Oklahoma Yodeling Cowboy." Soon
other singing cowboys were featured in the
movie houses. Some of the songs they sang,
along with those on records, entered the oral
transmission process and are considered by
some singers to be folk songs; indeed, a few of
the songs, such as "Cool Water," "Tumbling
Tumbleweeds," or "Riding Down the Canyon,"
have become traditional songs of the
cowboy and the Plains. The cowboy singing
and songwriting traditions have been continued
into the twenty-first century by numerous
performers such as the popular horseman-
singer-songwriter Ian Tyson of Alberta.

Cowboys love to dance; each cow town had
dance halls, and they were not always associated
with saloons. In the 1920s Bob Wills, a
fiddle-playing son of a cotton farmer in West
Texas, started playing ranch-house dances.
His desire to play dances eventually developed
a dance genre known as western swing.
While the music has elements of jazz and
blues, it actually evolved from the specific
merger of cowboy and farmer folk song and
instrumentation.

In the early 1930s, when drought struck the
Great Plains and continued through the decade,
the Southern High Plains was designated
the "Dust Bowl." Woody Guthrie was
born and reared in Okemah, Oklahoma, but
moved to Pampa, Texas, in 1929. There he experienced
the Dust Bowl storms that devastated
farms, ranches, and towns from Canada
to Mexico; his songs "So Long, It's Been Good
to Know You," "Talking Dust Bowl," "Do, Re,
Mi," "Dust Can't Kill Me," and many more
chronicle the era, as does his autobiographical
novel, Bound for Glory (1943). Guthrie and his
Great Plains songs were instrumental in creating
the folk-song revival that swept the nation
in the 1950s and 1960s. In such ways, the folk
songs of the Great Plains are cultural contributions
to the world of music, and they will be
sung and played as long as there is music in
the soul of mankind.

See also FILM: Autry, Gene / 
MUSIC: Cowboy Music; Guthrie, Woody; 
Wills, Bob.


Guy Logsdon
Tulsa, Oklahoma




Guthrie, Woody. Bound for Glory. New York: E. P. Dutton
and Co., 1943. Logsdon, Guy. "The Whorehouse Bells Were Ringing" and Other Songs Cowboys Sing. Urbana: University
of Illinois Press, 1989. Lomax, Alan. The Folk Songs of North America. Garden City NY: Doubleday and Co., 1960.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>