<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.gen.045</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Women Warriors</field>
      <field name="author">Lang, Sabine</field>
      <field name="text">

 




WOMEN WARRIORS

Raiding and warfare were an integral part of
the men's role among Plains Indian nations,
but it was by no means uncommon for women
to engage in these activities as well. Their motivations
were the same as those of the men:
revenge, defense, and a desire for prestige and
wealth. Most frequently, a woman would join
or even lead a war party in order to take revenge
for relatives slain by some enemy.
Women would also take up arms to defend
their camp against hostile intruders. In other
cases, women, by means of visions, received
the command to go to war. Capturing horses
and other property on a raid also brought great
prestige to both men and women.

The term "woman warrior," while commonplace,
is misleading. To be a warrior was a
lifetime occupation for Plains Indian men, but
most women who went to war did not pursue a
warrior's life permanently. Many women went
to war only once or twice in their lives. Others
were married and accompanied their husbands
on war or raiding parties, especially
while the couple was still young and childless.
Some women served as sentries and messengers;
others fought in battle alongside the
men, counted coup, and took scalps. Eventually,
they quit warring and raiding, raised
children, and did their share of work within
the gendered division of labor. In this they
differed from the female two-spirits, or berdaches,
who took up the culturally defined
man's role completely and permanently.

In some cases, however, success as a warrior
would pave a woman's way to a quasi-masculine
role and status. The war deeds of Woman
Chief, who lived among the Crow around
1850, were so daring that the men invited her
to join their council meetings, where she
ranked as the third leading warrior in a group
of 160 lodges. She became an accomplished
trader and hunter and eventually married
four wives, who processed the hides and did
the other standard women's chores around
her lodge. Another example is Brown Weasel
Woman, a Piegan female warrior. A major
battle with an enemy tribe brought her–the
only female in her tribe's history to be so
honored–a man's name, Running Eagle, that
was reserved for famous warriors.

The role of the woman warrior was socially
accepted wherever it occurred among the
Plains nations. The same holds true for other
role alternatives in which women could gain
prestige by exhibiting behavior culturally defined
as masculine. The prestige system of the
Plains cultures was clearly male-dominated,
centering on warlike activities and personality
traits considered masculine. It is true that
Plains Indian women could gain great prestige
by excelling in women's occupations such as
beadwork and agriculture, by assuming certain
roles in ceremonies, and by expressing
culturally valued ideals of femininity. Yet the
masculine prestige system was the measure for
both sexes. Even feminine achievements were
sometimes expressed in masculine terms.
Within that system, however, women could
compete for the prestige associated with war
and raiding on equal terms with men and did
so if they had the inclination.


Sabine Lang
Hamburg, Germany




Hungry Wolf, Beverly. The Ways of My Grandmothers. New
York: Quill Books, 1982. Lang, Sabine. Men as Women, Women as Men: Changing Gender in Native American Cultures.
Austin: University of Texas Press, 1998. Medicine,
Beatrice. "'Warrior Women': Sex Role Alternatives for
Plains Indian Women." In The Hidden Half: Studies of Plains Indian Women, edited by Patricia Albers and Beatrice
Medicine. Washington DC: University Press of America,
1983: 267–80.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>