<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ct.054</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Urban Indian Reserves</field>
      <field name="author">Wheeler, Winona</field>
      <field name="text">

 




URBAN INDIAN RESERVES

Reserve towns are not as prevalent on the Canadian
Prairies as reservation towns are on
the U.S. Plains. However, the recent development
of urban Indian reserves is unique. In
2000 there were fourteen urban reserves in
Saskatchewan, one each in Manitoba and Alberta,
with more in the planning stage. The
number of urban reserves in the Canadian
Prairies will continue to increase.

Following the treaty process (1871–77),
many reserve surveys allowed for the development
of village sites. Churches and the
Hudson's Bay Company, for example, often
secured lots on reserves, and over time small
villages grew around them. Non-Indian town
sites on alienated reserve lands were established
as a result of the land rush accompanying
the building of the Canadian Pacific Railway.
Many Indian reserves within the railway
belt were subject to expropriation for railway
right-of-ways or to accommodate growing
municipalities. The town of Hobbema
(population 9,000), for example, is situated
on lands once reserved for the Samson First
Nation in the Bear Hills (Maskwacîsihk), Alberta.
The reserve was surveyed in 1881 but a
few years later fell within the reach of the proposed
Edmonton-Calgary line. Reserve lands
were expropriated or surrendered to accommodate
the line and siding (train station landings
and town sites).

Often urban pressures resulted in the loss of
entire reserves. Papascase First Nation was
surveyed in 1884 well beyond the city limits
of Edmonton, but the railway line and the urban
explosion soon targeted it for future development.
Within a few years most of the
band members enfranchised (withdrew from
treaty), and their reserve was surrendered. The
Mill Woods area, south of 51st Avenue and
north of the Tourist Information Centre, sits
on the surrendered Papascase reserve. Often
First Nations surrendered reserves after relentless
pressures from government officials and
local settlers; sometimes the legalities of the
appropriations were questionable.

In Saskatchewan, very few reserves were
established near settler villages and towns
largely because federal Indian policies for the
Prairies were developed to facilitate clearing
the fertile region for railway and settlement
and to suppress First Nations' resistance to
treaties and their demands for the creation
of a large Cree-Assiniboine territory in the
southern Prairies. The Plains Cree movement
was crushed in 1885, and the disbanded dissenters
were removed to small, isolated reserves
north of the railway belt.

More recently, urbanization and economic
diversification trends have precipitated First
Nations' investments in urban properties.
Currently, there are two types of urban First
Nations landholdings: those subject to municipal
jurisdiction like other private holdings,
and those that have been converted to
Indian reserve status, now referred to as urban
reserves.

The process by which lands are converted
to reserve status is defined by two instruments:
section 9.3.2 of the 1987 Additions to
Reserves Policy of the Department of Indian
Affairs and Northern Development, and article
9 of the 1992 Saskatchewan Treaty Land
Entitlement Framework Agreement, a comprehensive
land claims agreement between
Saskatchewan First Nations, the federal government,
and the province of Saskatchewan.
Both instruments were precipitated by First
Nations' specific and Treaty Land Entitlement
claims. Once transformed into Indian
reserves, urban reserves are subject to the Indian
Act and have the same legal status as
rural Indian reserves: they are held in trust by
the federal government, fall under First Nations
jurisdiction, and are exempt from municipal
and provincial taxation and most laws.

While formal agreements between First Nations
and municipalities are not required,
they are encouraged and are becoming the
norm. Comprehensive agreements between
First Nations and municipalities address a
range of substantive issues: the application
and enforcement of provincial and municipal
laws and their compatibility with First Nations
bylaws; compensation for lost tax revenue;
First Nation taxation jurisdiction over
Indian and non-Indian residents; service delivery
(for example, sewage, water, garbage
disposal) to urban reserves; and dispute-resolution
mechanisms.

In January 1997 the Centre for Municipal-
Aboriginal Relations (CMAR) was created by
the Federation of Canadian Municipalities
and the Indian Taxation Advisory Board.
cmar serves as a clearinghouse and resource
center and undertakes applied research in the
area of municipal-Aboriginal relations.

See also NATIVE AMERICANS: Reserves.


Winona Wheeler
Saskatchewan Indian Federated College




Barron, F. Laurie, and Joseph Garcia, eds. Urban Indian Reserves: Forging New Relationships in Saskatchewan. Saskatoon:
Purich Publishing, 1999. Tobias, John L. "The
Subjugation of the Plains Cree, 1879–1885." Canadian Historical Review 64 (1983): 519–48.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>