<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.tra.019</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Lincoln Highways</field>
      <field name="author">Ahlgren, Carol</field>
      <field name="text">

 




LINCOLN HIGHWAY

The Lincoln Highway, one of the United
States' major historic east–west routes, crosses
the Great Plains states of Nebraska and Wyoming.
Referred to as the nation's first transcontinental
highway, it originated in 1912
when automobile manufacturers and businessmen
formed the Lincoln Highway Association
in Detroit. The highway was intended
to be a paved, toll-free memorial to Abraham
Lincoln that would offer the most direct route
from New York to San Francisco. In 1913 the
route was designated along existing roads
through twelve states: New York, New Jersey,
Pennsylvania, Ohio, Indiana, Illinois,
Iowa, Nebraska, Wyoming, Utah, Nevada, and
California.

The Lincoln Highway entered Nebraska at
Omaha and followed section line roads through
small towns in the historic transportation corridor
of the Platte River valley. The highway
closely paralleled the Union Pacific main line,
nineteenth-century immigrant trails, and a portion
of the Pony Express route. The route of the
Lincoln Highway evolved as segments were
straightened and improved. In some places it is
still possible to find one or more versions of the
highway as gravel section line roads, brick
streets, and abandoned roadbed along the
Union Pacific tracks.

From 1913 until it disbanded in 1928, the
Lincoln Highway Association mounted a national
publicity campaign to raise funds to
mark and improve the route. A network of
state and local boosters, or "counsels," was established
to aid in these efforts. In addition to
publishing a series of guidebooks that provided
maps and described road conditions,
the association encouraged towns and cities
along the route to rename appropriate streets
as "Lincoln Way." Kearney, Nebraska, for example,
renamed the route through the city on
Central Avenue as Lincoln Way. Although the
name has since reverted in Kearney, the route
through downtown Cheyenne, Wyoming, is
still known as Lincoln Way.

Another promotional effort of the Lincoln
Highway Association was the sponsorship of
"seedling miles." These demonstration road
segments varied in length from one to several
miles and were constructed with portland cement
using funds supplied by the Lincoln
Highway Association and local organizations.
Seedling miles were constructed in Ohio, Illinois,
Indiana, Iowa, and Nebraska. The program
was implemented between 1915 and 1917.
When seedling miles were constructed at Fremont,
Grand Island, and Kearney, the concrete
road segments represented some of the
only pavement along hundreds of miles of the
Lincoln Highway from Nebraska west.

By the late 1920s, when the federal highway
numbering system went into effect, the work of
the Lincoln Highway Association was largely
finished. Through the years, federal and state
funds had aided in the improvement of the
route. Before it disbanded, the Lincoln Highway
Association lobbied to have the Lincoln
Highway's new designation as U.S. Route 30
apply to the entire transcontinental route. Instead,
U.S. Route 30 diverged from the Lincoln
Highway in western Wyoming to continue
north and east to Portland, Oregon. Meanwhile,
the Lincoln Highway became a series of
federal and regional routes through western
Wyoming, Nevada, and Utah, terminating at
Lincoln Park in San Francisco.


Carol Ahlgren
National Park Service




Ahlgren, Carol, and David Anthone. "The Lincoln Highway
in Nebraska: The Pioneer Trail of the Automotive
Age." Nebraska History 73 (1992): 173-79. Hokanson,
Drake. The Lincoln Highway: Main Street across America.
Iowa City: University of Iowa Press, 1988. Lincoln Highway
Association. The Complete Official Road Guide of the
Lincoln Highway. Tucson AZ: Patrice Press, 1993.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>