<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ea.034</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Simpson, George (1787-1860)</field>
      <field name="author">Wishart, David J.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




SIMPSON, GEORGE (1787-1860)

Sir George Simpson, in his role as governor
of the Hudson's Bay Company territories in
North America from 1826 to 1860, had a major
impact on the development of the Canadian
Prairies. He visited the region frequently, inspecting
posts, meeting with the chief factors
who supervised each district, organizing the
government of the Red River Settlement in
Assiniboia (which the Hudson's Bay Company
had originally granted to the Earl of Selkirk in
1812, then reacquired in 1836), or simply passing
through rapidly, as he did on his journey
to the Columbia River in 1824–25.

Simpson was suited for a life spent in remote
places (although after 1833, following his
marriage to his cousin Frances Ramsey Simpson,
he was based at Lachine, near Montreal),
having been born in distant Rosshire, Scotland,
in 1787. As a young man he clerked for a
London firm that did business in the West
Indies. He must have impressed, because in
1820 the Hudson's Bay Company sent him to
Canada as a possible replacement for Governor
William Williams, who seemed likely to
be arrested in the conflict with the North West
Company. After the two companies amalgamated
in 1821, Simpson was appointed governor
of the Northern Department. Five years
later he was put in charge of the entire North
American operations.

Governor Simpson was an autocratic administrator
who prioritized economy and efficiency.
Immediately following the 1821 merger
he inaugurated a series of reforms akin to
modern-day corporate restructuring. He radically
reduced the number of employees, closed
unproductive posts, and overhauled the transportation
system. He cut back on gift-giving
and the provision of credit to the Native trappers
and curtailed the use of alcohol as a trade
inducement, ostensibly for the Native people's
own good but also to economize. And, with
considerable insight, he worked to put the fur
trade on a sustained-yield basis: Native trappers
were encouraged to rotate their trapping
grounds, to refrain from taking cub beaver,
and to trap different animals in alternating
seasons to allow populations to recover. Recognizing
that it would be difficult to force
the Native peoples to adopt such alien conservation
practices, Simpson also periodically
opened and closed trading posts to draw the
Native people to different trapping grounds,
thus achieving the same goals. In the region
between the South Saskatchewan and Missouri
Rivers, however, where competition with
American traders was intense, he suspended
conservation measures and set out to create a
"fur desert" that would keep Americans out.
Simpson's management systems worked: from
1825 to 1860 Hudson's Bay Company stockholders
never earned dividends of less than
10 percent a year.

Simpson was knighted in 1841 for his service
to the Hudson's Bay Company and his
contributions to exploration. He died of apoplexy
in Lachine on September 7, 1860, leaving
behind a considerable fortune, as well as five
legitimate and, from his "country marriages,"
five illegitimate children.

See also: INDUSTRY: Hudson's Bay Company.


David J. Wishart
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Ray, Arthur J. Indians in the Fur Trade: Their Role as Trappers, Hunters, and Middlemen in the Lands Southwest of Hudson Bay, 1660–1870. Toronto: University of Toronto
Press, 1974.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>