<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ag.049</field>
      <field name="titleMain">The Land Institute</field>
      <field name="author">Bender, Marty</field>
      <field name="text">

 




THE LAND INSTITUTE

The Land Institute is a nonprofit organization
that was established in 1976 on 370 acres near
Salina, Kansas. It operates four programs devoted
to sustainable agriculture and human
communities.

The research program in Natural Systems
Agriculture (NSA) has been exploring a new
agricultural model that mimics the native
prairie ecosystem in order to develop a biodiverse,
perennial grain agriculture that preserves
soil, requires minimal or no fossil fuel
inputs, yields adequately, and does not rely on
harmful synthetic chemicals for fertility or
pest management. A formal advisory board of
sixty-four researchers in the fields of agronomy,
ecology, and other sciences assists in setting
the program's research agenda. NSA fellowships
are offered to graduate students
to foster relevant research done either at
the fellow's home institution or at the Land
Institute.

Since 1992 the Sunshine Farm Research
Program has been investigating the possibilities
of farming without fossil fuels, synthetic
fertilizers, or pesticides by using renewable
energy technologies and innovative management
practices to raise crops and livestock
typical of Great Plains agriculture. The goal of
this ten-year project is to examine the energetics
of food production and its ecological
costs.

The Intern Program, begun in 1983, annually
provides stipends for eight graduatelevel
students who spend ten months as research
assistants in NSA and the Sunshine
Farm. The program focuses on the broader
issues of sustainable society and agriculture as
well.

The Rural Community Studies Program,
situated in the small town of Matfield Green
in the Kansas Flint Hills, has been examining
community viability along ecological lines
rather than conventional economic ones. The
program aims to maximize possibilities for
cultural innovation in rural agricultural communities.
Recent efforts include a small conference
center, an education program for
teachers and school administrators, and research
into "ecological community accounting"
that will measure the flow of energy and
materials into and out of the community.


Marty Bender
The Land Institute




Jackson, Wes. Becoming Native to this Place. Lexington:
University Press of Kentucky, 1994. Soule, Judith D., and
Jon K. Piper. Farming in Nature's Image. Washington DC:
Island Press, 1992.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>