<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.073</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Stead, Robert (1880-1959)</field>
      <field name="author">Harrison, Dick</field>
      <field name="text">

 




STEAD, ROBERT (1880-1959)

Robert James Campbell Stead was a pioneer of
realist fiction on the Canadian Prairies. Born
on September 4, 1880, in Middleville, Ontario,
to Richard and May Campbell Stead, he grew
up on a farm near Cartwright, Manitoba. Stead
quit school at fourteen to work at various
jobs, including journalism, and before he was
twenty he had founded a rural weekly. By 1913
he was publicity director for the Canadian Pacific
Railway's colonization department in Calgary,
and in 1919 he moved to Ottawa to direct
publicity for federal departments, including
immigration and colonization, until his retirement
in 1946.

Stead's literary career began with The Empire Builders (1908) and other volumes of Kiplingesque
patriotic verse. He then wrote a
series of popular romances of pioneering, including
The Cow Puncher (1918), which sold
more than 70,000 copies, and The Homesteader
(1916), which went through multiple
editions and was reprinted in 1973 as a classic
of its genre, representing the garden view of
the Prairies.

What is remarkable about Stead's career is
that in the 1920s he abandoned popular (and
lucrative) romances for realist fiction. Grain
(1926), in particular, with its ironic narrative
voice and its stumbling hero, Gander Stake,
marked an antiromantic shift in his fiction.
Stunted by the numbing labor and cultural
deprivation of the farm, Gander is unable to
relate even to the soil he tills.

With Frederick Philip Grove and Martha
Ostenso, Stead is credited with initiating the
sober view of European settlers' spiritual alienation
from the land that distinguishes Prairie
realism. Stead died in Ottawa on June 25, 1959.


Dick Harrison
Sechelt, British Columbia




Fee, Margery. "Robert J. C. Stead." In Dictionary of Literary Biography, edited by W. H. New, 92: 370–73. Detroit:
Gale Research, 1990. Thompson, Eric. "Robert Stead
(1880–1959)." In Canadian Writers and Their Works, Fiction
series, edited by Robert Lecker, Jack David, and Ellen
Quigley, 3: 214–76. Toronto: ECW Press, 1988.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>