<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.040</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Malin, James C. (1893-1979)</field>
      <field name="author">Bogue, Allan G.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MALIN, JAMES C. (1893-1979)

A distinguished historian of the Great Plains,
James Malin was born on the homestead of his
father, Jared Nelson Malin, near Edgeley,
North Dakota, on February 8, 1893, and lived
there and at nearby Kulm while his father was
by turns farmer, store clerk, real estate and
agricultural implement salesman, sheep man,
and lay preacher. The family moved to Edwards
County, Kansas, in 1903. Young Malin
experienced Plains country farming and sheepherding
at first hand as well as life in Lewis,
Kansas, before entering Baker University at
Baldwin City, Kansas, in 1910. Initially enrolled
as a mathematics major, he switched to history
and also completed the equivalent of majors in
philosophy and biology before his graduation
in 1914. After periods of high school teaching,
graduate study at the University of Kansas, and
military service, he completed a doctorate and
joined the history department at the University
of Kansas in 1921. He retired in 1963. He
long served as associate editor of the Kansas Historical Quarterly and was president of the
Agricultural History Society, the Kansas Historical
Society, and the Kansas History Teachers
Association. A fellow of the American Association
for the Advancement of Science, he
served on committees of major associations in
American history, geography, and American
studies.

Malin wrote fifteen books, more than 100
articles, and many book reviews. He prepared
two survey texts during his early career and
later published in the philosophy of history,
but most of his publications deal with the history
of his native state and the adjacent grasslands
of the Plains. Several of Malin's books
focus on the regional and national politics involved
in establishing Kansas Territory and the
subsequent state: Indian Policy and Westward Expansion (1921), John Brown and the Legend of Fifty-Six (1942), and The Nebraska Question, 1852–1854 (1953). In the early 1930s he began to
investigate the accommodation of European
Americans to the subhumid environment of
the grasslands, innovating methods for studying population turnover and community development
and investigating relevant research
in other disciplines. He described his results as
"history from the bottom up" in articles and
books such as "The Turnover of Farm Population
in Kansas" (Kansas Historical Quarterly,
1935), Winter Wheat in the Golden Belt of Kansas: A Study in Adaptation to Subhumid Geographical Environment (1940; reprint, 1944),
"Dust Storms, 1850–1900" (Kansas Historical Quarterly, 1946), and The Grassland of North America: Prolegomena to Its History (1947).

Malin significantly advanced understanding
of the history of the North American grassland
regions. He particularly illuminated the factors
underlying mid-nineteenth-century Indian
policy, the activity of political factions in
territorial Kansas, the Kansas-Nebraska Act,
settler and agricultural adaptation, the incidence
of dust storms, and the influence of
science and technology in shaping regional
development. He was the first American historian
to make extensive use of federal and state
census returns at the farm level. Alone among
western historians of his generation, he drew
heavily on ecological research, and he believed
that ecology paralleled history in its objectives.
However, he disputed some of the generalizations
of ecologist Frederic Clements and his
followers concerning the American grasslands.

Sensitive to editorial oversight, Malin published
most of his own books during the last
third of his career, a practice that impeded the
circulation of his ideas. Malin died on January
16, 1979, at Lawrence, Kansas.

See also PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT: Grasses / POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT: Kansas-Nebraska Act.


Allan G. Bogue
University of Wisconsin-Madison




Bogue, Allan G. "James C. Malin: A Voice from the Grassland."
In Writing Western History: Essays on Major Western Historians, edited by Richard W. Etulain. Albuquerque:
University of New Mexico Press, 1991: 215–46. Malin,
James C. History and Ecology: Studies of the Grassland,
edited by Robert P. Swierenga. Lincoln: University of Nebraska
Press, 1984.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>