<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.arc.047</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Tankhouses</field>
      <field name="author">Kent, Robert B.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




TANKHOUSES

Tankhouses are outbuildings constructed to
provide water storage for domestic consumption
and to insure dependable water pressure.
The basic design is simple and straightforward–
a large water tank (2,000 to 3,000 gallons)
sits on an elevated platform some twenty
to forty feet in height. Usually both the tank
and the tower structure are enclosed. The area
inside the tower is used for a workshop or
storage or occasionally as a dwelling area.
Wood is used most frequently in the construction
of a tankhouse, although in some areas
stone, brick, masonry block, or a combination
of these materials is employed. Square,
straight tower construction is most common
in the Great Plains, but tapered towers are
found occasionally, and in Nebraska circular
towers occur in some counties.

In the Great Plains the construction of tankhouses
dates from the 1880s and 1890s, although
it occurred earlier in eastern Corn Belt
states and in California. Notable, although
modest, concentrations of tankhouses are in
western Kansas and eastern Colorado, in Nebraska,
and in central Texas. Initially, windmills
provided the power needed to pump well
water into the tanks, and both freestanding
and attached windmills were constructed.
Later, the availability of internal combustion
engines and electric power from rural electrification
projects provided alternative power
sources, and windmills fell increasingly into
disuse. The development of the hydropneumatic
pump ended tankhouse construction by
allowing water to be pumped directly from
wells into homes under pressure. Some tankhouses
are still used for their original purpose,
but most have either fallen into disuse, been
razed, or been converted to other uses.


Robert B. Kent
University of Akron




Boucher, Aaron S., and Robert B. Kent. "Tankhouses in
Nebraska: Distribution, Construction Styles, and Use."
Material Culture 24 (1992): 43–58. Kent, Robert B. "Tankhouses
on the High Plains of Western Kansas and Eastern
Colorado." Material Culture 24 (1992): 33–41.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>