<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.med.013</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Daily Oklahoman</field>
      <field name="author">Patterson, Philip D.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




DAILY OKLAHOMAN

When E. K. Gaylord arrived in Oklahoma City
in 1902 he found a young town of 7,000 residents
with two newspapers, including the one
he would work at and own for more than seventy
years–the Daily Oklahoman. After Gaylord
met with Roy E. Stafford, the publisher
of the eight-year-old Oklahoman, the men
reached an agreement for Gaylord to become
Stafford's business manager and financial
partner.

The newspaper had passed through several
hands since its founding in 1894. Gaylord began
his duties on January 27, 1903, and two
days later the Oklahoma Publishing Company
(OPUBCO) was incorporated. In less than a
century, Gaylord's original five-thousand-dollar
investment in a fledgling newspaper
would become a billion-dollar media empire.

Oklahoma became a state on November 16,
1907, and soon the state capital was moved
from Guthrie to Oklahoma City. Gaylord
chaired the Oklahoma City campaign for the
capital site. With the move came higher statewide
status for the Daily Oklahoman. However,
the Oklahoman's early growth was impeded
by circulation wars with both paid and
free newspapers and a fire that destroyed its
building and melted its printing equipment
in 1909.

In 1916 OPUBCO purchased the Oklahoma Times, which it operated until 1984. That purchase
left only one rival, the Oklahoma City News, an afternoon daily owned by the Scripps-
Howard chain. The News folded in the 1970s
when afternoon newspapers across America
faced circulation declines with the advent of
evening television news, making Oklahoma
City one of the many cities in American with a
single newspaper.

Gaylord's efforts to buy and beat the competition
and his courage in facing down political
opposition and an advertising boycott impressed
the directors of OPUBCO, and in 1916
they named him president of the company,
despite the fact that Stafford owned the majority
of the stock. Stafford, who perceived the
directors' action as a vote of no confidence,
quickly sold his interest in the newspaper for
$300,000.

Stafford's departure set the stage for a remarkable
career for Gaylord as president of a
growing newspaper in a growing state, a career
that lasted until his death in 1974 at the
age of 101. In those years Oklahoma saw both
bad times–the Great Depression and the
Dust Bowl–and good–the discovery of huge
oil fields throughout the state. Through them
all the Daily Oklahoman steadily maintained
its mission to be the newspaper of record for
the state. National attention focused on the
city and the newspaper in 1995, when the federal
building in Oklahoma City was bombed
in the largest act of domestic terrorism in the
nation's history. Reporters and editors worked
nonstop for more than a month, covering the
story in a manner praised by consumers and
industry insiders alike.

Over the years the Daily Oklahoman gained
a reputation for embracing new technology,
shunning special interests, and encouraging
economic growth in the city and state. From
their earliest days, radio and television fascinated
Gaylord with their possibilities. OPUBCO
brought radio to Oklahoma City in 1928 and
television in 1949, often pioneering technologies
and fostering talent later enjoyed nationwide.
Edward L. Gaylord, who followed
his father into the OPUBCO presidency in 1974,
expanded the OPUBCO media holdings, purchasing
television stations in Seattle, New
Orleans, Cleveland, and Fort Worth. In 1983
OPUBCO bought the Opryland hotel and entertainment
complex in Nashville, Tennessee,
and media properties, including the Nashville
Network, Country Music Television, wsm Radio,
and the Grand Ole Opry, forming the
publicly held Gaylord Entertainment in the
process.

The Daily Oklahoman stands today as the
centerpiece of the Oklahoma Publishing Company
and is one of the largest family-owned
newspapers in the United States, with circulation
in excess of 225,000 daily and 330,000 on
Sunday.

See also CITIES AND TOWNS: Oklahoma City, Oklahoma.


Philip D. Patterson
Oklahoma Christian University




Daily Oklahoman Archives, Tom and Ada Beam Library,
Oklahoma Christian University, Oklahoma City. Dary,
David. "A Work in Progress: The Oklahoma Publishing
Company Celebrates 95 Years." Daily Oklahoman, supplement,
November 8, 1998: 1–17.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>