<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fol.038</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Roadside Attractions</field>
      <field name="author">Dorst, John</field>
      <field name="text">

 




ROADSIDE ATTRACTIONS


Garden of Eden, Lucas, Kansas


What most people mean by "roadside attraction"
is a site that has in some way been
"framed" and consciously presented to a public
audience for visitation and viewing. It is a
"roadside" phenomenon both in the obvious
sense that it exists in some proximity to regular
routes of public movement and in the
sense that it has the particular capacity to
draw, at least briefly, a traveler's attention
away from the goal of reaching an intended
destination. The modern roadside attraction
has precursors in such features as wayside
chapels along pilgrimage routes and sales exhibits
of regional souvenirs along early railway
lines (as in some of the Harvey House hotels
on the Santa Fe Railroad), but it is primarily a
creature of the modern highway and road system.
Although roadside attractions are components
of a touristic landscape, they are in
most cases not primary destinations for recreational
travelers. Characteristically, such attractions
evoke spontaneous reactions and
relatively brief stops rather than preplanned
and extended visits.

There are many locations that might or
might not be considered a roadside attraction,
depending on the qualities one chooses to emphasize.
The Great Plains has one of the most
notable such cases in Mount Rushmore National
Memorial, located in the Black Hills
of western South Dakota. While some might
argue that its social status as a premier National
Park Service site disqualifies it as a
"mere" roadside attraction, a good case could
also be made that it is the epitome of this landscape
genre. The monumental sculptures are
elaborately "framed" for viewing and have no
other purpose than to induce wonder and
perhaps even awe. At the same time, Mount
Rushmore is not the primary destination for
at least most long-range travelers, and a couple
of hours at the site is probably the limit for
the typical visitor.

Mount Rushmore has one other quality that
links it to the less-spectacular roadside attractions
of the Great Plains and elsewhere. Central
to its appeal is its inherent strangeness. The
uncanny apparition of the gigantic presidential
visages in a "wilderness" context is, depending
on one's tastes, sublime, inspiring
(even religiously so), bizarre, tacky, kitschy, or
even frightening or repulsive. Roadside attractions
in general are typified by some form of
exceptional strangeness or landscape dissonance,
though few to the degree of this national
monument. It is this quality that sets
roadside attractions apart from some other
features of the landscape that might prompt
travelers to pause, such as scenic overlooks,
historical markers, or war memorials. As moments
of arresting strangeness, roadside attractions
may be human constructions, like
Mount Rushmore, or natural features, like
the nation's first national monument, Devils
Tower, in northeastern Wyoming, a strikingly
uncanny geological formation.

These two monuments are particularly
grand examples of one subset of such attractions–
the officially endorsed or civic sites
that sometimes become signature emblems of
the communities that maintain them. The
Corn Palace in downtown Mitchell, South Dakota,
is a more modest and so perhaps a better
representative of this type. With fantastically
orientalist architecture and an exterior covered
in annually changing murals made entirely
of South Dakota corn, seeds, and grains,
the building functions mainly as a civic auditorium,
sports arena, and agricultural exposition
site.

Along with these more or less official attractions,
two other types may be distinguished,
the commercial and the folk or vernacular.
Commercial roadside attractions are perhaps
the most pervasive form of this landscape
characteristic and the type most associated
with the term in the popular imagination. The
notion of the "tourist trap," suggesting hokum,
hucksterism, and crass commercial interests, is
evoked by many sites of this sort, giving them
an air of tawdriness and sly deceit. The nineteenth-
century dime museum and the carnival
sideshow are precursors to this brand of attraction,
and the rhetoric of excess–the biggest,
the oldest, the first, and so on–is especially
prominent in them. Many Plains towns have
built gigantic animal sculptures to attract travelers.
Jamestown, North Dakota, has a sixtyton
concrete buffalo, reputed to be "the world's
largest." Not to be outdone, New Salem, North
Dakota, takes pride in "Salem Sue," the world's
largest Holstein cow, and in the same state the
town of Dunseith is the home to "W'eel," the
world's largest turtle. While many travelers
perceive such sites only as roadside clutter and
tasteless purveyors of garish come-ons, for
others they have an appeal as nostalgically
seedy alternatives to the plastic, franchised,
strip-mall-studded roadside landscape that
has become increasingly pervasive in the Great
Plains, as elsewhere in North America.

In some cases, sites of this sort have become
so notable and elaborated as to transcend the
dubious associations of their origins. Wall
Drug–now virtually a town unto itself–is
perhaps the most famous instance of this phenomenon
in the region. Located, like the Corn
Palace and Mount Rushmore, along the Interstate
90 corridor in South Dakota (one of the
most fertile routes for roadside attractions in
the Plains), Wall Drug is especially famous for
its novel advertising strategy of posting mileage
signs at remote locations around the
country and even abroad.

A third subset of roadside attractions includes those sites that arise in vernacular or
folkloric contexts and from primarily personal
rather than commercial or civic motivations.
In many cases they are the products of
individual obsession, hobbyist enthusiasm, or
private commemoration, and they frequently
reflect a folk art aesthetic of playful bricolage.
While many such sites remain fairly obscure
and available mainly to local travelers, those
that become known to a wider public do so, at
least at first, more by word-of-mouth communication
than by conscious design and advertising.
Often produced from inexpensive,
low-tech, or recycled materials and with skills
learned on the job or through a hobby, such
sites become true roadside attractions to the
degree that they achieve sufficient flamboyance
and public visibility to set them off dramatically
from the surrounding landscape.

One of the best-known and most interesting
sites in this category is the "Garden of
Eden," located in a residential neighborhood
of Lucas, Kansas. Growing to remarkable proportions
over the years from 1905 until the
death of its creator in 1933, the Garden of
Eden was produced by Samuel Dinsmoor as a
monumental folk sculpture display devoted to
biblical and early-twentieth-century political
themes (e.g., antitrust advocacy). With its
large figures constructed of concrete and overlaid
with a sculptural layer of limestone plaster,
the Garden is one of the masterpieces of
this surprisingly common genre of display environment.
It is an excellent example of a personal
vision reaching sufficient proportions
and notoriety to become one of the premier
roadside attractions of the Great Plains.

It is debatable whether the Great Plains is
better supplied than other parts of North
America with sites of the sort described here.
However, it does seem that such instances of
cultural strangeness and landscape dissonance
stand out with special vividness against the
(relatively speaking) neutral background of
Plains roadsides.

See also ARCHITECTURE: Roadside Architecture / 
IMAGES AND ICONS: Corn Palace; 
Mount Rushmore National Memorial; Wall Drug.


John Dorst
University of Wyoming




Andrews, J. J. C. The Well-Built Elephant, and Other Roadside Attractions. New York: Congdon and Weed, Inc., 1984.
Clay, Grady. Real Places: An Unconventional Guide to America's Generic Landscape. Chicago: University of Chicago
Press, 1994. Marling, Karal Ann. The Colossus of Roads: Myth and Symbol along the American Highway.
Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 1984.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>