<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.tra.042</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Whoop-Up Trail</field>
      <field name="author">Thomas, Phillip Drennon</field>
      <field name="text">

 




WHOOP-UP TRAIL

Although the origins of the name Whoop-Up
Trail are unclear, the fabled history and significance
of this trail, which ran from Fort Benton
in Montana to the notorious whiskey fort,
Fort Whoop-Up (Fort Hamilton), and later
Fort Macleod on the Oldman River in Canada,
are not debated. Playing an important
role in the history of the U.S.-Canadian frontier
from the 1850s until the late 1880s, this
trail of approximately 240 miles roughly paralleled
or followed the Great North Trail along
which Native Americans had traveled for millennia
on the eastern side of the Rocky Mountains.
Founded in 1850, Fort Benton, on the
west side of the Missouri some 3,575 miles
from its mouth, became a center for trade for
northern Montana and southern Alberta for
more than four decades.

From 1860 to 1890 more than 600 steamboat
landings allowed goods and commerce to
reach both U.S. and Canadian frontier communities.
Passing through grasslands with few
physical barriers, the trail was traversed on
foot, on horseback, by mule train, and by trade
wagons by Native Americans, fur trappers,
whiskey traders, the U.S. Army, the North-West
Mounted Police (NWMP), cowboys,
miners, ranchers, and settlers. Through Fort
Benton passed many of the bison robes that
made their way to eastern markets from 1865 to
1882. Furs, whiskey, and trade goods were a
staple of the commerce on this trail, although
with the coming of the NWMP to western Canada
in 1874, the whiskey forts and the whiskey
trade began to decline. Supplies for the nwmp
and Indian reservations became part of the
goods carried by bull trains (consisting of six
to twelve yoke, or pair, of oxen) across the
border. The coming of the railroad lessened
the need for the trail, and by 1890 it no longer
played a significant role in the economic life of
this region.


Phillip Drennon Thomas
Wichita State University




Berry, Gerald L. The Whoop-Up Trail. Edmonton, Alberta:
Applied Art Products, 1953. Cushman, Dan. The Great
North Trail. New York: McGraw-Hill Book Company,
1966. Sharp, Paul E. Whoop-Up Country: The Canadian-American
West, 1865–1885. Norman: University of Oklahoma
Press, 1973.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>