<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ind.024</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Goodnight, Charles (1836-1929)</field>
      <field name="author">Zontek, Ken</field>
      <field name="text">

 




GOODNIGHT, CHARLES (1836-1929)

Charles Goodnight epitomized the plainsman.
Born in Macoupin County, Illinois, on
March 5, 1836, Goodnight, riding bareback,
first came to the Southern Plains of Texas in
1846. During his young adulthood in the
Brazos River valley, he worked as a farmhand,
freighter, and cowboy. In 1856 Goodnight
hired himself out to a local rancher and received
every fourth calf as pay. Within a year
he had also become a Texas Ranger. Meanwhile,
he continued to add to his small herd of
cattle, which he moved to Palo Pinto County,
Texas.

His eight-year Ranger career, filled with
frontier patrols, ended when the twenty-nineyear-
old entrepreneur decided to take his 180
head of cattle west to reservation agencies. He
became partners with Oliver Loving, a man
twenty-five years his senior with experience in
driving cattle long distances. The two adventurers
planned to trail their combined herd
from Fort Belknap, Texas, to Fort Sumner,
New Mexico. While preparing for departure,
Goodnight invented the chuck wagon by remodeling
the back end of an existing wagon
into a mess area. In 1866 the two men took
2,000 cattle guided by eighteen cowboys and
struck out southwest for the Pecos River,
which they would follow north. The 700-mile
journey, 96 miles of it without water on the
Staked Plains, established the Goodnight-
Loving Trail that later extended to Cheyenne,
Wyoming.

The two stockmen quickly made a successful
second trip but met disaster on their third trip
in 1868, when Comanches mortally wounded
Loving. Goodnight made three more trips on
the trail from 1869 to 1871 while simultaneously
operating a corn farm and way station ranch in
southeastern Colorado. In 1871 he wed Mary
Dyer from Fort Belknap, Texas. Subsequently,
they lost their Colorado holdings in the Panic
of 1873.

Charles returned to his trail-driving days by
blazing the Goodnight Trail from Alamogordo
Creek, New Mexico, to Granada, Colorado,
in 1875. The following year, he moved his
remaining cattle into the Palo Duro Canyon in
the Texas Panhandle, where he found a partner
in John Adair from Ireland. Their spread,
the ja Ranch, eventually covered one million
acres and included more than 100,000 cattle.
To these cattle, Goodnight added bison from a
captive breeding program he had initiated in
1878 at the request of his wife. Goodnight bred
bison with cattle, thereby developing the "cattalo."
He later abandoned the project, but his
knack for cattle breeding resulted in the improvement
of his herds with Hereford bulls.
In 1880 Goodnight became the inaugural president
of the Panhandle Stockman's Association.

Goodnight retired from the ja Ranch in
1888 and within a couple of years purchased a
smaller ranch at nearby Goodnight Station.
He spent the remainder of his life as a cattle
breeder, an active member of the American
Bison Society, and a leading citizen. Goodnight
died on December 12, 1929, in Phoenix,
Arizona. His family buried him next to his
wife in Goodnight, Texas. Goodnight was
commemorated by the U.S. Postal Service
with a stamp and postcard in its 1993 Legends
of the West series.

See also AGRICULTURE: Ranches / TRANSPORTATION: Cattle Trails.


Ken Zontek
University of Idaho




Goodnight, Charles, Emanuel Dubbs, and John A. Hart.
Pioneer Days in the Southwest from 1850 to 1879. Guthrie
OK: State Capital Company, 1909. Haley, J. Evetts. Charles Goodnight: Cowman and Plainsman. Norman: University
of Oklahoma Press, 1936. Hamner, Laura. The No-Gun Man of Texas: A Century of Achievement, 1835–1929. Amarillo:
Hamner, 1935.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>