<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pd.033</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Malcolm X (1925-1965)</field>
      <field name="author">Conyers, Jr., James L.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




MALCOLM X (1925-1965)


Malcolm X


Malcolm X was born Malcolm Little at University
Hospital in Omaha, Nebraska, on May
19, 1925. He was also known later in life by his
religious name, El-Hajj Malik El-Shabbazz.
His parents, Earl Little and Louise Norton Little,
were both active members of Marcus Garvey's Universal Negro Improvement Association
and they wrote for the UNIA paper, the
Negro World.

The Littles' home was reportedly attacked
by Ku Klux Klansmen in December 1926, and
they left immediately for Milwaukee, Wisconsin.
In January 1928 they moved to Lansing,
Michigan. There, Earl Little, as an organizer
for the Garvey movement, continued his community
activism. In September 1931 his body
was found by the railroad tracks, cut in half
by a locomotive car. Historical accounts differ:
some believe that local white supremacist
organizations committed this murder; others
have speculated that his death was a suicide.
Whatever the case, from 1931 to 1939 the Little
family disintegrated. In 1939 Malcolm's
mother, Louise, was diagnosed as legally insane
and committed to the state mental hospital
in Kalamazoo, Michigan, where she remained
for more than twenty years. Malcolm
began having problems with the social welfare
system and was placed in foster care. He also
spent time in juvenile detention homes.

By 1941 Malcolm had moved to the Roxbury
section of Boston to live with his sister
Ella. He held various jobs, such as laborer
and porter on the New Haven Railroad line,
and he slipped into a life of petty crime. He
moved back to Michigan in December 1942
but quickly returned to New York, where he
continued working for the New Haven Railroad.
From 1944 to 1946 Malcolm was continually
involved in illegal activity, ranging
from drugs and burglary to gambling and
prostitution. In February 1946 he began serving
an eight- to ten-year prison sentence at the
Charlestown (Massachusetts) Prison for burglary.
There, he began a self-taught study in
reading and writing. After being relocated to
the Concord Reformatory in 1947, Malcolm
was exposed to the teachings of Elijah Muhammad
by a fellow inmate. His life was
transformed. Malcolm's siblings were also
converted and accepted membership into the
Nation of Islam.

After fifteen months at the Concord Reformatory,
Malcolm was transferred to Norfolk
Prison Colony, then sent back to Charlestown
to serve the remainder of his sentence. Paroled
in 1952, he went to live with his brother Wilfred
in Inkster, Michigan, where he worked as
a furniture salesman. That same year he was
assigned his "X" to replace the name that
had been taken from his slave ancestors and
became an active member in the Nation of
Islam.

From this point on, Malcolm X's activity
and membership in the Nation of Islam intensified:
in the fall of 1953 he became first minister
of Boston Temple No. 11; in March 1954 he
was assigned acting minister of Philadelphia
Temple No. 12; and in June of that year, he was
appointed minister of New York Temple No. 7.
His message in the temple and on the streets
of Harlem stressed black nationalism and
lambasted integration as a hoax.

At the same time, Malcolm X also made an
important transition in his family life. In 1958
he married Betty X (Sanders). In November
his first daughter, Attallah, was born. She was
followed in later years by daughters Quibilah
(1960), Ilyasah (1962), and Gamilah (1964).
When he died, his wife was pregnant with
twins and gave birth to daughters, Malaak and
Malikah, in November 1965.

Taking on the responsibilities and duties as
a national spokesperson for the Nation of Islam,
Malcolm traveled widely, expressing his
views in television interviews, court cases involving
civil rights, and forums on black
equality and leadership. By 1963, however, his
status was beginning to deteriorate within the
leadership circle of the Nation of Islam. That
year in Detroit, he gave one of his most influential
lectures, "Message to the Grass Roots,"
arguing for black nationalism and thereby
challenging Elijah Mohammad's conception
of the Nation of Islam as a purely religious
movement. Days later he referred to the death
of President John F. Kennedy as "chickens
coming home to roost." Immediately after
making this comment, he was suspended
from his position as national spokesperson for
the Nation of Islam and banned from public
speaking for ninety days. In March 1964, after
his period of suspension, he announced that
he was leaving the Nation of Islam to establish
Muslim Mosque Incorporated and the Organization
of Afro-American Unity. He moderated
his views, moving toward accommodation
with Martin Luther King's crusade for
civil rights.

In April 1964 Malcolm journeyed to Mecca
to make hajj, fulfilling his religious requirements
and duties. This period also served as
time for self-reflection and meditation. When
he returned to the United States and founded
the Organization of Afro-American Unity, he
hoped to link the freedom struggles of blacks
in Africa with those in the United States. The
end came on February 21, 1965, when he was
assassinated by four gunmen while giving a
speech at the Audubon Ballroom in Harlem.

Malcolm X was only thirty-nine years old
when he died, but in that brief lifespan he
became one of the most important African
American leaders of the twentieth century. Although
often out of step with civil rights
leaders because of his separatist views and his
refusal to eschew violent means of change, he
nurtured pride and self-respect in African
Americans, and more than anyone else he reestablished
their connection to Africa.

See also AFRICAN AMERICANS: Civil Rights / RELIGION: Islam.


James L. Conyers Jr.
University of Nebraska at Omaha




Gallen, David, ed. A Malcolm X Reader. New York: Carroll
and Graf Publishers, Inc., 1994. Malcolm X, with Alex
Haley. The Autobiography of Malcolm X. New York: Grove
Press, 1965. Perry, Theresa, ed. Teaching Malcolm X. New
York: Routledge, 1996.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>