<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fol.042</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Tall Tales</field>
      <field name="author">Taft, Michael</field>
      <field name="text">

 




TALL TALES

Called yarns, lies, windies, or bullshit, tall tales
are stories of exaggeration that act like verbal
practical jokes. Most often, tellers begin their
stories as if relating a true incident, but part
way through the tale they stretch the facts beyond
credulity, thereby "catching" their listeners,
who then appear to be gullible fools.
Sometimes, tall tales are traded by two or
more tellers as a contest to see who can tell the
most artful whopper. In all cases, however, the
tall tale is a clever mixture of truth and fiction.

Many of these stories have ancient roots
and have migrated far and wide. Consider the
tall tale of weather that is so cold that speech
freezes, so that you have to wait until spring
thaw to hear winter conversations. It is a wellknown
story in the Plains, but it can be traced
back as far as Plutarch (347 B.C.) and has been
told throughout Europe and North America.
Wherever storytellers have encountered extremes
of nature, landscape, or human behavior,
they have responded by exaggerating
these extremes further through tall tales.

At the same time that the tall tale is an international
form of folklore, it is also a marker of
regionalism. The explanation for this seeming
paradox is that each locality chooses only that
part of the great pool of stories which best
comments on regional conditions. Thus, people
of the seacoast tell tall tales about heavy
fog, great fish, and canny mariners. Mountain
folk tell of "side-hill gougers"–small animals
whose left legs are shorter than their right legs
so that they can stand upright in hilly country.
And people of the forest lie about trees so big
that two gangs of loggers can chop on opposite
sides without being aware of each other's
existence.

It is no surprise, therefore, that Plains people
comment upon their land through a similar
selection from the international storehouse
of lies. Tales of extreme cold, like the frozen
conversation, are common, but the extreme
variability of flatland weather generates its
own kind of stories. The warm chinook winds
that rush down the Rockies into the Plains
during wintertime create scenes such as a
team of horses struggling through high snow
while the driver's cart bogs down in mud, and
meanwhile the dog running behind kicks up
dust from the dry road. The gumbo mud of
springtime causes problems for pigs: the mud
builds up on their tails to such an extent that it
stretches the skin on their backs so that they
can't close their eyes and they often die from
lack of sleep. Other tales comment on summer
heat and drought ("the day it rained") and the
resulting dust storms when gophers are seen
ten feet in the air digging down.

If mountain people have side-hill gougers,
then Plains folk have "jackalopes"–jackrabbits
with antelope prongs on their heads–or
their larger cousins, the "elkhares." Prairie
grasshoppers grow so big they're mistaken for
cattle or airplanes. Venomous snakes strike at
wagon tongues, which swell so much they
provide enough kindling to last the winter.

In good times, prairie wheat is so thick that
it must be swathed twice before it will fall, and
cabbages are large enough to shelter pigs from
the sun. In bad times, it's so dry that bullfrogs
don't know how to swim because they've
never had a chance to learn; parents pour water
through a screen so that their children will
know what rain looks like.

Just as tall tales comment upon the land
and the climate, they also describe regional
occupations, especially outdoor, primary-resource
industries. For this reason, the tall
tale is often seen as a preserve of men, the
traditional workers in such occupations, although
on occasion women have been known
to lie. Farmers tell of strong pitchers who
could unload a rack of hay in two forkfuls.
Ranchers recall riding on the backs of jackrabbits
to herd far-ranging cattle. Oil drillers
speak of derricks so tall that they are hinged to
let the moon pass.

Sometimes the tellers of these tales turn
into folk heroes in their own right, becoming
Münchhausens of their particular region or
occupation. For example, the oil driller Gib
Morgan (1842–1909) was a prodigious teller of
tall tales, and he soon became the protagonist
in oil-patch stories. Instead of oil, he drilled
for cream or champagne, used snakeskins for
a pipeline, and when he heard a distant thunderstorm,
single-handedly capped a gusher in
mid-blow.

Other heroes were entirely fanciful, sometimes
the work of popular writers. Although
Paul Bunyan was best known in the forests of
the East and Midwest, he was also a tall-tale
figure in the Plains. In fact, he logged the
Northern Plains so completely that the Dakotas
are almost devoid of trees. The tall-tale
cowboy Pecos Bill was the invention of writer
Edward O'Reilly, who probably based his
character on Paul Bunyan. Pecos Bill rode tornadoes
and lit cigarettes with lightning bolts.
At the age of one month, he killed a panther;
his life ended when he laughed himself to
death looking at a Bostonian in a cowboy suit.

Just as authors have used the tall-tale tradition
to their advantage, so too have commercial
artists. For example, the art of the taxidermist
may be seen in Plains saloons, where
stuffed and mounted jackalopes are on display.
More popular, however, are tall-tale postcards.
Since the early twentieth century, postcard
manufacturers have used trick photography to
show giant ears of corn (three to a wagon), furbearing
trout (from especially cold streams),
hunters carrying large grasshoppers on poles,
and the jackrabbit-riding cowboys mentioned
above.

Whether told during roundup or sent as
postcards to eastern relatives, the tall tale is a
sardonic commentary on the harshness and
changeability of life in the Great Plains. Exaggeration
allows flatlanders to temper the disappointment
of crops that are not abundant,
weather that is less than moderate, and occupations
that involve more drudgery than
heroism. The humor of tall tales resides in a
delicate balance of fact and fiction that reflects
both the dreams and realities of Plains life.


Michael Taft
American Folklife Center
Library of Congress




Boatright, Mody C. Gib Morgan: Minstrel of the Oil Fields.
Publications of the Texas Folklore Society, no. 20. Dallas:
Southern Methodist University Press, 1945. Halpert, Herbert.
"Tall Tales and Other Yarns from Calgary, Alberta."
California Folklore Quarterly 4 (1945), 29–49. Reprinted in
Folklore of Canada, edited by Edith Fowke. Toronto: Mc-
Clelland and Stewart Ltd., 1976: 171–89. Welsch, Roger L.
Shingling the Fog and Other Plains Lies. Lincoln: University
of Nebraska Press, 1980.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>