<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ag.072</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Texas Fever</field>
      <field name="author">Hoy, James</field>
      <field name="text">

 




TEXAS FEVER

Texas, or Spanish (as it later came to be
called), fever was first detected in Pennsylvania
in 1796, following the delivery of cattle
from South Carolina. On the Plains, this infectious
bovine disease, particularly prevalent
in Texas, was influential in the development of
the cattle trails and cow towns of the Great
Plains.

The longhorn cattle from the Southern
Plains that carried the disease were immune to
its fatal effects, but the domestic cattle of the
Midwest were not. The problems caused during
the 1850s by the smaller droves of cattle
passing through Missouri on their way to eastern
markets were multiplied greatly when tens
of thousands of Texas longhorns were trailed
to Sedalia in 1866. The hostility of the Missouri
legislature and local farmers resulted in
the closing off of Missouri as a shipping point
and the opening of the Kansas cow towns, led
by Abilene in 1867.

Dispute over the cause of the disease between
Texas drovers, whose cattle showed
no symptoms, and local stockmen, many of
whose cattle died, led to the establishment of
quarantine lines that prohibited the importation
of Texas cattle unless they had been wintered
over in the north. In 1885 the entire state
of Kansas was closed to Texas cattle, interrupting
the trail drives and contributing to the
demise of the cattle trailing business. The
cause of the fever–a tick that was host to a
microscopic organism that attacked the bovine
spleen–was not discovered until 1889.
Dipping vats and insecticides eventually replaced
quarantine lines as the most effective
method of controlling the spread of
the disease, although the Kansas City stockyards
maintained separate areas for southern
and northern cattle well into the twentieth
century.

One of the last major outbreaks of Texas
fever on the Plains occurred in 1919 when a
shipment of faultily dipped Texas cattle arrived
in Wabaunsee County, Kansas, for summer
grazing in the Flint Hills.

See also TRANSPORTATION: Cattle Trails.


James Hoy
Emporia State University





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>