<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ea.025</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Lewis and Clark</field>
      <field name="author">Moulton, Gary</field>
      <field name="text">

 




LEWIS AND CLARK

Meriwether Lewis (1774-1809) and William
Clark (1770-1838) were the first Americans to
investigate the Great Plains. Both men were
born in Virginia (Lewis near Charlottesville
on August 17, 1774, and Clark in Caroline
County on August 1, 1770) and served in the
army together briefly in the mid-1790s. Clark
resigned his commission and returned home
in 1796, while Lewis continued in military service
and in 1801 became President Thomas Jefferson's
private secretary. In 1803 Jefferson
placed Lewis as leader of the Corps of Discovery,
and Lewis offered Clark an invitation to
greatness as co-commander. In the nearly two
and a half years on the expedition, the two
men shared command responsibilities and a
friendship that has become legendary.

The men's conclusions about the region
were more optimistic than some later explorers
and tended to support a garden concept of
the region. As the men entered the Plains environment
in the summer of 1804, they had a
chance to test this idea. Beyond the Platte
River, terms like "high and dry" were more
frequent than the usual "beautiful and wellwatered,"
but their impressions did not change
greatly. Indeed, it was the profusion of wildlife
that caught their attention rather than the
endless grassland and semiarid climate. Fascinated
by the varied animal life, the captains
wrote scientific descriptions of a host of Plains
animals. Moreover, they told of vast numbers
of bison. And it was the captains' reports of
abundant beaver that sent fur trappers into
the interior. From the party's Fort Mandan, in
present-day North Dakota, Lewis penned this
overall impression: "This immense river so far
as we have yet ascended, waters one of the
fairest portions of the globe, nor do I believe
that there is in the universe a similar extent of
country, equally fertile." This positive evaluation
of the Plains resulted from a river-bottom
perspective–a fact that prejudiced Lewis's
opinion.

As the explorers turned west in the spring of
1805, the terrain became more arid, treeless,
and rugged. Nonetheless, along the riverbanks
Lewis still sighted groves of trees, and in the
underbrush he saw thick stands of berry-laden
bushes. New animals, like bighorn sheep, were
seen farther west, and the famed grizzly bear
appeared. The men discounted stories about
its ferocity, but after several bouts with bears,
Lewis concluded, "I must confess that I do not
like the gentlemen and had reather fight two
Indians than one bear." As the party moved
into a harsher terrain, Lewis's evaluations of
the land became increasingly bleak, until he
finally called the region a "desert barren country."
The negative appraisals were restricted,
however, to the far northwestern edge of the
Great Plains.

Lewis and Clark's meetings with Plains Indians
focused on two principal goals. One was
diplomatic–to apprise the tribes of United
States' sovereignty under the Louisiana Purchase
and to explain the purposes of their mission.
They also wanted to establish intertribal
peace. It is doubtful that many Plains Indians
understood the purpose of exploration, nor
did they grasp the idea of diplomacy outside
of trade. Lewis and Clark envisioned trade in
the long run; the Indians desired an immediate
exchange of goods. Lewis and Clark
wanted to expand the United States' commercial
influence, while Plains Indians wanted the
best goods at the lowest price from the most
dependable supplier. Nor were the Indians
ready to talk of peace with their traditional
enemies without some assurance of security.
Lewis and Clark could not give that.

The commanders' other function was
ethnographic–to gather information about
tribes in order to increase knowledge. In this
regard, Lewis and Clark interviewed Indians
and resident traders, reported on observations,
participated in Indian activities, and
collected cultural objects. The captains did
their best work in recounting objective matters
and describing external cultural aspects.
They were not as good at relating ritualistic
behavior or subjective matter, and they misunderstood
or misinterpreted some activities.
They also missed some important ceremonies
due to timing. Nevertheless, they rose above
the prejudices of their time and left a valuable
ethnographic legacy.

After the expedition Lewis became governor
of Louisiana Territory but did not fare
well. Mounting difficulties in St. Louis and
disputes with federal officials sent him to
Washington in 1809. Along the way, plagued
by multiple problems, he took his life on
the Natchez Trace in Tennessee on October 11.
Clark, on the other hand, lived a prosperous
and productive life as a politician and public
servant, most notably as superintendent of Indian
affairs in St. Louis, where he died on September
1, 1838.

See also IMAGES AND ICONS: The Garden.

Lewis and Clark Journals Online website.


Gary Moulton
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Ambrose, Stephen E. Undaunted Courage: Thomas Jefferson and the Opening of the American West. New York:
Simon and Schuster, 1996. Moulton, Gary, ed. The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition. Lincoln: University
of Nebraska Press, 1983-1999.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>