<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ha.018</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Gutiérrez, José Angel (b. 1944)</field>
      <field name="author">Ellis, Mark R.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




GUTIERREZ, JOSE ANGEL (b. 1944)


José Angel Gutierrez, between 1965 and 1980


José Angel Gutierrez,along with Cesar Chavez,
Reies Tijerina, and Corky Gonzales,
stands out as an important leader in the Chicano
movement of the late 1960s and early
1970s. He was born into a middle-class family
on October 25, 1944, in Crystal City, Texas.
When he was still in grade school, his father
died and young Gutierrez was forced to work
in the fields to help support his family. Despite
facing such hardships early in his life, Gutierrez
emerged as a bright student and gifted
leader; he served as the student body president
of his high school. Gutierrez earned a bachelor's
degree in political science in 1966 from
Texas A&amp;M University in Kingsville and a master's
degree in the same field two years later
from St. Mary's University in San Antonio.

While at St. Mary's Gutierrez continued his
role as a student leader by helping to organize
a chapter of the Mexican American Youth Organization.
By 1970 Gutierrez had returned to
Crystal City, where he organized the Mexican
American population through a new political
party, La Raza Unida. With a mobilized Mexican
American electorate, Gutie;rrez was elected
to the city council and later to the school
board. From these positions of power, Gutierrez
and other Mexican American leaders enacted
changes in the school system, including
the introduction of bilingual and bicultural
education programs, and improved relations
between the Chicano and Anglo communities.

By the mid-1970s Gutierrez was less involved
in politics, but he continued to represent
his community. In 1974 he was elected to
a judgeship in Zavala County. He also continued
his education, earning a doctorate in
political science in 1976 from the University of
Texas. Gutierrez served as a judge until 1981
when he resigned to take a teaching position,
first at Colegio Cesar Chavez in Mt. Angel,
Oregon, and later at Western Oregon State
College. By 1986, however, Gutierrez was back
in Texas working on his law degree (which he
earned in 1988) at the University of Houston.
In 1993 he ran unsuccessfully for Lloyd Bentsen's
vacated U.S. Senate seat. Gutierrez was a
professor of political science at the University
of Texas at Arlington in 2001.


Mark R. Ellis
University of Nebraska at Kearney





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>