<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.med.009</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Capper, Arthur (1865-1951)</field>
      <field name="author">Socolofsky, Homer E.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




Capper, Arthur (1865-1951)

Publisher of agricultural journals, governor of
Kansas, longtime U.S. senator from Kansas,
and philanthropist Arthur Capper was born
in Garnett, Kansas, on July 14, 1865. In 1884,
after high school graduation, Capper moved
to Topeka, where he found employment with
the Topeka Capital and became a leading reporter.
He married Florence Crawford, only
daughter of the third Kansas governor. They
had no children. Acquiring his first weekly
newspaper in 1893, Capper consolidated it
with others, forming the Mail and Breeze. In
1900 he acquired a monthly agricultural journal.
In 1901 he added the Topeka Capital and
its Weekly Capital. Vigorous in increasing the
circulation and advertising revenues of all his
journals, Capper gained wealth rapidly. He
built a five-story plant across the street from
the capitol in Topeka and an elaborate mansion
nearby.

While some of his publications had a general
audience, Capper was best known for his
agricultural journals, such as the monthly Missouri Valley Farmer (known later as Capper's Farmer) and the Farmer's Mail and Breeze,
which acquired the Kansas Farmer and assumed
that name. In 1910 he purchased the
Missouri Ruralist, and for a time he owned
Nebraska and Oklahoma farm papers as well
as one covering the Rockies. He became partial
owner of leading farm papers published in
Cleveland, Ohio. All his other journals were
published in Topeka, with editorial offices in
the states of circulation: Kansas Farmer, Missouri Ruralist, Ohio Farmer, Michigan Farmer,
Pennsylvania Farmer, and Capper's Farmer
were all well known as the Capper Farm Press.

In 1912, as a Republican, Capper lost a close
race for Kansas governor, but he won in 1914
and 1916. In 1918 he was elected to the first of
five terms in the U.S. Senate. He was a conservative
and the leader of the Farm Bloc but not
an initiator of legislation. When he died on
December 19, 1951, his beneficiaries were a
surviving sister, leading employees, and the
Capper Foundation for Crippled Children.


Homer E. Socolofsky
Manhattan, Kansas




Socolofsky, Homer E. Arthur Capper: Publisher, Politician, Philanthropist. Lawrence: University Press of Kansas, 1962.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>