<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pg.061</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Oklahoma</field>
      <field name="author">Morgan, David R.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




OKLAHOMA

When Oklahoma became the forty-sixth state
in 1907, it brought together two disparate territories.
The eastern half of the state was Indian
Territory, a place where the federal government
had been sending Native Americans
since 1817. The western region, officially unassigned
land, eventually became Oklahoma
Territory. These two regions, reflecting significant
topographical differences, were even
more distinctive in history, culture, and political
orientation.

In the Land Run of 1889, white settlers
poured into the "unassigned lands" of what
would become Oklahoma Territory. These
homesteaders came largely from the Midwest,
bringing their Republican politics and the
values of frontier individualism. The northern
and western Oklahoma Plains was ideal wheat-growing
country. Today, it remains sparsely
settled, primarily agriculture land. Beginning
in the mid-1800s, other settlers, mostly whites
from Texas and the South, had begun a relentless
invasion of Indian Territory. The land in
the southeastern region, with rolling hills and
scrub forest, was far less suitable for large
farms. Many of the new occupants became
subsistence farmers. They brought along their
Democratic heritage and a southern cultural
and political outlook.

The enduring question remains: is Oklahoma
primarily a Plains or southern state? It
is both, and distinctive regional differences are
still visible today. The northwestern wheat-growing
region is still far more Republican
than the rural southeast. The political fault
line bisects the state from northeast to southwest,
largely reflecting the Indian Territory.
Oklahoma Territory division at statehood.
Old-timers still refer to the southeast as "Little
Dixie." It is the poorest part of the state and
remains the most Democratic. Since World
War II the state's two large metropolitan areas,
Oklahoma City and Tulsa, have joined the
rural northwest as Republican strongholds.

Statewide, more and more Oklahoma voters
have turned to Republican candidates. The last
Democratic presidential nominee to carry the
state was Lyndon Johnson in 1964. Unlike the
states of the Deep South, race has not been a
major cause of this shift. With an African
American population of about 8 percent, race
has never been the defining issue in Oklahoma
politics. A key influence in the state's shifting
political allegiance has been religion. With an
abundance of Protestant fundamentalists and
evangelicals, the state has become a bastion of
social conservatism. In 2000 the Christian
Right dominated the state's Republican Party.
Oklahoma's six House members, and senators
Don Nickles and Jim Inhofe, were all Republicans,
a first in state history. All had 100 percent
Christian Coalition voting records.

For statewide offices, the Republicans have
fared less well. In the year 2000 Gov. Frank
Keating, a Tulsa Republican, was serving his
second term. Of the additional ten statewide
offices, the Republicans held five. Democrats
controlled the state legislature, holding about
three-fifths of the seats in the House (60 of
101) and the Senate (33 of 48). Although party
registration favors the Democrats (about 57
percent to 35 percent Republican, with 8 percent
Independent), more Sooners self-identify
as Republicans than Democrats. At the end of
the twentieth century a statewide survey of
party identification shows 39 percent Republican,
31 percent Democrat, and the balance Independent
or other. These figures represent a
precise reversal of party identification from
the 1980s.

The state's populist-influenced constitution
scatters power widely. Boards and commissions
abound, mostly controlled indirectly, if
at all, by the state's chief executive. In formal
power, Oklahoma's governor ranks below
average. The office is especially weak on appointment
power and the authority to reorganize
the executive branch.

Following a 1960s bribery scandal in the state
supreme court, the voters approved a constitutional
amendment removing the courts from
partisan politics. The governor now appoints
members of the two highest courts to a six-year
term (the supreme court has nine members and
the court of criminal appeals five members).
The nominees must come from a list of three
names provided by a judicial nominating commission.
Each six years, the incumbents may
seek a new term by appearing on a retention
ballot. The voters elect lower-level judges on
nonpartisan ballots.

Oklahoma's political culture has been called
"frontier individualism" or "agrarian populist."
With a pro-gun, antiregulation electorate,
the state enjoys a low tax burden. Still, it
has a higher than average number of state and
local government employees. Such an anomaly
results in part from the continued political
strength of rural Oklahoma. The state contains
seventy-seven counties, each electing
eight separate officials, and there are more
than 500 independent school districts.

The state's population (about 3.4 million in
2000) grew less rapidly than the nation's as a
whole, causing the loss of a congressional seat
following the 2000 census. The economy has
diversified and is far less dependent today on
extractive industry and agriculture. Still, the
state's per capita income is below average and
is only partly offset by a lower cost of living. As
the state's quest for a more diversified economy
continues, Oklahoma struggles to find its
place in a global technology economy.

See also IMAGES AND ICONS: Boomers / NATIVE AMERICANS: Indian Territory.


David R. Morgan
University of Oklahoma




Markwood, Christopher L., ed. Oklahoma Government
and Politics: An Introduction. Dubuque IA: Kendall/Hunt
Pub. Co., 2000. Morgan, David R., Robert E. England, and
George G. Humphreys. Oklahoma Politics and Policies.
Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1991. Scales, James
R., and Danney Goble. Oklahoma Politics: A History. Norman:
University of Oklahoma Press, 1982.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>