<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.art.061</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Whittredge, Worthington (1820-1910)</field>
      <field name="author">Jansen, Anthony F.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




WHITTREDGE, WORTHINGTON (1820-1910)

Worthington Whittredge, the American landscape
artist, was born on May 22, 1820, on a
farm near Springfield, Ohio. He began his career
in Cincinnati, then spent a decade in
Düsseldorf and Rome before settling in 1861 in
New York City, where he became a leading
member of the Hudson River school.

Spurred on perhaps by Albert Bierstadt,
whom he had befriended in Europe, Whittredge
joined Gen. John Pope on an inspection
tour of the Central Plains in 1866 that left
Fort Leavenworth, Kansas, in early June for
Fort Kearney, Nebraska Territory, then followed
the Oregon Trail and South Platte River
to Fort Collins and Denver, Colorado Territory.
These areas provided him with most of
his western subjects. From there the expedition
went to Santa Fe, Albuquerque, and Fort
Union, New Mexico, before returning to Fort
Riley, Kansas, via the Old Santa Fe and Cimarron
Trails. He returned for shorter visits in
1870 in order to sketch some trees near Fort
Collins for his major work Crossing the Ford
(1868–70) and again the following year to the
Denver area.

Unlike Bierstadt, Whittredge was impressed
not by the lofty height of the Rockies but by
the breadth of the Plains, and the mountains
provide no more than a backdrop in most of
his paintings. The western pictures before
1870 are filled with romantic imagery inspired
by the poems of William Cullen Bryant, who
decisively influenced Whittredge's Hudson
River pictures, while the later ones retain
the freshness of his oil sketches, from which
they are often nearly indistinguishable. The
artist relied on his experiences in Europe to
describe the Plains, but his paintings are
mainly distinctive for an uncommon directness
and lyricism that reflect his personality.
He paid particular attention to conditions
of light and atmosphere. Native Americans,
however, served mainly to set the scene, and
he had little interest in recording their ways of
life, which he nevertheless depicted accurately.
Whittredge built up a sizable stock of subjects
showing the Plains and foothills of the
Rockies, but in his large canvases he concentrated
mainly on variants of several favorite
compositions: On the Plains (1872), Crossing the Platte River (1872–74), and On the Cache La Oudre River (1876).

Despite his success in treating western landscapes,
Whittredge stopped painting them after
1876, when his art underwent a major
change under the impact of French Barbizon
painting, especially the light-filled style of
Charles Daubigny. Along with the other Hudson
River painters, Whittredge was soon
eclipsed by the American Barbizon school, but
he remained a respected member of the New
York art community until his retirement in
1900. He died on February 25, 1910, in Summit,
New Jersey, where he had lived since 1880.


Anthony F. Jansen
University of North Carolina-Wilmington




Janson, Anthony F. Worthington Whittredge. Cambridge:
Cambridge University Press, 1990.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>