<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.na.045</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Indian Cowboys</field>
      <field name="author">Iverson, Peter</field>
      <field name="text">

 




INDIAN COWBOYS

Plains Indians have been cowboys for a long
time. Their involvement in the cattle industry
of the region began in the late nineteenth century
and continues to the present. Indian men
and women have also been involved for an
extended period of time in the world of rodeo.
Their participation in ranching and rodeo is
significant both in economic and cultural
terms.

After the American Civil War, cattle ranching
played an important role in the economic
development of the Plains. This development
came at considerable cost. Native communities
lost millions of acres through treaties,
agreements, land allotment, land cessions, and
long-term leases. With bison hunting no
longer possible, Plains Indian peoples had to
find alternative means to sustain themselves.
Cattle ranching offered Indian men a chance to
ride, an alternative to farming, and an opportunity
to demonstrate both competence and
generosity. Cattle could be given as presents,
used to feed people at a gathering, and employed
to teach young people about responsibility
and reciprocity. Given their needs and
given the success their new neighbors were
enjoying, it is not surprising that so many Indian
individuals and communities turned to
cattle ranching. Some, like Quanah Parker,
knew spectacular, if too brief, success. Others
started ranches that continue to our own day.
Many Native cowboys also found work as cowboys
on ranches owned by non-Indians.

Progress in the Indian cattle industry during
the twentieth century was limited by fluctuating
federal policies and market conditions, as
well as the problems of fractionated land-ownership
because of the division of allotted
land through inheritance and sale. Nonetheless,
many Indian ranchers continue in the
business, either through tribal or community
enterprises or as individuals. They know the
same satisfactions and experience the same
problems as their non-Indian counterparts.
Access to better legal counsel has permitted
tribes in many instances to obtain more equitable
leases or to promote ranching by tribal
members.

Plains Indian rodeo dates back to the turn of
the century. At agricultural fairs at the Crow
Indian Reservation and elsewhere, rodeos began
to be featured as prominent components
of annual gatherings. The Crows took great
pride in their abilities and accomplishments
as bronc riders. At Rosebud and other reservations
in the Dakotas, Lakota cowboys also
demonstrated their talents in various rodeos.
The best Indian cowboys, like Sam Bird in
Ground (Crow) and George Defender (Standing
Rock Sioux), captured world championship
titles early in the twentieth century. Tom
Three Persons (Blood) won instant immortality
by riding Midnight in the first Calgary
Stampede rodeo in 1912.

The Plains Indian rodeo tradition continues.
Plains Indian cowgirls and cowboys
participate in regional competitions, often instructed
and judged by relatives eager to pass
along their love for the sport, and they have
also enjoyed considerable success in the Indian
National Finals Rodeo. Names like Gladstone
and Guardipee, Bird and Bruised Head are
immediately recognizable to all those who
cherish the history and heritage of Indian
rodeo.

See also AGRICULTURE: Cattle Ranching / SPORTS AND RECREATION: Crow Fair; Rodeo.


Peter Iverson
Arizona State University




Dempsey, Hugh A. Tom Three Persons: Legend of an Indian
Cowboy. Saskatoon: Purich Publishing, 1997. Iverson, Peter.
When Indians Became Cowboys: Native Peoples and
Cattle Ranching in the American West. Norman: University
of Oklahoma Press, 1994. Iverson, Peter, and Linda Mac-
Cannell. Riders from the West: Portraits of Indian Rodeo.
Seattle: University of Washington Press, 1999.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>