<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.076</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Travel Literature</field>
      <field name="author">Cook, Nancy</field>
      <field name="text">

 




TRAVEL LITERATURE

Whether traveling as part of an exploratory
expedition, for trade purposes, as emigrants,
or as tourists, since the sixteenth century writers
have tried to represent the vast, often disorienting
spaces of the Great Plains. Beginning
with Francisco Vasquez de Coronado,
travelers have created metaphorical links with
the familiar in order to convey the unfamiliar
to their readers. Coronado compared the
Plains to the sea, a trope that remains common
in the twenty-first century. Drawing on a
European tradition that offered no models of
description for such land forms, writers have
struggled to describe both the vastness and the
sense of disorientation they felt in a Plains
landscape.

During the period of exploration, travelers'
views depended upon their course and mode of
transportation. Whereas French explorers and
Lewis and Clark, traveling by river, found
beauty and abundant wildlife and vegetation,
overland travelers such as Zebulon Pike found a
Great American Desert. Others such as Englishman
Henry Kelsey, traveling in 1690 across what
are now the Prairie Provinces, noted with some
exasperation that during the long trek he saw
only "Beast and grass." Repeatedly, these travelers
registered their own sense of insignificance
when confronted with the great openness of the
Plains. Most of these accounts take the journal
form, which allows readers to better gauge the
effect of the Plains on travelers. Through the
usually daily journal entries, readers gain a sense
of the distances traversed, the harshness of travel
conditions, and the unrelenting boredom for
travelers with inadequate skills for making distinctions
in a land new to them.

Travelers, whether explorers, scientists, traders,
immigrants, or tourists, write of the difficulty
adjusting to the Plains. They feel disoriented,
their accustomed sense of perspective
fails them, and they notice odd optical effects.
Distances deceive, objects appear much larger,
and travelers are tricked by mirages. While
these effects tend to make travelers uncomfortable,
the Plains offer compensation in the clear
and healthy air, the sense of boundless freedom,
and the restorative powers of Plains life for the
ill and the invalid. Josiah Gregg, Santa Fe trader
and author of Commerce of the Prairies (1844),
felt that his Plains travels healed him, and
he only reluctantly returned to the settlements.
Many women travelers found the open spaces
exhilarating, viewing the Plains in spring as a
vast garden. In her 1846 diary, published as
Down the Santa Fe Trail and into Mexico: The Diary of Susan Shelby Magoffin (1926), Susan
Magoffin describes the freedom she felt on the
Plains in spite of traveling with Gen. Stephen
Kearny's Army of the West.

Yet the great expanses continued to resist attempts
at description. Frequently, travelers
write of their own inadequacy at representing
what they experience. The phrase "words cannot
convey" appear repeatedly in many accounts.
Many critics claim that words failed so
many travel writers because they were too dependent
upon European literary models. The
well-educated tourist in particular was too attached
to aesthetic conventions to see the
Plains in any other way than from a "civilized"
point of view. And the Plains rarely corresponded
with the attributes accorded aesthetic
models such as the beautiful, the picturesque,
and the sublime. Nevertheless, references to
the sublimity or lack thereof dot many accounts.
In spite of the writer's scientific or documentary
goals, the language of European romanticism
prevailed among many educated
travelers, with Native Americans compared to
Moors in many accounts from the nineteenth
century.

Related to this tradition, both nineteenthand
twentieth-century travelers to the Great
Plains often lamented what they saw to be the
imminent extinction of the bison and the Indians
and the very vastness of the Plains. Consequently,
accounts from George Catlin's Illustrations of the Manners, Customs, and Conditions of the North American Indians with Letters and Notes (1841) to Francis Parkman's The Oregon Trail (1849) to Ian Frazier's Great Plains (1988)
offer a sense of both consequence and urgency
for getting the details right.

Many travelers had their sense of the Plains
formed by reading earlier accounts before they
arrived. Parkman read Prince Maximilian of
Wied-Neuwied, Gregg, and John Charles Fremont
before his journey, and Susan Shelby
Mago.n read Gregg before her trip over the
Santa Fe Trail. Classic American writers as diverse
as James Fenimore Cooper and Edgar
Allan Poe read published accounts and then
created characters experienced in Plains life;
neither actually traveled to the Plains. Not surprisingly,
with published accounts in mind if
not in hand, such writers projected their own
and others' expectations onto Plains landscapes.
While travel writing about the Great
Plains offers a fascinating look at the way writers
of European descent have struggled with
a powerful and unfamiliar landscape, it remained
for inhabitants to find a language adequate
to convey a sense of place.

See also GENDER: Victorian Women Travelers.


Nancy Cook
University of Rhode Island




Dondore, Dorothy. The Prairie and the Making of Middle America: Four Centuries of Description. New York: Antiquarian
Press, 1961. Francis, R. Douglas. Images of the West: Responses to the Canadian Prairies, 1690–1960. Saskatoon:
Western Producer Prairie Books, 1989. Thacker,
Robert. The Great Prairie Fact and Literary Imagination.
Albuquerque: University of New Mexico Press, 1989.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>