<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ct.045</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Rural-Urban Population Change</field>
      <field name="author">Johnson, Kevin M.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




RURAL-URBAN POPULATION CHANGE

In this synthesis of historical demographic
trends in rural and urban areas of the Great
Plains, an updated version of the regional definition
used by the Economic Research Service
of the Department of Agriculture is used.
In all, 484 counties in eleven states are included,
all of them within the boundaries delineating
the Great Plains region. Comparisons
are offered for those portions of the
Great Plains in Canada.

In the United States, counties are subdivided
into metropolitan and nonmetropolitan
based on the 1993 Office of Management and
Budget definition. Metropolitan areas contain
a core county with a city of at least 50,000
and any adjacent counties that are socially
and economically integrated with the urban
county. To avoid problems of compatibility
over time, any county classified as metropolitan
in 1993 is here considered metropolitan
throughout the entire study period,
even though it might have been nonmetropolitan
under an earlier definition. Of the 484
Great Plains counties, 444 are classified as
nonmetropolitan and 40 as metropolitan. The
terms metropolitan and urban are used interchangeably
here, as are the terms nonmetropolitan
and rural. Such usage is consistent
with the extensive research literature examining
recent population redistribution trends
but differs from the Census Bureau definition
of urban, which includes individuals residing
in places of 2,500 or more.

In 1870 approximately 127,000 people lived
in the Great Plains of the United States. The
population grew rapidly over the next six decades.
By 1930 more than 6.8 million people
resided in the region. Migration fueled much
of this population gain as the great agricultural
potential of the region attracted millions
of settlers. Natural increase also contributed
to the rapid population gains, as high rural
fertility produced a significant excess of births
over deaths.

In 1870 nearly 80 percent of the Plains residents
lived in rural areas; in 1930 almost 74
percent of the Plains population still lived in
rural areas, which had gained more than 4.9
million residents during the period. Places
that were urban or would soon become urban
grew by 1.8 million during the same period.
However, after 1930 the growth patterns in urban
and rural areas diverged: the rural population
peaked in 1930, whereas the urban population
continued to grow.

Between 1930 and 1940 the American Great
Plains suffered a population loss of 208,000.
More than 75 percent of the counties in the region
lost population during the decade. Most
of the loss resulted from net out-migration.
The Great Depression and severe drought
forced many rural families to abandon farms,
stores, and other enterprises. In such a difficult
situation, parents chose to have fewer children,
resulting in a lower rate of natural increase.
Population declines were most severe
in rural areas, which lost 363,000 residents;
fewer than 20 percent of the nonmetropolitan
counties gained population. For example, in
the Texas Panhandle, twenty-three of thirtytwo
counties lost population; the nine that
gained were oil- and gas-producing counties.
By contrast, the urban counties of the region
added 154,000 people.

Growth resumed again during the 1940s,
when the region as a whole gained 558,000
residents. Natural increase fueled almost all of
this growth. Migrants continued to leave the
rural areas, attracted by the recovering industrial
sector of the nation's cities. The growth
that did occur was selective geographically:
only 35 percent of the counties actually gained
population, and nearly all of that growth was
in urban areas. Overall, urban counties gained
631,000 residents, more than enough to offset
the 72,000-person loss in rural areas. Only
about 31 percent of the rural counties grew
during the decade, compared to 78 percent of
the urban counties.

Population growth accelerated during the
1950s. However, the substantial gain of 1.1 million
was concentrated in only 35 percent of
Plains counties. All of this growth resulted
from the substantial natural increase associated
with the baby boom, because the region
actually experienced a net migration loss of
322,000. Though the region as a whole gained
population, rural areas saw a slight population
decline during the 1950s caused by a staggering
migration loss of 753,000. This loss represents
16 percent of the population residing in
rural areas at the beginning of the decade.
The exodus of young adults was particularly
severe: rural areas lost more than 229,000
twenty- to twenty-nine-year-olds between
1950 and 1960, or 44 percent of the age group.
Because this age group produces most of the
children, the out-migration had significant
demographic implications and represented a
substantial loss of human capital.

Between 1960 and 1970 the population of
the Great Plains grew by only 385,000, the
smallest decennial gain on record, apart from
the 1930s. Natural increase was sufficient to
offset net out-migration (611,000) in the area
as a whole, but overall only 23 percent of the
counties experienced population gain. While
the rural population declined by 231,000 in the
1960s, the urban population grew by 668,000.
The rural losses resulted from a net outflow of
708,000, which was only partially offset by natural
increase. By contrast, urban areas gained
97,000 by migration and 571,000 by natural
increase. By the end of the 1960s the population
residing in metropolitan areas of the
Great Plains exceeded that in rural areas for
the first time in history.

At the national level, the 1970s witnessed
a remarkable nonmetropolitan demographic
turnaround characterized by widespread inmigration
and substantial population increase.
The Great Plains participated in this
reversal of trends to a certain extent. Rural
population grew for the first time in four decades.
However, the rural gain of 241,000 was
almost entirely due to natural increase. Outmigration
continued from rural areas, albeit
at a dramatically reduced rate. In contrast, urban
areas had a net migration gain of 473,000
and a natural increase gain of 486,000. This
substantial urban growth, coupled with modest
rural growth, produced an overall population
gain of nearly 1.2 million in the 1970s.

The turnaround did not last long. The region
only grew by 379,000 during the 1980s,
and only 21 percent of the counties increased
their populations, the fewest in history. Outmigration
again became common in the 1980s,
with a net loss of 562,000. The population
grew modestly because births exceeded deaths
and offset out-migration. Both rural and urban
areas of the Great Plains suffered migration
losses during the 1980s. However,
the magnitude of the rural losses was much
greater. Rural areas experienced a net migration
loss of 519,000 people compared to an
urban loss of only 42,000.

During the 1990s nonmetropolitan America
experienced a rural rebound. Some evidence
of this rebound is reflected in the demographic
patterns of the Great Plains, which
as a whole experienced net in-migration, primarily
in the metropolitan areas. Rural areas
continued to experience net out-migration,
though at a rate considerably below that of the
1980s, and many rural areas close to urban
centers gained population because of their appeal
as residential and employment centers.
Still, Plains rural population grew by only
42,000 between 1990 and 1998. Long years of
out-migration of young people from rural
areas had left few adults to produce children.
Metropolitan areas of the Great Plains, on the
other hand, enjoyed both significant net inmigration
and substantial natural increase in
the 1990s. From 1990 to 1996, for example, net
migration gain in the Denver region was
175,000, making it one of the fastest growing
metropolitan areas in the United States.

Generally similar demographic trends have
occurred in the Prairie Provinces. Initial settlement
was largely rural but later than on
most of the Great Plains. About two-thirds of
all homestead entries on the Canadian Prairies
from 1870 to 1930 were registered in the
fifteen years before World War I. Rural population
has diminished since the 1930s, but the
declines have not been uniform. Rural areas
close to Canadian urban centers and those
with scenic or economic advantages were less
likely to lose population. Metropolitan areas
on the Canadian Great Plains gained population,
as did their U.S. counterparts. For example,
Calgary, Alberta, known as the "Energy
Capital of Canada," has been one of the fastest
growing cities in Canada since the 1940s. In
1941 Calgary's census metropolitan area (CMA)
population was 93,000; by 1981 this figure had
risen to 625,966. In 1996 Calgary's cma population
was 821,628, making Calgary the sixth
largest cma in Canada. Canada also enjoyed
a similar rural turnaround during the 1970s.
However, again as in the case of the United
States, the impact of the turnaround was considerably
less pronounced on the Plains than
it was elsewhere in Canada.

In sum, the patterns of population change
in the Great Plains over the past 130 years have
been complex. From 1870 to 1930 the population
of the U.S. Great Plains grew significantly,
with most of the growth occurring in areas
that remain rural to this day. As late as 1930, 75
percent of the Plains population was rural;
thereafter, the rural population generally diminished,
while the urban population grew
dramatically. In 1998 nearly 61 percent of the
11.1 million people of the U.S. Plains lived
in metropolitan areas. Only 4.4 million remained
in rural areas, down from a peak of 5
million in 1930. Since 1950 the rural Great
Plains of the United States have suffered a net
migration loss of 2.1 million people, many of
them young adults. This loss of so many potential
parents has now drained much of the
demographic resilience from the rural Plains.
As a result, more than 200 of the 444 rural
counties in the Great Plains had more deaths
than births between 1990 and 1998. The proportion
of Great Plains counties with such
natural decrease is greater than in any region
of the country at any time in history.


Kenneth M. Johnson
Loyola University Chicago




Albrecht, Don E. "The Renewal of Population Loss in
the Non-Metropolitan Great Plains." Rural Sociology 58
(1993): 233–46. Carlyle, William J. "Rural Population
Change on the Canadian Prairies." Great Plains Research 4
(1994): 65–87. Johnson, K. M. "When Deaths Exceed
Births: Natural Decrease in the United States." International Regional Science Review 15 (1993): 179–98.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>