<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.na.015</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Black Kettle (ca. 1800-1868)</field>
      <field name="author">Johansen, Bruce E.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BLACK KETTLE (ca. 1800-1868)

Southern Cheyenne chief Black Kettle


Black Kettle (Moketavato) was a leading chief
of the Southern Cheyennes through the difficult years of the 1850s and 1860s. Born in the
Black Hills before that area was part of the
United States, Black Kettle married a woman
of the Wotapio band and lived with his wife's
people, as was customary. When the chief of
that band, Bear with Feathers, died in 1850,
Black Kettle was elected chief. In time, Black
Kettle married another three women, all sisters
to his first wife, and with them Black Kettle
had seventeen children.

Black Kettle was a "Peace Chief," dedicated
to strong leadership through nonaggression.
After the discovery of gold in Colorado in
1858, the hunting lands of the Southern Cheyennes
became increasingly encroached upon
by Americans, and resentment developed on
both sides. In 1864 Black Kettle and his band,
which had avoided hostilities and tried to
forge a peace, were camped on Sand Creek,
an intermittent tributary of the Arkansas
in present-day Kiowa County, Colorado (now
called the Big Sandy). On November 28, Col.
(and Reverend) John M. Chivington, with 600
to 1,000 men of the Colorado Volunteers,
mounted a surprise attack on the village. As
Black Kettle hoisted a white flag and an American
flag in an attempt to stop the violence,
Chivington's men massacred between 100 and
200 Indians, mainly women and children.

The Cheyennes retaliated by killing several
hundred settlers during the following four
years. Black Kettle worked to reestablish peace.
His mark, for example, appears second on the
Treaty of Medicine Lodge Creek of October 28,
1867, an attempt to establish peace on the Central
and Southern Plains. But Black Kettle's
efforts all came to nothing on November 27,
1868, when his sleeping village on the Washita
River, in present-day Roger Mills County, Oklahoma,
was attacked by troops led by George
Armstrong Custer. Black Kettle and more than
100 of his people were killed.

See also WAR: Sand Creek Massacre; Washita, Battle of the .


Bruce E. Johansen
University of Nebraska at Omaha




Hoig, Stan. The Sand Creek Massacre. Norman: University
of Oklahoma Press, 1961. Moore, John H. The Cheyenne Nation: A Social and Demographic History. Lincoln: University
of Nebraska Press, 1987.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>