<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ct.015</field>
      <field name="titleMain">County Seats</field>
      <field name="author">Schellenberg, James A.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




COUNTY SEATS

Approximately 500 counties exist in the Great
Plains, and each of them has a county seat, that
is, a city or town designated as the county's
center for local government.

The county-centered Virginia system had a
stronger influence upon the organization of
local governments during U.S. westward expansion
than the town-centered system begun
in colonial New England. Although townships
do exist in states as far west as Nebraska and
the Dakotas, they are clearly less important
than the county unit. The prevailing form of
county government in the Great Plains included
locally elected commissioners and a
number of elected county executive officers
operating from the courthouse of the county
seat. State or territorial legislation also generally
recognized the importance of popular
sovereignty in selecting which town became
the county seat.

With few exceptions, the county seat was
(or became, after it was selected as the county
capital) the town with the largest population.
In a few cases, when the largest town lacked
a central location, the county seat went to a
smaller town nearer the county center. Examples
of leading cities failing to become county
seats include Coffeyville and Pittsburg in Kansas
and Crete and Norfolk in Nebraska.

The likelihood for future growth of a town
chosen by a county-seat election often led
such elections to be highly disputed. In some
cases (such as in Pratt, Stevens, and Wichita
Counties in Kansas), battles between rival
towns resulted in deaths. More commonly, a
raiding party from a town seeking to become
the new county seat (often following a disputed
election) forcibly seized the county records
from a rival town. This was the case in at
least twenty different counties in Nebraska
and the Dakotas.

The rapid settlement of the Great Plains led
to the organization of many counties within a
few years. For example, all of the counties in
northwest Texas were organized in the same
year, 1876, and in 1873 no fewer than 45 counties
(of the 120 now existing in North and
South Dakota) were organized in Dakota Territory.
Rapid settlement and county organization
were leading factors in the most violent
county-seat controversies, often pitting very
young towns (and sometimes only projected
locations for towns) against each other. Most
of the "county-seat wars" (as the more bitter
controversies have been called) occurred in
the Great Plains during the last quarter of the
nineteenth century.

Few county seats were changed during
the twentieth century, though this has happened
in several cases when strong population
growth of one town supported its claim to
county-seat honors. This occurred in Logan
and Morton Counties in western Kansas as
late as the 1960s, when new county seats were
located at Oakley and Elkhart, respectively.
With very few exceptions, however, the counties
and county seats that had been established
by the early twentieth century have remained
unchanged.

See also POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT: 
Civil Divisions of Government.


James A. Schellenber
Indiana State University




Kane, Joseph Nathan. The American Counties. New York:
Scarecrow Press, 1983. Schellenberg, James A. Conflict between
Communities. New York: Paragon House, 1987.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>