<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.rel.018</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Doukhobors</field>
      <field name="author">Friesen, John W.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




DOUKOBORS


Ruins of a Doukhobor prayer home near Kamsack, Saskatchewan (above), Doukhobor prayer home in Saskatoon, Saskatchewan (below)


Originating in seventeenth-century southern
Russia, the Doukhobors (Spirit Wrestlers)
were one of nearly 200 sects to break away
from the Russian Orthodox Church. The
Doukhobors renounced all human institutions,
including church and government, and
became pacifists.

Persecution in Russia and generous immigration
policies framed by Clifford Sifton,
Canada's minister of the interior, lured a constituent
of 7,500 Doukhobors to Canada in
1899. The Canadian government agreed to
their two stated requirements: that they be exempt
from military service and that they
be permitted to settle in solid blocks. They
soon established fifty-seven successful farming
communes in east-central Saskatchewan.
Sifton wanted experienced farmers to settle
the Great Plains, and the Doukhobors certainly
qualified. For generations they had
tilled the soil, and Leo Tolstoy called them
"the best farmers in Russia."

In 1902, without warning, the Canadian
government insisted that the Doukhobors individually
register their settlement lands by
swearing allegiance to the Crown, something
the Doukhobor conscience would not allow.
Reaction to the demand caused a three-way
split among the Doukhobors. One group,
composed of 236 families, complied and became
known as Independent Doukhobors.
They continue to farm in east-central Saskatchewan
around the towns of Blaine Lake,
Canora, and Kamsack. Another more zealous
faction, known as the Sons of Freedom, determined
to embarrass the government with a
protest march, but the cold October weather
drove them back home. The main group (the
Community Doukhobors) sent for their leader
from Russia, Peter the Lordly Verigin, and he
led them to British Columbia, where previously
owned lands were purchased that did
not require the dreaded oath of allegiance.

The Doukhobor contribution to Plains agriculture
cannot easily be exaggerated. By 1903
the community owned sixteen steam engines,
eleven threshing machines, six flour mills, and
five sawmills. They had amassed 600 horses,
400 oxen, and 865 cows. Just prior to their
migration to British Columbia, they managed
258,880 acres of farmland, of which 49,429
acres had been seeded. The land was cultivated
the hard way, with oxen, and sometimes
even by hand. Although challenged by harsh
winds, unpredictable water supplies, and the
occasional prairie fire, the Doukhobors prevailed.

The fate of the British Columbia Doukhobors
(the Christian Community of Universal
Brotherhood, or CCUB) bordered on the
tragic. Peter Verigin was killed on October 24,
1924, when the train he was riding from Castlegar
to Grand Forks, British Columbia, was
hit by an explosion. In 1938, partially in fear
of such a large utopian experiment, involving
some 10,000 people with property worth $6
million, the Canadian government initiated
a surprise foreclosure on the community.
Doukhobor lands and properties were seized
and sold at prices well below cost, and the
ccub was liquidated.

Eager to keep their vision alive, the Doukhobors
formed the Union of Spiritual Communities
in Christ (USCC), which continues to
sponsor a number of local and national events
related to Doukhobor history, spirituality, and
culture.

See also POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT: Sifton, Clifford.


John W. Friesen
University of Calgary




Friesen, John W., and Michael M. Verigin. The Community
Doukhobors: A People in Transition. Ottawa: Borealis
Press, 1996. Tarasoff, Koozma J. Plakun Trava: The
Doukhobors. Grand Forks, British Columbia: Mir Publication
Society, 1982. Woodcock, George, and Ivan Avakumovic.
The Doukhobors. Toronto: McClelland and Stewart
Ltd., 1977.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>