<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.art.054</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Russell, Andrew J. (1829-1902)</field>
      <field name="author">Williams, Susan E.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




RUSSELL, ANDREW J. (1829-1902)

Born on March 20, 1829, in Walpole, New
Hampshire, Andrew Joseph Russell apprenticed
with a local artisan in Nunda, New York,
and began his professional career painting
portraits and landscapes for influential men
in railroading and politics. He recruited for
the Union army, was elected company captain,
and served in the defenses of Washington
in 1862. Brig. Gen. Herman Haupt appointed
him government photographer on March 1,
1863, and he served in Virginia as acting quartermaster
to the United States Military Rail
Road Construction Corps until September 9,
1865.

To encourage settlement and investment
in the West, Union Pacific vice president
Thomas C. Durant commissioned Russell
to document the transcontinental railroad.
During 1868 the photographer lived in the
construction camps and periodically sent his
negatives east for printing as stereographs. He
returned to New York in December and published
The Great West Illustrated in the spring.
On his second trip west he photographed
Omaha and the growing Nebraska towns
of Fremont, Columbus, Grand Island, and
North Platte on his way to the joining of the
rails at Promontory, Utah, on May 10, 1869.
Thousands of newspaper readers viewed his
images and read his description of the ceremony
in Frank Leslie's Illustrated. The center
spread–East Meets West at Laying of Last Rail–became historic immediately. During
the summer Russell camped in the Wasatch
and Uinta Mountains and then took the train
to California; in December he returned to
Omaha. Russell established the Decoration
and Designing Company in New York City
after his publishing partnership failed in 1870.
He worked as a photojournalist for Frank
Leslie and died in Brooklyn of congestive
heart failure on September 20, 1902.



Susan E. Williams
Oakland, California




Combs, Barry B. Westward to Promontory. New York:
Crown Publishers, 1986. Naef, Weston, and James N.
Wood. Era of Exploration: The Rise of Landscape Photography in the American West, 1860-1885. New York: Metropolitan
Museum of Art, and Buffalo: Albright-Knox Art
Gallery, 1975. Williams, Susan E. "The Truth Be Told: The
Union Pacific Railroad Photographs of Andrew J. Russell."
View Camera (January-February 1996): 36-43.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>