<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.war.048</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Texas Revolution</field>
      <field name="author">Lack, Paul D.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




TEXAS REVOLUTION

The events known as the Texas Revolution
separated Texas from Mexico in 1836. It resulted
from efforts of Texas residents, mostly
Anglo Americans who had emigrated from
the United States, to retain their virtual political
autonomy. Disputes over immigration
policy and slavery had led to growing tensions
and protests between them and the government
of Mexico. These became irreconcilable
in 1835, when Mexico abandoned its federalist
constitution in favor of a centralized order.
Texas resistance brought a military response
from Mexico, which in turn resulted in war,
beginning in October 1835. To promote internal
unity and elicit support from Mexican federalists,
provisional authorities refrained from
declaring independence until March 2, 1836.

The war involved about an equal total number
of soldiers on each side (approximately
4,000), but the Texas armies consisted of undisciplined
volunteers, including many from
the United States. They served in units headed
by elected officers and often without an overall
commander. The war consisted of two offensive
campaigns. The first, by the Texas
army under Stephen F. Austin and others, resulted
in the capitulation of Bexar (San Antonio)
and surrender of Mexican forces on
December 10, 1835. The second, under President
Antonio Lopez de Santa Anna, focused
on redeeming that loss by attacking the Alamo,
while other Texas armies succumbed to
indecision and a swift movement of Mexican
forces under José Urrea. Texas volunteers then
rallied under Gen. Sam Houston and retreated
deep into East Texas until they halted
and assaulted the Mexicans at San Jacinto on
April 21. A captive himself, Santa Anna ordered
the remainder of Mexican forces to
withdraw from Texas and gave his own recognition
to the Texas Republic, though this act,
conducted under compulsion, did not bring a
true accord. In 1837 Sam Houston was elected
the first president of the Republic of Texas.


Paul D. Lack
McMurry University




Barr, Alwyn. Texans in Revolt: The Battle for San Antonio,
1835. Austin: University of Texas Press, 1990. Lack, Paul D.
The Texas Revolutionary Experience: A Political and Social
History, 1835–1886. College Station: Texas A&amp;M University
Press, 1992.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>