<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.art.028</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Gohlke, Frank (b. 1942)</field>
      <field name="author">Rohrbach, John B.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




GOHLKE, FRANK (b. 1942)

Born in Wichita Falls, Texas, on April 3, 1942,
artist-photographer Frank Gohlke took up
the medium in the mid-1960s while a graduate
student in English literature at Yale University.
Encouraged and influenced by photographers
Walker Evans and Paul Caponigro, he initially
worked under the sway of New England's
thick woods and rolling hills. Yet Gohlke
found his true artistic voice after moving to
Minneapolis in 1971. Drawn to a bundle of
grain elevators near his new home, he began
what became a six-year photographic meditation
that explored how these great behemoths
have come to define the landscape, acting as
focal points for regional communities.

Gohlke gained national acclaim in 1975 as
one of the nine photographers featured in the
influential exhibition New Topographics: Photographs of the Man-Altered Landscape. The
artists in this show were heralded for bucking
the fine art landscape tradition by drawing
attention to the often-prosaic beauty of
the built environment. The following year
Gohlke contributed to the Seagram Corporation's
renowned Courthouse Project, photographing
courthouses in North Texas. In 1984
he took part in the "Contemporary Texas"
photographic project. He also has completed
extensive photographic series on the aftermath
of the 1980 Mount St. Helens eruption
in Washington and the Sudbury River in
Massachusetts.

A potent sense of place marks the core of
Gohlke's art. Reflecting his Plains roots, his
work is infused with quiet, an appreciation for
space and balance, and a recognition of the
fragility of humanity's relationship with nature.
Time also is important. For every photograph
capturing a moment like a flash of
lightning or a signpost acutely bent by tornado
winds, he offers elegiac visions of ordinary
structures, objects, and places. At times
his work comes infused with a wry humor. In
this personal nexus he seeks to clarify how we
come to define what we call home.


John B. Rohrbach
Amon Carter Museum




Gohlke, Frank. Landscapes from the Middle of the World, Photographs 1972–1987. San Francisco: Friends of Photography,
1988. Gohlke, Frank. Measure of Emptiness: Grain Elevators in the American Landscape. Baltimore MD:
Johns Hopkins University Press, 1992.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>