<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.art.048</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Ranney, William (1813-1857)</field>
      <field name="author">Dippie, Brian W.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




RANNEY, WILLIAM (1813-1857)

William Tylee Ranney, born in Middletown,
Connecticut, on May 9, 1813, achieved a substantial
reputation as a genre artist specializing
in hunting and western scenes prior to his
death in Hoboken, New Jersey, on November
18, 1857, at the age of forty-four.

Since he was born and died in the East,
Ranney's affinity for western subjects requires
explanation. The war for Texas independence
lured him west in 1836, when he was an art
student in Brooklyn, and he spent a formative
year in the Southwest that left no impression
on his work as a portraitist and painter of
history and genre scenes until 1846, when the
annexation of Texas and the Mexican War created
a demand for western subjects. Unlike
George Catlin, Ranney was not a painter of
Indians. He concentrated on white pioneers
and, a contemporary thought, "caught the
spirit of border adventures."

Ranney's style was highly refined if rather
static, and he was adept at the precise detail
dear to genre painting with its focus on everyday
life. His western scenes depicted parties
of pioneer men and women on the move and
picturesque frontier types sometimes fighting
Indians, more often gossiping in and meandering
through a spacious land tinted in sunset
colors. Though his only personal experience
was in Texas, Ranney generalized the
settings in his western paintings. Texas became
the "broad prairie" in The Retreat
(1850), which showed three trappers fleeing
from pursuing Indians across an open country
devoid of shelter, and in Advice on the Prairie
(1853), which showed a party of emigrants
listening raptly to a veteran plainsman tell
them of what lay ahead. Ranney, in short,
worked his own variations on the West as a
theater for perilous adventure and as a prospective
paradise for those who dreamed of a
land of milk and honey.


Brian W. Dippie
University of Victoria




Dippie, Brian W. West-fever. Los Angeles: Autry Museum
of Western Heritage in Association with the University of
Washington Press, 1998. Grubar, Francis S. William Ranney: Painter of the Early West. New York: Clarkson N.
Potter, 1962.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>