<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.arc.048</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Tipis</field>
      <field name="author">Deaver, Ken Deaver, Sherri</field>
      <field name="text">

 




TIPIS

"A young Oglala girl sitting in front of a tipi, with a puppy beside her, probably on or near Pine Ridge Reservation, 1891." (John C. Graybill collection, Library of Congress)


Tipis are the conical skin- or canvas-covered
dwellings used by the Plains Indians as permanent
or seasonal dwellings. The Sioux word
tipi literally translates as "used to live in." In
the nineteenth century each tipi accommodated,
on average, eight to ten adults and children.
Minimally, tipis consist of a number
of long, thin poles placed vertically to form
a conical framework, a hide or canvas cover,
and tent pegs, rocks, or sod used to hold the
cover to the ground.

The framework of tipis consists of peeled
poles trimmed of all knots and branches and
thinned at the base. Tipis normally utilize fifteen
to twenty-five poles, two to adjust the
smoke flaps and the rest for the frame. The
poles are tied together at the peak of the cone,
but poles extend several feet beyond the point
where they cross. Size is limited by available
pole size. An eighteen- to twenty-footdiameter
tipi uses sixteen to eighteen poles,
each twenty-two to twenty-five feet long.
Some tribes, particularly the Crows, preferred
longer poles that extended higher above the
cover. The poles were usually two to three
inches in diameter where they crossed and
three to six inches at their butts.

In many parts of the Northern Plains,
lodgepole pine was the preferred tree for poles
because it tends to grow tall and straight and
requires less thinning at the base. Where
lodgepole was not available, other conifers
such as yellow pine, tamarack, and cedar were
used, but these were normally heavier or required
more trimming.

The tipi cover was made by piecing together
hides or lengths of canvas. Buffalo hides were
used until the second half of the nineteenth
century, when they were gradually replaced by
canvas. The hides were thinned, tanned, and
cut to the desired shapes. The entire cover is a
semicircle with a smoke flap on each side of
the center point. The radius of the semicircle
is close to the basal diameter of the finished
tipi. A traditional tipi with a diameter of fifteen
to sixteen feet required thirteen to sixteen
buffalo hides. A modern tipi with a diameter
of eighteen feet requires sixty-eight square
yards of canvas.

Some tipi covers were painted. The painting
was done before the tipi was erected. Designs
included geometric shapes, sacred animals
important to the designer, legends, and
battle scenes. Women usually made, erected,
dismantled, and maintained tipis, but men
painted the designs, and the overall design
was exclusive to the painter. The Kiowas of
the Southern Plains and the Blackfeet of the
Northern Plains were particularly renowned
for their painted tipis.

Plains Indians set up tipis by first lashing
three or four poles to form the frame. Most
Siouan-speaking groups used a three-pole
frame, whereas western Plains tribes such as
the Crows and Blackfeet favored the four-pole
frame. The remaining poles are placed on the
frame, and the cover is stretched over the
poles. The cover is laced together in the front
of the tipi from the ground to the smoke flaps,
leaving an opening for the doorway. The final
step is to secure the bottom of the cover to the
ground. Today, tipis are tied down with tent
pegs. In the past, stones or sod blocks often
secured the base of the cover. When the tipi
was removed, the rocks were rolled off the
cover and left as circular alignments, now
called tipi rings. These provide the main archaeological
evidence of early tipi use.

Tipis are not perfectly circular. The poles
on the back are usually slightly closer to the
center, creating a steeper surface. This produces
a slightly tilted cone, with the steeper
back side facing windward and a more gradual
slope on the leeward side with the doorway.
This arrangement improves stability in strong
winds. The difference between the long and
short axis is less than 10 percent, and the floor
plan is slightly egg shaped.

Tipis are, surprisingly perhaps, quite heavy.
The poles for an average tipi weigh around
400 pounds, and a hide cover adds another
100 to 150 pounds. When Plains Indians acquired
the horse, they could travel ten to fifteen
miles a day using the poles as a travois
and putting portions of the cover on each
travois. Before the horse, however, dogs were
the only pack animals, and it was a strenuous
job for a family to move 500 to 600 pounds of
tipi poles and cover, plus another 100 pounds
or more of bison robes, stored food, and personal
possessions five or six miles a day.

Tipis have probably been used since the
Middle Archaic period, about 4,000 years ago.
Most archaeological evidence dates to the period
2,500 to 500 years ago. Tipi use increased
steadily over time and was probably one of the
major factors that enabled more intensive and
specialized use of the open Plains. Virtually
all tribes in the Great Plains from Texas to
southern Canada used tipis. Eastern Plains
groups who lived in earth-lodge villages used
them seasonally when hunting; western Plains
hunting and gathering groups used them as
year-round dwellings.

Tipis were ideal, adaptable dwellings for
the seminomadic Plains Indians. They could
be taken down or erected in a few hours and
moved to anywhere the group chose to set up
camp. They could be adapted to accommodate
the number of occupants. In inclement
weather they could be modified to include
liners and insulation, and, with an internal
fire, they offered protection from strong
winds and frigid temperatures.

Today, tipis are important symbols of ethnic
and tribal identity. They symbolize adherence
to traditional ways, evoking lifestyles
that persisted for centuries but that have since
been effaced. Nevertheless, tipi designs, the
knowledge of how to erect tipis, and the right
to paint them remain a prized part of the rich
Plains Indian heritage.


Ken Deaver
Sherri Deaver
Billings, Montana




Ewers, J. C. The Blackfeet: Raiders on the Northwestern Plains. Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1958.
Frison, G. C. Prehistoric Hunters of the High Plains. New
York: Academic Press, 1978. Laubin, Reginald, and Gladys
Laubin. The Indian Tipi: Its History, Construction, and Use.
Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1977.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>