<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ea.019</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Immigration Boards</field>
      <field name="author">McDanal, Erin</field>
      <field name="text">

 




IMMIGRATION BOARDS

The peopling of the Great Plains in the United
States was significantly fueled by the promotional
activities of state and territorial immigration
boards. Following the Civil War many
U.S. citizens looked for a fresh start in the
sparsely populated Plains. Overpopulation
and a lack of land on which to build a livelihood
also influenced many Europeans to emigrate
and create a new life for themselves in
the opened tracts of the Great Plains. The
Homestead Act of 1862 provided another major
impetus by giving any U.S. citizen, or alien
who intended to become a citizen, 160 acres
of land.

Developed settlements encouraged law and
order, provided entrepreneurial opportunities
in agriculture and industry, and offered better
methods of reliable transportation for the new
transplants. The railroads promoted settlement
by providing land along their tracks and
by mounting vigorous advertising campaigns.
Attracting immigrants to the Plains was economically
important for land companies, as
well as for the already settled residents of the
territories and many newly organized states.
In the early 1870s, for example, the community
of Yankton paid local merchants who
were in New York on business to meet incoming
steamships and make a pitch to immigrants–
particularly German Russians, who
knew how to farm the prairie–to settle in
southeastern Dakota Territory. Many state or
territorial governments established boards or
bureaus of immigration to foster the settlement
of the Plains.

The immigration boards advertised primarily
in the United States and Europe through
newspapers and pamphlets and by setting up
exhibits at World Fairs and various conferences.
Colorado's immigration board was typical
of these government agencies. In 1872 the
Territory of Colorado established the Board of
Immigration to promote Colorado as an attractive
and desirable locality for those seeking
homes, to supply immigrants with full and
authoritative information, and to aid and facilitate
their journey to the territory. Similarly,
the Dakota Territory's legislature set up an Immigration
Bureau in January of 1871, headed by
a commissioner who published promotional
pamphlets and spent time in New York competing
with agents from Kansas and Nebraska
for potential Plains settlers. The size of the
bureau was increased to five in 1875, including
a German who was responsible for immigrants
disembarking from steamboats in New York
and from trains in Chicago, and a Norwegian
who was assigned to attract Scandinavians.
The bureau operated until 1877, by which
time immigration had its own momentum,
prompted by settlers' letters back to the Old
Country.

For most people, moving to the Great
Plains was difficult, not least because of the
environmental challenges. Information about
the climate and living conditions was particularly
helpful for many prospective settlers.
Immigration handbooks and publications
provided necessary facts, but they
sometimes exaggerated the qualities of the environment
and the settlements in order to attract
more people. These handbooks became
an important genre of literature throughout
the latter part of the nineteenth and early part
of the twentieth centuries. Although the immigration
boards were not above overrating
their advertised regions, most agencies published
credible and honest information so that
the newcomers would be successful in their
pursuits. A failed settlement, after all, could
not significantly contribute to the growth and
development of the region.


Erin McDanal
Colorado State Archives




Board of Immigration. Collection. Colorado State Archives,
Denver. Greenleaf, Barbara Kaye. America Fever: The Story of American Immigration. New York: Four
Winds Press, 1970. Schell, Herbert S. History of South Dakota.
Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1961.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>