<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.arc.017</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Dow, Wallace (1844-1911)</field>
      <field name="author">Bedeau, Michael</field>
      <field name="text">

 




DOW, WALLACE (1844-1911)

Born in Croydon, New Hampshire, on September
22, 1844, Wallace Leroy Dow learned
building skills by working in his father's Newport,
New Hampshire, contracting business.
In 1873 Dow formed his own contracting company
there and was involved in the construction
of several public buildings. He also
studied under his uncle Edward Dow, who
operated a successful architecture firm.

Wallace Dow moved to Pierre, Dakota Territory,
in October 1880. He relocated to
Yankton in the winter of 1880-81 and maintained
an architectural and contracting office
there until 1883. Dow's first major job was supervising
the construction of John M. Allen's
design for the original Main Building (now
the Conservatory of Music) at Yankton College.
Beginning in 1882 Dow served as architect
for the territorial penitentiary at Sioux
Falls. During his time in Yankton, Dow also
designed the first structure at the Territorial
Hospital for the Insane.

In 1883 Dow moved his offices to Sioux Falls
and dominated the architectural field in South
Dakota during the 1880s and 1890s. He was
well connected to the Republican territorial
and state governments, so there is hardly a
state institution dating from the late nineteenth
century that does not have at least one
Dow building.

Dow was a versatile designer, at home with
all the popular styles of his time. He utilized
local quartzite and jasper in many of his most
striking commissions. Quartzite was particularly
suited to the masonry Romanesque
style popularized by H. H. Richardson in the
1870s and 1880s. One of Dow's most important
commissions, the Minnehaha County
Courthouse in Sioux Falls (1889–92), is a tribute
to Richardsonian design rendered in massive
rough-finished quartzite blocks. Dow was
also an early advocate of concrete. His design
for the South Dakota Pavilion at the 1893 Columbian
Exposition was composed entirely in
precast concrete panels attached to a wooden
frame.

Dow retired in 1905, but he remained active.
He had patented a device for making
concrete blocks in 1904, and he spent his later
years promoting concrete building technology
as the owner of the Prefection Block Machine
Company. He died in Sioux Falls on July 5,
1911.


Michael Bedeau
Idaho State Historic Preservation Office





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>