<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pd.006</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Ameringer, Oscar (1870-1943)</field>
      <field name="author">Norwood, Stephen H.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




AMERINGER, OSCAR (1870-1943)

Oscar Ameringer, a principal leader of the socialist
movement on the Southern Plains, was
born in Achstetten, Germany, on August 4,
1870, the son of a cabinetmaker. Evading military
service, he emigrated to the United States
in 1886 and earned his living as a furniture
worker, salesman, painter, and musician. He
joined the Socialist Party shortly after it was
formed in 1901 and became editor of the Labor
World, financed by the Brewery Workers
Union. He reported on the general strike that
tied up the port of New Orleans in 1907. The
dockworkers' success there in forging a longterm
biracial alliance reinforced Ameringer's
commitment to both racial equality and industrial
unionism.

After the strike's collapse, Ameringer moved
to Oklahoma, where he quickly assumed a leading
role in the Socialist Party. Although lacking
a sizable industrial working class, Oklahoma
boasted the nation's largest Socialist Party, polling
close to a third of the statewide vote. On his
first speaking tour in 1907, traveling by covered
wagon and on horseback, Ameringer realized
that Oklahoma's farmers, primarily impoverished
tenants, constituted the party's major potential
base of support. Ameringer stayed in
dirt-floored tenant shacks and homes dug out
of hillsides and saw human suffering at its most
intense. The Oklahoma farmers' socialist commitment
deeply impressed him. He praised
their determination by recalling that the man
who presided at his first speech had arrived
soaked to the skin, having swum across a river
in his only suit because the bridge had been
washed out.

Ameringer was one of the most popular
speakers at the weeklong socialist encampments,
frequently held in Oklahoma from
1908 until the U.S. entry into World War I.
Farm people numbering in the thousands
traveled vast distances, often in covered wagons
bearing red flags, to hear Ameringer and
other socialist orators. In 1911 Ameringer
polled 23 percent of the vote in a three-way
race for mayor of Oklahoma City.

In 1910 Ameringer led the fight against Oklahoma's
adoption of the so-called grandfather
clause, which was introduced by the
Democrats to eliminate black suffrage. His
effort was opposed by a faction in the Oklahoma
Socialist Party based in the Little Dixie
section of the state, which resented Ameringer
as an outsider and feared losing white supporters.
In 1913 this faction assumed control of
the Socialist Party in Oklahoma, and Ameringer
moved to Milwaukee.

Although opposed to U.S. intervention in
World War I, Ameringer advised Oklahoma
farmers against launching the Green Corn Rebellion,
an abortive uprising intended to force
the government to end the war. The repression
it precipitated, along with a decline in
farm tenancy, caused the swift collapse of the
Oklahoma Socialist Party.

Returning to Oklahoma City after the war,
Ameringer published a radical newspaper, the
Oklahoma Leader, which, as the American
Guardian from 1931 to 1941, developed a national
circulation. Ameringer waged a high-profile
campaign in the Leader against the
Ku Klux Klan, which was highly influential in
Oklahoma during the early 1920s. From 1922
to 1931 Ameringer also published the Illinois
Miner in Oklahoma City, an insurgent newspaper
that challenged John L. Lewis's control
of the United Mine Workers. He contributed a
column under the pseudonym Adam Coaldigger.
In his preface to Ameringer's 1940 autobiography,
If You Don't Weaken, Carl Sandburg,
an old socialist comrade and friend,
compared him as a humorist to Mark Twain
and Will Rogers. Oscar Ameringer died in
Oklahoma City on November 5, 1943.


Stephen H. Norwood
University of Oklahoma




Ameringer, Oscar. If You Don't Weaken. Norman: University
of Oklahoma Press, 1983. Green, James R. Grass-Roots
Socialism: Radical Movements in the Southwest, 1895–1943.
Baton Rouge: Louisiana State University Press, 1978. Meredith,
Howard L. "A History of the Socialist Party in Oklahoma."
Ph.D. diss., University of Oklahoma, 1969.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>