<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.rel.024</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Hinduism</field>
      <field name="author">Stoddard, Robert H.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




HINDUISM

Hinduism is the Western name given to a religious
tradition developed over thousands of
years in India. Because it has no creed or major
institutional structure, it is intricately intertwined
with societal systems, and some
scholars declare that it is impossible to separate
Hinduism as a religion from other aspects
of Indian society. This means it is virtually
impossible to define precisely what constitutes
the Hindu religion, especially when transferred
into a different cultural setting such as
the Great Plains.

Lacking a set of rigid doctrines, Hinduism
encompasses a large diversity of religious beliefs
and practices. Nevertheless, devotion to a
particular deity expressed through worship
(puja) is important to most Hindus. The ritual
of worship usually occurs individually or
with other family members in the home and
at local shrines and temples. Traditionally,
large congregational meetings were rare, but
in recent years within North America, group
meetings for worship, spiritual messages, and
the celebration of religious festivals have become
common.

Both the diversity of beliefs and religious
practices by Hindus and the inevitable changes
that occur whenever a religion is transported
to another cultural setting contribute to a wide
diversity in the expression of Hinduism in the
Great Plains, especially because Asian Indians
who have migrated to North America, primarily
during the last half century, have not
formed large ethnic enclaves, which might
have encouraged centers of orthodoxy. Likewise,
the non-Asian citizens of Canada and the
United States who have adopted various beliefs
and rituals associated with Hinduism have followed
a variety of gurus, each emphasizing
different aspects of this equivocal religion.

The many societies, ashrams, and study
groups (more than 100 are identified in the
1996 edition of Encyclopedia of American Religions
for the United States) tend to be localized
and unrelated to one another. Followers may
meet informally in homes, community buildings,
and interfaith centers. Also, Hindus in
the Great Plains may seek individual spiritual
guidance from printed materials and from
Web sites on the Internet and by making a
special journey to an ashram in India or elsewhere
in North America.

Hinduism has not had a major impact on
the dominant society in the Great Plains: its
arrival in this region occurred generally during
only the last three decades of the twentieth
century; it tends to be nonproselytizing, with
private worship; and its adherents are few in
number and scattered. Nevertheless, more
than thirty temples and numerous other religious
structures contribute to the urban
landscapes of Calgary and Edmonton, Alberta;
Saskatoon and Regina, Saskatchewan;
Winnipeg, Manitoba; Denver, Boulder, Aurora,
Fort Collins, and Littleton, Colorado;
Shawnee, Kansas; Kansas City, Missouri;
Omaha, Nebraska; Oklahoma City and Tulsa,
Oklahoma; and Irving, Austin, and Dallas,
Texas. Less evident visually but functioning as
a part of community life in more than three
dozen cities are centers of Hindu-related societies
such as Ammachi, Art of Living, Chinmaya
Mission West, Integral Yoga, Sathya Sai
Baba, Science of Spirituality, and the Theosophical
Society, as well as the transcendental
meditation programs maintained by the Maharishi
Vedic Universities. In addition to participating
in special events occurring within
the Great Plains, many Hindus travel to
neighboring places to attend religious festivals
(such as Diwali and Holi), special pujas, pilgrimages,
and summer camps.


Robert H. Stoddard
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Gaustad, Edwin Scott, and Philip L. Barlow. The Historical
Atlas of Religion in America. New York: Oxford University
Press, 2000. Melton, J. Gordon. Encyclopedia of American
Religions. Detroit: Gale Research, 1996. Tweed, Thomas A.
"Asian Religions in America: Reflections on an Emerging
Subfield." In Religious Diversity and American Religious
History: Studies in Traditions and Cultures, edited by Walter
H. Conser Jr. and Sumner B. Twiss. Athens: University
of Georgia Press, 1997: 189–217.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>