<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.na.023</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Crowfoot (ca. 1830-1890)</field>
      <field name="author">Dempsey, Hugh A.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




CROWFOOT (ca. 1830-1890)
 
Photographic portrait of Crowfoot, Head Chief of the Blackfoot, circa 1885 (Alex Ross) (Provincial Archives of Alberta)


Crowfoot (Isapo-muksika, or "Crow Indian's
Big Foot") was head chief of the Blackfoot
(Siksika) tribe. A great orator and warrior,
Crowfoot contributed in a significant way to
the peaceful settlement of the Canadian West.

Crowfoot was born around 1830 on the
Belly River, near present-day Lethbridge, Alberta.
He first went to war at about the age of
thirteen and showed great bravery in striking
an enemy tipi with his whip and rescuing his
wounded brother. He was in nineteen engagements
with enemy tribes and was wounded six
times. His greatest feat of bravery occurred in
1866 when, in full view of his camp, he killed
a grizzly bear with a spear. Shortly thereafter
he became leader of the Big Pipes Band, and
by 1870 he was one of three head chiefs of
the tribe.

Crowfoot maintained good relations with
the Hudson's Bay Company, appreciating that,
unlike American traders, they did not flood
the land with alcohol. Crowfoot also befriended
the Catholic missionary Albert Lacombe
in 1865 and later rescued him when he
was in a camp that was attacked by a Cree war
party. Crowfoot allowed Lacombe to preach
to his people, though Crowfoot himself paid
little attention to Christianity.

In 1874, when the North-West Mounted Police
extended their control over western Canada,
Crowfoot established friendly relations
with its commander, James F. Macleod. In 1877
he willingly signed the Blackfoot treaty (Treaty
Number 7) with the Canadian government,
ceding much of southern Alberta. However,
after the Blackfoot were obliged to live, mired
in famine, on their reserve east of Calgary,
Crowfoot became disillusioned with the government.
Nevertheless, he continued to mediate
between his people and government officials. By the last decade of his life, most of his
children had died of tuberculosis and he was
almost constantly in mourning. Crowfoot died
on April 25, 1890, in a tipi in the Bow Valley. He
is now considered to be one of Canada's national
heroes.

See also LAW: Macleod, James.


Hugh A. Dempsey
Glenbow Museum




Dempsey, Hugh A. Crowfoot, Chief of the Blackfeet. Norman:
University of Oklahoma Press, 1972.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>