<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.art.046</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Peale, Titian Ramsay (1799-1885)</field>
      <field name="author">Nichols, Roger L.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




PEALE, TITIAN RAMSAY (1799-1885)

Titian Ramsay Peale, naturalist, scientific illustrator,
and explorer, meticulously depicted
the birds, insects, and plants of the Central
Plains with high-quality sketches and paintings
during the 1820s and 1830s.

Peale was born on November 2, 1799, in
Philadelphia, the son of Charles Willson Peale,
an artist who founded the Philadelphia (or
Peale's) Museum. From an early age he demonstrated
an unusual ability as a naturalist
and artist. Peale's first exploration came on an
1817 trip to eastern Florida and the Sea Islands
of Carolina. Then, in 1819, he was appointed as
the assistant naturalist for Maj. Stephen H.
Long's scientific expedition. Ordered to explore
the Central Plains and the major streams
that crossed it, the scientists began their journey
aboard the steamboat Western Engineer.
They halted for the winter of 1819–20 near
present-day Fort Calhoun, Nebraska. The next
summer Long led the group overland along
the Platte River to the Front Range of the
Rockies. For three months they observed,
mapped, sketched, and gathered plant and animal
specimens, returning along the Arkansas
and Canadian Rivers. Because of the scarcity
of water and trees on the Plains they traversed,
the explorers labeled the region the Great
American Desert.

Peale's ensuing reputation as a scientific illustrator
resulted from the 122 paintings and
drawings he made while on the expedition. His
work included colored plates of birds drawn
for Alexander Wilson's American Ornithology
(1824-33) and of insects for Thomas Say's
multivolume American Entomology (1824-28).
For the next several decades he remained one
of the top scientific illustrators of the flora and
fauna of the Central Plains while serving as the
curator of Peale's Museum and also designing
coins for the U.S. Mint. He joined Charles
Wilkes's 1838-42 scientific expedition to the
Pacific, but conflicts with Wilkes prevented a
definitive publication of his drawings from the
voyage. Peale then worked for the U.S. Patent
Office until his retirement in 1873. He died on
March 13, 1885, in Philadelphia.

See also WAR: Long, Stephen H..



Roger L. Nichols
University of Arizona




Poesch, Jessie. Titian Ramsay Peale, 1799–1885 and His Journals of the Wilkes Expedition. Philadelphia: American
Philosophical Society, 1961. Porter, Charlotte M. The Eagle's Nest: Natural History and American Ideas, 1812– 1842. Tuscaloosa: University of Alabama Press, 1986.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>