<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.ind.032</field>
      <field name="titleMain">International Trade</field>
      <field name="author">MacPhee, Craig R.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




INTERNATIONAL TRADE


Commodity Exports of the Great Plains States and Provinces in 1996

State/ProvinceTotal exports U.S. dollars (millions)Exports per capita U.S. dollars (millions)Major products

Texas53,6622,805machinery, oil
Colorado10,7492,812machinery
Kansas5,3122,065agriculture
Oklahoma2,752834machinery
Nebraska2,5731,557processed food
New Mexico935546agriculture
North Dakota632981agriculture
South Dakota422577machinery
Montana358407metals
Wyoming130270chemicals, machinery
U.S. total77,525
Alberta22,6347,950oil, gas
Saskatchewan9,1979,290grain, oil
Manitoba4,5714,031vehicles, grain
Canadian total36,402
Total113,927


The international trade of the Great Plains is
dominated by Texas, which exports more, by
value, of almost every important Plains product
than any other state or province in the
region. One significant balance in the North is
the large amount of Alberta's exports of oil
and natural gas. In total, Texas exports almost
as much, by value, as all the other Great Plains
states and provinces combined.

Texas probably imports more than the other
states as well, but there are no estimates of
imports by state. This data void is unfortunate,
because imports contribute to the standard of
living by providing a greater variety of goods at
lower costs than we would be able to produce
ourselves, and it would be interesting to observe
the differences in import patterns across
the Plains. These commodity export data also
ignore trade in services such as finance, transport,
consulting, and tourism. Finally, it should
be noted that the data are assembled by state
and therefore reflect substantial exports originating
outside of the Plains areas of several
states. Primary metals and wood products
from Alberta and Montana come mainly from
their mountain regions, and much of Texas's
oil and chemical exports originates in the Gulf
Coast region. On a per capita basis, trade appears
to be most important to Saskatchewan,
Alberta, and Manitoba, in that order. Colorado
and Texas are the only Plains states above
the U.S. national average of $2,308 worth of
exports per person.

Most of the international trade is between
the United States and Canada, which are each
other's largest international trade partners.
The European Union and Japan are the next
largest foreign trade partners for both the
United States and Canada. These trade patterns
have been maintained in the aftermath
of the 1989 free-trade agreement between the
United States and Canada and after the 1994
implementation of the North American Free
Trade Agreement, which included Mexico as
well. However, trade with Mexico and the developing
countries of Asia and Africa has been
growing rapidly, especially in the categories of
food and other agricultural products. For example,
the largest export market for Kansas
hard winter wheat in 2003 was Nigeria.

Despite the significance of international
trade for the Great Plains, it pales in significance
next to intranational trade. Oil, grain,
and livestock products are major exports from
the Plains to the East and West Coasts of the
United States and Canada, while the Plains
imports primarily manufactured products
from the more populated areas of the two
countries.

The composition of Plains exports partially
reflects the resource endowment of this region.
Raw and processed agricultural products are
major exports from Saskatchewan, North Dakota,
Nebraska, Manitoba, and Kansas, metals
from Alberta and Montana, and petroleumrelated
products from Alberta, Saskatchewan,
Oklahoma, and Texas. Major metropolitan
areas in Colorado, Manitoba, New Mexico,
Oklahoma, and Texas, however, have taken advantage
of economies of scale and technology
to make machinery and equipment their major
exports.


Craig R. MacPhee
University of Nebraska-Lincoln




Hayward, David J., and Rodney E. Erickson. "The North
American Trade of U.S. States: A Comparative Analysis of
Industrial Shipments, 1983–91." International Regional Science Review 18 (1995): 1–31. Massachusetts Institute for
Social and Economic Research. National Trade Data Bank, Exports, State of Origin, Series II. Amherst: University of
Massachusetts Press, 1998.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>