<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.lt.028</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Immigrant Literature</field>
      <field name="author">Blair, Linda Norberg</field>
      <field name="text">

 




IMMIGRANT LITERATURE

Immigrant literature takes various forms and
is usually written by immigrants and secondand/
or third-generation Americans. Often
autobiographical in nature, these narratives
reflect the experience of immigration and acculturation
and the associated uneasiness of
these processes. The anxiety that immigrant
literature exposes is a combination of determination,
success, loneliness, and abandonment.
Repressed desires of attachment to the
homeland juxtaposed with the uncertainties
surrounding assimilation assert themselves as
underlying conflicts. Added to these struggles
are issues of self-identity that stem from the
intricacies of cultural adaptation.

Tension in immigrant literature centers on
association with the new land, identification
of the self and other, and language acquisition.
First, the land itself offers a powerful blend of
freedom and fear. Whether the landscape is
the wilderness that Cotton Mather writes
about in Magnalia Christi Americana (1702) or
the flat expanse of the Great Plains that Per
Hansa finds exhilarating and Beret, his wife,
renders intolerable in O. E. Rölvaag's Giants in the Earth (1927), the New World offers an
abundance of possibilities even as it diminishes
emotional security. Immigrant writings
illustrate ambivalence surrounding the land:
the untouched wilderness offers both freedom
from past constraints and fear of independence
associated with pleasures derived from
the land.

Immigrant literature also explores the idea
of self and other. The writings seek to affirm
the new immigrant self while simultaneously
using the other to restructure the immigrant's
new identity. Fundamentally, the notion of
self and other becomes manifest as the narrators
and characters reflect the ambiguities of
the immigrant experience. When people emigrate,
they strive to give up that which they
were in order to become the other, that which
they desire to be. The former self remains part
of the immigrant's psychological structure. In
Giants in the Earth, Per Hansa and Beret represent
self and other. While Per Hansa sublimates
his Old World self by conquering physical
obstacles, Beret's transformation to her
New World self emerges only after a descent
into extreme loneliness. The juxtaposition of
these characters reflects the heroic illusion
and difficult reality of immigrant life.

A third characteristic of immigrant literature,
intertwined with aspects of self and
other, is the acquisition of a new language. In
many immigrant narratives, acquiring English
becomes a traumatic experience. The writings
often point out the fact that children become
more fluent in English than their parents. The
first language of the immigrant is that of the
home, containing implications and idioms
that make the native language familiar and
comfortable. English initially resides outside
of the immigrant and belongs to the other.
Eventually, the immigrant adopts English to
conduct the business of social interactions,
education, and commerce. English, however,
intrudes on the comfort of the home, creating
an abyss that widens with time as the immigrant
embraces the new cultural modes of
behavior.

As immigrants and settlers moved to the
interior regions of America, they brought
with them their native languages, cultures,
dreams of success, and fears of the unknown.
In their writings, relationships of characters
and narrators to the physical land, the development
of self and other, and the acquisition
of language appear as central themes not
only in literature written by immigrants and
their children who made the trek but also in
works by authors who may be generations removed
from the actual experience but whose
collective past embodies acculturation. The
symphony of voices echoing the immigrant
experience form a multiethnic framework for
the literature of the Great Plains.

See also EUROPEAN AMERICANS: Giants in the Earth.


Linda Norberg Blair
Springfield, Virginia




Gunn, Giles. The Interpretation of Otherness: Literature, Religion, and the American Imagination. New York: Oxford
University Press, 1979. Kolodny, Annette. The Lay of the Land: Metaphor as Experience and History in American Life and Letters. Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina
Press, 1975.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>