<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pd.032</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Lease, Mary Elizabeth (1853-1933)</field>
      <field name="author">Edwards, Rebecca</field>
      <field name="text">

 




LEASE, MARY ELIZABETH (1853-1933)

In the heyday of the Populist Party, 1890–96,
Mary Lease was one of the most prominent
women in America, celebrated as the "Kansas
Joan of Arc." She was born on September 11,
1853, in Ridgway, Pennsylvania, the daughter of
Irish immigrants. Her father died as a Union
prisoner of war, a calamity that plunged the
family into poverty. In 1870 his widow sent
twenty-year-old Mary to teach at Osage Mission,
Kansas, where she married local pharmacist
Charles Lease in 1873. The couple lost
everything in the Panic of 1873 and moved to
Denison, Texas. While her husband shifted
from job to job, Lease took in washing and
bore six children, two of whom died in infancy.
She also joined the temperance movement and
discovered her talent as an orator.

In the 1880s the family moved to Wichita,
where Lease became a Knights of Labor organizer
and women's suffrage advocate, as well
as one of the first women to pass the Kansas
bar. When the Populist Party formed in 1890,
it seemed poised to address a broad range of
Lease's concerns, and she plunged into the
campaign. Her speeches were famously fiery,
though she did not–as myth has it–urge
farmers to "raise less corn and more hell."

Lease's agenda did not match those of many
other Populist leaders. Denouncing those who
cooperated with Democrats, she also offended
anti-imperialists with her 1895 book, The
Problem of Civilization Solved, advocating U.S.
colonization of Latin America. In 1896 Lease
declared herself a socialist but stumped reluctantly
for William Jennings Bryan. After Bryan's
defeat, Lease divorced her husband and
moved with her children to New York, where
she worked as a lawyer and lecturer until her
death on October 30, 1933.

Though Lease repudiated the Populists, she
left an enduring legacy from her years in the
Plains. According to reports from an 1890
convention, it was she who gave the People's
Party its name. She inspired novelist Hamlin
Garland to fictionalize her in A Spoil of Office
(1893). The first woman to be appointed a
state superintendent of charities (by a Populist
governor in Kansas), she blended with passion
the advocacy of women's rights, overseas expansion,
and domestic economic reform.

See also POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT: Populists (People's Party).


Rebecca Edwards
Vassar College




Blumberg, Dorothy Rose. "Mary Elizabeth Lease, Populist
Orator: A Profile." Kansas History 1 (1978): 3-15. Clanton,
O. Gene. "Intolerant Populist? The Disaffection of Mary
Elizabeth Lease." Kansas Historical Quarterly 34 (1968):
189-200.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>