<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.afam.026</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Little, Cleavon (1939–1992)</field>
      <field name="author">Sylvester, Melvin R.</field>
      <field name="text">

 




LITTLE, CLEAVON (1939-1992)


Cleavon Little


Cleavon Jake Little, stage, screen, and television
actor, was born in Chickasha, Oklahoma,
on June 1, 1939. His father was a native
Mississippian and his mother was a Texan.
Both parents were of African and Native
American ancestry. Cleavon attended grade
school in Chickasha, but the family moved to
the Linda Vista section of San Diego, California,
in 1953. There, Cleavon went to Kearny
High School from 1954 to 1957 and was active
in several school drama productions. From
1957 to 1960 he took classes at San Diego City
College and from 1962 to 1965 he attended San
Diego State University, where he earned a
bachelor of arts degree in speech therapy with
a minor in dramatic arts. His first job was as a
speech therapist at a developmental disabilities
center, but he dreamed of becoming a
professional actor.

His opportunity came when he entered
a nationwide competitive talent search for
promising actors sponsored by ABC Television.
Cleavon was one of sixteen selected out of
25,000 applicants to receive a full scholarship
to the Academy of Dramatic Arts in New York
City. While still at the academy he displayed
his talents in Shakespeare's A Midsummer
Night's Dream and Othello. He received the
academy's highest honors, the Charles Jehlinger
Award, when he graduated in 1967.
Off Broadway he appeared in Americana Off Broadway (1966), MacBird (1967), and Scuba Duba (1967). Cleavon went on to act on
Broadway in Jimmy Shine with Dustin Hoffman
(1968), Someone's Comin' Hungry (1969),
and Ofay Watcher (1969). In 1970 he won a
Tony Award for best actor in a musical (for
Purlie). Cleavon considered his best works to
be I'm Not Rappaport (1985) and his one-man
show All God's Dangers (1989). His 1991 appearance
as a guest star in Judd Hirsch's TV
series "Dear John" won him an Emmy.

Altogether, Cleavon Little appeared in seventeen
movies from 1970 to 1991, but he is
remembered most for his hilarious role as
mild-mannered Sheriff Bart in Blazing Saddles
(1974). This quintessential actor of theater,
film, and television died of cancer in Sherman
Oaks, California, on October 22, 1992. The
American Academy of Dramatic Arts set up
an endowed scholarship in his name in 1994.



Melvin R. Sylvester
Long Island University
C. W. Post Campus




Cleavon Little, Archival Student File, American Academy
of Dramatic Arts, New York City.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>