<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.fil.009</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Butler, Hugo (1914-1968)</field>
      <field name="author">Allan, Blaine</field>
      <field name="text">

 




BUTLER, HUGO (1914-1968)

Photographs of some of Hugo Butler's film scripts written under pseudonyms after Butler was blacklisted
       

Hugo Butler wrote motion picture stories and
scripts for three decades. Born in Calgary, Alberta,
on May 4, 1914, he soon abandoned the
Canadian Prairies. His British parents divorced
after World War I, and his father,
Frank Butler, who worked for the Canadian
Pacific Railway, relocated to Hollywood and a
career as an actor and writer, while young
Hugo moved with his mother to Victoria,
British Columbia.

After studying journalism at the University
of Washington, Butler left without a degree for
a junior writer's job at MGM. Credited with
eleven movies there, he specialized in adapting
children's classics. He soon joined the fledgling
Screen Writers Guild, while his father opted
for the rival, industry-endorsed Screen Playwrights
Inc. Hugo Butler's cowritten story, Edison, the Man (1940), earned an Academy
Award nomination. Four years later, as a guild
vice president, he presented the writers Oscars,
one to his father. His postwar credits include
scripts directed by Jean Renoir and
Joseph Losey, among them Losey's The Prowler
(1950), which Butler cowrote with Dalton
Trumbo, though he received sole credit, fronting
for the blacklisted Trumbo.

Butler and his wife, Jean Rouverol Butler,
were active Communist party members, and
they were identified to the House Committee
on Un-American Activities in 1947. They fled
a 1951 huac subpoena with their children,
choosing exile in Mexico over Butler's native
Canada, because Butler disliked Canada's cold
climate. Butler continued to write pseudonymously
for Luis Buñuel and Robert Aldrich,
contributed to scripts without credit, and
codirected two documentaries as Hugo Mozo
(Hugo the Houseboy). In Italy in the 1960s he
wrote again for Aldrich and the also-exiled
Losey. Returning to Hollywood in 1964 and
about to rise from the blacklist with Aldrich's
The Legend of Lylah Clare (1968), cowritten
with his wife, Butler died in Los Angeles on
January 7, 1968, of a coronary occlusion after
several years' struggle with arteriosclerotic
brain disease.

In 1997 his rightful credits were restored to
five films cowritten during the blacklist. Butler's
films include The Adventures of Huckleberry Finn (1938), A Christmas Carol (1938),
Lassie Come Home (1942), The Southerner
(1945), The Big Night (1951), The Adventures of Robinson Crusoe (1953), World for Ransom
(1954), Torero! (1956), Los pequeños gigantes/
How Tall Is a Giant? (1958), La joven/The Young One (1960), Eva (1962), and Sodom and Gomorrah (1963).


Blaine Allan
Queen's University




Conrad, Randall. "No Blacks or Whites: The Making of
Luis Buñuel's The Young One." Cineaste 20 (1994): 28–34.
McGilligan, Patrick, and Paul Buhle. Tender Comrades: A Backstory of the Hollywood Blacklist. New York: St. Martin's,
1997. Rouverol, Jean. Refugees from Hollywood: A Journal of the Blacklist Years. Albuquerque: University of
New Mexico Press, 2000.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>