<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.edu.001</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Education</field>
      <field name="author">Underwood, Kathleen</field>
      <field name="text">

 




EDUCATION

Education has always been part of human life
in the Great Plains, a means of passing on
necessary skills, values, and history. While today
we tend to think of education in formal
terms that include institutions and administrative
structures, Native peoples had wellestablished
means of transferring knowledge
between generations long before Europeans
arrived. For pioneers, education in the form of
schooling was fundamental to the "civilization"
they carried with them. Schools were
among the first institutions established, and as
society matured, so did the levels of education.
Within a decade of initial settlement and often
much earlier, states and provinces in the Great
Plains had institutions of higher education.
Throughout the region today, an energetic system
of education exists. Virtually all children
attend elementary schools, most graduate
from high school, and many have attained
at least some postsecondary schooling.

This level of education has not been easily
secured. The story of education in the Great
Plains has been one of reform and resistance
over the past two centuries.

The earliest European and American educators
in the Plains were missionaries who
were motivated to bring Christianity to Native
peoples through education. Later reformers
determined that schooling would not only
be the best way to separate Indians from
their traditional cultures, thereby assimilating
them, but it would also instruct African
Americans and immigrants about their place
in society. Reformers also sought ways to
improve education: they legislated compulsory
education and longer school terms and
pushed for vocational training, adult education,
and, in rural areas, agricultural education
and eventually school consolidation. In
an attempt to improve the quality of education,
reformers also promoted formal teacher
training. Many reforms met resistance from
the outset as parents challenged the implementation
of schooling as well as attempts
to alter it. Sometimes, they simply refused
to participate; at other times, they used the
courts to contest school practices.


Schooling Indians


Indian parents waiting for children who will be going home for summer vacation, Birtle Residential School, Manitoba, 1904


The first attempts at formalizing education in
the Great Plains involved the long tradition of
ministry to Native peoples. Much of the story
of "educating the Indians" centered on replacing
long-standing customs with indoctrination.
Missionaries accompanied the fur trade
in Canada's earliest years, and the tie there
between religion and Indian education was
strong until the 1970s. Similarly, in the United
States missionaries were present at the earliest
stages of exploration and settlement. When
the United States forcibly removed Native
Americans from the eastern woodlands to the
Southern and Central Great Plains, missionaries
followed them. By the 1830s missionaries
were present in many parts of the region. In
both countries the federal government relied
on various religious organizations to help administer
Indian policy, particularly education.

Strategies for Indian education have followed
a common pattern throughout the
Great Plains: initial contact with Native peoples
and attempts to bring them to Christianity
and European-derived values; day schools on
reservations; boarding schools that took children
from their families, first on the reservation
and then off; integrating Indian children
into public schools; and, most recently, admitting
tribal influence back into education.

By the mid.nineteenth century, provisions
for education had become commonplace
in treaties negotiated between Indians
and whites. Tribal peoples sought skills to help
them deal with a rapidly changing world, and,
for different motives, politicians, missionaries,
and humanitarians believed education
would ease that transition. At first, missionaries
established day schools near villages
where children could attend and still reside at
home. Day schools were strongly preferred by
parents, so much so that when negotiations
were under way in a series of treaties between
Canadian and First Nations leaders in the
years following Confederation, local education
was a consistent demand. Such schools
were also cheap to administer, and missionaries
and government officials hoped that
the children would take their newfound ideas
back to their families and thus accelerate assimilation
for everyone. These hopes were not
fulfilled; far from assimilating their parents,
children often held tenaciously to traditional
values. Neither bureaucrats nor missionaries
ever understood that Indian parents wanted
whatever advantages education might bring
but steadfastly rejected the underlying principles
of assimilation that went hand in hand
with schools.

By the 1870s boarding schools had become a
cornerstone of Indian education in both Canada
and the United States. At first, educators
built boarding schools near the reserves or
reservations. When close proximity to tribal
and family influences proved too strong, perpetuating
old ways, missionaries and government
officials decided that total separation
was necessary. The thinking was that only by
disconnecting children physically as well as
culturally from their families would they learn
the educational and economic skills necessary
for assimilation into society. Although the tactics
they used proved execrable, educators'
primary concern was how to prepare Indian
children for the world they would face as
adults, a world that could not rely on the buffalo
hunt.

The first and probably best known off-
reservation boarding school in the United
States was Carlisle Indian Industrial School,
located in rural Pennsylvania, far from the
homes of Great Plains children who were sent
there. Carlisle opened in 1879, and over the
next two decades an additional twenty-five
off-reservation boarding schools, all located
in the West, were established. Almost a third
were in the Great Plains: Chilocco, Indian Territory
(1884); Genoa, Nebraska (1884); Lawrence,
Kansas (1884); and Pierre (1891), Flandreau
(1893), Chamberlain (1898), and Rapid
City (1898), South Dakota. In 1883 the Canadian
Parliament approved funding for three
off-reservation schools dedicated to industrial
education, all in what was then the Northwest
Territory: Battleford and Lebret, Saskatchewan,
and Dunbow, Alberta. Other industrial
schools were subsequently established at Elkhorn,
Manitoba (1888), and at Red Deer
(1893) and Regina (1895), Saskatchewan. These
schools initially provided agricultural skills to
boys; later, girls also attended and were taught
mainly domestic skills.

The children found much to dislike about
attending boarding schools. Often their hair
(their specific identity) was cut, and they were
obliged to wear uniforms. They were also
forced to abandon their Native languages.
They were lonely and found life at the residential
schools harsh. Not only was the labor
physically hard, but it was also designed to
train them in tasks and gender roles that paralleled
white society and contradicted their
own. Punishments for even minor infractions
were severe. Scores of children ran away, and
many died, particularly from contagious diseases,
which spread rapidly in the crowded
conditions.

Indian parents were ambivalent about
boarding schools. Over time, many had come
to believe that their children needed to learn
nontraditional skills to survive in their changing
world. Tribal leaders sometimes actively
sought schooling with great hopes that it
would help preserve tribal autonomy. At the
same time, they detested teaching methods
that relied on punishment and coercion, and
they missed their children during the long absences.
Many resisted sending their children to
school even though their refusal led to punishments
such as having their annuities withheld.

By the late 1890s, however, there was growing
concern about residential schools. Humanitarians
and policy makers, both outside
and inside the government in Canada and in
the United States, voiced opinions that policies
aimed at educating Native peoples were dismal
failures, particularly at boarding schools. Although
it would take several years before they
were closed, the period between 1900 and
1920 marked a shift in policy away from off-
reservation schools.

The first four decades of the twentieth century
were turbulent times for Indian education.
Growing criticism since the turn of
the century, combined with constant financial
woes, brought a major reorganization of Indian
schooling in Canada in 1910. Industrial
education lost its privileged status and after
that date received no extra funding. In the
United States more and more Indian children
attended public schools, for which school districts
received per capita payments. Criticism
also led to the closing of the Carlisle Indian
Industrial School in 1918. Continuing financial
problems during World War I, the 1920s,
and the Great Depression resulted in greatly
reduced funding for Indian education. Nevertheless,
the proportion of Indian children
in school increased during this period. Taken
together, Canadian day and boarding schools
were, by 1910, providing education to about
half (54.4 percent) of the 20,000 school-age
Indian children, although in the northern districts
attendance was erratic because many
Natives there continued to follow a huntingand-
gathering lifestyle. In the United States in
1913 about 75 percent of the 65,000 school-age
Indian children attended. By 1927 Canadian
enrollment proportions equaled those of the
United States. Nonetheless, the goal of that
education, assimilation, was not achieved.

A number of reports, both private and
government-sponsored, concluded that even
after several years at school, few Native Americans
had achieved the necessary skills to succeed
in the larger society. At the same time,
throughout the Great Plains, additional criticisms
were leveled at federal policies regarding
education. One criticism pointed to the unhealthy
conditions at the schools, which resulted
in much illness and death. Dr. P. H.
Bryce, a medical examiner for Canadian Indian
Affairs, concluded a study in 1904 of the
devastating health conditions in residential
schools. None of his recommendations were
implemented.

A second and new criticism was directed at
the central objective of the education programs:
destruction of Indian culture. In the
United States this criticism culminated in the
report entitled The Problem of Indian Administration
(known as the Meriam Report after
its chief investigator, Dr. Lewis Meriam), published
in 1928, which provided, among other
topics, a detailed description of life for Native
American children in boarding schools. The
Meriam Report also influenced the appointment
of John Collier as commissioner of Indian
Affairs in 1933, a post he held for the next
dozen years. Under his direction, federal Indian
policy radically changed, particularly in
education. He instituted instruction in Native
American languages and required teachers to
develop curricula about Indian culture. He
also closed boarding schools in favor of day
schools.

Between World War II and the emergence
of Native American and First Nations activism
in the 1960s, both countries tried to find ways
to reshape policy regarding education. In the
United States a new policy, aptly named "termination,"
sought to end federal responsibility
and jurisdiction over many tribal nations.
Families were encouraged to leave reservations
and relocate in cities, where, theoretically,
they would become part of mainstream
society. The results were disastrous. Unwelcome
in urban schools, Native Americans
came to be the most poorly educated people
in the United States by the 1950s.

In Canada too First Nations children academically
lagged behind their contemporaries
in public schools. The Canadian government,
in cooperation with provincial education authorities,
radically changed its policy. Indian
students would attend provincial elementary
and high schools. Mainstreaming the
students would take them away from the
poorly staffed, inadequately equipped, heavily
church-oriented day schools and thereby
speed up assimilation. In many ways, the attempt
to mainstream these children was quite
similar to the rejected boarding schools. They
faced long bus rides or, once again, living away
from their families. This shift in policy proved
no more successful than had previous plans in
terms of academic achievement or assimilation.
Indian students enrolled in large numbers,
but few completed high school, and even
fewer matriculated.

The social activism of the 1960s led Indians
in both Canada and the United States to demand
control of their own education programs.
In specific legislation passed in the
United States in the 1960s and 1970s, especially
the Bilingual Education Act of 1968,
the Indian Self-Determination and Education
Assistance Act of 1975, and the Education
Amendments Act of 1972, Indian parents
gained control over the money spent for
schools and for the first time in many generations
could help determine the education of
their children. At the same time, education in
Canada became more Indian centered. The
Department of Indian Affairs and Northern
Development adopted a policy on education
that shifted much responsibility to local communities
and demanded new curricula, instruction
in Native languages, and a focus on
Native culture.

The same activism that led First Nations
peoples to demand control over elementary
and secondary education made them seek access
to and representation in higher education,
both in Canada and the United States.
Programs in "Native studies" or "Native
American studies" were developed in colleges
throughout the Great Plains in the 1970s. Not
content with representation in the curriculum,
Native Americans also successfully demanded
that programs be developed for them
as well as about them. At the University of
Regina, for example, the Indian Cultural College
receives federal funding. In the United
States, federal legislation such as Title III of
the Elementary and Secondary Education Act
of 1965, the Indian Education Act of 1972, and
the Indian Self-Determination and Education
Assistance Act of 1975 support institutions
for Native students. Thus by the 1980s education
for Indian children throughout the Great
Plains was more clearly grounded in tribal society
than at any time since 1850.



The Development of Public Schools

With European, American, and Canadian settlement
of the Great Plains came school systems
that replicated seasoned educational
models in the East. In copying existing modes
of education, Great Plains settlers maintained
a link to the places they had left. They also
shared the belief that schools would moderate
the instability associated with migration to
the frontier. Schooling was to provide children
with an understanding of reading, writing,
and arithmetic as well as a patriotic sense
of their country's history. Students were also
expected to grasp the virtues of the work ethic
and Christian values as a route to success.
While settlers in both countries borrowed
heavily from existing school practice, there
were also differences. In the United States central
issues included the philosophy of education
and who had access to schooling; in Canada
a major concern was the role religion and
language played in public education.

By the 1860s, when pioneers began to settle
the Great Plains, the United States had established
a school system that drew funding from
property taxes to provide free education to
all children through eight grades. That model
would eventually extend through high school.
Even access to higher education was relatively
inexpensive in the Great Plains. In the belief
that an educated public was necessary to uphold
democracy, public lands were set aside to
support education. Pioneers were quick to set
up schools, and western legislatures just as
quickly established the framework to guide
and fund the schools. In most U.S. territories,
public schooling of some sort was available
within the first year of settlement. The territory
of Nebraska, for example, was opened to
settlement in 1854, and the territorial legislature
approved a school system the following
year. Many school systems, however, existed
only on paper because land sales and tax funds
often could not support a school. In such
cases, private schools, both religious and secular,
or subscription schools (schools organized
by individual communities) often met
the needs of students.

Over the long term, as territories became
more densely populated, formal public education
spread. Then, with statehood, legislatures
once again mimicked eastern structures, establishing
departments of public instruction
and creating hierarchies to direct education.
At the top was the state superintendent of
public instruction, followed by county superintendents
who were responsible for administering
several local schools, which in turn
had boards of education. Even with formal
structures in place, public education frequently
was sketchy, especially for rural children,
who seldom had a school close by. Even
in 1918 many rural schools on the Northern
Great Plains had no wells or indoor plumbing.
Such schools were generally one-room shacks,
sometimes with a basement that served as
poor accommodation for a lonely teacher.

Manitoba had established schools in 1819
along the Red River settlement, and the
Church of England and the Hudson's Bay
Company established the first school in Saskatchewan
in 1840. However, the commitment
to public education was not initially as deeply
entrenched in the Prairie Provinces as in the
United States. Until the 1840s, when Egerton
Ryerson, superintendent of education for
Canada West, initiated a reform of education
in the new province of Ontario, schooling
in the Canadian colony copied the British
model, which provided schooling based primarily
on social class. Ryerson borrowed ideas
from European and American educators to
design a centralized system of education that
used property taxes to provide free schooling.
His innovations were not enthusiastically received,
but he steadfastly worked to bring various
schools under control. Beginning in 1841
with the Common School Act, Ryerson tried
to initiate a uniform school system based on
the sale of public lands with local or municipal
councils serving as boards of education.
Subsequent school acts in 1846 and 1850 were
aimed at school administration and how to
fund education so that all children could attend.
Ryerson's structure was embodied in
the British North America Act in 1867 and was
in place as the territories in the West were
first settled and later sought admission to the
Dominion.

Language and religion also distinguish the
schools set up in Canada from those in the
United States. In the Canadian West both
Catholics (mainly French speaking) and Protestants
(mainly English speaking) have had an
active voice in staffing classrooms and determining
curriculum; in the United States, by
contrast, such decisions had long rested in
civil hands. Recognizing the importance of
private religious schools that were already in
place, the Manitoba Act ensured that minority
rights were retained. The implementation of
this system was left to the new legislatures, and
it took different forms in each of the Prairie
Provinces. In 1871 the Manitoba legislature
created a provincial board of education to direct
schools and oversee funding. At the local
level, various denominations managed their
respective schools, and appointed officials
oversaw the public schools. This dual school
system also existed in the Northwest Territory,
which in 1905 was split into Saskatchewan and
Alberta. These two provinces also inherited
already-functioning school systems and, like
Manitoba, created centralized departments of
education, with a minister at the top and locally
elected boards of trustees in the various
communities that were responsible for operating
the schools. Over time, however, language
became a more important issue than
religion as new immigrants from central Europe
added to the population mix. In Saskatchewan
a provincewide dual system persisted,
with each system receiving tax support,
while Alberta adopted a system based on central
administration that permits local options
for separate schools.

Educators' strong beliefs in the power of
schooling to transform cultural norms and to
bring about social change is evident in a series
of reforms in the late nineteenth and early
twentieth centuries. None of these reforms
was initiated in the Great Plains; rather, educators
there were influenced by the larger
forces for change in that period.

Forming a national identity and inculcating
in future citizens the responsibilities that accompany
that citizenship have long formed a
cornerstone of educational reform. Such beliefs
underlay the origins of public schools in
the United States, and patriotic themes had
been central in the curriculum there since the
1840s. Concerns about patriotism and about
national identity were heightened by the massive
immigration from eastern and southern
Europe after 1900. Canadians also utilized
schools to encourage nationalism, but until
after World War I, that nation was part
of the British Empire. Only in the 1920s did
educators develop a curriculum that focused
more closely on Canadian history, replacing
stories of English patriotism with Canadian
examples.

In addition to designing a curriculum that
encouraged nationalism, school reformers
were determined that students would be in
school and for longer periods of time. School
superintendents at all levels throughout the
Great Plains successfully pushed for laws
that required attendance and lengthened the
school year. By 1920 all states and provinces in
the Great Plains had compulsory education
laws, but even then, in many cases, that law
required attendance for only three months
each year. In towns, where the population was
larger and children had fewer work responsibilities,
school terms were much longer, often
eight or nine months.

Concerned about the quality of education
in rural areas, where attendance was erratic
and staffing a constant concern, reformers began
to push for consolidation based on the
argument that the districts could not afford
to maintain distant schools with comparable
curriculum. Annual reports written by
state superintendents of public instruction
throughout the Great Plains sung the praises
of school consolidation. Such praise fell on
the deaf ears of parents and their elected legislators,
who ignored or rejected this reform
well into the twentieth century. World War II,
however, hastened the consolidation of rural
schools and the standardization of the length
of the school term for all students–roughly
nine months long.

High school education also came quickly to
the towns and cities of the Great Plains, encouraged
by the influx of new settlers in the
early twentieth century and by changes in the
role of the high school in education. In the
mid-nineteenth century high schools were
viewed as a course of study only for those students
who were college bound, but over time
they came to be seen as the logical completion
of public schooling instead of simply a prep
school for college. As a result, the curriculum
changed radically. Rather than courses solely
in the liberal arts and sciences, high schools
began to offer classes in vocational and business
education. Students could graduate ready
to enter the workforce. Some historians have
argued that this development was closely tied
to the needs of industry and that immigrant
children in particular were tracked away from
college and into vocational, technical, or commercial
education. Whether these charges are
valid for the Great Plains is difficult to discern.

What is clear is that students and their parents
valued a high school education. Since the
1940s the demand for high schools to provide
rural students the same multipurpose education
that their contemporaries in towns and
cities receive has led to regional high schools
that enroll students from several rural districts.
By the end of World War II most young
people in the Great Plains received at least
some secondary education. This, of course,
often involved long-distance transportation to
schools, frequently as far as fifty miles each
way every day in sparsely populated areas such
as the Nebraska Sandhills or eastern Montana.
Many rural children boarded in towns in order
to complete the program. This was still the
case in 1981 in Jordan, the county seat of Garfield
County, eastern Montana, where a dormitory
was attached to the only high school
serving this vast space.

Teacher preparation was a central aim of
the first high schools, especially in the stages
of rapid immigration in the late nineteenth
and early twentieth centuries. School administrators
throughout the region lamented
the shortage of trained teachers. High schools
seemed to provide an obvious solution. There,
as they completed their own public schooling,
young people, primarily young women,
could also pick up pedagogical skills to enter
elementary classrooms. Hundreds of young
women in the Great Plains taught during a
summer term in a rural school and worked
on their own diplomas during the regular
term. Many high schools also provided specific
courses in teacher training, particularly
in Canada, where normal schools as separate
institutions were less common than in the
United States.

In addition to teacher training, many high
schools provided instruction in other vocations.
Schools that emphasized business or
commercial education prepared graduates for
various aspects of office work; others focused
on technical skills to train students for industrial
work. In 1910, for example, Winnipeg had
a composite high school that offered commercial
and technical programs in addition to academic
courses. The Technical Education Act
of 1919 gave federal money to provinces that
provided such training.

As important as teacher training, agricultural
education was also offered in high
schools throughout the region. The Agricultural
Instruction Act of 1913 provided federal
funding to Canadian provinces to encourage
high schools that taught agricultural science
and farm mechanics. In 1917 the United States
followed suit with the Smith-Hughes Act.



Colleges and Universities

Just as Plains settlers were quick to establish
public schools, they also wanted institutions
of higher education. Most states provided for
state universities in their constitutions; some
even planned such institutions during the territorial
period. Dreams about higher education
were fostered by federal support. Recognizing
the importance of higher education,
the federal government set aside two townships
(sections 16 and 36) as an endowment
for a university when a state was admitted to
the Union. As with public education, the state
could use whatever funds the land generated
to support higher education. In some states,
like Wyoming, the land set aside was rich in
minerals and has provided substantial funds
to the state university. Most other states were
not so fortunate. The Morrill Act of 1862 provided
additional lands (30,000 acres for each
representative and senator for each state)
to support higher education, specifically in
agriculture and mechanical arts. The timing
of this legislation was fortuitous for the
Great Plains, and states such as Kansas, Colorado,
Texas, and Oklahoma developed strong
"A&amp;M" programs. In the Dakotas, Montana,
and Wyoming, these two provisions were supplemented
by the Land Act of 1881, which held
back land from sale during the territorial days
so that states would have access to it after
statehood. As a result, all Great Plains states
were able to develop public systems of higher
education.

Like elementary education, funding for
higher education was seldom su.cient, and
for many years these universities existed only
on paper. Nevertheless, as population increased
and parents and students came to demand
higher education, the necessary public
structures were put in place. In addition to
these public institutions, dozens of privately
endowed colleges and universities dot the
American Great Plains. North Dakota, for example,
has ten accredited institutions of higher
education: one is private, three are church supported,
and the remainder are state schools. Of
the twenty-three accredited schools in Kansas,
two thirds (sixteen) are religious.

One group that benefited from early planning
for higher education in the United States
was women. Because the legislation establishing
land-grant institutions did not prohibit
women's matriculation, when these schools
did open, women took advantage of the opportunity
and enrolled in large numbers. In
the first years more women than men attended.
While these legal provisions were not
unique to the Great Plains, women there were
among the first to profit from the broadened
access to education.

Ideological differences about who should
obtain a college education also influenced
higher education in Canada, where matriculation
has been more difficult. Nevertheless,
all three Prairie Provinces established universities
shortly after admission to the Dominion
and have received federal funding. Moreover,
agricultural education at the university level,
while primarily a responsibility of the province
rather than the federal government, has
been a central component of postsecondary
schooling. Agricultural education in Manitoba,
for example, is centered at the Manitoba
Agricultural College, established in 1906 and
since 1924 a part of the University of Manitoba.
In Saskatchewan and Alberta agricultural
studies have been part of the provincial
universities from the beginning. Like American
land-grant universities, the University
of Saskatchewan was located where land was
readily available for farming, animal science,
and experimental agriculture and today retains
its reputation as an "ag school." As part
of the Agricultural Schools Act, Alberta also
opened agricultural schools at Vermilion and
Olds in 1913.

Proportionally fewer students attended the
Prairie Province universities than those on the
American Plains until the 1950s, when increasing
urbanization, industrialization, and
expanded communication demanded a more
highly trained workforce. These economic demands,
combined with a shift in consciousness
that more students should have the opportunity
for higher education, resulted in the
creation of more colleges and universities in
the Prairie Provinces.



Vocational Education

Despite the courses historically offered to high
school students to prepare them for the workforce,
many were unable to find jobs. Some
students dropped out before completing the
high school program, but others who did earn
their diplomas found that a gap existed between
the training they received and the skills
required on the job. To meet the needs of both
workers and employers, vocational and technical
training has been available since the late
nineteenth century in Canada and the United
States. Initially, this training was a responsibility
of the provinces or states. As early as 1911
Saskatchewan passed legislation authorizing a
course in manual training. About a decade
later, the federal government also became involved.
The Technical Education Act (1919)
provided shared funding for provinces that
established technical schools.

Responsive to the need for an adequately
trained workforce, federal governments in
Canada and the United States have continued
to provide funds to build schools that are
strictly vocational, especially during World
War II and the postwar years. Canada's Vocational
Training Co-ordination Act of 1942
provided a strong impetus to the provinces to
establish facilities for postsecondary vocational
training. The act offered federal funds
to help such programs, and the Prairie Provinces
quickly took advantage of it and set up
vocational schools in several communities, especially
to meet the needs of returning veterans.
In 1948, for example, the Manitoba Technical
Institute opened at Winnipeg. Other
federally funded schools were established in
Brandon and The Pas. Continued enrollment,
coupled with demands for a broader curriculum,
had by the late 1960s modified the original
mission of these schools from strictly vocational
training to include some liberal arts
courses. Saskatchewan also took advantage
of the Vocational Training Co-ordination Act
and set up vocational training at Moose Jaw,
Prince Albert, Saskatoon, and Regina. Following
Manitoba's pattern, the school at Prince
Albert added liberal arts courses and evolved
into a community college.



Agricultural Extension and Education

In keeping with the spirit of agricultural education,
reformers sought the means to transfer
academic research to the men and women on
farms. Funded by both federal and state or
provincial governments, these programs provide
a variety of services, including personal
contacts as well as demonstrations and lectures.
Specialists were trained to address issues
of importance to rural families, including diverse
topics such as pesticides and hybrid corn
as well as sanitary measures for food preservation
and better-laying chickens. The Hatch
Act of 1887 funded agricultural experiment
stations that would demonstrate new techniques
and crops in the United States. Since
then, government support for agricultural education
has generally increased. A formal division
of the Department of Agriculture, the
Cooperative Extension System, was created in
1914 (the Smith-Lever Act). The same legislation
transferred federal money to the states to
organize agricultural clubs for girls and boys,
which, in the 1920s, became known as 4-h
Clubs. Agricultural clubs for Canadian youth
started at the same time and in the early 1930s
organized nationally as the Canadian Council
on Boys' and Girls' Clubs.



Teacher Training and Professionalism

Reformers have always looked to teachers as
the main purveyors of educational norms, and
for more than a century they have been concerned
about how to provide an adequately
prepared teaching force. State and provincial
legislatures began to demand that teachers receive
some sort of formal instruction and
pass tests aimed at ensuring a qualified teaching force. In the United States teachers were
trained in departments of education at state
universities. More important in sta.ng classrooms,
however, were the normal schools established
throughout the Great Plains in the
last decades of the nineteenth century. Massive
immigration from border states and provinces
and from Europe mandated more teachers, especially
for the elementary grades. The first
was Kansas State Normal School, which initially
enrolled students in 1865, followed by
Nebraska State Normal School at Peru in 1867.
Other states in the region did not establish
schools for another twenty years. One of these,
Colorado State Normal School at Greeley,
which opened in 1891, became known for its
innovative methods and stood out in the first
quarter of the twentieth century as one of
the leading teachers colleges in the nation. In
western Canada, teacher training was often offered
as part of the high school curriculum,
but there too separate schools prepared teachers
to meet increasing standards. Saskatchewan
created normal schools when it became a
province in 1905.

At the same time that school reformers
tried to improve the teaching force, teachers
formed professional organizations to further
their own interests. They too were interested
in curricular change and compulsory education.
The Alberta Teachers' Association was
particularly active in politics in the 1920s and
1930s. A number of the association's members
were elected to positions of power, and
they were able to change both the structure
of and curriculum in public schools. Perhaps
more important, they were able to make clear
that the association represented the teachers.
Teachers associations were never as politically
strong in the United States, but, like their
counterparts in Canada, they fought for tenure,
retirement, hospitalization, and fair pay.



Resistance

Not everyone agreed with the developments
in education. There have been resistance and
challenge from the earliest days, and they continue
to the present. A central issue is minority
school rights.

The first resistance came from Native peoples
who rightly saw the imposed education
systems as direct attacks on their ways of life.
Immigrants also resisted the forces of assimilation.
While settlers willingly migrated into
the Great Plains, many insisted on retaining
their own cultures, especially their language
and religion. Because of the religious pluralism
in the United States, religion was rarely
the crucial issue for immigrants. Moreover,
until recently it has always been clear that English
would be the sole language. The main
exception is Spanish, which in the Texas, New
Mexico, and Colorado Plains is in widespread
use. Attempts to preserve bilingualism, which
emerged in the 1960s and 1970s, have been
hampered by contemporary nativism, which
calls for "English only."

In contrast, issues of religion and language
in the Prairie Provinces have been contested
since settlement. The best-known conflict is
the "Manitoba schools question." Reflecting
the ethnic mix of the population as well as
tradition, the federal legislation that separated
Manitoba from the other western territories
protected the educational rights of Protestants
and Roman Catholics when schools were first
established but did not make provisions about
language. Respective boards of education administered
each set of schools and received
tax support, but in 1889 the more populous
Anglo-Protestant residents determined to
abolish tax support of Roman Catholic and
French-language schools. French Catholics
naturally objected that their constitutional
rights were being abridged. After years of litigation,
a compromise in 1897 resolved that
Catholic teachers would be hired if there were
sufficient students to teach. Moreover, if ten
or more students in a school spoke another
language, instruction might be in that language.
Because of the massive immigration to
Manitoba between 1890 and 1910, this compromise
led to linguistic disarray. By then instruction
was being held not only in English
and French but also in German, Ukrainian,
Polish, Icelandic, and Scandinavian languages.
Several factors encouraged the provincial government
in 1916 to repeal the bilingual section
of the school law.

Minority school rights in the United States
have been most successfully won through the
courts. Access to equal education has been a
central issue for African Americans since Reconstruction.
Jim Crow legislation by 1900
had firmly established the concept of "separate
but equal" education in Great Plains
states and elsewhere. In Oklahoma segregated
schools were written into the first state constitution
in 1907. Since the 1930s civil rights organizations,
particularly the National Association
for the Advancement of Colored People
(NAACP), have filed lawsuits under the equal
protection clause of the Fourteenth Amendment.
Many of these cases had their origins in
the Great Plains. The first focused on access
to postgraduate programs where none existed
or where those that did could not offer equal
facilities like libraries. In Sweatt v. Painter
(1950), the Supreme Court ruled that African
Americans must be admitted to the University
of Texas law school; in McLaurin v. Oklahoma
State Regents (1950) the Court determined
that African Americans must be admitted to
graduate school. The most far-reaching of the
naacp cases was Brown v. The Board of Education
of Topeka (1954), which overturned the
separate but equal concept and concluded that
race could not be used to determine which
schools students would attend. Equal access
has not translated into equal education, however,
especially in regard to funding. In many
Plains states where a proportion of the financing
for public education rests on property
taxes, great disparities exist between rich
and poor districts.

Contemporary concerns about minority
rights focus on the curriculum, both in content
(especially evolution versus creation) and
pedagogy (whole language versus phonics and
spelling skills). Neither issue is new. Concerns
about content reach back decades, as do arguments
about how students should learn. What
is new is the increasing number of families
who homeschool their children.



Conclusion

To a large extent, the school systems that
emerged in the Great Plains mirrored those in
eastern Canada and the United States. But to
conclude that education in the Great Plains
simply replicated earlier models ignores the
unique and sometimes controversial issues
that shaped education there. One contentious
issue involved schooling for the Aboriginal
population. The large Indigenous population,
there either by long custom or by removal,
could not be ignored. The Great Plains provided
a crucible for working through conflicting
ideologies about the role and scope
of education for Native Americans and First
Peoples. Today, after many failures, that education
rests once more in the hands of the
various tribes.

Other issues that have played out in the
Great Plains focus on the rights of minorities
to education. In Canada that issue has centered
on language and religion; in the United States,
on the access of African Americans first to
graduate training and later to public schools.
Finally, the access of American women to
higher education at state-supported institutions,
which took place first in the Great Plains,
distinguishes the region. Many recent pressures
have also been important in shaping education:
more ardent demands by minorities for
civil rights and, especially on the American
Plains, the increasing role of the courts in education.
Today education and schools continue
to confront the same issues of two centuries
ago: what is the purpose of education, and who
controls it?

See also AGRICULTURE: 
Agricultural Extension Service / GENDER: 
Hooker, Evelyn / 
HISPANIC AMERICANS: Escuela Tlatelolco / LAW: Brown v. The Board of Education of Topeka;
Meyer v. Nebraska; North Dakota Anti-Garb Law / NATIVE AMERICANS: Assimilation Policy.




Kathleen Underwood
University of Texas at Arlington




Adams, David Wallace. Education for Extinction: American
Indians and the Boarding School Experience, 1875–1928.
Lawrence: University Press of Kansas, 1995. Axelrod, Paul.
The Promise of Schooling: Education in Canada, 1800–1914.
Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 1997. Barman, Jean,
Yvonne Herbert, and Don McCaskill, eds. Before Canada:
Toward an Ethnohistory of Indian Education. Vancouver:
University of British Columbia Press, 1986. Bruno-Jofre,
Rosa del C. Issues in the History of Education in Manitoba:
From the Construction of the Common Schools to the Politics
of Voices. Lewiston NY: Mellon, 1993. Burchart, Ronald
E. "Education and Culture in the Trans-Mississippi
West: An Interpretation." Journal of American Culture 3
(1980): 351–73. Campbell, John Martin. The Prairie Schoolhouse.
Albuquerque: University of New Mexico Press,
1996. Friesen, Gerald. The Canadian Prairies: A History.
Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 1984. Gaskell, Jane
S., and Arlene Tigar McLaren, eds. Women and Education:
A Canadian Perspective. Calgary: Detselig Enterprises,
1987. Gulliford, Andrew. America's Country Schools. Washington
DC: Preservation Press, 1984. Jones, David C.,
Nancy M. Sheeban, and Robert M. Stamp, eds. Shaping
the Schools of the Canadian West. Calgary: Detselig Enterprises, 1979. Miller, J. R. Shingwauk's Vision: A History of
Native Residential Schools. Toronto: University of Toronto
Press, 1996. Sheehan, Nancy M., J. David Wilson, and
David C. Jones, eds. Schools in the West: Essays in Canadian
Educational History. Calgary: Detselig Enterprises,
1986. Titley, E. Brian, and Peter J. Miller, eds. Education in
Canada: An Interpretation. Calgary: Detselig Enterprises,
1982. West, Elliott. Growing up with the Country: Childhood
on the Far Western Frontier. Albuquerque: University
of New Mexico Press, 1989.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>