<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">egp.pe.022</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Dust Bowl</field>
      <field name="author">Hurt, R. Douglas</field>
      <field name="text">

 




DUST BOWL


Dust cloud rolling over western Kansas town, February 21, 1935


The Dust Bowl was an area of drought and
severe wind erosion in southwestern Kansas,
southeastern Colorado, northeastern New
Mexico, and the panhandles of Oklahoma and
Texas during the 1930s. This area extended approximately
400 miles from north to south
and 300 miles from east to west, although the
boundary was never precise because of fluctuations
in annual precipitation.

The area was first given the name "Dust
Bowl" by Robert E. Geiger, a reporter for the
Washington DC Evening Star, who used the
term in an article following a severe dust
storm, known as a black blizzard, on April 14,
1935. Soon, the Soil Conservation Service and
the public were using the phrase Dust Bowl to
identify the area of the Southern Great Plains
that experienced the worst drought, wind erosion,
and dust storms.

Although drought and dust storms are natural
phenomena in the Great Plains, it was the
rapid expansion of wheat production following
World War I that destroyed soil-holding
native grasses and created the Dust Bowl. After
drought ruined the wheat crop during the
autumn of 1931, the prevailing winds began to
lift the soil and plague the region with dust
storms by late January 1932.

As the drought and dust storms worsened
during the mid-1930s, the federal government
responded to the economic and technical
needs of the drought-stricken farmers in the
Dust Bowl with a host of programs. The Agricultural
Adjustment Administration provided
funds to farmers who agreed to limit wheat
and cotton production, while the Commodity
Credit Corporation offered price supporting
loans on these crops. The Soil Conservation
Service demonstrated terracing, strip cropping,
and grass seeding techniques that prevented
wind erosion and provided financial
assistance that enabled farmers to apply these
techniques. The Resettlement Administration
and the Farm Security Administration furnished
loans to the most destitute farmers who
could not receive credit from other lending
institutions to sustain their families and
agricultural operations. The Farm Security
Administration also purchased wind-eroded
lands from farmers and returned those areas
to grasslands. Originally known as landutilization
projects, they are now identified as
national grasslands.

In 1935 the Resettlement Administration
filmed the documentary The Plow That Broke
the Plains, hoping to gain public and congressional
support for its program to resettle
people from the worst of the eroded lands. In
1937 Life magazine published several paintings
by Alexandre Hogue that depicted conditions
in the Dust Bowl. Residents of the Dust Bowl
criticized these works because they seemed to
place the blame for the dust storms on the
farmers and their new laborsaving technology,
such as tractors and combines, rather than on
drought. In 1940, Congress ordered the film
withdrawn from circulation.

In 1938 wind erosion began to diminish with
the return of near-normal precipitation to
many areas of the Dust Bowl. By 1940 the
drought on the Southern Great Plains had
ended. The federal programs that had helped
farmers remain on the land, practice soil conservation,
and endure the economic crisis of
the Great Depression were not without their
critics. Given the problems of drought, dust,
and economic depression, however, these programs
provided essential assistance at a time
when abnormal climatic conditions and poor
farming practices created unprecedented wind
erosion and earned the Southern Great Plains
its reputation as the Dust Bowl.

See also AGRICULTURE: Agricultural Adjustment Administration; Farm Security Administration/ ART: Dust Bowl Photographers;
Hogue, Alexandre / FILM: The Grapes of Wrath;
The Plow That Broke the Plains / MUSIC: Guthrie, Woody.


R. Douglas Hurt
Iowa State University




Hurt, R. Douglas. The Dust Bowl: An Agricultural and Social
History. Chicago: Nelson-Hall, 1981. Riney-Kehrberg,
Pamela. Rooted in Dust: Surviving Drought and Depression
in Southwestern Kansas. Lawrence: University Press of
Kansas, 1994. Worster, Donald. Dust Bowl: The Southern
Plains in the 1930s. New York: Oxford University Press,
1979.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>