<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ag.058">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Sheep</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Rodney W. Kott</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ag.058</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Kott, Rodney W.">Rodney W. Kott</author>. <title level="a">"Sheep."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">50</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-12-18</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">SHEEP</head>

<p>More than 20 percent of the sheep in the
United States are located in Great Plains states,
mainly in the drier western reaches. Six of the
top ten states in sheep production are in the
Plains: Texas (1), Wyoming (2), Montana (5),
South Dakota (6), Colorado (7), and New
Mexico (8). Colorado is also ranked first in
commercial sheep slaughter.</p>

<p>Sheep production in the Great Plains states
is extremely diverse. It varies from large extensive
range sheep operations in West Texas,
western South Dakota, eastern Montana, Wyoming,
and New Mexico to more intensively
managed flocks in the farming areas of North
and South Dakota, Nebraska, Kansas, and
Oklahoma. As a general rule, the productivity
of pasture or forage crops dictates the maximum
levels of productivity that a sheep producer
can achieve and thus the type of operation
best suited to the area. Production goals
for sheep units in the Plains vary from commercial
sheep operations to purebred or registered
seed stock operations to operations catering
to 4-<hi rend="smallcaps">H</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">FFA</hi> market sheep projects.</p>

<p>In areas of low rainfall, such as West Texas,
limited feed resources restrict production potential.
Since in these areas expected outputs
are low, production systems are extensive and
resource inputs are minimized. Sheep numbers
are large in order to offset the low level of
outputs per animal unit. Although in these
operations lamb production still accounts for
the majority of the income (usually 70 to 80
percent), wool provides a more significant
contribution to the total income of the enterprise
than in the systems to the east.</p>

<p>In the farming areas of the Great Plains
states, forage production capability of the land
is not limited and thus sheep production systems
involve intensely managed operations
with much greater levels of output: production
goals may approach up to 200 pounds of
lamb per ewe per year. This usually involves a
smaller total number of ewes per operation
than on the western Plains. In many instances,
these operations involve a greater reliance on
harvested feed. And they tend not to be complete
economic units but are used to support
other farm income. The sheep will often use
land, labor, and feed resources which otherwise
may go unused on many farming and
ranching operations.</p>

<p>Because of the proximity of the major
slaughter plants in the United States (particularly
in eastern Colorado and western
Iowa) and the vast feed resources, lamb feeding
is an important industry in the Great
Plains states and provinces. Feeding centers
are located in Colorado, Wyoming, South Dakota,
and Alberta. In addition, there is an active
farmer-feeding industry in the farming
areas of the Great Plains states. In some instances,
it is beneficial for farmers to use a
livestock fattening enterprise as a method to
market their grain.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Rodney W. Kott<lb/>
Montana State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>