<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->


<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.arc.027">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Greene, Herb (b. 1929)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Arn Henderson</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.arc.027</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Henderson, Arn">Arn Henderson</author>. <title level="a">"Greene, Herb (b. 1929)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">83-84</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-13</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">GREENE, HERB (b. 1929)</head>

<p>Herb Greene is an architect, painter, and author
who developed a highly original interpretation
of organic design. Born in Oneonta,
New York, on September 13, 1929, Greene
studied with the architect Bruce Goff at the
University of Oklahoma and practiced architecture
in Texas, Oklahoma, and Kentucky. He
returned to the University of Oklahoma to
teach in 1957 and was later a professor of architecture
at the University of Kentucky until
1982. Two Oklahoma houses built in the late
1950s&#8211;the Joyce House in Snyder and the
Greene House in rural Norman&#8211;reflect the
synthesis of aesthetic and philosophic ideals of
his mature work.</p>

<p>The Joyce House, built on a bluff strewn
with large granite boulders and with distant
views of flat grasslands, represents a synthesis
of both site characteristics and the clients' desire
to include their collection of antique furniture
in the design. The unrestricted views of
the surrounding landscape dictated walls of
wood and glass placed upon a pedestal of
granite to accommodate the unusual collection
of furniture. Moreover, the design strategy
suggested a high degree of contrast with
multidirectional meanings. The anchoring
pedestal of granite contrasts with the floating
roof above. The upper walls of wood, modulated
to accommodate stained-glass windows,
are terminated with a winglike mansard protecting
the glass walls on the lower floor. The
scaly and articulated form of the asymmetrical exterior, with its animalistic, hornlike roof
drain, is further contrasted with the smooth,
white, crystalline wall forms of the symmetrical
interior. At the very center of the octagonal
plan is a fountain and pool of water, placid
and in contrast to the arid landscape beyond.</p>

<p>The Greene House, built as a family home,
is a more complex design than the Joyce
House. The two-story, wood-frame house
atop a prairie knoll extended Greene's interest
in creating an architecture composed of diverse
and ambiguous metaphors. The inclusion
of diverse elements is, theoretically, an attempt
to express meaning through an organic
process of cognition. Central to this concept,
which Greene derived from Alfred North
Whitehead, is the notion that any object is not
a static entity but has multiple aspects that are
apparent by various cues that can be measured
against our own emotional and intellectual
experiences.</p>

<p>In the Greene House, forms that are both
barnlike and creaturelike are organized into a
synthesis of images. The elliptical shape is a
form that presents the least surface to Oklahoma
storms approaching from the southwest.
The color and texture of the house echo
the farm buildings of the region. The animal
metaphor is also an apparent attempt to make
reference to both the living and the passage of
time. The weathered boards and shingles on
the exterior sustain the metaphors of both
creature and barn and relate to the forms of
ravines and windblown grass of the landscape.
The design reflects deliberate suggestions of
opposites. Even the sheet-metal canopy, with
its insectlike legs, suggests contradictions. As
the canopy climbs upward to hover over the
roof, it is transformed into a machined element
like a rocket about to launch.</p>

<p>Both the Joyce House and the Greene
House are complex and mysterious images.
Philosophically, the images suggest associations
with regional history, ecology, the passage
of time, and pathos. Certainly, they are
profound statements of the traditional elements
of architecture (form, space, texture,
and color), but the arrangement and juxtaposition
of images encourage contemplation.
Greene constructed an ensemble of startling
metaphors and thereby invites speculation
into meaning by drawing upon the past experiences
of the beholder.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Arn Henderson<lb/>
University of Oklahoma<lb/>
</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Farmer, John. <title level="m">Green Shift: Toward a Green Sensibility in Architecture</title>. Oxford: Butterworth-Heinemann, 1996.</bibl>
<bibl>Greene, Herb. <title level="m">Mind and Image: An Essay on Art and Architecture</title>.
Lexington: University Press of Kentucky, 1976.</bibl>
<bibl>Greene, Herb, and Nanine Hilliard Greene. <title level="m">Building to Last: Architecture as Ongoing Art</title>. New York: Hastings
House, 1981.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>