<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fil.038">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main"><hi rend="italic">The Last Picture Show</hi></title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>David J. Wishart</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fil.038</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</author>. <title level="a">"The Last Picture Show."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">271</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-12</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main"><hi rend="italic">THE LAST PICTURE SHOW</hi></head>
<figure n="egp.fil.038" rend="granted" type="noclick">
<figDesc>The Last Picture Show DVD Special Edition Cover</figDesc>
</figure>         

<p>In the opening scene of <title>The Last Picture Show</title>
(1971), directed by Peter Bogdanovich, it appears
as if gunshots are echoing through the
empty dirt streets of Anarene, Texas. But it
is only the backfiring of Sonny Crawford's
(Timothy Bottoms) truck, and the viewer is
forewarned that though this may look like a
frontier town, right down to the tumbleweeds,
it no longer has the energy to give rise to a
gunfight. The stores are boarded up, the highway
sign to Routes 25 and 79 points to the
way out, and the Royal, the town's theater,
is showing its final movie, Howard Hawks's
<title>Red River</title>.</p>

<p>The year is 1951, and Sonny and his best
friend, Duane (Jeff Bridges), have just lost
their last football game, and, like other teenagers
in Anarene, they have no idea what to
do with their lives. The adults offer no model:
there is Ruth Popper (Cloris Leachman), the
aging and lonely wife of the boorish coach
who finds respite from despair in the arms of
Sonny; there is Lois Farrow (Ellen Burstyn),
rich and bored and worried that her daughter&#8211;
the self-centered and manipulative Jacy
(Cybill Shepherd)&#8211;is following in her footsteps;
there are nameless old men who aimlessly
gather at the pool hall, its air heavy with
dust and tedium; and everywhere there are
open secrets and unmentioned infidelities.
Only the dignified Sam the Lion (Ben Johnson),
a former cowboy and now the theater
owner, is a reminder of a more vibrant past.
But Sam dies, the movie house closes, Duane
heads off to Korea, and Sonny is left with no
prospects in this atrophied place.</p>

<p>Director Peter Bogdanovich audaciously
(by 1970 nearly all feature films were in color)
shot the film in black and white on location in
Archer City, which, like the fictional Anarene,
lies just to the southwest of Wichita Falls. Bogdanovich
and Larry McMurtry wrote the
Academy Award–winning screenplay, which
was adapted from McMurtry's 1966 novel of
the same name. (The screenplay is a less bitter
though no less desolate view of McMurtry's
hometown of Archer City.) The music of
Hank Williams, Hank Snow, and Bob Wills
and the Texas Playboys, among others, confirms
the time and place. With its unhappy
marriages and failed lives, the movie could
easily have degenerated into a soap opera, but
Bogdanovich's skilled, unobtrusive direction
and the superb cast of actors&#8211;both Ben Johnson
and Cloris Leachman won Oscars and
Ellen Burstyn won a New York Film Critics
Award for their supporting roles&#8211;ensure the
authenticity of this sad, elegiac portrayal of
the dying days of a Great Plains town.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">CITIES AND TOWNS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ct.049">Small Towns</ref> / 
<hi rend="smallcaps">LITERARY TRADITIONS</hi>: <ref n="egp.lt.044">McMurtry, Larry</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>David J. Wishart<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Dawson, Jan. "Review of The Last Picture Show." <title level="j">Sight and Sound</title> 47 (1972): 107–8.</bibl> <bibl>Lorenz, Janet E. "The Last Picture
Show." In <title level="j">International Dictionary of Films and Filmmakers</title>,
edited by Nicholas Thomas. Chicago: St. James
Press, 1990: 1: 497–99.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>