<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fil.041">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Lloyd, Harold (1893-1971)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Keith Semmel</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fil.041</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Semmel, Keith">Keith Semmel</author>. <title level="a">"Lloyd, Harold (1893-1971)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">272</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-12</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">LLOYD, HAROLD (1893-1971)</head>
<figure n="egp.fil.041" rend="granted" type="noclick">
<figDesc>Harold Lloyd in An Eastern Westerner (1920)</figDesc>
</figure>    

<p>Harold Lloyd has been called the third genius
of silent film comedy. The films of Charles
Chaplin and Buster Keaton may be better
known to modern audiences, but Lloyd's films
are equally as innovative and entertaining as
those of his famous contemporaries. While
Chaplin was the master of pathos, and Keaton
deftly battled the machinery of the modern
age, Lloyd's Great Plains sensibility allowed
him to mine the humor found in day-to-day
experiences. His Everyman character paid
tribute to the resiliency of the American spirit
and the wisdom of everyday people.</p>

<p>Harold Clayton Lloyd was born on April
20, 1893, in Burchard, Nebraska. His father,
James "Foxy" Lloyd, was frequently unemployed,
requiring the Lloyds to move constantly.
Harold acquired his mother Elizabeth's
love for dramatics, and when he was
twelve years old he performed with a traveling
stock company directed by John Lane Connor.
In 1910 the Lloyds divorced. Harold and his
father moved to San Diego, where Harold
once again studied drama with Connor, his
mentor. Lloyd's film debut came in 1912, when
he landed a small part as a Yaqui Indian in the
Edison Company's production of <title>The Old Monk's Tale</title>. In 1913 Harold moved to Los Angeles,
where he performed in several Keystone
comedies. He was also hired as an extra at
Universal, becoming friends with another aspiring
filmmaker, Hal Roach.</p>

<p>When Roach opened his own studio in
1914, he hired Lloyd to play a character named
Willie Work in a series of comedy shorts.
Willie Work was quickly replaced by Lonesome
Luke, a Chaplinesque character who
wore tight-fitting clothes and sported a twopiece
mustache. In 1916 and 1917 Lloyd and
Roach produced more than a hundred of the
Luke action comedies, but Lloyd was never
completely satisfied with the character. In 1917
he devised a new character who wore normalfitting
clothes and the black horn-rimmed
glasses that soon became Lloyd's comic trademark.
A series of short comedies starring
Lloyd's new character, often referred to simply
as Harold, or "the Boy," soon made the comic
star the highest paid actor in Hollywood. In
1921 Roach and Lloyd produced their first feature
film, <title>A Sailor-Made Man</title>, and Lloyd began
outdrawing both Chaplin and Keaton at
the box office.</p>

<p>In 1923 Lloyd married Mildred Davis, his
leading lady in several films, including the
masterpiece <title>Safety Last</title>, filmed that same year.
Also in 1923 Lloyd and Roach parted company
on friendly terms following their final collaboration,
<title>Why Worry?</title> Lloyd began producing
his own films for Path&#233; and later for Paramount.
One of Lloyd's biggest commercial
hits, <title>The Freshman</title>, was released in 1925. In
1929 Lloyd made the transition into sound
films with <title>Welcome Danger</title>, but his style of
gentle, optimistic comedy was poorly received
by Depression audiences. Lloyd made his final
film, <title>Mad Wednesday</title>, in 1947.</p>

<p>In 1952 Lloyd received a special Academy
Award inscribed to a "master comedian and
good citizen." In 1962 Lloyd produced a compilation
of his work entitled <title>Harold Lloyd's World of Comedy</title>, which he presented at the
Cannes Film Festival to a rave response. During
the 1960s Lloyd traveled to colleges and
film festivals, introducing his work to new audiences.
Harold Lloyd died of cancer on March
8, 1971. He left behind over 200 films, more
than Chaplin and Keaton combined, documenting
his extraordinary contributions to
American film comedy.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Keith Semmel<lb/>
Cumberland College</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Brownlow, Kevin, and David Gill, producers. <title level="m">Harold Lloyd: The Third Genius</title>. Thames Television Production,
1989.</bibl> <bibl>Katz, Ephraim, ed. <title level="m">The Film Encyclopedia</title>. New York:
Harper Collins, 1994: 833–34.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>