<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fil.065">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main"><hi rend="italic">The Wizard of Oz</hi></title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Nancy Tystad Koupal</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fil.065</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Koupal, Nancy Tystad">Nancy Tystad Koupal</author>. <title level="a">"<hi rend="italic">The Wizard of Oz</hi>."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">280-281</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-12</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main"><hi rend="italic">THE WIZARD OF OZ</hi></head>
<figure n="egp.fil.065" rend="granted" type="noclick">
<figDesc>Screenshot from The Wizard of Oz (1939) </figDesc>
</figure>    

<p>Rated sixth on the American Film Institute's
list of the country's 100 greatest movies, <title>The Wizard of Oz</title> has become a defining feature of
American culture. From its sepia-toned opening
shots of Kansas to its Technicolor fantasy
world of Oz, the 1939 Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer
production permeates the American imagination
with lines such as "Toto, I've a feeling
we're not in Kansas anymore" and songs such
as "We're Off to See the Wizard." The Cowardly
Lion (Bert Lahr), the Scarecrow (Ray
Bolger), the Tin Man (Jack Haley), and Dorothy
Gale (Judy Garland) sang and danced
their way into America's collective imagination
in a script adapted from L. Frank Baum's
book, with lyrics by E. Y. "Yip" Harburg and a
score by Harold Arlen. In the process, Kansas
and the Great Plains came to epitomize the
drab and ordinary, the foil against which Oz
and other parts of America, especially urban
areas, seem fantastic and magical.</p>

<p>The Wizard of Oz opened in August 1939, a
phenomenal year in movie history&#8211;<title>Gone with the Wind</title>, <title>Wuthering Heights</title>, <title>Stagecoach</title>,
and <hi rend="italic">Mr. Smith Goes to Washington</hi> also premiered
that year. Nonetheless, <title>The Wizard of Oz</title>, directed by Victor Fleming, captured
Academy Awards for best original score and
best song ("Over the Rainbow"). Judy Garland
also received a juvenile Oscar for her performance
as Dorothy. Because the film played
to large audiences of children, who did not
pay full rates, the production did not make
money until it was leased to television in 1956.
Running each year on cbs or <hi rend="smallcaps">NBC</hi>, the show
became standard family viewing fare.</p>

<p>Like the book before it, the film tells a
uniquely American fairy tale, and in the new
medium Americans related to it in greater
numbers. At the same time, its audience
broadened throughout the world, largely because,
as author Salman Rushdie notes, the
film actually improved on a good book, creating
a work of art. An important aspect of this
film transformation is the much larger role
assigned to Kansas and its people. In Baum's
book, only six pages in chapter 1 and under
twenty lines in the final chapter are devoted to
the sun-seared Great Plains. Only Auntie Em,
Uncle Henry, Dorothy, and Toto appear. In
contrast, the movie introduces three farmhands
(played by Lahr, Bolger, and Haley), an
itinerant salesman (Frank Morgan), and Miss
Gulch (Margaret Hamilton). These characters
mirror the most important characters in the
Land of Oz. Introducing evil in the person of
Miss Gulch and her counterpart, the Wicked
Witch of the West, the film takes on an immediacy
and drama not possible in the book. The
Kansas sequence, shot in black and white and
placed in a brown bath to mute the tones,
emphasizes the stark difference between the
reality of Kansas and the colorful fairyland of
Oz.</p>

<p>Whether in Baum's book or the mgm movie,
the sharp contrast between Kansas and Oz has
always been a defining feature, suggesting that
Oz is something more than it seems&#8211;a metaphor
for America. In 1900, when the book was
first published, America's economy was depressed,
and Baum's Oz can be interpreted as a
parody of America under the influence of the
Populist party, which had arisen at the turn of
the century to champion farmers and laborers
against corporate America. In 1939 the country
was in the depths of the Great Depression, and
some viewers suggest that <hi rend="smallcaps">MGM</hi>'s Oz might be a
commentary on President Franklin D. Roosevelt's
administration. In a 1981 interview in the
<title level="j">Washington Post</title>, songwriter Yip Harburg,
who had considerable creative freedom on the
film, claimed that the Emerald City represented
the New Deal. Regardless of specific
interpretations, however, both book and
movie have lent themselves to political allusion,
being recast in each new era. In the 1970s
political pundits likened President Richard
Nixon to the bogus Wizard of Oz caught behind
the curtain in the movie, while illustrator
Barry Moser modeled his wood engravings for
a 1986 edition of the book on members of the
Ronald Reagan White House. First Lady Nancy
Reagan was identifiable as the Wicked Witch of
the West.</p>

<p>No matter what the political interpretation,
the 1939 film evokes a joyful, still innocent,
can-do world in which each person already
holds the solution to his or her own problems.
In setting this up, however, <title level="j">The Wizard of Oz</title>
also creates a no-can-do Kansas, a dull drabness
in the heart of America, making it one of
the most controversial film portrayals of the
Great Plains.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">LITERARY TRADITIONS</hi>: <ref n="egp.lt.003">Baum, Frank L.</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</hi>: <ref n="egp.pg.063">Populists (People's Party)</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Nancy Tystad Koupal<lb/>
South Dakota State Historical Society</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Harmetz, Aljean. <title level="m">The Making of "The Wizard of Oz."</title> New
York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1977.</bibl> <bibl>MacDonnell, Francis. "'The
Emerald City Was the New Deal': E. Y. Harburg and <hi rend="italic">The
Wonderful Wizard of Oz</hi>." <title level="j">Journal of American Culture</title> 13
(1990): 71–76.</bibl> <bibl>Rushdie, Salman. <title level="m">The Wizard of Oz</title>. <hi rend="smallcaps">BFI</hi>
Film Classics. London: <hi rend="smallcaps">BFI</hi> Publishing, 1992.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>