<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.rel.036">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Native American Church</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Wynema Morris</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.rel.036</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Morris, Wynema">Wynema Morris</author>. <title level="a">"Native American Church."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">752-753</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-19</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">NATIVE AMERICAN CHURCH</head>
<figure n="egp.rel.036" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Logo for the Native American Church</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Native Americans have long been subjected
to various policies of the United States in
an attempt to "civilize" them. Conversion to
Christianity was among such policies. As with
most issues dealing with Native Americans,
the picture is not complete without providing
some insight into both the traditional and legal
backgrounds.</p>

<p>Many denominations of mainstream Christianity
made initial forays into Indian Country
in the attempt to convert Native Americans
to Christianity and as part of federal
policy. The success of these efforts is reflected
by the single Christian creed professed by various
tribes. For example, many Omahas originally
adhered to Mormonism. Some Sioux
tribes are substantially Catholic or Episcopalian.
It depended upon who arrived first to
begin the conversion process.</p>

<p>In the early part of the twentieth century,
a unique Native Christian religion founded
upon the basic tenets of Christianity began to
sweep throughout Indian Country. While conversion
to Christianity was a slow and painful
process, the tenets of the Native American
Church were most readily accepted. While the
exact origins of the Native American Church
and its incorporation of peyote as a sacrament
of communion are shrouded in oral history,
Native believers generally agree that it began in
the Southwest and worked its way up from
Mexico. Among the Plains Indians, the Omahas,
Poncas, Winnebagos, and Sioux readily
accepted the belief system of the Native American
Church.</p>

<p>The tenets of the Native American Church
are similar to mainstream Christianity. The
leap from traditional belief in a universal creative,
mysterious, and holy power (God) who
now has a son, Jesus Christ, was initially surprising. However, ready acceptance of God
having a son was not that difficult, as all things
were believed to be possible through the Creator.
Peyote is also considered sacred and holy
as a sacrament and the means in which to
commune with God and Jesus Christ.</p>

<p>The use of peyote, a cactus plant of the mescal
family, within the Native American Church
has spawned both case law and federal legislation.
The legal controversy over peyote resulted
in its legal classification as a controlled
drug. Therefore, only card-carrying members
of the church are allowed to possess, transport,
and use peyote for religious purposes.</p>

<p>The Indian Religious Freedom Act of 1978
was passed to provide legal protection for the
Native American Church in its use of peyote.
All peyote has to be transported from Texas,
where it grows. Of the fifty states, only twentyeight
states have enacted laws similar to, or
in conformance with, federal regulation intended
to protect its use. However, in the U.S.
Supreme Court case of <title>Employment Division
v. Smith</title> (1990), the Court held that the First
Amendment does not provide protection for
practitioners of the Native American Church.
Two subsequent amendments, in 1994 and
1996, intended to clarify and provide the
much-needed protections.</p>

<p>As for the actual religious ceremony itself, it
is an act that requires deep commitment and
faith. It is generally held in a tipi or, in inclement
weather, a large area indoors. The Native
American Church also requires that a pastor,
priest, or elder conduct the services. This person
is referred to as the Roadman, who from
time to time must travel from tribal community
to community, similar to early Christian
missionaries who covered wide geographical
areas.</p>

<p>The Roadman is assisted by a Fireman,
whose task is to care for the holy fireplace
by making sure that it burns continuously
throughout the night. His own instruments for
conducting the church services are the prayer
staff, his eagle feather, a beaded and feathered
gourd, a small drum, cedar, and the peyote
chief, which is always present at the altar. Other
peyote is ground finely or made into a mush
and passed around in a circle to all participants
as a sacrament to commune with God and his
Son. The Roadman's wife or other female relative
prepares seven sacramental foods and the
"second breakfast" that are part of the church
services. Her part takes place very early, between
4:30 and 5:00 in the morning. The seven
sacramental foods are water, shredded beef,
corn mush, rice, strawberries, cookies, and
soft, individually wrapped candies. To counter-balance
the bitterness of the peyote consumed
during the services, the sweet foods
were added later. The second breakfast is like
any other breakfast. It generally includes
boiled eggs, toast, hash brown potatoes, coffee,
and juice. This meal is served well after sunrise
and just prior to the closing of the church
services.</p>

<p>Church services are not regular Sunday occurrences
but are held in accordance with special
requests by a family for celebrating a
birthday, or for a memorial or funeral service.
Services begin at sundown on either a Friday
or Saturday evening and end at sunrise. Thus,
a participant "sits up" all night, giving up a
full night's rest as part of a small sacrifice to
the Great and Holy Spirit and his Son.</p>

<p>The church services culminate in a feast for
the whole community the following day. Because
peyote is a stimulant, all of the participating
members are wide awake, so they,
too, attend the feast. The need for sleep is generally
felt in the late afternoon, particularly
after the feast. Gifts are given to the Roadman
and all his helpers by the sponsoring family at
the feast to show deep appreciation for all his
hard work.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Wynema Morris<lb/>
Walthill, Nebraska</signed>
</closer>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>