<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.pd.029">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Industrial Workers of the World</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Ted Grossardt</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.pd.029</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Grossardt, Ted">Ted Grossardt</author>. <title level="a">"Industrial Workers of the World."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">714</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-06</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">INDUSTRIAL WORKERS OF THE WORLD</head>

<p>The Industrial Workers of the World (<hi rend="smallcaps">IWW</hi>),
or Wobblies, originated in Chicago in 1905 as a
loose amalgam of labor and political entities,
principally the Western Federation of Miners
(<hi rend="smallcaps">WFM</hi>) and various socialist political parties.
The union aspired to organize all workers by
industry (hence the name "Industrial") instead
of by skill categories, as did trade unions
like the American Federation of Labor. Led by
"Big Bill" Haywood from the <hi rend="smallcaps">WFM</hi>, the Wobblies
moved from organizing eastern factories
full of unskilled immigrants and women in
the early years to organizing the huge migrant
labor force in the western United States that
worked in the extractive industries of lumbering,
mining and petroleum, and agriculture.
Immigrant, homeless, relying on the railroads
for transportation, and camping on the edges
of towns in so-called jungles, the migrant
worker was the ultimate invisible person. The
Wobblies created an organization that enlisted
migrant workers as the foot soldiers in their
"army of the revolution."</p>

<p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">IWW</hi> did not see itself as a political party
and eschewed involvement with any political
system. Rather, it favored "direct action"&#8211;the
use of labor action to solve labor problems.
Rich in symbolism, and using a variety of visual
images to present its story to a largely
immigrant and often illiterate audience, the
Wobblies became identified by the black cat
and the French wooden shoe (<hi rend="italic">sabot</hi>), the symbol
for sabotage. Although the Wobbly newspaper
<title level="j">Solidarity</title> hinted broadly at the advantages
of sabotage for realizing goals, it is
not clear to what extent sabotage was actually
practiced.</p>

<p>In the Great Plains, the Wobblies reached
their greatest extent and impact just prior to
the World War I with a concerted effort to
organize migrant wheat harvesters, the socalled
bindlestiffs. They used a "contagion"
method of organizing, where any new member
could sign up additional new members.
Capitalizing on the fact that railroads were
really the only means of long-distance transportation,
Wobblies took control of boxcars,
organizing everyone in the car as the freight
trains moved from town to town. Small-town
sheriffs had no idea what to do when boxcar
after boxcar loaded with singing, shouting
Wobblies landed in their town. If they arrested
one or two for disturbing the peace, the rest of
the union would surround the jail and demand
release. Employers were unaccustomed
to having migrant workers band together to
demand higher pay.</p>

<p>Between 1915 and 1917 the <hi rend="smallcaps">IWW</hi> swept across
the Plains like a prairie fire. By the summer of
1916 the <hi rend="smallcaps">IWW</hi> was collecting dues from more
than 18,000 migrant harvesters, and its organizers
boasted of an "800-mile picket line"
from Oklahoma to South Dakota. The Wobblies'
mobility, developed from many years of
practice as migrants, allowed them to appear
to be everywhere at once.</p>

<p>After the onset of World War I, the image of
the saboteur was used effectively against the
union by state and federal agencies. When the
Wobblies attempted to capture, in the form of
increased wages, some of the money being fed
into wartime industry, they were accused of
sympathizing with Germany. Following the
success of the Russian Revolution in 1917, the
"army of the revolution" was dealt a serious
blow by a series of coordinated government
raids on <hi rend="smallcaps">IWW</hi> headquarters across the United
States in September of that year. Hundreds of
iww leaders were arrested and tried for treason
and other charges, draining the union's
coffers. Wichita, Kansas, became infamous for
its rotating jail cells, in which at least one
Wobbly died and many more wasted away
waiting for trial. Big Bill Haywood emigrated
to communist Russia following the war.</p>

<p>Ultimately, the advent of combine wheat
harvesters obviated the need for huge numbers
of migrant laborers, and the adoption of the
automobile split migrants into small groups
that could not be organized as effectively as
entire boxcar loads. By the late 1920s the <hi rend="italic">I
Won't Works</hi>, as the Wobblies were nicknamed,
were little more than an exciting memory in
the Great Plains.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Ted Grossardt<lb/>
University of Kentucky</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Brissenden, Paul F. <title level="m">The I.W.W.: A Study of American Syndicalism</title>.
New York: Columbia University, 1919.</bibl> <bibl>Kornbluh,
Joyce L. <title level="m">Rebel Voices: An I.W.W. Anthology</title>. Ann Arbor:
University of Michigan Press, 1965.</bibl> <bibl>Sellars, Nigel Anthony.
<title level="m">Oil, Wheat, and Wobblies: The Industrial Workers of the
World in Oklahoma, 1905–1930</title>. Norman: University of
Oklahoma Press, 1998.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>