<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.sr.041">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">National Wildlife Refuges</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Charles I. Zinser</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.sr.041</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Zinser, Charles I.">Charles I. Zinser</author>. <title level="a">"National Wildlife Refuges."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">783-784</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-21</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">NATIONAL WILDLIFE REFUGES</head>

<p>The National Wildlife Refuge System is a network
of U.S. lands and waters that are managed
specifically for wildlife, especially migratory
birds and endangered species. This
92,873,832-acre system is comprised of 512 national
wildlife refuges, 198 waterfowl production
areas, and 50 coordination areas as well as
3 wildlife research centers, 41 administrative
sites, 64 national fish hatcheries, and 6 fishery
research stations. The Fish and Wildlife Service
in the Department of the Interior administers
the system. In the Great Plains there are
110 national wildlife refuges on 1.8 million
acres (22 percent of the number of refuges but
only 2 percent of the acreage nationwide). The
greatest concentration of the refuges in the
Great Plains is in North Dakota and Montana.
These refuges range in size from 27-acre
Stump Lake (North Dakota) to 903,300-acre
Charles M. Russell (Montana). Additionally,
the ‘‘prairie pothole'' land (often referred to as
‘‘duck factories'') of North and South Dakota
contains 84 percent of the waterfowl production
areas in the country (1,107,300 acres in
North Dakota and 966,000 acres in South Dakota).
These waterfowl production areas are
wetland areas acquired pursuant to the Migratory
Bird Hunting and Conservation Act and
administered as part of the National Wildlife
Refuge System.</p>

<p>The National Wildlife Refuge System represents
the most comprehensive wildlife resource
management program in the world.
The refuges are managed to maintain habitat,
food supplies, and water for animals. In the
Great Plains water is the prime factor determining
their location. The conservation aspect
of resource management governs the
National Wildlife Refuge System. Hunting,
growing agricultural crops, cutting hay, logging,
and trapping are allowed, yet the preservation
aspect dominates in seven refuges
where eight units of the National Wilderness
Preservation System have been designated on
64,743 acres: Medicine Lake National Wildlife
Refuge (11,366 acres), Montana; Bend National
Wildlife Refuge (20,819 acres), Montana;
Fort Niobrara National Wildlife Refuge
(4,635 acres), Nebraska; Bitter Lake National
Wildlife Refuge (Salt Creek Wilderness, 9,621
acres), New Mexico; Chase Lake National
Wildlife Refuge (4,155 acres), North Dakota;
Lostwood National Wildlife Refuge (5,577
acres), North Dakota; and Wichita Mountains
National Wildlife Refuge (Charons Garden
Wilderness, 5,723 acres, and North Mountain
Wilderness, 2,847 acres), Oklahoma.</p>

<p>Although refuges are not managed specifically
for recreation, a broad range of recreational
opportunities is possible on many of
them; virtually all of these recreational opportunities
revolve around wildlife. Activities
vary with each refuge and may depend on the
season. Some refuges have elaborate visitor
centers and are equipped to handle a large
number of visitors, but others are not. Some of
the national wildlife refuges in the Great Plains
are major tourist attractions and receive very
heavy visitation; others are so lightly used that
visitation data are not even collected.</p>

<p>Kansas has four national wildlife refuges.
Although the Quivira (21,800 acres) is the
largest, most visitation occurs at the Kirwin
(10,800 acres) and the Flint Hills (40,650
acres). Kirwin is a valuable recreational resource
on the North Fork of the Solomon
River in north-central Kansas where a Bureau
of Reclamation Dam (Kirwin Dam) impounds
the river.</p>

<p>In Montana fourteen national wildlife refuges
extend over 1,055,00 acres, but most of
this acreage is in the huge Charles M. Russell
Refuge, the second largest refuge in the lower
forty-eight states. This refuge, named after this
country's most venerable cowboy artist, extends
for almost 150 miles upstream on the
Missouri River above the Fort Peck Dam. Motor
vehicles are permitted on over 700 miles of
designated refuge road, and boating, fishing,
exploring, camping (backcountry), and seasonal
hunting are all popular. There are developed
state park and Army Corps of Engineers
recreational facilities adjacent to the refuge. A
twenty-mile, thirteen-stop interpretive tour
that takes about two hours provides a good
overview of the refuge. The ul Bend National
Wildlife Refuge borders Charles M. Russell.
Medicine Lake National Wildlife Refuge (31,500
acres) is located in the glaciated rolling plains of
northeast Montana and contains 11,366 acres of
the National Wilderness Preservation System.</p>

<p>Nebraska has eight national wildlife refuges
on 148,633 acres. Most of the recreational use
occurs at just one refuge, the DeSoto, which
lies in both Iowa (3,500 acres) and Nebraska
(4,300 acres) and includes an old oxbow lake
that was once the course of the Missouri River.
The section open for public use is on the Iowa
side of the refuge. Sitting on the shore of DeSoto
Lake is one of the finest visitor centers
and museums to be found on U.S. public
lands. Artifacts from the 1860s stern-wheeler
Bertrand (recovered in 1968 from the sunken
ship) are on display here. Other large refuges
in Nebraska include the Valentine (71,500
acres) in north-central Nebraska and the
Crescent Lake (45,800 acres) in western Nebraska.
Nebraska's newest refuge (September
30, 1997), the Boyer Chute, began with the
donation of 1,953 acres from the Papio Missouri
River Natural Resource District.</p>

<p>In the Great Plains of New Mexico there are
four national wildlife refuges on 40,100 acres.
The greater portion of this acreage is in one
refuge, the Bitter Lake (25,000 acres). This refuge
and the Las Vegas (8,700 acres) are by far
the leaders in visitation.</p>

<p>North Dakota has sixty-two national wildlife
refuges that cover 289,300 acres. The largest
of these is J. Clark Salyer (59,400 acres), named
after the individual credited with being "the
father of the National Wildlife Refuge System."
A twenty-two-mile-long interpretive auto tour
route threads its way through marshlands,
grasslands, sandy hills, and forested areas. Designated
as a unit of the National Canoe Trail
System, a thirteen-mile stretch of the Souris
River offers opportunities for exploration and
wildlife observation by canoe. The refuge attracting
the most visitors is the Upper Souris
(32,300 acres), which is located west and upstream
on the Souris River from J. Clark Salyer.
Most of Chase Lake (4,155 from 4,400 acres)
and 5,577 acres of Lostwood (26,900 acres) are
two of the eight units of the National Wilderness
Preservation System on national wildlife
refuges in the Great Plains. A small refuge on
the south shore of Devils Lake, Sullys Hill
(1,675 acres), has a unique historical background.
President Theodore Roosevelt proclaimed
it a national park in 1904, but in 1931
Congress transferred it to the National Wildlife
Refuge System. The refuge is one of four
managed by the Fish and Wildlife Service for
American bison and elk.</p>

<p>Of the six national wildlife refuges in Oklahoma,
encompassing 116,100 acres, the Wichita
Mountains (59,000 acres) in southwest
Oklahoma is the largest and receives the most
visitors (1.5 million annually). This refuge was
first set aside as the Wichita Forest Reserve in
1901. It became the Wichita Forest and Game
Preserve in 1905 and received its present designation
in 1934. In 1907 a fence was built and
the New York Zoological Society donated fifteen
bison, and in 1927 thirty head of Texas
longhorns were introduced. These herds have
increased to about 525 bison and 300 longhorns
today. This refuge oãers as wide a range
of recreational opportunities as can be found
at any refuge in the country. Another very
popular refuge in Oklahoma is the Salt Plains
(150,000 annual visitors and 32,100 acres) in
the north-central part of the state. The refuge
is divided into almost equal parts of salt flats,
open water, and vegetated land (marsh, woods,
grassland, and cropland).</p>

<p>There are 48,000 acres in six national wildlife
refuges in South Dakota. The largest (22,000
acres) and most visited (almost 100,000 visitors
annually) is Sand Lake, twenty-five miles north
of Aberdeen. The James River supplies water to
the Mud and Sand Lakes, which cover over half
the refuge. The Lacreek National Wildlife Refuge,
with 35,000 annual visitors and covering
17,000 acres, ranks second in the state in both
categories.</p>

<p>Very few national wildlife refuges are located
in the Great Plains of Colorado, Texas,
and Wyoming. Colorado has only one refuge
in the Great Plains: Rocky Mountain Arsenal
(17,000 acres). The Fish and Wildlife Service
has only secondary jurisdiction over this refuge
and will not receive primary jurisdiction
until a contamination cleanup is completed.
There are only four refuges totaling 17,000
acres in the Texas Plains. Muleshoe (5,800
acres) hosts one of the largest concentrations
of sandhill cranes in North America from October
through March. Balcones Canyonlands
(3,500 acres) offers a valuable public hunting
area in the Texas Hill Country. Only 5 acres of
Grulla National Wildlife Refuge are in Texas;
3,230 acres are in New Mexico. In the Great
Plains of Wyoming there are three refuges on
19,900 acres, most of which are accounted for
by Pathfinder Refuge (16,800 acres).</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">WATER</hi>: <ref n="egp.wat.039">Wetlands</ref>.</p>

<p><ref target="http://www.fws.gov/refuges/">National Wildlife Refuge System</ref> website.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Charles I. Zinser<lb/>
Pittsburgh State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Zinser, Charles I. <title level="m">Outdoor Recreation: United States National
Parks, Forests and Public Lands</title>. New York: John
Wiley and Sons, 1995.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>