<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ag.067">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Sustainable Agriculture</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Charles A. Francis</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ag.067</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Francis, Charles A.">Charles A. Francis</author>. <title level="a">"Sustainable Agriculture."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">53-54</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2009-01-12</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">SUSTAINABLE AGRICULTURE</head>

<p>To maintain human economic activity and
quality of life in the Great Plains, it is essential
to develop a strategy that efficiently
uses and conserves natural resources over the
long term. Agriculture provides the opportunity
to use the water, soil, and other renewable
resources of the Plains, but strategies and
systems for crop, forage, and livestock production
need to be designed for maximum
sustainability. This means an agriculture that
does not overly exploit or deplete these resources,
an agriculture that is productive, economically
sound, environmentally benign,
and socially viable. One of the most successful
models that meets these criteria, including
maintaining rural communities, is a sustainable
agriculture based on renewable resources,
private farm ownership, and family farming
units.</p>

<p>What defines the Plains climate for agriculture
is a rate of evapotranspiration (water loss
from soil and plants) that exceeds the rate
of rainfall for an important part of the crop-growing
season. There are many ways to compensate
for this adverse climate, all involving
capturing and storing moisture in the soil so
that it will be available when crops are growing.
They include reduced or zero tillage during
land preparation, choosing crops that have
low water needs, planting lower crop populations
that will use less water, and managing
weeds in a way that limits their water use. Application
of chemical herbicides, coupled with
minimum or zero tillage, can drastically reduce
water loss from the soil surface, but there
is the potential hazard of chemical contact by
human applicators or nontarget members of
the ecosystem. Woody perennial windbreaks
can reduce transpiration from crops and increase
production. A combination of these
water-saving and harvesting methods makes
maximum possible use of accumulated water
storage from snow and rain.</p>

<p>Irrigation was long used in the Great Plains
by Native Americans and later by European
American immigrants who settled near rivers.
There is now a large irrigated acreage in Nebraska,
western Kansas, the Texas Panhandle,
and southern Alberta. Although some acres
depend on surface water supplies that are renewed
each year, a large portion of irrigation
in the Central and Southern Plains comes
from the Ogallala Aquifer. During the past two
decades this source of groundwater has been
seriously depleted, especially in the Southern
Plains. Farmers there have shifted from irrigated
corn to less demanding crops such as
grain sorghum and cotton. The Ogallala Aquifer
is recharged through the Sandhills of Nebraska
and from playa lakes on the Southern
Plains, and thus can recuperate if irrigation is
curtailed. Deeper aquifers below the Ogallala
are composed of fossil water that, once depleted,
is lost. Although irrigated production
of cereals such as corn, grain sorghum, and
wheat has been profitable over the past five
decades, it is unlikely that production will
continue, because Plains farmers have to compete
with farmers farther east in the United
States and in other countries with better rainfall
conditions and much lower production
costs. It is likely that scarce irrigation will be
used only on specialty, higher-value crops in
the future, hence the importance of sustainable
agriculture.</p>

<p>Sustainable agriculture generally includes
such production practices as crop rotation,
integrated pest management, soil fertility that
depends to the greatest extent possible on
legumes and grasses in the sequence, and a
minimum program of tillage that helps prevent
soil erosion. Many proponents maintain
that raising livestock as an integral component
of the system is essential to long-term soil fertility
and sustainability. Livestock provide a
ready outlet for green forages and hay and
speed the cycling of nutrients by consuming
these forages and leaving manure in the fields.
They also can graze crop residues in place,
making use of such forages and cycling nutrients
through manure. Composting animal
manures and urban organic wastes is another
method of returning important nutrients to
the land and building soil organic matter. Although
much of the nitrogen and some other
elements are lost during the composting process,
the nutrients are present in a more stable
condition that makes them less susceptible to
loss from the system after incorporation into
the soil.</p>

<p>To be sustainable, an agricultural system
must be economically viable in both the short
term and the long term. Thus it is essential
to design systems that enhance the resources
on which productivity is based rather than
pursuing a simplified system that exploits
nonrenewable resources such as fossil fuels
and sacrifices long-term sustainability for
short-term gain. Federal price-support programs
for specific crops distort the long-term
biological and ecological realities, since farmers
feel forced to seek monoculture strategies
that maximize short-term gains. Likewise,
short-term rental or lease agreements for land
provide little incentive for the operator to
conserve soil and focus on the future value of
this resource. For these reasons, an agriculture
based on family farm ownership and entrepreneurship
seems the most likely to provide
stability in food production and conservation
of resources.</p>

<p>Social viability of rural communities is the
final dimension of sustainable agriculture.
When farms in the Great Plains were consolidated
over the past century, the result was
fewer people on the land as well as fewer in
rural communities to provide support services
and social infrastructure. Many small towns in
the Plains have disappeared. In part this is a
natural consequence of mechanization of agriculture,
with fewer hands needed to till and
harvest. It is also a result of improved transportation,
since commodities can now be
marketed over a wide area rather than depending
on a local elevator or other buyer. On
the business side, it is clear that the larger the
farm the less the reliance on local services—
pesticides, fertilizers, and equipment now may
be purchased from a several state area rather
than from the local dealer. The impact of large
farms is loss of local business and consequently
the loss of other rural infrastructure:
churches, schools, medical facilities, entertainment,
in short the loss of community.
Such a system is clearly not sustainable from
the family standpoint, and an agriculture that
depends on distant ownership and minimumwage
jobs does not promote conservation of
natural or human resources. Building systems
that add value to products locally, that generate
both food and income for local residents,
and that cycle dollars around in the community,
rather than extracting them from the
land and people, can lead to a more sustainable
agriculture and food system for the Great
Plains.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">CITIES AND TOWNS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ct.049">Small Towns</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">WATER</hi>: <ref n="egp.wat.011">Irrigation</ref>; <ref n="egp.wat.018">Ogallala Aquifer</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Charles A. Francis<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Edwards, Clive A., Rattan Lal, Patrick Madden, Robert H.
Miller, and Gar House, eds. <title level="m">Sustainable Agricultural Systems</title>.
Ankeney <hi rend="smallcaps">IA</hi>: Soil and Water Conservation Society,
1990.</bibl> <bibl>Francis, Charles A., Cornelia B. Flora, and Larry D.
King. <title level="m">Sustainable Agriculture in Temperate Zones</title>. New
York: John Wiley &amp; Sons, 1990.</bibl> <bibl>Hegyes, Gabriel, and
Charles Francis. <title level="m">Future Horizons: Recent Literature in Sustainable Agriculture</title>. Lincoln: Center for Sustainable Agricultural
Systems, University of Nebraska–Lincoln, 1997.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>