<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.med.017">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Edwards, Bob (1864-1922)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Diane Howard</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.med.017</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Howard, Diane">Diane Howard</author>. <title level="a">"Edwards, Bob (1864-1922)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">511-512</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-26</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">Edwards, Bob (1864-1922)</head>

<p>One of Canada's leading journalists, Bob Edwards
was a critic of government officials and
the excessive moralism of the churches as well
as a supporter of the emancipation of women
and the temperance crusade. He was best
known as the one-man staff, editor, and publisher
of the <title level="j">Calgary Eye Opener</title> and remembered
for his off-color tales and jokes. Edwards
built the paper's circulation and his
own reputation for social criticism combined
with humor.</p>

<p>Robert Chambers Edwards was born on
September 12, 1864, in Edinburgh, Scotland.
He was orphaned at an early age and, with his
brother Jack, raised by an aunt. He was educated
at Glasgow University, where he studied
philosophy and literature. For a brief period,
Edwards traveled throughout Europe, settling
in the south of France, where he continued
the family tradition of newspaper writing and
publishing. His first enterprise was an English
newspaper named the <title level="j">Traveler</title>, which he published
on the Riviera and which catered to
English gentry traveling abroad.</p>

<p>In 1884 Bob traveled with his brother to the
United States and for the next ten years found
assorted jobs working on farms and cattle operations
in Wyoming, Iowa, and Alberta, Canada.
In 1897 he finally settled down in the
small town of Wetaskiwin, fifty miles south
of Edmonton. There he established the <title level="j">Wetaskiwin Free Lance</title>, the first newspaper to
be published between Edmonton and Calgary.
Edwards wrote less about "real news" and
more on the social issues of the day. The editor
of the <title level="j">Calgary Herald</title> was impressed by Edwards's
humor and witty journalistic prose
and offered to reprint some of his articles in
the Calgary paper.</p>

<p>In 1898 Bob Edwards moved to Calgary,
where he continued to publish and write for
the <title level="j">Wetaskiwin Free Lance</title>. He soon moved on
to Winnipeg, where he struggled as a news
reporter for the <title level="j">Winnipeg Free Press</title>. Disillusioned
as a writer for a large daily, Edwards
returned to the small-town life he so enjoyed
and set up shop in High River, where he published
the first edition of the <title level="j">Eye Opener</title> in
March 1902. The hard-drinking, carefree Edwards
created fictional characters and tales
considered shocking by small-town standards,
and eventually he moved his operation to Calgary.
As soon as he was settled, Edwards continued
to build his reputation by reporting on
various local scandals with satire and wit.</p>

<p>Over the next twenty years Bob Edwards
became known for standing up for the common
person, highlighting the plight of prostitutes,
and revealing the scams of fraudulent
real estate developers. Personally, he battled
severe alcoholism, so much so that in 1916 he
was one of the supporters of prohibition in
Alberta. A year later he married a Scottish
woman who was less than half his age.</p>

<p>In the summer of 1920 Edwards published a
soft-cover book of some of his best stories,
editorials, and jokes. It was an enormous success
and appeared regularly as an annual edition
for the remainder of his life. Edwards
died on November 14, 1922, leaving a long
legacy of witty writings depicting the political,
social, and economic times of the early Canadian
western frontier. To honor Bob Edwards,
Alberta Theater Projects initiated an award in
his name recognizing Canadian writers who
exemplify the spirit of freedom of expression.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Diane Howard<lb/>
University of Calgary</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Dempsey, Hugh. <title level="m">The Best of Bob Edwards</title>. Edmonton, Alberta:
Hurtig Publishers, 1975.</bibl> <bibl>Longpr&#233;, Kerry, and Margaret
Dickson. <title level="m">Provocative Canadians: In the Spirit of Bob Edwards</title>. Calgary, Alberta: Bayeux Arts, 1999.</bibl> <bibl>MacEwan,
Grant. <title level="m">Eye Opener Bob: The Story of Bob Edwards</title>. Saskatoon,
Saskatchewan: Western Producer Prairie Books,
1974.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>