<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fil.064">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Westerns</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>John L. Simons</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fil.064</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Simons, John L.">John L. Simons</author>. <title level="a">"Westerns."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">279-280</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-12</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">WESTERNS</head>
<figure n="egp.fil.064" rend="granted" type="noclick">
<figDesc>Book cover for the novel The Plainsman featuring information about the film version (1936)starring Gary Cooper</figDesc>
</figure>      

<p>Plains Westerns typically center on two key
elements, historical and geographical, each of
which assumes importance by virtue of the
specific character of the Plains experience.</p>

<p>One of the representative traits of Western
films involving or located within the Great
Plains is their pronounced obsession with actual
historical events and historical characters.
This may be so because in the Western film
dialectic between East and West, the Plains
form a sort of Middle Landscape, mixing history
and myth, between the more historically
mapped East and more exotically romanticized
and mythologized West. Real historical
events and persons occur much more often in
Plains Westerns, which helps to explain why
John Ford's silent film epic of the building of
the transcontinental railroad, <title>The Iron Horse</title>
(1924), is filled with so many historical events
and characters, many more than any other of
his more "western" Westerns. The history, of
course, has often been radically altered for
narrative, dramatic, and ideological reasons.
While it is unusual to find the Civil War, Abraham
Lincoln, westward expansion, Wild Bill
Hickok, Buffalo Bill, Calamity Jane, the Plains
Indian Wars, and Gen. George Armstrong
Custer (though most of them appeared together
in <title>The Iron Horse</title>) all cobbled together
as they are in Cecil B. De Mille's wildly improbable,
spectacularly inaccurate, actionfilled
<title>The Plainsman</title> (1936), nevertheless,
many other Plains films are also based, if ever
so loosely, on actual historical events and
characters primarily because the Plains Western
mixes myth and history more readily than
does the Far West Western.</p>

<p>Key Plains historical events include the great
pioneer migration after the Civil War (<title>The Covered Wagon</title>, 1923; <title>How the West Was Won</title>,
1962); the blazing of the great cattle trails (<title>Red River</title>, 1946; <title>Abilene Town</title>, 1951); the brief career
of the Pony Express, an especially popular
topic for very early Westerns made by <title>Great Train Robbery</title> (1903) director Edwin S. Porter
and stars Bronco Billy Anderson and Tom Mix;
the founding of cattle towns (<title>Dodge City</title>, 1939;
<title>Wichita</title>, 1955; and many others); the advent of
railroads (<title>Iron Horse</title>, 1924; <title>Dodge City</title> and
<title>Union Pacific</title>, both 1939) and the telegraph
(<title>Western Union</title>, 1941); numerous wars with
the Plains Indians, the greatest of which and
the most prescient and sympathetic to Native
Americans is Kevin Costner's <title>Dances with Wolves</title> (1990); the Missouri-Kansas border
wars (<title>Dark Command</title>, 1940; <title>The Outlaw Josey Wales</title>, 1976); and historical figures such as Kit
Carson, William Clark Quantrill, John Brown,
Jesse and Frank James, the Dalton Gang, Wyatt
Earp, Bat Masterson, Sitting Bull, Crazy Horse,
and many more, all of whom appear in numerous
films. Propelled by the mythic and historical
provenance of Manifest Destiny and the
more literal promise of vast new lands for exploration
and settlement, the Great Plains
hovered in a special zone of the imagination
between myth and history, fact and fantasy,
with each feeding the other in rich, energizing,
though at times blatantly jingoistic and racist
ways.</p>

<p>As is virtually the case with all Westerns,
landscape figures prominently in nearly every
film, from the very early settler epic, <title>The Covered Wagon</title>, through the more racially, culturally,
and ecologically sophisticated <title>Dances with Wolves</title> and the more gender-conscious
<title>Westward the Women</title> (1951), <title>The Ballad of Little Jo</title> (1993), and <title>Unforgiven</title> (1991). Almost no
Westerns have been actually shot on location
in the Central Plains, though more recently
Montana, Wyoming, and the Canadian Prairies
have been used as locations for filming
Westerns. Nevertheless, numerous films are
able to convey through cinematography and
editing a feeling for the oceanic vastness of the
Plains, the winds, the droughts, the sudden
storms, the vast buffalo herds, and the Native
Americans so that a sense of the Plains' dwarfing
presence offers a kind of historical and
political, moral and spiritual landscape out of
which the narratives of the Plains experience
emerge. <title>How the West Was Won</title> (1962) is a
hodgepodge of many Westerns, but its sense
of visual space, enhanced by the Cinerama
process (note especially Henry Hathaway's
section on "The Prairie"), still makes it worth
looking at if not listening to. The same is true,
although the stories are much more interesting,
in the depiction of the Southern and
Northern Plains, respectively, in Terrence
Malick's sumptuously photographed <title>Days of Heaven</title> (1978) and in Michael Cimino's saga of
the Wyoming Johnson County War, <title>Heaven's Gate</title> (1980).</p>

<p>From the approving heavenly choirs that
herald a wagon train's sinuously curved journey
across the vast Central Plains at the beginning
of Howard Hawks's epic <title>Red River</title> (1946)
to the journey of a soul broken by war, violence,
and personal tragedy in Clint Eastwood's
masterly <title>The Outlaw Josey Wales</title>, the
best directors merge landscape, story, and
character in a unified whole. The story of Josey
Wales, which begins in catastrophe, ends in a
vision of cosmic and comic harmony in nature
and in society, closer in kind to a Shakespearean
romance than to a traditional Western.
Throughout this remarkable pilgrim's progress
the landscape continues to underscore the
imperatives of both plot and character.</p>

<p>Since all Westerns are about versions and
visions of history, no Western can be understood,
then, outside of its doubled historical
focus on both the remembered and interpreted
past and the self-interpreting present.
Thus the more "triumphalist" 1930s and 1940s
studio Westerns of Cecil B. De Mille (<title>The Plainsman</title>, <title>Union Pacific</title>) and Raoul Walsh
(<title>The Big Trail</title>, 1931; <title>They Died with Their Boots On</title>, 1941), Howard Hawks (<hi rend="italic">Red River</hi>),
and Michael Curtiz (<title>Santa Fe Trail</title>, 1940;
<title>Dodge City</title>) are placed in sharp relief with
films more critical, more conflicted and paradoxically
puzzling, of the settling of the West
such as Fred Zinnemann's <title>High Noon</title> (1952),
John Ford's <title>The Searchers</title> (1956), filmed in
Ford's mythical signature landscape, Monument
Valley, but really a story of the arduous
post–Civil War settling of Texas, and Arthur
Penn's <title>Little Big Man</title> (1970).</p>

<p>No film presents a more stark contrast with
the lush, lyrical beauty of the epic, mythically
charged story of the embodiment of Manifest
Destiny, epitomized by <title>Red River</title>, than the
radically revisionist <title>High Noon</title>, a parched
and sparse view of the almost unrepresented
Plains. The most deliberately <title>plain</title> of the
Plains Westerns, <title>High Noon</title> presents a landscape
not seen in many other films, a vision of
the end of an era, closer in spirit to a contemporary
film about the death of the Old West,
Peter Bogdanovich's <title>The Last Picture Show</title>
(1971), than to the more optimistic tradition of
the American Western. <title>High Noon</title> offers a
troubling account of the Plains West in the
aftermath of its vitalizing frontier settlement.
Topographically, the film's central irony turns
on the etiolated city streets of "civilized" (all
too civilized) Hadleyville, themselves metamorphosing
into a terrifying spatial void, as
threatening as the Plains themselves. The town
that Marshal Will Kane (Gary Cooper) has
tamed and to which he has brought law and
order now questions his leadership and turns
its back on him in this misanthropic Western.
We have come a long way from John Wayne's
mythical larger-than-life Tom Dunson in Red
River, a man who revels in the wild, vitalizing
spaces he inhabits, who sees only more and
more land in which to "grow good beef for
hungry Americans." Will Kane looks outside of
Hadleyville&#8211;and inside&#8211;and sees nothing
but nothingness. His Plains America no longer
affords a Turneresque vision of the creative
fusion of wilderness and society at the edge of
the frontier, for in this film each cancels out the
other.</p>

<p>The great majority of Plains Westerns, of
course, celebrate an expanding, optimistic
America, a land of perpetual plenty. But if the
Western mirrors American history, and it
does, then the Plains Western proffers the
same pleasures and discontents we contemplate
as we simultaneously look backward and
forward at the history of our country through
the already passed, always present, prism of
the Western film.</p>

<closer>
<signed>John L. Simons<lb/>
Colorado College</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Buscombe, Edward, ed. <title level="m">The <hi rend="smallcaps">BFI</hi> <hi rend="italic">Companion to the Western</hi></title>.
New York: DaCapo, 1988.</bibl> <bibl>Slotkin, Richard. <title level="m">Gunfighter Nation: The Myth of the Frontier in 20th Century America</title>.
New York: Atheneum, 1992.</bibl> <bibl>Smith, Henry Nash. <title level="m">Virgin Land: The American West as Symbol and Myth</title>. Cambridge:
Harvard University Press, 1950.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>