<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ind.043">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Oilseeds</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Patrick M. Carr</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ind.043</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Carr, Patrick M.">Patrick M. Carr</author>. <title level="a">"Oilseeds."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">428</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-04</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">OILSEEDS</head>

<p>The Great Plains is a principal production region
for several crops grown for the oil contained
in the seed. Changes in U.S. farm legislation
and world market conditions may make
it possible for oilseeds to become an even
more prominent component of the repertoire
of crops grown in the Great Plains in the future.
Crushing facilities for extracting oil from
seeds have been built in the Great Plains, while
facilities outside the region convert or incorporate
the seed oil into finished products.</p>

<p>Canola (<hi rend="italic">Brassica campestris</hi> and <hi rend="italic">B. napus</hi>) is
the most widely grown oilseed crop in the
Great Plains region of Canada and has increased
in popularity among northern U.S.
growers. For example, production in North
Dakota increased from 18,000 acres in 1991 to
more than 400,000 acres in 1997. Canola acreage
will expand in the near future, specifically
on the Northern Plains and in the Prairie
Provinces. Canola oil contains less saturated
fat than many other vegetable oils. As a result,
consumption of canola oil in the United States
has risen dramatically since it was first granted
gras (generally recognized as safe) status for
human food use by the U.S. Food and Drug
Administration in 1985. Plant geneticists have
altered the fatty acid composition of the seed
oil, thus increasing the number of varieties
available to growers and oil types available to
end users.</p>

<p>Crambe (<hi rend="italic">Crambe abyssinica</hi>) is grown on
around 40,000 acres annually in the Great
Plains, all of which are located in North Dakota.
Rapeseed (<hi rend="italic">Brassica campestris</hi> and <hi rend="italic">B.
napus</hi>) is grown on approximately 100,000
acres each year in Canada. The seed oil of both
crambe and rapeseed contains erucic acid.
This fatty acid is used in the manufacture of
slip agents, plasticizers, lubricants, and corrosion
inhibitors. Neither rapeseed nor crambe
produce seed oil that is suitable for human
consumption. Currently, world demand for
crambe and rapeseed oil is stable.</p>

<p>Flax (<hi rend="italic">Linum usitatissimum</hi>) is grown on approximately
two million acres in Canada each
year. An additional 100,000 to 150,000 acres
are produced in the United States, with about
80 percent occurring in North Dakota. Linseed
oil (obtained from flax) is used in the
manufacture of paints and varnishes. Interest
in flax within the health food industry has
evolved as the benefits of incorporating flax
into the human diet have been identified. The
development of flax oil as an edible vegetable
oil also has contributed to a renewed interest
in flax production.</p>

<p>Mustard (<hi rend="italic">Brassica juncea</hi> and <hi rend="italic">B. hirta</hi>)
is grown in northern portions of the Great
Plains region, primarily in Canada. Production
in the United States is mostly limited
to North Dakota and Montana, where between
12,000 and 60,000 acres were grown annually
between 1991 and 1997. Most mustard is
used in the processed meats industry and as
a flavoring agent in sauces and condiments.
Market demand for mustard presently is stable,
with little change anticipated in the near
future.</p>

<p>SaÄower (<hi rend="italic">Carthamus tinctorius</hi>) is grown
in dry, northern portions of the Great Plains.
The area under saÄower ranged from 20,000
to 85,000 acres between 1991 and 1997. Most
saÄower is grown for the vegetable oil market.
Worldwide, Japan is the principal importer.
Enhanced promotion of traditional safflower
oil, which contains a relatively high level
of polyunsaturated fatty acids compared to
many other vegetable oils, could increase market
demand for saÄower oil. High-oleic safflower
also is being grown.</p>

<p>Sunflower (<hi rend="italic">Helianthus annuus</hi>) was grown
on almost 3.5 million acres of the Great Plains
in 1997, primarily in North and South Dakota.
Sunflower acreage is expanding, particularly
in eastern Colorado and western Kansas. Most
of the sunflower is grown for the vegetable oil
market. About 20 percent of the sunflower
crop is a nonoil type that is eaten as a snack
food or sold in the bird food market. Traditional
sunflower oil is high in linoleic acid. It
is used as a cooking oil, in salad oil, and in the
manufacture of margarine. High-oleic sunflower
has been developed as a high-value,
premium cooking oil. The NuSun sunflower
produces an oil with moderate levels of oleic
acid and low levels of saturated fats.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">AGRICULTURE</hi>: <ref n="egp.ag.017">Canola</ref>; <ref n="egp.ag.041">Flax</ref>; <ref n="egp.ag.066">Sunflowers</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Patrick M. Carr<lb/>
North Dakota State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Carter, Jack F. "Potential of Flaxseed and Flaxseed Oil in
Baked Goods and Other Products in Human Nutrition."
<title level="j">Cereal Foods World</title> 38 (1993): 753–59.</bibl> <bibl>Van Dyne, Donald
L., Melvin G. Blase, and Kenneth D. Carlson. <title level="m">Industrial Feedstocks and Products from High Erucic Acid Oil: Crambe and Industrial Rapeseed</title>. Columbia: University of Missouri
Press, 1990.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>