<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ha.012">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main"><hi rend="italic">Empresarios</hi></title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>John Kelly Robison</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ha.012</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Robison, John Kelly">John Kelly Robison</author>. <title level="a">"<hi rend="italic">Empresarios</hi>."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">355-356</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-25</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main"><hi rend="italic">EMPRESARIOS</hi></head>

<p>From its independence from Spain until it lost
Texas to revolt, Mexico enlisted the aid of <hi rend="italic">empresarios</hi>
to recruit colonists to its sparsely settled
province of Texas. The Mexican Colonization
Law of August 18, 1824, provided general
guidelines for the settlement of remote corners
of the new republic and required the individual
states to pass their own laws, which
the state of Coahuila y Texas did on March 24,
1825. Although the national colonization law
gave preference to Mexican citizens, the Colonization
Law of Coahuila y Texas invited foreigners
to that territory. Individuals could and
did migrate to Texas, mostly from the United
States, but because of the language barrier
and the difficulties in acquiring land through
the Mexican bureaucracy, most colonists obtained
land in Texas through the offices of the
empresarios.</p>

<p>Empresarios were contractors empowered
by the government of Coahuila y Texas to recruit
specific numbers of families to the territory.
Mexican citizens were preferred as empresarios
and as colonists, but the majority of
the empresarios were from the United States.
The empresario received a grant of land on
which to settle the colonists he recruited,
though he did not, in fact, own this land. It
was the empresario's responsibility to survey
the land and then issue title to that land. The
empresario grants extended northwestward
from the Gulf Coast Plain of Texas across the
Balcones Escarpment and well into the Great
Plains. Most empresarios agreed to recruit 100
families within a six-year span. They also
served as immigration agents, determining
the moral character of those who wished to
enter their colony. The empresarios received
no pay or compensation for their endeavors
up front. When they had settled at least 100
families within their colonial grant, thus fulfilling
their contract, they acquired land of
their own. For every 100 families an empresario
recruited and settled within Texas, the
state gave him five <hi rend="italic">sitios</hi> (22,140 acres) of pastureland
and five <hi rend="italic">labors</hi> (885 acres) of farmland.
An empresario could receive compensation
in land for settling up to 800 families,
making him a very wealthy man.</p>

<p>The only empresario who received compensation
for so many recruited families was
Stephen F. Austin. By far the most successful
of the empresarios in terms of numbers of
colonists settled, Austin put into action the
plans of colonization conceived by his father,
Moses Austin. Between 1823, when he recruited
300 families under the old Spanish Imperial
Colonization Law and his final colonization
contract, Austin settled more than
1,500 families in an area extending from the
Texas Hill Country, at the edge of the Plains,
to the Gulf of Mexico. No other empresario
was able to recruit and settle even one-quarter
of this number. Green DeWitt received a contract
for 400 families but granted land titles to
only 166 families. Some empresarios, such as
Dr. John G. Purnell and Benjamin Drake
Lovell, were never able to fulfill their contracts.
By 1832 the empresarios had signed almost
thirty contracts calling for the settlement
of more than 10,000 families. But the
government of Coahuila y Texas, growing suspicious
of increasing Anglo-American influence
in Texas, ceased issuing grants after 1832
and finally closed the land offices in November
of 1835. The era of the empresarios, the
colonizing agents of Texas, came to an end.</p>

<closer>
<signed>John Kelly Robison<lb/>
Martin Luther University Halle-Wittenberg</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Fehrenbach, Theodore R. <title level="m">Lone Star: A History of Texas and the Texans</title>. New York: Colliers Books, 1968.</bibl> <bibl>Haley, James
L. <title level="m">Texas: An Album of History</title>. Garden City <hi rend="smallcaps">NY</hi>: Doubleday
and Co., 1985.</bibl> <bibl>Richardson, Rupert Norval, Ernest Wallace,
and Adrian Anderson. <title level="m">Texas: The Lone Star State</title>. Englewood
Cliffs <hi rend="smallcaps">NJ</hi>: Prentice-Hall, 1981.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>