<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.pd.031 SYSTEM "egp.pd.031.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.pd.031">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Ku Klux Klan</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Michael W. Schuyler</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.pd.031</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Schuyler, Michael W.">Michael W. Schuyler</author>. <title level="a">"Ku Klux Klan."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">715</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-06</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">KU KLUX KLAN</head>

<figure n="egp.pd.031" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Ku Klux Klan, probably in Denver, Colorado, between 1921 and 1930</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>There are three separate and distinct periods
of the Ku Klux Klan's history in the United
States. The first Klan, founded at Pulaski, Tennessee,
in 1865, did not have much of a presence
in the Great Plains. Although it began as
a local social club with secret rituals and costumes
that usually featured flowing robes,
pointed hats, and masks, the Klan spread
quickly throughout the South with the promise
that it would defend the Constitution and
help the weak and oppressed. However, the
Klan resorted to terror and extreme violence
when blacks were given civil and voting rights.
In 1877, when Reconstruction came to an end,
the Klan officially disbanded.</p>

<p>The second Klan, founded in 1915 by William
Joseph Simmons at Stone Mountain, Georgia,
had a greater impact in the Plains. Simmons
emphasized that the Klan was a fraternal charitable
organization that supported white supremacy.
The Klan grew rapidly after 1919, when
it launched a national campaign to attract members.
It was especially strong in urban areas, and
by the mid-1920s it was organized in every state.
Nationally the Klan claimed 10 million members
by 1924, but recent scholars estimate that
the membership was closer to two million. It is
estimated that between 1915 and 1944, Klan
membership in the Plains states made up
20 percent of the Klan's total membership.
During this period, Klan membership was
strongest in Texas (190,000) and Oklahoma
(95,000), and declined northward through
Colorado (45,000), Kansas (40,000), Nebraska
(25,000), South Dakota (5,000), and North
Dakota (3,000). The Klan was also strong in
Alberta and Saskatchewan during the 1920s,
drawing support for its anti-Catholic and anti-immigrant
positions.</p>

<p>The Klan grew rapidly between 1921 and
1925 because it was able to exploit the fears
and anxieties of post–World War I America.
The Klan's promise to preserve traditional
values and morals gave people a sense of
power, fraternity, and security. Although the
Klan still used antiblack rhetoric, especially in
the Southern Plains, the Klan's primary message
in the 1920s was that it stood for law and
order, traditional morality, and most important,
"100 percent Americanism." It was successful
because it tailored its appeal in every
community to respond to local issues and
concerns. The Klan's appeal to "100 percent
Americanism" allowed local Klans to target
any group&#8211;blacks, Jews, radicals, immigrants,
Mexicans, and especially Catholics.</p>

<p>The Klan used moral suasion, political influence,
social pressure, and violence to accomplish
its objectives. In the Northern Plains
the Klan was rarely involved in acts of violence,
and, while it influenced some local elections,
it had a negligible impact on the political process.
In Texas and Oklahoma, however, the
Klan was involved in widespread public whippings,
tar and featherings, lynchings, and brutal
homicides. In Texas and Oklahoma alone
there were as many as 1,000 victims of Klan
violence. In Dallas the Klan was credited with
sixty-eight floggings in 1922; in Oklahoma
there was near civil war in 1923 when Gov.
John C. Walton declared marshal law in an
effort to control Klan violence. In Texas, Oklahoma,
and Kansas the Klan was a major political
force, and many Klansmen were elected to
local, state, and national offices.</p>

<p>In Texas in the early 1920s the Klan controlled
the lower house of the Texas legislature
and elected Klansman Earl B. Mayfield to
serve in the U.S. Senate. In 1924 in Kansas,
William Allen White, the editor of the <title level="j">Emporia
Gazette</title>, gained national attention when
he ran for governor in an attempt to resist the
Klan's efforts to control the Republican Party.</p>

<p>Klan membership declined rapidly after
1925. Escalating violence, organized opposition,
and corruption within the Klan organization,
as well as the conviction of one the
Klan's most important leaders for rape and
murder, robbed the Klan of its claim to moral
leadership. By the end of the 1930s the Klan
was increasingly viewed as un-American. In
1944, when the government sued the Klan for
back taxes, it disbanded.</p>

<p>The Klan revived after World War II to
resist the civil rights movement. Lacking a
national organizational structure, the Klan
quickly split into a number of small, violent
factions. It was involved in numerous bombings
and murders in the South, particularly
during the 1960s, but the Klan's nationwide
membership numbered only in the tens of
thousands. The Klan's violent, un-American
reputation limited its appeal in the Plains.
Still, by the early 1990s Klanwatch, a project of
the Southern Poverty Law Center, reported
that although Klan membership nationally
had fallen to only 5,000, violent hate crimes
were rapidly increasing and that small Klan
units were again active in Colorado, Nebraska,
Kansas, Oklahoma, and Texas.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Michael W. Schuyler<lb/>
University of Nebraska at Kearney</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Chalmers, David. <title level="m">Hooded Americanism: The History of the
Ku Klux Klan</title>. New York: New Viewpoints, 1981.</bibl> <bibl>Jackson,
Kenneth T. <title level="m">The Ku Klux Klan in the City, 1915–1930</title>.
New York: Oxford University Press, 1967.</bibl> <bibl>Lay, Shawn. <title level="m">The
Invisible Empire in the West: Toward a New Appraisal of the
Ku Klux Klan of the 1920s</title>. Chicago: University of Illinois
Press, 1992.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>