<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.pd.030">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Junta de Iindignaci&#243;n</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Phillip B. Gonzales</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.pd.030</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Gonzales, Phillip B.">Phillip B. Gonzales</author>. <title level="a">"Junta de Iindignaci&#243;n."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">714-715</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-06</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">JUNTA DE IINDIGNACI&#211;N</head>

<p>While the native Hispanos formed the majority
of the population throughout New Mexico's territorial
period and into the early statehood years
after 1912, they were nevertheless subject to the
powerful forces of Americanization. As Anglo-American
and foreign settlers prepared New
Mexico for full incorporation into the United
States, considerable ethnic conflict arose. Seeing
many threats to their social and cultural interests,
Hispanos responded with ethnic protest.
By the turn of the twentieth century, a distinct
tradition of Hispano collective resistance
emerged. Some of the most significant Hispano
protest took place within the vast region that the
Spanish <hi rend="italic">pobladores</hi> (yeoman settlers) first called
<hi rend="italic">las vegas grandes</hi> (the great meadows) and <hi rend="italic">el
llano estacado</hi> (the Staked Plains), which extended
from the Rockies onto the western fringe
of the Great Plains. Anglo newcomers came
upon Hispanos who were already settled in the
Plains counties of San Miguel, Mora, Colfax,
Union, and Guadalupe.</p>

<p>A major form of protest innovated by Hispanos
living in the Plains was <hi rend="italic">la junta de indignaci&#243;n</hi>
(mass meeting of indignation). In the
typical junta de indignaci&#243;n, a spontaneous
demonstration was organized to deal with an
issue suddenly affecting the Hispanos as an
ethnic group. One of the biggest and most
significant of such juntas took place in Las
Vegas in 1901 in response to a Methodist missionary
who disparaged in a local newspaper
column the "pagan" religious customs of the
Hispano folk. A crowd of 600 Hispanos rallied
to refute the missionary's alleged "lies" and
"calumnies." Typical of the Hispano junta de
indignacion, a round of speakers denounced
the offender in harsh and sarcastic terms. Also
typical of this protest genre, the leaders appointed
a committee and charged it with
crafting resolutions to be published in the
press calling for Anglos to cease their racial
prejudices.</p>

<p>Hispano ranchers in the Plains also applied
la junta de indignacion in efforts to keep legal
possession of communal lands. On the important
Las Vegas Land Grant, for example, a
"people's" movement, consisting of hastily
convened meetings, formed in response to the
actions of a group of elite townsmen who attempted
to gain control of the grant. In this
case, juntas de indignaci&#243;n intertwined with
dramatic court cases and local elections.</p>

<p>Statewide juntas also erupted in 1933 when
a psychology professor at the University of
New Mexico disseminated negative stereotypes
of Hispanos in his racial attitude scale.
Protests erupted in the two Plains communities
of Springer and Taylor Springs in Colfax
County. Both involved the rituals of indignant
speakers and a petition calling on the governor to fire the professor whose "slanders" insulted
the Hispano people.</p>

<p>As a collective repertoire, la junta de indignaci&#243;n
enabled Hispanos to forge a homeland
ethnic identity. It served as a means for
giving notice that they would not tolerate the
denial of rights in the land that their ancestors
had settled. The classic turn-of-thecentury
junta de indignaci&#243;n went out of style
in the mid-1930s as the Great Depression and
the New Deal caused significant changes in
New Mexico's structure of political and civic
engagement.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">HISPANIC AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ha.021">Hispano Homeland</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Phillip B. Gonzales<lb/>
University of New Mexico</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Arellano, Anselmo F. "People Versus Trustees: Protest Activity
on the Las Vegas Land Grant." In <title level="m">Las Vegas Grandes
on the Gallinas, 1835–1985</title>, edited by Anselmo F. Arellano
and Juli&#225;n Josu&#233; Vigil. Las Vegas <hi rend="smallcaps">NM</hi>: Editorial Telera&#241;a,
1985: 66–74.</bibl> <bibl>Gonzales, Phillip B. <title level="m">Forced Sacrifice as Ethnic
Protest: The Hispano Cause in New Mexico and the Racial
Attitude Confrontation of 1933</title>. New York: Peter Lang Publishing,
2001.</bibl> <bibl>Gonzales, Phillip B. "La Junta de Indignaci&#243;n:
Hispano Repertoire of Collective Protest in New
Mexico, 1884–1933." <title level="j">Western Historical Quarterly</title> 31 (2000):
161–86.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>