<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ha.031">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main"><hi rend="italic">Pastores</hi></title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Eileen Johnson</author>
<author>J. Kent Hicks</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ha.031</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Johnson, Eileen">Eileen Johnson</author> and <author n="Hicks, J. Kent">J. Kent Hicks</author>. <title level="a">"<hi rend="italic">Pastores</hi>."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">363-364</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-02</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main"><hi rend="italic">PASTORES</hi></head>

<p>The <hi rend="italic">pastores</hi> are a little-known Hispanic sheepherding
group whose homeland was the grasslands
of north-central New Mexico (<hi rend="italic">Quechero</hi>,
or Mescalero Plains). Established there by at
least the early nineteenth century, the pastores
practiced a transhumance lifestyle with their
flocks. The long circuits made in search of
pasturage and water for the flocks took males
away from their homes for extended periods.
For these sheepherders, material possessions
were basic and sparse as they traveled hundreds
of miles with their sheep. Economically,
the pastores were part of either the <hi rend="italic">partido</hi>
system of herd management or a family business
that owned and managed the flock. The
New Mexico partido system, adapted from
that of Spain, was a means of lending capital at
interest that allowed a sheepherder to build up
his own flock, thereby moving to the family
business system.</p>

<p>A burgeoning sheep industry necessitated
new, open rangelands that were safe from
raids by Native peoples. Despite risks, pastores
began their incursion into the upper Canadian
River valley of eastern New Mexico by
1849 and the Canadian River valley of the
Texas Panhandle in the 1860s. In the middle
1870s, with the removal of the Native peoples
and near extermination of the bison herds on
which they depended, the vast grasslands
of the Texas Panhandle and Southern High
Plains became open territory. The value of this
area was realized quickly by the pastores as
they moved their flocks into the region. Part
of a longer circuit bringing the flocks back
to New Mexico, family settlements soon lined
the Canadian River valley and its tributaries
in the Texas Panhandle. By 1880, 340 pastores
were in that area. The pastores established
small settlements in previously used summer
grazing pastures with the intention of remaining
in the area on a year-round basis. Known
as <hi rend="italic">plazas</hi>, the largest one (founded by Casimero
Romero in 1876) became the town of
Tascosa. The Canadian and Red River drainage
systems were the primary routes for circuits
and settlements.</p>

<p>Pastores sites have been identified in archeological
surveys along the middle Pecos
River near Santa Rosa, New Mexico, and the
Canadian River valley in the Texas Panhandle.
Rock corrals were common among a small
variety of site types. Rock corrals, used by pastores,
have been found in the eastern canyon
lands of the Rolling Plains and within the
drainages and on the uplands of the Southern
High Plains.</p>

<p>The pastores fashioned a distinctive architecture
and favored specific topographic and
environmental settings. Corrals, built for shelter
and protection, were located where abundant
pasture and surface water coexisted. The
locally available rock used in construction also
influenced structure placement. Corrals, built
of local materials and without mortar, were of
variable size and were square, rectangular, or
oval. Rocks were stacked with the larger ones
near the bottom and smaller ones on top, and
the walls were not faced. The corrals constructed
in the various areas were substantial
and took time and effort. The majority were
single-space enclosures, although partitioned
corrals have also been identified. Machine-cut
square iron nails (manufactured between 1860
and 1884) have been commonly found within
and around the corrals. The settlements made
efficient use of available resources within a localized
area while providing a safe haven within
a controlled pasturage for people and sheep.</p>

<p>Anglo-American cattle ranchers also recognized
the value of the vast grasslands, which
they used first as open range and then, by 1881,
controlled with land titles and barbed-wire
fencing. Restrictions on free range, several
harsh winters, and a general atmosphere of
distrust and dislike between the sheepherders
and cattlemen led to a rapid decline of pastores
settlements in the region. By 1887 all the
plazas were abandoned and most pastores had
returned to New Mexico.</p>

<p>During their short tenure on the western
Texas Plains, the pastores were always in
transition&#8211;from seasonal use to permanent
settlement to withdrawal from the region.
Abandonment was not only quick but also
unexpected, brought about by changes over
which the pastores had no control. Their influence
on the regional culture is neither fully
understood nor appreciated. Nevertheless, the
pastores' brief presence left its mark on the
landscape of the region and influenced early
settlement patterns. Plazas became town sites
and corrals and camps provided an infrastructure
for European American reuse and
settlement of the region.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Eileen Johnson<lb/>
J. Kent Hicks<lb/>
University of Nebraska at Kearney</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Archambeau, Ernest R. "Spanish Sheepmen on the Canadian
at Old Tascosa." <title level="j">Panhandle-Plains Historical Review</title>
19 (1946): 45–72, 96.</bibl> <bibl>Hicks, J. Kent, and Eileen Johnson.
"Pastores Presence on the Southern High Plains of Texas."
<title level="j">Historical Archaeology</title> 34 (2000): 46–60.</bibl> <bibl>Rathjen, Frederick
W. <title level="m">The Texas Panhandle Frontier</title>. Austin: University of
Texas Press, 1973.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>