<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.lt.064">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Publishing Houses</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Stephen F. Cox</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.lt.064</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Cox, Stephen F.">Stephen F. Cox</author>. <title level="a">"Publishing Houses."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">491</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-24</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">PUBLISHING HOUSES</head>

<p>Lacking the population to sustain commercial
publishing, the Great Plains has been, in book
publishing, largely the domain of university
presses, notably those at Oklahoma, Nebraska,
and Kansas.</p>

<p>The first influential book publisher in the
Great Plains was Haldeman-Julius of Girard,
Kansas, publishers of the Little Blue Books.
Between 1918 and 1928 Haldeman-Julius published
some 2,000 titles, each priced at five
cents a copy and sixty-four pages in length, on
every imaginable topic, from abridgments of
classics of philosophy to religion to politics to
sex, and sold 100 million books worldwide.
With a distinct skeptical and socialist bent,
Haldeman-Julius fed an enormous hunger&#8211;
and market&#8211;for intellectual stimulation
among newly literate classes of Americans.</p>

<p>The Little Blue Books were not primarily
literary, and a relative dearth of literary publishing
has characterized the Great Plains ever
since. But a mission to cultivate a literate and
informed citizenry was evident in the program
of the next significant publisher to arise
on the Plains, the University of Oklahoma
Press, founded in 1928.</p>

<p>At first the Oklahoma list showed a fondness
for the common person and the common
voice&#8211;the journal <title level="j">Folk Say</title> (1929) and the
longtime bestseller, E. H. Faulkner's <title level="m">Plowman's Folly</title> (1943), come to mind—and at the
same time a commitment to making Greek
and Latin classics readily available. The list reflected
the tastes of the press's second director
(from the mid-1930s until the late 1960s), Savoie
Lottinville, a Rhodes scholar, classicist,
and committed Oklahoman with a vision of
greatness, and the hard work of his editor,
Mary Stith. Oklahoma made its most lasting
contribution by publishing books of scholarly
rigor about the people of the Western Hemisphere,
notably in the Civilization of the
American Indian series, which between 1932
and 1997 had extended to 225 titles. Like
Haldeman-Julius, the early University of Oklahoma
Press had its own printing plant. Under
the motto "Books Worth Keeping," however,
Oklahoma went Haldeman-Julius one better,
using its plant to produce prize-winning design
and high-quality letterpress printing in
hard bindings.</p>

<p>It was by capitalizing on new trends in printing
and binding that the University of Nebraska
Press challenged Oklahoma. In many
ways, Nebraska followed Oklahoma's road to
success. Oklahoma published histories of the
surrounding states. So did Nebraska. Oklahoma
reprinted classics of the western frontier
and of Native American cultures. So did Nebraska,
sometimes reprinting the same public
domain books. However, while Oklahoma reprinted
regional books by typing fresh manuscripts
and reediting, redesigning, and retypesetting
them in hot lead, printing them letterpress,
and publishing them in cloth bindings,
Nebraska took advantage of the rising quality
of photo-offset printing technology to publish
paperbacks.</p>

<p>The University of Nebraska Press had been
founded in 1941, but it was only in 1959, when
its editor, Virginia Faulkner, and its hardworking
director, Bruce Nicoll, established
Bison Books (the first university press quality
paperback imprint in the United States), that
Nebraska rose to prominence. Today it offers a
dynamic list in several areas of scholarship.
Nebraska has built a substantial list in Native
studies and western history, translations of
European literature, creative nonfiction, and
sports history.</p>

<p>The third university press to rise to prominence
on the U.S. Great Plains, the University
Press of Kansas, was founded in 1946 and
came into its own in the late 1980s. The press's
director, Fred Woodward, its longtime editor,
Kate Torrey, and its marketing head, Susan
Schott, learned from their predecessors and
achieved success by following a specialized editorial
program in a very business-like manner.
Alone among the three, Kansas publishes
books strictly about the United States, including
series on the American presidency and
natural resource policy. As its name suggests,
the University Press of Kansas is supported by
a consortium of state campuses.</p>

<p>These three presses, hosted by universities,
have focused on scholarship, not on contemporary
literature. Literary publishing in the
Great Plains has been the domain of several
small university presses in Texas; trade houses
such as the Swallow Press, originally in Denver;
small presses like Frank Parman's Point
Riders Press in Norman, Oklahoma, and Ted
Kooser's Windflower Press in Lincoln, Nebraska;
and a few fine printers like the Abattoir
Press at the University of Nebraska at
Omaha. Among textbook publishers on the
Plains are branches of Harcourt Brace and
Holt, Rinehart, and Winston in Texas and, until
1998, when it relocated to Indianapolis,
Cliff's Notes.</p>

<p>Canadian Plains publishers include presses
at the Universities of Alberta, Calgary, and
Manitoba and the Canadian Plains Research
Center at the University of Regina. Fifth House
in Saskatoon, Coteau in Regina, and NeWest
and Hurtig in Edmonton are influential regional
presses, while Winnipeg's Pemmican is
one of the oldest and best established Native
presses in North America, producing books by
Native authors and reaching a wide Native audience
in Canada.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">EDUCATION</hi>: <ref n="egp.edu.013">Cliffs Notes</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Stephen F. Cox<lb/>
University of Arizona Press</signed>
</closer>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>