<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fil.042">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Loy, Myrna (1905-1993)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>David J. Wishart</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fil.042</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</author>. <title level="a">"Loy, Myrna (1905-1993)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">272</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-12</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">LOY, MYRNA (1905-1993)</head>
<figure n="egp.fil.042" rend="granted" type="noclick">
<figDesc>Manhattan Melodrama film poster (1934)</figDesc>
</figure>    

<p>Myrna Loy, Hollywood's top female box office
attraction in the mid-1930s, was born on August
2, 1905, on a sheep and wheat ranch near
Raidersburg, Montana, where the Rocky
Mountains meet the Great Plains. She grew up
in nearby Helena in comfortable circumstances,
just up the street from another future
Hollywood star, Gary Cooper. Her father was
a member of the Montana legislature, and
early on Myrna developed her own strong political
conscience. When her father died in the
1918 flu epidemic, her mother moved the family
to Los Angeles, settling in Culver City, near
Hollywood.</p>

<p>Long interested in theater and dance, Myrna
started doing screen tests when she was eighteen.
She landed bit roles in <title>The Ten Commandments</title>
(1923) and <title>Ben Hur</title> (1925) before
being typecast as a mysterious vamp in numerous
films over the next ten years. Her casting
opposite William Powell in <title>Manhattan Melodrama</title> in 1934 shattered this stereotype,
and in subsequent films, thirteen of them with
Powell, she reinvented herself as a witty and
beautiful heroine, the model of the "perfect
wife." The public loved the image, and in
1936 she was crowned "Queen of the Movies"
in a poll, alongside the anointed "King," Clark
Gable.</p>

<p>During World War II Loy put her film career
on hold and channeled her energies into
the Red Cross. She continued her political activism
after the war as U.S. representative to
unesco and as campaigner for John F. Kennedy
and Eugene McCarthy in their runs for
the presidency. She continued to find time for
movies, most notably, <title>The Best Years of Our Lives</title> (1946).</p>

<p>Loy was never nominated for an Oscar, but
at the 1991 ceremony she was presented with
an honorary Academy Award. That same year
the Myrna Loy Center opened in Helena with
a mission to bring the arts to the citizens of
Montana. Myrna Loy died in New York on
December 14, 1993.</p>

<closer>
<signed>David J. Wishart<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Kotsilibas-Davis, James, and Myrna Loy. <title level="m">Myrna Loy: Being and Becoming</title>. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1987.</bibl> <bibl>Thompson,
Frank. "Loy, Myrna." In <title level="m">International Dictionary of Films and Filmmakers</title>, edited by Nicholas Thomas. Chicago:
St. James Press, 1990: 3: 203–6.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>