<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.na.087">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Plenty Coups (1848-1932)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>C. Adran Heidenreich</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.na.087</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Heidenreich, C. Adran">C. Adran Heidenreich</author>. <title level="a">"Plenty Coups (1848-1932)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">593</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-15</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">PLENTY COUPS (1848-1932)</head>
 <figure n="egp.na.087" rend="granted" type="noclick">
<figDesc>Photograph of Crow leader Plenty Coups, taken by Edward Curtis</figDesc>
</figure>
    
<p>Plenty Coups (<hi rend="italic">Alaxchiiaahush</hi>, or Aleck chea
ahoos) was a Crow warrior, diplomat, and mediator.
He was born in 1848 at "the cliff that
has no pass" in present Billings, Montana.
Also known as Bull Who Goes Into (Against)
the Wind, he was a Mountain Crow. His parents
died when he was about ten years old.
Orphaned and in grief, he was encouraged by
camp criers to go on vision quests. He was
adopted by the Little People and guided by
eagles, who became his guardians. In a vision
in the Crazy Mountains he saw the buffalo
disappear and be replaced by cattle, a windstorm
destroy all trees except the one in which
the chickadee lived, and himself as an old man
sitting by a house.</p>

<p>By his mid-twenties Plenty Coups had accomplished
each of four war deeds to achieve
the distinction of chieftain, or "good man."
He carried a Medicine Pipe and Pipe Holder's
bag as a leader of the Fox Warrior Society. One
of many Crows who scouted for the U.S. military,
he was a leader in the Battle of the Rosebud
on June 17, 1876. Years later he stated
his reason for aiding the Americans: "[W]e
plainly saw that this course was the only one
which might save our beautiful country for
us." In 1880 he traveled with five other Crow
leaders to Washington <hi rend="smallcaps">DC</hi>. The main purpose
was to negotiate the sale of the western part of
the reservation and a Northern Pacific Railroad
right-of-way up the Yellowstone Valley.
At George Washington's home, he pondered
the difficulties of his "small nation." Inspired
by the visit, he later willed land in 1928 to be
used as a park, recreation ground, and display
of his possessions as "a reminder to Indians
and white people alike that the two races
should live and work together harmoniously."
His house, a Montana state park, is a National
Historic Landmark.</p>

<p>By 1890 Plenty Coups and Pretty Eagle were
recognized as head chiefs of the tribe. Plenty
Coups settled in Pryor Valley, on land he had
seen in his vision, where he farmed, raised
cattle and horses, and established a general
merchandise store. He was involved in "pan-
Indian" intertribal networks and fought the
continual pressure to sell Crow land. In preparation
for hearings on yet another bill for
opening and settlement of the reservation in
1917, Plenty Coups and other leaders held traditional
war ceremonies in a Washington dc
hotel room, including burning buffalo chips
and offering songs and prayers. He promoted
Crow Fair and also led parades at regional
fairs. He encouraged Crow support of U.S.
efforts during World War I. Chosen to be the
representative of all Indians and called "Chief
of All Chiefs" for dedication of the Tomb of
the Unknown Soldier at Arlington National
Cemetery in 1921, he placed his war bonnet
and coup stick before the casket; they are on
display there today.</p>

<p>Following the example of the chickadee to
be observant and learn from others, Plenty
Coups lived according to his own Crow values
and also accommodated non-Indian culture.
He practiced traditional Crow religion, including
the vision quest, sweat lodge, and Sacred
Tobacco Society. He was baptized into the
Catholic Church at St. Xavier on the Crow
Indian Reservation. He was married several
times, but his two children died young, so he
and his wives adopted and raised other children.
He considered all the Crows as his "children."
He understood that education is important
and donated part of his land for a school.
His most famous statement was "Education is
your most powerful weapon. With education
you are the white man's equal; without education
you are his victim." Plenty Coups passed
to the "Other Side Camp" on March 4, 1932, at
age eighty-four. Funeral services were held according
to both Catholic and traditional Crow
customs, including proclamation in the Crow
language of his deeds. The tribe voted to honor
him as their last traditional chief.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">SPORTS AND RECREATION</hi>: <ref n="egp.sr.012">Crow Fair</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>C. Adrian Heidenreich</signed>
Montana State University-Billings</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Hoxie, Frederick E. <title level="m">Parading through History: The Making
of the Crow Nation in America, 1805–1935</title>. New York: Cambridge
University Press, 1995.</bibl> <bibl>Linderman, Frank B. <title level="m">Plenty-
Coups, Chief of the Crows</title>. 1930. Lincoln: University of
Nebraska Press, 1962.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>