<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.art.034 SYSTEM "egp.art.034.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.art.034">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Howe, Oscar (1915-1983)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>John A. Day</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.art.034</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Day, John A.">John A. Day</author>. <title level="a">"Howe, Oscar (1915-1983)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">120-121</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-22</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">HOWE, OSCAR (1915-1983)</head>

<figure n="egp.art.034" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Oscar Howe in his studio at the University of South</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Internationally acclaimed Yanktonai Nakota
painter Oscar Howe was a major force in the
evolution of the Native American fine arts
movement. In the 1950s and 1960s Howe led
his generation in the transition from the
highly prescribed Studio style to greater personal
expression and active engagement with
mainstream modern art.</p>

<p>Oscar Howe was born on May 13, 1915, at
Joe Creek on the Crow Creek Reservation
in South Dakota. His Indian name, Mazuha
Hokshina, translates as Trader Boy, which
proved particularly appropriate given his lifelong
commitment to bridging Native American
and European American cultures. Howe
came from a distinguished Yanktonai family
that included hereditary chiefs and noted orators.
At age seven Howe was sent to the Pierre
Indian School, which was administered by the
Bureau of Indian Affairs on a military model
that actively promoted assimilation. Serious
health problems interrupted Howe's education,
but he subsequently graduated from the
school in 1933. Howe enrolled in the Santa Fe
Indian School in New Mexico in 1935, two
years after Dorothy Dunn had established an
innovative art program known as the Studio.
Here he was one of a select group of young
artists to receive the training and encouragement
necessary to pursue careers in art. Howe
graduated in 1938 as salutatorian of his class.</p>

<p>Returning to South Dakota, Howe taught
art at the Pierre Indian School until 1940,
when he joined the <hi rend="smallcaps">WPA</hi> South Dakota Artist
Project, illustrating several books and painting
murals in Mitchell and Mobridge. In 1942 he
was drafted into the U.S. Army and served for
three and a half years with combat forces in
Europe. Honorably discharged in 1945, Howe
returned to his art and in 1947 won the grand
prize at the second annual National Indian
Painting Competition at the Philbrook Museum
of Art in Tulsa, Oklahoma. With the
prize of $350, he married Adelheid Hample,
whom he had met in Germany; their only
child, Inge Dawn, was born in 1949. Howe attended
Dakota Wesleyan University in Mitchell
on the gi Bill, receiving a bachelor of arts
degree in 1952. During this period, the artist
began designing the murals for Mitchell's
"world-famous" Corn Palace, a commission
he executed annually until 1971. Howe once
again returned to Pierre, South Dakota, between
1953 and 1957 and taught high school art.
He entered the master of fine arts program at
the University of Oklahoma, graduating in
1954. In 1957 Howe accepted a position as professor
and artist in residence at the University
of South Dakota in Vermillion, beginning a
distinguished twenty-five-year tenure at that
institution.</p>

<p>These were the artist's most productive
years, marked by over sixty solo exhibitions,
fifteen grand or first-place prizes, and numerous
awards. By this time, Howe had rejected
the last vestiges of the Studio style for
strong colors, pulsating space, dynamic movement,
and a high degree of abstraction. <title>Sioux Seed Player</title> (1974), a casein painting on paper,
is an excellent example of Howe's mature
style. Masterfully executed, the painting is intensely
pristine and compositionally complex,
but its most compelling feature is its dynamism.
Utilizing highly colorful flat shapes,
Howe created a fluid, ambivalent, and virtually
pulsating spatial illusion that is unique in
Native American art.</p>

<p>A signature event in Howe's life, often cited
as helping to change the direction of Native
American art, occurred in 1958. That year the
artist challenged the jurors at the Philbrook's
annual National Indian Painting Competition
after they assessed one of his more abstract
submissions as not Indian enough to qualify
for an award. In a justifiably famous letter,
Howe advanced the cause of personal expression,
with the result that a new experimental
category was added to future competitions&#8211;a
decision that was a powerful incentive to
younger artists.</p>

<p>During his life Howe was honored with the
Dorothy Field Award from the Denver Art
Museum (1952); the Mary Benjamin Award
from the Museum of New Mexico, Santa Fe
(1960); the Waite Phillips Trophy for Outstanding
Contributions to American Indian
Art from the Philbrook Museum of Art,
Tulsa (1966); the South Dakota Governor's
Award for Creative Achievement (1973); and
the Golden Bear Award from the University of
Oklahoma (1978).</p>

<p>Oscar Howe retired from the faculty of the
University of South Dakota in 1980 and was
recognized with a major retrospective exhibition
that toured nationally between 1981 and
1983. After a prolonged illness, he died on October
7, 1983. Throughout his life, Oscar Howe
demonstrated a strong connection with the
land of his forebears and passionately advanced
the creation of a Northern Plains style
of Native American fine arts. Today his aesthetic
leadership is widely acknowledged, and
his work is celebrated for its revolutionary impact
and its assertion of the creative vitality of
Native American art in contemporary culture.
Howe's achievements are memorialized with
major collections of his work in South Dakota
at the Oscar Howe Art Center in Mitchell, the
South Dakota Memorial Art Center in Brookings,
and the Oscar Howe Gallery and Archives
at the University Art Galleries in Vermillion,
South Dakota.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">IMAGES AND ICONS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ii.014">Corn Palace</ref>.</p>


<closer>
<signed>John A. Day<lb/>
University of South Dakota</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Dockstader, Frederick J., ed. <title level="m">Oscar Howe: A Retrospective Exhibition</title>. Tulsa: Thomas Gilcrease Museum Association,
1982.</bibl> <bibl>Howe, Oscar. <title level="m">Oscar Howe, Artist of the Sioux</title>. Vermillion
<hi rend="smallcaps">SD</hi>: Oscar Howe, 1974.</bibl> <bibl>White, Mark Andrew. "Oscar
Howe." <title level="j">American Indian Art Magazine</title> 23 (1997):
36–43.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>