<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fol.021">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Ghost Stories</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Duane Hutchinson</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2009</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fol.021</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2009</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2009 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Hutchinson, Duane">Duane Hutchinson</author>. <title level="a">"Ghost Stories."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">302</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-16</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">GHOST STORIES</head>

<p>Characteristic ghost stories of the Great Plains
may now be found in collections from Alberta
to Texas. This was not always so. People of the
Great Plains have traditionally evinced a wry
skepticism toward ghosts. Typical is Lisa Hefner,
a collector of ghost stories from Kansas.
When asked if she believed in ghosts, she responded
that she believed in stories. In Nebraska
an Omaha Indian expressed dislike for
the word "ghost." He said Native Americans
preferred to think of these encounters with
the dead as grandparents returning to give advice.
He said that many times his dead grandfather
had returned to guide him to a better
way. Nevertheless, everywhere in the Great
Plains ghosts are used to explain unexplained
sounds, sights, feelings, or movements.</p>

<p>A willingness to believe in ghosts can be
a disadvantage. For example, in a story called
"The Phantom Piccolo Player," historian Everett
Dick tells how one homesteader, haunted
nightly by the same melody and, eventually,
by gunshots, abandoned his homestead in Dakota
Territory. When he returned years later
he found the owner of his former claim whistling
the same haunting tune. Soon he learned
that his erstwhile haunter had been privy to
information about where the railroad was
to be built and had made a fortune on that
knowledge.</p>

<p>From collecting three volumes of ghost stories,
mostly from Nebraska and Iowa, storyteller
Duane Hutchinson identified several
characteristics of Plains ghosts: they seem unable
to think; they do not speak and, if approached,
they vanish; most often, they seem
to be carrying out some task that they repeat
mindlessly, trapped in some habitual action;
and in a few cases, they respond to shouts and
commands to go away and leave the living
alone. Furthermore, the costume the ghost
wears appears and vanishes with the apparition,
which raises the question: are overalls
immortal?</p>

<p>In the course of research that took three
and a half years, Debra Munn interviewed 137
people and scoured the records of historical
societies for evidence of Wyoming ghosts. The
ghost stories of Wyoming share attributes of
ghost stories everywhere&#8211;mysterious footsteps,
machines that malfunction, doors that
open and close, and rocking chairs that rock
with no one in them&#8211;but Wyoming ghost
stories are also place-specific. There is Dolly
Carson's haunted trailer (a common Wyoming
house type) in Cody, where her dead
husband and mother carry on the feud that
defined their living relationship; there is the
restaurant on the outskirts of Cheyenne where
weary travelers once sought refuge in a Plains
blizzard but could never find again; and there
is Fort Laramie, with its layers of history, perhaps
Wyoming's most haunted site. Of course,
some ghosts are purely imaginary: the door at
Fort Laramie that kept unlocking itself was
only a case of a lock responding to Wyoming's
temperature extremes.</p>

<p>In his collection of "eerie true tales" from
his native Oklahoma, David Farris documents
numerous sightings of <hi rend="smallcaps">UFO</hi>s, overgrown fish,
and strange beasts, as well as ghosts. Philanthropist
Thomas Gilcrease is said to still (forty
years after his death) walk the hallways of the
Gilcrease Museum, and a phantom hitchhiker&#8211;
a young boy&#8211;has been picked up on a
lonely stretch of Highway 20, just east of Clarence,
only to disappear mysteriously. Meanwhile,
in Ghost Hollow, near Cushing, the old
elm that once was a hanging tree glows luminously
when there is a full moon.</p>

<p>The farther south you go in the Plains, the
more the ghost stories take on a Mexican flavor.
This is evident from some of the titles
in Docia Schultz Williams's collections from
Texas: "The Ghost of San Pedro Playhouse,"
"Jose Navarro's Haunted Homestead," and
"Shadows of El Tropicana." The stories are
filled with historical and cultural details and
convey the essence of the Plains environment:
old army posts molder into the earth; night
breezes carry the fragrance of pi&#241;on and mesquite;
and for those willing to believe, ghosts
drift through the West Texas night.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">ART</hi>: <ref n="egp.art.025">Gilcrease, Thomas</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Duane Hutchinson<lb/>
Lincoln, Nebraska</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Farris, David A. <title level="m">Mysterious Oklahoma: Eerie True Tales from the Sooner State</title>. Edmond <hi rend="smallcaps">OK</hi>: Little Bruce, 1995.</bibl>
<bibl>Hutchinson, Duane. <title level="m">A Storyteller's Ghost Stories</title>. Lincoln
<hi rend="smallcaps">NE</hi>: Foundation Books, 1989, 1990, 1992.</bibl> <bibl>Munn, Debra D.
<title level="m">Ghosts on the Range: Eerie True Tales of Wyoming</title>. Boulder
<hi rend="smallcaps">CO</hi>: Pruett Publishing, 1989.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>