<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.ind.020 SYSTEM "egp.ind.020.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ind.020">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Feedlots</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Terry J. Klopfenstein</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ind.020</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Klopfenstein, Terry J.">Terry J. Klopfenstein</author>. <title level="a">"Feedlots."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">418</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-02</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">FEEDLOTS</head>

<figure n="egp.ind.020" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Feedlot east of Dodge City, Kansas</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Grass, corn, and cattle are abundant in the
Great Plains. When corn production became
efficient, corn was fed to produce rapid and
efficient body weight gains in cattle. American
consumers developed a taste for "finished
beef," which has sufficient marbling to produce
the taste and juiciness we have become
accustomed to. Cattle feeding based on corn
first developed in the Corn Belt, and markets
were centered around Chicago. The Corn Belt
expanded into the Great Plains due to irrigation,
and sorghum was produced in drier
areas to substitute for corn in feedlot finishing
diets.</p>

<p>In the traditional Corn Belt, cattle were fed
in barns and paved feedlots. In the 1950s and
1960s, as the Corn Belt was expanding west, it
was established that the drier climate of the
Great Plains was appropriate for feeding cattle
without the expense of barns and completely
paved feedlots. Cattle feeding expanded rapidly
in the 1960s, and the majority of U.S. cattle
feeding now occurs in the Great Plains,
with southwestern Kansas a particularly notable
concentration. Similarly, Canadian cattle
feeding has also expanded in the Great Plains
area.</p>

<p>Today's feedlots range from farmer-feeders
to large custom feedlots. Farmer-feeders generally
produce most if not all of the corn and
forage fed to their cattle and typically own
most of the cattle. These feedlots may have
capacity for 1,000 to 10,000 cattle at one time.
Custom feedlots are generally larger, with
numbers up to 100,000 at one time. Cattle are
typically fed for customers who own the cattle.
The customer pays for the feed, health
supplies, and "yardage"&#8211;the cost of facilities,
equipment, labor, and so on. The custom
feedlot makes a profit by maintaining
customer cattle near capacity. The feedlot
must operate very efficiently to maintain the
customers.</p>

<p>Feedlots vary from simple facilities to sophisticated,
computer-operated feedlots with
veterinary and nutritionist consultants. Feed
is mixed and fed to the cattle two or three
times daily with feed trucks. Larger feedlots
have feed mills that operate with computers,
in some cases unattended by employees. The
feed trucks have electronic scales and in many
cases onboard computers that are used to record
the amount of feed allocated to each pen.
These records are then downloaded to the primary
computer for accurate recording and
billing to customers.</p>

<p>Health of the cattle is monitored daily by a
"cowboy crew." These individuals typically
ride a horse through each pen of cattle (usually
200 head). Sick animals are removed from
the pen and taken to a "hospital" area for
treatment and recovery. Innovative feedlots
now have mobile hospitals that move to the
cattle pens, where the cattle are treated. Most
common health problems are respiratory diseases;
however, few cattle become sick.</p>

<p>Feedlots typically employ one person for
each 1,000 cattle. Primary jobs are feeding and
health care, but maintenance and business
procedures are also important jobs. Cattle enter
feedlots at different ages and weights and
spend 100 to 200 days in the feedlot. This diversity
is necessary to provide a consistent supply
of cattle to consumers. Cattle require forty to
sixty bushels of grain while in the feedlot and
the equivalent of about one-third ton of hay. It
takes about one-half acre of cropland to produce
this much feed. Because of the forage
used for cows and growing of feedlot cattle,
only two to three pounds of corn are required
to produce a pound of finished animal. Typically,
feedlots have extensive runoff facilities to
ensure that no waste leaves the feedlot uncontrolled
to enter surface or groundwater. The
waste from the feedlot is returned to the cropland
as organic fertilizer. Cattle are typically
worth $700 to $900 each at market time. Most
feedlots market two and one-half times their
one-time capacity. Therefore, a 10,000-head-capacity
feedlot would have sales of $20 million
per year.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Terry J. Klopfenstein<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Albin, Robert C., and G. B. Thompson. <title level="m">Cattle Feeding: A Guide to Management</title>. Amarillo <hi rend="smallcaps">TX</hi>: Trofton Printing,
1996.</bibl> <bibl>Ball, Charles E. <title level="m">Building the Beef Industry</title>. Denver:
National Cattlemen's Foundation, 1998.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>