<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.mus.001">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Music</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Randall L. Snyder</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.mus.001</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Snyder, Randall L.">Randall L. Snyder</author>. <title level="a">"Music."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">529-533</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-31</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">MUSIC</head>

<p>The people of the Great Plains have created a
diverse spectrum of musical practices whose
initially autonomous forms have combined to
generate a wellspring of acculturative popular
music that is now heard throughout the
world. Native peoples have maintained a musical
life of great spirituality in spite of repression
and isolation. White settlers entering the
area evolved sturdy uses of European folk music
into a sophisticated tradition of American
art music, reflected in regional symphony and
opera companies as well as university music
programs. Evolving through gospel, blues,
and ragtime, African American musicians created
a distinct jazz style centered on the territory
bands. Many facets of African American
music were incorporated into rhythm and
blues and combined with western swing and
rockabilly to help define rock and roll. From
Woody Guthrie and Buddy Holly to Lawrence
Welk and Garth Brooks, from Jay McShann
and Ornette Coleman to Howard Hanson and
k. d. lang, musicians from the Great Plains
illustrate a diversity that is central to American
and Canadian life.</p>
</div1>

<div1>
<head type="sub">The First Musicians</head>

<p>The earliest music in the great swath of open
space dissecting the middle of North America
collectively known as the Great Plains has, like
the constant winds that scour the open land,
been lost to time. The Native peoples of the
Great Plains traditionally practiced a musical
culture that was rich in diversity yet unified by
important issues. Like many tribal societies,
especially those seminomadic ones with a
minimum of material possessions, the Plains
Indians developed much of their cultural expression
through music. Music and religion
were inseparable, and symbolic ritual maintenance
of natural law through ceremonial affirmation
played a central role in coordinating
tribal life. Prayers for divine intervention in
hunting and war, healing songs, and clerical
divinatory songs all connected the individual
with the supernatural.</p>

<p>Music was also used to regulate the more
mundane social needs of the community. The
rhythms of narrated songs that perpetuated
the history of the people, social singing and
dancing at feasts, love songs, boasting songs,
work songs, and lullabies, performed by all
members of the community, not just a professional
elite, filled the daily life of the group.
Another commonality the Native Plains peoples
shared with other Indigenous groups in
North America was the interconnection between
music and dance. Musicians moved
while singing, and dancers sang and played
(with anklets) while dancing. Though many
forms of musical expression were lost in the
turmoil of the European American incursion,
others have persisted and remain a vital part
of Native American life and of Great Plains
music.</p>

<p>Even more than other regions, the Native
American music from the Great Plains was
predominantly vocal. Men singing with an ecstatic
high register (falsetto) or the unison
singing of men and women was the most common
(singing in harmony was not practiced).
Loud, robust melodies appropriate to the open
spaces of the Plains tended to begin in the
upper register (in contrast with the European
folk song curve, which begins low before
reaching a high point near the end). Another
important characteristic of Plains singing was,
and is, the use of vocables, or "nonsense" syllables.
While considered a coded hermetic language
by some, most scholars believe nonlexical
sounds are used for their euphonious
sensuality. Often a song will begin with vocables,
giving way in the middle to a text section,
often sung by an individual. These lyrics may
be altered to fit changing conditions.</p>

<p>As to the question of authorship, the concept
of the "composer" is a much different one
from that found in European music. In Native
cosmologies, all songs are in existence; the individual
singer receives the song as a supernatural
gift. For example, through the vision
quest, the arduous process involving fasting
and other self-sacrifices, a song is granted as a
gift from the supernatural. Perhaps the most
famous result of such divine intervention
is the complex series of visions and songs bestowed
upon the Lakota chief Black Elk as
a boy:</p>

<lg>
<l>Then I looked up at the clouds and two</l>
<l>men were coming there, headfirst like arrows</l>
<l>slanting down; and as they came, they</l>
<l>sang a sacred song and the thunder was like</l>
<l>drumming. I will sing it for you. The song</l>
<l>and drumming were like this:</l>
</lg>
<lg>
<l>Behold, a sacred voice is calling you;</l>
<l>All over the sky a sacred voice is calling</l>
</lg>

<p>Another, less cosmic approach to composing
consisted of assembling a new song out of sections
of other tunes. Contrary to popular
opinion, improvisation holds a smaller role in
tribal music than is generally believed. While
individual songs may change when passed on
in the oral tradition from generation to generation,
the creative function of the individual is
secondary to the continuity of the community;
therefore, the songs are conducted within
careful structures. The misconception of
"primitive" music being primarily improvised
was perpetuated by the racist belief in the superiority
of notated (nonimprovised) European
art music.</p>

<p>Purely instrumental music not connected
with singing was uncommon in Native American
music. The most important instruments
are percussive. Drums, especially the collectively
played large tom-tom, are central
to Plains Indian music, and their cosmic significance
to the community can be compared
to the role of the gamelan in Javanese society
or the organ in European church music.
Smaller drums, rattles, and whistles are also
common. String instruments are virtually
nonexistent. Flutes were much less common
on the Plains than in the Pacific Northwest
and the Southwest.</p>

<p>The arrival of Spanish, French, and English
explorers, trappers, and settlers, beginning
with the Spanish in the 1500s, while influencing
Indian music, never led to the kind of acculturated
music found in Mexico or parts of
South America, where Indigenous elements
were more fully integrated into the new society.
Rather than blending in with the new
cultures, Native Americans remained separate,
and music in general tended to unify around a
kind of "Pan-Indian" style, much of which was
derived from the Plains style. Two important
instances of this during the nineteenth century
were the Ghost Dance and peyote songs. Begun
after 1880 in the Great Basin area of Nevada,
the Ghost Dance was an attempt to reverse the
recent tragic tide of history. In 1890 the U.S.
Congress cited the dance's popularity with
Plains warrior groups as an excuse to outlaw it.
Similarly, peyote songs, revolving around the
sacramental ingestion of peyote buds, which
contain the hallucinogen mescaline, originated
in Mexico and were introduced to the
Plains area by the Apaches. They remain an
important element in many Native societies
today.</p>

<p>Traditional Native American music today
has become dominated by the Plains style and
has witnessed a surge in popularity since the
1950s through powwows and the growth of
Indian-oriented recording companies such as
Canyon Records. While the purity and motives
of some of this music, with its obvious
appeal to a white, tourist, New Age audience,
may be deplored by some, authentic music
and ritual true to its ancient and sacred heritage
continues to be practiced, representing a
vital living tradition as well as an invaluable
link to the past.</p>

<p>Contemporary Indian blues, country, and
rock can also serve as a powerful vehicle for
social statement. The mixing of politics, music,
and poetry is particularly evident in the
work of John Trudell. Trudell was born in
Omaha, Nebraska, and grew up on the Santee
Sioux Reservation. He first came to prominence
as a national spokesman during the Indians
of All Tribes' occupation of Alcatraz in
1969. He was national chairman of the American
Indian Movement (<hi rend="smallcaps">AIM</hi>) from 1973 to
1979, a period of intense Indian activism. His
first album on a major label, <title><hi rend="smallcaps">AKA</hi> Graffiti Man</title>,
released in 1992, was highly acclaimed and featured
the work of the late Kiowa guitarist Jesse
Ed Davis.</p>
</div1>

<div1>
<head type="sub">O Pioneers</head>

<p>While often lacking the mystical element so
important for Native peoples, music for the
first European American settlers in the Great
Plains played an important functional role in
their daily lives. Music was used to cope with
an alien environment, alleviate a drab, lonely
existence, and perpetuate traditional cultures.
In its path from the rural to the urban tradition,
pioneer music was defined first and foremost
as entertainment, with the emphasis on
family singing and community dances. Folk
songs inherited from various ethnic backgrounds,
popular songs, and hymns (aided by
hymnals that contained only the words) constituted
the early repertoire. They were sung
and passed on by oral transmissions and provided the principal form of home entertainment.
Instruments, whether homemade jugs
and spoons or fiddles, guitars, banjos, and
Jew's harps, were present from the beginning.
Later, piano became the most important parlor
instrument, a symbol of "civilization" in
the Great American Desert. As villages began
to grow, organized dances evolved from family
jam sessions and became a focal point of
community life. Spurred on by the hornpipes
and reels of the fiddler, the vigorous dancing
provided an important emotional and physical
outlet. Similar to these dances were the
"play party games," featuring circle and line
dancing. In time, these amateur affairs turned
into barn dances, hops, and stepping bees featuring
more trained musicians.</p>

<p>The legacy of this emphasis on dance survived
in polka bands and popular dance bands,
including those of Lawrence Welk. Welk, born
in Strasburg, North Dakota, in 1903, became a
popular television icon in that particular mid-
American mold that also produced comedian
Johnny Carson and newscaster Walter Cronkite.
Welk's long-running program defined an
unabashedly sweet, sentimental, "corny" musical
idiom drawn from Slavic folk dances and
semiclassical and country selections and featured
accordion solos that have been copied by
legions of lesser-known players. The central
European polka heritage has remained particularly
vital in the Northern Plains, highlighted
by the annual Czech Festival, during
which Wilbur, Nebraska, showcases homegrown
artists such as Math Sladky and Ernie
Kucera.</p>
</div1>

<div1>
<head type="sub">Classical Music</head>

<p>With the influx of American settlers and the
establishment of towns, the musical life of
the Great Plains entered a new, more refined
existence. The first true professional musicians
were probably itinerant singing teachers who
taught both round and shape notes and teachers
of piano and violin. Communities rushed
to acquire fife and drum corps, bands, orchestras,
vocal ensembles, and opera companies
as status symbols indicating their civilizing
position in the "wilderness." For example,
as early as 1880 the town of Lincoln, Nebraska,
had a philharmonic society, three orchestras,
a military band, two string bands, an opera
house (opened in 1873), an oratorio society,
and two male chorales. European artists, including
Ignace Paderewski, Leopold Goldowsky,
Josef Hofmann, Pablo Casals, and Jan
Kubelik, as well as European opera companies
began concertizing the Great Plains. In addition
to these public arenas, private musical
clubs offering recitals and lectures on the arts
proliferated. Eventually, symphony orchestras
and opera companies would be established in
Fort Worth, Tulsa, Wichita, Omaha, and Colorado
Springs. Beginning in 1897, Canadian orchestras
were founded in Calgary, Winnipeg,
Regina, and Saskatoon. The Royal Winnipeg
Ballet, Canada's oldest, was established in 1938.</p>

<p>Concurrent with these developments was
the rise of music education. Among the earliest
schools of music and conservatories in
the area were those at the Universities of Kansas,
Oklahoma, and Colorado. A seminal figure
in this movement was Willard Kimball,
who, after studying in Leipzig, graduated from
Oberlin and lived in Iowa for nineteen years
before moving to Nebraska to establish what
eventually became the University of Nebraska
School of Music in 1894. Kimball also organized
the Trans-Mississippi and International
Exposition, held in Omaha in 1898. This lavish
<hi rend="italic">fin-de-siecle</hi> World's Fair, which was seen as an
important "coming of age" of Plains culture,
featured members of the Chicago Symphony
and the U.S. Marine Band as well as the famous
black cornetist Percy Lowery. The Canadian
Prairie Provinces also began developing
music programs at universities, beginning
with the University of Winnipeg in 1880 and
followed by the Universities of Saskatoon
(1907), Edmonton (1908), Regina (1911), and
Calgary (1945).</p>

<p>The legacy of this rich musical tradition can
be appreciated in the number of classical musicians
born or educated in the Great Plains
who became prominent during the twentieth
century. Three important composers from the
region helped create an American music that
was more homegrown and less dependent on
European classical models. Pulitzer Prize winner
Howard Hanson (1896–1981) was born in
Wahoo, Nebraska, and graduated from the
University of Nebraska. He went on to direct
the Eastman School of Music in Rochester,
New York, which became one of the most
prominent in the world. Hanson forged an
accessible American romantic style that incorporated
material reflecting his Scandinavian
ancestry. Roy Harris (1898–1979), born in Lincoln
County, Oklahoma, studied in Paris before
composing his Third Symphony in 1939, a
classic of musical populism. Another Pulitzer
Prize winner, Virgil Thomson, born in Kansas
City, Missouri, in 1896, expressed regionalism
in his operas and film scores and, as music
critic for the New York Herald Tribune, promoted
the cause of American music.</p>

<p>Later composers born or active on the
American Great Plains included Anthony Donato,
Cecil Effinger, and Robert Beadell. All
enjoyed long careers as teachers and composers.
Prominent composers from the Canadian
Prairie Provinces include Barbara Pentland,
who studied at Juilliard before teaching at
Toronto and Vancouver; Harry Freedman,
who was raised in Medicine Hat, Alberta, and
later became composer in residence with the
Toronto Symphony; and Sydney Hodkinson,
who was born in Winnipeg, later taught
at Eastman and Southern Methodist University,
and also directed the St. Paul Chamber
Orchestra.</p>
</div1>

<div1>
<head type="sub">From Cowboy to Coutnry: The Importance of the Lone Star State</head>

<p>In spite of the European-derived Plains music
described above, for most classically trained
musicians, like Willa Cather's heroine in <title level="m">The Song of the Lark</title>, Thea Kronenborg, the ultimate
success of "making it" necessitated relocation
to the East, especially New York. The
unique and significant contribution of music
from the Great Plains lies not in replication of
an outside aesthetic but in the creation of a
vital new form of American popular music
that drew its strength from a mixture of European
American, African American, and Latino
sources. Some of the first stirrings of
this truly authentic music originated on the
Southern Great Plains, especially in the state
of Texas. From a potent mix of Appalachian
folk songs, Cajun music from nearby Louisiana,
Mexican <hi rend="italic">norte&#241;a</hi>, mariachi, and corridos,
along with the influence of a distinctive
regional African American blues, Texas musicians
created or popularized a host of forms
such as the cowboy song, honky-tonk, western
swing, and various Tex-Mex hybrids that
eventually merged into the country and western
music of the late 1940s.</p>

<p>The cowboy, one of the most enduring of
American myths, emerged from the brief period
of the open-range cattle drives from 1865
to 1885 and endured because of romantic
dime-novel portrayals of heroes such as Buffalo
Bill Cody (1846–1917). Cowboy song lyrics
began to appear in the early twentieth century.
Some of the most important were collected by
N. Howard "Jack" Thorpe. Thorpe, an authentic
cowboy who worked in eastern New Mexico
and West Texas, published an important collection
of 101 cowboy songs (lyrics only) in
1921. The first recordings of cowboy songs followed
in 1925. Among the initial stars of this
new genre was Woodward "Tex" Ritter, who
became interested in singing while a drama
student at the University of Texas at Austin. His
first recordings in 1933 are considered among
the most authentic. Paradoxically, his famous
nickname was acquired in New York while appearing
on a popular radio program.</p>

<p>Of all the singing cowboys from Texas, the
most famous was undoubtedly Gene Autry.
Born on a ranch near Tioga, Texas, in 1907,
Autry grew up in neighboring Oklahoma until
he ran away from home to join the Fields
Brothers Marvelous Medicine Show as an Al
Jolson impersonator. Following some advice
from Jimmie Rodgers, he adopted the cowboy
persona, billing himself as Oklahoma's Yodeling
Cowboy. Autry later starred in many
movies that elevated him, along with his chief
rival, Roy Rogers, to superstar status.</p>

<p>Among the other important musicians from
the Lone Star State were the Traveling Troubadour,
Ernest Tubb (1914–84), and fiddler
Bob Wills (1905–75). Born near Kosse, Texas,
Wills formed his first band, the Light Crust
Doughboys, in 1931 before moving to Tulsa
with his most famous group, the Texas Playboys.
Wills and his band were broadcast regularly
on radio station kvoo from 1934 through
1942 before moving to Hollywood to pursue a
film career. Wills's music helped define an approach
that became known as western swing, a
hybrid style incorporating instrumental elements
of jazz and blues within the country
string-band tradition. Another Texan, Roy Orbison,
born in the town of Vernon in 1936,
became a top rockabilly star after he signed
with Sun Records in 1956 before moving to
Nashville. Orbison's ballad style exerted a tremendous
influence on both American and
British singers, including the Beatles, who
opened for Orbison on his 1963 tour of England.
The preeminent position of Texas country
music has continued unabated with the
success of the outlaws who spurned Nashville
conventions, including Willie Nelson, Waylon
Jennings, and David Allen Coe as well as newer
country groups like Asleep at the Wheel.</p>

<p>While only peripherally part of the cowboy
tradition, mention must be made of the contributions
of folksinger Woody Guthrie, the
person who, perhaps more than any other,
shaped American folk music. Woodrow Wilson
Guthrie was born in Okemah, Oklahoma,
in 1912, and as a young man he experienced
the deprivations of the Great Depression. Taking
to the road as a wandering minstrel, Guthrie
created a repertoire of protest songs championing
the rights of the poor and oppressed.
His songs speak to the plight of migrant workers
and coal miners, and he strongly supported
the cause of the unions. His song
"Pretty Boy Floyd" interprets the outlaw of the
1930s as a Robin Hood character, stealing from
the banks and giving to the poor disenfranchised
farmers. He published a collection of
folk songs and an autobiography and became
a major influence on later singers such as Bob
Dylan and Bruce Springsteen. In 1961 Dylan
made a pilgrimage to Guthrie's bedside in
New Jersey as he lay dying from Huntington's
disease, and his early composition, "Song to
Woody," was his commemoration to this
American original.</p>
</div1>

<div1>
<head type="sub">Black Music on the Plains</head>

<p>Originating at first in segregated isolation,
then finally merging with white styles in the
period after World War II, black music of the
Great Plains developed unique and influential
forms of blues, ragtime, swing, and jazz. The
first major entry of African Americans onto
the Plains began after the Civil War. Between
1868 and 1895 more than 5,000 black cowboys
worked the ranges from Texas to Kansas. Like
their white counterparts, they passed the
lonely time with singing and fiddle music.
These cowboy minstrels included "Big" Jim
Simpson, who worked the Chisholm Trail before
settling in Wyoming, and fiddlers George
Washington and Sabrien Bates, who rode with
Billy the Kid.</p>

<p>Another access for African American music
onto the Great Plains occurred through regimental
bands. The black Ninth and Tenth
Cavalry and Twenty-fourth and Twenty-fifth
Infantry bands served from Texas to the
Dakotas.</p>

<p>Emerging out of the African American
band tradition was Perry George Lowery
(1870-1942). Born in the Flint Hills country of
eastern Kansas, Lowery was the product of a
small but successful group of self-sufficient
African American farmers. He began by playing
drums, then switched to cornet. After
studying in Boston, Lowery became known as
the World's Greatest Colored Cornet Soloist
and was featured at the 1898 Trans-Mississippi
and International Exposition.</p>

<p>Most distinctive forms of African American
music that emerged in the twentieth century
were based on the blues. Blues-derived music
evolved from slave field hollers and gospel music
and had a major impact on jazz, country,
and rock. Rooted in the South, the blues developed
into several distinctive regional styles.
One of these early country blues styles arose in
Texas and was characterized by single-string
guitar playing and a more relaxed vocal sound
than found in the nearby Mississippi Delta.
Male blues singers from the Plains region include
Roy Brown and Amos Milburn from
Texas, Robert Jeffrey and Lemuel Johnson
from Oklahoma, and "Gatemouth" Moore
from Topeka, Kansas. Two important female
blues artists, both from Kansas City, Kansas,
were Hattie "Hi Hat" McDaniel and Ada
Brown (a cousin of ragtime composer James
Scott). McDaniel later moved to Hollywood
and became a film star in 1939, when she was
awarded the first Academy Award ever given to
an African American for her role in <title>Gone with the Wind</title>.</p>

<p>Note should also be made here of another
great musician from the Southern Plains who
began as a blues guitarist before moving east
and almost single-handedly defining the electric
guitar as a jazz solo instrument. Charlie
Christian, from Bonham, Texas, recorded
with Benny Goodman from 1939 to 1941 and
also played in with Charlie Parker, Dizzy
Gillespie, and Thelonious Monk. Christian
created a clean, linear style that became the
model for most later jazz guitar players. He
died from tuberculosis in 1942 at the age of
twenty-five.</p>

<p>The blues also was the basis of a new type
of piano music that developed in the Great
Plains region. Dubbed boogie-woogie, Texas
barrelhouse, or honky-tonk, this exciting style
featured a steadfast, rocking bass line synchronized
under tremolos and triplets in the right
hand. These traits, especially the active bass
line, became prominent in later Kansas City
jazz, urban blues, rhythm and blues, and rock
and roll. Complete with melody, harmony, and
bass, blues piano was a self-sufficient music
machine, able to provide solo entertainment
for dances at roadhouses and private parties.
One variation was the house rent party, when
guests, for a small fee to help pay a month's
rent, would be treated to good food and piano
music. Plains pianists included Sammy Price,
Pete Johnson, and Jay McShann. At the time of
writing, McShann, in his eighties, is still active
and a consummate master of virtually every
classic jazz piano idiom.</p>

<p>Beginning after World War I and continuing
throughout the 1920s until their decline
during the Depression, territory bands flourished
in the Great Plains. Stated simply, a territory
band is an ensemble based in an outlying
area, where sparse population necessitated
traveling great distances for social activities.
Territory bands tended to monopolize the
music of these regions, and, like big fish in
small ponds, they enjoyed a local but not a
regional reputation. Because the early recording
industry was centered in the East, many of
these barnstorming groups have not been preserved
on vinyl; however, several future jazz
and blues stars cut their teeth in territory
bands. The goal of most groups was eventually
to relocate to the big cities, especially Kansas
City, which by the mid-1930s had become a
mecca for jazz.</p>

<p>The musical styles of these groups, though
varying considerably, involved an approach,
distinct from the recorded groups in the East,
that eventually became defined in the Kansas
City style of the late 1930s and was also an
integral component of bebop jazz, which
emerged after World War II. A brash exuberance,
heavily based on the blues, marked the
sound of the territory bands. Using the familiar
blues as a framework encouraged improvisation,
and some of the arrangements were
assembled on the spot without written charts.
These "head arrangements" used short, repeated
motifs called "riffs" that could be easily
picked up by ear and that served as melodies
and backgrounds behind soloists. Another ingredient
of the sound of these groups was the
use of syncopated ragtime rhythms. Much of
ragtime was developed in nearby Missouri, especially
in Sedalia, with the work of Scott
Joplin. The typical instrumentation of these
bands consisted of about three saxophones,
three or four brass instruments, and a rhythm
section of piano, guitar or banjo, bass (tuba
later replacing string bass), piano, and drums.
Over time, the size of the orchestra was increased
with the addition of more reed and
brass instruments.</p>

<p>One of the most important Plains territory
bands was Andy Kirk and the Clouds of Joy,
which originated in Oklahoma City and included
future piano sensation Mary Lou Williams.
Buster Smith's troop began in Dallas
before relocating and gaining fame as the
Oklahoma City Blue Devils. This legendary
group included Walter Page on bass, the influential
Lester Young on tenor saxophone, blues
shouter Jimmy Rushing, and the great Bill
"Count" Basie on piano. George Morrison's
band, which dominated the Denver scene well
into the 1940s, served as an apprenticeship for
John Lewis (later of the Modern Jazz Quartet)
and Jimmy Lunceford.</p>

<p>The most classic synthesis of African American
musical evolution on the Plains was Kansas
City jazz. In the competitive struggle of the
territory bands for preeminence, the band of
Bennie Moten and Count Basie won the day.
Moten began leading bands in the early 1920s,
making his first recording in 1923. Eventually,
he lured an impressive lineup away from rival
bands, including Walter Page, Jimmy Rushing,
trumpeter "Hot Lips" Page, and, most importantly,
Count Basie, who joined Moten in 1929.
During an East Coast tour, Bennie Moten's
Kansas City Orchestra recorded what many
scholars feel are the first definitive swing classics.
Moten died unexpectedly during minor
surgery in 1935, and, after a brief hiatus, the
band was reassembled with Basie as the leader.
This ensemble featured Lester Young, Walter
Page, Freddie Green on guitar, and Jo Jones on
drums. Basie's orchestra went on to rival Duke
Ellington's as the most important black ensemble
of the period. Its no-nonsense, "straightahead"
style is still emulated by many traditional
big bands of today.</p>

<p>It remained for a native of Kansas City,
Kansas, to complete the transformation of the
territory band tradition to modern jazz. Charlie
"Yardbird" Parker, born in 1920, came of age
during the decade of the 1940s, the golden age
of Kansas City jazz. Wide-open jam sessions
featuring traveling musicians provided a democratic
forum for young players to learn and to
prove themselves. Playing professionally by
age fifteen, Parker made his first important
recordings in Wichita, Kansas, in 1940 with Jay
McShann's blues-based band. There he also
acquired his nickname, "Yardbird" or "Bird."
Parker, along with Dizzy Gillespie, Thelonious
Monk, and others, went on to create bebop, the
first modern jazz style, combining the energy
of the blues and territory bands of the Plains
with the harmonic sophistication of the East
Coast. Parker died in New York City in 1955, a
victim of hard living.</p>

<p>The Plains region has proven especially fertile
soil for saxophonists. These include tenor
saxophonist Ben Webster, born in Kansas City,
Missouri, and Herschel Evans, from Denton,
Texas. Webster's deep tone was a feature of the
great Ellington bands of the 1930s. Evans
played with Count Basie alongside Lester
Young. Later players included the iconoclastic
Ornette Coleman, born in 1930 in Fort Worth,
Texas. Playing in a highly original style that
combined elements of blues and bebop, Coleman
helped create a new, avant-garde language
for jazz in the 1960s. More recently,
Dewey Redman and Julius Hemphill, both
also from Fort Worth, have continued the rich
tradition of Plains saxophonists.</p>

<p>Previously separated for the most part by
segregation, the streams of black and white
music began swimming together after World
War II, leading directly to the rock and roll of
the 1950s. The most important immediate precursor
to rock was rhythm and blues. R&amp;B (the
term was first coined by <title level="j">Billboard Magazine</title> in
1949) combined elements of earlier blues and
gospel, big band swing and boogie-woogie,
and resulted in an infectious dance music that
appealed to both white and black listeners. Initially
shunned by major labels, R&amp;B was recorded
by small, independent recording companies
and disseminated over radio.</p>

<p>Important R&amp;B artists from the Plains included
Wynonie Harris and King Curtis (born
Curtis Outen). Harris, born in Omaha in 1915
(or possibly 1913), began as a big band singer
before making his most influential R&amp;B recordings
with King Records. King Curtis became
one of R&amp;B's most sought after saxophonists.
Born in Fort Worth in 1934, he
went on to record with the Coasters, Wilson
Pickett, Sam and Dave, and Aretha Franklin
before launching a successful solo career. He
was stabbed to death in New York City in 1971.</p>
</div1>

<div1>
<head type="sub">Rockabilly and Rock and Roll</head>

<p>During the 1950s white musicians began combining
elements of rhythm and blues with
country music in a classic phase of early rock
and roll known as rockabilly. The most important
early rock and roll musician from the
Great Plains was Buddy Holly. Charles Hardin
Holley, born in 1936 in Lubbock, Texas, was
one of rock's first great composers, guitarists
(he helped popularize the Fender Stratocaster),
vocalists, and bandleaders. He had a direct
influence on many later artists, including
Bob Dylan and the Beatles, whose very name
is a tribute to Holly's band, the Crickets. Yet
his career, cut short by a plane crash that also
claimed the lives of the Big Bopper and Richie
Valens, only lasted two years. Holly started out
playing western swing, but after his band
opened for Elvis Presley in 1957 he turned to
rock and roll. Spurred on by the success of his
number one hit, "That'll Be the Day," Holly
and the Crickets became one of the few white
bands to play the Apollo Theater in Harlem.
Unlike his chief competitors, Elvis and Jerry
Lee Lewis, Holly's success was based more on
his musicianship than on a frantic stage demeanor.
Another early rock star from the
Plains was Eddie Cochran, who like Holly had
a spectacular brief career cut short by an accident.
He was born in Oklahoma City and enjoyed
his greatest success as a singer-guitarist
with "Summertime Blues" in 1957. He died in
an auto crash in London in 1960.</p>

<p>Perceived as a menace to society and incurring
the envy of the major recording companies,
rock and roll came under attack at the
end of the 1950s, and a clean-cut, toned-down,
more acceptable form of rock was created that
centered on so-called teen idols. While many
of them came from Philadelphia (home of the
influential Dick Clark TV program <title>American Bandstand</title>), one of these popular singers
hailed from Fargo, North Dakota. Bobby Vee
got his start when his band filled in for the late
Buddy Holly in Moorhead, Minnesota. His innocent
songs of teenage love made him a star
by the early 1960s. While hardly a teen idol,
mention should be made of another popular
success from North Dakota, Peggy Lee. Born
in 1920 in Jamestown, Lee's long and varied
career began as a vocalist with the Benny
Goodman Orchestra.</p>
</div1>

<div1>
<head type="sub">Popular Music of the Sixties</head>

<p>The decade of the 1960s saw an explosion of
popular music, the most important of which
adopted a political and social agenda not
found in the music of the previous decade.
Furthermore, the music deepened in technological,
compositional, and textual complexity,
creating a myriad of styles that combined
and reconfigured older forms. While
the principal creative arenas for this activity
were on the coasts and in England, some
prominent rock stars of the 1960s originated
in the Great Plains.</p>

<p>The most influential rock styles emanating
from the Great Plains quite naturally reflected
the region's long background in blues and
country music. Buddy Miles was born in
Omaha, Nebraska, in 1946. His early solo
efforts combined R&amp;B with psychedelic rock.
He has also enjoyed a diverse career, playing
with Wilson Pickett, Electric Flag, Jimi Hendrix,
and Santana. Elvin Bishop, born in Tulsa,
Oklahoma, absorbed the Chicago blues style
and played with Bob Dylan and the Paul Butterfield
Blues Band before leading his own rock
band in the 1970s. Other rock musicians from
the Plains include Randy Bachman, J. J. Cale,
and the band reo Speedwagon. Bachman was
born in Winnipeg and was a founding member
of the Guess Who. After leaving the band, he
went on to form Bachman-Turner Overdrive,
which reaped immense success and helped to
define a middle ground between the emerging
heavy rock of the mid-1970s and more conventional
rock idioms. J. J. Cale, born in Oklahoma
City, Oklahoma, is a prolific country-blues-
rock singer-songwriter whose songs
have been recorded by Eric Clapton and Lynyrd
Skynyrd.</p>

<p>Just as rock dipped into country music for
new fusion possibilities, progressive country
purposefully incorporated rock elements to
broaden its fan base. Delbert McClinton, born
in Lubbock in 1940, has recorded in blues and
country styles. Closer to the country style are
such well-known performers as John Denver
(born in Roswell, New Mexico, in 1943) and
Tanya Tucker (born in Seminole, Texas, in
1958). Garth Brooks, born in Tulsa, Oklahoma,
in 1962, became country's biggest star
of the 1990s. Influenced by diverse bands such
as Kiss, Lynyrd Skynyrd, and Styx, combined
with traditional models such as Hank Williams
Sr. and Lefty Frizzell, Brooks's music appealed
to crossover fans of both country and
rock. Listed by Billboard Magazine as the top
grossing country artist from 1991 to 1993,
Brooks led the way in creating a new eclectic
style and confirmed country's position as the
most popular musical genre in America.</p>

<p>Another fusion music developing in the
Southern Plains reflects a Latino, Tex-Mex
heritage. Joe "King" Carrasco was born in
Dumas, Texas, and began working in the Austin
area in 1973 performing what he calls
"nuevo wavo," a combination of rock, Chicano
polkas, and new wave. Brave Combo,
also from Texas, blends polka, rock, salsa, and
other Latin styles to create a quirky, iconoclastic
mix. Both Carrasco and Brave Combo,
while enjoying regional fame, have yet to
achieve national attention.</p>

<p>Combining the improvisation of bebop with
the rhythms and amplified instruments of blues
and rock, jazz rock (or fusion) became an important
direction in the 1970s. Two Plains bands
reflecting two different approaches to fusion are
Kansas and Mannheim Steamroller. Kansas,
formed in Topeka in 1970, began as a high
school garage band before evolving into an
ornate art rock ensemble, utilizing classical
and jazz elements. Chip Davis and his synthesized
Mannheim Steamroller came out of
Omaha and have maintained a large following
through a commercial, formulaic mix of New
Age and fusion patterns.</p>

<p>Although relatively few in number, singersongwriters
from the Canadian Plains exerted
their special influence on mainstream popular
music. Buffy Sainte-Marie, a Cree Indian, was
born in Saskatchewan in 1941. She became the
first popular Native American musician, recording
extensively from 1964 to 1981. An activist
for Native peoples' rights, she also appeared
on the children's TV program Sesame Street from 1976 to 1981. Joni Mitchell, born
Roberta Joan Anderson in Fort Macleod, Alberta,
in 1943, began performing while a student
at Alberta College of Art in Calgary.
Mitchell emerged as a distinctive voice in midsixties
folk rock with her sophisticated confessional
lyrics sung in a unique recitative style.
Continuing to evolve, she has incorporated
jazz elements and world music into her repertoire.
The controversial k. d. lang (Katheryn
Dawn Lang) was raised on a farm in Consort,
Alberta, in 1962. lang (she prefers the lower
case) studied classical piano and guitar before
turning to country music with a style partly
modeled on that of Patsy Cline. She was voted
vocalist of the year by >Rolling Stone Magazine
in 1983 and achieved international recognition
with her performance at the 1988 Calgary
Winter Olympics. Her open lesbianism and
activity as a spokesperson for the "antimeat"
movement have imbued recordings such as <title>All You Can Eat</title> (1995) with the kind of controversy
associated more with rock than country
music.</p>

<p>Another seminal figure from the Canadian
Plains, one who has defied categorization by
covering a variety of rock idioms during his
career, is Neil Young. Born in Toronto in 1945,
Young moved to Winnipeg when he was fifteen
before moving to California in 1966,
where he helped form the rock band Buffalo
Springfield. An ensuing solo career that has
lasted to the present day was punctuated by a
stint with Crosby, Stills, Nash and Young, including
an appearance at Woodstock. One of
the most enduring and consistently creative of
the 1960s generation of rock stars, Young has
turned out more than fifty albums, ranging in
style from acoustic ballads to country rock
and especially hard rock.</p>
</div1>

<div1>
<head type="sub">The Present</head>

<p>The Great Plains region continues to provide a
nurturing environment for young musicians:
Melissa Etheridge from Leavenworth, Kansas,
Matthew Sweet from Lincoln, Nebraska, and
Reba McIntire out of McAlester, Oklahoma,
are among the most recent in this distinguished
parade of artists. The winds that have
eavesdropped on so much diverse music still
blow unimpeded through the Great Plains, but
today this music is no longer lost to the open
spaces. Classical music, no longer an imported
product from Europe or the East Coast, flourishes
in universities and in symphony and opera
companies. Community bands with summer
concerts in the park as well as the polka
bands of the Sokol Halls and roadhouses are
still found in numerous Czech, Swedish, and
German communities and help maintain a
sense of cultural continuity. New country music,
especially on the Southern Plains, continues
to combine and reinvent itself, while
blues and jazz are studied and preserved in
schools and community ensembles and played
in venues throughout the region. The underground
rock scene prospers in college communities,
and, perhaps most significantly, given
its longevity, Native American music is alive
and evolving while still maintaining its ties to
tradition.</p>
</div1>

<div1>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">AFRICAN AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.afam.013">Christian, Charlie</ref>; <ref n="egp.afam.015">Coleman, Ornette</ref>; <ref n="egp.afam.021">Harris, Wynonie</ref>;
<ref n="egp.afam.029">McDaniel, Hattie</ref>; <ref n="egp.afam.030">McShann, Jay</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">FILM</hi>: <ref n="egp.fil.005">Autry, Gene</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">NATIVE AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.na.091">Powwows</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">RELIGION</hi>:
<ref n="egp.rel.005">Black Elk, Nicholas</ref>; <ref n="egp.rel.023">Ghost Dance</ref>; <ref n="egp.rel.036">Native American Church</ref>; <ref n="egp.rel.051">Vision Quest</ref>.</p>
</div1>

<div1> <p/>
<closer>
<signed>Randall L. Snyder</signed>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Carr, Patrick, ed. <title level="m">The Illustrated History of Country Music</title>.
New York: Doubleday, 1979.</bibl> <bibl>Dyer, Karen. "Music on the
Nebraska Plains." Master's thesis, University of Nebraska.
Lincoln, 1979.</bibl> <bibl>Garofalo, Reebee. <title level="m">Rockin' Out: Popular Music in the</title> <hi rend="smallcaps">USA</hi>. Boston: Allyn and Bacon, 1997.</bibl> <bibl>Hitchcock,
H. Wiley. <title level="m">Music in the United States</title>. Englewood Cliffs <hi rend="smallcaps">NJ</hi>:
Prentice-Hall, 1988.</bibl> <bibl>Keil, Charles. <title level="m"><hi rend="italic">Urban Blues</hi></title>. Chicago:
University of Chicago Press, 1966.</bibl> <bibl>Neihardt, John G. Black
<title level="m">Elk Speaks</title>. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1961.</bibl>
<bibl>Nettle, Bruno. <title level="m">Folk Music in the United States</title>. Detroit:
Wayne State University Press, 1976.</bibl> <bibl>Romanowski, Patricia,
and Holly George-Warren, eds. <title level="m">The New Rolling Stone Encyclopedia of Rock and Roll</title>. New York: Fireside, 1995.</bibl>
<bibl>Russell, Ross. <title level="m">Jazz Style in Kansas City and the Southwest</title>.
London: University of California Press, 1971.</bibl> <bibl>Schuller,
Gunther. <title level="m">Early Jazz</title>. New York: Oxford University Press,
1968.</bibl> <bibl>Southern, Eileen. <title level="m">The Music of Black Americans</title>. New
York: W. W. Norton, 1983.</bibl> <bibl>Thorp, N. Howard. <title level="m">Songs of the Cowboy</title>. New York: Clarkson N. Potter, 1966.</bibl>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>