<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.lt.079">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Welch, James (1940-2003)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Kathryn W. Shanley</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.lt.079</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Shanley, Kathryn W.">Kathryn W. Shanley</author>. <title level="a">"Welch, James (1940-2003)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">496</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-25</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">WELCH, JAMES (1940-2003)</head>

<p>Born in Browning, Montana, where the mountains
break into foothills and then prairie, James
Welch, a writer of Blackfeet and Gros Ventre
heritage, remained rooted in Montana. His
writings reflected a lifetime spent primarily in
the magnificent and variable geographic terrain
of the West. Welch attended schools in
Montana, Oregon, and Alaska before graduating
in Minneapolis, Minnesota, in 1958. He
received a bachelor of arts degree in liberal arts
from the University of Montana in 1965, where
he also enrolled in the master of fine arts in
creative writing program from 1966 to 1968 but
did not earn a degree.</p>

<p>Since the publication of his first novel, <title level="m">Winter in the Blood</title> (1974), Welch has been widely
recognized as a leading figure in Native American
literature. His novels have been translated
and published in France, Italy, Germany, Holland,
Japan, Sweden, and England. Subsequent
to the rave reception his first novel received
(it was reviewed on the front page of
the <title level="j">New York Times Book Review</title>), Welch republished
his first and only collection of poetry,
<title level="m">Riding the Earthboy 40</title> (1971; reprint,
1976). In 1979 <title level="m">The Death of Jim Loney</title> appeared,
a second novel set around the Fort
Belknap Reservation in Montana. Both novels'
protagonists grapple with their familial
histories, the deaths of loved ones, and excessive
alcohol use.</p>

<p>With his third novel, <title level="m">Fools Crow</title> (1986),
Welch moved to depictions of historical events.
Set in the Rocky Mountains, home of the Piegan
(Pikuni) band of the Blackfeet Confederacy in
the 1870s, <title level="m">Fools Crow</title> offers a fictional view
of Pikuni life around the time of the virtual
extinction of the bison and just before Blackfeet
people signed a treaty that forever changed
their way of life. Based on historical figures
such as Pikuni leader Heavy Runner and U.S.
Army officer Gen. William Tecumseh Sherman,
the novel takes as its central subject the
growth into manhood of White Man's Dog
into Fools Crow, a chief. Fools Crow must
grapple with what living with honor versus
shame is and might be in the face of cultural
upheaval. That same year Welch coedited <title level="m">The Real West Marginal Way</title> (1986), a volume
based on Richard Hugo's life and work, together
with his wife, Lois Monk Welch, and
Ripley Hugo, widow of Richard Hugo.</p>

<p>In his fourth novel, <title level="m">The Indian Lawyer</title>
(1990), Welch drew on his ten years of experience
as vice chairman of the Montana State
Board of Pardons (1979–88) to depict another
sort of Indian protagonist. Sylvester Yellow
Calf, a descendant of Fools Crow, becomes a
lawyer and a Senate hopeful. In <title level="m">The Indian Lawyer</title> Welch moves beyond depictions of familial
and personal identity struggles to present
a man who learns he can make or break
himself.</p>

<p>The traumatic events in U.S.-Native relations
gripped Welch's imagination more fully
after he wrote <title level="m">Fools Crow</title> and <title level="m">The Indian Lawyer</title>.
Along with Paul Stekler, he created a
video, <title level="m">Killing Custer: The Battle of the Little Bighorn and the Fate of the Plains Indians</title>
(1994), that reflects Native American points of
view regarding the Battle of the Little Bighorn.
In his last novel, <title level="m">The Heartsong of Charging Elk</title> (2000), Welch told the poignant story of a
Lakota who is left stranded and sick in Marsailles
when the Wild West show that had employed
him moved on.</p>

<p>Welch occasionally taught at the University
of Washington and Cornell University as a visiting
professor, and lived in Missoula, where
he wrote full-time. Welch died of a heart attack
August 4, 2003, in Missoula.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">WAR</hi>: <ref n="egp.war.025">Little Bighorn, Battle of the</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Kathryn W. Shanley<lb/>
University of Montana</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Beidler, Peter G., ed. "James Welch's Winter in the Blood."
<title level="j">American Indian Quarterly</title> 4 (1978): 93–172.</bibl> <bibl>McFarland,
Ron. <title level="m">James Welch</title>. Lewiston <hi rend="smallcaps">ID</hi>: Confluence Press, 1986.</bibl>
<bibl>Velie, Alan R. "James Welch's Poetry." <title level="j">American Indian Culture and Research Journal</title> 3 (1979): 22–23.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>