<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->


<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.arc.033">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Literary Architecture</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Diane Dufva Quantic</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.arc.033</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Quantic, Diane Dufva">Diane Dufva Quantic</author>. <title level="a">"Literary Architecture."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">87</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-13</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">LITERARY ARCHITECTURE</head>

<p>The term <hi rend="italic">literary architecture</hi> can be defined
in a number of ways. Three definitions can
serve as points of reference on a continuum.
The first definition focuses on architecture&#8211;
structural design&#8211;in Great Plains literature.
The structures that people live in are frequently
a concern, especially in stories of the
first European settlers. The dugouts and sod
houses originate out of necessity, not preference.
The settlers' wives especially resist living
in the ground itself. Their reluctance springs
not only from the inconveniences associated
with setting up housekeeping in dark, leaking,
bug-infested structures but, more important,
from their cultural antipathy to living like
burrowing animals and thereby becoming
beastlike, uncivilized. O. E. R&#246;lvaag's novel <title level="m">Giants in the Earth</title> (1927) is a classic example of
this aspect of literary architecture. As Per
Hansa pursues his grandiose dreams of a
prairie kingdom, his wife, Beret, equates their
sod house on the open prairie with cultural
isolation and psychological erasure.</p>

<p>A second definition refers to works in
which the design and building of a house form
a central theme. In some instances, the conflict
centers on the woman's dream of the
amenities realized in a clean, fashionable
frame house, while the man focuses on the
acquisition of land and the equipment necessary
to realize financial security. Ironically,
once the family's homestead is established and
the fine house is built, the structure often becomes
a symbol not of fulfillment but of entrapment
or pride, as in Frederick Manfred's
novel <title level="m">This Is the Year</title> (1947). The grand house
begins to crumble as soon as it is completed, a
reminder of European Americans' misplaced
confidence in their ability to control natural
forces in the Great Plains. In other novels, the
house becomes a trap or a garrison that not
only protects the characters from the threatening
landscape but also isolates them from
social contact with the developing community,
as in Martha Ostenso's <title level="m">Wild Geese</title> (1925).
In some instances, the fortresslike structure
provides a site for predation and greed, as
in Mari Sandoz's novel <title level="m">Slogum House</title> (1937).
This theme of enclosure is reworked by authors
such as Wright Morris in <title level="m">The Home Place</title> (1948) and <title level="m">The World in the Attic</title> (1949)
and by Larry Woiwode in <title level="m">Beyond the Bedroom Wall</title> (1975).</p>

<p>A third definition focuses on the literary
structure of Great Plains works themselves.
Most Great Plains writers are aware of the
complex relationship between the geography
of place and the social structures that people
create around themselves and in their communities.
Although there are many variations,
the conflicts&#8211;and characters' reactions to
them&#8211;fall into some familiar patterns. The
most common conflict juxtaposes a character
who focuses on the land's promise of abundance
or wealth against another's insistence
on the primacy of societal values: home, family,
community. Because Great Plains literary
works are about a place that seems spare, the
style of Great Plains fiction is also deceptively
plain, but, like the intricate roots of prairie
grasses, this plain style is often the result of the
deliberate planning of a literary work's structure.
Willa Cather codified this definition
of literary architecture in her essay "The Novel
D&#233;meubl&#233;" (1922). In the "unfurnished"
novel, Cather declared, the artist's aim is not
to re-create a realistic world but to select material
and present it by a "suggestion rather
than by enumeration." A work of art should
enable the reader to "feel what is on the page"
without having it specifically named. In Great
Plains literature, the focus on the elemental
struggle to survive and the parallel need for
personal fulfillment within a community has
created a body of carefully designed works.
Cather's own novels are perhaps the best illustration
of this third definition of literary
architecture. Her deceptively simple stories
reveal, upon examination, layers of "felt" but
unarticulated realities. Other authors, most
notably Wright Morris, have recast this unfurnished
style in the postmodern age, relying on
the reader's knowledge of the region's apparently
simple surface and its underlying complexities
as well as the Great Plains literary
tradition to provide the framework for an appreciation
of the region's literary architecture.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">EUROPEAN AMERICANS</hi>: 
<hi rend="italic"><ref n="egp.ea.013"><title level="m">Giants in the Earth</title></ref></hi>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Diana Dufva Quantic<lb/>
Wichita State University<lb/>
</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Lutwack, Leonard. <title level="m">The Role of Place in Literature</title>. Syracuse
<hi rend="smallcaps">NY</hi>: Syracuse University Press, 1984.</bibl> <bibl>Quantic, Diane Dufva.
<title level="m">The Nature of the Place: A Study of Great Plains Fiction</title>.
Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1995.</bibl> <bibl>Thacker, Robert. <title level="m">The Great Prairie Fact and Literary Imagination</title>. Albuquerque: University of New Mexico Press, 1989.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>