<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.arc.012">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Country Club Plaza</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Richard Longstreth</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.arc.012</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Longstreth, Richard">Richard Longstreth</author>. <title level="a">"Country Club Plaza."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">73</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-12</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">COUNTRY CLUB PLAZA</head>

<p>Announced in 1922 and begun according to a
substantially revised plan the following year,
Kansas City, Missouri's Country Club Plaza
was the most ambitious and the most influential
comprehensively planned retail complex
realized in the United States before the mid–
twentieth century. Through this work, real estate
developer J. C. Nichols became the nation's
foremost exponent of a revolutionary
new approach to the creation of business centers,
an approach that has had a profound impact
on the American landscape since World
War II.</p>

<p>While not the first example of its kind, the
plaza far exceeded any precursors in the scope
and detail of its program. The complex was
conceived to encompass more than 200 retail
outlets and approximately the same number
of professional offices and other services for
the consumer public. Planned in conjunction
with Nichols's vast Country Club District,
the plaza was intended eventually to serve
a population of tens of thousands from that
precinct and other parts of the metropolitan
area as well.</p>

<p>Nichols's plans broke with convention in
several important ways. First, the plaza was
planned as a physically unified entity: buildings
and all other components of the landscape
were designed to present a harmonious
ensemble that would be visually distinct and
engaging. Second, the complex was planned
to have a unified tenant structure: businesses
were carefully selected not only for the quality
of the goods and/or services they purveyed
but also in terms of how each contributed to
the greater whole. Third, this ensemble would
operate in a coherent manner under the auspices
of a single management office and a
business association to coordinate hours, special
events, and advertising, among other features.
Fourth, rather than having a defined
center, with a hierarchy of land values based
on proximity to it, all property in the Plaza
would be of more or less equal importance in
order to foster market return. Fifth, the complex
was oriented to motorists rather than to
public transportation routes. Streets were unusually
numerous and wide to facilitate movement
and parking. Buildings could be no
more than two stories high to preclude vehicular
congestion as well as to equitably distribute
land value. In 1928 two parking lots
were added in prime locations, to be followed
by several others designed to facilitate access.
Finally, all these objectives were possible because
every aspect of the scheme was undertaken
by the J. C. Nichols Company, which
retained ownership of the property and control
of the operation.</p>

<p>The plaza was designed to be built incrementally
as demand in the Country Club District
and other outlying areas increased. Construction
was brought to a halt by the Great
Depression, then resumed in the late 1930s.
Numerous additions were made following
World War II and fewer in recent years.
Through the years the plan has been fluid and
dynamic, adjusting to ongoing change.</p>

<p>Nichols intended the plaza to complement
rather than compete with the downtown
shopping district. Early tenants mostly retailed
high-end specialty and convenience
goods. By the late 1930s a few chain stores
had been included. During the postwar years
branches of several major downtown stores
and a large Sears unit were added, rendering
the complex a more significant regional
destination.</p>

<p>Nichols was instrumental in advancing the
term <hi rend="italic">shopping center</hi> for his 
unusual venture. Within a few years of its commencement, 
the plaza began to be emulated by other developers,
and it soon acquired legendary status.
Although the layout and exuberant Spanish
baroque–inspired imagery were no longer
considered relevant in the postwar era, the
success of the plaza's underlying concept had a
decisive impact on the proliferation of shopping
centers nationwide.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">CITIES AND TOWNS</hi>: 
<ref n="egp.ct.028">Kansas City, Kansas and Missouri</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Richard Longstreth<lb/>
George Washington University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Longstreth, Richard. "The Diffusion of the Community
Shopping Center Concept during the Interwar Decades."
<title level="j">Journal of the Society of Architectural Historians</title> 56 (1997):
268-93.</bibl> <bibl>Longstreth, Richard. "J. C. Nichols, the Country
Club Plaza, and Notions of Modernity." <title level="j">Harvard Architecture Review</title> 5 (1986): 120-35.</bibl> <bibl>Worley, William S. <title level="m">J. C. Nichols and the Shaping of Kansas City</title>. Columbia: University
of Missouri Press, 1990.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>