<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.rel.001">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Religion</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Charles H. Lippy</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.rel.001</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Lippy, Charles H.">Charles H. Lippy</author>. <title level="a">"Religion."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">731-735</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-18</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">RELIGION</head>

<p>A rich religious life marks the Great Plains
throughout its history. Long before many Native
Americans&#8211;the Sioux, Blackfoot, Comanches,
Apaches, Cheyennes, and Arapahos
&#8211;moved into the Plains, other Indigenous societies
flourished along the rivers and streams
of the region. For all of them, religion was not
a distinct arena of existence but was interwoven
with every other aspect of common
life. Identifying particular beliefs and specific
activities as religious reflects an understanding
of religion more characteristic of the Europeans,
whose presence in the Plains began
with the Spanish explorers of the early 1500s.
In time, efforts first of the Spanish and then in
the early 1700s of the French to Christianize
tribal peoples planted Roman Catholicism in
the Plains. Some of these missions left an influence
that endures to the present.</p>

<p>Perhaps the most significant era that shaped
the present religious configuration of the
Plains was the nineteenth century. By the mid–nineteenth century, thousands of persons of
European background began making their way
across the Plains. Some remained there while
others pushed on to California, Utah, and Oregon.
The primary infusion of European Americans
came in the latter decades of the nineteenth
century and early twentieth century
when railroads made access much easier.</p>

<p>The religious styles of these migrants reflected
the tremendous diversity that had
come to characterize organized religion in
Canada and the United States. Most of the
Protestant denominations were represented
among those settlers who made the Plains
their home. But there is an additional ingredient
in the story, not only for Protestantism
but also for Catholicism: ethnicity. New communities
frequently were comprised of persons
who shared a common ethnic heritage.
To understand the religious life of the Plains,
then, we must be sensitive to the particular
style, for example, of Norwegian Lutheranism
and Czech Catholicism. And we must also be
alert to groups such as the Mennonites who
fused a shared ethnic identity with a distinctive
religious orientation.</p>

<p>In time, other communities, other religious
groups, and other social forces were to leave
their imprint on Plains religious culture. Japanese
immigrants, for example, have made
Buddhism a vital part of the religious story
of Alberta. Experimental Jewish agricultural
communities in the Prairie Provinces and in
North Dakota have also given a special dimension
to the religious heritage of the Plains. As
urbanization came to the Plains, so, too, came
a concern for relating religion to public life
not only in movements like the Social Gospel
but in the establishment of hospitals, educational
institutions, and a host of other social
service agencies.</p>

<p>Other movements that defy denominational
boundaries, such as fundamentalism,
Pentecostalism, and revivalism, have likewise
left an abiding influence. With the coming of
the electronic age, religious broadcasting on
radio and television linked the religious life of
the Plains to that of the entire North American
continent in new ways. But to understand
the contours of the religious landscape of the
Plains today, we must begin with an appreciation
for the religious world of the Native
American cultures of the region.</p>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Native American Traditions and Christian Missions</head>

<p>To generalize about the religious dimension of
Plains Indigenous cultures is to ignore the distinctive
elements of the numerous individual
societies that once flourished in the region. Yet
there are sufficient common elements to warrant
some summary statements. Location was
the paramount factor in determining both
cultural and religious style. Those who clustered
in villages along the Missouri River and
its tributaries in the eastern Plains were oriented
more toward agriculture, especially cultivation
of corn. What later interpreters would
identify as religious rites thus tended to focus
on fertility, cementing the close relationship
between people and the land. Those to
the west, approaching the Rocky Mountains,
where a semiarid climate precluded agriculture,
were more dispersed and migratory, and
bison hunting was central to their way of life.
Among these peoples, vision quests, which
brought individuals into contact with supernatural
power, thereby increasing their prowess
as hunters while connecting them to powerful
mythic figures, were basic to the religious
beliefs and practices. Sacred sites, such as Bear
Butte in present-day South Dakota were, and
are, particularly important for such quests.</p>

<p>The case of the Sioux is instructive, although
by no means representative of all the
peoples of the Plains. Traditionally from what
is today part of Wisconsin and Minnesota, the
western Sioux by the mid-seventeenth century
were pushed by the Ojibwas and drawn
by the bison toward the Great Plains. As the
Sioux adapted to Plains life, they moved toward
dominance because they quickly incorporated
the horse (brought first to the Southern
Plains by the Spanish) into their culture,
and agricultural pursuits gave way to bison
hunting. Adaptation in the religious sphere
followed, as the concern for fertility was superseded
by concern for success in hunting,
and vision quests assumed greater importance.
One well-known consequence was the
emergence of the Sun Dance, an annual rite
symbolically re-creating and renewing the
cosmos in order to assure the well-being of the
people. The role of shamans, with their ability
to call on supernatural power to effect both
healing and success in hunting and other
tribal endeavors, grew in importance.</p>

<p>External forces, such as increased migration
of non-Native Americans into the Plains, government
policies that were frequently inimical
to tribal life, and Christian proselytizing,
spurred other changes. We should here note
three currents that had significant long-term
consequences: increased efforts among Christian
groups to establish missions among the
tribes; the rise to prominence of the Ghost
Dance; and the development of peyotism.</p>

<p>Three examples of mission work may be
taken as examples. Earliest are the missions
among Native Americans started by the Spanish.
By the mid-eighteenth century the Spanish
had sent around 100 expeditions into what
is now Texas; many included the establishment
of missions designed both to convert
and, ostensibly, to civilize Natives by organizing
them into something akin to agricultural
colonies. The earliest, founded by Franciscans
in 1682, lay just outside the Plains near El Paso.
Although these missions often served to protect
their Native inhabitants from even worse
exploitation by the Spanish conquerors, they
still disrupted tribal life and represented the
imposition of an alien religious style. These
missions demonstrate a characteristic that was
to mark similar enterprises throughout the
Plains, namely the missionary as both friend,
who offered security and protection from outside
invaders, and foe, whose very presence
undermined traditional tribal ways.</p>

<p>To the north, Belgian priest Pierre-Jean De
Smet was one of the most influential of the early
Catholic missionaries. De Smet's efforts to raise
money and call attention to mission needs, beginning
in 1838, took him from the Potawatomis
in Iowa to the Columbia and Willamette Valleys
of the Pacific Northwest. De Smet stands out as
well for his genuine appreciation of Native ways,
making him repeatedly a valued mediator between
tribal peoples and white settlers who encroached
on their lands. Twenty years before
De Smet began his labors, Joseph-Norbert Provencher
assumed leadership of mission work on
the Red River of the North, intent on providing
spiritual leadership for the French Canadians
already there, as well as establishing agricultural
colonies and schools for the Indigenous peoples.
By the 1830s numerous mission stations
were operating, many later sustained through
assistance from the French Order of Oblates of
Mary Immaculate. Provencher was instrumental
in persuading both the Oblates and the Grey
Nuns to undertake mission work in western
Canada. Also by the 1830s, the Anglican Church
Missionary Society, hoping to minister to British
Canadians and Native Americans alike, was
extending its work from its base along the Red
River Valley of the North. Most of these endeavors
share another feature that was to mark
much mission work, namely the establishment
of schools that would provide Native Americans
with something like a western-style education.
Even here, however, there was a paternalistic
assumption of great import, for many harbored
the conviction that education would "civilize"
or impress western ways on the Indigenous inhabitants,
rendering them easier to control and
more amenable to conversion to Christianity.</p>

<p>This conviction comes into sharp relief in
the third example, the work of Stephen Return
Riggs, an agent of the American Board of
Foreign Missions from 1837 until his death in
1883, who translated both the Bible and secular
works into the Dakota language of the Santee
Sioux. Riggs was convinced that education
would bring a "higher" standard of living to
the tribes by preparing them for participation
in "Christian civilization." His work, how
ever, also illustrates another long-term impact
of the missionary enterprise. In 1862, when
armed conflict erupted between the Sioux and
American forces, many of Riggs's converts
were loath to participate in the fighting. When
they, too, suffered reprisals, many of the Sioux
believed that white culture had so destroyed
the supernatural powers that once shaped
tribal life that conversions to Christianity, the
religion of the apparently more powerful white
culture, increased.</p>

<p>The Ghost Dance, a fusion of millenarian
hopes and rituals uniting the living and the
dead, began as a revival of Wodziwob's Round
Dance of 1870. A Paiute shaman named Wovoka,
who lived on the Walker River Reservation
in Nevada, had participated in the 1870
movement and had a vision that gave birth to
a new revitalization movement that spread
quickly to the Plains tribes during the winter of
1888–89. Wovoka's vision endowed him with a
message promising the ultimate restoration of
tribal integrity at a time when the cohesion of
tribal cultures was increasingly challenged by
external forces. Wovoka called for the renewal
of traditional tribal mores through the practice
of trance dances in which supernatural
empowerment would come to the faithful.
Short Bull and Kicking Bear, Lakota representatives
of the Sioux, visited Wovoka and carried
the message back to their people. The
Ghost Dance also took firm root among the
Canadian Sioux, where the movement was
known as New Tidings.</p>

<p>In an effort to exert control over the Plains
peoples, the American government had banned
ritual enactment of the Sun Dance in 1883. The
Ghost Dance appeared to be even more of a
threat, as it brought renewed solidarity and
hope to the tribal cultures. It also increased
militant resistance to further external domination,
especially among the Sioux who believed
that their "ghost shirts" were bulletproof. The
massacre at Wounded Knee Creek in 1890
brought these millennial expectations and the
hope for revitalized tribal life to a sudden halt
for many Sioux, but Wovoka's religion persisted
among the Oklahoma tribes, Canadian
Native peoples, and the Great Basin peoples
well into the twentieth century.</p>

<p>Among the Canadian Crees, the Ghost
Dance had a rather different character, reflecting
perhaps the generally less violent nature of
tribal relations with the Canadian government.
In this context, the Ghost Dance served
more as a means for the Prairie tribes to form
a united front in their dealings with the government.
However, the Riel Rebellion of 1885,
which was spurred primarily by the Metis but
also counted several Cree bands among its
participants, essentially thwarted efforts to
maintain this united front.</p>

<p>By the dawn of the twentieth century the
disintegration of traditional ways among the
Plains tribes was evident. Confined to reservations
and increasingly dependent on government
annuity payments and assistance from
Christian missionaries, who rarely appreciated
the richness of Native American religiosity, the
tribal peoples of the Plains faced what seemed
a bleak future. Some sought to return to traditional
practices such as the Sun Dance. Others
moved toward assimilation into white culture,
manifested in part through the adoption or
adaptation of practices associated with Christianity.
Yet others hoped to revitalize Native
American life through promoting a shared
"Indian" consciousness. Peyotism, regarded
by many as the most important twentiethcentury
religious development among Native
American peoples, fused aspects of all three
adjustments.</p>

<p>Long part of tribal religiosity in Mexico
where the peyote cactus grows, peyote rites
became part of Kiowa and Comanche life
around 1870. Peyotism spread rather slowly,
usually making its way into tribal life when its
advocates, such as Quanah Parker, traveled
from tribe to tribe promoting it. Administered
under strict ceremonial guidelines,
peyote generates visions that often combine
Christian symbols with traditional ones, for
example, by linking Christ with the Great
Spirit. Peyotism also encouraged a return to
traditional ethics that would simultaneously
renew tribal integrity and allow more peaceful
accommodation with white society.</p>

<p>In the United States, the Native American
Church, in which peyote rituals are central,
was first legally chartered in Oklahoma in
1918. However, as the larger culture developed
increasing concern about use of controlled
hallucinogenic substances, sporadic efforts
were made to quash the practice, culminating
first in a U.S. Supreme Court case in 1990 that
upheld the right of states to prohibit the practice,
and then in federal legislation enacted in
the wake of that court decision that protected
the practice. Despite the apprehension of the
larger culture, peyotism remains one of the
most vital means for sustaining a Native American
cultural and religious identity. It is estimated
that the Native American Church has
200,000 members.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Christianity in the Plains</head>

<p>For the most part, the planting of Christianity
in the Great Plains mirrors patterns of migration
of persons of European stock into the
region. Today, most of the old-line Protestant
groups have pockets of strength in the Plains,
as do Roman Catholicism and the Orthodox.
This great religious diversity prevents generalization
except at the broadest scale. The United
Church of Canada is the dominant religion in
many parts of the Prairie Provinces, a Lutheran
belt (the product of Scandinavian immigration)
stretches across much of North and
South Dakota, Methodism is the leading religion
in much of the Central Great Plains, although
this is also the area with the greatest
religious diversity in the region, and the Southern
Plains, particularly in Texas, is dominated
by the Southern Baptist religion. The highest
percentage of church membership in the region
is in the Lutheran and Southern Baptist
belts.</p>

<p>But the story is not simply one of transplanting
religious institutions from Europe or
the eastern United States and eastern Canada.
In many cases there is a vital ethnic component
that has given religious communities a
distinctive flavor, for in some situations immigrants
moved to the Plains as entire communities,
where a particular religious style, a cultural
tradition, and an ethnic heritage were
inextricably intertwined.</p>

<p>Roman Catholic Christianity in the Southern
Plains has its roots in Spanish exploration
and conquest; the missions to the Native
Americans frequently sought to serve the religious
needs of soldiers and traders whose
presence cemented Spanish control. Even today,
given the increase in migration from
Mexico into the Southern and Central Plains
over the last several decades, Catholicism
there retains a vital Hispanic cast.</p>

<p>In the Canadian portion of the Great Plains,
institutional Catholicism owes much to those
who sought to plant the seeds of Presbyterianism
there. In 1812, Thomas Douglas, the
Fifth Earl of Selkirk, established his Kildonan
colony, populated by Scottish immigrants,
along the Red River of the North near today's
Winnipeg. As a Scottish community, Lord Selkirk's
settlement was overwhelmingly Reformed
(Presbyterian) in religious sentiment.
But there were already some French Canadian
traders in the area who were Roman Catholic
by heritage, and in time Selkirk hired German
soldiers, largely Roman Catholic as well,
to provide protection for his people. What
brought Joseph-Norbert Provencher to launch
his mission to the Indigenous people in the
area was Selkirk's request for a priest to provide
spiritual guidance for those who were Catholic.
Provencher's work is central to Roman
Catholic growth in western Canada, which
benefited from the gradual movement of Catholics
to the area. In 1847 Provencher became
the first bishop of St. Boniface (Manitoba).</p>

<p>As Roman Catholics moved into areas of the
Plains, they brought with them their commitment
to work in education through parochial
schools and to promote health care through
the establishment of hospitals&#8211;all in some
ways also an extension of earlier missions to
Native Americans. Other groups were to follow
suit, and the story of higher education
especially, and the developing networks of
health-care institutions, is inextricably tied to
the religious history of the Great Plains. For
Roman Catholics, much of the labor that sustained
such enterprises came from the numerous
orders of nuns that sent workers wherever
there were Catholic people to be served.
For example, the Presentation Sisters have long
been recognized as leaders in health care in
Montana and the Dakotas.</p>

<p>The Scottish community at Kildonan was
also indirectly the key to bringing the Anglican
Church to the Prairie Provinces. When
these settlers could not procure the services of
a Presbyterian clergyman, they turned to the
Anglican John West for spiritual leadership.
For twenty years West served in Kildonan as
the community awaited the arrival of a Presbyterian
minister. But West used his post to
promote Anglican work, overseeing for a time
the labors among Native peoples sponsored by
the Anglican Church Missionary Society.</p>

<p>The major influx of Protestants who remained
permanently in the region came as a
result of two factors: the expansion of railroads
that linked the more heavily settled East
with the Pacific in both the United States and
Canada and the surge in immigration that
marked the period after 1880 until restrictions
were imposed in 1919 by a Canadian Order in
Council and in 1924 by the United States. In
Canada, for example, after the Canadian Pacific
Railway extended service to Winnipeg in
1881 and to British Columbia in 1885, settlers
flocked to Alberta and Saskatchewan. In both
the United States and Canada, for several decades
the bulk of the organized churches were
to be found along the railroad lines. The landscape
of towns and rural areas throughout
the region was imprinted with churches and
graveyards that told the story of the origins of
the settlers.</p>

<p>The Scandinavian and German immigrants
who came to the Dakotas were largely Lutheran
and tended to organize churches based on
country of origin. Even when English became
the language of education and business, Swedish,
Norwegian, and Finnish remained the
languages for worship, helping sustain a cultural
and ethnic heritage. Not until generations
had passed and languages of origin had
faded did these groups enter into mergers
with other Lutheran bodies, gradually diminishing
their ethnic aura. A similar pattern occurred
in Canada, where Swedish immigrants
organized the Evangelical Covenant Church
in Winnipeg in 1904; Norwegian and Danish
Lutherans soon replicated the pattern in establishing
their Evangelical Free Church.</p>

<p>Three examples bring into bold relief the fusion
of religion, culture, and ethnicity among
groups intent on preserving a distinctive identity:
the Doukhobors, the Mennonites, and the
Ukrainians who ultimately separated from the
Russian Orthodox Church. The Doukhobors,
the largest group of whom is known formally
today as the Union of Spiritual Communities in
Christ, trace their origins to a schism in the
Russian Orthodox Church in the seventeenth
century. Many of the more mystical among
them began to regroup. Those who were followers
of Peter Verigin migrated en masse to
Saskatchewan in 1899. At times experimenting
with communal living&#8211;the last of these attempts
was largely done in by the economic
turmoil of the Great Depression&#8211;the Doukhobors
have sustained a Russian mystical pietism
that stresses the inward apprehension of the law
of God and a divinity that even in seventeenthand
eighteenth-century Russia the more orthodox
regarded as heretical. This inner-directed
mysticism has also brought conflict with the
Canadian government since Doukhobors refused
to subscribe to any oaths of allegiance to
the government.</p>

<p>Many of the Mennonites who found their
way to the Plains also had Russian backgrounds.
By 1812 Mennonites from Poland and
Prussia had established several colonies in
southern Russia, where one group that later
called itself the Kleine Gemeinde (today's
Evangelical Mennonite Conference) broke
away from the larger body. That year they began
to migrate in large numbers to Manitoba
and Nebraska, although the smaller Nebraska
cluster eventually dissipated. Blending their
own pietism with the agrarian ways of southern
Russia, the Kleine Gemeinde flourished in
western Canada, where, by the late twentieth
century, adherents spread across five provinces.
Yet other Mennonites, forerunners of
today's Church of God in Christ, Mennonite,
experienced rapid growth in the Great Plains
because they were able to gain converts among
the increasing numbers of immigrants who
came from Russia and Germany to parts of
Kansas and Manitoba in the late nineteenth
century.</p>

<p>A second wave of Mennonites came particularly
to Alberta, Saskatchewan, and Manitoba
following World War I. There the availability
of land offered promise for sustaining a
simple agrarian existence that had been disrupted
by the violence and land dispossessions
of the Russian Revolution. Mennonite
migration had received earlier encouragement
when the Canadian government created preserves
for the group in Manitoba in the 1870s
and in Saskatchewan in the 1890s. Adhering to
a quasi-communal way of life and encouraging
the young to marry fellow believers, the
various clusters of Mennonites represent both
a religious community and an ethnic group.</p>

<p>A similar story is that of the Hutterites who
came to the Northern Great Plains. With roots
in the sixteenth-century Moravian Anabaptist
movement that saw adherents persecuted and
pushed into the Ukraine and elsewhere, Hutterites
came to the United States in the 1870s.
They established colonies (Bruderhofs) in
South Dakota and Montana, where they hoped
to maintain a simple agrarian life in which they
shared common ownership of goods and
property. But fearing persecution because of
their pacifist principles (and because of their
largely German heritage), hundreds crossed
the border into western Canada during World
War I, although some later returned to the
United States.</p>

<p>A significant Ukrainian migration into the
Canadian Plains also provides an illustration of
the fusion of religious, cultural, and ethnic dimensions
into a single whole. In the Ukraine,
the Russian Orthodox Church had established
itself as dominant, but because it was seen as an
agency of the state many Ukrainians regarded
the church as ethnically Russian, an arm of a
regime that imposed its will on the Ukrainian
people. Hence, when the Ukrainian National
Republic asserted its independence following
German occupation during World War I and
the disarray that came with the Russian Revolution,
some Ukrainians in Canada moved to
establish a separate church that would merge a
distinctive ethnic heritage with Orthodox
Christianity. Thus in July 1918 the Ukrainian
Greek-Orthodox Church of Canada was organized
in Saskatoon, Saskatchewan. Less tied to
Ukrainian nationalism is the Russian/Ukrainian
Baptist Union of the United States, formed
in 1901. Although now reduced to a handful of
churches, this body had its genesis in an immigrant
community in Kiev, North Dakota,
made up of persons who had come from
southern Russia and the Ukraine in the late
nineteenth century.</p>

<p>Many other Protestant denominations took
root in the Great Plains. Congregationalists,
for example, owed their growth largely to those
who migrated to the Northern Plains from
New England, although when the United
Church of Christ was formed through mergers
in the twentieth century, many whose origins
were in German Congregationalism, as manifested
in the Evangelical and Reformed
Church, became part of the new venture.
Methodism, the largest Protestant body in the
United States in the mid–nineteenth century,
also traces its strength in the Plains to conventional
patterns of migration. But Methodism,
which by 1950 boasted having at least one
church in every county in the Great Plains
south of the Canadian boundary, can also look
to its pattern of itinerant ministry, the practice
of sending clergy from place to place to minister
to a scattered flock, as another reason for
its growth. In the Canadian Prairie Provinces,
most of the Methodist, Congregationalist, and
Presbyterian churches joined their parent denominations
in forming the United Church of
Canada in 1925.</p>

<p>In the twentieth century, congregations' associations
with the Southern Baptist Convention
have grown rapidly and extended westward
from a traditional stronghold in the
South into the Great Plains of Texas, Oklahoma,
and New Mexico. In a solid block of
counties in West Texas, stretching from Amarillo
on the north to Odessa on the south,
Baptists account for more than 50 percent of
church membership. Beyond this block, in adjacent
areas of western Oklahoma and eastern
New Mexico, Baptists constitute 25 to 50 percent
of church membership. The main exception
to this dominant Baptist presence in this
entire area is a handful of counties where more
than 25 percent of church members are Catholics,
the result of Hispanic immigration.</p>

<p>The social conservatism of the Southern
Baptist Convention has had a great influence
on ways of life in the Southern Great Plains.
Their abhorrence of alcohol, for example, delayed
the emergence of a successful wine industry
in West Texas until the 1970s and today
makes difficult the passage of any referendum
that proposes easing public access to liquor.</p>

<p>The story of individual Christian groups in
the Plains would fill many volumes. Virtually
every denomination that is not restricted to a
single American region has at least a handful of
congregations in the U.S. Great Plains. By the
late twentieth century, the same held true for
the Canadian Prairie Provinces. But throughout
the Plains there are countless independent
churches as well. Many of the smaller denominations
and independent churches trace
their beginnings to religious movements such
as fundamentalism or pentecostalism that cut
across traditional denominational lines.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Crossdenominational Movements and Currents</head>

<p>Fundamentalism is a many-faceted phenomenon.
Many forces coalesced to give it birth in
the decades surrounding the start of the twentieth
century: a rejection of modern critical
methods of biblical interpretation, perceived
intellectual threats to orthodox Protestant
theological formulation, a surge of interest in
biblical prophecy informed by dispensationalism,
reactions to immigration, urbanization,
industrialization, and a host of others. In the
United States, fundamentalism had its greatest
early impact in the Northeast, particularly
among Baptists and Presbyterians; in Canada,
Toronto and the ministry of the controversial
and colorful Thomas Todhunter Shields were
at the core of early fundamentalism. Fundamentalism's
base of support expanded across
both nations, in part because of the popularity
of the study Bible produced by C. I. Scofield
(the Scofield Reference Bible), first published
in 1909. Scofield's own career in law and ministry
took him to Kansas, Missouri, Colorado,
Texas, and Massachusetts. His personal influence
in the Southern Plains was enhanced especially
by his pastorates in Dallas.</p>

<p>Indeed, it was use of the Scofield Reference
Bible that first drew Canadian Presbyterian
and then Baptist layman William "Bible
Bill" Aberhart into the dispensationalist-fundamentalist
orbit. At the heart of dispensationalism
lies an understanding that history
from Creation to its final consummation is
divided into different epochs or dispensations
and that humanity now is approaching the
final dispensation. Hence there is a passionate
concern for unraveling biblical prophecy to
identify links with contemporary events. This
concern, fostered by a host of prophetic Bible
conferences in the United States and Canada
that started in the 1880s, means that the Bible
itself is of tremendous significance to dispensationalism.
The conviction that the Bible
is an inerrant guide to history cements the
connection between dispensationalism and
fundamentalism.</p>

<p>Aberhart was a dynamic Bible teacher based
for many years at the Westbourne Baptist
Church in Calgary, Alberta, who derived much
of his early thinking from a correspondence
course written by Scofield. Aberhart was quick
to take advantage of advancing media technology
to promote his teaching, issuing a monthly
fundamentalist magazine (Prophetic Times)
and in 1929 beginning a regular radio broadcast
from Calgary that soon gained a large audience.
Indeed, radio was to prove a major
medium for the transmission of evangelical
and fundamentalist thinking throughout the
Plains. Aberhart also founded the Prophetic
Bible Institute that served as an educational
agency and at times as a church.</p>

<p>Unlike many fundamentalists of the 1920s
and 1930s, Aberhart took a keen interest in
economics and politics, adapting the economic
ideas of C. H. Douglas on "Social
Credit" as the foundation for a political party
that for a time dominated the Alberta legislature
and allowed Aberhart to serve as premier
of the province. Many of his social ideas distressed
other fundamentalist leaders, who believed
that Aberhart had abandoned a religious
vocation for political expediency.</p>

<p>A more moderate evangelicalism, albeit
laced with some fundamentalist ideas in popular
understanding, has remained more deeply
entrenched in Protestant religiosity in the
Plains. Mass revivalism and deft use of the
media are largely responsible for its enduring
impact. Evangelist Charles E. Fuller was
among the first to make extensive use of radio
in addition to organizing revival meetings that
drew thousands in attendance. Launching his
radio ministry from California in 1930, Fuller
found that his program, ultimately named the
<title>Old-Fashioned Revival Hour</title>, became one of
the most popular radio shows of the late 1940s
and early 1950s. It reached millions of homes
in the Great Plains of the United States and
Canada.</p>

<p>Further cementing the presence of evangelicalism
in the Plains has been the multifaceted
ministry of Billy Graham. Although
not a native of the region, Graham has held
crusades in many of the major cities of the
Great Plains, proclaiming to millions his gospel
of simple trust in God as the answer to
personal and social problems. Like Aberhart,
Graham has deftly used broadcast media, especially
radio, and publications ranging from
his own <title level="j">Decision</title> magazine to <title level="j">Christianity Today</title>
to make a conservative religious message
plausible and respectable. Today, television
brings virtually every media preacher into the
homes of the Plains.</p>

<p>Modern pentecostalism has also secured a
place in the religious life of the Plains. Revivals
conducted in 1901 by Charles Fox Parham in
Topeka, Kansas, where he had already founded
a Bible college, are one of the formative events
of neo-pentecostalism, with its emphasis on
speaking in tongues and divine healing. A generation
later, in 1948, a revival emanating from
an independent Bible school at North Battleford,
Saskatchewan, was critical in the spread
of the Latter Rain Pentecostal movement
across North America, giving fresh power to
belief in healing through the laying on of
hands. Oral Roberts, perhaps the best-known
healing evangelist of mid-twentieth-century
North America, conducted his own brand of
tent revivals in many Great Plains locales.
Based in Tulsa, Oklahoma, since 1947, Roberts
has been a major force in making a pentecostal
style acceptable in many Protestant circles. All
of these streams of pentecostalism have helped
fuel the growth of both independent churches
and denominations, such as the Assemblies of
God, that emphasize the reality of charismatic
gifts of the Spirit.</p>

<p>More liberal religious currents have also influenced
religious developments in the Plains.
In the later nineteenth and early twentieth
centuries, Social Christianity, or the Social
Gospel, emerged as another response to the
way industrialization and urbanization were
reshaping life in North America. Informed by
modernist theological ideas that applied critical
analysis to Scripture, the Social Gospel
sought to apply the ethical principles derived
from the teachings of Jesus to contemporary
social issues, particularly those having to do
with labor, working conditions in factories,
and living conditions in urban slums. In the
United States, the more industrialized areas of
the Northeast were the major centers of the
Social Gospel impulse, but in Canada its core
was in Winnipeg. This was the result of the
work of the Methodist Salem G. Bland, professor
at Wesley College there, and particularly
of the efforts of another Methodist,
James Shaver Woodsworth, who as head of All
Peoples Mission in Winnipeg had a powerful
ministry among the unemployed and illhoused
of the city. Woodsworth's <title level="m">Strangers
within Our Gates</title> (1909) and <title level="m">My Neighbor</title>
(1911), written for a popular audience, served
to instill Social Gospel ideas in the religiosity
of ordinary men and women.</p>

<p>Another piece of popular literature helped
make Social Gospel principles bywords for the
faithful in the United States. In 1896 Topeka,
Kansas, pastor Charles M. Sheldon published
a series of sermons he had preached to his
Sunday evening congregation. Appearing as a
novel the following year, <title level="m">In His Steps</title> remains
in print today. It represents a critical effort
to personalize and individualize the corporate
ethic of the Social Gospel through its depiction
of a band of women and men who covenant
for one year to ask the question "What
would Jesus do?" before making any business
decision. All are driven to abandon the traditional
trappings of success for work with the
poor and outcast. And although the result is
not the social change sought by the larger
movement, the individuals involved undergo
significant personal transformation. By reaching
a mass audience, Sheldon ensured that the
Social Gospel's impact would not be restricted
to a single denomination in its impact. However,
in both the United States and Canada the
coming of World War I and then the Great
Depression shattered the optimism that undergirded
the Social Gospel's hopes for farreaching,
immediate social change. Nevertheless,
its heritage lived on in the United States
in the enduring strains of progressive politics
and in much of the New Deal promoted by
Franklin Roosevelt, and in Canada in the policies
of the Cooperative Commonwealth Federation
government that came to power in
Saskatchewan in 1944.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Other Religious Movements and Communities</head>

<p>Countless other religious movements and
communities have found the Plains fertile soil
for propagating their own visions of life here
and hereafter. Some groups have come into
the Plains because they believed that conditions
there favored their growth. For example,
in 1887 Charles Ora Card led a small group of
Latter-day Saints, better known as Mormons,
from Utah to Alberta, where they founded
what is today Cardston. At the time they left
Salt Lake City, the U.S. government was placing
increasing pressure on the Mormons to
renounce the practice of polygamy as a condition for admitting Utah as a state. What drew
Card's group to Canada was both the limited
toleration of already existing polygamous
marriages (although not recognition of future
ones) and the availability of land suitable for
the irrigation methods developed by the Mormons.
From Alberta, Mormon missionaries
fanned out across Canada.</p>

<p>The famous mid-nineteenth-century gold
rush and then the need for workers to build
rail lines brought an upsurge in immigration
to Canada and the United States from Asia.
Chinese and Japanese settlers helped establish
a Buddhist presence in western Canada; Lethbridge,
Alberta, has remained the center of a
vibrant Japanese Buddhist community. More
recently, new immigrants from South Asia
have broadened the ethnic and religious pluralism
of the Great Plains, though their total
numbers remain small. Nonetheless, the presence
of a wider range of Asian religions promises
to bring new challenges. In Canada, for
example, there has been conflict centering on
the growing Sikh community, some of whose
members have fought government regulations
that sought to require them to wear
the traditional headgear rather than turbans
while serving in the Royal Canadian Mounted
Police.</p>

<p>Throughout the Plains, the Jewish population
remains small, concentrated more in the
larger towns and cities. Yet the Plains plays
a significant role in Jewish history in North
America. The large emigration from Russia
around the turn of the century included thousands
of Jews. Although many remained in the
major ports of entry for immigrants, several
thousand ultimately made their way to the
Plains, some as a result of the conscious efforts
of Jewish groups to establish agricultural colonies
and farm communities. In such settings,
it was thought, Jewish identity would be less
threatened by the religious pluralism of the
larger culture, and immigrants would be able
to replicate their traditional agrarian life without
the danger of the Russian pogroms that
had forced many to leave their homeland. A
Jewish farming community was organized in
Oxbow, Saskatchewan, in 1892; other Canadian
ventures followed in Alberta and Manitoba.
Winnipeg remains an important Jewish
center. Farther south, the Am Olam, a group
of Jewish farmers in eastern South Dakota,
owe their genesis as a community to similar
impulses. Early in the twentieth century, some
Jewish leaders in the United States mustered
support for the "Galveston plan," an organized
movement to bring immigrant Jews directly
to Galveston, Texas, and from there to
relocate them in towns and farming communities
scattered throughout the interior of
North America. As with similar programs, the
stated rationale for the Galveston plan was to
protect Jewish immigrants from the religious
and social corruption of the cities in the East.</p>

<p>Although Islam in North America has witnessed
steady expansion since the close of World
War II, so that it is now among the fastestgrowing
religions in the United States and Canada,
Muslims have been in the Plains at least
since the start of the century. Evidence reveals,
for example, that in 1900 a Muslim family in
Ross, North Dakota, was using their home as a
mosque for communal prayer on a regular
basis. Around the same time, Muslim immigrants
came to Edmonton, Alberta, working as
peddlers. The community there, although
small, was su.ciently stable and prosperous
that it erected a mosque in 1938. It has continued
to grow to the point that in Edmonton,
Muslims are now able to take advantage of
government provisions that allow for religious
instruction in public schools after regular
school hours.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">An Increasing Diversity</head>

<p>Over the years, the religious life of the Great
Plains has become increasingly diverse. Despite
years of suppression, the religions of the
Indigenous peoples of the Great Plains have
endured and adapted to changing circumstances.
The westward migration of Americans
on both sides of the border and the heavy
influx of European immigrants coming in
the later nineteenth and early twentieth centuries
added greatly to the diversity. In countless
towns and communities from Alberta to
Texas, the heritage of the immigrant past endures
in religious beliefs and landscapes. More
recent immigration from Mexico (the latter
augmenting a Hispanic and Roman Catholic
presence that has existed on the fringes of the
Southern Great Plains for centuries) and from
Asia has contributed even more detail to this
rich tapestry of regional religious life.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">ARCHITECTURE</hi>: <ref n="egp.arc.040">Religious Architecture</ref>
/ <hi rend="smallcaps">EDUCATION</hi>: <ref n="egp.edu.019">Indian Boarding Schools, United States</ref>; <ref n="egp.edu.020">Indian Residential Schools, Canada</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">EUROPEAN AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ea.008">Douglas, Thomas (Earl of Selkirk)</ref>; <ref n="egp.ea.022">Jews</ref>; <ref n="egp.ea.038">Ukrainians</ref> /
<hi rend="smallcaps">LAW</hi>: <ref n="egp.law.037">North Dakota Anti-Garb Law</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">NATIVE
AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.na.102">Sacred Geography</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">PROTEST
AND DISSENT</hi>: <ref n="egp.pd.002">Aberhart, William</ref>; <ref n="egp.pd.061">Woodsworth, James Shaver</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">WAR</hi>: <ref n="egp.war.056">Wounded Knee Massacre</ref>.</p>
</div2>

<closer>
<signed>Charles H. Lippy<lb/>
University of Tennessee at Chattanooga</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Ahlstrom, Sydney E. <title level="m">A Religious History of the American
People</title>. New Haven <hi rend="smallcaps">CT</hi>: Yale University Press, 1972.</bibl> <bibl>Blau,
Joseph L. <title level="m">Judaism in America: From Curiosity to Third
Faith</title>. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1976.</bibl> <bibl>Bowden,
Henry Warner. <title level="m">American Indians and Christian Missions</title>.
Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1981.</bibl> <bibl>Epp,
Frank H. <title level="m">Mennonites in Canada, 1786–1920: The History of
a Separate People</title>. Toronto: Macmillan Publishing Company,
1974.</bibl> <bibl>Epp, Frank H. <title level="m">Mennonites in Canada, 1920–
1940</title>. Toronto: Macmillan Publishing Company, 1982.</bibl>
<bibl>Gaustad, Edwin Scott. <title level="m">A Religious History of America</title>. San
Francisco: Harper and Row, 1990.</bibl> <bibl>Hennesey, James, S.J.
<title level="m">America's Catholics: A History of the Roman Catholic Community
in the United States</title>. New York: Oxford University
Press, 1981.</bibl> <bibl>Kilbourn, William, A. C. Forrest, and Patrick
Watson. <title level="m">Religion in Canada: The Spiritual Development of
a Nation</title>. Toronto: McClelland and Stewart, Ltd. 1968.</bibl>
<bibl>Lippy, Charles H., and Peter W. Williams, eds. <title level="m">Encyclopedia
of the American Religious Experience</title>. New York:
Charles Scribners Sons, 1988.</bibl> <bibl>Noll, Mark A. <title level="m">A History of
Christianity in the United States and Canada</title>. Grand
Rapids <hi rend="smallcaps">MI</hi>: William B. Eerdmans Publishing Co., 1992.</bibl>
<bibl>Woodcock, George, and Ivan Avakumovic. <title level="m">The Doukhobors</title>.
Toronto: Oxford University Press, 1968.</bibl> <bibl><title level="m">Yearbook of
American and Canadian Churches</title>. Nashville: Abingdon
Press, published annually.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>