<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ha.024">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Lisa, Manuel (1772-1820)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>David J. Wishart</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ha.024</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</author>. <title level="a">"Lisa, Manuel (1772-1820)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">360</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-25</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">LISA, MANUEL (1772-1820)</head>

<p>In a letter to William Clark, written in 1817,
Manuel Lisa offered this self-assessment: "I go
a great distance while some are considering
whether they will start today or tomorrow. I
impose upon myself great privations." Indeed
he did. Ambitious and impetuous, Lisa was
the first St. Louis trader to respond to Lewis
and Clark's revelation of an area "richer in
beaver and otter than any country on earth" at
the headwaters of the Missouri.</p>

<p>Lisa was born in New Orleans on September
8, 1772, to Christobal de Lisa and Maria
Ignacia Rodriquez. He learned his trade on
the Mississippi and Ohio Rivers in the 1790s
before settling on a Spanish land grant in St.
Louis. There he went into direct competition
with the resident French trading aristocracy
over the commerce with the Osage Indians.
But after the return of Lewis and Clark, he
turned his sights to the upper Missouri River</p>

<p>In the spring of 1807 Lisa organized an expedition
of about sixty men, which ascended
the Missouri and built a trading post, Fort
Raymond, at the confluence of the Yellowstone
and Bighorn Rivers. From there he dispatched
trappers to the Rocky Mountains
while plying a successful trade with the Crows.
Encouraged by the large quantity of furs they
obtained, Lisa returned to St. Louis to mount
a larger expedition.</p>

<p>In 1809, 160 men in the employ of Lisa's
Missouri Fur Company left St. Louis for the
upper Missouri. They established posts along
the river for all the Indians who wanted to
trade, thus satisfying the Indians' wants and
keeping the river open, while at the same time
garnering furs. But Lisa's main objective was
to trap in the headwaters of the upper Missouri,
and there his plans disintegrated. The
furs were there, but so were the Blackfeet.
When his enterprise was abandoned in the
summer of 1810, only thirty packs of beaver
had been accumulated, and twenty of his men
were dead.</p>

<p>Lisa's trading activities&#8211;indeed all the activities
of the St. Louis fur trade&#8211;were curtailed
during the War of 1812. When trade resumed
in 1819, Lisa formed a second Missouri
Fur Company with the same objectives as the
first. But before the enterprise got under way,
Lisa contracted a serious illness. The enterprising
Spaniard died in St. Louis in the summer
of 1820 and was buried in what became
Bellefontaine Cemetery. He never realized his
ambition to create a fur empire that combined
trading along the Missouri River with trapping
in the Rocky Mountains, but he left a
blueprint that others, like William Ashley,
would follow with great success.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">INDUSTRY</hi>: <ref n="egp.ind.022">Fur Trade</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>David J. Wishart<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Oglesby, Richard E. <title level="m">Manuel Lisa and the Opening of the Missouri Fur Trade</title>. Norman: University of Oklahoma
Press, 1963.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>