<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.pg.047">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Meighen, Arthur (1874-1960)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Laura Madokoro</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.pg.047</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Madokoro, Laura">Laura Madokoro</author>. <title level="a">"Meighen, Arthur (1874-1960)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">674-675</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-30</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">MEIGHEN, ARTHUR (1874-1960)</head>

<p>Arthur Meighen has been described as the
greatest Canadian parliamentarian ever. Born
on June 16, 1874, in the small community of St.
Mary's, Ontario, Meighen spent most of his
life in politics, becoming prime minister of
Canada in 1920 and again briefly in 1926.</p>

<p>Raised in a staunch Protestant environment,
Meighen was a quiet and studious youth. His
most outstanding characteristics were his abilities
as an orator and debater, which he displayed
even in his earliest schooling. After
studying mathematics at the University of Toronto
and trying his luck as a shopkeeper and
teacher, Arthur Meighen headed west to seek
adventure in the Prairies. After a failed attempt
in the dried-fruit industry, Meighen proceeded
to article as a lawyer and soon found
himself established in the small town of Portage
La Prairie, Manitoba. It was here that
Arthur Meighen discovered two great loves,
Isabel Cox, whom he married in 1904, and the
Conservative Party of Canada.</p>

<p>Arthur Meighen proved to be a most loyal
party member. First elected to Parliament in
1908, Meighen became an eloquent defender
of a variety of government initiatives, including
tariffs, naval policies, and railway nationalization.
Meighen was also the author and
instigator of several of the most controversial
pieces of legislation in Canadian history. During
World War I he prepared the Wartime
Elections Bill, the War Measures Act, and the
Military Service Act, which opponents allege
corrupted the electoral process and infringed
traditional civil rights.</p>

<p>The aftermath of World War I was an unsettling
time in Canada. The Union government
that had steered the country through the turbulent
wartime years came to an end. When
Arthur Meighen became leader of the ruling
Conservative Party in 1920, following prime
minister Sir Robert Borden's resignation, he
faced the difficult task of keeping not only the
party but the entire country united. Meighen's
uneasy relationship with particular parts of the
country limited his effectiveness in this capacity.
In 1919 Meighen had acted as mediator in
the Winnipeg General Strike. When violence
erupted, many criticized him for being unsympathetic
to labor concerns. Furthermore, western
farmers were angry with Meighen for having
sent their sons to war after promising that
they would be protected from conscription.
This sentiment was echoed in Quebec, where
many were also angry with Meighen for introducing
wartime conscription.</p>

<p>While Meighen enjoyed international success
at the Imperial Conference of 1921, his
inability to band the country together resulted
in his electoral defeat that year at the hands of
his long-time rival, Mackenzie King. Although
he formed a minority government in 1926 after
a constitutional crisis resulted in King's
resignation, Meighen's government was shortlived,
lasting only three days. Meighen retreated
from the fray to pursue business interests
in Toronto, but the lure of politics proved
irresistible. On February 3, 1932, he was appointed
to the Senate of Canada. Determined
to play a leading role, Meighen was one of
the first to caution about events developing
in Europe, but his warnings went unheeded.
Meighen left politics forever in 1942, after suffering
a crushing electoral defeat as he sought
the Conservative Party leadership a final time.
He died on August 4, 1960, in Toronto.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">PROTEST AND DISSENT</hi>: <ref n="egp.pd.057">Winnipeg General Strike</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Laura Madokoro<lb/>
University of Waterloo</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>English, John. <title level="m">Arthur Meighen</title>. Don Mills, Ontario: Fitzhenry
and Whiteside Publishers, 1977.</bibl> <bibl>Graham, Roger.
<title level="m">Arthur Meighen: A Biography</title>. Toronto: Clarke, Irwin and
Company, 1960–65.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>