<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.arc.038">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Railroad Depots</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>James J. Reisdorff</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.arc.038</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Reisdorff, James J.">James J. Reisdorff</author>. <title level="a">"Railroad Depots."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">90-91</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-13</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">RAILROAD DEPOTS</head>

<p>During the era when railroads were the main
method of transportation in the Great Plains,
the railroad depot was both the economic and
social gateway to the community it served.
The railroad station, whether a roughly hewn
shack or an ornate masonry structure, was the
place where people could assemble to board a
train for faraway places or welcome arriving
travelers. It provided a central delivery point
where a community's life-sustaining goods
could be shipped or delivered by rail. And in
the period from approximately 1865 to 1920 it
served as a place where people could come to
hear the news of the day, socialize with others,
or simply be entertained by the daily arrival
and departure of the trains.</p>

<p>When railroad builders first pushed their
lines west across the Plains, they realized the
importance of establishing railroad stations
approximately every ten miles. The concept of
having closely spaced stations made sense at a
time when farmers used horse-drawn wagons
to deliver their goods for shipment by rail.
These stations also served as communication
points for dispatching trains, fueling facilities
for steam locomotives, and potential town
sites that could provide future revenue for the
carrier.</p>

<p>For isolated communities established on
the Plains prior to the arrival of a railroad,
obtaining a railroad station once the tracks
did arrive in the area was vital to their continued
existence. Quite frequently, local citizens
and railroad officials disputed the exact
location of the town's depot. Most often, the
railroad won out. And if the depot was located
at some distance from the original town site,
residents would usually relocate to the depot
site.</p>

<p>In their initial rush to lay tracks, railroad
companies often hastily used portable shacks
or old boxcar bodies as the first depot for a
new community. If the community grew into
an established town, the initial roughshod
structure was replaced with a frame depot of a
standard design adopted by the particular rail
carrier. These designs allowed depots of nearly
identical appearance to be cheaply and efficiently
constructed at hundreds of towns
along the lines of a rail system. Minor changes
in design were made to conform to the needs
of a particular station site; for example, station
buildings in more isolated areas had living
quarters for the station agent.</p>

<p>Most depots constructed for small towns
otherwise followed the combination station
plan devised by railroad architects. This combination
design essentially provided all railroad
services for the public under one roof. A
ticket and work office for the agent was most
often situated in the center, flanked by a passenger
waiting room and a freight room for
express shipments. As business grew at some
stations, a separate building for freight business
was established.</p>

<p>Major railroad companies of the Great
Plains such as the Atchison, Topeka and Santa
Fe in the United States and the Canadian Pacific
in Canada came to be closely identified
with their standard design depots (much as
fast food restaurants are today). However,
as towns grew, local promoters often pressed
railroad o.cials to replace their community's
old wood depot with a larger and more ornate
building of brick or stone. The railroad station
was the first impression that travelers
received of a town, and citizens obviously
wanted their station to reflect a prosperous
image. Railroad officials would sometimes
comply, especially if the community was a vital
center for railroad operations such as a
county seat or college town.</p>

<p>The rise of competing forms of transportation
in the early to mid–twentieth century
eventually all but eliminated the railroad depot
as a Great Plains landmark. Passenger
trains and branch lines were abandoned as
first the automotive age and then the Great
Depression cut into railroad profits. Fewer
freight trains were needed as steam locomotives
were replaced by diesel engines that
could pull longer trains. New communication
technologies eliminated the need for an agent
to be employed at each town. All these factors
prompted the major railroad companies serving
the Great Plains region to close almost
all their remaining railroad stations by the
late 1970s.</p>

<p>Currently, a limited number of Plains depots
remain open to the public in communities
that have government-subsidized passenger
train service. But the majority of extant
station buildings have been acquired by private
citizens or public municipalities and converted
to other uses. A number of these structures
now serve as museums devoted to a time
when adventure began or ended on a railroad
station platform.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">TRANSPORTATION</hi>: <ref n="egp.tra.028">Railroads, United States</ref>; <ref n="egp.tra.029">Railways, Canada</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>James J. Reisdorff<lb/>
David City, Nebraska<lb/>
</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Grant, H. Roger. <title level="m">Kansas Depots</title>. Topeka: Kansas State Historical
Society, 1990.</bibl> <bibl>Grant, H. Roger, and Charles W.
Bohi. <title level="m">The Country Railroad Station in America</title>. Boulder
<hi rend="smallcaps">CO</hi>: Pruett Publishing Company, 1978.</bibl> <bibl>Potter, Janet Greenstein.
<title level="m">Great American Railroad Stations</title>. New York: John Wiley and Sons, 1996.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>