<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.na.006">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Archaic Period Sites</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>George C. Frison</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.na.006</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Frison, George C.">George C. Frison</author>. <title level="a">"Archaic Period Sites."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">563-564</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-03</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">ARCHAIC PERIOD SITES</head>

<p>For approximately 6,000 years, between about
8,000 and 2,000 years ago, the Archaic period
in the Great Plains was a time of human adjustment
to changing ecological conditions.
Paleo-Indian bison hunting decreased markedly
after about 9,000 years ago, due to a
steady deterioration of ecological conditions.
Subsequently there were several late Paleo-
Indian groups, such as Lusk, Angostura, Frederick,
and James Allen, which were beginning
to shift toward the use of small animal and
plant resources. By about 8,000 years ago,
both bison and human populations in the
Great Plains had decreased significantly. Some
groups may have moved into the foothills and
mountains to the west and others into the
prairies on the east. The Plains was not abandoned
during the Archaic period, but ecological
conditions made it a much less desirable
place.</p>

<p>Much of what is known about the Plains
Archaic period comes from archeological sites
on the edges of, and just outside, the Plains. A
widespread change in projectile point styles
from lanceolate to notched forms is arbitrarily
used to mark the beginning of the Plains Archaic
period. Some argue that the change was
the result of new groups moving into the area,
while others believe it was simply a technological
modification accepted by the existing residents.
The best evidence for these changes is
found in areas adjacent to the Plains and in
areas of topographic relief within the Plains,
such as the Black Hills of western South Dakota
and northeast Wyoming and the Pryor
Mountains in southern Montana.</p>

<p>In the Northern Plains, the Early Plains Archaic,
also known as the Altithermal, is dated
from about 8,000 to 5,500 years ago; the Middle
Plains Archaic lasted from about 5,500 to
3,000 years ago; and the Late Plains Archaic
lasted from about 3,000 years ago until between
2,000 and 1,500 years ago. A slightly
different chronology is used in the Central
and Southern Plains. The Early Archaic period
there is 8,500 to 6,500 years ago; the Middle
Archaic is 6,500 to 4,500 years ago; and the
Late Archaic is 4,500 to 2,500 years ago.</p>

<p>Evidence from the Early Plains Archaic suggests
that the Black Hills may have been a kind
of oasis where bison were able to maintain
their numbers. The Hawken site in northeast
Wyoming, a 6,500-year-old bison kill site, contained
animals that were intermediate in size
(probably <hi rend="italic">Bison occidentalis</hi>), smaller than the
ones found in earlier Paleo-Indian kills but
larger than the modern bison found in kill sites
after about 5,500 years ago. The Itasca site,
close to the Plains in Minnesota and dating
from between 7,000 and 8,000 years ago, contained
similar bison. The Cherokee site in Iowa
has Late Paleo-Indian and Early Archaic bison
evidence. The Rustad and Smilden-Rostburg
sites in western North Dakota are Early Archaic
sites with bison remains. The lowest level
at the Oxbow Dam site in southern Saskatchewan
is Early Archaic. The Logan Creek complex
in eastern Nebraska and Iowa and the Sutter
site in eastern Kansas are also Early Archaic.
Early Archaic sites in the Southern Plains include
the Gore Pit site in south-central Oklahoma
and the Wilson Leonard site on the Edwards
Plateau, which has a stratified sequence of
Early through Late Archaic levels.</p>

<p>Pronghorn remains are found in Great
Plains sites of all ages. The Trappers Point site
at a seasonal migration route along the Green
River, just beyond the Plains in western Wyoming,
contains communal pronghorn kills
dating from about 8,000 to 5,000 years ago
and is a strong indicator of similar pronghorn
procurement throughout much of the Plains.</p>

<p>The Medicine House and Split Rock pit
house sites along the North Platte River in
southern Wyoming contain evidence of the
use of grinding stones, plants, and small animals.
Rock shelters and open sites in the Big
Horn Mountains of northern Wyoming and
in the Pryor Mountains of southern Montana
also hold Early Archaic evidence.</p>

<p>Improved climatic conditions and a resurgence
of bison hunting appeared during the
Middle Plains Archaic, around 5,500 years ago
on the Northern Plains. The Head-Smashed-
In buffalo jump near Lethbridge, Alberta, is
one of the more spectacular of these bison
procurement features, showing continuous
use from the end of the Early Plains Archaic
into historic times. Oxbow Dam, Mortlach,
and Long Creek are deep, stratified sites in
southern Saskatchewan with both Middle and
Late Archaic levels.</p>

<p>McKean sites, named after the McKean site
in the Wyoming Black Hills, are widespread
over the Northern Plains. The Scoggin site, for
example, a bone bed inside an artificial bison
corral, is located in western Wyoming close to
the North Platte River. The Laidlaw site in
southern Alberta is Middle Archaic, with
drive lines and a pit used to trap pronghorns.
Flat stone grinding slabs, manos (handheld
grinding stones), and stone-filled fire pits are
numerous in the southern part of the McKean
occupation area, indicating a trend toward
broad-spectrum hunting and gathering.</p>

<p>The Middle Archaic of the Edwards Plateau
of Texas is well represented at the Wilson
Leonard site by a wide variety of diagnostic
traits. Middle Archaic levels are also present at
the Magic Mountain site on the Front Range
west of Denver, Colorado.</p>

<p>Late Plains Archaic sites are widely distributed
throughout the Great Plains. First
thought to be late Paleo-Indian because of
large lanceolate projectile points, the Late Archaic
Nebo Hill complex, widespread along
the Kansas-Missouri border, contains a wide
variety of artifact material, features, and faunal
and plant food resources. The Late Archaic
Pelican Lake complex, named from sites in
southern Saskatchewan, is found over most of
the Northern Plains. Pelican Lake levels are
found at Head-Smashed-In buffalo jump in
Alberta and in jump and arroyo bison kills in
Montana. South of the Montana border, Pelican
Lake demonstrates less dietary emphasis
on bison and more on smaller animals, including
pronghorn and deer. Grinding stones
and stone-filled food-preparation pits are also
common. Along the Powder River in northern
Wyoming and Montana are arroyo bison kill
sites known as Yonkee from a site in southern
Montana, with dates of about 2,500 years ago.
Stone circles (tipi rings) are widespread features
from this period, most of which are believed
to have held down the edges of hide
coverings of conical lodges.</p>

<p>Besant cultural groups, another Late Archaic
group named from sites in southern
Saskatchewan, may have been the most sophisticated
pedestrian bison hunters to appear
in the Plains. The Ruby site in eastern
Wyoming is a large bison corral alongside a
religious structure. Farther west is the Muddy
Creek site, a large Besant bison corral located
in a depression, with a wooden ramp built to
stampede the animals into the enclosure.
Large stone circle concentrations represent associated
living areas, and a large boulder pile
on a high point overlooking the site is a religious
structure.</p>

<p>In the Central and Southern Plains, the
Late Archaic subsistence strategy was broadspectrum
hunting and gathering. There is a
2,600-year-old bison jump at Bonfire Shelter
at the mouth of the Pecos River in Texas. Late
Archaic groups on the eastern margins of the
Great Plains may have been encouraging the
propagation of native plants, but there is no
evidence of corn, beans, or squash.</p>

<p>Following the Archaic in the Northern
Plains was the Late Prehistoric period, between
about 2,000 and 1,500 years ago, which
witnessed the appearance of the bow and arrow
and intensified bison hunting. Avonlea,
one of the earliest hunting groups to use the
bow and arrow, was contemporaneous with
some late Besant groups. On the eastern edge
of the Plains, agricultural villagers with ceramics
and Central American cultigens appeared
and persisted into historic times.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT</hi>: <ref n="egp.pe.010">Bison</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>George C. Frison</signed>
University of Wyoming-Laramie</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Johnson, Alfred E., ed. <title level="m">Archaic Prehistory on the Prairie Plains Border</title>. Lawrence: University of Kansas Publications
in Anthropology, no. 12 (1980)</bibl> <bibl>Larson, Mary Lou and Julie Francis eds. <title level="m">Changing Perspectives on the Archaic on the Northwestern Plains and Rocky Mountains</title>. Vermillion: University of South Dakota Press, 1997.</bibl> <bibl>Wood, W.
Raymond, ed. <title level="m">Archaeology on the Great Plains</title>. Lawrence: University Press of Kansas, 1998.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>