<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.art.057 SYSTEM "egp.art.057.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.art.057">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Stanley, John Mix (1814-1872)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Charles Vollan</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.art.057</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Vollan, Charles">Charles Vollan</author>. <title level="a">"Stanley, John Mix (1814-1872)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">129-130</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-22</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">STANLEY, JOHN MIX (1814-1872)</head>

<figure n="egp.art.057" rend="granted">
<figDesc>John Mix Stanley. Herd of Bison Near Lake Jesse, ca. 1853. Color lithograph.</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>John Mix Stanley was one of a number of
painters who came west in the first half of the
eighteenth century to paint what they believed
were the last days of the Native Americans.
Born in Canandaigua, New York, on January
14, 1814, Stanley progressed from painting
signs to painting portraits and landscapes. He
was enamored with George Catlin's works and
followed his example, retracing some of the
same ground and even painting portraits of
the same people.</p>

<p>Stanley traveled throughout Indian Territory
from 1842 to 1845. In 1846 he accompanied
American soldiers during the Mexican War,
arriving in Santa Fe just weeks after Stephen
Watts Kearny's Army of the West. Kearny hired
him as a topographical draftsman, and Stanley
fought in battle under Kearny in San Diego.
Probably the most traveled of western artists,
Stanley soon made his way to Oregon, where
he narrowly avoided being killed in the Whitman
massacre. He spent one year in Hawaii
before returning to New York in 1850. There he
began the first of several unsuccessful attempts
to sell Congress his "Indian Gallery," approximately
150 paintings done in Indian Territory
and the Southwest. Unable to sell his paintings
to the government, he accepted an offer by the
Smithsonian Institution to house his works. In
1853 he joined the northern railroad survey
headed by Isaac Stevens, producing sixty images
that were printed in the official reports of
the expedition, several of which are of Great
Plains scenes.</p>

<p>His western travel behind him, Stanley
moved to Washington <hi rend="smallcaps">DC</hi>, where he further
labored to sell his paintings to Congress. Stanley
never again traveled among the Native
Americans, but he continued to paint them,
based on memory and imagination. Like Catlin,
Stanley believed that the Native Americans
were incompatible with American civilization
and would fade away, a process he believed
inevitable and ultimately just.</p>

<p>Exhibiting great realism, in part because he
was one of the first artists to base his work on
photographs, which he began using in the late
1840s, Stanley's works show greater skill than
those of Catlin. <title>The Trial of Red Jacket</title> (1868) is
his best-known work. Stanley's "Indian Gallery"
was lost in the great Smithsonian Institution
fire of January 1865, and a second
fire that year at the New York City museum of
P. T. Barnum, followed by an 1872 fire in his
own studio, destroyed most of his remaining
works. Stanley died of heart failure in Detroit,
Michigan, on April 10, 1872, still hoping for
compensation for his destroyed work. His remaining
works are housed in the Smithsonian
Institution; the Gilcrease Museum in Tulsa,
Oklahoma; the Detroit Institute of Arts; the
Stark Museum of Art in Orange, Texas; and
the Buffalo Historical Society.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Charles Vollan<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Dippie, Brian W. <title level="m">Catlin and His Contemporaries: The Politics of Patronage</title>. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press,
1990.</bibl> <bibl>Taft, Robert. <title level="m">Artists and Illustrators of the Old West, 1850–1900</title>. New York: Bonanza Books, 1953.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>