<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.art.038">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Jefferys, Charles W. (1869–1951)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Norman A. Geske</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.art.038</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Hepburn, Suzanne">Suzanne Hepburn</author>. <title level="a">"Jefferys, Charles W. (1869–1951)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">122</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-22</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">JEFFERYS, CHARLES W. (1869–1951)</head>

<p>Born in Rochester, England, on August 25,
1869, Charles William Jefferys immigrated
with his family to Philadelphia in 1875. He
moved to Canada in 1878 and settled in Toronto
three years later. He took evening classes
at the Ontario School of Art and Design (now
known as the Ontario College of Art and Design),
had a five-year apprenticeship with
the Toronto Lithographic Company, and received
art lessons from accomplished Canadian
painter George A. Reid. Under the instruction
of C. M. Manly of the newly formed
Toronto Art Students League, which he joined
in 1888, Jefferys gained fundamentals and
sound practices that were the foundation of
his work throughout his life. He became Canada's
earliest and most influential historical
illustrator and muralist.</p>

<p>When Jefferys first journeyed to the Prairie
Provinces, the vastness and simple beauty of
the landscape shattered his stifling commitment
to detail, a commitment engendered by
his career as a reportage illustrator and spare
time spent capturing the rugged yet intricate
details of the Ontario landscape. Jefferys's first
Prairie visit marked the beginning of a prolific
and creative episode in his artistic life.</p>

<p>During the early 1900s Jefferys journeyed
across Canada as an official illustrator for numerous
Canadian magazines, playing a key
role in recording the development of the West.
When he first arrived in the southern regions
of Saskatchewan and Alberta Jefferys was awestruck
by the wide-open spaces and expansive
skies. The subtle but complex palette of prairie
colors offered artistic opportunities that
rivaled other rocky outcroppings of the Canadian
Shield.</p>

<p>His first Prairie painting, <title>Afternoon in the Wheat Fields</title> (1906), was completed during
a visit to Portage-La-Prairie in northwestern
Winnipeg, Manitoba. This work inspired his
first large oil painting, entitled <title>Wheat Stacks on the Prairie</title> (1907), and both are examples of
his exploration of this newly discovered and
rich palette. Also from this period and in this
vein are <title>Western Sunlight (Last Mountain Lake)</title> and <title>A Storm on the Prairie (Allegro Maestoso)</title>, both from 1911. The latter two oils
mark the artist's maturation in this subject
matter.</p>

<p>A pioneer in Canadian landscape painting,
Jefferys inspired the Group of Seven and their
followers through his support of native Canadian
subject matter. He died in Toronto on
October 8, 1951.</p>


<closer>
<signed>Suzanne Hepburn<lb/>
Trianon Gallery</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Brown, Craig. <title level="m">The Illustrated History of Canada</title>. Toronto:
Key Porter Books, 1997.</bibl> <bibl>Reid, Dennis. <title level="m">A Concise History of Canadian Painting</title>. Toronto: Oxford University Press,
1973.</bibl> <bibl>Stacey, Robert H. <title level="m">C. W. Jefferys</title>. Ottawa: National
Gallery/National Museums of Canada, 1985.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>