<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fol.033">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Plains Indian Narratives</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Rodney Frey</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2009</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fol.033</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2009</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2009 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Frey, Rodney">Rodney Frey</author>. <title level="a">"Plains Indian Narratives."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">308-309</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-16</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">PLAINS INDIAN NARRATIVES</head>

<p>For the Indian peoples of the Plains, narratives,
or what are often referred to as oral traditions,
convey their most cherished values
and contribute to the perpetuation of their
worlds. The narratives encompass a variety of
categories, two of the most prominent being
stories of creation and tales of human heroes.
While recognizing the rich variation of narratives
that issue from the tribal diversity of the
region, it can be generalized that creation stories
typically involve powerful mythic beings,
often identified by animal names, who transform
a dangerous world and prepare it for the
coming of the human peoples. In the "earth
diver" accounts among the Arapahos, Blackfoot,
and Crows, for example, mud is brought
forth from the bottom of a primordial sea by a
waterbird and, with a small piece of the earth,
Coyote, or Old Man, fashions the landscape,
creates other animals and plants, helps establish
various customs and institutions, and ultimately
molds from the earth and gives life
to the first human beings. These ancient personages
simultaneously embrace the traits
and qualities of human, animal, and spiritual
beings, and, through their deeds, display tremendous
transformative powers.</p>

<p>Paramount among these creation mythic
beings is the trickster, known by the Blackfoot
as Napi or Old Man, by the Crows as Isaahkawuattee
or Old Man Coyote, by the Lakotas as
Iktomi or Spider, and by many tribes simply as
the Coyote. While acknowledged as a benevolent
creator, the trickster can also exhibit a
self-serving character. Old Man Coyote might
attempt to apply deception and trickery to gain
a free meal, the woman of his dreams, or some
other object of his desires. Yet Coyote's elaborate
schemes to outwit an opponent are just as
likely to end in failure, with himself being
duped by his own trickery and made to look
foolish.</p>

<p>Hero tales express the ideals of courage,
brotherhood, generosity, and self-effacing
valor. In the "Scar Face" (or "Burnt Face")
stories of the Blackfoot or Crows, for example,
the protagonist finds himself disfigured, poor,
and ostracized, and consequently unable to
obtain full adult status and marry. Alone, he
sets out on a great journey to face seemingly
overwhelming obstacles and challenges. Because
of his bravery, generosity, and "heart,"
Scar Face receives a guardian spirit and its
powerful assistance, his physical shortcomings
are removed and any antagonists overcome,
his family position is restored, he is allowed
to marry, and he goes on to live a full
and bountiful life. In the Blackfoot story, Scar
Face, like other culture heroes, also brings an
important ceremonial institution, the Sun
Dance, to his people.</p>

<p>Embedded within the oral traditions are essential
values and discernible lessons. Key
among these values is the understanding that
the world and its many inhabitants are spiritually
endowed and maintained, that the animal
peoples share in a fundamental kinship
with the human peoples, and that reciprocity
is the means by which one should relate to
other kinsmen, whether human or animal. An
elk is addressed as a "brother" and will offer
its meat to a hunter when properly respected.
An eagle can become a "father" as a result of
the food and water sacrifices offered during a
vision quest, and, from the spiritual medicine
bestowed during the vision, the eagle can
guide, nurture, and bring health to a person
throughout his life. From the narratives one
learns the likely consequences of being a selfserving
Coyote, and from the hero tales one is
encouraged to seek the assistance of a guardian
spirit and strive to benefit others.</p>

<p>Because the narratives of the Plains Indian
emanate from an oral-based medium, the act
of storytelling is an essential component of the
story. In the past, a storyteller had to have the
right to tell stories, typically having inherited
the authority. Both men and women could
become accomplished storytellers. For most
tribes it was only during the winter season,
from the first frost in the fall until the first
thunder heard in the spring, that the stories of
Coyote should be told. Again, acknowledging
variation from storyteller to storyteller, it can
be said that among the various styles and techniques
exhibited by storytellers were the use of
repetition of phrases to signal key actions
within the narrative, the singing of associated
songs, the dramatic use of intonation and
pauses, the accentuation of body movement
and hand gesturing, and the requirement that
listeners of the story affirm their involvement
in the story by periodically saying aloud, <hi rend="italic">&#233;e</hi>
(yes), or motioning in some other fashion.
Should the storyteller fail to receive such acknowledgments,
the telling would immediately
cease for the evening.</p>

<p>The act of storytelling is made particularly
potent through the use of Native language.
For example, when told in the Crow language,
the words of the story are understood as having
the power to bring forth and manifest that
which is being spoken. This pivotal notion is
conveyed in the Crow term <hi rend="italic">dassh&#250;ssua</hi>, literally
meaning "breaking with the mouth." That
which comes though the mouth has the power
to affect the world. The understanding of the
creative power of language, coupled with the
various techniques used by storytellers, encourages
listeners to become participants within
the story, traveling the same trails alongside
the Coyote or Scar Face.</p>

<p>In addition to disseminating the knowledge
and wisdom brought forth by the heroic and
mythic figures celebrated in the narratives,
oral traditions have another essential role. The
narratives help re-create and revitalize the
worlds of the Plains Indians. In the act of telling
of the deeds of Coyote and Scar Face, that
which is conveyed in word and gesture is
brought to life, viewed, and engaged in by the
participants in the oral tradition. A landscape
is renewed and a people are reinvigorated. Today,
the telling of the oral traditions remains
an essential act of tribal affirmation, identity,
and perpetuation, and is a testament to the
continued vitality of the Plains Indian life.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">LITERARY TRADITIONS</hi>: <ref n="egp.lt.054">Oral Traditions</ref> / 
<hi rend="smallcaps">NATIVE AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.na.024">Crows</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">RELIGION</hi>: 
<ref n="egp.rel.046">Sun Dance</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Rodney Frey<lb/>
University of Idaho</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Dorsey, George. <title level="m">Traditions of the Arapaho</title>. 1903. Lincoln:
University of Nebraska Press, 1997.</bibl> <bibl>Lowie, Robert. <title level="m">Myths and Traditions of the Crow Indians</title>. 1918. Lincoln: University
of Nebraska Press, 1993.</bibl> <bibl>Wissler, Clark, and D. C.
Duvall. <title level="m">Mythology of the Blackfoot Indians</title>. 1909. Lincoln:
University of Nebraska Press, 1995.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>