<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.pd.001.01 SYSTEM "egp.pd.001.01.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY egp.pd.001.02 SYSTEM "egp.pd.001.02.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY egp.pd.001.03 SYSTEM "egp.pd.001.03.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.pd.001">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Protest and Dissent</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>William C. Pratt</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.pd.001</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Pratt, William C.">William C. Pratt</author>. <title level="a">"Protest and Dissent."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">699-704</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-05</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">PROTEST AND DISSENT</head>

<p>Protest and dissent have helped shape the history
of the Great Plains in the modern era.
Dramatic episodes like the 1919 Winnipeg
(Manitoba) General Strike and the 1973 occupation
of Wounded Knee, South Dakota,
are just a few of the many efforts that have
made their impact felt in the region and beyond.
On numerous occasions, individuals
and groups have taken a public stand to denounce
a perceived evil or promote a desired
good. Sometimes protest was tied to a more
permanent effort, such as the labor movement,
a farmers' organization, or an ideological
cause; other times, it was a single outburst
of anger or complaint. Dissenting views
also were advanced by the formation of local
civil rights groups like Omaha's De Porres
Club or radical newspapers like Kansas's <title level="j">Appeal
to Reason</title>, or even in letters written to
the local press. Protest and dissent have not
been isolated topics in the Great Plains; rather,
they have been major elements in the region's
history.</p>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Farm Protest</head>

<figure n="egp.pd.001.01" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Deputies with nightsticks line the highway coming into Omaha, Nebraska, to protect trucks against Farmers Holiday Association demonstrators, September 1, 1932.</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Much of the protest has an economic origin.
Hard-pressed farmers from Texas to Alberta
have organized repeatedly in an effort to obtain
better prices for their crops and livestock,
fairer treatment from railroads and other corporations,
and better community and public
services. On a number of occasions, farm
groups that first organized in the United States
spread to Canada's Prairie Provinces. For example,
in the late nineteenth century, the Patrons
of Husbandry, or the Grange (formed in
1867), preached a gospel of education, economic
cooperation, and social activity for the
farm family. It met with great success initially
when it launched a cooperative crusade in the
1870s. Although its strongest outposts were in
the Midwest, the Grange also enjoyed a strong
following in some Plains states and in the
Prairie Provinces. Its experience was shared
by numerous other farm organizations that
emerged in the region in subsequent decades.
In the early twentieth century, the American
Society of Equity (organized in 1902) emerged
as an influential transborder movement as
well. It focused most of its energies on marketing
and cooperatives, although it also lobbied
politicians and sponsored social and educational
programs. Ultimately, the Society of
Equity on both sides of the forty-ninth parallel
played a role in the emergence of the Nonpartisan
League (<hi rend="smallcaps">NPL</hi>), an agrarian political
movement that had its origins in North Dakota
in 1915.</p>

<p>Time and time again, Great Plains farmers
have organized to avoid the middleman, advance
the interests of rural people, and preserve
the family farm. They met with their
greatest successes between 1910 and 1960. In
the Prairie Provinces, the Grain Growers Associations,
the United Farmers of Alberta (<hi rend="smallcaps">UFA</hi>),
the United Farmers of Canada, Saskatchewan
Section, and the United Farmers of Manitoba
were the important farm groups that emerged
prior to 1930. They promoted a gospel of farm
cooperatives and agrarian politics. Among
their greatest assets was <title level="j">The Western Producer</title>,
a newspaper that served a major educational
and propaganda role for decades. South of the
forty-ninth parallel, the comparable movement
for American farmers, particularly from
the World War I era into the 1950s, was the
National Farmers Union (<hi rend="smallcaps">NFU</hi>). Cooperatives,
education, and political activity were all part
of the agenda of this effort, which had its
greatest presence in the Plains states, particularly
in North Dakota and Oklahoma.
There were numerous parallels between the
Canadian and American farm movements,
one of which was the important role that
women often played in sustaining these
efforts, but the response to particular problems
often differed from province to province
and from state to state. For example, the oncenonpartisan
ufa entered politics in 1922 and
dominated the Alberta provincial government
until 1935. In the United States, however, the
<hi rend="smallcaps">NFU</hi> was never tempted to transform itself
into a political organization.</p>

<p>The Great Depression of the 1930s presented
an enormous challenge to existing farm groups
in the Great Plains. Cooperative marketing was
not a remedy for low farm prices, and farmers
across the region were threatened with foreclosure
and other economic disasters. Government
at all levels in the United States and Canada
was slow to respond to the unprecedented
crisis. What emerged was a grassroots protest
movement, or what some have coined the farm
revolt of the 1930s. The major American organization
was the Farmers Holiday Association,
which sponsored farm strikes or withholding
actions and interfered with forced farm sales
through "penny auctions." The Farmers Holiday
Association began in 1932 and spread across
the Upper Midwest and Northern Plains. Hundreds
and even thousands of farmers took
part in demonstrations, penny auctions, and
marches on state capitols. In February 1933 an
estimated 4,000 farmers gathered on the steps of
the new state capitol building in Lincoln, Nebraska,
demanding a moratorium law.</p>

<p>But the first skirmishes of the farm revolt
of the 1930s were fought by smaller groups.
Communist-led organizations, the United
Farmers League (<hi rend="smallcaps">UFL</hi>) and the Farmers Unity
League (<hi rend="smallcaps">FUL</hi>), conducted penny auctions before
the better-known Farmers Holiday Association
came into existence. A Manitoba farm
sale was halted by an <hi rend="smallcaps">FUL</hi> group in early 1931,
and similar episodes soon took place on both
sides of the border. For a short time it looked
as if the countryside in the Great Plains was
in revolt. Ultimately, federal farm programs
helped undercut the appeal of agrarian insurgency
in the United States. Yet the farm revolt
of the 1930s dramatized the plight of American
and Canadian farmers, pressured government
to provide assistance, and played a role
in reconfiguring the political culture of the
region.</p>

<p>Farm protest in the more recent era has had
less impact. During the 1950s and 1960s a new
American farm group emerged, the National
Farmers Organization (<hi rend="smallcaps">NFO</hi>). It focused its attention
on marketing, ultimately opting for
collective bargaining. Like the farmers' groups
of the 1930s, <hi rend="smallcaps">NFO</hi> initially attracted widespread
publicity. It, too, sponsored withholding actions
or strikes but soon settled down, establishing
a niche particularly among dairy and
hog farmers. The National Farmers Union of
Canada, largely a Saskatchewan group, developed
a parallel course of action in more recent
years as well. In the late 1970s and early 1980s,
farmers again were faced with low prices and
high debt and interest rates. A new farm revolt
ensued on both sides of the border, and the
older farm groups were often bypassed by the
insurgency. The main vehicle of this protest in
the United States was the American Agriculture
Movement, which was formed in 1978. It
was accompanied by many smaller groups in
the next several years, most of which were organized
in the early 1980s. A Canadian Agriculture
Movement was formed, and an umbrella
group, the North American Farm Alliance,
emerged in 1982, open to both American and
Canadian membership. The 1980s probably
witnessed more farm protest than any time
since the early 1930s. These efforts sometimes
borrowed tactics and rhetoric from earlier
eras; for example, Mary Elizabeth Lease's alleged
comment from the late nineteenth century,
"Farmers need to raise less corn and more
hell," was often quoted with approval. Such
efforts again drew attention to the plight of
farmers, but there were significantly fewer of
them than previously, so their political influence
was correspondingly reduced as well. By
the end of the twentieth century, the ranks
of family farm organizations throughout the
Plains fell far short of earlier days, when farm
protest and farm votes determined elections
on both sides of the border.</p>

<p>Yet the legacies of those earlier efforts are
manifest in the region. Farm cooperatives to
buy wheat and sell oil and gasoline dot the
Plains from Texas to Alberta; North Dakota
continues to operate a state-owned bank; Nebraska
forbids nonfamily farm corporations
from owning and operating farms; and the
Canadian medicare system, first promoted
by the farmer-dominated Cooperative Commonwealth
Federation in Saskatchewan, remains
in place.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Labor Protest</head>

<figure n="egp.pd.001.02" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Socialist group at Minot, North Dakota, convention, 1910</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Workers in the Great Plains often have protested
because of their wages and working
conditions. While the region generally has not
had the reputation as a center of labor protest,
organized labor has had an extended history
in Winnipeg, Brandon (Manitoba), Edmonton,
Calgary, Regina, Saskatoon, Omaha, and
Kansas City, as well as in other railroad and
mining centers. Craft unions organized skilled
workers such as printers, carpenters, and
bricklayers in the late nineteenth century in
many communities in the Plains, and they,
along with railroad unions, ranked among the
most successful unionization efforts in that
era. An important effort outside the craft
unions was that of the Knights of Labor (organized
in 1867), an attempt to organize workers
regardless of skill, gender, or race. Although
the Knights had their greatest success in the
northeastern and midwestern United States,
they also had a significant presence in the
Plains states and parts of the Prairie Provinces.
Winnipeg, Omaha, and Kansas City, Kansas,
were among the strongest Knights of Labor
communities in the region, and the Kansas
City Knights emerged as a strong political
force in the 1880s. Then, the Knights seemed a
real alternative to the craft union approach.
Ultimately, however, the "bread and butter"
unionism of Samuel Gompers and the American
Federation of Labor prevailed in the
United States and in Canada as well.</p>

<p>However, in the early twentieth century a
more militant form of unionism—often called
industrial unionism because it sought to organize
workers in particular industries regardless
of job skill—had a strong presence in some
cities and in the countryside. The Industrial
Workers of the World (<hi rend="smallcaps">IWW</hi>) was formed in
1905 and sought to organize all workers into
one big union. More radical than craft unions,
Wobblies (as <hi rend="smallcaps">IWW</hi> members were called)
sought to replace the existing economic and
political order with workers' rule. Although
the iww tried to recruit members from all occupations,
in the Great Plains this union met
with its greatest success in the wheat fields,
where it organized harvest hands. From 1915 to
1917 thousands of migratory workers from
Oklahoma to North Dakota had red cards signifying
iww membership. At one point, a tentative
closed shop arrangement between the
<hi rend="smallcaps">NPL</hi> in North Dakota and the iww was negotiated,
only to be repudiated by the farm group's
members soon after. Local authorities often
suppressed the Wobblies, two noteworthy
crackdowns occurring in Minot, North Dakota,
and Mitchell, South Dakota. After the
United States entered World War I in 1917, repression
of radical groups became the norm,
and the Wobblies were harassed repeatedly.
During the war years and the anticommunist
"Red Scare" that followed World War I, the
iww was decimated in the Plains states.</p>

<p>The "one big union" idea also had appeal
north of the forty-ninth parallel, as the iww
established a foothold in western Canada prior
to World War I. The war experience itself had a
radicalizing effect on many Canadian workers,
and western Canada experienced its greatest
labor strife in history in 1919. Pent-up resentment,
increased militancy, and the example of
the Bolshevik revolution in Russia all served to
encourage Canadian unionists to take the offensive
after World War I. When the Western
Labor Conference met in Calgary in March of
1919, militant labor sentiments were at fever
pitch. The gathering denounced the capitalist
economic order, extended greetings to the government
of the Soviet Union, and opted to
form a new union open to all workers, called
the One Big Union (<hi rend="smallcaps">OBU</hi>). Like the <hi rend="smallcaps">IWW</hi> before
it, the obu was a rejection not only of the
existing economic order but also of the traditional
labor movement led by conservative labor
leaders like Samuel Gompers.</p>

<p>Growing labor strife across Canada coincided
with the formation of the <hi rend="smallcaps">OBU</hi>. A showdown
between employers and the new labor
militancy occurred in Winnipeg in the summer
of 1919. The famous Winnipeg General
Strike has been portrayed as both a revolutionary
upheaval and a repressive counterrevolution
against legitimate trade union aspirations.
As a practical matter, the labor troubles in
Winnipeg did not grow out of a confrontation
between the <hi rend="smallcaps">OBU</hi> and local employers. Rather,
they were related to more conventional disputes
over wages and the right of collective
bargaining. When workers went out on strike,
many other local unions walked out in sympathy
with the strikers. Employers and politicians,
however, portrayed the Winnipeg General
Strike as the beginning of a revolution and
seized every opportunity to suppress the strikers.
General strikes in other western Canadian
cities followed, as unionists sought to show
their support for the Winnipeg strikers. Police,
soldiers, employers, and returning veterans all
joined in the fray in Winnipeg, and the strikers
were routed after three weeks of struggle. This
defeat marked the end of an era and a turning
point in labor history in the Great Plains.
Never again, north or south of the forty-ninth
parallel, would there be such a confrontation
between employers and workers.</p>

<p>The 1920s were labor's lean years in both the
United States and Canada. Kansas miners, Nebraska and Kansas packinghouse workers, and
railroad workers across the U.S. Plains all suffered
defeat in the early 1920s, as did miners
and others in the Prairie Provinces. One noteworthy
episode in southeast Kansas involved
female relatives of male coal miners. During
the coal strike of 1921, these women organized
the "Amazon Army," which toured mine sites,
picketing and attacking strikebreakers. This
strike ended in failure, as did miners' strikes in
western Canada in this era.</p>

<p>Organized workers had little to celebrate anywhere
in the Great Plains until the mid- to late
1930s, when the labor movement regrouped and
launched new organizational drives during the
Great Depression. This time, benefiting from
new labor legislation and the example of union
success elsewhere in the United States, workers
organized new unions and flocked to old ones.
One of the most important developments was
the formation of the Congress of Industrial Organizations
(<hi rend="smallcaps">CIO</hi>), which was a federation of
industrial unions. Workers flocked to the new
industrial unions on both sides of the border.
(In both Canada and the United States, unions
often are referred to as internationals, as they
have affiliates in both countries.) Yet union
growth was not limited to the new unions. Old
craft unions, including the Teamsters, which
emerged as a major union for the first time, also
enjoyed important organizational successes.
With the outbreak of World War II, union militancy
was replaced by no-strike pledges, but
union membership and political influence continued
to grow. In Saskatchewan, a farmer-labor
political coalition, the Cooperative Commonwealth
Confederation (<hi rend="smallcaps">CCF</hi>), first came to power
in 1944, and prolabor candidates were elected to
ridings in numerous assembly districts there
and in Manitoba. South of the border, however,
a conservative reaction to labor gains ensued
in the war years and the immediate postwar
period.</p>

<p>On earlier occasions, anti-union sentiment
had resulted in employer counteroffensives
known as the open shop movement. The
movement had been particularly strong in
Omaha and Fargo; the Omaha Business Men's
Association asserted that "Omaha is the best
open shop city of its size in the United States."
Such efforts had been swept away by the late
1930s in the wake of union successes, but employers
regrouped following World War II and
launched a major effort to revive the open
shop. In the Dakotas and Nebraska, they
successfully promoted "right-to-work" laws.
Both South Dakota and Nebraska amended
their constitutions to prohibit the union shop
in 1946, and more than a decade later Kansas
passed a right-to-work measure as well. These
anti-union efforts amounted to a businessmen's
protest movement.</p>

<p>Labor membership in Plains states lagged behind
that in more industrialized states, but the
labor movement continued to represent tens of
thousands of workers. Later, in the 1960s and
1970s, as teachers and other public employees
opted for unionization across the country,
Plains states passed measures providing for collective
bargaining, particularly for teachers. One
noteworthy episode occurred in South Dakota,
when Rapid City teachers went out on strike in
1970. Today, university and college professors in
the Prairie Provinces, South Dakota, Nebraska,
and Kansas are among public employees exercising
their right to bargain for wages and
working conditions.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Political Protest and Dissent</head>

<p>Political protest and dissent has been an integral
feature of the political culture of the
Plains states and Prairie Provinces. Aside from
the Populist movement of the 1890s, third parties
in the Plains states have been more a vehicle
for protest and advocacy than a means of
assuming political power. In the Prairie Provinces,
on the other hand, third parties such as
Social Credit and the <hi rend="smallcaps">CCF</hi> (and its successor,
the New Democratic Party) have met with
much greater electoral success in the twentieth
century. There, too, however, minor third parties,
including the Communist Party, have
played a similar protest role. Socialists often
ran for office in the early twentieth century,
but their campaigns proved to be more protest
than a means of gaining public office. The exception
was Oklahoma, where members of
the Socialist Party were elected to five state
legislatives seats and to more than 100 local
offices in 1914.</p>

<p>A key element in the pre-World War I Socialist
effort was a highly successful weekly newspaper,
<title level="j">Appeal to Reason</title>, published in Girard,
Kansas, by Julius Wayland. Folksy, well-written,
and controversial, <title level="j">Appeal to Reason</title> may have
had the largest circulation of any political paper
in the United States (more than 760,000 of some
issues), and subscribers across the country read
this paper for years. (Upton Sinclair's novel <title level="m">The
Jungle</title> first appeared in serial form in the <title level="j">Appeal
to Reason</title>.)</p>

<p>Itinerant speakers also played a major role
in promoting the Socialist cause in the U.S.
Plains, and Kate Richards O'Hare was among
the best known. She spoke at Socialist encampments
in Oklahoma and at other party
gatherings across the region. During World
War I she was convicted of violating the Espionage
Act for antiwar comments she allegedly
made in a speech in Bowman, North
Dakota.</p>

<p>In the U.S. Great Plains, farmers and smalltown
folk were more likely than city folk to be
Socialists. Beatrice, Nebraska, Sisseton, South
Dakota, and Minot, North Dakota, were among
the communities that elected Socialist mayors.
The emergence of third parties as a kind of
protest was behind the more successful npl that
dominated North Dakota politics and took over
courthouses in portions of eastern South Dakota
and northeastern Montana from 1916 to
1922.</p>

<p>Other third-party political protest involved
Communists in the early 1920s and after.
Though there never were many Communists
in the U.S. Plains, small pockets existed in Finnish
settlements in the Dakotas and Montana
and in a number of other communities across
the Northern Plains at different times. Key
Communist leaders Earl Browder and James
Cannon both came from Kansas and underwent
their baptism of fire in radical causes
there. (Cannon subsequently broke with the
Communists and served as the chief leader of
the American Trotskyist movement until his
death.) Ella Reeve "Mother" Bloor was the
most prominent Communist figure in the region
during the Great Depression. An energetic
agitator despite her age, the sixty-sevenyear-
old Bloor played a key role in the farm
revolt of that era, traveling across the Dakotas,
Montana, and Nebraska from 1930 to 1934,
speaking and organizing wherever she went.
While most of her efforts involved farmers,
she was arrested in Nebraska for her role in
the 1934 Loup City Riot in which Communists
and their allies tried to organize women in a
local chicken-processing plant. She ultimately
served thirty days in jail.</p>

<p>Communists also played a role in the labor
and unemployment struggles of the 1930s.
They likely had a stronger presence in the
Prairie Provinces than in the U.S. Plains states.
Communists had a following in some mining
districts, Ukrainian settlements, and Winnipeg's
North End. In 1935 they played a key
part in the unemployment march across western
Canada that was halted dramatically with
the Regina Riot. Marchers had trekked to Regina
en route to their ultimate destination,
Ottawa, where they planned to petition the
federal government for relief. At Regina, however,
local authorities and the Royal Canadian
Mounted Police intercepted the trekkers, attacking
a mass meeting and brutally dispersing
them.</p>

<p>Communists participated in the larger farm
and labor organizations in the region. Their
strongest base after the 1930s probably was in
Winnipeg and smaller Ukrainian communities.
As late as the 1960s, a Communist represented
the North End in the Winnipeg City
Council. Some Communists had participated
in the <hi rend="smallcaps">CCF</hi> in Saskatchewan and the <hi rend="smallcaps">NFU</hi> in the
Northern Plains states at times. Yet their role
should not be exaggerated. Opponents often
used the "red" issue as a way of discrediting
liberal causes, and the <hi rend="smallcaps">NPL</hi>, <hi rend="smallcaps">CCF</hi>, and <hi rend="smallcaps">NFU</hi> all
were subjected to such attacks. Many liberal
groups in this region often found themselves
the target of right-wing protest groups.</p>

<p>Political protest and dissent have not been a
left-of-center monopoly. An important early
right-wing protest group in the Plains states
and Prairie Provinces was the Ku Klux Klan.
It quickly attracted a strong following, particularly
in Oklahoma, but had a presence
throughout the entire region in the 1920s.
Governors in both Oklahoma and Kansas
went to war with the Klan, though Oklahoma
governor John C. "Our Jack" Walton's primary
motivation in doing so was to avoid impeachment
and removal from office. (This
effort failed, as his bizarre and arbitrary behavior
alienated many of his former supporters.)
The Klan spread to Canada in the
mid-1920s and attracted a strong following in
both Alberta and Saskatchewan. There, its
drawing power came from its anti-Catholic
and anti-immigrant stance. Recent historians
of the Klan increasingly stress the complexity
of this topic, observing that its adherents often
were motivated more by a desire to preserve
existing moral codes than by racism and anti-Catholicism. While scholars disagree on the
significance of the Klan in this era, there
seems little question that Protestant clergymen
often promoted its cause on both sides of
the border.</p>

<p>Right-wing protest probably has come in as
many varieties as its counterparts on the left.
In the 1930s, coinciding with President Franklin
Roosevelt's New Deal (and sometimes in
response to it), an articulate right-wing protest
element emerged in the Plains. Key figures
in this grouping included Gerald B. Winrod
and Elmer J. Garner, both then from Wichita.
Winrod published the <title level="j">Defender</title> magazine,
and Garner edited <title level="j">Publicity</title>, a newspaper. By
the late 1930s both of them identified the New
Deal with Jews and communists. Anti-Semitic
and isolationist, they saw the Roosevelt administration
dominated by Jews and vehemently
denounced U.S. foreign policy. Following
Pearl Harbor, however, both tempered
their remarks. Still, in 1942 they were indicted
for sedition, along with twenty-nine other
right-wing figures. Garner died two weeks after
the trial began, and the case against Winrod
and other defendants ended in a mistrial
in 1946. Some historians maintain that this
prosecution was an overreaction to the right
wing, a kind of "brown scare," analogous to
the overreaction to the left, or "red scare," of
the post–World War II era.</p>

<p>Support for Sen. Joseph McCarthy emerged
in the Plains states during the cold war
years. While there was no McCarthyite movement
per se, McCarthyite attacks were made
against many groups and people. For example,
in northeast Montana, a Farmers Anti-Communist Club appeared and ran advertisements
in two local weekly newspapers in the
mid-1950s. The chief target of this group apparently
was the <hi rend="smallcaps">NFU</hi>, and the advertisements
often portrayed the liberal farm group as a
Communist front or an organization in which
Communists played a major role. Later, in the
1960s, the John Birch Society appeared in the
region. Its national leader denounced Dwight
Eisenhower's presidency as too liberal, sometimes
suggesting that the popular president
had been a tool of the Communists. Birch Society
members probably had their greatest influence
at the local level, particularly on
school boards.</p>

<p>An even more extreme right-wing protest
movement emerged in the 1980s and 1990s. At
the depths of the farm crisis of the 1980s, the
Posse Comitatus and other extremist groups
recruited among hard-pressed farmers. Built
on a racist and anti-Semitic ideology, this
movement preached a harsh, antigovernment
gospel that justified violence and fraudulent
financial practices. Numerous publications,
speakers, and workshops promoted this message.
While observers differed in their assessment
of the recruitment success of these
groups, all agreed that the groups built a following
in the countryside. Gordon Kahl of
North Dakota and Arthur Kirk of Nebraska
were two of their recruits. Both men resisted
arrest and died in shootouts with authorities,
becoming martyrs to their extremist causes.</p>

<p>The Posse Comitatus has faded from view
while continuing as an intermittently active
arm of antigovernment protest. Its torch
has been picked up by newer organizations,
including some militia groups. In Garfield
County in northeastern Montana, a group
calling themselves the Freemen claimed they
had established sovereignty in Justus Township
and constructed a stockade around their
farm in 1996. They financed their actions
by passing millions of dollars' worth of bad
checks. A long siege of more than two months
ensued before the group surrendered to the
authorities, who included a large number of
<hi rend="smallcaps">FBI</hi> agents. A similar episode occurred in West
Texas in 1997. In Jeff Davis County, a rightwing
group claimed they had reestablished the
Republic of Texas, arguing that the United
States' annexation of Texas in 1846 had been
invalid. Also heavily armed, this faction subscribed
to many of the political ideas of the
Posse Comitatus and threatened to shoot anyone
who interfered with their activities. After
the kidnapping of a local couple, authorities
acted and suppressed the would-be secessionist
group. Its leaders were sentenced to long
prison sentences for kidnapping and passing
millions of dollars' worth of bad checks.</p>

<p>Unlike earlier protesters, these contemporary
right-wing extremist groups do not seek
to change government policy; instead, they
want to form their own kind of government
outside existing political institutions. In the
wake of the 1995 Oklahoma City bombing, the
media and others have focused much more
attention on right-wing protest groups who
preach violence and vigilante-type justice.
Once simply characterized as tax protestors,
they now are subject to greater scrutiny and
concern.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Civil Rights and Ethnic Protest</head>

<p>An early protest involving Native Americans
was that of Thomas H. Tibbles and Standing
Bear. In 1879 the U.S. government ordered
Gen. George Crook to return Standing Bear
and his Ponca band from their traditional
homeland in northeastern Nebraska to Indian
Territory, where they had been removed two
years previously. Crook, appalled by the assignment,
notified Tibbles, a reporter for the
<title level="j">Omaha Daily Herald</title>, who used the story to
focus attention on citizenship rights for Native
Americans. Tibbles also arranged for two
local attorneys to file a writ of habeas corpus
on behalf of the Ponca leader in federal court.
The judge ruled that Standing Bear and his
followers were U.S. citizens who had withdrawn
from the Ponca tribe, and that the federal
government had no basis to order their
return to Indian Territory. Following the trial,
Crook and Tibbles continued to aid the Ponca
cause to regain their land in northeast Nebraska.
Susette La Flesche, the daughter of an
Omaha chief, joined the effort, later marrying
Tibbles. She devoted much of her life to working
for Indian rights, including the recognition
of their U.S. citizenship.</p>

<p>African Americans often were treated as second-class citizens in the Plains. After World War
I there were several violent outbreaks against
African Americans, including a 1919 lynching in
Omaha and the 1921 Tulsa Race Riot that resulted
in the deaths of at least thirty-nine African
Americans, and probably many more.
Some African Americans organized chapters
of the National Association of Colored People
(<hi rend="smallcaps">NAACP</hi>), while others formed units of Marcus
Garvey's back-to-Africa group, the Universal
Negro Improvement Association (<hi rend="smallcaps">UNIA</hi>). By
the mid-1920s Oklahoma City and Omaha had
both <hi rend="smallcaps">NAACP</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">UNIA</hi> affiliates, Topeka and
Lincoln had <hi rend="smallcaps">NAACP</hi> chapters, and Kansas City
and Tulsa had <hi rend="smallcaps">UNIA</hi> divisions.</p>

<p>Civil rights activism had a long history in
the region. Plains blacks protested the film
<title>Birth of a Nation</title> as racist and sought to eliminate
discrimination in employment and education.
The U.S. Supreme Court's 1954 landmark
decision in <title>Brown v. The Board of Education</title>,
which paved the way for desegregation of
the public schools, was the result of several
naacp lawsuits, including one on behalf of
Linda Brown and other black students in Topeka,
Kansas. Some African Americans in the
Great Plains opted for direct action even before
the outbreak of activism in the South in
the 1960s. Omaha's De Porres Club, organized
in 1947, integrated a Catholic parish and pressured
the local Coca Cola bottling works (located
in the city's largest black neighborhood)
and the transit company to hire blacks. For a
time, this group was affiliated with the Congress
of Racial Equality (<hi rend="smallcaps">CORE</hi>). In 1958 <hi rend="smallcaps">NAACP</hi>
youth groups in Wichita and Oklahoma City
conducted successful lunch-counter sit-ins in
order to obtain service for blacks.</p>

<p>One of the region's most dramatic protests
was the 1973 takeover of Wounded Knee. The
American Indian Movement (<hi rend="smallcaps">AIM</hi>) launched a
frontal assault on both discrimination against
Native Americans and the existing power
structure on reservations. In early 1973 <hi rend="smallcaps">AIM</hi>
took control of the community of Wounded
Knee, South Dakota, which was the site of the
1890 massacre of more than 200 Sioux men,
women, and children by the U.S. Seventh Cavalry.
While <hi rend="smallcaps">AIM</hi> sought to dramatize the plight
of contemporary Indians, the takeover also
was aimed at overthrowing the current tribal
leadership on the Pine Ridge Reservation. The
occupation lasted seventy-one days. Although
<hi rend="smallcaps">AIM</hi> was not successful in achieving its stated
objectives, this episode heightened media attention
on the problems faced by Indians in
the region. Canadian Indians supported the
South Dakota occupation, and the Ojibwa
Warrior Society briefly took over a site across
the Manitoba line in western Ontario later the
same year. Native American protest on both
sides of the forty-ninth parallel became commonplace
in the late twentieth century.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Ubiquity of Protest</head>

<figure n="egp.pd.001.03" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Protesting against animal activists in South Dakota</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Not all dissent involves political causes. One
noteworthy example of quiet dissent that still
resulted in serious controversy was an effort to
provide cooperative medical care in the small
southwestern Oklahoma town of Elk City. A
Lebanese immigrant, Michael Shadid, settled
in this community in 1911 after graduating
from medical school. Determined to provide
access to adequate health care, he and the local
Farmers Union raised funds to establish a cooperative
hospital. Although boycotted and
opposed by the local medical establishment,
the Elk City facility persisted and provided
excellent and inexpensive health care to the
community for a generation. Ultimately, in
1964, it became a local community hospital,
no longer based on cooperative principles.</p>

<p>A different kind of dissent regarding medical
services emerged in Saskatchewan, when
the ccf government established medicare in
1962. There, doctors went out on strike, opposing
what they saw as socialized medicine.
A "Keep Our Doctors Committee" appeared
even before the walkout, and most of the hospitals
in the province were closed. The strike
itself lasted less than a month, but ultimately
the medical establishment across Canada became
reconciled to publicly funded, universal
medical care.</p>

<p>The themes of protest and dissent are also
present in the cultural history of the region.
One of the most significant examples is the
1978 film <title>Northern Lights</title>, which tells the story
of an <hi rend="smallcaps">NPL</hi> organizer in northwestern North
Dakota in 1915–16. Directed by John Hanson
and Rob Nilsson, this black-and-white film
featured mostly local people in its cast and
premiered in the small town of Crosby, North
Dakota. It won an award at the 1979 Cannes
Film Festival. The film was narrated by Henry
Martinson, then in his nineties and poet laureate
of North Dakota, who was a veteran of
numerous social and political causes dating
back to his involvement with the Socialist
Party and the <hi rend="smallcaps">NPL</hi> of the World War I era.</p>

<p>Perhaps the best-known artist of the Great
Plains to emerge out of a protest tradition was
songwriter-folksinger Woody Guthrie of Oklahoma.
Among his numerous songs and ballads
were "Talkin' Dust Bowl Blues" and "This
Land Is Your Land." Guthrie met with his
greatest success on the East Coast, where he
performed and recorded songs. His work was
an influence on a number of other singers,
including his friend Pete Seeger, Bob Dylan,
and Bruce Springsteen. Agnes "Sis" Cunningham
was another Oklahoma protest singer
who emerged in the 1930s. She participated in
a left-wing theater troupe known as the Red
Dust Players and helped organize cio unions
in her home state. Later, in the 1940s, she
joined Guthrie in New York City as a member
of the well-known Almanac Singers.</p>

<p>The literature of the Great Plains also contains
dissenting themes. Marie Sandoz's <title level="m">Capitol
City</title>, while not one of her strongest works,
reveals the author's estrangement from the
dominant culture and her sympathies with the
underdog, including embattled farmers, worried
by foreclosures, and striking Teamsters in
the 1930s. Another regional protest novel is
William Cunningham's <title level="m">Green Corn Rebellion</title>.
(Cunningham was the older brother of Sis
Cunningham). This work, published in 1935, is
an example of the proletariat novel that appeared
in the 1930s. It treats a rural Oklahoma
uprising that was quickly suppressed by local
authorities in the wake of the U.S. entry into
World War I.</p>

<p>Nonfiction works treating Great Plains topics
reflect regional dissenting themes as well.
Bruce Nelson's <title level="m">Land of the Dacotahs</title>, first published
in 1946, offers an episodic history of the
Dakotas and Montana. It sides with Indians,
homesteaders, and North Dakota's <hi rend="smallcaps">NPL</hi>. Unlike
Nelson, who was from Minnesota, Angie
Debo lived almost all of her ninety-eight years
in the Great Plains. Trained at the Universities
of Oklahoma and Chicago, she is recognized
as one of the leading authorities on the history
of Southern Plains Indians. Her most important
work may have been <title level="m">And Still the Waters
Run</title>, a historical treatment of how white
Oklahomans stole large amounts of Indian
land. A number of the culprits were still alive
and were prominent citizens at the time Debo
wrote the manuscript, and the University of
Oklahoma administration refused to allow its
press to publish the book. Finally, <title level="m">And Still the
Waters Run</title> was published in 1940 by Princeton
University Press. Debo's work was characterized
by a strong sympathy toward Indians
at a time when that stance was unpopular in
Oklahoma.</p>

<p>Critical treatments of the Great Plains
sometimes themselves provoked protest. Local
responses to Pere Lorentz's 1936 film documentary,
<title>The Plow That Broke the Plains</title>, and
John Steinbeck's novel <title level="m">The Grapes of Wrath</title>
constituted yet another variety of regional
protest. Lorentz's classic twenty-eight-minute
film provoked a firestorm of journalistic and
political criticism for defaming South Dakota,
even though none of its footage was shot in
that state. Likewise, <title level="m">The Grapes of Wrath</title> was
perceived as a libel on Oklahoma by some local
editorial writers, especially in Oklahoma
City.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Conclusion</head>

<p>Protest and dissent permeate the recent history
of the Great Plains. In some cases, especially
in regard to farm and labor protest,
they constitute an important part of the background
of new organizations and institutions.
On other occasions, protestors and dissenters
have had little lasting effect; their voices were
raised or their remarks recorded, and then
they faded into obscurity, only to be rediscovered
later (if at all) by enterprising journalists
or historians. New causes have appeared in
recent decades, but they often utilize tactics
introduced long ago. In the 1980s and 1990s,
for example, protestors on both sides of the
abortion issue picketed and sometimes resorted
to civil disobedience, following courses
of action earlier laid out by the labor and civil
rights movements. Historically, many people
on numerous occasions have demonstrated
their approval or opposition to current practices
or proposed changes. The frequency and
the geographic extent of their efforts demonstrate
that protest and dissent have not
been an aberration in the Great Plains; rather,
they constitute an irreducible element of the
region.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">AFRICAN AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.afam.014">Civil Rights</ref>;
<ref n="egp.afam.032">Omaha Race Riot</ref>; <ref n="egp.afam.041">Tulsa Race Riot</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">AGRICULTURE</hi>:
<ref n="egp.ag.023">Corporate Farming</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">FILM</hi>: <ref n="egp.fil.026"><hi rend="italic">The Grapes of Wrath</hi></ref>; <ref n="egp.fil.051"><hi rend="italic">Northern Lights</hi></ref>; <ref n="egp.fil.055"><hi rend="italic">The Plow That Broke the Plains</hi></ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">LAW</hi>: <ref n="egp.law.004">Anti-Corporate Farming Law</ref>; <ref n="egp.law.011"><hi rend="italic"><title>Brown v. The Board of Education of Topeka</title></hi></ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">LITERARY TRADITIONS</hi>: <ref n="egp.lt.014">Debo, Angie</ref>;
<ref n="egp.lt.070">Sandoz, Mari</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">MEDIA</hi>: <ref n="egp.med.048"><hi rend="italic">Western Producer</hi></ref> /
<hi rend="smallcaps">MUSIC</hi>: <ref n="egp.mus.019">Guthrie, Woody</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</hi>:
<ref n="egp.pg.014">Cooperative Commonwealth Federation</ref>;
<ref n="egp.pg.055">New Democratic Party</ref>; <ref n="egp.pg.063">Populists (People's Party)</ref>.</p>
</div2>

<closer>
<signed>William C. Pratt<lb/>
University of Nebraska at Omaha</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Barthelme, Marion K. <title level="j">Women in the Texas Populist Movement:
Letters to the Southern Mercury</title>. College Station:
Texas <hi rend="smallcaps">A&amp;M</hi> University Press, 1997.</bibl> <bibl>Bumsted, J. M. "1919:
The Winnipeg Strike Reconsidered." <title level="j">The Beaver</title> (June–
July 1994): 27–44.</bibl> <bibl>Corcoran, James. <title level="m">Bitter Harvest: Gordon
Kahl and the Posse Comitatus: Murder in the Heartland</title>.
New York: Penguin Books, 1990.</bibl> <bibl>Dyson, Lowell K. <title level="m">Red
Harvest: The Communist Party and American Farmers</title>.
Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1982.</bibl> <bibl>Green, James
R. <title level="m">Grass-Roots Socialism: Radical Movements in the Southwest,
1895–1943</title>. Baton Rouge: Louisiana State University
Press, 1978.</bibl> <bibl>Haug, Charles James. "The Industrial Workers
of the World in North Dakota, 1913–1917." <title level="j">North Dakota
Quarterly</title> 39 (1971): 85–102.</bibl> <bibl>Henson, Tom M. "Ku Klux
Klan in Western Canada." <title level="j">Alberta History</title> 25 (1977): 1–8.</bibl>
<bibl>Joyce, David D. <title level="m">An Oklahoma I Had Never Seen Before:
Alternative Views of Oklahoma History</title>. Norman: University
of Oklahoma Press, 1994.</bibl> <bibl>MacPherson, Ian. "Selective
Borrowings: The American Impact upon the Prairie
Co-operative Movement, 1920–39." <title level="j">Canadian Review of
American Studies</title> 10 (1979): 137–51.</bibl> <bibl>McCormack, A. Ross.
<title level="m">Reformers, Rebels, and Revolutionaries: The Western Canadian
Radical Movement 1899–1919</title>. Toronto: University of
Toronto Press, 1991.</bibl> <bibl>Monod, David. "The Agrarian Struggle:
Rural Communism in Alberta and Saskatchewan,
1926–1935." <title level="j">Historie sociale/Social History</title> 35 (1985): 98–
118.</bibl> <bibl>Pratt, William C. "Workers, Bosses, and Historians on
the Northern Plains." <title level="j">Great Plains Quarterly</title> 16 (1996):
229–50.</bibl> <bibl>Saloutos, Theodore, and John D. Hicks. <title level="m">Twentieth-
Century Populism: Agricultural Discontent in the
Middle West, 1900–1939</title>. Lincoln: University of Nebraska
Press, 1964.</bibl> <bibl>Sharp, Paul F. <title level="m">The Agrarian Revolt in Western
Canada: A Survey Showing American Parallels</title>. Minneapolis:
University of Minnesota Press, 1948.</bibl> <bibl>Shover, L. John.
<title level="m">Cornbelt Rebellion: The Farmers' Holiday Association</title>. Urbana:
University of Illinois Press, 1965.</bibl> <bibl>Wilson, L. J. "Educational
Role of the United Farm Women of Alberta."
<title level="j">Alberta History</title> 25 (1977): 28–36.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>