<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fil.057">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main"><hi rend="italic">Red River</hi></title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>William M. Wehrbein</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fil.057</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Wehrbein, William M.">William M. Wehrbein</author>. <title level="a">"<hi rend="italic">Red River</hi>."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">277-278</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-12</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main"><hi rend="italic">RED RIVER</hi></head>
<figure n="egp.fil.057" rend="granted" type="noclick">
<figDesc>Screen shot from Red River (1948)</figDesc>
</figure>      

<p>This famous motion picture was directed by
Howard Hawks, with a script by Charles
Schnee and Bordon Chase (from his <title level="j">Saturday Evening Post</title> serial) and music by Dimitri
Tiomkin. Released in 1948, <title>Red River</title> featured
John Wayne, Montgomery Clift, Walter Brennan,
and Joanne Dru plus a number of actors
who appeared in Westerns from the silent film
era through the television era. The film was
shot at Rain Valley Ranch at Elgin (near Tucson),
Arizona.</p>

<p>Lying at the intersection of history and
myth, <title>Red River</title> is the story of the first cattle
drive along the Chisholm Trail from Texas to
Abilene, Kansas, and, according to Hawks, the
story of Texas's famed King Ranch. Beginning
with one cow, which belongs to the orphaned
youngster Matt Garth (Clift), and his own
bull, Tom Dunson (Wayne) builds a herd of
10,000 cattle on the Red River d ranch north
of the Rio Grande. But by the end of the Civil
War there is no market for beef in impoverished
Texas. In desperation Dunson decides to
drive his entire herd north to Sedalia, Missouri,
in spite of the dangers of weather, rustlers,
Indians, and stampedes. As living and
working conditions for his cowboys deteriorate,
Dunson becomes more and more tyrannical.
In spite of reports of bandits in Missouri
and the possibility of an alternative market in
Abilene, he continues to drive his men ruthlessly
toward the original destination. When
Dunson threatens to hang two recaptured deserters
Matt seizes control of the drive. Incensed,
the wounded Dunson vows to catch
up and kill him. Later, the drive encounters a
wagon train of gamblers and women headed
to Nevada, and cardsharper Tess Millay (Dru)
falls in love with Matt. When the drive reaches
Abilene they find the railroad and buyers
waiting for them, and Matt sells the herd for a
good price. Dunson arrives the next day.
However, instead of the gunfight that all had
expected, neither man will shoot the other. A
fistfight ensues that Tess halts by firing a pistol.
Tess points out that their actions indicate that
Dunson and Matt must actually love each
other, and in recognition of the successful
completion of the cattle drive, Dunson volunteers
to add Matt's "M" to the Red River d
brand.</p>

<p>While lacking the iconographic images of
John Ford's Westerns, <title>Red River</title> has a number
of memorable sequences, including the beginning
of the cattle drive (a 180-degree pan followed
by nineteen insert shots of yahooing
cowboys), the crossing of the Red River, the
stampede, Wayne reading over the grave of a
dead cowboy, cattle herds choking the streets
of Abilene, and the climactic fistfight. As in
many of Hawks's films, <title>Red River</title> includes
themes of male camaraderie and professionalism,
and the primary relationship is not the
one that includes the actress. The conflict between
Tom Dunson and Matt Garth is not
only generational but reflects the tension between
Dunson's virtue of grim individual determination
and Matt's "softer" virtues that
build community.</p>

<closer>
<signed>William M. Wehrbein<lb/>
Nebraska Wesleyan University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Bogdanovich, Peter. <title level="m">Who the Devil Made It</title>. New York: Alfred
A. Knopf, 1997.</bibl> <bibl>Mast, Gerald. <title level="m">Howard Hawks, Storyteller</title>.
New York: Oxford University Press, 1982.</bibl> <bibl>McBride,
Joseph. <title level="m">Hawks on Hawks</title>. Berkeley: University of California
Press, 1982.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>