<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.wat.025">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Riparian Doctrine</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Theron Josephson</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.wat.025</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Josephson, Theron">Theron Josephson</author>. <title level="a">"Riparian Doctrine."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">860</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-29</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">RIPARIAN DOCTRINE</head>

<p>The riparian doctrine is a system of water law
that gives the owner of land bordering a stream
or river, or riparian land, the legal right to use
the water of the stream. The right to water use
comes from the spatial connection between
the stream or river and the riparian land. The
riparian right cannot be bought or sold. Nor
can a riparian right be extinguished due to
nonuse or ine.cient use of the water. The riparian
right cannot be separated from the land
and thus is a permanent benefit of owning
riparian land.</p>

<p>Riparian rights are correlative, which means
all riparian landowners have an equal right to
use the stream or river. Under the riparian
doctrine, a riparian landowner has the right to
use a reasonable amount of stream water to
supply needs naturally arising from living next
to a watercourse. However, uses of water must
not significantly reduce stream quantity, diminish
the quality of the water, or change the
spatial pattern of flow, as these alterations may
affect the rights of others living along the
stream.</p>

<p>Normal riparian uses are not extensive. Traditionally
these include domestic water uses,
such as supplying household needs and stock
watering. Some nonconsumptive commercial
uses such as powering a mill are also acceptable.
Alternate uses are presumed to be legitimate
so long as the use does not negatively
affect other riparian rights to the same stream.
Riparian rights are based on the theory that
most of the water used on riparian land will
eventually return to the stream because the
water is used in the same drainage basin.</p>

<p>The riparian doctrine was the pioneering
water law in the legal landscape of the Great
Plains. The first riparian rights were introduced
into Texas by the Spanish more than
200 years ago. Subsequently, the riparian doctrine,
bundled as part of the common law,
came to the Great Plains with the westward
expansion of European American settlement
in the nineteenth century.</p>

<p>The riparian principles of water law had
worked well for settlers in the eastern parts of
North America. However, as settlers moved to
the drier climates of the western Plains, riparian
methods of environmental adaptation did
not necessarily yield the same results as those
achieved in more humid environments. As
population in the marginal environments of
the Great Plains increased, and as the settlers
tried to duplicate the lifestyles and population
densities of the east, demands for water also
increased. This led to competition for scarce
water and a demand for more efficiency in
water usage. Early disputes centered over irrigation
diversions, and riparian rights were
increasingly circumscribed by allowing only
"reasonable" uses of water. Court decisions in
Dakota Territory (1866), Nebraska (1903), and
Kansas (1905) established this principle. Gradually
the competing doctrine of appropriation
rights displaced riparian rights in Plains states,
with the exception of Texas. But even in Texas,
grants of state lands have not conveyed riparian
rights since 1895.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Theron Josephson<lb/>
Ferris State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Dunbar, Robert G. <title level="m">Forging New Rights in Western Water</title>.
Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1983.</bibl> <bibl>Hutchins,
Wells A. <title level="m">Water Rights in the Nineteen Western States</title>. Washington
<hi rend="smallcaps">DC</hi>: Government Printing Office, 1974.</bibl> <bibl>Trelease,
Frank J., and George A. Gould. <title level="m">Cases and Materials on
Water Law</title>, 4th ed. St. Paul <hi rend="smallcaps">MN</hi>: West Publishing Company,
1986.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>