<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.ag.019 SYSTEM "egp.ag.019.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ag.019">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Cattle Ranching</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Kenneth C. Dagel</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ag.019</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Dagel, Kenneth C.">Kenneth C. Dagel</author>. <title level="a">"Cattle Ranching."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">37-38</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-12-10</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">CATTLE RANCHING</head>

<figure n="egp.ag.019" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Cattle ranching</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Perhaps no other activity has so well defined
the character of the Great Plains in literature,
movies, and the national psyche as cattle ranching. 
Ranching, as it developed on the Plains,
was well adapted to the physical environment.
Cattle were able to consume the nutrient-rich
grasses, just as the bison had. Even today, grass
is the most important natural resource for
ranchers, and little tillage agriculture takes
place in order to sustain the herds.</p>

<p>Cattle ranching in the Great Plains of the
United States and Canada differs from the
raising of beef cattle on small farms farther
east. In the Great Plains it is the primary activity,
not an adjunct to farming, and it is conducted
on horseback (and, more recently, out
of a pickup truck). Nearly 50 percent of beef
cattle in the United States are raised in the
Great Plains, and 33 percent of Great Plains
ranches have 1,000 or more cattle. Sixty percent
of Canada's beef cattle are raised in the
Prairie Provinces, but the average number of
cattle per ranch is slightly less than in the
United States.</p>

<p>Although modified by Californian and
midwestern involvement, Great Plains cattle
ranching was formed primarily by Texan influences.
The impetus for cattle ranching in
the Great Plains began just south of the Edwards
Plateau in Texas. In a diamond-shaped
area reaching south of San Antonio to Mexico,
free-roaming cattle of Spanish bloodlines existed
in large numbers by the early 1800s.
Texans returning home after the Civil War
rounded up as many of these cattle as they
could in an attempt to make money. Some
started ranches in Texas. Others drove their
newfound herds north to the railhead at Sedalia,
Missouri. As the railroad and farmers
pushed westward, cattle were trailed to terminals
at Abilene, Newton, Ellsworth, and
Dodge City, Kansas. From the railhead, cattle
were shipped east, where they brought
as much as $4.75 per hundredweight in 1884.
Prices varied considerably depending on the
quality of cattle shipped and where they were
shipped, but the profit margin was high
enough during the cattle-trailing period from
1866–90 that more than 5 million head were
moved out of Texas to eastern markets and to
ranges farther north in the Great Plains. For
all of its glory, however, cattle trailing was not
cattle ranching but merely a prelude to large,
permanently established cattle ranches that
developed late in the trailing period.</p>

<p>Ranches were established throughout the
Great Plains from Texas to the Prairie Provinces.
Ranching in Canada developed coincident
with that in the United States and was
not simply an extension of the cattle business
north of the border. A major difference
between the two countries was that a government
program in Canada allowed up to
100,000 acres to be leased to ranchers, while
early ranchers and other, sometimes foreign,
interests ran large numbers of cattle on huge
tracts of grassland in both countries. The
Texas-based <hi rend="smallcaps">XIT</hi> Ranch controlled 3 million
acres in Texas and another 2 million acres in
Montana. The Hash Knife Ranch near Belle
Fourche, South Dakota, ran 96,000 cattle.</p>

<p>In the United States, Texas served initially as
a mild-weather breeding ground from which
cattle were sold to ranchers farther north. The
open range of the Northern Great Plains was
the fattening ground. Roundups were performed
in the spring to brand and count the
cattle and in the fall to cut out the beef cattle
to be sold at market. The roundups completed
in the late 1800s were the same in principle,
and much the same in practice, as contemporary
roundups. Indeed, striking similarities
exist between the calendar of ranch activities
in 1890 and that of today. Then, as now, the
cycle was closely tied to the seasons and the
grass that provided the main source of food
for the cattle. The feeding of hay and grain
supplements on contemporary ranches has
only slightly altered the basic cycle.</p>

<p>The annual sequence of events varies in timing
and technique from Texas to Canada but is
similar in purpose and structure throughout
the region. During the coldest months of the
year, cattle remain on those areas of the range
that offer some protection from the elements.
This can include rolling topography close to
the ranch that provides a natural barrier to
wind and snow. This is also the time when
supplemental feeding is most important, especially
if heavy snow cover makes it difficult
for cattle to graze. Cattle from backgrounding
operations, where cattle are kept over winter,
are marketed during the first three months of
the year.</p>

<p>Calving season can begin as early as the last
week in January and continue until June. This
is frequently a time of round-the-clock work
for ranchers when they ride close to the herd
to watch for any cow that may have difficulty
calving. If the cows are located at some distance
from the base ranch, cowboys may be
hired to help watch the herd on a daily basis
and then return to their homes at night. When
old enough, the calves are branded, vaccinated,
and eartagged, and bull calves are castrated
prior to trailing them to summer pasture
around the middle of June when grasses
are reaching their peak. In early summer, the
job of putting up hay for the winter begins in
earnest, and, depending on the precipitation
and the type of grass or legume, this work may
continue well into the fall.</p>

<p>In the fall, cattle are rounded up from the
summer pasture and given necessary vaccinations,
while calves are weaned. In operations
that do not background calves, steer calves
weighing 600–800 pounds are shipped to
market in early to mid-October. By November,
the cattle are moved to winter pasture in
protected areas or areas of the ranch that were
not grazed during the summer and fall during
the normal rotation of pastures. Winterfeeding
begins and continues through February if
conditions demand it.</p>

<p>Of the different types of agricultural operations
in the Plains, ranching has changed the
least in the last century. While, in essence,
it remains a straightforward method of producing
food, the adjustments and techniques
needed to maintain an efficient and environmentally
sustainable outfit are more complex
than before. Ranchers must contend with
drought, cattle diseases, predators, and government
intervention, just as in the past.
Modern ranchers must also be concerned
with changing technologies and the vagaries
of market demand for red meat. Still, most
operators consider cattle ranching a lifestyle
as well as a business. With proper management,
ranching is a productive and attractive
activity in semiarid environments like the
Great Plains.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">IMAGES AND ICONS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ii.015">Cowboy Culture</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Kenneth C. Dagel<lb/>
Missouri Western State College</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Jordan, Terry. <title level="m">North American Cattle Ranching Frontiers</title>.
Albuquerque: University of New Mexico Press, 1992.</bibl>
<bibl>Schlebecker, John T. <title level="m">Cattle Raising on the Plains 1900–
1961</title>. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1963.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>