<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.mus.013">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Denver, John (1943-1997)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Timothy J. Kloberdanz</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.mus.013</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Kloberdanz, Timothy J.">Timothy J. Kloberdanz</author>. <title level="a">"Denver, John (1943-1997)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">537</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-02</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">DENVER, JOHN (1943-1997)</head>

<p>John Denver was a popular entertainer and
songwriter whose music exalted simple living
and the natural beauty of the American West.
He was born Henry John Deutschendorf Jr. in
Roswell, New Mexico, on December 31, 1943.
His parents, Henry John "Dutch' Deutschendorf
and Erma Swope, were native Oklahomans
who moved frequently due to Dutch
Deutschendorf 's career as an Air Force flight
instructor and test pilot.</p>

<p>The Deutschendorfs were descendants of
German Russian colonists who settled on the
Ukrainian steppes during the reign of Czar
Alexander I. By the 1920s an American branch
of the Deutschendorf family had put down
roots near Cordell, Oklahoma, along the Washita
River. For years afterward, their prairie farmstead
in Oklahoma would serve as the home
place of the Deutschendorf family. John Denver
composed some of his earliest songs while he
labored in the dusty wheat fields of western
Oklahoma during the summer months. He was
only a teenager at the time, but the experience of
working so close to the land exerted a profound
and lasting influence on his life philosophy and
his music.</p>

<p>Henry John Deutschendorf Jr. rose to fame
after a song he had written, "Leaving on a Jet
Plane," was recorded by the musical trio Peter,
Paul, and Mary in 1968. His career as a songwriter
soon blossomed into that of a popular
performer and also a movie and television actor.
By the mid-1970s his new name, John
Denver, had become a household word, and
both his music and his shy yet upbeat personality
endeared him to millions of fans all
around the world.</p>

<p>John Denver wrote and recorded many musical
hits, including "Rocky Mountain High,"
"Sunshine on My Shoulders," "Take Me Home,
Country Roads," and "Annie's Song." Despite
Denver's frequent reference to the Rocky
Mountains of Colorado, he also wrote songs
about memorable experiences and characters
drawn from the Plains of western Oklahoma
and Kansas. The song "Matthew," for example,
was inspired by real-life wheat farmer and
close relative Dean Deutschendorf.</p>

<p>One of the many causes that Denver championed
was that of the environment, and it
was a theme that dominated the musical compositions
of his later years. On October 12,
1997, he was killed in a single-engine plane
crash near Pacific Grove, California. A few
days later, a memorial service was held for
John Denver in Aurora, Colorado, at the edge
of both the Rocky Mountains and the Great
Plains, the two regions he so proudly celebrated
in his distinctive and uplifting music.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">EUROPEAN AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ea.012">German Russians</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Timothy J. Kloberdanz<lb/>
North Dakota State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Denver, John. <title level="m">Take Me Home: An Autobiography, with Arthur Tobier</title>. New York: Harmony Books, 1994.</bibl> <bibl>Deutschendorf,
Abe. "Memories of My Nephew John Denver."
<title level="j">Journal of the American Historical Society of Germans from Russia</title> 21 (1998): 6–7.</bibl> <bibl>Kloberdanz, Timothy J. "Henry John
Deutschendorf, Jr.: The World Knew Him as John Denver."
<title level="j">Journal of the American Historical Society of Germans from Russia</title> 21 (1998): 1–5.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>