<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.art.004">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Art Museums</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Norman A. Geske</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.art.004</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Geske, Norman A.">Norman A. Geske</author>. <title level="a">"Art Museums."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">111</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-14</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">ART MUSEUMS</head>

<p>The appearance and growth of museums of
art in the Great Plains have taken place mainly
in recent decades. Although nearly 100 museums
devoted to the collection and display of
art in one form or another can be counted in
the region at present, it should be recognized
that they are frequently of an embryonic
nature&#8211;historic houses, collections of popular
or Native American art, exhibition facilities
without permanent collections, and gallery
adjuncts to teaching institutions. The
collections themselves have ranged from work
produced by local artists, to collections of
American art as a whole, to the more restricted
range of the art of the American West,
to the art of Native Americans. Collections of
modern and contemporary art have been the
last to appear, evidence as they are of the transcending
of the historically regional characteristic
of the Great Plains.</p>

<p>Outstanding among the institutions located
from Edmonton, Saskatchewan, to Marfa,
Texas, are the collections of Native American
art at the Buffalo Bill Historical Center in
Cody, Wyoming, the Denver Art Museum in
Denver, Colorado, and the Philbrook Museum
of Art and the Gilcrease Museum in
Tulsa, Oklahoma. Important collections of the
art of the American West, especially in its pioneer
phase, are located at the Glenbow Museum
in Calgary, Alberta (which also specializes
in the art of Canada's First Peoples), the
Joslyn Art Museum in Omaha, Nebraska, and
the Woolaroc Museum in Bartlesville, Oklahoma.
Collections of the work of individual
artists, important to the history of the region,
are those devoted to Harvey Dunn at
the South Dakota Memorial Art Center in
Brookings, South Dakota; Oscar Howe at the
University Art Galleries in Vermillion, South
Dakota; Sven Birger Sandzen at the Birger
Sandzen Memorial Gallery in Lindsborg,
Kansas; and Charles M. Russell at the C. M.
Russell Museum in Great Falls, Montana, and
the Center for Great Plains Studies Art Collection
in Lincoln, Nebraska. A museum devoted
exclusively to the art of a single state is a recent
development of the Museum of Nebraska Art
in Kearney.</p>

<p>Some of the museums of the Great Plains
region have developed holdings of national
importance. Among them are the collections
of American art of the twentieth century at the
Sheldon Memorial Art Gallery in Lincoln, Nebraska,
at the Wichita Art Museum in Wichita,
Kansas, and at the Amon Carter Museum
in Fort Worth, Texas. The Winnipeg Art Gallery,
the nation's first civic art gallery, houses
the world's largest collection of contemporary
Inuit art. The arts of Europe, Asia, Africa, and
Latin America are represented by works of
world-class quality in the collections of the
Nelson-Atkins Museum in Kansas City and
the Kimbell Art Museum in Fort Worth.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Norman A. Geske<lb/>
Lincoln, Nebraska</signed>
</closer>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>