<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.arc.014">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Danish Architecture</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Thomas L. Carter</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.arc.014</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Carter, Thomas L.">Thomas L. Carter</author>. <title level="a">"Danish Architecture."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">74-75</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-12</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">DANISH ARCHITECTURE</head>

<p>Danish architecture in the Great Plains reads
as a minority report. The number of Danes
coming to the region was always small in comparison
to other immigrant groups, and the
fact that they tended to settle individually
rather than in concentrated ethnic communities
makes them relatively invisible on the
landscape. Several Danish cultural strongholds
do exist near and on the Plains: the area
around Tyler in western Minnesota is one; another
is found in the vicinity of Elkhorn
and Kimballton in western Iowa; and another
lies in the area around Dannebrog, Dannevirke,
and Nysted in Howard County, Nebraska.
Wherever they ended up, however,
the Danes, like many other immigrants, constructed
buildings that mirrored in their diversity
the turbulent conditions under which
they were conceived.</p>

<p>Danish emigration occurred largely in the
years between 1870 and 1920 and was directly
linked to the social upheavals caused by industrialization.
As production shifted from farm
to factory, people in the Danish countryside
found themselves on the move, seeking employment
first in their country's urban centers
and then, after finding jobs there insufficient
to match the demand, overseas. It was a time
of great change: not only were people physically
removed from familiar surroundings,
but traditional practices of all kinds were
being replaced by newer and more modern
ways associated with the urban bourgeoisie.
Architecturally, change came in the form of
new popular designs flooding in from all sides
that challenged the older folk forms associated
with the increasingly discredited rural past.
The Danes who came to the Great Plains left
behind a building tradition very much in flux,
and to make things more confusing, they were
greeted in their new homes by even more architectural
choices. It is not surprising that
Danish architecture in the Great Plains and
everywhere else the Danes went defies easy
description.</p>

<p>Like most Plains settlers, Danish families
were forced on arrival to live in dugouts or sod
houses that lacked, due to their size and circumstance,
a clear national or ethnic a.liation.
As the occupation became more firmly
established, however, architectural expectations
increased, and a great number of permanent
buildings, including farmhouses and
outbuildings, stores, town houses, churches,
and schools, were erected. These buildings
display remarkable variety in design and execution,
but they generally adhere to a strong
progressive ethic lodged within the immigrant
community. There are instances where older
Danish folk traditions were followed, particularly
in the use of half-timber, wattle-and-daub,
and unfired clay brick construction. But
such practices were extremely rare and found
only in the first generation. Most Danish immigrants
appear to have chosen, like their
European neighbors, the new balloon-frame
structural system or, more infrequently because
of its high cost, fired brick. The same
willingness to experiment with new ideas is
found in the designs for the buildings as well.</p>

<p>Danish houses fall into three general categories:
houses with origins in Danish
nineteenth-century popular culture; houses
that are American in origin but nevertheless
strongly reminiscent of turn-of-the-century
Danish designs; and, finally, houses that have
no connection to Denmark whatsoever. This
last group is by far the largest, suggesting
that most Danish immigrants simply adopted
whatever American house forms were popular
at the time they arrived. In the 1870s a range of
classically inspired rectilinear houses like the
hall-parlor type prevailed; in the 1880s and
1890s Victorian cottages were the answer; and
after 1900 it was foursquares and bungalows.
Although Danish decorative elements and
furnishings were often retained on the inside,
the exterior treatments betray a strong interest
within the immigrant population in affiliating
with the dominant culture.</p>

<p>When houses do have Danish references,
they are almost always to modern rather than
traditional sources. For example, a number of
immigrants from Denmark during the 1870s
and 1880s built distinctive houses that are
three rooms wide and one or two rooms deep
and have symmetrically tripartite neoclassical
facades. These buildings differ significantly
from typically two-room-wide American
forms but are not traditionally Danish
either. Rather, they refer to a house form that
was introduced into Denmark only during the
second quarter of the nineteenth century and
championed as a symbol of economic achievement
by members of the emerging merchant
and farmer classes. Transplanted to the Great
Plains, the houses granted their occupants
both economic status and national ethnic
identity. The same connection is found, albeit
more indirectly, in the second category of
Danish houses. In the Elkhorn/Kimballton
area, for example, Danish immigrants mostly
built American-style houses. One of these
houses, a one-and-a-half-story bungalow with
a front wall dormer, appears strikingly similar
to the house with a gable roof and front dormer
that was gaining popularity in turn-of-the-
century Danish suburbs. In Denmark the
house usually faced away from the street, with
the main entrance opening onto a protected
courtyard, while in the Great Plains region,
according to American convention, the house
and front door directly addressed the street.</p>

<p>Other kinds of buildings demonstrate a
similar spirit of progress. Danish stores were
aligned along the main street and follow the
American one- or two-part commercial block
variety. Danish churches are similarly nondescript;
except for a few Lutheran churches
that have Flemish-inspired, stepped-gable
parapets and crenellated towers, the predominant
design for religious buildings in Danish
immigrant communities was the ubiquitous
gabled rectangle with engaged front tower
form. Although usually clothed in standard
American architectural garb, Danish folk
schools, part of a sweeping attempt at reforming
the educational system, are another feature
of the Danish architectural landscape that
should be recognized.</p>

<p>One other aspect of the Danish architectural
experience involves the self-conscious
revival of ethnic identity during the second
half of the twentieth century. By the 1950s
most Danish families had become so thoroughly
assimilated into American life that little
or no connection remained with their ancestral
homeland. Since most actual sources
of ethnic identity had been abandoned, new
ones had to be created, and this the descendants
of immigrants did by self-consciously
highlighting elements of the traditional national
culture like costume and food at family
and community celebrations. The residents of
Elkhorn, Iowa, have gone a step further in
dressing up their main street stores in pseudo-
Danish half-timbering, moving a Danish
windmill to the town park, and commissioning
for the town a replica of the famous Little
Mermaid statue.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">EUROPEAN AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ea.006">Danes</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Thomas L. Carter<lb/>
University of Utah</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Betsinger, Signe. "Danes in Iowa and Minnesota." In <title level="m">To Build in a New Land: Ethnic Landscapes in North America</title>,
edited by Allen G. Noble. Baltimore <hi rend="smallcaps">MD</hi>: Johns Hopkins
University Press, 1992: 211–25.</bibl> <bibl>Carter, Thomas. "Danes."
In <title level="m">America's Architectural Roots: Ethnic Groups That Built America</title>, edited by Dell Upton. Washington <hi rend="smallcaps">DC</hi>: Preservation
Press, 1986: 115–23.</bibl> <bibl>Faber, Tobias. <title level="m">Danish Architecture</title>.
Copenhagen: Danske Selskab, 1978.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>