<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.na.112">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Standing Bear (ca. 1829-1908)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>James Lake Sr.</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.na.112</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Lake, Sr., James">James Lake, Sr.</author>. <title level="a">"Standing Bear (ca. 1829-1908)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">605</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-20</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">STANDING BEAR (ca. 1829-1908)</head>
<figure n="egp.na.112" rend="granted" type="noclick">
<figDesc>Formal portrait of Ponca chief Standing Bear</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>In the Nebraska Hall of Fame in the State Capitol
building is a bust of Standing Bear. He is
there among other honored Nebraskans because
of the pivotal role he played in resisting
the United States' efforts to move his people
from their homeland and for his victory in a
famous trial, which projected American injustices
against Native Americans into the
public mind.</p>

<p>Standing Bear was born around 1829 in the
traditional Ponca homeland near the confluence
of the Niobrara and Missouri Rivers.
The Poncas sold this homeland to the United
States in 1858, retaining a 58,000-acre reservation
between Ponca Creek and the Niobrara.
In 1865 the reservation boundaries were modified,
resulting in a larger reservation that
fronted on the Missouri River. On this reservation
the Poncas lived a life of deprivation
and fear&#8211;the United States did little to protect
them from attacks from the Brulé Sioux.
Furthermore, when the United States created
the Great Sioux Reservation in 1868, the Ponca
Reservation was included within its boundaries,
arguably depriving them of title to their
remaining land.</p>

<p>This was the context for the removal of the
Poncas to Indian Territory in 1877. Standing
Bear was among the chiefs who protested this
eviction, and for this he was imprisoned at
Yankton in early 1877. But they were forced
to move. Standing Bear went with the second,
more resistant, group of migrants. On
the way, his daughter Prairie Flower died of
consumption.</p>

<p>On their new reservation in Indian Territory,
the Poncas continued to die in great
numbers. Unknown to their agent, Standing
Bear and twenty-nine other Poncas had been
storing their rations in preparation for the
daunting journey back to the Niobrara. They
left on January 1, 1879, and trekked through
the Plains winter to reach the reservation of
their relatives, the Omahas, in mid-March.
Standing Bear carried with him the bones of
his son to be buried in the familiar earth along
the Niobrara.</p>

<p>Again the federal government intervened.
Standing Bear and his followers were arrested
by order of Gen. George Crook and taken to
Fort Omaha, the intention being to return
them to Indian Territory. At this point Thomas
Henry Tibbles, an Omaha newspaperman, became
interested in their plight and secured
two Nebraska lawyers to represent them. The
lawyers filed a federal court application for
habeas corpus to test the legality of the detention.
Judge Elmer Dundy, after permitting
Standing Bear to make a moving speech, ruled
the detention illegal and the prisoners released.
Dundy reasoned that Indians were indeed
"persons" under the law and entitled to
sever tribal connections and to live where they
desired.</p>

<p>Standing Bear subsequently toured the eastern
United States with Tibbles, arousing support
for the reform of federal Indian policy. In
the 1880s he lived with his followers in the bend
of the Niobrara, farming successfully. They became
known as the Northern Poncas, and their
lives increasingly separated from the Southern
Poncas who had remained in Indian Territory.
Standing Bear died in 1908 and was buried
alongside his ancestors.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">PROTEST AND DISSENT</hi>: <ref n="egp.pd.053">Trial of Standing Bear</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>James Lake Sr.</signed>
University of Nebraska College of Law</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Lake, James A., Sr. "Standing Bear, Who?" <title level="j">Nebraska Law
Review</title> 60 (1981): 451–503.</bibl> <bibl>Tibbles, Thomas Henry. <title level="m">The
Ponca Chiefs: An Account of the Trial of Standing Bear</title>.
Edited by Kay Graber. Lincoln: University of Nebraska
Press, 1972.</bibl> <bibl>Wishart, David J. <title level="m">An Unspeakable Sadness: The
Dispossession of the Nebraska Indians</title>. Lincoln: University
of Nebraska Press, 1994.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>