<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.na.007">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Arikaras</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Mary Jane Schneider</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.na.007</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Schneider, Mary Jane">Mary Jane Schneider</author>. <title level="a">"Arikaras."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">564-565</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-03</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">ARIKARAS</head>

<p>Long before European Americans entered the
Great Plains, the Arikaras, who called themselves
<hi rend="italic">Sahnish</hi>, meaning "People," separated
from the Skiri Pawnees and moved northward
to the Missouri River valley in present-day
South Dakota. From that time on, they were
associated more with the nearby Siouanspeaking
Mandans and Hidatsas than with
their fellow Caddoan-speaking Pawnees to the
south.</p>

<p>Like the Mandans and Hidatsas, the Arikaras
centered their lives on the river, using its
high bluffs for their earth lodge villages and the
rich soil of the bottomlands for gardens of
corn, beans, squash, sunflowers, and tobacco.
In early spring, Arikara women planted and
tended the gardens. Then the people left on
summer bison hunts. They returned to the
village in the fall to harvest the crops. In late fall
they undertook another bison hunt before
moving to the winter villages in the bottomlands,
where there was convenient wood
and water. The earth lodges, like those built
by other horticultural tribes of the Plains,
were dome-shaped structures large enough to
house several generations of a family and all
their belongings. Arikara women made clay
cooking vessels, decorated with stamped or
etched designs, and distinctive willow harvest
baskets. These square baskets, marked by
brown and white geometric patterns woven
around bent wood frames, are unique to the
Arikaras, Hidatsas, and Mandans. Most other
tools and utensils were common to other
Plains tribes. The earth lodges, built and
owned by the women, were usually occupied
by sisters and their families. This kind of system
is often associated with matrilineal clans,
but there is no evidence for such a system
among the Arikaras. It may be that their village
organization and voluntary societies or
associations replaced the functions of the
clans. Some of these societies were military,
encouraging their members to participate in
raids and warfare, while others acted as police
or cared for the poor. Belonging to a society
helped a man attain the military successes and
religious devotions that were required for village
leadership.</p>

<p>Each Arikara village was autonomous, and
leadership was diffuse, organized by rank
rather than hierarchically. When the fur trader
Pierre Antoine Tabeau called a council meeting
in 1804, forty-two of the best-known military
and religious leaders&#8211;called "men of first
rank"&#8211;attended. The second level consisted of
men and women who had been initiated into
the honorary society called Piraskani based on
their excellence of character. The third group
was composed of men who had significant war
honors, probably members of important societies.
The lowest level included all remaining
warriors.</p>

<p>Men who desired leadership positions also
had religious duties. Arikara religious beliefs
and practices centered around a belief in a
principal creator, Nesharu, and a principal
helper, Mother Corn. Mother Corn led the
Arikaras out of the underworld and taught
them what they needed to know to live in
this world. Mother Corn instructed them to
build the Medicine Lodge where the sacred
ceremonies were held and gave each village a
sacred bundle to ensure its well-being and
continuance. In addition, each man had to
seek a spirit guardian, who gave him prayers
and objects to put in a personal sacred bundle.
Throughout the year, the owners of sacred
bundles sponsored ceremonies associated
with corn growing and bison hunting. The
Medicine Lodge ceremony took from fifteen
to twenty days and marked the end of the year
with demonstrations of sacred power, feasting,
curing, and other sacred events.</p>

<p>Arikara culture changed dramatically in the
eighteenth century, as the Lakotas challenged
them for bison-hunting territory, and smallpox
epidemics decimated the tribe. By 1804,
when Tabeau lived with the Arikaras, their
eighteen villages had been reduced to three
fortified settlements. That same year, Lewis
and Clark described the Arikaras as "tenants
at will" to the Lakotas. The Arikaras occupied
these villages off and on until 1823, when they
were attacked by Col. Henry Leavenworth as
punishment for Arikara attacks on traders. In
1837, reeling from the effects of another devastating
smallpox epidemic, most of the tribe
moved north to join the Mandans and Hidatsas
at Fort Clark. Ever since, Arikara history
has been bound with that of the Mandans and
Hidatsas, and in 1862 they settled with them at
Like-a-Fishhook Village.</p>

<p>In 1871 the Arikaras, Mandans, and Hidatsas
ceded their homeland of about 12 million
acres, retaining the eight-million-acre Fort
Berthold Reservation (in present-day North
Dakota). Allotments subsequently reduced the
reservation to about one million acres. At the
end of the 1880s Like-a-Fishhook Village was
abandoned and the Arikaras settled around
the community of Nishu, where they became
ranchers and farmers. Spread across the reservation,
on both sides of the river, the three
tribes led relatively separate lives until 1934,
when they accepted the Indian Reorganization
Act and adopted the name Three A.liated
Tribes of Fort Berthold Reservation. The damming
of the Missouri River in 1954 caused most
tribal members to be relocated. The Arikaras
centered around the town of White Shield,
near some of their most important cultural
sites. In the 1970s about 700 Arikaras lived on
the reservation, and in 1990 the U.S. census
reported a total Arikara population of 1,583.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">WATER</hi>: <ref n="egp.wat.019">Pick-Sloan Plan</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Mary Jane Schneider<lb/>
University of North Dakota</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Meyer, Roy W. <title level="m">The Village Indians of the Upper Missouri: The Mandans, Hidatsas, and Arikaras</title>. Lincoln: University
of Nebraska Press, 1977.</bibl> <bibl>Parks, Douglas R. <title level="m">Traditional Narratives of the Arikara Indians</title>. Lincoln: University of
Nebraska Press, 1991.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>