<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.na.086">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Plains Crees</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>David Meyer</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.na.086</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Meyer, David">David Meyer</author>. <title level="a">"Plains Crees."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">592-593</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-15</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">PLAINS CREES</head>

<p>Plains Crees traditionally occupied&#8211;and still
occupy&#8211;a large section of the Canadian Plains,
extending through much of central Alberta and
central and southeastern Saskatchewan. Most of
this territory is within the Parkland Belt, a transitional
zone between the open grasslands on
the south and the boreal forests to the north.
Plains Crees speak a dialect of Algonquian.</p>

<p>Archeological remains (Selkirk composite)
attributed to the western boreal forest Crees
date from at least <hi rend="smallcaps">A.D.</hi> 1350 in northern Saskatchewan.
Whether Crees also occupied the
Aspen Parklands at this time is not certain,
although there are some late archeological
materials in this zone that reflect Selkirk influence.
Indeed, when Henry Kelsey, the first European
known to have visited the Canadian
Plains, traveled through the Aspen Parklands
of eastern Saskatchewan in 1690, he met Crees
there, along with Nakotas (Assiniboines). Certainly,
the detailed observations of Hudson's
Bay Company employees in the mid-1700s
record the presence of at least four named
Cree groups&#8211;Susahanna, Sturgeon, Pegogamow,
and Kiskatchewan&#8211;in the Aspen Parklands
of Saskatchewan through to central Alberta.
The nature of the social and political
organization of these groups remains uncertain.
It should be noted that the predominant
occupants of the Parklands of Saskatchewan
and Manitoba at this time were the Nakotas
(Assiniboines), who were friends and allies of
the Crees. They often located their camps in
close proximity, particularly at bison pounds.</p>

<p>Beginning in the late seventeenth century
and continuing through most of the eighteenth
century, many of these Crees (and
Nakotas) played a prominent role in the developing
fur trade. In particular, they acted
as middlemen traders, and each summer they
took canoe loads of furs to York Factory on
Hudson Bay. These they traded for European
goods, which, upon returning to the borders of
the Plains, they exchanged with other Native
peoples for furs. Of particular importance was
the Blackfoot-Cree alliance, which formed in
the 1730s and continued throughout the eighteenth
century. At the heart of this alliance was
the provision of guns by the Crees to the Blackfoot
in return for furs.</p>

<p>Important changes occurred in the second
half of the eighteenth century, including the
establishment of a number of fur trade posts
on the fringes of the Canadian Prairies, beginning
with the French posts in the 1740s and
1750s. By 1780 the Hudson's Bay Company, the
North West Company, and some smaller companies
operated many posts in the western interior.
The Parkland Crees and the Nakotas
became much involved in the provisions trade,
producing pemmican for the support of the
employees of the trading companies. An even
more important agent of change was disease,
particularly the smallpox epidemics of 1780–81
and 1837–38, which greatly reduced the Cree
population. Notably, during 1838 most of the
Parkland Crees were vaccinated against smallpox,
a reflection of their close relations with
the Hudson's Bay Company. Unfortunately,
this was not the case with most of the Nakota
bands, which were decimated. The Parkland
Crees then emerged as the predominant occupants
of the Aspen Parklands and adjacent
grasslands of central Saskatchewan and Alberta,
and very quickly became a new tribal
group&#8211;the Plains Crees.</p>

<p>Through the mid–nineteenth century, the
Plains Crees maintained an economic cycle
that positioned them near the grassland/parkland
interface during the winter. A common
method of taking bison at this season involved
building a pound&#8211;a circular corral with an
opening on one side. Wings extending outward
from the opening for a considerable distance
were employed to funnel small herds
into the pound where they were dispatched. In
the course of the winter, some families traveled
into the forest edge to trap fur-bearing
animals, an activity that continued through
the spring. During the latter season they
sometimes built fish weirs on streams in order
to intercept spawning runs. Following this
they moved out into the Plains for the summer.
While the Plains Crees valued horses
highly, the number of horses remained low
because the northern winters impeded their
reproduction and caused a high general mortality.
Therefore, dogs remained an important
draft animal.</p>

<p>By the second half of the nineteenth century
the Plains Crees were divided into eight major
bands. Each of these bands had at least one
prominent chief who often was the focus of a
large camp group; however, all the members of
each band gathered together only once a year,
during the summer. At this time, in late June or
early July, there was a ceremonial gathering at
which the Sun (Thirsting) Dance was celebrated.
The Plains Crees also observed nine
other sacred ceremonies, the most prominent
of which was the Smoking Tipi. However,
in central Saskatchewan the Goose Dance&#8211;a
ceremony of certain boreal forest Crees with
elements adapted from the Midewiwin (the
Grand Medicine Society) of the Ojibwas&#8211;was
also important.</p>

<p>During the second half of the nineteenth
century the bison herds were decimated, their
range contracting to the south and southwest.
As a result, many Crees were drawn far out
onto the grasslands of southwestern Saskatchewan
and northern Montana, where they
came into conflict with their former allies, the
Blackfoot. In the 1870s, with the approaching
extirpation of the bison, most of the Plains
Cree bands entered into treaty agreements
with the Canadian government and took up
residence on some twenty-four reserves in Alberta
and Saskatchewan, where they survived
by farming and ranching.</p>

<p>Over the years, many of the Plains Crees
(and Plains Ojibwas) had intermarried with
French traders, creating the M&#233;tis culture. In
1885, led by chiefs Poundmaker and Big Bear,
they joined their relatives in the North-West
Rebellion. Defeated after two major battles,
Cree leaders were imprisoned, and one group
left Canada and eventually settled on the
Rocky Boy's Reservation in northern Montana.
In the late 1800s the Plains Cree population
was about 7,000; by 1998 it had increased
remarkably to 62,330 persons, with 37,314 living
in Saskatchewan and 25,016 in Alberta. In
recent decades there has been considerable
out-migration from the reserves to the cities
of the Canadian Prairies, and there are now
probably more Plains Crees living in urban
areas than on the reserves.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">WAR</hi>: <ref n="egp.war.032">North-West Rebellion</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>David Meyer</signed>
University of Saskatchewan</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Ahenakew, Freda, and H. Christoph Wolfart, eds. <title level="m">Kwayask
&#234;-k&#238;-p&#234;-kiskinow&#226;pahtihicik. Their Example Showed Me the
Way</title>. Told by Emma Minde. Edmonton: University of Alberta
Press, 1997.</bibl> <bibl>Mandelbaum, David G. <title level="m">The Plains Cree:
An Ethnographic, Historical and Comparative Study</title>. Canadian
Plains Studies no. 9. Regina: Canadian Plains Research
Centre, 1979.</bibl> <bibl>Russell, Dale. <title level="m">Eighteenth-Century
Western Cree and Their Neighbours</title>. Archaeological Survey
of Canada Mercury Series Paper no. 143. Hull, Quebec:
Canadian Museum of Civilization, 1991.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>