<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.med.039">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Sevareid, Eric (1912-1992)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Raymond A. Schroth</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.med.039</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Schroth, Raymond A.">Raymond A. Schroth</author>. <title level="a">"Sevareid, Eric (1912-1992)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">520</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-30</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">SEVAREID, ERIC (1912-1992)</head>

<p>Like many writers who grew up in frontier
towns and achieved national reputations, Eric
Sevareid, cbs World War II correspondent
and tv commentator of the 1960s and 1970s,
viewed his youth in Velva, North Dakota
(population 800), with ambivalence. As a
small boy he climbed the surrounding hills
and gazed over the wheat fields, gaining an
early sense of the infiniteness of his human
possibilities. In his memoir, <title level="m">Not So Wild a Dream</title> (1946), he idealizes Velva as a symbol
of the spirit of democracy that won World
War II. But after moving to Minneapolis at the
age of twelve in 1926, following his father's
bank failure, he returned only three times,
twice as a magazine or <hi rend="smallcaps">TV</hi> journalist to write
about himself.</p>

<p>Born Arnold Eric Sevareid on November
26, 1912, son of Alfred Eric Sevareid, a local
banker, and Clara Hougen, daughter of a Norwegian
Lutheran minister and a regal woman
who encouraged him to read widely, Sevareid
inherited Norwegian reticence and Lutheran
moral integrity.</p>

<p>Young Sevareid crammed more adventure
into his youth than most men experience in a
lifetime. At seventeen, with an older boy, Walter
Port, he paddled a canoe 2,000 miles from
Minneapolis to the Hudson Bay. He rode the
rails to California during the Great Depression
to work for the summer in a gold mine.
At the University of Minnesota his greatest
love was the student paper, the <title level="j">Minnesota Daily</title>, and his greatest disappointment was
not being named editor because, he was convinced,
the university president resented his
opposition to <hi rend="smallcaps">ROTC</hi>. As a cub reporter for the
<title level="j">Minneapolis Star</title> he saw the local establishment's
use of police power to brutally suppress
the truckers strike as one face of domestic
fascism; the other face was the Silver Shirts
movement, which Sevareid exposed in a series
for the <title level="j">Minneapolis Journal</title>.</p>

<p>In 1935 he married Lois Finger, the law student
daughter of the university's track coach,
and they moved to Paris, where Sevareid became
a reporter for the Paris edition of the
<title level="j">New York Herald</title>. Impressed by his coverage
of a murder trial, <hi rend="smallcaps">CBS</hi>'s London-based Edward
R. Murrow invited him to join the news team
&#8211;eventually including William L. Shirer, Charles
Collingwood, Winston Burdett, and Howard
K. Smith and known as "Murrow's Boys"&#8211;that
he was putting together to cover the outbreak
of World War II. Lois, who had just given birth
to twins, Peter and Michael, returned home as
Sevareid covered the fall of Paris, which he
described as "a beautiful woman in a coma, not
knowing or asking why."</p>

<p>Sevareid joined Murrow in London and endured
the blitz, then rejoined his family in
Washington, amazed to discover that his broadcasts
from France and England had made him
a celebrity. When his plane crashed in the
jungles of Burma on his way to China, he and
his party survived two weeks among the Naga
tribesmen, and he emerged more famous than
ever. He returned to the European front and
covered North Africa, the Italian campaign,
the invasion of southern France, and the final
thrust across the Rhine into Germany.</p>

<p>In the 1950s, in his <hi rend="smallcaps">CBS</hi> evening radio news
commentaries, Sevareid developed a unique
journalistic form, the carefully wrought brief
commentary that was erudite without being
pedantic, eloquent but clear. He moved reluctantly
into television, because the lights made
him nervous and because he resented the image
being more powerful than the words. But
his final two-minute commentaries on Walter
Cronkite's <title><hi rend="smallcaps">CBS</hi> Evening News</title>, rendered more
effective by his dignified appearance, made
him one of the most respected American journalists.
His high points were in his condemnations
of the Vietnam War, his defense of freedom
of the press in response to an attack from
Vice President Spiro Agnew, and his Watergate
commentaries.</p>

<p>In 1959, unable to cope with Lois's manic
depression, he fled to Europe with Belen Marshall,
a Cuban songwriter whom he married
in 1963. They had a daughter, Cristina, and
were divorced in 1973. Later, following retirement
in 1977, he married Suzanne St. Pierre,
a producer for <title>60 Minutes</title>. He died in his
Georgetown home of stomach cancer on July
9, 1992. Visitors to his rustic country cabin
outside Warrenton, Virginia, saw how much it
recalled the North Dakota frontier.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Raymond A. Schroth<lb/>
Fordham College</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Schroth, Raymond A. <title level="m">The American Journey of Eric Sevareid</title>.
South Royalton <hi rend="smallcaps">VT</hi>: Steerforth Press, 1995.</bibl>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>