<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.wat.008">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Drought</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Donald A. Wilhite</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.wat.008</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Wilhite, Donald A.">Donald A. Wilhite</author>. <title level="a">"Drought."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">852-853</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-29</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">DROUGHT</head>

<p>Drought is a normal feature of the climate for
virtually all portions of the United States and
some portions of Canada, but it is one of the
defining characteristics of the North American
Great Plains. Early maps referred to this
region as the Great American Desert, a belief
attributed to the explorations of Zebulon Pike
across the Southern Plains in 1806 and of Stephen
Long across the Central Plains in 1819.
20. The drought of the 1890s and, in particular,
the Dust Bowl years of the 1930s define the
region's climatic past. More recently, droughts
have occurred at regular intervals, affecting, at
one time or another, all portions of the region.</p>

<p>Drought is the consequence of a natural reduction
in the amount of precipitation received
over an extended period of time, usually
a season or more in length. Drought is
never the result of a single cause but, rather,
the result of many causes that are synergistic
in nature. Prolonged droughts in the Great
Plains occur when large-scale anomalies in atmospheric
circulation patterns become established
and persist for periods of months, seasons,
or longer. Impacts are complex, vary on
spatial and temporal scales, and depend on
the societal context of the drought. The impacts
of drought in the Great Plains consequently
differ from those experienced in other
portions of the United States and Canada.</p>

<p>Historical climate records for the Great
Plains only reach back to about 1900, and at
only a few locations. Tree-ring data have been
used to reconstruct the earlier drought history
of the region, and these data illustrate a pattern
of periodic and extended droughts, sometimes
continuing for several decades. For example,
H. E. Weakly identified a drought period of
thirty-six years from 1631 to 1667 from an analysis
of tree rings in western Nebraska.</p>

<p>A number of conclusions can be drawn
from the occurrence of severe to extreme
drought in the Great Plains over the last 100
years. First, the percentage of the area in
drought is highly variable from year to year.
The peak drought year was 1934, when 95 percent
of the region experienced severe to extreme
drought. Second, it is rare for severe
drought not to occur somewhere in the region
every year. Third, clusters of drought years,
although rare, appear in the 1890s, 1930s,
mid-1950s, late 1970s, late 1980s to early 1990s,
and, to date, the first three years of the twenty-first
century.</p>

<p>Drought produces a complex web of impacts
that not only reverberate throughout the
region's economy but may also affect other
regions, extending even to the global scale (if,
for example, harvests fail and crop exports are
reduced). These impacts are commonly classified
as economic, environmental, and social.
Many economic impacts occur in broad agricultural
and agriculturally related sectors, because
these sectors are dependent on surface
and subsurface water supplies. In addition to
crop and livestock production losses, drought
is associated with increases in insect infestations,
plant disease, and wind erosion. The
incidence of wildfires increases substantially
during extended droughts, which in turn
places human and wildlife populations at
greater risk. Income loss is another indicator
used to assess drought, because so many sectors
are affected. Reduced income for farmers
has a ripple-down effect as their purchasing
power is reduced, leaving small-town businesses
without customers.</p>

<p>Environmental losses are the result of damages
to plant and animal species, wildlife habitat,
and air and water quality; forest and range
fires; degradation of landscape quality; loss of
biodiversity; and soil erosion. Some of the effects
are short-term, and conditions quickly
return to normal after the drought. Other environmental
effects linger for some time or
may even become permanent. For example,
short-term effects might entail a reduction of
fish or wildlife species or impacts on air quality.
Permanent or long-term effects could be
reduced soil productivity from soil erosion or
an extinction of fish or wildlife species.</p>

<p>Social impacts mainly involve public safety,
health, conflicts between water users, reduced
quality of life, and inequity in the distribution
of impacts and disaster relief. Many of the impacts
that are considered economic and environmental
have social components as well.
The economic hardships of the 1930s drought,
for example, caused significant population
out-migration from and massive flows of aid
into the Great Plains.</p>

<p>Although drought is a natural hazard, vulnerability
to its impacts can be reduced. Improving
management of drought effects requires
identifying both the natural and social
repercussions. The Great Plains has historically
had a very high incidence of drought, and
there is no reason to believe that this incidence
will diminish in the future. Vulnerability, on
the other hand, is determined by factors such
as population numbers, demographic characteristics,
technology, government policy, and
social behavior. These factors change over
time, and vulnerability may increase or decrease
in response to these changes. There was
relatively little dust blowing in the 1890s
drought, for example, for much of the grass
cover had not yet been removed by farming.</p>

<p>Much has been done to lessen societal vulnerability
to drought in the Great Plains. Irrigation,
conservation tillage practices, soil
evaporation reduction measures, snow management,
and irrigation scheduling have all
proved effective in stabilizing agricultural production
in a region exposed to the vagaries of
weather.</p>

<p>The impacts of recent droughts, however,
illustrate the continuing vulnerability. In 1988,
drought affected nearly 40 percent of the nation
and resulted in nearly $16 billion in agricultural
losses. In the Great Plains, this
drought reduced spring wheat yields by 54 percent.
In 1996, drought in the Southwest and the
Southern Great Plains resulted in substantial
agricultural losses, increased incidence of forest
and range fires, municipal water supply
problems, and losses in recreation and tourism.
In Texas alone, drought losses were estimated
to be $6.5 billion. In 1998, drought in
Texas and Oklahoma was estimated to have
resulted in $5.8 billion and $2 billion in losses,
respectively.</p>

<p>Drought planning is one mechanism that
states and provinces have employed to reduce
the economic losses and personal hardships.
The goal of such plans is to improve the effectiveness
of response and preparedness
efforts through improved monitoring and
early warning; impact and vulnerability assessment;
and mitigation programs. These plans
are also directed at improving coordination
and building partnerships within state government
agencies and between state and provincial,
local, and federal governments. Most
Great Plains states currently have drought
plans in place. Plans recently developed by
New Mexico and Nebraska are the most progressive
because they incorporate mitigation
actions as a key component of the planning
process. Formal drought plans do not exist in
the Prairie Provinces.</p>

<p>Drought is a complex, recurrent, and insidious
natural hazard that inflicts considerable
pain and hardship on Plains residents. The
economic, social, and environmental repercussions
of drought result from complex interactions
between physical and social systems,
and they are difficult to quantify. Scientists and
policymakers must understand the characteristics
of drought and appreciate the magnitude
and complexity of impacts in order for viable
assessment, response, and mitigation strategies
to be established.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">ART</hi>: <ref n="egp.art.018">Dust Bowl Photographers</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT</hi>: <ref n="egp.pe.019">Climate</ref>; <ref n="egp.pe.022">Dust Bowl</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Donald A. Wilhite<lb/>
National Drought Mitigation Center</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Hurt, R. Douglas. <title level="m">The Dust Bowl: An Agricultural and
Social History</title>. Chicago: Nelson-Hall Publishers, 1981.</bibl>
<bibl>Wilhite, Donald A., ed. <title level="m">Drought Assessment, Management,
and Planning: Theory and Case Studies</title>. Boston: Kluwer
Academic Publishers, 1993.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>