<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.rel.017">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Distribution of Religions</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>James R. Shortridge</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.rel.017</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Shortridge, James R.">James R. Shortridge</author>. <title level="a">"Distribution of Religions."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">741-742</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-18</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">DISTRIBUTION OF RELIGIONS</head>

<p>The pattern of allegiance to religious groups in
the Great Plains is largely a function of immigration
history. Although denominational
mergers and missionary activities over the
years have made linkages to specific ethnic
groups difficult to discern in places, they nevertheless
remain largely intact. Four broad
bands of dominance trend east and west across
the region: the United Church of Canada in the
Prairie Provinces; a Lutheran-Catholic mix in
the Dakotas, Montana, Wyoming, and northern
Nebraska; a diverse amalgam headed by
Catholicism and Methodism in Kansas, Colorado,
and southern Nebraska; and a Southern
Baptist hegemony throughout most of Oklahoma
and Texas.</p>

<p>The United Church of Canada, a body created
in 1925 by a merger of most of the nation's
Congregational, Methodist, and Presbyterian
congregations, dominates religious life in the
Prairie Provinces. This authority is partly by
default. Canadian Catholics did not move
west from Quebec in large numbers, and most
early Prairie settlers avoided the Anglican
Church because they associated it with the upper
social classes of Southern Ontario. Catholicism
(counting both Latin and Byzantine
rites) is the second most important grouping
in the region, some of it connected with the
early M&#233;tis population and some with the
Ukrainian colonists who came to the northern
fringe of settlement in Manitoba and
Saskatchewan. French Canadian settlers established
St. Boniface, now a part of metropolitan
Winnipeg. Other important religious
regions in the Prairies have evolved from two
German Russian Mennonite colonies south of
Winnipeg and an American Mormon settlement
at Cardston in southwestern Alberta.</p>

<p>When Dakota Territory was first settled by
Europeans and Americans in the 1870s, it and
other parts of the Northern Plains attracted primarily
Yankee settlers drawn from the northern
tier of American states. They brought with
them Congregational, American Baptist, and
Unitarian churches. Most of these people decided
to move elsewhere after a long drought in
the 1890s, however, and left this land to be occupied
by a variety of more permanent immigrants
and faiths from Bohemia, Germany,
Holland, Russia, and Scandinavia. Norwegians
and other Scandinavians came first and concentrated
their Lutheranism in northeastern Nebraska
and in the Red River Valley of eastern
North Dakota. Two counties there (Steele and
Traill) still report that more than 70 percent
of their church membership is Lutheran. Norwegian
Lutheranism also dominates across extreme
northern North Dakota and into extreme
northeastern Montana.</p>

<p>Germans and German Russians settled
widely across the Northern Plains and brought
along with them Catholic, Hutterite, Lutheran,
Mennonite, and Reformed churches. Catholicism
is the leading religion in most of the
Plains counties of Montana and Wyoming,
plus those in the western half of South Dakota.
Most of these churches are German and Bohemian-based,
but some are the product of successful
missionary work among Native Americans.
Episcopalians were active on the mission
front as well, and this church can claim more
than 20 percent of the religious adherents reported
in five counties populated by Lakotas.
Several of the smaller denominations in the
Plains have exceptional strength in certain
places, including the United Church of Christ
in the Nebraska Sandhills; the (Dutch) Reformed
Church in Douglas County, South Dakota;
and the Hutterian Brethren (or Hutterites)
southwest of Lewistown, Montana.
The Native American Church and other Indigenous
religions are important in parts of the
Northern Plains as well, but reliable statistics
for them are unavailable.</p>

<p>In most of the counties of the Central Plains
in Kansas and Nebraska, the United Methodist
Church claims more members than any other
religious body. This preeminence is similar to
that found in rural sections of Ohio, Indiana,
Illinois, and southern Iowa and reflects the origins
in these states of most early immigrants to
the midsection of the Plains. Kansans, in turn,
extended Methodism southward several counties
when they participated in the late-nineteenth-century
land rushes into northwestern
Oklahoma. In many communities across these
states, Methodists account for about a third of
the church membership. Catholicism is the
other major church in this section. With a
strong presence in Kansas City, Omaha, Wichita,
and other large cities, this faith actually has
the largest number of adherents in the Plains.
Catholicism also is important in several rural
areas, including the Volga German communities
of Ellis County, Kansas.</p>

<p>Neither Catholicism nor Methodism is
really dominant over the Central Plains as a
whole, because settlers came from a comparatively
wide variety of places in the United
States and abroad. Northerners scattered
American Baptist and Presbyterian churches
across the region, for example, and people
from the Ohio Valley brought their Disciples
of Christ faith. Similarly, various Europeans
established Catholic, Lutheran, Mennonite,
and other congregations. The biggest of the
Protestant immigrant churches is the Lutheran
Church, Missouri Synod, with 11 percent of the
religious membership in Nebraska and 5 percent
in Kansas. This organization was created
by German settlers in Illinois and Missouri and
it came west with them. Another Germanic
faith, Mennonitism, is a major presence in
Harvey, Marion, and McPherson Counties in
Kansas. The ancestors of local people there
bought land from the Santa Fe Railroad.</p>

<p>With the exception of some Germans in the
Hill Country of Texas, European settlers generally
avoided the Southern Plains. So did emigrants
from the northern states. The religious
scene in Oklahoma and Texas is thus dominated
by the traditional southern denominations,
the Southern Baptist Convention and
the United Methodist Church. Both faiths
grew because they encouraged local leadership
and worked hard on the mission front. In
the past their strength was nearly equal to one
another, but in the 1990s Baptists could claim
about 50 percent of the church membership in
a typical Southern Plains county and the
Methodists only about 15 percent. Fundamentalist
Protestantism is a significant and growing
presence in the region. The Church of
Christ claims 4 percent of the religious adherents
in Oklahoma, for example, as does the
Assemblies of God, the largest of the nation's
pentecostal groups.</p>

<p>The western and southern fringes of the
Southern Plains are a transition zone between
Latino and Southern culture, and thus between
the Catholic and Baptist religious traditions. Expansion
of settlers into eastern New Mexico
took place nearly simultaneously from east and
west, with Latinos seeking irrigation sites and
Anglos grass for their cattle. Since 1900 the Latino
migration has continued eastward and
northward. Some of this is to rural counties, but
most has been to urban, industrial areas. Lubbock,
Texas, now has a major Catholic presence.
So do Pueblo, Colorado, Garden City, Kansas,
and Lexington, Nebraska.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">ARCHITECTURE</hi>: <ref n="egp.arc.040">Religious Architecture</ref>
/ <hi rend="smallcaps">EUROPEAN AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ea.032">Settlement Patterns, Canada</ref>; <ref n="egp.ea.033">Settlement Patterns, United States</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>James R. Shortridge<lb/>
University of Kansas</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Bradley, Martin B., Norman M. Green Jr., Dale E. Jones,
Mac Lynn, and Lou McNeil. <title level="m">Churches and Church Membership
in the United States 1990</title>. Atlanta: Glenmary Research
Center, 1992.</bibl> <bibl>Gaustad, Edwin S. <title level="m">Historical Atlas of
Religion in America</title>. New York: Harper and Row, 1976.</bibl> <bibl><title level="m">The
National Atlas of Canada</title>. Ottawa: Department of Energy,
Mines, and Resources, 1985.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>