<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.war.025">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Little Bighorn, Battle of the</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Douglas Scott</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.war.025</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Scott, Douglas">Douglas Scott</author>. <title level="a">"Little Bighorn, Battle of the."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">830-831</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-28</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">LITTLE BIGHORN, BATTLE OF THE</head>
<figure n="egp.war.025" rend="granted">
<figDesc>" 'The Custer Fight' by Charles Marion Russell. Lithograph. Shows the Battle of the Little Bighorn, from the Indian side." (1903) (Library of Congress)</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>On Sunday, June 25, 1876, Lt. Col. George
Armstrong Custer led 210 men of the U.S. Seventh
Cavalry to their deaths at the Battle of the
Little Bighorn. It was the army's worst defeat
of the Plains Indian Wars.</p>

<p>The prelude to "Custer's Last Stand" began
at the 1868 Treaty of Fort Laramie, which created
the Great Sioux Reservation, including
the Black Hills, as a homeland for the bands of
the Lakotas and Cheyennes. The government's
objective was to settle the Indians down on the
reservation, where they could be more easily
controlled. In 1874 rumors of gold in the Black
Hills were confirmed by a geological team accompanying
Custer's expedition, and white
miners invaded the sacred land. This abrogation
of the treaty rights by Americans encouraged
the Lakotas and Cheyennes to resist restriction
to the reservation and to continue
bison hunting on the ranges of Nebraska, Wyoming,
and Montana. In December 1875 the
United States gave the tribes a thirty-day
deadline to return to their reservations or be
subject to military reprisals.</p>

<p>In the spring of 1876 the United States
launched a three-pronged campaign against
the Cheyennes and Lakotas. The first prong,
under Col. John Gibbon, marched east from
Fort Ellis (near present-day Bozeman, Montana). The second prong, led by Gen. Alfred
Terry (and including Custer) headed west
from Fort Abraham Lincoln near present-day
Bismarck, North Dakota. The third prong
consisted of Gen. George Crook's men moving
north from Wyoming into Montana.
These three units planned to meet near the
end of June in the vicinity of the Little Bighorn.
Unknown to Terry and Gibbon, Crook
encountered the Indians near Rosebud Creek
in southern Montana and was defeated by
them about a week before Custer's battle. After
this, his force withdrew to Wyoming,
breaking one side of the triangle. Meanwhile,
Terry was moving west up the Yellowstone
River to the Little Bighorn. The Seventh Cavalry,
under Custer, scouted ahead on June 22.
On the morning of the 25th, they reached the
divide between Rosebud and the Little Bighorn
Rivers. From a spot known as the Crow's
Nest, they observed a large Indian camp. Worried
the Indians might escape, Custer decided
to attack down the valley of the Little Bighorn.
Custer assumed his approximately 600-member
command would face at the most
800 warriors. Instead he found a camp of
5,000 to 8,000 Indians, with about 2,000 of
them warriors.</p>

<p>Custer divided the Seventh Cavalry into
three elements during the early phases of the
battle and then subdivided his immediate
command into wings. The Lakota and Cheyenne
warriors, although surprised by the
army's attack, quickly rallied and put all elements
of the Seventh Cavalry's attack on the
defensive. The Indians fought in small, loosely
affiliated groups. They used their superior
numbers, took advantage of available cover,
and sniped at the soldiers from long distances.
The soldiers deployed in open skirmish order,
as they were trained, with the result that they
were widely dispersed and became easy targets
for the warriors' guns. Encircled by mounted
forces led by Crazy Horse and Gall, Custer's
entire command perished.</p>

<p>The news of Custer's defeat reached the
American public during the celebration of the
nation's centennial. The reaction was outrage
and military reprisals that confined most of
the Lakotas and Cheyennes to the reservation
by the spring of 1877. Following the Battle of
the Little Bighorn, the Black Hills were confiscated
by the United States in direct contradiction
of the terms of the 1868 treaty. The site of
the battle is now the Little Bighorn Battlefield
National Monument (previously, before December
10, 1991, the Custer Battlefield National
Monument).</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">FILM</hi>: <ref n="egp.fil.015">Custer Films</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">IMAGES AND ICONS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ii.017">Custer, George Armstrong</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Douglas Scott<lb/>
National Park Service</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Scott, Douglas D., Richard A. Fox, Milessa A. Conner, and
Dick Harmon. <title level="m">Archaeological Perspectives on the Battle of
the Little Bighorn</title>. Norman: University of Oklahoma
Press, 1989.</bibl> <bibl>Utley, Robert. <title level="m">Cavalier in Buckskin: George
Armstrong Custer and the Western Military Frontier</title>. Norman:
University of Oklahoma Press, 1988.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>