<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.edu.013">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Cliffs Notes</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>James L. Roberts</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.edu.013</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Roberts, James L.">James L. Roberts</author>. <title level="a">"Cliffs Notes."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">201</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-02</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">CLIFFS NOTES</head>

<p>Cliff Hillegass was born in 1917 in the Great
Plains of Nebraska in the town of Rising
City. He graduated from Rising City High
School, entered Midland College in Fremont,
Nebraska, and, after graduation, began graduate
work as an assistant in geology at the University
of Nebraska in Lincoln.</p>

<p>After a stint in the Army Air Corps in the
1940s Hillegass began work at Long's Book
Store, which soon was renamed Nebraska
Book Company, a firm that is among the nation's
largest handlers of used books. He rose
rapidly through the ranks and became a buyer
of used textbooks throughout a large portion
of the United States. Because of the company's
widespread wholesale network, his enthusiasm,
and his grasp of the value of books, Hillegass
became friends with bookstore managers
from coast to coast. These close business
friendships became the lynchpins that would
later help him launch Cliffs Notes.</p>

<p>In the late 1950s, while Hillegass was visiting
Jack Cole, a Canadian book dealer, Cole suggested
that Hillegass publish a line of literary
study guides similar to Cole's Notes. Cliff
liked the idea, returned to Nebraska, borrowed
money, and arranged with Boomers
Printers to publish 4,000 copies each of sixteen
of Cole's top-selling Shakespeare titles.
Many book dealers were dubious about the
venture, but, because of their longtime friendship
with Hillegass, they agreed to stock Cliffs
Notes, which were boxed and shipped from
Hillegass's basement in Lincoln, Nebraska.</p>

<p>CliffsNotes were an immediate success. So
much so that the business moved from the
basement to a large warehouse in downtown
Lincoln. The series continued to prosper, doubling
in sales every year, and numerous employees
were added to the firm, including professional
editors, a consulting editor, and
many university professors as writers. Along
the way, competing firms began selling literary
study guides (in the early 1970s, for example,
there were thirteen competitors), but
Cliffs Notes outsold them all and survived to
become the generic term for all study guides.</p>

<p>Today, Cliffs Notes are sold all over the
world, and many of the titles have been translated
into other languages. In the United
States they are often used as a teaching tool in
high schools and are recommended or required
reading for many university graduate
courses. Cliffs Notes remained a Lincoln, Nebraska,
firm until it was acquired by <hi rend="caps">IDG</hi>
Books Worldwide, Inc., in 1998 and operations
were moved to Indianapolis, Indiana.
Cliff Hillegass died in Lincoln, Nebraska, on
May 5, 2001.</p>

<closer>
<signed>James L. Roberts<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>