<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.pg.013">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Colorado</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Robert D. Loevy</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.pg.013</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Loevy, Robert D.">Robert D. Loevy</author>. <title level="a">"Colorado."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">658-659</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-29</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">COLORADO</head>

<p>Colorado is famous for its high Rocky Mountains,
but the eastern one-third of the state
consists of High Plains. There is a dynamic
relationship between the mountains and the
Plains. The rain and snow that falls in the
mountains almost every day of the year flows
down to the Plains and is used to irrigate
highly productive farms and ranches. On the
other hand, the mountains create the rainshadow
effect that condemns the Colorado
Plains to a meager annual average of fifteen
inches of precipitation.</p>

<p>Originally, the land area that is now Colorado
was part of four other U.S. territories&#8211;
Nebraska, Kansas, New Mexico, and Utah.
The major event in the governmental history
of Colorado was the discovery of gold near
present-day Denver. The year was 1858, and
news of the gold strike attracted large numbers
of prospectors and miners to the area.
One of the high Rocky Mountains&#8211;Pikes
Peak&#8211;rises above the Plains just seventy miles
south of Denver. Gold seekers rushing into the
region simply steered their horses and covered
wagons toward Pikes Peak, which was readily
visible on the western horizon.</p>

<p>As the population around Denver increased,
there was a movement to make the gold-mining
areas a separate territory and, eventually, a
separate state. In 1861 the U.S. Congress went
along with this idea, and the same legislation
that granted statehood to Kansas created Colorado
Territory. The boundary of the new territory
was nothing more than a big rectangle
drawn around the city of Denver.</p>

<p>The gold mines continued to produce valuable
ore, and then silver was discovered. By 1876
there was enough mining activity and population
for Congress to grant statehood to Colorado.
Because Colorado became a state in the
same year as the 100th anniversary of the Declaration
of Independence, Colorado adopted the
nickname "Centennial State."</p>

<p>The government of Colorado, like that of
most states, is based on the national government.
The legislative power is vested in a bicameral
state legislature, the upper house
known as the Colorado Senate and the lower
house called the Colorado House of Representatives.
Most of the executive power is vested
in a governor. Other elected executive officials
include the treasurer, the attorney general,
and the secretary of state. Starting in 1990 all
state elected officials in Colorado, legislative
and executive, have been limited to two four-year
terms in office.</p>

<p>Because Colorado is a large state with high,
isolating mountain ranges, the state government
has granted a great deal of power
to county and city governments. Cities in particular
have strong home-rule powers and
are allowed to govern themselves, with reduced
interference from state officials or the
state legislature. In the Plains counties, which
are mainly rural and small town in character,
local governments have extensive powers
over welfare programs, road paving, and law
enforcement.</p>

<p>Colorado mainly votes for Republican Party
candidates, but the state has a two-party flavor
and qualified Democrats often do win high
political office. From 1976 to 2000 the Republican
Party enjoyed comfortable majorities in
both houses of the Colorado state legislature.
In the twenty-four years from 1974 to 1998,
however, the Democrats controlled the governorship.
Richard Lamm, a Democrat and a
nationally known environmentalist, was elected
governor in 1974 and served twelve years in
office. Roy Romer, a Democrat with many
business connections in Colorado, was elected
to succeed Lamm in 1986 and also served as
governor for twelve years. Romer had to leave
the governor's office following the 1998 election
when the eight-year term limits took effect.
He was succeeded by a Republican, Gov.
Bill Owens.</p>

<p>Gold and silver mining are no longer the
mainstays of the Colorado economy. During
World War II the U.S. government located a
large number of military facilities in Colorado,
mainly in Denver and Colorado Springs,
two cities located in the Plains right at the foot
of the Rocky Mountains. As a result, Colorado
enjoyed a post–World War II economic and
population boom. That boom was sustained
in the late twentieth century by a large number
of "high-tech" computer and data processing
firms locating in Colorado. In 2000
the population of Colorado was 4.3 million
persons and continuing to grow.</p>

<p>Most of the economic and population
growth in Colorado is concentrated along the
Front Range, an urbanized area running from
north to south at the eastern foot of the Rocky
Mountains. To the east, the High Plains of
Colorado did not share in this rapid growth,
but the region has remained a productive and
successful agricultural area, due in part to irrigation
from rivers and from deep wells.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">AFRICAN AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.afam.044">Webb, Wellington and Wilma</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">HISPANIC AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ha.032">Pe&#241;a, Federico</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Robert D. Loevy<lb/>
Colorado College</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Cronin, Thomas E., and Robert D. Loevy. <title level="m">Colorado Politics
and Government: Governing the Centennial State</title>. Lincoln:
University of Nebraska Press, 1993.</bibl> <bibl>Lorch, Robert S. <title level="m">Colorado's
Government</title>. Niwot <hi rend="smallcaps">CO</hi>: University Press of Colorado,
1991.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>