<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ea.037">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Thompson, David (1770-1857)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Barbara Belyea</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ea.037</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Belyea, Barbara">Barbara Belyea</author>. <title level="a">"Thompson, David (1770-1857)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">249</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-09</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">THOMPSON, DAVID (1770-1857)</head>

<p>David Thompson was schooled for a career
in the Royal Navy; at the end of the Seven
Years War, when the navy was downsized, he
was apprenticed instead to the Hudson's Bay
Company. His first years in the fur trade were
spent at the bay and along the North and South
Saskatchewan Rivers. At the inland posts he
was caught up in the rivalry between the Hudson's
Bay Company and Canadian traders who
had recently joined together as partners in the
North West Company. In 1778–88 the young
man went "a full month's march at about fifteen
miles a day . . . over a fine country" west–
southwest of the river posts in order to trade
with "Peeagans" camped along the front
ranges. Thompson's rudimentary knowledge
of Cree allowed him to converse with Sarka-
map-pee, an old man who had personal experience
of the Plains tribes' shifting alliances
and the smallpox epidemic of 1781. Five years
later Peter Fidler, a fellow Hudson's Bay Company
apprentice, also wintered with "Peeagans"
and served at the Saskatchewan River
posts.</p>

<p>A broken leg forced Thompson to winter at
Cumberland House, which, he wrote, "by the
mercy of God turned out to be the best thing
that ever happened to me." He and Fidler
studied surveying with Philip Turnor, sent
from England to verify claims of Peter Pond's
map of Northwest America. Both apprentices
became accomplished surveyors and cartographers.
But after ten years of routine inland
trade Thompson grew impatient to explore
and chart beyond the Hudson's Bay Company's
trading frontier. In 1797 he left his winter
post in the "Rat Country" west of Hudson
Bay and joined the North West Company.</p>

<p>In order to regulate their southwest trade,
the partners from Canada commissioned
Thompson to ascertain the positions of the
Missouri and Mississippi headwaters relative
to Lake Superior and Lake of the Woods. As of
1792 the forty-ninth parallel had been proposed
as the western boundary between British
and American territories. This line would
replace the earlier treaty of 1783 that agreed on
a border along the supposed northerly source
of the Mississippi near Lake of the Woods.</p>

<p>Thompson's route for this survey lay south
to the Assiniboine River and south again to
Turtle Mountain and the Souris River. He and
his nine men walked overland in December
storms, finding little shelter or wood and few
animals to hunt. The only advantage to traveling
so late in the season was a lowered risk
of running into "Sieux," who would have opposed
their trade with the "Mandanes." On
December 30, 1797, Thompson arrived at the
first of five villages of "Mandanes" and "Willow"
or "Fall Indians" located near the junction
of the Missouri and Knife Rivers. He
stayed for two weeks, long enough to map the
region, compile a vocabulary, and inquire
how the hundreds of domed houses were
built. Thompson wrote that his time was
"spent in noticing their Manners and conversing
about their Policy, Wars, Country, Traditions,
&amp;c &amp;c." Watchful for the interests of the
North West Company, he concluded that "no
hopes could be entertained of their ever coming
to our Settlements to Trade&#8211;indeed they
seem to have but little that is valuable to us."
Nothing in this remark indicates awareness
of the importance of the villages in a longdistance
network of Native trade. In 1803 Samuel
King would use Thompson's survey of this
region as well as Fidler's information on the
upper Missouri to draw a map for Lewis and
Clark. The American explorers wintered at
the "Mandane" villages in 1804–5.</p>

<p>Soon after his return to the Assiniboine
River in the spring of 1798, Thompson set out
again to discover the source of the Mississippi,
which he identified as "Turtle Lake in Latitude
47.39.15 N Longitude 95.12.45 W." As Thompson
explained, the supposition of a more
northerly source was due to "the Fur Traders
. . . counting every pipe a League of three
miles at the end of which they claimed a right
to rest and smoke a pipe. By my survey I found
these pipes to be the average length of only
two miles, and they also threw out of account
the windings of the River." This location,
while not exact, at least placed the Mississippi
well south of Lake of the Woods and was crucial
in promoting the forty-ninth parallel as
the international boundary across the Plains.</p>

<p>Unlike these two trips of 1797–98, Thompson's
later explorations west of the continental
divide were once more subordinated to his
role of trader. From 1807 to 1812 Thompson
worked to establish a new fur-trade department
between two Rocky Mountain passes
and the mouth of the Columbia River. He also
surveyed this region, later incorporating his
regional charts into three huge manuscript
maps of the continent from Hudson Bay and
the Great Lakes to the Pacific Ocean. The historical
construction of a "race to the sea,"
which places Thompson a poor third behind
the Corps of Discovery and the Astorians,
misreads Thompson's fur-trade role and his
most important contribution to western exploration:
his patient, meticulous mapping of
the Columbia River from source to sea.</p>

<p>Thompson retired from the fur trade in
1812 but continued survey work for the international
border along the Great Lakes and in
Lower Canada. His hope of a comfortable settled
life vanished with poor investments; he
was still camping with survey crews when he
was well past sixty years of age. In 1845 he
began a commentary on his years in the fur
trade, based on the journals he had kept during
that period. The fluent, poetic style of this
text has made it a favorite among exploration
accounts since its publication in 1916. Some of
his journals have also been edited: these terse,
detailed, professional records are of great interest
to regional and fur-trade historians.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi>: <hi rend="smallcaps">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</hi>: 
<ref n="egp.pg.027">Forty-ninth Parallel</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Barbara Belyea<lb/>
University of Calgary</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Thompson, David. <title level="m">Columbia Journals</title>, edited by Barbara
Belyea. Montreal: McGill-Queen's University Press, 1994.</bibl>
<bibl>Thompson, David. <title level="m">Narrative</title>, edited by Richard Glover.
Toronto: Champlain Society, 1962.</bibl> <bibl>Wood, W. Raymond,
and Thomas D. Thiessen. <title level="m">Early Fur Trade on the Northern Plains: Canadian Traders among the Mandan Indians, 1738–1818</title>. Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1985.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>