<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.wat.011 SYSTEM "egp.wat.011.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.wat.011">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Irrigation</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>David E. Kromm</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.wat.011</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Kromm, David E.">David E. Kromm</author>. <title level="a">"Irrigation."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">854-855</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-29</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">IRRIGATION</head>

<figure n="egp.wat.011" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Center-pivot sprinkler irrigation system, Alberta</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>In response to moisture deficiency, farmers
irrigate more than 20 million acres in the
Great Plains. Plains irrigation gives water stability
to agriculture, permits a wider diversity
of crops than possible with rain-fed cultivation,
and promotes economic growth through
increased productivity and associated processing
and livestock feeding activities. Irrigation
is most commonly used in the western reaches
of the region, where it is drier and there is
available groundwater and rivers sustained by
Rocky Mountain meltwaters.</p>

<p>Small-scale irrigation in the nineteenth century
involved diverting water onto fields or
using windmills to pump water from shallow
aquifers. By 1900 community and corporate
ditch irrigation enterprises were expanding on
the Platte and Arkansas Rivers, and, through the
efforts of Mormon settlers and railroads, along
various rivers in southern Alberta. Windmills
were commonly used to pump water for people,
stock, and gardens from Texas north to the Dakotas
and Manitoba. A huge windmill near Garden
City, Kansas, provided enough water to irrigate
fifteen acres.</p>

<p>In the American Great Plains large-scale irrigation
began with the Reclamation Act of
1902 that authorized the secretary of the interior
to construct reservoirs, diversion dams,
and distribution canals in the West, including
the Plains states. Subsequently, pump technologies of the 1930s made it possible to lift
water from the Ogallala and other formations
of the High Plains Aquifer. In the Prairie Provinces,
the federal government of Canada and
provincial government of Alberta passed legislation
supporting irrigation. The Alberta Irrigation
District Act of 1915 enabled farmers to
organize into districts that could raise capital
to finance construction of dams, canals, and
other irrigation works.</p>

<p>The Canadian irrigation districts and American
reclamation projects provide water to farmers
through a system of dams on rivers, on- and
off-stream storage reservoirs, diversion canals,
and smaller ditches that lead directly to fields.
Gravity flow is most common, but in some
newer districts in Saskatchewan and rehabilitated
facilities elsewhere, water is provided
under pressure. Farmers receive a specified
amount of water at a set price, with the district
or project maintaining the diversion, storage,
and distribution system. Farmers from Nebraska
south to Texas pump groundwater directly
from the Ogallala Aquifer. Each farmer
holds the right to use a given amount of water,
measured in acre-feet (the volume of water
needed to cover one acre to a depth of one
foot). Allocations usually range between two
and three acre-feet a year. The depth to the
aquifer varies greatly, but a majority of irrigators
pump their water from between 100 and
200 feet. Electricity, diesel fuel, or natural gas
power most of the pump engines. Alternative
sources of water for irrigation, such as eƒ¢uent
from livestock operations or urban areas, provide
water in limited areas.</p>

<p>Most Plains farmers apply water to their
fields using either surface or sprinkler methods.
The main form of surface irrigation is
furrow, whereby furrows are plowed between
crop rows along which water flows from a
pipe with holes called gates. Furrow irrigation
is employed when the land is relatively flat
and the soils absorb water slowly. The leading
form of sprinkler irrigation is the center pivot.
It is a lateral pipe&#8211;with spray nozzles, often
suspended on drop tubes and mounted on
wheeled structures called towers&#8211;that is anchored
at the center of the field and automatically
rotates in a circle. A typical center pivot
has a one-quarter-mile radius and waters approximately
130 acres. More or less ground
can be irrigated by adding or subtracting
pipeline and towers. Center-pivot systems require
more capital investment than furrows,
but they take less labor to operate and can
water uneven terrain and fast absorbing soils.</p>

<p>Irrigation is most developed in areas of good
soils where the saturated thickness is greatest
or where irrigation districts and reclamation
projects have diverted river flow. In 1998 Nebraska
led the Plains states with more than 6.3
million irrigated acres, followed by Texas with
more than 4.4 million irrigated acres in the
Plains part of the state. Next in importance
were Kansas (2.7 million acres), Colorado (1.7
million acres in the Plains), and Alberta (1.5
million acres). Montana, Oklahoma, New
Mexico, South Dakota, Saskatchewan, Wyoming,
and North Dakota each had between
180,000 and 800,000 irrigated acres; Manitoba
irrigated some 32,000 acres. Most of the irrigated
land in Nebraska, Texas, and Kansas relies
on water from the High Plains Aquifer
system. At the beginning of the twenty-first
century irrigated acreage continued to increase
in nearly all areas.</p>

<p>A wide array of crops is irrigated in the
Great Plains. Corn occupies about two-fifths
of the irrigated land. Nebraska irrigates more
than 4.7 million acres of corn and Kansas
nearly 1.2 million acres. Hay, grown throughout
the region, accounts for nearly 12 percent
of the acres irrigated. It is relatively most important
in Wyoming and Montana, where irrigated
pasture is also significant. Irrigated
wheat is most important in Oklahoma, Kansas,
Alberta, and Texas. Grain sorghum is irrigated
on about 1.4 million acres, nearly twothirds
of which is in Texas, where feedgrains
are replacing once-dominant cotton. The irrigated
area for all these crops is expanding, as it
is also for soybeans, sugar beets, and potatoes.</p>

<p>The sustainability of irrigation in the Great
Plains is threatened by soil salinization and
by groundwater depletion. Most irrigationinduced
soil salinity results from water losses
in transport, where seepage from canals raises
the water level and brings natural salinity
nearer to the surface and within the root zone
of crops. Lining irrigation canals and ditches
reduces the problem, but it can be very expensive.
In Alberta much of the 4,500 miles of
canals in the conveyance system has been rehabilitated
in this way. Poor on-farm management
of irrigation water also can cause salinity,
especially in low-lying areas where water
ponds and soil become salinized after evaporation.
Soils with saliency programs can be
reclaimed if the water table is brought below
the root zone and the excess salts are leached
out of the soil. The depletion of the High
Plains Aquifer concerns farmers, as saturated
thickness (the vertical extent of the watered
zone in the aquifer) is limited in many areas,
especially in Texas and New Mexico, and recharge
is minimal. In some areas there is
not enough water remaining to support irrigation.
The distance to the water increases as
irrigation lowers the water table, and lifting
water becomes too costly when energy prices
are high. There also is concern for groundwater
quality when agricultural chemicals
reach an aquifer.</p>

<p>In response to groundwater depletion, the
desire to increase irrigation, and competing
demands for water, irrigation efficiency has
become a priority for most Plains irrigators.
Water-saving practices have been widely
adopted by farmers. Furrow irrigation has become
less water-consumptive through the use
of surge flow, whereby water is intermittently
released from the gated pipes to discharge in
surges that achieve relatively even watering
along the entire length of a row. Center-pivot
sprinklers are being fitted with low-energy
precision application (<hi rend="smallcaps">LEPA</hi>) systems that use
low-pressure emitters on drop tubes to apply
the water directly on or near the soil. Drip
irrigation, wherein water drips or trickles
from perforations in a low-pressure pipe
placed alongside the base of a row of plants,
and subsurface drip irrigation, with the water
carried directly to the root of the plants, have
moved from experimentation to actual field
use. Most farmers employ some form of irrigation
scheduling to apply only the water required
by a crop under different evaporative
conditions. Water-saving innovations extend
the available water supplies to assure the continuance
of irrigation in the Great Plains.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">INDUSTRY</hi>: <ref n="egp.ind.011">Center Pivots</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>David E. Kromm<lb/>
Kansas State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Green, Donald E. <title level="m">Land of the Underground Rain: Irrigation
in the Texas High Plains, 1910–1970</title>. Austin: University
of Texas Press, 1973.</bibl> <bibl>Kromm, David E., and Stephen E.
White, eds. <title level="m">Groundwater Exploration in the High Plains</title>.
Lawrence: University Press of Kansas, 1992.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>