<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.pg.034 SYSTEM "egp.pg.034.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.pg.034">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Johnson, Lyndon Baines (1908-1973)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Patrick L. Cox</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.pg.034</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Cox, Patrick L.">Patrick L. Cox</author>. <title level="a">"Johnson, Lyndon Baines (1908-1973)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">668-669</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-29</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">JOHNSON, LYNDON BAINES (1908-1973)</head>

<figure n="egp.pg.034" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Lyndon Baines Johnson and Secretary of Agriculture Orville Freeman at LBJ Ranch, November 1964</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Lyndon Baines Johnson, thirty-sixth president
of the United States, was one of the most controversial
and important chief executives since
World War II. Born on a small farm in the
scenic Texas Hill Country near the community
of Stonewall on August 27, 1908, Johnson grew
up in a family where politics and public affairs
took center stage. He married Claudia Alta
"Lady Bird" Taylor in 1934 while serving as
secretary to Texas congressman Richard Kleberg.
Johnson served as Texas director of the
National Youth Administration in the 1930s
and won his first election to Congress in 1937 as
a New Deal Democrat and an ardent Franklin
Roosevelt supporter. He subsequently won a
seat in the U.S. Senate in 1948 by narrowly
defeating Gov. Coke Stevenson in one of the
most controversial elections in modern political
history.</p>

<p>Johnson became Senate majority leader in
1955 and gained recognition for his ability to
pass legislation while cooperating with the Republican
presidential administration. In 1960
he ran as John Kennedy's vice president to
provide experience and balance to the ticket.
His presence on the ballot helped deliver key
states like Texas, while increasing Democratic
votes throughout the Great Plains states.
Johnson unexpectedly achieved his goal of the
presidency following Kennedy's assassination
in Dallas on November 22, 1963. With the sentiment
of the nation behind him, Johnson
pushed the landmark Civil Rights Act of 1964
through Congress as he planned his election-year
strategy.</p>

<p>The Great Plains had provided a bastion of
political support for the Republican Party
since the demise of the Populist movement.
Between 1952 and 1996 the majority of states in
the region supported Republican presidential
candidates. The only exception was 1964,
when Lyndon Johnson steamrolled Republican
Barry Goldwater in one of the most lopsided
presidential elections in history. In a
whirlwind campaign tour through the area,
Johnson quoted Texas historian Walter Prescott
Webb in saying, "America's frontier is different.
It lies inside our country, not at the
edge." Johnson rode a wave of sentiment and
popularity in sweeping the electoral votes of
the Great Plains in 1964, bringing many new
Democratic congressmen to Washington on
his coattails.</p>

<p>With his popular mandate and an overwhelming
congressional Democratic majority,
Johnson pushed legislation at a frantic pace.
The War on Poverty, the Voting Rights Act,
Medicare, Head Start, the National Endowment
for the Arts, the National Aeronautics
and Space Administration (<hi rend="smallcaps">NASA</hi>), and a multitude
of other initiatives were launched, greatly
expanding the federal presence at every level.
His "Great Society" programs exceeded those
of the New Deal, as Johnson crafted an agenda
that fundamentally reshaped American society
and culture. Johnson also wanted an impact on
the land itself. As part of his "New Conservation"
efforts, Congress passed landmark environmental
legislation: the Clean Air Act, the
Wilderness Act, the Endangered Species Act,
the Water Quality Act, and many more that
brought long-term change to America's heartland.
Immensely impressed with this record,
Sen. Clinton Anderson (Democrat–New Mexico)
called Johnson "the smartest politician I
ever knew."</p>

<p>Johnson launched new programs to aid
rural America and agriculture. The Food
Stamp Act reduced farm surpluses and increased
income while setting up a popular
program that enabled less-fortunate Americans
to purchase basic commodities. More
than $2 billion went to the Rural Electrification
Administration (<hi rend="smallcaps">REA</hi>) to extend electricity
and telephones. The largest loan in <hi rend="smallcaps">REA</hi>
history allowed a North Dakota cooperative to
provide electricity to over one million residents
in eight states. Personal income levels in
the Great Plains during the Johnson years increased
in a region still largely dependent on
agriculture.</p>

<p>As part of his civil rights program, Johnson
sought to bring Native Americans into the national
mainstream. In a reversal of federal policies
in the 1950s that attempted to relocate
Native Americans from their lands to cities,
Johnson's administration pushed for aid to
expand education and economic opportunities
and placed a new emphasis on Indian cultures.
More than $10 billion in federal aid
went to Indians in an attempt to reduce poverty
and unemployment that ran as high as 85
percent on some reservations. He appointed
Robert L. Bennett, an Oneida Indian, as the
first Native American to head the Bureau of
Indian Affairs in the twentieth century. In
1968 Johnson's speech on "The Forgotten
American" urged approval of the "Indian Bill
of Rights." The legislation extended protection
of the U.S. Constitution for Indians in
their own tribal constitutions amid a resurgence
of Indian sovereignty.</p>

<p>However, foreign affairs diverted Johnson's
attention, as he inherited Kennedy's commitment
to Vietnam. Johnson expanded the nation's
military commitment, and by 1965 the
United States assumed primary responsibility
for the Vietnam War. Vietnam soon replaced his
domestic agenda as the cost of maintaining the
war forced the administration to choose guns
over butter. Opposition steadily increased at
home as casualties mounted with no discernible
end to the conflict. Faced with rising opposition
within Congress and his own party, coupled
with his overall decline in popularity, Johnson
surprised the nation on March 31, 1968, when he
announced on television that he would not seek
reelection, and he called for renewed efforts for
peace. Like many others, Sen. Gale McGee
(Democrat-Wyoming), a Johnson stalwart, reacted
with shock to Johnson's decision: "I had to
listen to the replay again to still believe it," Mc-
Gee said. McGee and others were soon disappointed,
as the peace initiatives failed to end the
fighting in Vietnam before Johnson left office
and Democratic presidential nominee Hubert
Humphrey lost a close election to Republican
Richard Nixon in November 1968.</p>

<p>Johnson's liberal nationalism left a legacy of
achievement but opened the door for conservative
reaction and political realignment as a
result of his ambitious domestic agenda. His
many accomplishments are now part of the
nation's heritage and illustrated his deep conviction
to civil rights and economic opportunity
to all Americans. His decisions concerning
Vietnam demonstrated the limits of
American power during the cold war era. In
1969 Johnson and his wife, Lady Bird, retired
to their ranch, where he lived until a heart
attack ended his life on January 22, 1973.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Patrick L. Cox<lb/>
University of Texas at Austin</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Anderson, Clinton, and Max Magee. Interviews. <title level="m">Oral History
Collection</title>. Lyndon Baines Johnson Presidential Library,
Austin.</bibl> <bibl>Dallek, Robert. <title level="m">Flawed Giant: Lyndon Johnson
and His Times, 1961-1973</title>. New York: Oxford University
Press, 1998.</bibl>  <bibl> <title level="m">Public Papers of the Presidents of the United
States: Lyndon B. Johnson</title>. Washington <hi rend="smallcaps">DC</hi>: Government
Printing Office, 1964-69.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>