<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.gen.040 SYSTEM "egp.gen.040.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.gen.040">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Women Homesteaders</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>H. Elaine Lindgren</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.gen.040</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Lindgren, H. Elaine">H. Elaine Lindgren</author>. <title level="a">"Women Homesteaders."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">339-340</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-23</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">WOMEN HOMESTEADERS</head>

<figure n="egp.gen.040" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Agnes Lamb on the day she filed on her homestead land near the town of Washburn, North Dakota, ca. 1906</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Thousands of women took advantage of the
Homestead Act (1862) that offered free land in
the American Great Plains. Women who were
single, widowed, divorced, or deserted were
eligible to acquire 160 acres of federal land
in their own name. The law discriminated
against women who were married. A married
woman was not allowed to take land in her
own name unless she was considered the head
of the household. The majority of homesteading
women were young (at least twenty-one),
single, and interested in adventure and the
possibility of economic gain.</p>

<p>Lucy Goldthorpe told how she got caught
up in the excitement of the times. "Even if you
hadn't inherited a bit of restlessness and a pioneering
spirit . . . it would have been difficult
to ward off the excitement of the boom." Pauline
Shoemaker remarked, "I've done everything
else, I might as well try homesteading."
Louise Karlson was looking for a good investment:
"When in 1908 I heard about the homestead
land one could get . . . I thought, here is
my chance." A few women homesteaded land
to help a male relative expand his acreage.
This was the exception rather than the rule,
and even in these cases the women usually
received some compensation for their efforts.</p>

<p>Homesteading provided widows with an
economic opportunity often denied them
elsewhere. Many had children to support.
Tyra Schanke, when widowed, was left with
three children, ages three, four, and five. Kari
Skredsvig brought up her seven children on
a homestead near Bowbells, North Dakota.
Even the elderly women took part in this venture.
Anna Hensel was sixty-seven when she
immigrated to the United States from Bessarabia
in southern Russia. A year later, in 1903,
she declared her intent to become a citizen and
applied for a homestead in Hettinger County,
North Dakota. Women from almost all ethnic
groups took advantage of homesteading opportunities.
An extensive but not all-inclusive
list would include Anglo-Americans, Norwegians,
Swedes, Danes, Finns, Hollanders,
Icelanders, Germans, Germans from Russia,
Bohemians, Poles, Ukrainians, Lebanese, Irish,
English, Scottish, Italian, African Americans,
and Jewish Americans.</p>

<p>Although the initial experiences of homesteaders
varied considerably, few women or
men struck out on such an undertaking by
themselves. Settlers usually came with family
or friends, but a few managed alone. Kirsten
Knudsen left Norway with two other young
women, but she came to Mountrail County,
North Dakota, by herself. She knew no one
and could not speak English. She carried only
a letter of introduction to an attorney from a
mutual friend.</p>

<p>The length of time it took to "prove up," or
receive title to the land, varied over the years.
The Homestead Act of 1862 required a five-year
residence, but the definition of residence was
ambiguous. Some homesteaders left their land
for lengthy periods of time to earn money, visit
family, or escape severe weather. Others remained
on the land most of the time. Shortly
after the initial Homestead Act was passed,
amendments provided for other ways of "commuting"
the claim. One such option allowed
the homesteader to reside on the claim for only
fourteen months and then pay $1.25 an acre to
receive title.</p>

<p>Women who took homesteads tended to
"work out" as well. Many of them pursued
careers as teachers, nurses, seamstresses, and
domestic workers, but a few followed less traditional
paths such as journalism or photography.
Many eventually married, but some remained
single. Those who achieved economic
success used their resources in a variety of
ways. Some stayed on their homestead and
accumulated additional land. Others sold
their holdings and invested elsewhere. In
some cases homesteaders rented out the land
and used the proceeds for personal or family
needs. Ida Popp sold her land in Bowman
County, North Dakota, and bought land adjoining
her husband's claim. Lucy Gorecki
traded her 160 acres for a commercial building
in Fordville, North Dakota. Anna Mathilda
Berg traded her homestead for a boardinghouse
in Warwick, North Dakota.</p>

<p>In many ways, women who homesteaded
resemble contemporary women. Their schedules
were demanding, requiring flexibility, ingenuity,
and endurance. Most would be considered
community movers and shakers, as
their initiatives were instrumental in building
schools, churches, and other community institutions.</p>

<p>The homesteading period of history usually
brings to mind stories of blizzards, prairie
fires, and other catastrophic events. Yet tragedy
is but one dimension of human life. To
dwell on that aspect is to distort reality. In
spite of their heavy demands, many homesteaders
found time to devote to music, art,
literature, and even poetry. A sense of humor
was important in shaping their outlook
on life.</p>

<p>Visitors to the homestead of Kirsten Knudsen
likely were amazed to hear musical strains
from the scores of operas such as <title>La Traviata</title>
and <title>Aida</title> come floating through the prairie
air. When Kirsten arrived on her homestead
she brought with her the operas, memorized
when she had spent time as a chorus girl in the
National Theater in Oslo, Norway. Women as
well as men were proficient in violin, piano,
organ, and other instruments. Anna Zimmerman
told of playing for dances with her
brother. They both played accordion, violin,
and guitar. Anna often played the harmonica
and danced at the same time. Homesteading
was more than tears and suffering.</p>

<p>A closer look at the lives of women who
homesteaded does not reaffirm the old descriptions
that characterized them as secondary
"helpmates" or reluctant pioneers. Rather,
they, along with men, were main characters in
the settlement drama.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">EUROPEAN AMERICANS</hi>: 
<ref n="egp.ea.023">Land Laws and Settlement</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>H. Elaine Lindgren<lb/>
North Dakota State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Fairbanks, Carol. <title level="m">Prairie Women: Images in American and Canadian Fiction</title>. New Haven <hi rend="smallcaps">CT</hi>: Yale University Press,
1986.</bibl> <bibl>Lindgren, H. Elaine. <title level="m">Land in Her Own Name</title>. Norman:
University of Oklahoma Press, 1996.</bibl> <bibl>Muhn, James.
"Women and the Homestead Act: Land Department Administration
of a Legal Imbroglio, 1863–1934." <title level="j">Western Legal History</title> 7 (1994): 283–307.</bibl>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>