<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.pg.011">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Civil Divisions of Government</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>J. Clark Archer</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.pg.011</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Archer, J. Clark">J. Clark Archer</author>. <title level="a">"Civil Divisions of Government."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">657-658</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-29</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">CIVILIAN DIVISIONS OF GOVERNMENT</head>

<p>The lands and peoples of the North American
Great Plains fall within the territorial jurisdictions
of the Dominion of Canada and the
United States of America. These countries are
federal democracies with three distinct levels
of representation and administration: national
or federal, state or provincial, and local
levels of government. Citizens elect legislators
and other officeholders, pay taxes, and are
governed by laws enacted at each of the three
levels of governance. Canada's more formally
centralized parliamentary system is based on
the British principle of "responsible government,"
with members of the national executive
cabinet chosen from, and accountable to,
the legislature. There is no separately elected
executive, as in the U.S. presidential and congressional
system.</p>

<p>Lands of the Great Plains north of the fortyninth
parallel fall within Canada's three "Prairie
Provinces" of Alberta (provincehood 1905),
Manitoba (1870), and Saskatchewan (1905).
These provinces were formed from part of the
area controlled until 1870 by the Hudson's Bay
Company. The unicameral legislatures of each
of these provinces have principal authority
over such matters as natural resources, education,
land tenure, health, property, and civil
rights within their territories, and each legislature
shares authority with the Canadian
national government over inland waterways,
railroads, external trade, agriculture, old-age
pensions, and foreign immigration to their local
regions. Governmental units at the local or
third tier of government are formally subdivisions
of the provincial governments. Partly because
Canadians believed that extreme localism
had been one of the precipitating causes of
the American Revolution, local governments
in Canada generally have been restricted to
more limited roles than in the United States.
However, distance from the federal capital in
Ottawa, combined with the passage of time,
encouraged the establishment of stronger local
authorities in the Prairie Provinces than in
eastern Canada. The three Prairie Provinces
are subdivided into about 1,300 urban and
rural municipalities. However, some three-quarters
of the total population lives in thirty-five
of the larger municipalities that are classed
as cities. Small populations, weak tax bases,
and confusing overlaps between municipal,
school district, and hospital district boundaries
have forced considerable reorganization
and consolidation of local government units in
more rural areas of the Prairie Provinces in
recent years.</p>

<p>The Great Plains south of the forty-ninth
parallel falls within the territories of ten of the
fifty states of the United States. These include
Colorado (statehood 1876), Kansas (1861),
Montana (1889), Nebraska (1867), New Mexico
(1912), North Dakota (1889), Oklahoma
(1907), South Dakota (1889), Texas (1845), and
Wyoming (1890). These states span most of
the territories acquired from France via the
Louisiana Purchase in 1803 and from Mexico
via the annexation of Texas in 1845. Although
these states entered the Union relatively late,
they all have sovereign status under the U.S.
Constitution, which formally reserves all
powers not expressly delegated to the federal
government to the states and their citizens.
While the federal government holds primary
jurisdiction over several important matters,
such as currency, foreign relations, and national
defense, most aspects of governance involve
shared or overlapping federal and state
responsibilities. Both legally and practically,
the powers of state governments are maintained
and reinforced by governors and by
legislatures whose members are independently
elected by the citizens of each state. Except
for Nebraska's unicameral, all state legislatures
are bicameral.</p>

<p>Partly reflecting the strong localistic aspect
of American political culture, the lowest or
third tier of American governance tends to be
considerably more varied and complex than is
the case in Canada. In addition to the federal
government and their respective state governments,
most Americans also pay taxes to a
county government, a city or town government,
a school district unit, and several socalled
special districts. Although units of local
government are formally subdivisions of state
governments, they often tend to have considerable
legal and practical autonomy over their
own local affairs. Thus, levels of local tax
effort and pubic service provision can and do
vary greatly from place to place within the
United States. Moreover, the degree of governmental
localism that is encountered in the
American Great Plains is often even more intense
than elsewhere in the nation. One indicator
is the unusually high incidence of
patriotic names given to counties, towns, or
streets within the region, such as Washington,
Lincoln, Franklin, Union, Liberty, Independence,
Freedom, or Unity.</p>

<p>Another, more important indicator is the
sheer number of local governmental units
within the Great Plains. The ten Plains states
contain more than 21,000 local governments,
including 818 counties, 4,183 municipalities,
4,124 towns or townships, 4,148 school districts,
and 8,600 special districts. The citizens
of these ten states vote in various constituencies
for seventy-eight officials at the federal
level (for president, senators, and representatives)
and for 2,903 officials at the state level
(e.g., governors, attorneys general, judges, legislators).
In addition, the citizens of these ten
states elect an astonishing 110,328 local officials
(e.g., mayors, sheriffs, justices, county commissioners,
and members of city or town
councils, school boards, and special district
bodies). Indeed, in many of the more lightly
populated counties of the Central Plains,
more than one out of every twenty-five persons
is an elected local official of some type.
Among the more extreme cases is Arthur
County, Nebraska, with a 1990 population of
462 persons and fifty elected local officials
in 1992. In comparison, the average for the
United States as a whole is about one elected
local official for every 500 people. While the
overall average for Great Plains states is about
one elected local official for every 285 people,
the rate is much higher in many rural areas.
Though this indicates a very high rate of direct
participation in local government, it must be
recognized that efforts to maintain local government
services impose substantial burdens
on the residents of sparsely populated sections
of the Great Plains.</p>

<closer>
<signed>J. Clark Archer<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>U.S. Bureau of the Census. <title level="m">1992 Census of Governments</title>.
Washington <hi rend="smallcaps">DC</hi>: Government Printing Office, 1994.</bibl> <bibl>Zelinsky,
Wilbur. <title level="m">Nation into State: The Shifting Symbolic Foundations
of American Nationalism</title>. Chapel Hill: University
of North Carolina Press, 1988.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>