<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ea.033">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Settlement Patterns, United States</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>John L. Dietz</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ea.033</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Dietz, John L.">John L. Dietz</author>. <title level="a">"Settlement Patterns, United States."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">246-247</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-09</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">SETTLEMENT PATTERNS, UNITED STATES</head>

<p>The dominant settlement patterns of the
Great Plains of the United States reflect both
an initial 1800s pioneer landscape and subsequent
changes: the evolution of the region's
landscape is a continuing process.</p>

<p>The pioneer settlement process divided
the grasslands of North America into a vast
checkerboard where squares were separated by
section lines, which became roads, field divisions,
county lines, and even state lines. The
artificially imposed matrix of the U.S. Public
Land Survey System, originating with the
Ordinance of 1785, obliterated the natural
landscapes known to the Native Americans.
Six-mile-square townships were divided into
thirty-six one-mile-square sections of 640
acres. European-style <hi rend="italic">strassendorf</hi> villages or
earlier New England–style village commons
were virtually unknown, since the Homestead
Law of 1862 required that homesteaders live on
the land they claimed.</p>

<p>The homesteaders flowed into the Great
Plains from a wide variety of origins. Nativeborn
Americans moved in generally latitudinal
directions from former homes in the eastern
United States into the Plains. The children
of former pioneers from New York, born in
southern Wisconsin in the 1840s and 1850s,
were the first American settlers in Dakota Territory
in the 1870s and 1880s. To their south, a
mixture of settlers from New York, New England,
and Pennsylvania pioneered in a belt
from Ohio to Iowa, then sent their children on
to settle western Nebraska, southern Dakota
Territory, and northern Kansas. "Midlanders"
from Ohio, Indiana, and Illinois constituted a
major flow into Kansas, but that state's southern
part in particular was filled from the Upper
South, from Missouri, Kentucky, southern
Indiana, and southern Illinois. Farther south,
in the late-settled American frontiers of Oklahoma
and the Texas High Plains, the latitudinal
migration was again evident, with settlers
coming from Tennessee and the Deep South.
African Americans also settled in considerable
numbers in Kansas and Oklahoma after the
Civil War. Several African American homesteader
communities survive.</p>

<p>The population geography was diversified
by settlers from Europe. Chain migration, in
which early settlers wrote back to the home
folks in Scandinavia, Germany, Russia, and
the Austro-Hungarian Empire to encourage
their migration, led to many ethnic colonies
throughout the Plains, many of which survive
in some form to the present. In general, the
percentage of European-born settlers and
their children decreased from north to south.
Notable among these groups were the German
Russians, who brought hard red winter
wheat seed to central Kansas and laid the
foundation for the winter wheat belt. Scandinavians
overflowed to the Dakotas and Montana
from Minnesota and produced a Viking
veneer over the Northern Plains. In Kansas
and Nebraska, high school teams are still
known by such names as the Swedes or Cossacks
depending on the origins of the original
homesteaders. In Oklahoma, the land rush
produced an ethnic pattern that reflected Native
American, Confederate refugee, and European
origins. On the Texas Plains the pattern
was initially dominated by people of
southern U.S. and Mexican origin: in the
Texas Panhandle in 1880, for example, about
two-thirds of the population had origins in
the eastern United States, mainly from the
South, while one-fifth of the population was
Mexican, mainly from New Mexico. The Latino
component of the Plains population continued
to grow rapidly during the twentieth
century, with a core area in the New Mexico
and Texas Plains but also forming a major
presence in eastern Colorado, southeastern
Kansas, the meatpacking towns of Nebraska,
and elsewhere throughout much of the region.
This Latino immigration, and a growing
Asian population, continue the tradition of a
region enriched by waves of migration.</p>

<p>In most areas, homesteaders in the nineteenth
century located on dispersed farms of a
quarter-section (160 acres). There were occasional
interspersed rural schools, churches,
and post offices. Initial building construction
often utilized native sod, since lumber was
not available. Barbed wire fences were used to
divide fields because rails were not available
either. Sod homes were often replaced by relatively
expensive lumber construction as soon
as railroads and improved finances made it
possible.</p>

<p>The initial village pattern consisted of service
centers at critical stream fords and at
the intersections of wagon and horse trails. As
railroad expansion spread a vast web of iron
rails across the Plains, new sites emerged,
since steam locomotives required water every
eight to ten miles. These watering spots became
the nuclei from which permanent villages,
towns, or cities emerged. Here sprouted
railroad depots, water towers, grain elevators,
stockyards, stores, schools, and churches&#8211;
facilities to enable the dispersed homestead
farmers to obtain their supplies, market their
products, and provide for their basic living
needs. Early communities vied with each
other for the right to be the county seat, and
occasionally heated battles occurred. Such
a role was perceived as essential if a place
was to become dominant in the future urban
hierarchy.</p>

<p>As the twentieth century progressed, depression
and dust bowl conditions modified
the settlement pattern, initiating significant
changes that continue to the present. Rural
free mail delivery led to the discontinuance
of many of the open-country post offices.
Farm consolidation led to the abandonment
of many section-line roads, and operations
that were originally farms became ranches.
Removal of much of the rural population led
to the consolidation of rural schools and
churches. The advent of larger railroad steam
engines, and then of diesel engines, decreased
the need for water-tower villages&#8211;only the
grain elevator survives in many diminished
places. Additionally, improved highways and
the use of trucks doomed many of the branch
railroads and the villages they served.</p>

<p>The present settlement pattern of the Great
Plains reflects this consolidation process and
some unique situations. As the farm population
consolidated, the need for service centers
declined and a few strategically located centers
(often county seats) emerged as the dominant
centers. This pattern reflects to some extent
the division of the Plains into irrigated and
nonirrigated areas, with denser settlement
patterns in the irrigated oases of the river valleys
and High Plains Aquifer.</p>

<p>The original Plains peoples, the Native
Americans, remain an important and rapidly
growing component of the region's population,
especially on the Northern Plains and
in Oklahoma. On the reservations, residential
villages of Native Americans are interspersed
with farms, often occupied by European
Americans, which were homesteaded as
"surplus" lands or purchased as allotments in
the decades following the Dawes Act of 1887.
On some reservations, for example the Devils
Lake Sioux Reservation in North Dakota,
more than three-quarters of the land is owned
by non-Natives.</p>

<p>There are some places where the postconsolidation
pattern offers some semblance of a
European-style settlement pattern. In the German
Russian Hutterite colonies of the Dakotas
and Montana, large blocks of land were purchased
and central residential areas for communal
living were constructed. Vagaries of
the Great Plains climate and the quest for
profit led some large-scale operators to develop
"suitcase" and "sidewalk" farming operations.
In suitcase farming, the operator has
widely spread grain operations necessitating
overnight trips for farming. In sidewalk farming,
more localized dispersion makes living in
a town feasible but still permits scattered
fields, so that at least some will escape localized
drought and hail hazards. Both types of
operations have led to the semblance of a
compact farming-village settlement pattern.</p>

<p>The settlement patterns of the Great Plains
reflect the sum total of the effects of these
ongoing processes. Native Americans, who
only 150 years ago were the region's sole inhabitants,
have been relegated to relatively
small areas. Throughout the region a pattern
of large-scale farms is interspersed with abundant
artifacts of a much denser network of
farmsteads, railroads, and villages. At regular
intervals surviving towns continue to offer
supplies, markets, and life services to an increasingly
diverse population.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi>: <hi rend="smallcaps">AGRICULTURE</hi>: <ref n="egp.ag.065">Suitcase Farming</ref> / 
<hi rend="smallcaps">CITIES AND TOWNS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ct.049">Small Towns</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">TRANSPORTATION</hi>: <ref n="egp.tra.028">Railroads, United States</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>John L. Dietz<lb/>
University of Northern Colorado</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Hudson, John C. "Who Was 'Forest Man'? Sources of Migration
to the Plains." <title level="j">Great Plains Quarterly</title> 6 (1986): 69–
83.</bibl> <bibl>Kraenzel, Carl F. <title level="m">The Great Plains in Transition</title>. Norman:
University of Oklahoma Press, 1955.</bibl> <bibl>Shortridge,
James R. <title level="m">Peopling the Plains: Who Settled Where in Frontier Kansas</title>. Lawrence: University Press of Kansas, 1995.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>