<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.tra.038 SYSTEM "egp.tra.038.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.tra.038">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Travois</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Norman Henderson</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.tra.038</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Henderson, Norman">Norman Henderson</author>. <title level="a">"Travois"</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">812-813</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-22</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">TRAVOIS</head>

<figure n="egp.tra.038" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Husky and travois</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Unique to the Plains, the travois is a wooden
load-bearing frame fastened by a leather harness
to a dog or horse. The basic dog travois
consists of two aspen or cottonwood poles
lashed together at one end with buffalo sinew.
The other ends rest splayed apart. Crossbars
are lashed between the poles near the splayed
ends. The finished frame looks like a large letter
A with extra crossbars. The apex of the A,
wrapped in buffalo skin to prevent friction
burns, rests on a dog's shoulders, while the
splayed ends drag over the ground.</p>

<p>Used by Plains Indian nations, travois were
perfectly suited to their environment. Over
native grasslands the dragging travois ends
sweep silently and nearly without friction;
they appear almost to float through the same
prairie that cracks and breaks wheel axles.
Outside of grasslands the travois is not much
use, for bush and gullies are impassable.</p>

<p>Native women both built the travois and
managed the dogs, sometimes using toy travois
to train puppies. Bison meat and firewood
were typical travois loads. Dogs could
tack up and down grassy hill slopes and ford
shallow rivers with a travois. But temperature
was a serious constraint on travois work, for
on warm days dogs overheated easily.</p>

<p>In historic times Plains Indians constructed
much larger versions of the dog travois and
hitched them to horses. Horse travois allowed
the transport of the increased material wealth
accumulated by some Native nations skilled in
the mounted bison hunt. Children or ill adults
could ride on the horse travois load rack as
well. Their rack ride was smooth, but the legs
of the saddle-rider, typically female, hung uncomfortably
over the travois poles.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Norman Henderson<lb/>
University of East Anglia, England</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Ewers, John. <title level="m">The Horse in Blackfoot Indian Culture</title>. Bureau
of American Ethnology Bulletin 159. Washington <hi rend="smallcaps">DC</hi>:
Smithsonian Institution, 1955.</bibl> <bibl>Henderson, Norman.
"Replicating Dog Travois Travel on the Northern Plains."
<title level="j">Plains Anthropologist</title> 39 (1994): 145–59.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>