<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.med.030">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Moyers, Bill (b. 1934)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Bernard M. Timberg</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.med.030</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Timberg, Bernard M.">Bernard M. Timberg</author>. <title level="a">"Moyers, Bill (b. 1934)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">516-517</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-26</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">MOYERS, BILL (b. 1934)</head>

<p>Bill Moyers was born Billy Don in Hugo,
Oklahoma, on June 5, 1934. He grew up in
Marshall, Texas. Marshall was a small town,
and books were Moyers's entry into the larger
world outside his home. He attributes his love
of the spoken and written word to growing up
among storytellers in East Texas, including his
father, who had only a fourth-grade education
but was a well-known spinner of yarns.</p>

<p>Moyers's own first stories were as a print
journalist, beginning with a part-time job at
the age of fifteen on the local <title level="j">Marshall Messenger</title>.
He later attended the Southwestern
Baptist Theological Seminary and became a
fully ordained Baptist minister. Journalistic
and ministerial careers were followed by a
third one in politics. At twenty-seven he joined
the staff of Texas senator Lyndon Johnson, and
he served Johnson in one capacity or another
from 1959 to 1966. He was on Johnson's staff
through the Texas politician's first year as vice
president and his first three years as president
after John F. Kennedy's assassination. As Johnson's
press secretary during the early part of
the Vietnam War, Moyers later joked that the
administration faced a credibility gap "so bad
we didn't believe our own press releases." It was
an ironic position for him to be in, considering
his later image as journalistic truth seeker, and
it occasioned some bitter controversies with
critics in later years.</p>

<p>After leaving the Johnson administration
Moyers reentered the newspaper business for
three years as publisher of Long Island's <title level="j">Newsday</title>.
In 1970 the paper was bought by the <title level="j">Los Angeles Times</title>, and Moyers was replaced. Moyers
then began his distinguished career as a
journalist and reporter on public television.</p>

<p>More familiar with the worlds of politics
and publishing than television when he first
appeared on <hi rend="smallcaps">WNET-TV</hi>, New York's pbs station,
in 1970, Bill Moyers worked alternately
out of the Public Broadcasting Service and cbs
in a variety of settings and with a wide range
of producers. He extended the "think-piece"
tradition of Edward R. Murrow in filmed and
taped interviews. His dedication to the written
word, his ability to provide historical context
for central themes in American life, and
his moral passion recalled Murrow at his best.
In interviews with artists, scientists, politicians,
and provocative thinkers of all kinds,
Moyers brought to television what he called
the "conversation of democracy." The foundation
support and funding Moyers elicited in
the 1970s and early 1980s gave him degrees of
freedom few broadcasters possessed, and he
was constantly working to consolidate his
position of independence from both network
and governmental control. Never a talk-show
host in conventional terms, he produced 600
hours of programming (filmed and videotaped
conversations and documentary interviews)
between 1971 and 1989 alone, or the
equivalent of more than half an hour of programming
a week for eighteen years.</p>

<p>Many of Moyers's programs have also had
significant afterlives. Filmed conversations
with mythology scholar Joseph Campbell and
poet Robert Bly sold tens of thousands of
copies in videocassette after they were aired.
One of Moyers's programs, "Marshall, Texas,"
in the <title>Creativity</title> series, celebrated his own
hometown. Produced by David Grubin, many
consider it one of his finest pieces of work.
Moyers also produced books to accompany
many of his most successful television series,
for example, <title>The Secret Government</title> (1988), <title>A World of Ideas</title> (1989), <title>A World of Ideas II</title>
(1990), and <title>Healing the Mind</title> (1992). These
books consistently placed Moyers on the <title level="j">New York Times</title> best-seller list.</p>

<p>What Bill Moyers proved, beginning in the
1970s and then into the 1980s and 1990s, was
that television talk could be both subtle and
profound&#8211;and much more versatile than
most people thought. He showed that despite
limitations imposed on televised talk by the
"commodification" of most talk-show formats,
the range of what could be said on television
need not be limited to superficialities.
From early Great Plains roots, Moyers rose to
be considered one of the people who most
faithfully followed Edward R. Murrow in raising
the standards of journalism, public debate,
and inquiry on the most powerful medium
of public presentation in the United
States: television.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</hi>: <ref n="egp.pg.034">Johnson, Lyndon Baines</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Bernard M. Timberg<lb/>
Johnson C. Smith University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>