<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.lt.072">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Stafford, William (1914-1993)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Vern Rutsala</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.lt.072</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Rutsala, Vern">Vern Rutsala</author>. <title level="a">"Stafford, William (1914-1993)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">493</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-25</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">STAFFORD, WILLIAM (1914-1993)</head>

<p>Although William Stafford lived most of his
adult life in Oregon, he drew heavily on memories
of his early days in Kansas for his poetry.
Born in Hutchinson, Kansas, on January 17,
1914, Stafford received both his bachelor's and
master's degrees from the University of Kansas
and later earned his doctorate at the University
of Iowa. Following World War II, during
which he was a conscientious objector, Stafford
began his teaching career at Lewis and
Clark College, from which he retired in 1979.
He died in Lake Oswego, Oregon, on August
28, 1993.</p>

<p>Though he was widely published in magazines,
his first collection, <title level="m">West of Your City</title>, did
not appear until 1960. It was followed two
years later by <title level="m">Traveling through the Dark</title>,
which received the National Book Award.
Other awards include the Shelley Memorial
Prize, a Guggenheim Fellowship, a senior fellowship
from the National Endowment for
the Arts, and an appointment as poetry consultant
to the Library of Congress.</p>

<p>A master of the short lyric, Stafford wrote
poetry that was deceptively quiet and often
focused on natural settings but that frequently
contained an implicit criticism of the artifices
of urban life. There is a liveliness of imagery
and rhythm throughout his work that shows
his keen-eyed pleasure in invention. Very active
as a public reader of his poetry, he also
took part in many writers conferences and
workshops throughout his career. His prose&#8211;
essays, reviews, and interviews&#8211;was collected
in three volumes. Always responsive to small
magazines and presses, he published some
sixty collections and chapbooks over the years.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Vern Rutsala<lb/>
Lewis and Clark College</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Holden, Jonathan. <title level="m">The Mark to Turn: A Reading of William Stafford's Poetry</title>. Lawrence: University Press of Kansas,
1976.</bibl> <bibl>Stitt, Peter. <title level="m">The World's Hieroglyphic Beauty: Five American Poets</title>. Athens: University of Georgia Press, 1985.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>