<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.pe.067">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Wildflowers</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Kathleen H. Keeler</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.pe.067</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Keeler, Kathleen H.">Kathleen H. Keeler</author>. <title level="a">"Wildflowers."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">642-643</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-27</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">WILDFLOWERS</head>

<p>The term "wildflowers" usually refers to attractive
native flowering species. In the Great
Plains the category often includes plants that
are native elsewhere but have naturalized (reproducing
on their own) in the Great Plains
region. It rarely includes grasses, because grass
flowers are small, but some grass flowers are
very colorful and the foliage is often striking.
Flowering shrubs and trees are not usually
considered wildflowers, but there are a number
of handsome natives such as wild plums
(<hi rend="italic">Prunus</hi>) and redbuds (<hi rend="italic">Cercis</hi>).</p>

<p>The native wildflowers of the grasslands are
likely declining in numbers because their natural
habitats&#8211;native grasslands, forests, and
wetlands&#8211;have been replaced by fields as well
as urban and suburban areas. Some, such as
<hi rend="italic">Liatris</hi> (gay feather) and Coreopsis, have been
successfully brought into cultivation. Some
species, such as purple coneflowers (<hi rend="italic">Echinacea</hi>),
are being collected for their medicinal
properties to the point that they are increasingly
difficult to find in their natural environment.
Other species are decreasing because
they depend on parts of the ecosystem that are
no longer present, as is in the case of <hi rend="italic">Ruellia
humilis</hi> (Acanthaceae), which was once apparently
pollinated by a moth that has become
extinct in some areas.</p>

<p>The Great Plains is especially rich in showy
flowers of the plant families Asteraceae (sunflowers,
asters, coneflowers), Fabaceae (peas,
clovers), Onagraceae (evening primroses),
and Asclepiadaceae (milkweeds). Native wildflowers
are mostly yellow, blue, or purple in
color, with true reds being rare. White flowers,
especially those with long tubes (corollas),
usually open at night and some have wonderful
fragrances. Colors reflect the preferences
of pollinators: bees, flies, and butterflies prefer
bright colors and visit plants by day, while
moths and hawkmoths fly by night. Partly
white flowers (e.g., <hi rend="italic">Gaura</hi>) may be visited by
both kinds of pollinators.</p>

<p>The flowering of prairie plants can be divided
into five seasons: early spring, late spring, early
summer, late summer, and fall. Examples of
flowers reflecting that seasonal sequence include
pasque flower (<hi rend="italic">Anemone patens</hi>) early in the
spring; puccoon (various <hi rend="italic">Lithospermum</hi> species)
in late spring; scurf peas (<hi rend="italic">Psoralea</hi>) in June;
milkweeds (<hi rend="italic">Asclepias</hi> species) in late summer;
and asters and gentians in fall.</p>

<p>A few native wildflowers are found across the
entire region, but more often, similar species
occur in sequence along east–west and north–
south transects. These plants are adapted to the
area where they are found, and this local diversity
increases the variety of native species. Likewise,
in many cases there are distinctive species
or varieties confined to special growing conditions,
such as sand, rocky outcrops, and wetlands.
Milkweeds are a good example. The common
milkweed (<hi rend="italic">Asclepias syriaca</hi>) is found in
the Eastern Plains. It is replaced in the Western
Plains by the similar showy milkweed (<hi rend="italic">A. speciosa</hi>).
The swamp milkweed (<hi rend="italic">A. incarnata</hi>), with
leaves much narrower and the flowers a more
reddish pink than the previous two, is found
in marshy areas and wet meadows across the
region. And on sand the characteristic milkweed
is the green-flowered sand milkweed (<hi rend="italic">A.
arenaria</hi>).</p>

<p>Plants of human-disturbed environments
(highway margins, lawns) are usually called
weeds. Whether native or introduced, these occur
across the entire Great Plains. Many familiar
roadside wildflowers, such as goatsbeard (<hi rend="italic">Tragopogon</hi>),
sweet clover (<hi rend="italic">Melilotus</hi>), and dame's
rocket (<hi rend="italic">Hesperis</hi>), were introduced.</p>

<p>Within our region, forested areas harbor a
distinct group of wildflowers. In most cases
these are species shared with more extensive
forests in the east or southeast, such as spring
beauty (<hi rend="italic">Claytonia virginica</hi>), mayapple (<hi rend="italic">Podophyllum
peltatum</hi>), and touch-me-not (<hi rend="italic">Impatiens
species</hi>).</p>

<p>Since flowers are necessary for plant reproduction,
picking bouquets of wildflowers
poses a threat to their survival, especially for
the nonweedy species. As the human impact
in the Great Plains increases and more areas
are developed, threats to native wildflowers
will only get worse. Digging up native plants
as a method of collecting them frequently fails
because prairie natives are very deeply rooted
and difficult to dig up. This is, therefore, an
even greater threat to the survival of prairie
species than picking the flowers.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Kathleen H. Keeler<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Freeman, C. C., and E. K. Schofield. <title level="m">Roadside Wildflowers
of the Southern Great Plains</title>. Lawrence: University Press of
Kansas, 1991.</bibl> <bibl>Great Plains Flora Association. <title level="m">Flora of the
Great Plains</title>. Lawrence: University Press of Kansas, 1987.</bibl>
<bibl>Weaver, J. E. <title level="m">Native Vegetation of Nebraska</title>. Lincoln: University
of Nebraska Press, 1965.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>