<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.gen.030">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Rodeo Queens</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Renee M. Laegreid</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.gen.030</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Laegreid, Renee M.">Renee M. Laegreid</author>. <title level="a">"Rodeo Queens."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">335-336</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-23</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">RODEO QUEENS</head>

<p>Rodeo queens appear at rodeos all across the
Great Plains. Rhinestone tiaras adorning their
hats, and bedazzling in cowgirl regalia, the
queens reign over the rough-and-tumble rodeo
events. The idea of a ceremonial rodeo
queen might seem oddly out of place among
the physically demanding performances of
cowboys and cowgirls, yet the role of the queen
is inextricably linked with the rise of rodeo as a
spectator sport in the Great Plains.</p>

<p>The first rodeo queen is believed to have
made her appearance at the 1910 Pendleton
Round-Up in Oregon, but it took twenty years
for the idea to spread. Cheyenne Frontier Days
in Wyoming became the next well-known
rodeo to have a queen. It is no accident that the
first Miss Frontier Days, Miss Jean Nimmo
Doubois, appeared in 1931. Local businessmen,
worried that the Depression would keep ticket-buying
spectators away from the rodeo, devised
a competition: the young woman who
sold the most tickets would become queen of
the rodeo. The selection of a young woman
from within the community, and one who did
not compete in rodeo events, but instead used
her "royal" position to promote the rodeo to
a broad audience, was an innovation that
worked well and was widely copied.</p>

<p>During the 1940s hundreds of communities
throughout the Great Plains began holding
their own rodeos. Although the method of
choosing a queen varied widely, their purpose
was the same&#8211;to help sell tickets. Competition
was fierce among the towns to pull in
large crowds, thereby making the rodeo an
economic success, and rodeo queens worked
with the town promoters to attract spectators.
The role the queens played within their communities
depended on the goals of the community
sponsoring the rodeo.</p>

<p>In Cheyenne, a large town actively seeking
regional and national attention, the role of
queen gradually evolved into a rigorous twoyear
commitment, with activities planned not
only in Cheyenne but throughout the country.
In 1946 Miss Patsy Rogers was selected by the
Calgary Exhibition and Stampede Board to
serve as the first Calgary Stampede Queen.
Miss Rogers represented the Stampede locally,
regionally by traveling to rodeos in the surrounding
area, and internationally as a Ranch
Girl in Gene Autry's Madison Square Garden
and Boston Gardens rodeos. Nebraska's Big
Rodeo, held in Burwell, a small community
hoping to attract spectators from across the
state, often selected its queens from outside
Burwell. Ruby Dearmont, Miss Burwell 1949,
was one of the very few queens selected from
Burwell itself to represent the rodeo. Most
common, however, were small-town rodeos
where local queens appeared at numerous
civic and social functions in town and traveled
as visiting royalty to other nearby rodeos. In
fact, traveling to promote the rodeo is something
that most past rodeo queens recall as
an important and exciting part of their responsibilities,
even if the travel was only to the
next town.</p>

<p>Another type of queen promotion began in
the Plains in 1931, when the Texas Cowboy
Reunion in Stamford held the first sponsor
contest. In a unique promotional twist, Stamford
sent out a call to chambers of commerce
throughout the region to provide girls to participate
in the sponsor event at the Stamford
rodeo. Each town was responsible for holding
a competition to select a hometown representative;
the winner would then compete at the
Stamford rodeo in an event specifically designed
for them. The contestants were judged
on the appearance of their horse, their costume,
and horsemanship. The sponsor contests
held by these other towns were a remarkably
successful mechanism for publicizing the
rodeo, and within a few years of its founding
the Texas Cowboy Reunion was one of the
largest rodeos in the country.</p>

<p>The original intention of the sponsor contest
was to "add a little softness to the allmale
rodeo." However, the horsemanship part
of the competition became increasingly popular.
What started as a subjective evaluation
of the young women's ability to ride around
three randomly placed barrels evolved into a
timed event with a standardized cloverleaf
pattern. Later named barrel racing, this event
remains popular and highly competitive in
rodeo today.</p>

<p>A new dimension was added to the rodeo
queen phenomenon in 1955, when the first
Miss Rodeo America pageant was held in Casper,
Wyoming. Since its inception, twenty-two
of the forty-four Miss Rodeo America queens
have been from the Great Plains. The first
Miss Rodeo Canada also made her debut in
1955. In order to compete for the title, a young
woman must be sponsored by a Canadian
pro-rodeo association. The Canadian prorodeo
circuit is centered in the Plains&#8211;the
easternmost rodeo is held in Morris, Manitoba&#8211;
so twenty-six of the thirty-three Miss
Rodeo Canada queens have been from the region.
The role of the national queens is to
travel across their respective countries promoting
professional rodeo. In the 1960s it became
increasingly common for Miss Rodeo
America and Miss Rodeo Canada contestants
to also participate as athletes in rodeos, usually
competing in barrel racing events.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">SPORTS AND RECREATION</hi>: <ref n="egp.sr.045">Rodeo</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Renee M. Laegreid<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>LeCompte, Mary Lou. <title level="m">Cowgirls of the Rodeo: Pioneer Professional Athletes</title>. Urbana: University of Illinois Press,
1993.</bibl> <bibl>Shelton, Hooper. <title level="m">Fifty Years of a Living Legend: Texas Cowboy Reunion and Oldtimers Association</title>. Stamford <hi rend="smallcaps">TX</hi>:
Shelton Press, 1979.</bibl> <bibl>Stoeltje, Beverly. "Gender Representations
in Performance: The Cowgirl and the Hostess." <title level="j">Journal of Folklore Research</title> 25 (1988): 219–41.</bibl>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>