<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.lt.070">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Sandoz, Mari (1896-1966)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Barbara Wright Rippey</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.lt.070</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Rippey, Barbara Wright">Barbara Wright Rippey</author>. <title level="a">"Sandoz, Mari (1896-1966)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">492-493</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-25</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">SANDOZ, MARI (1896-1966)</head>
<figure n="egp.lt.070" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Nebraska author Mari Sandoz</figDesc>
</figure>
    
<p>Mari Sandoz was born into the hardships of
immigrant life in western Nebraska. In her
short stories, novels, and histories of the Great
Plains, Sandoz dramatized both the human
conflicts and the beauty and danger of the arid
environment. While Sandoz never directly
confronted the replacement of Native Americans
with families like her own, she was one of
the first to chronicle vividly and sympathetically
the cruel removal of Indians from their
homelands.</p>

<p>Sandoz was born on May 11, 1896, in the
Sandoz homestead on the Niobrara River,
south of Hay Springs, Nebraska. The first of
six children of Swiss immigrants, Jules and
Mary Fehr Sandoz, her childhood and young
adult years were difficult. A slight child, she
was burdened from the age of six with childcare,
kitchen, and garden chores. She faced
discrimination as an immigrant in a ranching
community and as the offspring of a quarrelsome
father who fought with neighbors and
abused his wife and children. Mari was nine
before she was allowed to attend school and to
learn to read and write English. These negative
experiences and a brief story of hers published
in an Omaha newspaper when she was
almost twelve strengthened her determination
to succeed as a writer.</p>

<p>Escaping from home into a marriage that
eventually failed, Sandoz fled to Lincoln, Nebraska,
to find work, enter the state university,
and concentrate on writing. In 1935, after a
long writing apprenticeship, Sandoz won the
<hi rend="italic">Atlantic Press</hi> nonfiction contest with <title level="m">Old Jules</title>, a biography of her father and the communities
he helped establish in the Niobrara
country. This remarkable characterization of
her father and his life, perhaps her best-known
work, combines both an objective
view of the opinionated, unkempt, brilliant,
and well-educated man and an unobtrusive
autobiographical view of his eldest daughter,
the young Mari. <title level="m">Old Jules</title> illuminates basic
themes that appear in her later works: the
struggle between ranchers and grangers; the
need for strong governmental policies to protect
freedom and prevent discrimination; respect
for Native Americans; and the power
and vulnerability of women on the frontier.
<title level="m">Old Jules</title> also introduces Sandoz's basic style,
which is judgmental in its ironic view of human
affairs and lyrical when it draws from her
intimate experience with the beauty and danger
of the Plains environment. Determined to
protect the distinctive voice of the West, she
fought her editors to protect her idiom and
her bold language.</p>

<p>Sandoz's taste for history as story and story
as history was whetted by evenings she spent
crouched in the wood box behind the kitchen
stove, listening to Jules swap stories with visitors:
other settlers, old trappers and traders,
and Indians. These stories reverberate in Sandoz's
Great Plains series, the core of her work.
The series includes three biographies&#8211;<title level="m">Old Jules</title>, <title level="m">Crazy Horse: The Strange Man of the Oglalas</title> (1942), and <title level="m">Cheyenne Autumn</title> (1953)
&#8211;and three histories&#8211;<title level="m">The Buffalo Hunters: The Story of the Hide Men</title> (1954), <title level="m">The Cattlemen: From the Rio Grande across the Far Marias</title> (1958), and <title level="m">The Beaver Men: Spearheads of Empire</title> (1964). A seventh book, a
partly researched history of oil exploration
and exploitation, was unfinished when, on
March 10, 1966, she died of cancer in New
York City, her last "outpost."</p>

<p>Sandoz's histories have received more positive
attention than her novels, which tend to be
didactic. However, in her first novel, <title level="m">Slogum House</title> (1937), the character of Gulla Slogum,
who attempts to capture a frontier county by
intimidation, theft, and murder, is strongly
enough drawn to have elicited both outrage
for its frankness and commendation for its
characterization. All her novels are storehouses
of the experiences and history of Plains
settlement.</p>

<p>In 1950 Sandoz was awarded an honorary
doctorate of literature by the University of Nebraska.
The citation included recognition of
Sandoz as an authority on Plains Indians. Her
last history, <title level="m">The Battle of the Little Bighorn</title>
(1966), was told primarily from Native American
perspectives. She insisted on going through
the proofs before leaving for the hospital, where
she spent her final days, an indication of Mari
Sandoz's indomitable will and spirit.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Barbara Wright Rippey<lb/>
College of Saint Mary</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Mari Sandoz Papers, Love Library, University of Nebraska.
Lincoln.</bibl> <bibl>Stauffer, Helen Winter. <title level="m">Mari Sandoz, Story Catcher of the Plains</title>. Lincoln: University of Nebraska
Press, 1982.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>