<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.na.109">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Sitting Bull (ca. 1831-1890)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Carole A. Barrett</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.na.109</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Barrett, Carole A.">Carole A. Barrett</author>. <title level="a">"Sitting Bull (ca. 1831-1890)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">602-603</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-20</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">SITTING BULL (ca. 1831-1890)</head>
<figure n="egp.na.109" rend="granted" type="noclick">
<figDesc>Indian chief Sitting Bull</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Sitting Bull (<hi rend="italic">Tantanka Iyotanka</hi>) was born in
the early 1830s along the Grand River at a place
called Many Caches near present-day Bullhead,
South Dakota. During the Plains Indian
Wars (1865–76) he rose to prominence as a
military and political leader among the Lakotas
and led resistance against U.S. military and
civilian encroachment through their traditional
homelands between the mouth of the
Grand and the Yellowstone River basin.</p>

<p>Sitting Bull distinguished himself early as a
hunter and warrior and rose to prominence
among his own people as a generous man and
capable war leader; consequently, he was inducted
into a number of prestigious warrior
societies. In 1866 he gained attention of the
American public for his attacks on soldiers and
settlers at Fort Buford (located at the confluence
of the Yellowstone and Missouri Rivers).</p>

<p>In response to intensifying outside pressures
the Hunkpapa and other Lakota bands,
principally the Itzipco, Minneconjou, Sihasapa,
and a loose alliance of Oglalas under
Crazy Horse, attempted to consolidate leadership.
In 1866 or 1867 Sitting Bull was recognized
as an important political and military
leader of these bands. In some accounts he is
labeled "supreme chief." Therefore, in 1867
and 1868, when Catholic missionary Pierre-
Jean De Smet sought to broker a truce with
the Lakotas, he dealt primarily with Sitting
Bull. In these negotiations Sitting Bull rejected
all overtures and stated his determination to
protect his people's homeland and lifeways,
a message he repeated often in subsequent
years.</p>

<p>For a time tensions abated due to troop
withdrawals along the Bozeman Trail as part of
the 1868 Treaty of Fort Laramie, which created
the Great Sioux Reservation. However, many
Lakotas left their agencies to join Sitting Bull
when federal officials failed to enforce provisions
of the treaty and prospectors poured into
the Black Hills after the government-sponsored
expedition in 1874, led by George Armstrong
Custer, confirmed the existence of gold there.
Clashes between the army and "the Sitting
Bull people," as they came to be known, were
frequent.</p>

<p>In June 1876, during the annual Sun Dance,
Sitting Bull had a vision of dead soldiers falling
into an Indian camp, and on June 25, 1876,
his prophecy came true with the defeat of
Custer's command at the Battle of the Little
Bighorn. After this fight, the army systematically
hunted Native peoples, and by the fall
of 1876 Sitting Bull was one of the few leaders
still resisting surrender and living outside his
agency. In October, Gen. Nelson Miles intercepted
Sitting Bull in Montana Territory and
demanded his surrender; typically, Sitting Bull
stated his determination to continue living in
the old way and resist federal demands. By
May of 1877 Sitting Bull and about 400 followers
had sought refuge in Saskatchewan,
settling between Wood Mountain and Fort
Qu'Appelle. Starvation was never far away,
and the Dominion of Canada would not provide
food or other support, so after lengthy
discussion with Canadian and American officials, on July 19, 1881, Sitting Bull and 200
followers crossed into the United States and
handed over horses and weapons at Fort Buford.
Despite the U.S. government's assurances
he would be repatriated with the Hunkpapa
at Standing Rock Agency, Sitting Bull
and about 100 of his people were held in
detention at Fort Randall in southeastern Dakota
Territory.</p>

<p>In May 1883 Sitting Bull was permitted to
join his people at Standing Rock. There he
came under the jurisdiction of Indian agent
James McLaughlin, and a sustained clash of
wills and philosophies ensued. Sitting Bull
struggled to maintain a sense of nationhood
and to preserve traditional Lakota values,
while McLaughlin enforced federal policy. Sitting
Bull left the reservation briefly in 1884 and
1885 to tour in two Wild West shows, then
returned to Standing Rock to continue his role
as outspoken critic of government attempts to
divest the Sioux of nine million acres of their
land. Nonetheless, the land was lost in 1889,
and against this backdrop word of the Ghost
Dance spread among the Sioux. Sitting Bull
permitted the Ghost Dance in his camp along
the Grand River, not far from his birthplace,
and Agent McLaughlin quickly seized on this
and petitioned the government to order his
arrest. On December 12, 1890, arrest orders for
Sitting Bull were sent from Washington. By
daybreak on December 15, 1890, following an
intense fight, Sitting Bull was dead, and eight
of his followers and six Indian police lay dead
or dying.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">IMAGES AND ICONS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ii.061">Wild West Shows</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">LAW</hi>: <ref n="egp.law.022">Indian Police</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">RELIGION</hi>: <ref n="egp.rel.023">Ghost Dance</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">WAR</hi>: <ref n="egp.war.025">Little Bighorn, Battle of the</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Carole A. Barrett</signed>
University of Mary</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Manzione, Joseph. <title level="m">"I Am Looking North for My Life": Sitting
Bull, 1876–1881</title>. Salt Lake: University of Utah Press,
1991.</bibl> <bibl>Utley, Robert M. <title level="m">The Lance and the Shield: The Life
and Times of Sitting Bull</title>. New York: Henry Holt, 1993.</bibl>
<bibl>Vestal, Stanley. <title level="m">Sitting Bull: Champion of the Sioux</title>. Norman:
University of Oklahoma Press, 1932.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>