<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.law.014">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Coffeyville Raid</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Robert B. Smith</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.law.014</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Smith, Robert B.">Robert B. Smith</author>. <title level="a">"Coffeyville Raid."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">450</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-04</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">COFFEYVILLE RAID</head>

<p>On October 5, 1892, five dusty horsemen
walked their horses through the bustling
streets of Coffeyville, Kansas. Dick Broadwell
and Bill Powers were professional bandits. The
other three men were brothers, Bob, Grat, and
Emmett Dalton. All five had bank robbery on
their minds.</p>

<p>Bob and Grat had been lawmen briefly, and
their elder brother, Frank, had been a well-known
U.S. deputy marshal, killed in 1887 in
the line of duty while riding for "hanging
judge" Isaac Parker. Most of the fifteen Dalton
kids turned out well, but for Bob, Grat, and
Emmett the lure of easy money was too strong,
and it would cost them dearly.</p>

<p>The Dalton boys knew Coffeyville well, for
their family had lived nearby ten years before,
and so they were surprised to find that Coffeyville's
passion for civic improvement had frustrated
part of the gang's plans: as part of a
design to build gutters and sidewalks, the
city fathers had removed the hitching rail to
which the outlaws had intended to tether their
horses. The gang tied their mounts to a pipe in
a narrow alley behind the police judge's house,
pulled their Winchesters from their saddle
scabbards, and walked down the alley toward
Coffeyville's central plaza and the town's two
banks.</p>

<p>The gang had enjoyed a brief run of success,
with four train robberies in Indian Territory
just to the south, but now the law was close
behind them. On their last raid, on the
Kansas-Texas (Katy) division of the Missouri
Pacific Railroad, at Adair, the gang had shot a
doctor who did no more than watch them
gallop out of town. Now every man's hand was
against them, and Bob, the gang's leader, was
determined to make one big strike and travel
on, far and fast.</p>

<p>They would hit two banks at once, Bob
boasted, something not even their famous
cousins, the Younger brothers, had ever done,
but the raid went bad from the start. In spite
of wearing false mustaches and beards, the
Daltons were recognized as they walked across
the plaza. As Bob and Emmett pushed into the
First National Bank and Grat, Powers, and
Broadwell entered the Condon Bank, the citizens
of Coffeyville armed themselves.</p>

<p>Nobody carried a gun in peaceful Coffeyville,
including the town marshal, but two
hardware stores had plenty of weapons and
handed out guns to anybody who wanted one.
There were plenty of takers. Meanwhile, inside
the First National, Bob and Emmett forced the
staff to hand over more than $20,000. But in
the Condon, a young bank teller convinced
Grat that the safe&#8211;long since unlocked&#8211;was
on a time lock and could not be opened for
ten more minutes. Grat was still staring at the
safe when his brothers left the First National
and a citizen fired at them.</p>

<p>In the firefight that followed, four townsmen
and four bandits died. Young Emmett
was the sole survivor of the gang, and he was
shot almost to pieces. The local doctor fended
off a lynch mob intent on hanging Emmett by
telling them that the outlaw would surely die
of his wounds. "Are you sure, Doc?" somebody
asked. "Hell yes," said the physician.
"Did you ever know one of my patients to
live?" Somebody laughed, the tension broke,
and Emmett survived to spend fifteen years in
the Kansas State Penitentiary.</p>

<p>Another brother, Bill, would join gang
members who had not participated in the
Coffeyville raid. These men carried on the
gang's lawless career until all of them, including
Bill Dalton, were run down and killed by
lawmen.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Robert B. Smith<lb/>
University of Oklahoma</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Barndollar, Lue Diver. <title level="m">What Really Happened on October 5, 1892</title>. Coffeyville <hi rend="smallcaps">KS</hi>: Coffeyville Historical Society, 1992.</bibl>
<bibl>Smith, Robert Barr. <title level="m">Daltons! The Raid on Coffeyville, Kansas</title>.
Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1996.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>