<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.sr.045 SYSTEM "egp.sr.045.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.sr.045">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Rodeo</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>James Hoy</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.sr.045</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Hoy, James">James Hoy</author>. <title level="a">"Rodeo."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">784-785</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-21</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">RODEO</head>

<figure n="egp.sr.045" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Homer Holcomb waves a cape at a Brahma bull, while another clown is thrown at the Colorado State Fair Rodeo in Pueblo, Colorado, between 1920 and 1930.</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Rodeo is distinctive, if not unique, among major
American spectator and participant sports
because it is based on the working skills of a
real occupation, even though the roping and
riding that take place in a rodeo arena are far
more refined than those that occur during the
daily work of a ranch. The origins of rodeo lie
in the impromptu competitions that naturally
arise among men working cattle from the
backs of horses&#8211;dares to ride an especially
cantankerous bucking horse, bets at a calf
branding on who can heel more calves without
missing, challenges to be first to rope a
herd-quitting steer.</p>

<p>The precursors of modern rodeo can be
found in the horse sports and races and the
riding and roping exhibitions that occurred at
the fiestas of Spanish missions in Mexico and
California in the late eighteenth and early
nineteenth centuries. In the United States
rodeo-like activities coincided with the big cattle
drives that followed the Civil War&#8211;a broncriding
contest between trail-driving crews near
Deer Trail, Colorado; steer-roping contests at
Pecos, Texas, and Dodge City, Kansas; tryouts
for Buffalo Bill Cody's Wild West show at
North Platte, Nebraska. The first complete
rodeo, in a modern sense, took place at Prescott,
Arizona, in 1888, and contestants paid to
enter roping and riding contests in which they
competed for trophies and cash prizes before
an audience of paying spectators. The bestknown
American rodeo, Cheyenne Frontier
Days, began in 1897. The equally famous Calgary
Stampede began in 1912. Many early
rodeos were held in pastures, a circle of buggies
and automobiles serving as an arena. Bucking
horses were held by mounted snubbers while
riders saddled them in the open.</p>

<p>Unscrupulous promoters often took advantage
of cowboys in the early days of rodeo, but
in 1936 a strike by contestants at the big eastern
rodeos resulted in the formation of the
Cowboys' Turtle Association, the forerunner
of today's Professional Rodeo Cowboys Association
(based in Colorado Springs). In addition
to the hundreds of rodeos sanctioned
each year by the association, there are also
thousands of so-called amateur rodeos, many
of them sanctioned by smaller regional associations.
The National Intercollegiate Rodeo
Association (which sponsors the national finals
at Montana State University in Bozeman),
the National High School Rodeo Association
(headquartered in Denver), and youth rodeos
of various types also sponsor many hundreds
of rodeos each year. Rodeo as organized sport
also is found in Australia and New Zealand.</p>

<p>Although early-day rodeos often had a
dozen or more contest events for both men
and women contestants, a contemporary rodeo
has seven standard events for men and a
cloverleaf barrel race for women. Rodeos generally
begin with quasi-patriotic ceremonies
that include a grand entry of riders led by the
American flag. The first contest event is bareback
bronc riding, in which the contestant
holds onto the handle of a leather rigging
cinched around a horse confined in a narrow
bucking chute. To qualify, the rider must spur
the horse above the point of the shoulders on
the first jump out of the chute, ride for eight
seconds, and not touch either himself or the
horse with his free hand. Two judges score
both the rider and the animal a maximum of
25 points each for a possible total of 100
points. The same rules also apply to saddle
bronc riding, during which the contestant
rides in a standard saddle whose design has
been approved by the Professional Rodeo
Cowboys Association holding onto a buck
rein attached to a halter. Bull riding, the last of
the rough stock events, has similar rules, except
that the rider holds onto a flat-plaited
loose rope and is not required to spur the animal
out of the chute.</p>

<p>Timed contests include calf roping, steer
roping, team roping, and steer wrestling, the
latter two the only events requiring two competitors.
In each of these events the animal,
held in a chute, is given a head start, ensured
by a barrier rope that, if broken, results in a
ten-second penalty. A roper must catch the
calf, throw it to the ground, and tie three legs
with a shorter rope called a pigging string. The
calf must stay tied for six seconds for a qualified
time, with the quickest time winning. Single
steer roping follows the same rules except
that the roper downs the steer by flipping the
rope over the steer's hip and tripping him. In
team roping the header catches the steer by
the horns, the heeler by the two back legs;
catching only one leg results in a five-second
fine. In steer wrestling, sometimes called bull-dogging,
the wrestler comes out of the chute
on the left side of the steer, while his helper,
called a hazer, comes out on the right to help
keep the steer running straight. The dogger
must jump off his running horse onto the
back of the steer, pull him to a stop, and twist
his horns to bring him to the ground with all
four legs pointing in the same direction.</p>

<p>Previous to World War II, cowgirls competed
among themselves in both roping and
riding events and sometimes competed against
men in trick-riding and trick-roping events.
Today, although women compete in riding and
roping events in rodeos sanctioned by the
Women's Professional Rodeo Association,
most female rodeo competitors are essentially
limited to the barrel race, a timed event in
which three barrels must be circled in a cloverleaf
pattern.</p>

<p>As professional rodeo has become more
popular in recent decades, attracting many
participants from urban backgrounds, it has
also become more removed from its ranching
roots. As a result, a backlash in the form of
ranch rodeo has arisen, beginning in Texas in
the 1980s and spreading from there throughout
most of the western states. In contrast to
the individual competition of regular rodeo,
ranch rodeo features cooperation among a
four-member team competing in events such
as calf branding, sorting, and wild cow milking
that are more closely attuned to actual
ranch work. Although not as accessible to the
general population, ranch rodeo has nevertheless
proven quite successful in bringing
rodeo back to its ranch-country roots.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">GENDER</hi>: <ref n="egp.gen.030">Rodeo Queens</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>James Hoy<lb/>
Emporia State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Fredriksson, Kristine. <title level="m">American Rodeo: From Buffalo Bill
to Big Business</title>. College Station: Texas A&amp;M University
Press, 1985.</bibl> <bibl>Westermeir, Clifford. <title level="m">Man, Beast, Dust: The
Story of Rodeo</title>. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press,
1987.</bibl> <bibl>Wooden, Wayne S., and Gavin Ehringer. <title level="m">Rodeo in
America</title>. Lawrence: University Press of Kansas, 1996.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>