<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fil.058">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Rogers, Will (1879-1935)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Douglas Gomery</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fil.058</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Gomery, Douglas">Douglas Gomery</author>. <title level="a">"Rogers, Will (1879-1935)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">278</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-12</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">ROGERS, WILL (1879-1935)</head>
<figure n="egp.fil.058" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Will Rogers in Steamboat Round the Bend</figDesc>
</figure>     

<p>Will Rogers was more than a movie star; he was
one of the greatest American show business
personalities of the first third of the twentieth
century. Born William Penn Adair Rogers at
Oolagah in Indian Territory, now Oklahoma,
on November 4, 1879, he entered show business
in a turn-of-the-century Wild West show,
already helping construct the myths of the
values and spirit of the Old West of his childhood.
Audiences loved him, and so producers
brought him to New York City. By 1912 he was
bringing the humor of the Great Plains to
Broadway; through the late 1910s and early
1920s he reigned as the top attraction of the
Ziegfeld Follies. This led to authorship of some
4,000 newspaper columns; a series of influential
articles for the <title level="j">Saturday Evening Post</title>; popular
phonograph records; six books, including
<title level="m">The Cowboy Philosopher on the Peace Conference</title>
(1919) and <title level="m">Letters of a Self-Made Diplomat to His President</title> (1926); an <hi rend="smallcaps">NBC</hi> radio show;
and ultimately to world fame as a Hollywood
movie star.</p>

<p>Rogers did not instantly rise to motion picture
stardom. Famed producer Samuel Goldwyn
signed him to play in silent films, and
between 1918 and 1922 he essayed cowboy
roles, but his career went nowhere. He needed
his verbal wit and humor; silent film titles
never captured his presence. While he spent
most of his adult life outside the Great Plains,
surely his homespun humor was based on a
persona of straightforward, unpretentious
traits developed from his childhood. For the
remainder of the silent film era, Will Rogers
returned to the vaudeville stage&#8211;except for
completing a handful of silent short subjects
for Hollywood's Hal Roach Studios.</p>

<p>The coming of talkies enabled Rogers to
shine. During the bleak years of the Great Depression
he came to represent the common
person, the casual humorist and raconteur,
the man who clung to the folkways of a mythical
nineteenth-century America that seemed
so long ago.</p>

<p>From 1930 on Will Rogers was Fox Films'
most important movie star. John Ford, the
great American film director, best understood
Rogers's image and persona and fully exploited
them in a series of hometown tales
that were as popular as any set of films made
during the Great Depression: <title>Doctor Bull</title>
(1933), <title>Judge Priest</title> (1934), and Rogers's best
film, <title>Steamboat 'round the Bend</title> (1935). Sadly,
Rogers's best was his last, and he was at the
height of his motion picture popularity when
he died in an airplane crash at Point Barrow,
Alaska, on August 15, 1935. His final two films,
<title>In Old Kentucky</title> and <title>Steamboat 'round the Bend</title>, were released after the actor's death by
the major studio he helped create, Twentieth
Century Fox.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Douglas Gomery<lb/>
University of Maryland</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Rogers, Will. <title level="m">The Autobiography of Will Rogers</title>. Boston:
Houghton Mifflin, 1949.</bibl> <bibl>Rollins, Peter C. <title level="m">Will Rogers: A Bio-Bibliography</title>. Westport <hi rend="smallcaps">CT</hi>: Greenwood Press, 1984.</bibl>
<bibl>Yagoda, Ben. <title level="m">Will Rogers: A Biography</title>. New York: Alfred
A. Knopf, 1993.</bibl>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>