<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.na.012">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Big Bear (ca. 1825-1888)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Hugh A. Dempsey</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.na.012</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Dempsey, Hugh A.">Hugh A. Dempsey</author>. <title level="a">"Big Bear (ca. 1825-1888)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">567</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-03</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">BIG BEAR (ca. 1825-1888)</head>
<figure n="egp.na.012" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Photograph of Plains Cree leader Big Bear taken in 1885</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Big Bear (Mistahimaskwa) was a leader of the
Plains Crees who carried on a nine-year struggle
to gain better treaty terms for his people
from the Canadian government. Born about
1825 to Ojibwa parents near Fort Carlton, Saskatchewan,
Big Bear was part of a transitional
camp that spent its summers on the open
Plains but in winter hunted and trapped in the
woodlands near Jackfish Lake, Saskatchewan.
After the death of his father, about 1865, Big
Bear became chief of a band of sixty-five
lodges. In addition, he received a number of
visions and was a religious leader who opposed
the work of Christian missionaries.</p>

<p>In 1876 Big Bear refused to sign Treaty
Number 6 with the Canadian government. Instead,
he said he would wait five years to see if
its promises were honored. As starvation began
to beset the Crees, many young dissidents
flocked to Big Bear's camp, and he became one
of the most important chiefs on the Canadian
Plains. During this time, he demanded better
terms from the government but was unsuccessful.
Finally, he was forced to sign the
treaty in 1882 when his own sons rebelled
against him.</p>

<p>In the spring of 1885, the Métis launched the
North-West Rebellion and, at the same time,
Big Bear's son, Little Bear (Ayimisis), joined
with war chief Wandering Spirit (Kapapamahchakwew)
to kill nine white residents of
Frog Lake. Several others were taken prisoner.
Big Bear tried to stop the killing and later protected
the prisoners. However, as chief, he was
convicted of treason and was sentenced to
three years in prison. He became ill while imprisoned
and was released after two years. He
died within a year of his release.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">WAR</hi>: <ref n="egp.war.032">North-West Rebellion</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Hugh A. Dempsey<lb/>
Glenbow Museum</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Dempsey, Hugh A. <title level="m">Big Bear: The End of Freedom</title>. Vancouver:
Douglas and McIntyre, 1984.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>