<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ag.013">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Bonanza Farming</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Hiram M. Drache</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ag.013</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Drache, Hiram M.">Hiram M. Drache</author>. <title level="a">"Bonanza Farming."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">35-36</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-12-10</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">BONANAZA FARMING</head>

<p>In 1864 the U.S. Congress provided an extensive
land grant to aid in financing the Northern
Pacific Railway Company (<hi rend="smallcaps">NP</hi>). When the
np encountered financial difficulty in the
Panic of 1873, it sought to shed its indebtedness
by exchanging land for its bonds and preferred
stock. It encouraged large-scale agriculture
in the Red River Valley of the North.
There, the almost totally flat, treeless, fertile,
stoneless prairie was ideal for establishing
showcase farms called bonanzas. After 1875
these bonanzas became the subject of national
farm periodicals and were visited by business
and political leaders of the United States and
Europe. A total of ninety-one farms, ranging
from 3,000 to 100,000 acres, qualified as bonanzas.
Nearly all of them were located within
forty miles of the Red River.</p>

<p>The bonanzas relied on professional farm
managers. To achieve maximum efficiency,
they specialized in the continuous cropping of
wheat, which was well suited to the area. By
concentrating on one crop, a limited number
of implements were needed&#8211;plows, harrows,
seeders, binders, and threshing machines. The
bonanzas were worked by migrant laborers,
ranging from as few as 15 to as many as 1,000
per farm. They lacked experience in operating
machinery, so they were divided into teams of
five to twenty men under a supervisor who
was referred to as the binder boss or plow
boss, depending on the job.</p>

<p>For ease of management, the farms were
broken down into divisions of 5,000 acres or
less. A work unit consisted of one worker with
a plow, a seeder, and a binder with at least five
horses. Each worker generally was expected to
handle 250 acres of crops. Extra workers and
horses were employed for seeding and harvesting.
Bunkhouses and dining halls were
erected, for management knew that good food
and facilities were sound economic practices
that helped to retain the workforce. Young
women did the domestic work and, like the
men, often were newly arrived immigrants.</p>

<p>After harvest the migrant laborers moved to
other areas, often to the forests of Michigan,
Minnesota, and Wisconsin to spend the winter
working in logging camps. The logging
companies often rented the horses for use in
the forest. In the off-season only a few laborers
remained on the bonanzas to repair machinery,
ship grain, care for horses, and keep
records.</p>

<p>Virtually all the bonanza farms were located
on the odd-numbered sections of the railroad
grant lands. The government reserved the
even-numbered sections for homesteaders.
Homesteaders did not like the bonanza farmers
because they did not do business locally
and did not take part in the local schools or
social institutions.</p>

<p>Changing world conditions and a surplus
of wheat, which caused a decline in prices,
made the bonanzas less profitable. New tax
laws discriminated against them. Migrant seasonal
labor became less plentiful and more
costly. All of the above made it difficult for the
business-operated bonanzas to compete with
homesteaders. By 1920 the bonanza era had
ended. Some bonanzas were subdivided and
sold on contract-for-deed agreements or were
rented to smaller scale farmers. Only a few of
the bonanza holdings remain intact today, operating
much differently than the originals.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Hiram M. Drache<lb/>
Concordia College</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Drache, Hiram M. <title level="m">The Day of the Bonanza: A History of
Bonanza Farming in the Red River Valley of the North</title>.
Fargo: North Dakota Institute for Regional Studies, 1964.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>