<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fil.004">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Astaire, Fred (1899-1987)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Al J. Laukaitis</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fil.004</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Laukaitis, Al J.">Al J. Laukaitis</author>. <title level="a">"Astaire, Fred (1899-1987)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">258-259</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-09</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">ASTAIRE, FRED (1899-1987)</head>
<figure n="egp.fil.004" rend="granted" type="noclick">
<figDesc>Fred Astaire in "You'll Never Get Rich" (1941)</figDesc>
</figure>    

<p>No one knows what possessed Fred Astaire to
put on a pair of ballet slippers in an Omaha
dance studio at the age of four and begin his
long journey to stardom. It happened at the
turn of the century at Chambers Dancing
Academy, where Astaire's sister, Adele, took
dance lessons. Astaire often accompanied his
mother or father to the studio to pick her up.
The young lad, not surprisingly, had no interest
in dancing. In his autobiography, <title>Steps in Time</title>, Astaire wrote: "Dancing was merely
something my sister did, something that all
little girls did. I let it go at that and the hell
with it." Unbeknownst to Astaire at that time,
dancing would consume his life and help him
create an entertainment legacy that includes
more than forty Hollywood films.</p>

<p>The son of an Austrian beer salesman, Astaire
was born Frederick Austerlitz in a humble
bungalow not far from downtown Omaha
on May 10, 1899. The house still stands at 2336
S. 10th Street, but without any marker of its
historical significance. The family moved to
the north side of Omaha near the old Storz
Brewery when Astaire was about a year old.
The dilapidated brewery still stands, but the
two homes where the Austerlitzes lived, 1429
N. 19th Street and later 1426 N. 19th Street, are
gone. Astaire recalled very little of his early
years in Omaha, except the sound of rumbling
locomotives in the nearby railroad yards and
taking Sunday afternoon buggy rides with his
father to a local cigar store.</p>

<p>When he was four years old, Astaire and his
sister boarded a train with their mother and
headed for New York and professional dance
training. Their father stayed behind and sent
money to help the family. It was in New York
that the two children began their dancing careers.
According to legend, their first job was
in a Keyport, New Jersey, theater, where they
danced on a large wedding cake as bride and
groom. Astaire wore what would eventually
become his trademark tails, white tie, and top
hat. They got $50 for their efforts.</p>

<p>Astaire spent his early youth traveling the
Orpheum circuit as a vaudeville act with his
sister. They played in Omaha and possibly
Lincoln, which also had an Orpheum Theater.
"We played every rat trap and chicken coop in
the Middle West," Astaire recalled in his autobiography.
He and his sister danced on Broadway
but split up their act in 1932, when Adele
married a British nobleman. Like most stars,
Astaire made his way to Hollywood.</p>

<p>After a screen test, one talent scout infamously
wrote: "Can't act. Can't sing. Balding.
Can dance a little." For a scrawny guy who
was never much of a looker, Astaire danced
with the cr&#232;me de la cr&#232;me of silver screen
stars: Audrey Hepburn, Cyd Charisse, Judy
Garland, and Eleanor Powell, to name only a
few. Most notably, he partnered Ginger Rogers
in ten films, beginning with <title>Flying Down to Rio</title> in 1933. His film career spanned fifty
years (1931-81), and for all of them he was a
star. He won almost every movie award, including
an honorary Academy Award in 1949.
He legitimized dance in movies, his repertoire
spanning tap, ballet, and jazz. He choreographed
all his own work, and he made it look
effortless. A national chain of dance studios
now carries the Astaire name.</p>

<p>The Adele and Fred Astaire Ballroom,
which takes up most of the top floor of the
historic Storz Mansion at 3708 Farnam Street,
stands as the only memorial to his Omaha
beginnings. Despite his accomplishments and
his status as one of the greatest figures in entertainment
history, Astaire remained a modest
man. "I don't understand what people see
in me," he wrote. "I don't look like a movie
star and I don't act like a movie star. I'm just
an old So and So from Omaha." Fred Astaire
died in Beverly Hills, California, on June 22,
1987.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Al J. Laukaitis<lb/>
Lincoln Journal Star</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Astaire, Fred. <title level="m">Steps in Time</title>. New York: Harper, 1959.</bibl>
<bibl>Basinger, Jeanine. "Astaire, Fred." In <title level="m">International Dictionary of Films and Filmmakers</title>, edited by Nicholas Thomas.
Detroit: St. James Press, 1992: 3: 34–36.</bibl>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>