<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.tra.041">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Western Trail</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>William E. Lass</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.tra.041</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Lass, William E.">William E. Lass</author>. <title level="a">"Western Trail"</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">814</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-22</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">WESTERN TRAIL</head>

<p>The Western Trail was the long cattle trail that
succeeded the Chisholm Trail. The boom in
driving Texas longhorns to Kansas railheads
started soon after the Civil War. By 1867 Abilene,
at the end of the Chisholm Trail (sometimes
called the Eastern Trail), was the main
cattle market. Abilene boomed for five years,
but farmer hostility to cattle drives and west-ward-advancing
railroads led Chisholm Trail
herders to shift to Newton, Wichita, and Ellsworth,
which soon succumbed to further railroad
advances. These circumstances coincided
with the Atchison, Topeka and Santa Fe
Railroad's 1872 arrival in Dodge City.</p>

<p>As the new cattle market, Dodge City initially
received its longhorns over a branch of
the Chisholm Trail. But Texas drivers soon
laid out the Western Trail, thereby saving
themselves 150 miles. The new route, which
experienced its first boom year in 1875, ran
from near San Antonio northward by Fort
Gri.n and then by way of a Red River crossing
on the northern edge of present-day Wilbarger
County and through the western part
of Indian Territory. North of Dodge City the
trail was extended to Ogallala, Nebraska, on
the Union Pacific Railroad. The heyday of the
Western Trail was 1875 to 1884. The trail north
from Ogallala was first run to the Black Hills.
By the early 1880s, when the Northern Pacific
Railroad was being extended into the Yellowstone
River valley, the Black Hills portion of
the Western Trail was continued to the Fort
Buford area in present-day western North Dakota,
and another branch was opened from
Ogallala to Miles City, Montana Territory, by
way of Cheyenne.</p>

<p>After the mid-1880s the Western Trail was
not important. Its cattle business had been
ruined by a combination of an outbreak of
Texas fever, rapid advances of the farming
frontier into grazing land during a wet cycle,
and railroad land sales to incoming farmers.</p>

<closer>
<signed>William E. Lass<lb/>
Mankato State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Hunter, J. Marvin, comp. and ed. <title level="m">The Trail Drivers of
Texas</title>. New York: Argosy-Antiquarian, 1963.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>