<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.war.017 SYSTEM "egp.war.017.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.war.017">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Frontier Forts</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>R. Eli Paul</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.war.017</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Paul, R. Eli">R. Eli Paul</author>. <title level="a">"Frontier Forts."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">827-828</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-28</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">FRONTIER FORTS</head>

<figure n="egp.war.017" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Frontier Forts</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>British, Canadian, French, Spanish, and American
forts were distributed from the Prairie Provinces
to West Texas and from the Missouri River
to the Rocky Mountains, although not evenly
and not all having a strictly military purpose. In
the early nineteenth century, American forts
helped to secure and maintain sovereignty in
the face of Native American opposition and European
schemes to limit the new nation's expansion.
Outposts proved a critical line of defense
in the south, especially after the Mexican
War, 1846–48, but not in the Northern Plains,
where the long international border lay virtually
undefended.</p>

<p>Broadly defined, Great Plains forts fell into
two groups. Forts of the first group were places
from which to carry on commerce, a staging
area for traders of furs and robes. Forts of the
second group, detailed here, were places from
which to execute war, a staging area for soldiers.
Fort Leavenworth (1827), Kansas, for example,
the oldest active army post west of the
Mississippi, was the starting point for several
western explorations. Camp Supply (1868) in
present-day Oklahoma served as George A.
Custer's departure point for a punitive expedition
against the Southern Cheyennes. Fort
Abraham Lincoln (1872), North Dakota, played
a similar&#8211;and less successful&#8211;role in 1876 in
Custer's foray against the northern tribes. Fort
Laramie, which passed from private to public
ownership in 1849, became an administrative
center at which to negotiate peace, the Fort Laramie
Treaty of 1868 its most notable legacy.</p>

<p>Great Plains forts invariably stood at strategic
points on the landscape, based on four
relationships: to Native American groups; to
predominantly east–west transportation lines
and communication networks; to burgeoning
settlements and urban centers; and to the military
chain of command. Since the Plains Indians
posed the greatest barrier to westward
expansion in the United States, most American
forts were located in this region and became,
as Gen. William T. Sherman proclaimed, "a
picket line of civilization."</p>

<p>Forts were concentrated along historic
transportation and communication routes,
including the Arkansas, Missouri, Platte, Rio
Grande, and Yellowstone Rivers, the Bozeman,
Oregon-California, Santa Fe, Smoky
Hill, and Southern Overland Trails, the Butterfield
Overland Mail and Pacific Telegraph
lines, and the Kansas Pacific, Northern Pacific,
Southern Pacific, Union Pacific, and Santa Fe
Railroads. Fort Dodge (1865), Kansas, first
guarded the Santa Fe Trail, then the Santa Fe
rail line. Fort Wallace (1865), Kansas, experienced
the same transformation when the
nearby Kansas Pacific Railroad replaced the
Smoky Hill Trail.</p>

<p>As the country looked to the Pacific Coast,
the command structure of the U.S. Army and
its system of posts, subposts, and cantonments
reflected this east–west shift. Omaha, Nebraska,
the terminus of the Union Pacific and
site of Fort Omaha (1868), also headquartered
the Department of the Platte. St. Paul, Minnesota,
shared the same relationship with the
Department of Dakota and the Northern Pacific
and Great Northern Railroads. Both military
departments, in turn, reported up the
chain to Division of the Missouri headquarters
in Chicago, the preeminent rail, commercial,
and industrial center in the Midwest.</p>

<p>The history of American forts in the Great
Plains falls into three time periods, each
roughly bracketed by wars (War of 1812, Mexican
War, Civil War, and Spanish-American
War). These events focused the attention of the
U.S. Army on new enemies and new missions.</p>

<p>The first period is defined by the early posts,
which extended north–south from Fort Snelling
(1819), Minnesota, to Fort Jesup (1822),
Louisiana. Others in this chain included Fort
Atkinson (founded in 1819 as Cantonment
Missouri) and the first Fort Kearny (1846) on
the Missouri River in Nebraska; Fort Leavenworth
and Fort Scott (1842), Kansas; Fort Gibson
(1824), Fort Towson (1824), and Fort
Washita, Oklahoma; and Fort Smith (1817),
Arkansas. The early forts were successful in
their limited purposes&#8211;to protect settlers, to
control Native Americans, and to foster the
growth of the fur trade. The period concluded
with hostilities with Mexico, the annexation of
Texas, and the discovery of California gold.
With the passage of the Kansas-Nebraska Act
in 1854 and the opening of Indian Country to
settlers, the emphasis changed from an impenetrable
north–south barricade between
Native Americans and frontier whites to safe
east–west travel corridors for emigrants and
entrepreneurs.</p>

<p>Two Platte River forts, the second Fort
Kearny and Fort Laramie, define the early years
of the second period. To the annoyance of their
commanders, emigrants came to depend upon
these outposts for essential services such as
resupply, medical attention, and blacksmithing.
Increased traffic also resulted in more armed
conflicts with Native Americans, which in turn
increased the military resources poured into the
Plains. Such forts symbolized a continual compromise
by the army&#8211;building large, fixed
posts to fight a mobile people, or at least to
encourage them with treaty-secured inducements
to live away from the trails. Ultimately,
the forts that guarded the trails, and their countless
feeder lines and alternates, proved more
valuable as bases of operations against the Native
Americans than as purely defensive systems.</p>

<p>Threats of trail closure in the 1850s came
from the Lakotas on the Oregon-California
Trail, the Cheyennes on the Smoky Hill Trail,
and the Comanches and Kiowas on the Santa
Fe Trail. Indian threats, combined with international
disputes, provoked the greatest military
response, in terms of sheer numbers of
new forts, on the expanding Texas frontier.
There, an elaborate defense system protected
Texans from raiders and defined the southwestern
military frontier. The initial chain
of forts in central Texas ran northeast–southwest,
from the Red River to the Rio
Grande, from Fort Washita to Fort Worth,
Fort Graham, Fort Gates, Fort Croghan, Fort
Inge, and Fort Duncan (all six founded in
1849). The next set shifted west, still running
northeast–southwest, consisting of Forts
Belknap on the Brazos River (1851), Phantom
Hill (1851), Chadbourne (1852), McKavett
(1852), Mason (1851), and Clark (1852) near the
Rio Grande. Another line ran from the Rio
Grande west, from Fort Davis (1854) to Fort
Bliss (1848) to Santa Fe's Fort Marcy (1846),
each designed first to counter the Mexican
Army, then to control area tribes. New Mexico
boasted its own string of forts along the Rio
Grande and the El Paso–Santa Fe Road, including
Forts Craig (1854), McRae (1863), and
Selden (1865). This massive infrastructure
also ensured a continuous line of communication
across the southern part of the trans-Mississippi West.</p>

<p>In the 1850s the Santa Fe Trail became truly
a military road, besides a route for emigration
and commerce, beginning with Kansas's Fort
Riley (1853) and Fort Larned (1859) and ending
with Colorado's Fort Lyon (1860) and New
Mexico's Fort Union (1851). A bustling center
of frontier defense in the Southwest for four
decades, Fort Union was the largest U.S. military
post and supply depot in the region. To
the north, the navigable reaches of the Missouri
River had a string of forts: Fort Pierre
(1855), replaced by Fort Randall (1856), and
Forts Sully (1863), Rice (1864), Stevenson
(1867), Buford (1866), Bennett (1870), Abraham
Lincoln (1872), and Yates (1874). At the
fringe of the Great Plains, Fort Abercrombie
(1858) guarded the head of navigation on the
Red River of the North.</p>

<p>The Civil War drew off regular army garrisons
from the Plains, and Confederate and
volunteer surrogates proved to be poor replacements.
Native Americans were successful
in closing some routes, most notably the
Platte Valley route in 1864–65 and later the
Bozeman Trail. Fort Fetterman (1867), Wyoming
Territory, assumed even greater importance
when the army bowed to Indian demands
and abandoned the three Bozeman
forts farther north&#8211;Reno (1865), Phil Kearny
(1866), and C. F. Smith (1866); all were burned
to the ground in 1868.</p>

<p>The post–Civil War period, when railroads
supplanted the trails, was a time of clear military
objectives. The army regarrisoned its
forts to protect railroad construction crews
and later the masses of settlers the new lines
brought west. Forts lined the Union Pacific
Railroad from Omaha to the Rockies: Forts
Omaha, Kearny, McPherson (1863), and Sidney
(1867) in Nebraska; Fort Sedgwick (1864)
in Colorado; and Forts Bridger (1858), Sanders
(1866), D. A. Russell (1867), and Fred Steele
(1868) in Wyoming. Ironically a fort's success
in protecting railroad construction crews
and promoting settlement usually led to its
obsolescence.</p>

<p>In post-Civil War Texas, new forts were established&#8211;Forts Concho, Griffin, and Richardson
in 1867&#8211;and old ones reactivated.
Forts Stockton (1858), Davis, Quitman (1858),
and Bliss. They joined Forts Clark and McKavett
in an irregular line running from El
Paso to the state's northeast border. Just to the
north, Fort Sill (1869) guarded the nearby
Kiowa-Comanche Agency. Fort Reno and the
Darlington Agency for the Cheyennes and
Arapahos were no longer at the frontier's edge,
but now in the center of Indian Territory. Fort
Sill became a major base from which the Red
River War (1874-75) could be waged, ending
armed resistance from the Southern Plains
tribes. With Fort Laramie as its major base, the
Sioux War of 1876-77 accomplished the same
in the Northern Plains, after which few new
significant posts were established. Fort Assiniboine
(1879), Montana, was founded to keep
the Lakota leader Sitting Bull, not Canadians,
in Canada. Across the border the North-West
Mounted Police formed in 1873 and established
several outposts in the Prairie region, most
notably Fort Macleod (1874), Alberta, and Fort
Walsh (1875), Saskatchewan. Together with the
occasional subpost on the international border,
their slim garrisons sought to prevent
smuggling, intertribal clashes, and the introduction
of diseased American cattle. It was
more police than military work.</p>

<p>The 1880s brought consolidation of the
American forts, regiment-sized garrisons, and
the replacement of many small posts. The ring
of "guardian forts" around the Indian reservations
tightened. In the Northern Plains these
were Fort Niobrara (1880) and Fort Robinson
(1874), Nebraska; Fort Meade (1878), South
Dakota; Fort Custer (1877) and Fort Keogh
(1876), Montana; and Fort Washakie (1869),
Wyoming. With large forts now placed in urban
centers, such as Denver's Fort Logan
(1887) and Omaha's Fort Crook (1891), authorities
had a handy police force to quell civil
disturbances.</p>

<p>By the time of the Spanish-American War
in 1898 there were barely a dozen posts in the
Northern Plains, as compared to three dozen
in 1880. Troops&#8211;and forts&#8211;were spread more
or less equally over the entire nation. The military
frontier in the Great Plains was closed.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">ARCHITECTURE</hi>: <ref n="egp.arc.022">Fort Architecture</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>R. Eli Paul<lb/>
Nebraska State Historical Society</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Prucha, Francis Paul. <title level="m">A Guide to the Military Posts of the
United States, 1789–1895</title>. Madison: State Historical Society
of Wisconsin, 1964.</bibl> <bibl>Utley, Robert M. <title level="m">Frontier Regulars:
The United States Army and the Indian, 1866–1891</title>. New
York: Macmillan Publishing Company, 1973.</bibl> <bibl>Utley, Robert
M. <title level="m">Frontiersmen in Blue: The United States Army and the
Indian, 1848–1865</title>. New York: Macmillan Publishing
Company, 1967.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>