<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.asam.006">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Calgary Chinatown</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Wayne K. D. Davies</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.asam.006</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Davies, Wayne K. D.">Wayne K. D. Davies</author>. <title level="a">"Calgary Chinatown."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">140-141</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-22</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">CALGARY CHINATOWN</head>

<p>The first small concentration of Chinese in
Calgary developed on the eastern edge of
downtown at the end of the nineteenth century.
Riots broke out in 1892 when some of the
Chinese were discovered to have smallpox,
and the Chinese population had to be protected
by the police. In 1901 another area of
concentration, again mostly a handful of residences,
laundries, and restaurants, developed
on the southwestern edge of downtown, on
the other side of the railway tracks, when a
local minister helped the Chinese obtain rental
property. In 1910 soaring property values
in the city led to the sale of the properties
rented by the Chinese. But this time local Chinese
businessmen were able to buy land, and
they reestablished themselves on the northern
fringe of downtown near the Bow River, on
Centre Street between 2nd and 3rd Avenues,
an area little valued because it was prone to
flooding.</p>

<p>This area of concentration did grow slightly
to include neighboring blocks as the population
of Chinese in Calgary grew from 485 in
1911 to 1,054 in 1931. But additional growth was
limited, because of the national prohibition
on Chinese immigration, and because of the
tendency for the Chinese to establish small
businesses in suburban areas, which allowed
little chance for community roots to grow.
But by 1961 immigration regulations were relaxed
and the census identified 2,232 Chinese
in the city of a quarter of a million inhabitants.
Chinatown contained approximately
two-fifths of this total and had eleven different
social associations, a school, two Chinese
Christian churches, and thirty businesses, a
majority of which were restaurants or other
food businesses.</p>

<p>During the 1960s a series of transportation
and slum clearance programs threatened to
destroy Chinatown. But vigorous lobbying
by the Sien Lok Society, founded in 1968 by
a group of Chinese businessmen and professionals,
suggested that business and residential
redevelopment should be initiated by Calgary's
Chinese population and should reflect
the area's heritage. These ideas were formalized
by the city's 1976 Design Brief for the area.
The streets were given Chinese names, and
street furniture and new buildings adopted
Chinese motifs, styles, and preferred colors,
such as red and gold. The climax of the redevelopment
was the creation of a cultural center
that was a replica of the Temple of Heaven in
Beijing, built by craftsmen imported from
China. Opened in September 1992, the building
contains a Chinese library, recreation hall,
meeting rooms, Saturday language school, and
restaurant and gift shop, and is actively used by
the city's Chinese community.</p>

<p>Chinatown is no longer home to the majority
of Calgary's Chinese population, whose
numbers had grown to more than 50,000 by
1996. Most live in suburbs, especially Edgemont,
Huntington Hills, and Marlborough.
Chinatown now has 1,400 residents&#8211;less than
3 percent of the city total&#8211;housed mainly
in three high-rise apartments. Ninety percent
of these are of Chinese ethnic origin and more
than half are senior citizens. However, Chinatown
has seen a remarkable increase in commercial
activity. It has expanded along Centre
Street to 4th Avenue and neighboring streets
to form a six-block commercial area, with interior
malls and a wide variety of and a large
number of businesses. Nevertheless, the historic
concentration on restaurants and retail
food outlets is still present, accounting
for a quarter and a fifth of the businesses,
respectively.</p>

<p>Planning surveys have shown that almost
three-quarters of the shoppers in Calgary's
Chinatown are from outside the area, but twothirds
of the total are of Chinese ethnic origin,
which shows that the area acts as a commercial
core for the dispersed Chinese population, as
well as for the city as a whole. However, new
concentrations of Chinese businesses have recently
developed: one is across the Bow River
along Centre Street north to 16th Avenue and
the others are in suburban locations, especially
in Pacific Plaza and International Avenue in
the eastern part of Calgary. Yet Chinatown is
still the largest concentration of Chinese businesses
in the city, and the presence of professional
activities and social organizations
provides it with a high degree of institutional
completeness. Chinatown is no longer a historic
ghetto. It acts as a refuge for the Chinese
elderly, contains an invented symbolic core for
Calgary's dispersed community, and is a distinctive,
yet specialized ethnic business area.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Wayne K. D. Davies<lb/>
University of Calgary</signed>
</closer>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>