<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.lt.051">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Nature Writing</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Susan Naramore Maher</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.lt.051</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Maher, Susan Naramore">Susan Naramore Maher</author>. <title level="a">"Nature Wriiting."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">487</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-24</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">NATURE WRITING</head>

<p>Nature writing has been a component of
American Great Plains literature ever since
Lewis and Clark captured their impressions of
the Plains in their journals. Long before, Native
peoples had described their existence in
stories about nature, passed on from generation
to generation. The land's presence indelibly
marks itself in language, making nature a
part of Plains fiction, poetry, nonfiction, and
drama. Frederick Philip Grove's <title level="m">Over Prairie Trails</title> (1922) marks the beginning of a vital
body of twentieth-century Great Plains nature
writing that has emerged in both the United
States and Canada. This literary tradition gazes
back upon the irrevocable environmental
changes on the Plains, noting the loss of species,
the depletion of resources, the economic
boom-and-bust cycles that have populated
and depopulated areas, and the traumatic displacement
of Native peoples. Grove's narrative
positions a lone traveler on the Plains both
fascinated with and distrustful of the natural
forces confronting him. This ambivalence toward
such a vast landscape is a signature mood
in much Plains nature writing.</p>

<p>The natural landscape today reveals an environment
vastly different from that encountered
by Lewis and Clark in 1804. The aftermath
of settlement haunts contemporary
Plains nature writers such as Gretel Ehrlich,
Ian Frazier, Don Gayton, Linda Hasselstrom,
Wes Jackson, William Least Heat-Moon, John
McPhee, and Wallace Stegner. Least Heat-
Moon's metaphor of deep mapping that conflates
natural and human history through
time and space provides an understanding of
contemporary nature writing of the Plains.
Like geologists, these writers create crosssectional
narratives of natural history, illuminating
the strata in which natural history
makes contact with human cultures, in which
deep time and human time collide. John Janovy's
textual journeys to Keith County, Nebraska,
illustrate the complex histories that
Plains nature writers create. Evolutionary history
is rich in Keith County (and in Don Gayton's
Saskatchewan), yet European Americans
have rapidly altered what has taken millions of
years to create. Plains human history unravels
at an even faster pace. Around the abandoned
homesteads, ghost towns, and empty schoolyards,
nature reasserts its claim. Species become
extinct, but the niches will be filled with
new plants and animals. In a "tallgrass dream,"
Gayton ponders the complexity of reestablishing
grasslands that are all but gone.</p>

<p>Nature writing of the Plains is as much
about the human response to change as it
is about the natural world's adjustment to
change. It examines the human need for spiritual
connection to the land. Kathleen Norris
coined the phrase "spiritual geography" to define
her search for meaning in western South
Dakota, and other nature writers of the Plains,
including Loren Eiseley, Sharon Butala, Don
Gayton, Linda Hogan, Least Heat-Moon, Norris,
and Dan O'Brien have also expressed with
memorable poignancy their spiritual hungers.
To counter the sense of fragmentation that
often accompanies life in embattled communities,
these writers seek wisdom in the land.
Some, like Linda Hasselstrom, are acutely
aware of how tenuous humans' hold on the
land is. An entire way of life is threatened when
ranchers and farmers face economic hardships.
Native writers in particular turn back to
the land to re-create their tribal legacies and to
recover suppressed spiritual traditions.</p>

<p>Nature writing of the Plains, therefore, expresses
multiple themes: to account for loss, to
acknowledge mistakes, to preserve and celebrate
what remains, and to retrace centuries
of change. To accomplish such layered narratives,
nature writers of the Plains cross boundaries
of genre and discipline, region and country,
gender and culture. In voicings rich and
variant, they examine complex issues of science,
history, and human desire.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Susan Naramore Maher<lb/>
University of Nebraska at Omaha</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Lyon, Thomas J. "The Nature Essay in the West." In <title level="m">A Literary History of the American West</title>, edited by J. Golden
Taylor. Fort Worth: Texas Christian University Press, 1987:
221–65.</bibl> <bibl>Quantic, Diane Dufva. <title level="m">The Nature of the Place: A Study of Great Plains Fiction</title>. Lincoln: University of Nebraska
Press, 1995.</bibl> <bibl>Thacker, Robert. <title level="m">The Great Prairie Fact and Literary Imagination</title>. Albuquerque: University of
New Mexico Press, 1989.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>