<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.med.024">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Immigrant Newspapers</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Kathleen L. Fimple</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.med.024</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Fimple, Kathleen L.">Kathleen L. Fimple</author>. <title level="a">"Immigrant Newspapers."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">514</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-26</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">IMMIGRANT NEWSPAPERS</head>

<p>Because the settlement of the Great Plains coincided
with a period of heavy immigration to
the United States, the immigrant press held
a prominent position in the region. One of
the primary roles played by immigrant newspapers
was to educate the newly arrived. To
accomplish this, the immigrant papers were
initially printed in the native language of the
target audience. Later, as immigrants learned
to speak English, some papers abandoned the
native language and converted to English.
Others printed in both languages, and one,
Die Staatspresse, was trilingual, printing in
English, German, and Norwegian. The papers
provided information about the local community,
including the culture, economy, and
government. News was reported on the national
and international levels, especially targeting
the immigrants' homeland. Some papers
even sent reporters to Europe to gather
information firsthand. It was also common
for fiction and poetry to be included in the
papers. Examples of these broad-based papers
are <title level="j">Den Danske Pionner</title>, a Danish paper published
in Omaha, and the <title level="j">Dakota Freie Presse</title>,
a German paper published in a variety of locations
in the Dakotas and Minnesota.</p>

<p>Other papers served the interests of particular
groups. Papers for fraternal organizations,
church groups, labor unions, and political
parties were published to provide specific
information for a relatively narrow audience.
The Slovonic Benevolent Society of Texas, for
example, published the <title level="j">Vestnik</title> every week in
West, Texas. The Mennonite was published for
the Mennonites who lived near Newton, Kansas.
The monthly <title level="j">Katolicky Delnick</title> was published
in Dodge, Nebraska, and, as its title suggests,
it served the Czech Catholic workman.
Also providing religious information was the
<title level="j">Ukrainski Visti</title>, serving Ukrainian immigrants
in and around Edmonton, Alberta.</p>

<p>The impact immigrant newspapers had on
the lives of their readers was twofold. First, the
papers aided assimilation into the society and
culture of the United States. They provided
information that helped immigrants adjust to
their new life and to fit in. However, the papers
also slowed assimilation. By supplying information
in the native language, the papers
provided a means for the immigrant to live
successfully in the United States with little or
no English. In the early twentieth century, for
example, the small Kaposvar Colony in Saskatchewan
supported a Hungarian-language
paper. Not only did the paper provide information
in Hungarian, but it was also an advocate
for cultural preservation issues such as
Hungarian schools with Hungarian teachers
to instruct in their native tongue. Some papers
helped the ethnic community to grow. In his
paper, <title level="j">Pokrok Zapadu</title>, Omaha resident John
Rosicky encouraged Czechs in Europe to immigrate
to Omaha and join the thriving Czech
community there. Dr. Friedrich Renner, editor
of the <title level="j">Nebraska Deutsche Zeitung</title>, declared
that the goal of his paper was to spread the
news of a territory where there was good land
and other employment opportunities. He
mailed copies of each issue to Germany, Austria,
Alsace, and Lorraine.</p>

<p>Immigrant papers varied greatly in size, frequency
of publication, location of publication,
circulation, and longevity. They ranged
from single page to multipage, from daily to
monthly, and from a few hundred subscribers
to several thousand. <title level="j">Den Danske Pionner</title>, for
example, was the largest of all Danish American
weeklies, with a mailing list of 40,000 and
an estimated readership of 100,000. Some
newspapers were published outside the Plains
but had wide circulation within the region.
Others originated in communities on the
Plains. Many of these were published in the
larger communities on the periphery of the
region, such as Omaha and Denver. Smaller
towns, however, also played a part in the immigrant
press. Some supported small papers,
often with short life spans. The <title level="j">Kansas Stats Tiding</title>, for example, survived for only one
year in the Swedish settlement of Lindsborg,
Kansas. Other small towns such as West,
Texas, supported more than one paper, some
of which were published well into the twentieth
century.</p>

<p>Immigrant newspapers in the twenty-first
century serve two audiences. Papers established
in the nineteenth and early twentieth
centuries are read primarily by the descendants
of the original subscribers and those
who are interested in maintaining their cultural
heritage. Many of these papers have converted
to English. The <title level="j">Western News</title>, for example,
began publishing in Swedish in 1888.
In 1941 the newspaper converted to a duallanguage
format (English and Swedish), a
practice it continues today. A few papers still
publish in the native language. <title level="j">Der Staats-Anzeiger</title>, begun in 1906, continues to publish
weekly in German from its Bismarck, North
Dakota, office. In Omaha, the <title level="j">American Citizen</title>
still publishes in Italian. New papers have
emerged, serving a second audience of more
recent immigrants to the Plains. <title level="j">Viltis</title>, for example,
has been published in Denver since 1942
for the Lithuanian population. The weekly
<title level="j">Rocky Mountain Jiho</title> has published in both
English and Japanese since 1962. There are also
numerous papers serving the Latino populations
of the Central and Southern Plains, although
many are published in towns lying just
outside the boundaries of the region.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Kathleen L. Fimple<lb/>
Wayne, Nebraska</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Park, Robert E. <title level="m">The Immigrant Press and Its Control</title>.
New York: Harper and Brothers Publishers, 1922.</bibl> <bibl>Wynar,
Lubomys R., and Anna T. Wynar. <title level="m">Encyclopedic Directory of Ethnic Newspapers and Periodicals in the United States</title>.
Littleton <hi rend="smallcaps">CO</hi>: Libraries Unlimited, 1976.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>