<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.lt.012">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Cowboy Poetry</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>James Hoy</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.lt.012</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Hoy, James">James Hoy</author>. <title level="a">"Cowboy Poetry."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">476</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-23</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">COWBOY POETRY</head>

<p>Ever since cattle first trod the Chisholm Trail
to Abilene in 1867, cowboys have been composing
verse, some of it sung as song lyrics,
some of it published in livestock journals, and
some of it recited as poetry around campfires
or in bunkhouses. In fact, according to cowboy
folk song authority Guy Logsdon, no
other occupational folk group in this country
has produced as much verse, partly because of
subject matter (the cowboy's exciting and
sometimes dangerous work occurs amidst
beautiful natural surroundings) and partly
because of opportunity (the cowboy has sufficient leisure, whether on the back of a horse
or behind the steering wheel of a pickup, in
which to reflect and compose). The cowboy,
in essence, puts into practice Wordsworth's
theoretical definition of poetry as emotion
recollected in tranquility.</p>

<p>In form, traditional cowboy poetry is rhymed
and metrically regular, usually cast in ballad
stanzas or tetrameter stanzas with second and
fourth lines rhyming and with narrative a predominant
element. While in earlier years cowboy
poetry tended to reflect the episodes and
duties of actual ranch work, recently innovative
cowboy poets have written in free verse
and have expanded their subject matter to include
themes such as the environment and
economic or governmental threats to the cowboy
way of life. In contrast to much mainstream
academic poetry, cowboy poetry is
marked by accessibility to a general audience
and emphasizes public oral performance.</p>

<p>Unlike the more visible aspects of cowboy
culture that were earlier adapted into our
popular culture, however, authentic cowboy
verse remained essentially unknown beyond
range country until the first Cowboy Poetry
Gathering, held at Elko, Nevada, in 1985. Since
then cowboy poetry has enjoyed a renaissance,
with scores of gatherings being held throughout
the West and performers such as Baxter
Black and Waddie Mitchell gaining national
prominence. Although this recent surge of
popularity has attracted a host of less-than-skilled
practitioners, the work of cowboy poets
such as J. B. Allen, Wallace McRae, Vess
Quinlan, Buck Ramsey, Andy Wilkinson, and
Paul Zarzyski, among many others, has the
technical skill, intellectual rigor, and universality
of emotion that are the hallmarks of
lasting poetry.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">IMAGES AND ICONS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ii.015">Cowboy Culture</ref>
/ <hi rend="smallcaps">MUSIC</hi>: <ref n="egp.mus.012">Cowboy Music</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>James Hoy<lb/>
Emporia State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Cannon, Hal, ed. <title level="m">Cowboy Poetry: A Gathering</title>. Salt Lake
City: Gibbs Smith, 1985.</bibl> <bibl>Lomax, John. <title level="m">Cowboy Songs and Other Frontier Ballads</title>. New York: Macmillan Company,
1910.</bibl> <bibl>Thorp, N. Howard (Jack). <title level="m">Songs of the Cowboys</title>.
Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1921.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>