<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.pe.030">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Grasses</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Mary Ann Vinton</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.pe.030</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Vinton, Mary Ann">Mary Ann Vinton</author>. <title level="a">"Grasses."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">631-632</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-22</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">GRASSES</head>

<p>Grasses are truly the defining feature of the
Great Plains landscape. They are key elements
in both the aesthetic appeal and the economic
value of the Plains. The various shapes, textures,
colors, and movements of grasses in a
wide sweep of Plains landscape has inspired
many artists, naturalists, and casual observers.
It is the very existence of grass&#8211;providing forage
for livestock and fostering nutritious soils
for farming&#8211;that has made the Great Plains
a hospitable place for human settlement and
agriculture.</p>

<p>Grasses are the third largest plant family,
and grass species are more broadly represented
around the world than the species of any other
family. Grasses include the plants referred to as
"grains," which form the major food group for
humans as well as many animals. Many cultivated
crops&#8211;corn, wheat, sorghum, millet,
barley, oats, rice&#8211;are grasses that have been
domesticated from their wild relatives. Large
portions of the Great Plains, particularly the
wetter region east of the ninety-eighth meridian,
have been converted from natural grasslands
to fields that are planted with the cultivated
grasses corn, wheat, and sorghum.</p>

<p>Grasses are classified as "monocots," which
means that their tissue does not form wood
and their stems do not increase in girth as they
grow. Monocots have root systems that tend to
form a dense, fibrous mat. Such a rooting
habit made it possible for early Plains settlers
to cut out blocks of soil, held together by the
dense mat of roots, to form sod houses. Another
diagnostic feature of grasses is the fact
that their flowers are quite unlike those of
other plant groups. The flowers are so small
and inconspicuous that many people have the
impression that grasses do not form flowers at
all. They do in fact form flowers, but these
tend to lack petals and sepals; most grasses are
wind-pollinated, so the need to attract pollinators
with bright and showy blossoms is
minimal. Grass flowers are arranged in tightly
packed vertical clusters called spikes, or more
branched and spreading clusters called panicles.
Although they do not have colorful petals,
the most obvious flower part is often the
bright yellow, pollen-filled anthers protruding
from the flower.</p>

<p>In the Great Plains grasses comprise most
of the biomass in the plant canopy; they form
a matrix in which other herbaceous plants
and shrubs are interspersed. While some
grasses have an annual growth form, most of
the native and abundant species are perennial.
The Great Plains region can be subdivided
into smaller subregions based on the type of
perennial grasses growing in each area. The
westernmost portion, adjacent to the Rocky
Mountains, consists of shortgrass prairie. This
region is one of the driest regions of the Plains
because of the rain shadow effect of the Rocky
Mountains. Short-statured, drought-tolerant
grasses such as <hi rend="italic">Bouteloua gracilis</hi> (blue grama)
and <hi rend="italic">Buchlo&#235; dactyloides</hi> (buffalograss) are the
dominant grasses. The easternmost portion is
classified as tallgrass prairie. This region receives
more moisture than the shortgrass region
because of the weakening of the Rocky
Mountain rain shadow and the increasing effect
of moist air from the Gulf of Mexico. The
dominant grasses in the tallgrass prairie are
<hi rend="italic">Andropogon gerardii</hi> (big bluestem), <hi rend="italic">Panicum
virgatum</hi> (switchgrass), and <hi rend="italic">Sorghastrum nutans</hi>
(Indiangrass). Between the short- and
tallgrass prairies is a type of grassland referred
to as mixed-grass prairie. This is a transitional
zone and includes the short- and tallgrass species
as well as increased dominance of the species <hi rend="italic">Schizachyrium scoparius</hi> (little bluestem)
and <hi rend="italic">Agropyron smithii</hi> (western wheatgrass).
The mixed-grass prairie can be further subdivided
into a northern and southern type.
The northern mixed-grass prairie includes
greater abundance of the cool season grasses,
<hi rend="italic">A. smithii</hi> and species of <hi rend="italic">Stipa</hi> (needlegrass)
while the southern mixed-grass prairie is
dominated by the warm season grasses, <hi rend="italic">S.
scoparius</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Bouteloua curtipendula</hi> (sideoats
grama). Both the northern mixed- and
tallgrass prairies extend from the United
States northward into Canada and form the
majority of what is termed the "Canadian
Prairie Province." This area of grassland also
includes the fescue prairie, dominated by <hi rend="italic">Festuca
scabrella</hi> (rough fescue). Fescue prairie
forms an arc around the northern and northwestern
perimeter of the mixed-grass prairie,
where grassland gives way to forest.</p>

<p>One often underappreciated ecological role
that grasses play is in the formation of the rich
soils, called mollisols, that typically underlay
grasslands. Why are these soils so rich in nutrients
and organic matter? The answer lies in
the growth patterns of the grasses themselves.
The aboveground portion of grass dies back
every year, and the dense, fibrous root system
is constantly growing and dying back. All of
this results in large inputs of organic matter
into the soil. The breakdown of the organic
matter supplies nutrients to plants. The presence
of the organic matter also increases the
nutrient&#8211;and water&#8211;holding capacity of the
soil. The richness of the soil has resulted in the
wetter portions of the Great Plains becoming
the breadbasket of the world.</p>

<p>A second important ecological role played
by grasses is their persistence under drought,
grazing, and fire, all forces that can kill other
types of plants. Many grasses withstand these
forces with little injury. A key reason is that
grasses have their perennating organs (from
which new growth arises) protected below the
surface of the soil. Because of the protection of
the perennating organ in the soil, grasses can
grow back after their aboveground biomass
has been removed by drought, grazing, or fire.
In addition to the belowground perennating
organs, the large amount of root biomass allows
grasses to store resources needed to replace
aboveground tissue lost to fire or grazers.
The amount of root biomass in grasslands
is often greater than the amount of aboveground
biomass; in fact, grasslands could be
called upside-down forests. Grass roots provide
habitat and food for a whole suite of animals,
bacteria, and fungi, just as a forest canopy
supports an array of life.</p>

<p>The belowground community (as well as
the aboveground canopy) is radically altered
by plowing and the conversion of natural
grasslands to agricultural fields in the Great
Plains. This conversion has already claimed
more than 90 percent of the tallgrass prairie
region, and other grassland types, especially
those in areas with reliable sources of water,
have also disappeared. Grasses are valuable in
both an aesthetic sense and for the critical
ecological roles that they play in ecosystems.
More and more conservation efforts are under
way to preserve what remains of the natural
grasslands in the Great Plains.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">ARCHITECTURE</hi>: <ref n="egp.arc.043">Sod-Wall Construction</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Mary Ann Vinton<lb/>
Creighton University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Brown, Lauren. <title level="m">Grasslands</title>. New York: Alfred A. Knopf,
Inc., 1997.</bibl> <bibl>Coupland, R. T., ed. <title level="m">Ecosystems of the World 8A:
Natural Grasslands: Introduction and Western Hemisphere</title>.
Amsterdam: Elsevier Science Publishers, 1992.</bibl> <bibl>Estes, J. R.,
R. J. Tyrl, and J. N. Brunken, eds. <title level="m">Grasses and Grasslands:
Systematics and Ecology</title>. Norman: University of Oklahoma
Press, 1982.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>