<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.ct.008 SYSTEM "egp.ct.008.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ct.008">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Calgary, Alberta</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Wayne K. D. Davies</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ct.008</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Davies, Wayne K. D.">Wayne K. D. Davies</author>. <title level="a">"Calgary, Alberta."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">160-161</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-22</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<figure n="egp.ct.008" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Calgary, Alberta</figDesc>
</figure>


<div1>
<head type="main">CALGARY, ALBERTA</head>

<p>The administrative city of Calgary had a population
of 876,519 in April 2001, with another
70,000 in the surrounding metropolitan area.
Calgary has been one of the fastest growing
centers in Canada, increasing from 139,000 in
1951 to 403,000 in 1971, 592,000 in 1981, and
711,000 in 1991. In the 1996–2001 period the
city grew by more than 109,000 people, twothirds
of whom were in-migrants. It is now
Canada's sixth largest metropolitan area and
second largest in area, covering 278.5 square
miles.</p>

<p>The city owes its origin to the fort established
by the North-West Mounted Police in
1875 at the confluence of the Bow and Elbow
Rivers near the junction of the Prairie grasslands
and the forested Foothills belt fringing
the Rocky Mountains. Calgary occupies an
area of mainly flat postglacial lake deposits at
a height of 3,400 feet downtown, with relief
provided by the scarps of the incised river valleys
and glacial overflow channels and the
eastern outliers of the Foothills belt. The
city has a cold and dry continental interior
climate—the typical Calgary day has an open
blue sky, and the mean precipitation level is
only fourteen inches. Locally, the altitude,
which reduces summer temperatures and the
number of frost-free days, and warm chinook
winds, which moderate the cold winter climate,
also exert their influence.</p>

<p>The transcontinental Canadian Pacific Railway
reached Calgary in 1883, creating a small
service center that was incorporated as a town
in 1884. Despite its designation as a city in
1896, the center only contained 4,000 people
by 1901, since most of the surrounding area
was still sparsely populated and dominated by
large cattle ranches to the west. The influx of
pioneering farming families led to Calgary's
first major boom as a regional service center
based on agricultural processing and railway
marshaling industries. A central business area
emerged, with buildings built of distinctive local
sandstones. By 1911 the population had
reached almost 44,000 and a decade later was
over 63,000, making Calgary the eighth largest
city in Canada.</p>

<p>The discovery in 1914 of the Turner Valley
gas and oil field, thirty miles to the southwest,
led to Calgary's rise as the administrative center
of the industry. Major oil and gas discoveries
in other parts of Alberta after World War II
fueled a boom in the industry, but the head
offices remained in Calgary despite the expanded
national and international roles of the
oil companies. The result is that Calgary has
always had a significant role as a corporate
headquarters center. The city is home to 103 of
the top 800 companies in Canada, as ranked by
revenue, compared to greater Toronto with
234, greater Montreal with 104, and Vancouver
with 51. Most of these head offices and their
ancillary companies in law, finance, geology,
surveying, and transportation remain downtown,
along with government offices and other
service industries. Hence Calgary's city center&#8211;
a distinctive modern high-rise complex
with 32 million square feet of office space and
more than 106,000 workers&#8211;has remained the
city's primary center of employment.</p>

<p>Calgary's government structure consists
of an elected mayor and fourteen councilors
elected on a ward basis. Calgary's concentrated
high-rise downtown contrasts dramatically
with the low-density sprawl of the rest of
the city, which explains why the city has the
highest per capita car ownership and gas consumption
in Canada. Yet strong planning controls by its unicity government structure have
meant that suburban residential development
has been based on detailed community plans
for more than forty years. A distinctive feature
of Calgary's suburban development has been
the creation of residential areas anchored by a
recreational complex, nine built around artificial
lakes and six around golf courses. The city
also has more than 130 residential community
associations, most of which have their own
community halls. Although these associations
occupy a relatively small role in most people's
lives, they are routinely consulted on planning
developments, and they play an active role
in recreational and social provision. When
added to the participation of the Calgarians in
other associations, the city has produced one
of the highest levels of citizen volunteerism in
cities in the Western world.</p>

<p>In view of the corporate basis of the city, it
is not surprising to find that its employment
structure is dominated by services: in 1996
only 9.4 percent of employed people were in
manufacturing, 6.7 percent in construction,
and 12.0 percent in transportation and communication.
Most of the industrial activity is
located in a distinctive sector extending southeast
from the inner city. The oil industry
has attracted one of the highest concentrations
of computer power on the continent,
which has stimulated a rapidly growing electronic-
and technology-based sector, with
more than 30,000 jobs. Another important
amenity is the University of Calgary, which
had a student enrollment of 24,000 and an
external research budget close to $100 million
in 2000. The 1990s also saw the city develop as
a transportation and depot hub for western
Canada, although it no longer has a regular
passenger rail service. Its airport, with more
than seven million passengers per year, is the
fourth largest in Canada.</p>

<p>Calgary has traditionally been peopled by
immigrants of British and Irish descent, who
accounted for 83.6 percent of the population
by 1921. There was also a strong American
presence, since 21 percent of Alberta's residents
at the time were born in the United States and
had joined the pioneering rush to the Canadian
Prairies. Americans were also attracted to
the oil industry, both in an administrative capacity
and in exploration and production. After
World War II the ethnic balance changed as
new immigrants from western and northern
Europe moved to the city. By 1971 only 56 percent
of the residents had a British Isles ethnic
background, another 21 percent were of German,
Scandinavian, and Dutch origin, while
3.9 percent and 2.4 percent were of Ukrainian
and Italian origin, respectively. Since the 1980s
the immigration streams have altered again.
The 1996 federal census revealed that 20.8 percent
of the city's population was born outside
Canada, and a third of this number come
from a variety of Asian countries. The largest
Asian group, numbering approximately
50,000 in 1996, are the Chinese. Most are scattered
throughout the city, although there is
still a significant concentration in a redeveloped
Chinatown on the edge of downtown
that contains a large number of restaurants,
businesses, high-rises, and a re-creation of
Beijing's Temple of Heaven as a cultural center.</p>

<p>The proximity of the city to the Rocky
Mountains and its national parks means that
Calgary has become a gateway for recreational
visits to the area. In addition, the Winter
Olympics of 1988 gave the city world exposure
and left a significant heritage in world-class
winter sports facilities in the city and vicinity.
The presence of a ranching industry in the
foothills to the west provides a link to the past,
but the ranching economy of the city has long
since disappeared. However, the annual Calgary
Stampede is still a major presence that
keeps the heritage alive. During Stampede
week the majority of people in the city, whatever
their ethnic heritage and occupation, take
pride in dressing up in cowboy costumes, giving
the city a distinctive if invented tradition
and character. This image has been enhanced
by the recent development of Spruce Meadows,
just outside the city boundary to the
south, which now hosts some of the world's
premier horse jumping events.</p>

<p>The annual re-creation of Calgary's cowboy
past may provide an easily recognizable image
but should not be allowed to conceal the city's
true character of a modern, affluent, corporate
metropolis. It has virtually no slum areas, a 68
percent home ownership figure, one of the
highest rates of postsecondary educated people
in Canada, and a median annual income of
$50,000 per census family in 1996. Calgary is
also characterized by large amounts of recreational
space, especially along the major rivers
and in a series of parks, of which Nose Hill is
the largest. Calgary's recent growth has made
it a demographically young city, and only 8.7
percent of the population is over sixty-five
years of age. The result is a dynamic and increasingly
cosmopolitan center, a city with
high levels of amenity but one still intimately
linked to the oil and gas industry, despite recent
trends in economic diversification.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">ASIAN AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.asam.006">Calgary Chinatown</ref>
/ <hi rend="smallcaps">SPORTS AND RECREATION</hi>: <ref n="egp.sr.007">Calgary Winter Olympics</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Wayne K. D. Davies<lb/>
University of Calgary</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Bradley, Andrew. <title level="m">Calgary: A Photographic Essay</title>. Canmore,
Alberta: Altitude Publishing Canada Ltd., 2002.</bibl>
<bibl>Lloyd, Tanya. <title level="m">Calgary</title>. Vancouver, British Columbia:
Whitecap Books, 2000.</bibl> <bibl>Tivy, Patrick. <title level="m">Portrait of Calgary</title>.
Canmore, Alberta: Altitude Publishing Canada Ltd., 1995.</bibl>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>