<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.ag.075 SYSTEM "egp.ag.075.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ag.075">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Wheat</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Patrick J. McCluskey</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ag.075</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="McCluskey, Patrick J.">Patrick J. McCluskey</author>. <title level="a">"Wheat."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">56-57</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2009-01-12</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">WHEAT</head>

<figure n="egp.ag.075" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Wheat harvest near Chilocco, Oklahoma, July 1984</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>What is commonly recognized as a kernel of
wheat is the caryopsis or fruit of a plant of
the genus <hi rend="italic">Triticum</hi> from the grass family
(Gramineae). Biologically the purpose of the
caryopsis is to reproduce the plant. Humans
recognized the food value of wheat, which today
is one of the most important cultivated
crops in the world. Commercially in the
United States, wheat is classified based on seed
coat color (red or white), kernel texture (hard
or soft), and growth habit (winter or spring).
In the Great Plains three market classes of
wheat are typically grown: hard red winter
wheat, hard red spring wheat, and durum
wheat. Hard red winter and hard red spring
wheats (species <hi rend="italic">Triticum aestivum</hi> L.) are
called common or hexaploid wheats and have
forty-two chromosomes; durum wheat (<hi rend="italic">Triticum
durum</hi> Desf.) is a tetraploid wheat having
twenty-eight chromosomes. Hard white
wheat, with winter and spring habit cultivars,
is another market class of wheat that
is increasing in commercial popularity in the
Plains.</p>

<p>Cultivation of wheat in the Central Great
Plains began in earnest when Russian Mennonite
immigrants brought the hard red winter
wheat variety (Turkey Red) to Kansas
around 1874, although wheat was grown in
Kansas prior to this. Turkey Red proved to
be well suited to the environment of southcentral
Kansas and diffused from there. Agricultural
records from 1900 show that Turkey
Red (or its sibling Crimea) was also grown
in Nebraska and Oklahoma Territory. Today
Colorado, Kansas, Oklahoma, Nebraska, and
Texas primarily grow hard red winter wheat.
Texas and Oklahoma, and to a lesser extent
Kansas, also use wheat stands for grazing cattle.
Montana and South Dakota grow both
hard red winter and hard red spring wheats (as
well as some durum wheat) with records of
such cultivation dating from 1841 in Montana
and the 1890s in South Dakota. North Dakota
produces hard red spring and durum wheat;
records indicate production of Fife and Bluestem
hard red spring types as early as 1879.
Production of wheat in the Canadian Prairie
Provinces started after the Dominion Lands
Act of 1872 and the westward expansion of the
Canadian Pacific Railway brought in settlers.
Hard red spring and durum wheats are primarily
grown because of the short growing
season in the region. The Prairie Provinces
now produce hard red spring wheats, spring
white wheats, durum wheats, and some red
winter wheats.</p>

<p>Conditions under which wheat is grown
are extremely diverse throughout the Plains.
Wide ranges exist in rainfall amounts, altitude,
daytime and nighttime temperatures,
soil conditions, and farming practices. Also,
the types and severity of diseases and insects
that attack wheat are many and varied. Winter
wheat is planted in fall and harvested in late
spring to early summer; it requires a cold period
in order to produce grain in the spring
(vernalization) but must possess tolerance to
adverse winter conditions (winter hardiness).
Wheat is usually harvested when the moisture
content is about 10 to 16 percent. Winter
wheat harvest typically begins in May in Texas
and is usually handled by custom harvest
crews with combines who move north as the
grain ripens. Spring wheat and durum wheat
are planted in April or May then harvested in
late summer. In the Canadian Prairie Provinces,
seeding occurs during May and June.
Harvest can begin as early as August and usually
runs well into September. Swathing,
where wheat is cut at physiological maturity
then threshed after drying in the sun, is a
common harvesting practice on smaller farms
in North Dakota and Canada; however, combining
of wheat is increasing there.</p>

<p>Grain yield is influenced by both genetic
and environmental factors. Average yield
ranges from twenty to forty bushels per acre
across the Plains, though in 1997 yields as high
as eighty bushels per acre were reported. Major
increases in grain yield occurred when
farmers shifted from tall to semidwarf varieties,
which produce less straw and more kernels
per plant. The short stature plants are also
sturdier thus more resistant to lodging (falling
over). This transition began in the late 1960s
in the Northern Great Plains and was completed
in the Southern Great Plains by the
early 1980s. Once wheat is harvested, it is
stored on the farm or taken directly to an elevator
for storage or sale. On-farm storage is
more prevalent in the Northern Plains. In
1997, approximately 79 million seeded acres
produced nearly 65 million metric tons of
wheat in the Great Plains.</p>

<p>While much of the wheat is consumed domestically,
both the United States and Canada
are major exporters. Domestic uses include
animal feed, starch and gluten production, industrial
applications, seed wheat, and most
importantly, milling into bakery flours. Hard
winter and hard spring wheats are noted for
having high protein content and are typically
used for making pan and hearth breads, hard
rolls, bagels, buns, other yeast leavened products,
and all-purpose flour. Durum wheat
is used almost exclusively for making pasta
products such as spaghetti and macaroni. In
an average year, about 40 percent of the wheat
grown in the Great Plains is exported. International
customers purchase U.S. and Canadian
wheat for such products as pan and
hearth breads, French breads, steamed breads,
chapatis, flat breads, Asian style noodles, pasta
products, and indigenous traditional foods.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">INDUSTRY</hi> <ref n="egp.ind.025">Grain Processing</ref>; <ref n="egp.ind.056">Swather</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Patrick J. McCluskey<lb/>
Kansas State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Bartholomew, David M. et al. <title level="m">Marketing Kansas Wheat</title>.
Kansas State Board of Agriculture, 1959.</bibl> <bibl>Pomeranz, Y.
<title level="m">Wheat: Chemistry and Technology</title>. St. Paul: American Association
of Cereal Chemists, 1988.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>