<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ea.029">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Norwegians</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>John M. Pederson</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ea.029</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Pederson, John M.">John M. Pederson</author>. <title level="a">"Norwegians."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">242-243</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-09</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">NORWEGIANS</head>

<p>Though the total number of Norwegians in
both the United States and Canada is small,
Norway is second only to Ireland in the percentage
of its population who emigrated from
Europe. Norwegian immigration to North
America in the modern era began in 1825. Before
the Civil War, Norwegian settlement centered
in Wisconsin, with large settlements also
forming in neighboring Iowa and Minnesota,
although some Norwegians settled as far
south as Texas. After the Civil War, Norwegians
followed the railroads westward onto
the Northern Great Plains. Some came directly
from Norway; others had been born in
places such as Houston and Fillmore Counties
in southeastern Minnesota, or Mitchell and
Worth Counties in northern Iowa, and had
moved on to the next available land.</p>

<p>Of all the states, North Dakota was, and
remains, the most Norwegian in proportion
to its total population. Traill County, in the
middle of the Red River Valley, between the
cities of Fargo and Grand Forks, was 74 percent
Norwegian in 1880. By 1900 Norwegians
comprised almost one-fourth of the state's
population. Norwegians settled almost the entirety
of the Goose and Sheyenne River valleys
in the eastern half of the state and spread out
along the Souris River in the western part
of the state. They were successful farmers,
quickly adjusting to Plains agriculture. In the
early years the men supplemented their incomes
by working as carpenters, teamsters,
and railroad laborers, and single women took
jobs in towns, often as maids or cooks. The
large Norwegian presence in northwestern
North Dakota led to the claim (a Plains tall
tale) that one could walk from the Garrison
Dam to the state's northwest corner without
leaving land owned by ethnic Norwegians.</p>

<p>North of the forty-ninth parallel, Saskatchewan
was the most Norwegian province by the
turn of the twentieth century. When the Canadian
Pacific Railway reached Calgary, entrepreneurs
sought to create a fortune by providing
lumber for settlers on the treeless prairie.
They recruited workers from the midwestern
lumber city of Eau Claire, Wisconsin, creating
a Norwegian colony in Calgary in the 1880s.
Most of those born in Norway came to Canada
by way of the United States; on the other hand,
many Norwegians who came to the United
States first landed in Quebec, because of its
proximity to Norway, before going to the Midwest
and the Great Plains. Of the 88,558 people
of Norwegian origin living in Canada in 1931,
almost 82 percent lived in the provinces of
Alberta, Saskatchewan, and Manitoba.</p>

<p>For most Norwegians religion played a central
role in community and private life. The
Norwegian state church was Lutheran, and in
the Great Plains most Norwegians remained
Lutheran. But this apparent source of cultural
unity was also one of division, as Norwegians
founded fourteen different Lutheran synods,
or denominations, all claiming to be Lutheran.
Many of these competing synods later merged
into larger organizations that are now part of
the multiethnic Evangelical Lutheran Church
in America. The different synods were maintained
by an assertive and vigorous clergy who
promoted an active cultural awareness.</p>

<p>In addition to the church, two other organizations
maintained and fostered Norwegian
culture in the Great Plains. The <hi rend="italic">bygdelag</hi>
movement was a distinctive Norwegian organization
formed by immigrant families and
their descendants from a specific Norwegian
valley, fjord area, or community district. They
tended to be a rural phenomenon and to have
a religious orientation. A strong attachment to
the local Norwegian community from which
they came was the major motivation behind
the creation of the <hi rend="italic">bygdelag</hi>. In contrast, the
Sons of Norway tended to be an urban organization,
a fraternal and secular society offering
life insurance to its members. Clergy often attacked
the Sons of Norway as a secret society
similar to the Masonic order.</p>

<p>The Norwegians' ethnic identity is a curious
combination of pride and humility.
Though a church or Sons of Norway lodge
may still serve a traditional meal of <hi rend="italic">lutefisk</hi>
and <hi rend="italic">lefse</hi>, most Norwegians are culturally assimilated.
The creation and continued existence
of the <hi rend="italic">bygdelag</hi> and the Sons of Norway
are indicative of cultural pride. On the other
hand, Norwegian humor tends to poke fun at
fellow countrymen, usually named Ole, Lars,
or Lena.</p>

<closer>
<signed>John M. Pederson<lb/>
Mayville State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Loken, Gulbrand. <title level="m">From Fjord to Frontier: A History of Norwegians in Canada</title>. Toronto: McClelland and Stewart Ltd.,
1980.</bibl> <bibl>Lovoll, Odd. <title level="m">The Promise of America: A History of the Norwegian-American People</title>. Minneapolis: University of
Minnesota Press, 1984.</bibl> <bibl>Thorson, Playford V. "Scandinavians."
In <title level="m">Plains Folk: North Dakota's Ethnic History</title>, edited
by William Sherman and Playford V. Thorson. Fargo:
North Dakota Institute for Regional Studies, 1988: 188–
257.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>