<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.na.118 SYSTEM "egp.na.118.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.na.118">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Treaties</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>David J. Wishart</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.na.118</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</author>. <title level="a">"Treaties."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">607-608</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-20</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">TREATIES</head>

<figure n="egp.na.118" rend="granted">
<figDesc>U.S. Army commissioners in council with chiefs, Fort Laramie, Wyoming, 1868</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>In both the United States and Canada, negotiated
treaties were the instrument for obtaining
Indian lands and more generally for extending
federal control over Native peoples,
while at the same time recognizing the sovereignty
they retained. In the United States,
the Constitution gave the executive branch the
authority to negotiate treaties and the Senate
the authority to ratify them. Treaty making
was abolished in 1871, but similar bilateral
agreements between the federal government
and the tribes continued thereafter. In Canada,
the provision for a treaty process was established
with the Royal Proclamation of 1763,
whereby the Crown reserved the sole right to
purchase Indian lands. That authority was
continued through the British North America
Act of 1867, which passed on the Crown's authority
over First Peoples to the new Dominion
of Canada.</p>

<p>In both Canada and the United States, early
treaties proclaimed peace and friendship between
the government and the Native peoples.
The fact is, neither of the colonizing powers
had the military power to defeat the Indians,
and treaties were a pragmatic alternative. After
1812, however, the population balance
swung in favor of the European Americans,
and treaties became the means to acquire Indian
lands. Especially in the United States, it
was a buyer's market. Pressured by settlers and
mired in poverty, Indians rarely had any option
but to sell. In many cases, consent to
treaties was obtained only through fraud and
duress. The surrender of the Black Hills by the
Lakotas (Sioux) in 1877 and the sale of the Red
River Valley of the North by the Red Lake and
Pembina bands of the Chippewas are notable
examples of such manipulation.</p>

<p>In the American Great Plains, treaty making
for the purpose of obtaining Indian lands began
with the cession of what is now southern Oklahoma
by the Quapaw in 1818. This land, and vast
areas subsequently obtained in the 1820s and
1830s in present-day Oklahoma, Kansas, and
southern Nebraska, were bought from Plains
Indians to make room for relocated Indians
from the eastern United States. The next wave of
treaties came in eastern Nebraska and southeastern
Dakota Territory in the second half of
the 1850s when the Pawnees, Omahas, Poncas,
Otoe-Missourias, and Yanktons sold their ancestral
lands, retaining only small reservations.
European Americans moved in to settle the
newly acquired public domain. This process was
repeated westward and northward throughout
the Great Plains in the following four decades.
Indian dispossession, achieved through treaties,
was the prerequisite for frontier settlement.</p>

<p>In Canada, the clearing of Indian title to the
Prairie Provinces was done more quickly. From
1871 to 1877, in a series of seven numbered treaties,
the many bands of Crees, Chippewas, Assiniboines,
and Blackfoot relinquished their
claims to the land and settled on reserves. The
terms of each treaty varied only in detail.
Through Treaties 1 and 2, for example, concluded
in 1871, the Swampy Crees and Chippewas
ceded 52,400 square miles of southern
Manitoba and Saskatchewan in return for a
reserve, a school, farm implements, a onetime
payment of $3 per person, and an annuity
of $3 per person.</p>

<p>Similar types of compensation were given
south of the forty-ninth parallel. In both countries,
payments for lands.the monies due the
Indians.were used to fund the government's
"civilization" programs, which aimed to assimilate
the Indians as independent, selfsu.
cient, Christianized farmers. But payments
for Indian lands were so low (they averaged
ten cents an acre in the Central and
Northern Great Plains) and the quality of services
and goods so poor, that the end product
of treaty making was poverty, not self-sufficiency.</p>

<p>On the one hand, then, treaties can be
viewed as a subterfuge, a means of acquiring
Indian lands legally and without the more expensive
and disruptive warfare. Negotiations
took place, the Indians had their say, and the
federal governments set the conditions of the
divestiture. On the other hand, treaties established
reservations and reserves where tribal
law and government still prevail despite challenges.
Treaties are not merely historical documents;
they are contracts between sovereign
powers, the foundation of Indian law, and
often the legal justification for claims cases.</p>

<closer>
<signed>David J. Wishart</signed>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Cohen, Felix S. <title level="m">Handbook of Federal Indian Law</title>. Buffalo:
William S. Hein Co., 1988: 33-67.</bibl> <bibl>McQuillan, Aidan D.
"Creation of Indian Reserves on the Canadian Prairies,
1870-1885." <title level="j">Geographical Review</title> 70 (1980): 219-36.</bibl> <bibl>Wilkinson,
Charles F. <title level="m">American Indians, Time, and the Law</title>.
New Haven <hi rend="smallcaps">CT</hi>: Yale University Press, 1987.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>