<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fol.003">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Animal Lore</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Angus Kress Gillespie</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2009</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fol.003</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2009</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2009 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Gillespie, Angus Kress">Angus Kress Gillespie</author>. <title level="a">"Animal Lore."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">291</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-16</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">ANIMAL LORE</head>

<p>Animal lore is the accumulated fact, tradition,
and belief about the fauna of a region. Larger
animals have a stronger grip on the human
imagination. Thus, the buffalo has long been
emblematic of the Great Plains. However,
farmers and ranchers who know the region
best have a rich store of knowledge of smaller
animals, including badgers, beavers, bobcats,
foxes, lynxes, minks, muskrats, opossums,
prairie dogs, rabbits, raccoons, skunks, squirrels,
and weasels.</p>

<p>The folkloristic sources of the ideas, images,
and stories about wild animals of the Great
Plains are many, but four types can be distinguished:
oral narratives, popular culture, performances,
and elite culture. These categories
provide a frame of reference for understanding
this body of animal lore.</p>

<p>First are the oral narratives, a key source of
ideas about wild animals of the Great Plains.
This genre includes the true "stories" people
pass on to explain to one another the meaning
of a wild animal. It is also the category that has
been treated to the most folklore scholarship.
Myths are representative of this genre, and
there are many Native American myths involving
such animals as the deer, coyote, elk,
or bear. Myths often explain the origins of
geographic features in the remote past. An example
is Devils Tower in eastern Wyoming, a
large stump-shaped cluster of rock columns,
overlooking the Belle Fourche River and rising
1,280 feet above the rolling grasslands. Noted
for its magnificence and beauty, this formation
has long been a landmark to explorers
and travelers heading west from the Black
Hills. In Kiowa mythology the striations on
the tower were formed when seven young
girls, playing far from camp, were chased onto
the rock by bears. The rock rose into the heavens
where the girls became stars, and the
bears, trying to follow, left their claw marks on
the surface.</p>

<p>Such legends are also set in the less-remote
past. For example, there is a nineteenthcentury
story about the "white mustang of the
prairies," whose coat and tail and mane were
pure white. He symbolized freedom and untamed
nature in an era before there were
barbed-wire fences. Many people claimed to
see him, especially on moonlit nights. The
white mustang was able to avoid all predators
and was never seen for very long at a time.
Cowboys tried to capture him, but they eventually
realized it was a waste of time because
of the white mustang's courage, speed, and intelligence,
which always kept him out of the of
ropes and bullets.</p>

<p>Popular culture is the second source of
ideas about wild animals of the Great Plains.
Included in this category are postcards, souvenirs,
cartoons, comics, television commercials,
print advertising, theatrical films, and
mass-circulation magazines. Popular culture
provides a repertoire of stories and images to a
wide audience. Popular material from commercial
culture can be found in abundance,
from the Warner Bros. cartoon character Wile
E. Coyote to the postcards from Nebraska featuring
the "jackalope," a legendary creature
combining a jackrabbit with an antelope.</p>

<p>The third source of ideas, images, and stories
are the performances that involve somehow
an interpretation of a wild animal. Oldest
in this category are the Native American performance
rituals and dances that involve the
armadillo, the coyote, the bear, and the rattlesnake.
European American settlers favored
participatory dramalike events that began
with Buffalo Bill's Wild West show and continue
in present-day tourist attractions, rodeos,
festivals, museum and zoo programs,
hunting expeditions, cooking events, and the
like. Significantly, Col. William F. Cody (Buffalo
Bill) was always pictured riding a white
stallion, recalling that persistent theme in
Plains animal lore.</p>

<p>The fourth source of our notions about animals
is elite culture, the body of fine literature
and fine arts that is the usual subject matter of
humanistic study. Fine painting, poetry, novels,
and short stories of the Great Plains often
feature animals such as Texas longhorn cattle,
descended from the wild cattle brought to
America by the Spanish, as central symbols
in the imaginative landscape of their fictive
works. But even here folk ideas are often still
present, just recast in more elegant language.
In American elite art we can trace the iconography
of Great Plains wildlife from the
earliest European renditions through the likes
of Thomas Hart Benton and Charles Marion
Russell up to the present.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">LITERARY TRADITIONS</hi>: 
<ref n="egp.lt.054">Oral Traditions</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Angus Kress Gillespie<lb/>
Rutgers University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Gillespie, Angus Kress, and Jay Mechling. <title level="m">American Wildlife in Symbol and Story</title>. Knoxville: University of Tennessee
Press, 1987.</bibl> <bibl>Lawrence, Elizabeth Atwood. "The
White Mustang of the Prairies." <title level="j">Great Plains Quarterly</title> 1
(1981): 81–94.</bibl> <bibl>Wilson, David Scofield. <title level="m">In the Presence of Nature</title>. Amherst: University of Massachusetts Press, 1978.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>