<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.pe.001.01 SYSTEM "egp.pe.001.01.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY egp.pe.001.02 SYSTEM "egp.pe.001.02.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.pe.001">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Physical Environment</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Bret Wallach</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.pe.001</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Wallach, Bret">Bret Wallach</author>. <title level="a">"Physical Environment."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">613-618</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-20</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT</head>

<p>The Great Plains of Canada and the United
States form an enormous piedmont flanking
the eastern slope of the Rocky Mountains.
Taken as a whole, this piedmont, some 300 to
400 miles wide and 1,800 miles long, is like a
stage before the backdrop of the Rockies. Visitors
have always been inclined to appreciate
that backdrop more than they have the stage,
but for the people who live on the Plains it
remains a debatable point which of the two is
really the more impressive.</p>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Topography</head>

<p>Explorers often used the phrase "great plains"
and even put it on maps, but the first person
to recognize the Great Plains as a physiographic
unit of North America appears to
have been John Wesley Powell, writing in 1895.
Leading geographers of the early twentieth
century, such as William Morris Davis and
Isaiah Bowman, picked up the term in this
technical sense and soon used it in textbooks.
During World War I, Nevin M. Fenneman began
work on his still authoritative physiography
of the United States, and his map of the
physical divisions of the country, published by
the U.S. Geological Survey and accompanying
his text of 1931, is still in print. It demarcates
not only the Great Plains, but also adds subdivisions
of the Plains that have now become
standard, including such colloquial ones as
the High Plains and other, more technical
ones such as the Plains Border and the Missouri
Plateau. Edwin Hammond in 1964 proposed
revisions to Fenneman's map, including
dropping the term Great Plains altogether and
replacing it with a set of terms including such
awkward ones as Upper Missouri River Broken
Lands, but Fenneman's terminology has
endured.</p>

<p>The Great Plains slopes gently eastward. As
defined here, the maximum height of its western
edge rises from about 2,000 feet above sea
level in Canada to more than 6,000 feet in
New Mexico. On its eastern edge, the Plains
drop to an elevation of about 1,000 feet along
a line from Winnipeg to Kansas City, Oklahoma
City, and the toe of the Balcones Escarpment
in Texas. The Great Plains, therefore,
slopes eastward approximately ten feet
per mile, a slant that is wholly imperceptible
to the unaided eye.</p>

<p>Most of the Great Plains, it should be
stressed, is not especially flat, and this general
slope can therefore be misleading. According
to Edwin Hammond, the only parts of the
Great Plains that are simultaneously both flat
and level are the valley of the Platte River in
Nebraska, the valley of the Arkansas River in
central Kansas, and several former glacial lake
beds, especially those now drained by the Red
and Souris Rivers in North Dakota and the
James River in South Dakota. There are other
equally flat but not so level parts of the Great
Plains: preeminent among these tilted plains
are the High Plains, which extend from the
Pine Ridge Escarpment in northern Nebraska
south to Midland-Odessa, Texas. (Their most
famous subdivision is the Llano Estacado, or
Staked Plains, that extends south from the Canadian
River near Amarillo and is spectacularly
rimmed on the east by the Caprock Escarpment
and on the west, in New Mexico, by
the Mescalero Escarpment.) Tilted they may
be, but to the eye the High Plains seem as level
as they are flat. Indeed, they seem so level and
flat that they can strike even the comfortable
modern traveler as faintly distressing, for their
flatness keeps the horizon always close and
can create a sense of confinement. The occasional
breaks in the High Plains&#8211;and there
are several, including the impressive valleys
of the Canadian, Cimarron, and Republican
Rivers&#8211;can therefore be a welcome respite
from the sense of being thrust upward and
pushed into the lid of the sky. The Great Plains
possesses other equally flat but tilted plains as
well, but these areas are much smaller than the
High Plains; economically, the most important
of them is probably the wheat-rich Wichita
Prairie of Kansas.</p>

<p>The greater part of the Plains south of the
Nebraska Sandhills is composed of irregular
or rolling, not flat, ground. Bounding the
High Plains, for example, there are tablelands
of moderate or considerable relief, both on
the west near Raton, New Mexico, and on the
east, with the Gypsum Plains of north-central
Texas. Farther east, there are low mountains in
the Wichitas near Lawton, Oklahoma; there
are plains with high hills in the Lampasas Cut
Plains of the dissected eastern edge of the
Edwards Plateau; there are hills such as the
Smoky, Flint, and Osage Hills of Kansas and
Oklahoma; and there are huge areas of gently
rolling plains, such as the Red River Rolling
Plains of Oklahoma and Texas and the Enid
Prairie of Oklahoma.</p>

<p>The Nebraska Sandhills, the largest area of
sand dunes in the Western Hemisphere, were
classified by Hammond as open hills; to their
north he delineated a complex topographic
mosaic including tablelands along the Missouri,
open high hills in the Powder River
Basin, low mountains in the Black Hills, and
open high mountains in the Bearpaw Mountains
south of Havre, Montana.</p>

<p>No classification like Hammond's has been
made for the landforms of Canada, but H. S.
Bostock of the Geological Survey of Canada has
subdivided the Canadian Great Plains into the
Alberta, Saskatchewan, and Manitoba Plains.
Despite these names, the boundaries of these
units follow topographical rather than political
features. Thus the Alberta Plain, largest of the
three, is bounded on the west by the Rocky
Mountain foothills, on the north by the Alberta
Plateau, which starts at the Athabaska River, and
on the east by the Missouri Coteau, an escarpment
that runs from near North Battleford
southeasterly into the Dakotas. The Saskatchewan
Plain extends eastward below the Coteau to
the Manitoba Escarpment, which lies just west
of Lakes Winnipegosis and Manitoba. The outstanding
topographic feature on the Canadian
plains, other than the subdividing escarpments,
is the Cypress Hills, which rise southeast of
Medicine Hat, Alberta. The Great Plains in Canada,
it should again be emphasized, are by no
means either entirely flat or entirely level; extensive
areas here, too, are rolling or even hilly.</p>

<p>Strikingly, our knowledge of the topography
of the Great Plains remains incomplete. This
may be surprising, since the main lines of natural
drainage were worked out nearly 150 years
ago: those in the United States, for example,
were shown in 1857 with startling accuracy on
the map prepared by Lt. G. K. Warren of the
U.S. Army Corps of Topographical Engineers.
In the century that followed, Dominion-land
surveyors in Canada and public-domain surveyors
in the United States drafted planimetric
maps showing almost every creek and hill on
the Plains; geodetic and topographic surveyors
added elevations. Yet significant details are
being discovered even today. Recent digital terrain
mapping by Gail Thelin and Richard Pike
of the U.S. Geological Survey, for example, has
revealed what appears to be an extraordinary
set of regional fractures trending from northwest
to southeast across the Plains, especially
north of the Sandhills. Thelin and Pike suggest
that these features were created by the collision
and fusion of an ancestral North America with
lands farther west.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Geology</head>

<p>As such details suggest, a real understanding of
topography requires a knowledge of geology.
Much sense can in fact be made of the topography
of the Great Plains if we remember that the
Great Plains rest upon the North American
craton, which is to say the Precambrian continental
core. Exposed in the United States primarily
in the Superior Upland of northern
Minnesota, but exposed far more extensively
in the Canadian Shield, these cratonic rocks
extend between the Appalachians and the
Rockies. At a few places on the Plains they
outcrop, most notably in the Black Hills of
South Dakota, where they emerge from between
encircling sedimentary layers. Less massively,
they are revealed in the Little Belt Mountains
south of Great Falls, Montana, and in the
Wichita Mountains northwest of Lawton, Oklahoma.
Elsewhere they are buried, often at
tremendous depth. At Amarillo, which is 5,000
feet above sea level, the cratonic rocks lie at a
depth of 3,000 feet below sea level; eastward,
they plunge to a basin whose surface lies approximately
30,000 feet below sea level.</p>

<p>This great thickness of sedimentary rocks
covering the craton accumulated over a period
of several hundred million years as sediments
from the Appalachians and Rockies
were carried across the often submerged but
intervening lowland. Periods of uplift and
erosion have removed most of the sediments
that at one time or another were laid down
upon the craton, but, with the few exceptions
mentioned above, at least some sedimentary
material still remains in place atop the cratonic
rocks of the Great Plains.</p>

<p>The surviving sections of the Tertiary, or
most recent of these major sedimentary accumulations,
form the floor of the High Plains.
Most of even these Tertiary rocks&#8211;including
the greater part of their most famous member,
the Ogallala Formation&#8211;have been stripped
away by erosion; as a result, the High Plains in
Texas and Oklahoma break away on the east to
a much older (indeed, Upper Paleozoic) sequence
of sedimentary rocks. Even on the
west, facing the Rockies from which the Tertiary
sediments were derived, erosion has
stripped away the Tertiary cover except in
southeastern Wyoming, where the so-called
Gangplank, near Cheyenne, provides a ramp
for both the Union Pacific and Interstate 80 as
they climb toward Sherman Summit. South of
the Gangplank, the sedimentary rocks exposed
in the Colorado Piedmont, which
stretches from the Wyoming state line south
nearly to Colorado Springs, are older&#8211;mostly
Cretaceous&#8211;and are lower topographically, as
well as stratigraphically, than the High Plains
materials exposed in easternmost Colorado
and in western Kansas. Cretaceous rock is exposed
south of the High Plains, too, where an
ancient limestone surface forms the Edwards
Plateau. Still older rocks are exposed west of
the Mescalero Escarpment, the western edge
of the High Plains in New Mexico. North of
the High Plains, sedimentary rocks of Mesozoic
age form most of the surface northward
into Canada, where they extend as far as the
western margin of Great Bear Lake.</p>

<p>These Mesozoic sedimentary rocks form a
surface whose irregularity may probably be
ascribed, at least in part, to ancient erosion
surfaces exposed when later sediments were
removed, but the modern surface of the Plains
owes a great deal also to repeated glaciations in
the last two million years. The great Laurentide
ice sheet, which blanketed all but insignificant
bits of central Canada, extended southward at
its maximum to about the present-day Missouri
River, whose course was profoundly
modified by the ice sheet and which, in Montana
and the Dakotas, approximately marks
the southern limit of the glacial advance.</p>

<figure n="egp.pe.001.01" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Badlands, South Dakota, ca. 1930</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>North of that line, of course, there are many
topographic features shaped by ice. Perhaps
the most famous is the Missouri Coteau itself,
a structural ridge topped with glacial sediments
along its entire course from the Saskatchewan
River south through the Dakotas.
There are countless smaller signs of ancient
ice: at Pingree, North Dakota, chains of lakes
indicate former meltwater channels; drumlins
(depositional hills) may be found near Priddis,
Alberta; and the world's largest glacial erratics
(boulders), transported 300 miles by ice,
sit in huge wheat fields near Okotoks, Alberta.</p>

<p>The effects of the ice and of Ice Age climates
are also evident, however, far south of the Missouri
River, for north winds blowing over glacial
outwash moved fine sand south to form
great beds of loess that now cover southern
Nebraska with a blanket more than thirty feet
thick. (It is no longer clear that the same winds
built up the Sandhills, which may have originated
at an earlier time.) The loess layer thins
drastically to the south, so that the High Plains
at Amarillo are topped with a layer about four
feet thick; the material, moreover, seems to
have come from the Pecos River rather than
from the north. Still, the loess of the southern
High Plains may well have been transported by
unusually strong winds associated with a glacial
climate.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Weather and Climate</head>

<p>The climatology of the Great Plains is, of
course, a subject in its own right, and one
whose foundations go back at least to the seminal
work published in 1854 by Lorin Blodget
of the Smithsonian Institution. Blodget at that
time published maps whose isothermal lines,
joining points of equal temperature, were surprisingly
accurate. His annual temperature
map, for example, showed the 60&#186; isotherm
essentially as modern maps do: coming across
central New Mexico, the line was draped over
the Llano Estacado and continued eastward to
the mouth of Chesapeake Bay. Blodget's precipitation
maps accurately indicated relatively
wet areas in the Northwest, in the Rockies and
Appalachians, and along the Gulf Coast; significantly,
they indicated a low in the Great
Plains. Blodget in fact drew what we would call
a twenty-inch isohyet running very close to the
100th meridian; he even correctly indicated
that in the Northern Plains this line, connecting
points of equal precipitation, lies slightly
east of that meridian but that in the Southern
Plains it crosses over to the west of it. (His
map, which spoke of the "Great Plains of the
Interior," made special mention of the "Desert
Plains" where we now recognize the High
Plains. Contrary to famous earlier assertions
that this part of the country was uninhabitable
by Europeans, Blodget wrote that these plains
had "much capacity for cultivation.")</p>

<p>With all his pioneering knowledge, Blodget
was keenly aware that there was much he did
not understand. Things we take for granted, he
advanced as tentative truths: that the atmosphere
in the midlatitudes has a generally westerly
flow; that the Cordilleran chains create
rain shadows in their lees; that continentality
induces a general decline in winter temperatures
at inland locations. (Here, however, Blodget
erred by attributing the decline entirely to
elevation.) Of other processes much studied today
Blodget had little or no conception: air mass
analysis was unknown to him; so were such
things as winter-storm dynamics, the role of
the Rocky Mountains in nurturing the formation
of the low pressure systems that contain
those storms, and the role of jet streams in guiding
storm movement.</p>

<p>The wealth of Great Plains climatological
data is now so great that it is difficult to provide
a coherent description of the climate of the
Plains. An unorthodox but perhaps useful approach
is to begin by noticing the dramatic
contrast in the frost-free period as one moves
northward from Texas. At San Angelo and Abilene,
for example, the frost-free period is about
230 days, but as one moves north the period
declines to 210 days in Amarillo; 174 days in
Garden City, Kansas; 160 days in North Platte,
Nebraska; 140 days in Bismarck, North Dakota;
and to between 100 and 120 days in southern
Alberta and Saskatchewan. The duration
of snow cover naturally mirrors this disparity.
North of the Black Hills, the ground is white
more than three months a year, but the ground
is white fewer than ten days annually south of a
line drawn from Roswell, New Mexico, eastward
through Plainview, Texas, Oklahoma
City, and Tulsa. (It is perhaps surprising, given
the duration of snow cover in the north and
the added fact that snow falls in the Dakotas
more than forty days a year, that total snowfall,
even in the Northern Plains, is not great by
continental standards: in the Dakotas, it averages
about thirty-two inches. In the south, of
course, accumulations are much less&#8211;hardly
an inch falls annually on the Edwards Plateau.)</p>

<figure n="egp.pe.001.02" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Blizzard, Allen, South Dakota, February 1946</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>This dramatic contrast in frost-free periods
can, however, exaggerate the differences between
the Northern and Southern Plains.
Granted, in winter the spread between daily
average temperatures in Edmonton and Amarillo
is fully 30&#186;F, but the temperature spread
between Edmonton and Amarillo in summer
is only 15&#186;F.and the record highs in those
two cities are less than 10&#186;F apart, which, one
may be surprised to learn, is about as far apart
as the highest temperatures recorded in
Amarillo and scorching Midland, only 200
miles to its south. Across the entire sweep of
the Plains, moreover, there are common
weather elements. Everywhere, days are sunnier
more often than they are cloudy: the total
sunshine at Regina, for example, exceeds
2,400 hours annually, which is far higher than
can be found anywhere else on the continent
at that latitude. There is relatively little fog on
the Plains, and average relative humidity in
the summer is lower than the average relative
humidity anywhere to the east. Another point
in common across the sweep of the Plains.
and a notorious one at that.is windiness: the
flow veers seasonally from a generally northerly
flow in January, especially in the Northern
Plains, to a generally southerly flow in
July, especially in the Southern Plains, when in
particular the wind flow is exceedingly strong.
The Plains are famous, too, for violent storms
and sudden weather changes. In May these are
classically associated with thunderstorms
and&#8211;particularly in Oklahoma&#8211;with tornadoes,
some fifty of which are reported annually
in that state alone, where they most
commonly form late in the afternoon or early
evening, then ominously meander in a generally
northeasterly path. In winter, the Plains
are associated with cold fronts sweeping south
and overnight lowering temperatures by fully
70&#186;F.</p>

<p>To this list of climatic elements that are
more uniform than disparate, one finally
must add precipitation, which by some measures
is the most important of the lot. There
can be few more arresting or compelling lines
on the North American map than that of the
sixteen-inch isohyet, which, like the neighboring
twenty-, twenty-four-, and twenty-eightinch
ones, runs almost straight from Canada
to Mexico. Only at the Rockies do the well-behaved
lines break up and turn into ovals
that encircle highland masses.</p>

<p>The precipitation that falls on the Plains is
well distributed for agriculture, with about
40 percent of the annual total occurring during
June, July, and August, and with only
about 10 percent occurring in December, January,
and February. The absolute levels of precipitation
on the Plains, however, were something
new for settlers from the east, where
equally dry climates are unknown, apart from
the agriculturally useless lands of northern
Canada. The consequences were tragic everywhere
on the Plains but perhaps more famously
in the south, where higher temperatures
raise evaporative potentials to 100 inches
a year or more, twice the figure at the Canadian
border.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Hydrology</head>

<p>The proportion of Great Plains precipitation
that returns directly to the atmosphere through
evaporation or transpiration is amazingly great:
South Dakota's Standing Rock Indian Reservation,
for example, receives very slightly more
than three million acre-feet of precipitation annually;
of that quantity, 95 percent&#8211;2.84 million
acre-feet&#8211;returns directly to the atmosphere.
Runoff from the Great Plains is therefore very
limited. Indeed, over most of the Plains hardly
more than one inch of precipitation runs off
annually, and on the High Plains and substantial
parts of the Northern Plains the figure is half
that. The rivers of the Plains are often reduced to
trickles. Granted, these trickles can turn on a
dime to raging torrents that wipe out bridges,
farms, and livelihoods, but by continental standards,
even the floods of the Great Plains are
small things and either very local or exotic, the
result of water coming from the Rockies.</p>

<p>Few rivers on the Plains can in fact resist the
tendency to flashiness. An exception must be
granted for Nebraska's Sandhills, where the
branches of the Loup River are recharged
by groundwater and remain remarkably constant.
A more typical example, however, would
be the Cimarron River near Fairview, Oklahoma.
The stream carries a mean annual flow
of 330 cubic feet of water per second, but 70
percent of the year its flow is less than 30 cubic
feet per second, and for only a quarter of the
year does its flow much exceed 200. In short,
one rarely sees the stream carrying its average
flow. Finding streams like these at moments of
average flow can be an exercise in itself, one
requiring planning: the North and South Saskatchewan
Rivers, for example, peak in June or
July, but their tributaries peak in April or May.
At first glance this seems anomalous, but the
tributaries depend on local snowmelt, while
the main streams depend on runoff coming
from distant mountains, where high elevations
imply a later date for snowmelt.</p>

<p>Most of the year, a visitor to a typical Great
Plains stream will be almost lost in a wide
floodplain dotted with thickets of cottonwood
and filled brim to brim with sand. Highway
bridges that come to these valleys are impressively
long, but if there are ten cantilever
sections to the bridge, chances are that water is
flowing under only one of them. The channel
below is continually being redefined: even in
periods of low flow one will hear splashes almost
by the minute. Looking up in expectation
of seeing an animal, instead one sees only
a lonely caving sandbank and a swirl of turbidity.
(Perhaps the rivers of the Plains are
siltier today than they were before the arrival
of farmers; in any event, the rivers of the Plains
rank today as the siltiest on the continent, save
only for those of the desert Southwest.)</p>

<p>The rivers of the Plains often mock the long
blue lines on maps and disappear altogether,
only reemerging miles downstream, as water
gently wells up from sandy streambeds. Some
portion of that stream flow, of course, percolates
underground. Once there, it is by
no means forgotten, however, for across the
sweep of the Great Plains groundwater is a
subject of the keenest interest. It has been so
from the earliest period of white settlement,
when the windmill became one of the chief
icons of the Plains. It remains so today, when
people are concerned not only for the quantity
of available groundwater but also with its
quality.</p>

<p>The most productive wells on the Plains are
generally found along watercourses, but the
Plains are famous for also having vast aquifers.
Individual wells here may not be as productive
as those in valleys, but these aquifers
in aggregate yield huge quantities of water that
can be extracted great distances from any substantial
source of surface water. The Dakota
sandstone, which takes its name from Dakota
County in the northeasternmost corner of
Nebraska, is a good example: indeed it is
a classic case of an aquifer containing water
under su.cient pressure to produce an artesian
flow many miles from the point where the
water sank underground.</p>

<p>The best known of the Plains aquifers is the
Ogallala, which was named in the 1890s by
N. H. Darton of the U.S. Geological Survey.
Together with several smaller hydraulically
connected formations that with it comprise
the Great Plains Aquifer, the Ogallala covers
some 177,000 square miles, across which the
aquifer is draped like a blanket. Its saturated
thickness varies from less than 100 feet in the
southern Texas Panhandle to more than 1,000
feet in the Nebraska Sandhills. Some 22 billion
acre-feet of sandy material are saturated in the
Ogallala with 3 billion acre-feet of water. Twothirds
of the water is in lucky Nebraska. Water
enters the aquifer at a rate averaging about six
inches annually, but this recharge rate depends
on soil porosity and varies from almost nothing
in parts of Texas to several feet annually in
sandy parts of Nebraska and Kansas. (Another
way of looking at this is to note that 80 percent
of the total recharge occurs north of a line
between Colorado Springs and Hays, Kansas.)
The water in the aquifer normally moves eastward
and downhill at about one foot per day.
Some of it returns to rivers, which generally
flow below the local water table; only a few
streams&#8211;the Cimarron, for example&#8211;flow
above the water table and contribute to aquifer
recharge. More serious groundwater loss,
however, has been suffered at the hands of
farmers, particularly in the southern half of the
aquifer. Willard D. Johnson of the U.S. Geological
Survey warned early in the twentieth
century that widespread irrigation of the High
Plains was not sustainable, but his prescription
of stock farming was ignored. Texas has been
particularly hard hit, for it has pumped more
water from the Ogallala than any other state,
even though it began with only about a tenth of
the aquifer's stored water. The quality of Ogallala
water has changed too; wherever the reservoir
underlies farmland rather than rangeland,
the water has grown increasingly alkaline.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Biogeography</head>

<p>In the time of Lewis and Clark, such rain and
snow as fell on the eastern side of the Plains
supported a veritable meadow: grasses six feet
high, set among deciduous trees like oak and
hickory. To the west, typically at an elevation
of 2,000 feet, that virgin prairie gave way to
a steppe. Trees were scarce here, except for
stream course cottonwoods, and the grass was
short&#8211;unless one dug up the roots and found
that the six inches of buffalo grass that one
saw above ground capped a tangle of roots six
feet deep.</p>

<p>By 1880, enough was known of America's
vegetation for Charles S. Sargent to map
America's forested regions with high accuracy.
Sargent said little about the sea of grass that is
the Great Plains, but he commented on the
difference between bottomland forests on the
eastern and western sides of the Plains: oaks,
walnuts, ash, and box elders disappeared one
by one, he wrote, until only cottonwoods survived
beyond the 100th meridian. Like many
other students, Canadian as well as American,
Sargent was well aware, too, of the complex
dynamics of this grassland, particularly on the
eastern margin, where trees quickly invaded if
fire was suppressed. The importance of fire in
grassland modification, relative to soil moisture
and other factors, has been the subject of
debate ever since.</p>

<p>Twenty years after Sargent's work, which
was published as a monograph accompanying
the Tenth Census, C. Hart Merriam of the U.S.
Biological Survey published the first map of
what we today would call ecoregions. The
terms he employed, such as the "austral life
zone," are little used today, but the concept of
an ecoregion is still indispensable. Other key
ecological concepts also arose in the Great
Plains in the early years of this century. The
ideas of plant succession and climax communities,
for example, were developed in the
Great Plains by Frederick Clements, a Nebraskan
by birth and training.</p>

<p>In 1923 Homer Shantz and Raphael Zon
published their great map of the natural vegetation
of the United States. The map showed a
continent forested on the east but coming, as
one moved westward, to an oak-hickory forest
whose western margin ran from central Texas
through the Ozarks to central Michigan. Immediately
west of that forest in Texas, and extending
to the Pecos River and the High Plains,
lay a desert savanna, with mesquite, but from
the southwestern corner of Oklahoma due
north to Nebraska (where it curved west around
the Sandhills and then resumed a northward
course) lay a line marking the western edge of a
tallgrass prairie, bluestems chiefly, into which
the oak-hickory forest penetrated along stream
courses. At an elevation of about 2,000 feet the
vegetation changed to much shorter grama and
buffalo grasses. Shantz, who was responsible for
the part of the map showing grasslands, recognized
that the line between tall and short grass is
not sharp and depends in part upon soil and soil
moisture conditions.</p>

<p>Since the 1920s, the study of Great Plains
vegetation has focused in large part on getting
a better understanding of the distribution of
tall and short grasses and their relationship to
forests. Much of this work, perhaps inevitably,
has led to finer and finer subdivisions of the
generalities laid out by Shantz. In 1964, for
example, A. W. Kuchler prepared a map of potential
natural vegetation that is widely used
today and which, following Clements rather
than Shantz, recognized transitional categories
on either side of the tallgrass prairie.
Kuchler saw the eastern part of the tallgrass as
a mosaic of bluestem and oak-hickory forest,
while the tallgrass prairie proper occupied
only a meridional swath reaching from Winnipeg
to Topeka, with arms stretching into
northwest Iowa and the Nebraska Sandhills.
Farther west, Kuchler recognized a bluestem
prairie mixed with wheatgrass in the north
and grama grass on the south; still farther west
lay the shortgrass proper. Kuchler subdivided
it latitudinally, with grama and buffalo grasses
dominating as far north as Nebraska; to the
north lay a domain of wheatgrass in the Dakotas
and buffalo grass in still drier Montana.</p>

<p>Kuchler did not map Canada, but the same
species of western wheatgrass and grama grass
extend north to an encircling arc of aspen savanna,
a parkland that itself grades into an
aspen-spruce forest or, at the edge of the
Rockies, into a spruce-pine forest. As in the
United States, forest invasion of the grassland
&#8211;in this case with aspen advancing by suckering
rather than by seed&#8211;occurs whenever fire
is suppressed, and the small amount of tallgrass
prairie that once existed in the Red River
Valley of the North has in this way been lost
almost entirely. Although shortgrass species
such as buffalo grass are now common in the
driest parts of the Canadian Great Plains, their
dominance appears to be the result of overgrazing
in historic times. The potential natural
vegetation, in other words, appears to contain
taller species like western wheatgrass.</p>

<p>The story of plant geography in the Great
Plains can hardly avoid taking notice of the
arrival of farming and ranching, which has
transformed the vegetation of the Plains, both
to our benefit and our loss. Some introduced
species are welcomed by farmers and ranchers
&#8211;brome and wheatgrasses in the Northern
Plains are a case in point. Others have become
serious problems, among them leafy spurge in
the north and prickly pear and eastern red
cedar in the south. Today, as a consequence,
one must hunt to locate sites where the vegetation
may be even approximately virginal. Sites
like the Konza Prairie near Manhattan, Kansas,
thus acquire special significance.</p>

<p>The impact of European settlement on the
animals of the Great Plains was perhaps even
more dramatic. Recent research suggests that
earlier accounts may have seriously overestimated
bison numbers at the start of the nineteenth
century and that the real number&#8211;
perhaps 30 million rather than the 60 million
or more often reported&#8211;may have been at a
momentary and unsustainable peak. Still, the
primeval bison herds beg comparison with
the herbivore populations of East Africa, and
their reduction to fewer than a thousand animals
by 1889 is therefore all the more appalling.
The pronghorn, once perhaps as numerous
as the bison and yet killed off until fewer
than 25,000 animals remained, supply almost
as gruesome a tale of human destruction. Today,
thanks to sustained efforts, the pronghorn
population has risen to more than a million
animals, perhaps half of them in Wyoming.</p>

<p>It is worth remembering, of course, that the
advent of European settlement was not always
so devastating. The rattlesnake is not yet endangered,
despite a century or more of methodical
killing. Some 250 species of grasshoppers
still reside on the Plains, to which most of
them are naturally restricted, and few night
sounds can be as familiar on the Plains as that
of the cicada. White settlement even proved a
boon for some animal species, at least temporarily.
The population of the greater prairie
chicken, for example, exploded with the introduction
of grain farming. After a peak about
1880, it began to decline with the loss of wetlands
and hayfields and with competition
from introduced species such as the ringnecked
pheasant, a native of China. Chicken
populations have recovered enough to sustain
legalized hunting today in several states, particularly
Kansas and Nebraska, where prairie
chicken numbers may exceed those of two
centuries ago.</p>

<p>A final point to remember is that a neatly
separated discussion of plant and animal geography
masks the actual and complex relationships
that exist between those organisms.
Much effort of late has gone into studying the
effect on grassland of intensive but short-duration
bison grazing. Smaller animals, too,
have influenced the vegetation of the Plains. A
good example is the once astronomically numerous
prairie dog, which was discovered for
science by Meriwether Lewis. We ourselves
play not only a major but often an unconscious
role in altering these several populations.
The shelterbelts that were so widely
planted in the 1930s, for example, are now
commonly dying of old age. Farmers tend not
to replant them but instead to bulldoze and
grub them out. One consequence is that local
populations of jackrabbits, pheasants, deer,
and squirrels are losing habitat. In the absence
of data, one can only wonder how many species
are declining as unintended consequences
of our actions.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Soils</head>

<p>People in an overwhelmingly urban society
naturally have a hard time grasping subjects
like topography and climatology or geology
and biogeography, for all these things are increasingly
removed from daily life. They have
an almost impossible time, however, trying to
muster any interest in soil and soil geography,
for these are subjects inescapably linked with
pejorative terms like dirt. Like all soils, however,
the soils of the Great Plains reflect all the
other elements of the physical environment,
which can at least in large part be deduced
from the crumbly or sandy, moist or dry,
warm or cold soil mantle that rests on the
earth.</p>

<p>The grass of the Great Plains, after all, is
responsible for the dark color that is one of the
two diagnostic traits of Great Plains soils. The
other diagnostic trait of these soils arises from
the climate of the Great Plains and is an alkaline
layer, usually calcium carbonate, which
occurs at the lowest level in the soil that is
seasonally saturated. The two traits overlap.
Dark color extends well east of the Great
Plains, but the alkaline layer is typical of arid
climates and extends well to the west. Hence
the logic underlying the statement of Curtis F.
Marbut, a pioneer soil scientist, that the Great
Plains is simply that part of the country where
these two traits overlap.</p>

<p>In a monograph published in 1935 as a part
of the <hi rend="smallcaps">USDA</hi>'s great <hi rend="italic">Atlas of American Agriculture</hi>,
Marbut went on to develop this idea: he
pointed out that there is an inverse relationship
between light soil color and deep layers of
carbonate accumulation. The darkest soils,
that is, are found in the wetter east, where the
zone of carbonate accumulation lies at a depth
of about six feet. Farther west, soil colors are
lighter because there is less soil moisture and
therefore less organic matter. Here, however,
the zone of alkaline accumulation is much
closer to the surface. On the High Plains, it is so
well developed that it forms an impervious
layer of so-called caliche. Marbut mapped parent
material and on this basis distinguished
three groups of soils based on where they were
formed: glacial deposits, windborne deposits,
and from bedrock&#8211;the latter lying chiefly in
Kansas and the non-panhandle parts of Oklahoma
and Texas. Yet when Marbut came to
formally classify the soils of the Great Plains,
he chose to ignore parent material and instead
focus on those two diagnostic criteria we have
already noted.</p>

<p>The eastern edge of the Great Plains thus
became for Marbut the line beyond which
there was enough precipitation that soil moisture
percolated through the entire soil profile;
there was no permanently dry zone here, and
therefore no zone of carbonate accumulation.
West of that line, however, one came to what
Marbut, using Russian nomenclature, called
the chernozems: black soils, though much
thinner than the chernozems of Russia. Marbut
distinguished a belt of these chernozems
centered roughly along the 100th meridian from
the eastern Dakotas through central Kansas,
western Oklahoma, and Texas as far south as the
Rio Grande. East of these chernozems generally
lay forested and acidic podsols in the north and
"prairie soils" to the south&#8211;soils formed under
grass but so humid that the soils were degraded.
West of the chernozems lay lighter-colored
"dark brown" soils that graded on the west into
patches of "brown" soils, which occurred in the
driest parts of the Plains.</p>

<p>In Canada, soil taxonomists still use this
nomenclature, so that most Canadian prairie
soils are mapped as chernozems in the wetter
and encircling savanna but dark brown and
brown in the drier core along the international
boundary. In the United States, however,
the soil taxonomy used by Marbut was
replaced in 1960 by another system, one that
introduced an entire lexicon of neologisms
and which is therefore exceedingly difficult for
all but experts to use comfortably.</p>

<p>This new classification system distinguishes
between Great Plains soils neither by parent
material nor by color but chiefly by soil temperature
and moisture. The Great Plains soils
of the United States are thus now classed
chiefly as mollisols, or soils formed under a
cover of grasses and forbs. Subdivisions are
then made on the basis of soil temperature, so
that the soils of the Dakotas, where the mean
annual soil temperature is below 47&#186;F, are recognized
as borolls, while moister soils to the
south are recognized generally as udolls or, in
Texas, where mean annual soil temperature
exceeds 72&#186;F, as thermic udolls. Further subdivision
is made on the basis of soil moisture.
East of the Missouri Coteau, for example, the
soil is recognized as a udic boroll, while to the
west the soil is classified as a typic boroll. Similarly,
the soils of the Central Plains are divided
into udolls when they have sufficient
moisture for plant growth much of the year;
where moisture is lacking for long periods, the
soils are labeled as ustolls; where, as in southeastern
Colorado, soils are usually dry and
therefore low in organic matter, they are
called ustic aridosols. Some soils, lacking profile
horizons, are mapped instead as entisols:
the most extensive areas are the Sandhills and
the gray soils developed on the thin glacial
debris of southeastern Montana.</p>

<p>It is easy for the layman to despair in the
face of such verbal arcana, but there is one
final point about soils that is easy to grasp.
Like the groundwater and vegetation of the
Plains, the soils of the Great Plains have not
fared well in the last century. Estimates are
that soil losses under range conditions on the
Plains today average two tons per acre annually,
while losses on cropland are twice that
or more. The Southern and Central Plains
have been hurt most, both by wind erosion on
the High Plains south of the Arkansas River
and by severe sheet erosion and gullying in the
deep loess south of the Sandhills and in the
once extensive cotton lands of Oklahoma.
Nearly a century after Willard Johnson's warnings,
the question of proper land use remains
an open one in the Great Plains, and for all the
work of the Soil Conservation Service since its
creation in the 1930s, one can still drive for mile
after mile across Oklahoma and see the deep
and unhealed red scars etched by farmers a
lifetime ago.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Significance</head>

<p>How, in sum, are we to comprehend this
place? Keep the question simple. Forget about
people. Forget about roads and railroads,
wires, cables, and pipelines. Forget about
towns and cities, wells for water and oil and
gas, cultivated fields, and the sorry pastures
that have been grazed bare by generations of
cattle that have been confined behind endless
miles of wretched fence lines. What are we to
make of this place as God created it?</p>

<p>A traditional answer would have us see the
Plains as a place of economic opportunity, a
resource. Such an outlook kept several generations
of scientists at work, supported by public
funding. Another answer, however, and
one more relevant to most people today, can
be inferred from the overtones of the question
itself. From this perspective, the Great Plains
is best comprehended as a place too magnificent
for fetters. Unique to the continent in
always open and seemingly endless vistas, the
Plains is a place to teach us how it feels to
be free.</p>

<p>One might think back to Josiah Gregg, who
in the 1830s crossed the Plains time and again
between the Missouri River and the then Mexican
town of Santa Fe. Gregg concluded his
famous <hi rend="italic">Commerce of the Prairies</hi> on an ironic
note. Tongue in cheek, he wrote that the reports
were accurate: the Great Plains was indeed
dangerous. Gregg went on to explain,
however, that the danger lay not in Indians
but in the freedom of the place: like a magic
elixir, the air of the Plains rendered civilized
men unfit for the East&#8211;its towns full of narrow
streets, its houses full of airless rooms, its
people confined by girdles and neckties.</p>

<p>We have come a long way in taming the
Plains. Perhaps Josiah Gregg was better off not
having seen the fences, better off not having
heard the radio stations with their incessant
wheedling, better off not having smelled the
feedlots that have sprung up so many places.
But the Great Plains is by no means defeated.
The skies remain as infinite in the day as skies
elsewhere can be only at night. Muddy, modest,
quietly occupied streams continue to find
their lonely ways across the immensity. Grass
continues to hiss before the steady wind.
Geese still fly over this place; so do white pelicans
en route from Great Salt Lake to the Gulf.
Scissor-tailed flycatchers and roadrunners still
call the Southern Plains home; other birds like
meadowlarks and bobolinks, dickcissels and
American kestrals are still commonplace. This
is still a very physical place, huge enough that
the human drama on it can shrink to insignificance.
We wish to be important, influential,
and so such a thought is not one we welcome.
Yet there is comfort in it nonetheless, for no
actor on earth could help but be thrilled by
the prospect of such a huge stage.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">WATER</hi>: <ref n="egp.wat.009">Floods</ref>; <ref n="egp.wat.018">Ogallala Aquifer</ref>; <ref n="egp.wat.027">Rivers</ref>.</p>
</div2>

<closer>
<signed>Bret Wallach<lb/>
University of Oklahoma</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Atwood, Wallace W. <title level="m">The Physiographic Provinces of North
America</title>. New York: Ginn, 1940.</bibl> <bibl>Bostock, H. S. "Physiographic
Regions of Canada," Map 1254A of the Geological
Survey of Canada, 1970.</bibl> <bibl>Fenneman, Nevin M. <title level="m">Physiography
of Western United States</title>. New York: McGraw-Hill,
1931.</bibl> <bibl>Flores, Dan. "Bison Ecology and Bison Diplomacy:
The Southern Plains from 1800 to 1850." <title level="j">The Journal of
American History</title> 78 (1991): 465-85.</bibl> <bibl>Great Plains Flora
Association. <title level="m">Flora of the Great Plains</title>. Lawrence: University
Press of Kansas, 1986.</bibl> <bibl>Hammond, Edwin. "Analysis
of Properties in Land Form Geography: Application to
Broad-scale Land Form Mapping." <title level="m">Annals</title>, Association of
American Geographers 54 (1964): 11-19.</bibl> <bibl>Kuchler, August
Wilhelm. <title level="m">Potential Natural Vegetation of the Coterminous
United States</title>. New York: American Geographical Society,
1964.</bibl> <bibl>U.S. Department of Agriculture. <title level="m">Atlas of American
Agriculture</title>. Washington <hi rend="smallcaps">DC</hi>: Government Printing Office,
1936.</bibl> <bibl>U.S. Department of Agriculture. <title level="m">Climate and Man</title>.
Washington, <hi rend="smallcaps">DC</hi>: Government Printing Office, 1941.</bibl> <bibl>U.S.
Geological Survey. <title level="m">The National Atlas of the United States
of America</title>. Washington <hi rend="smallcaps">DC</hi>: Government Printing Office,
1970.</bibl> <bibl>Visher, Stephen Argent. <title level="m">Climatic Atlas of the United
States</title>. Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1954.</bibl> <bibl>Weaver,
J. E. <title level="m">Prairie Plants and Their Environment</title>. Lincoln: University
of Nebraska Press, 1968.</bibl>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>