<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.rel.051">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Vision Quest</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Steven Foster</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.rel.051</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Foster, Steven">Steven Foster</author>. <title level="a">"Vision Quest."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">759-760</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-19</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">VISION QUEST</head>

<p>For thousands of years, the nations of the
Great Plains celebrated their interdependency
with nature in ceremonies such as the vision
quest. They accounted the environment that
sustained them to be sacred. They saw how the
buffalo gave itself to the people, how the grass
gave itself to buffalo, how the rain gave itself to
grass.how the people, like all their earthly
relations, gave themselves back to the vast
Plains that sustained them. They called the
dark earth "Mother" and the great sun "Father,"
and they revered the Great Creator, not
as some abstract principle but as the palpable
design, function, and constant presence of
their environment.</p>

<p>Hence, the great sun, the dark earth, and the
endless horizon, particularly as viewed from the
traditional precincts of Mateo Tepee (Devils
Tower), the Black Hills, and the Northern
Rockies, became the Great Creator's initiation
ground, the passageway for individuals in life
transition. Their rites involved spiritual education
that was fundamental to their existence. If,
indeed, they lived in the home of the Great
Creator, then clearly they would consider the
significant growth events of their lives to be occasions
for ceremony and spiritual edification.</p>

<p>Largely "confirmatory" in function (marking
the attainment of changed social status),
these rites followed the classic anthropological
definition of rites of passage: severance—preparation
to leave the former life and go into
a sacred time and space, including rites of purification
in a sweat lodge; threshold—existence
(often three or four days and nights) alone in a
sacred world of taboo and self-abnegation,
where the individual sacrificed the self to a
greater whole and attained "medicine" or visionary
power; and incorporation&#8211;return to a
council of elders and subsequent reintegration
within the community as individuals with
changed social status.</p>

<p>The objective of the threshold, or mountaintop,
experience, was a medicine vision of
benefit to the people as a whole. Without food,
water, companionship, shelter, or defenses
against predators, sometimes in great pain
from self-inflicted wounds, the body longed
for spiritual answers. The sacred ancestors sent
dreams to console and inspire, and the Great
Spirit provided "allies" or "helpers." When the
initiates returned from this time with the Great
Creator and the sacred ancestors, they were
considered to have confirmed visionary intent.
If the intent were not confirmed, the candidates
would often return again&#8211;and again&#8211;
until signs from nature indicated that the quest
had been consummated. Thus, the community
was blessed by the spiritual growth of its
members, and every vision took its place in the
legendary annals of the people.</p>

<p>Many forms of what, in the English language,
has become known as the vision quest
were practiced among the people of the Great
Plains. Traditions were passed down from
medicine men to their apprentices for many
generations. The most widely published traditions
were recorded by observant Europeans
when medicine chiefs were willing to teach
them the old ways. Black Elk's <title level="m">Sacred Pipe</title> (as
told to Joseph Epes Brown) contains a classic
depiction of the seven rites of the Oglala Sioux,
including a thorough description of the <hi rend="italic">hanblecheyapi</hi>,
or "crying for a vision." Similar noble
rites existed among the Crows, Blackfoot,
Cheyennes, Arapahos, Pawnees, Kiowas, Crees,
and many other peoples, including the Native
nations of the Northwest Coast, Great Basin,
Eastern Woodlands, and Southwest.</p>

<p>This same ritual vision-quest archetype
is known by many other names in cultures
throughout the world. Although this tradition
has declined in the face of modern life, the rite
is still practiced among the Indigenous people
of the Great Plains.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">NATIVE AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.na.102">Sacred Geography</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Steven Foster<lb/>
School of Lost Borders<lb/>
Big Pine, California</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Brown, Joseph Epes. <title level="m">The Sacred Pipe: Black Elk's Account
of the Seven Rites of the Oglala Sioux</title>. Norman: University
of Oklahoma Press, 1953.</bibl> <bibl>Mails, Thomas E. <title level="m">The Mystic
Warriors of the Plains: The Culture, Arts, Crafts, and Religion
of the Plains Indians</title>. New York: Mallard Press, 1972.</bibl>
<bibl>Van Gennep, Arnold. <title level="m">The Rites of Passage</title>. Chicago: University
of Chicago Press, 1972.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>