<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.pg.027 SYSTEM "egp.pg.027.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.pg.027">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Forty-Ninth Parallel</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Randy William Widdis</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.pg.027</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Widdis, Randy William">Randy William Widdis</author>. <title level="a">"Forty-Ninth Parallel."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">665-666</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-29</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">FORTY-NINTH PARALLEL</head>

<figure n="egp.pg.027" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Earthen boundary marker at the forty-ninth parallel</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>At just under 740 miles, the forty-ninth parallel
separating the Prairie Provinces from the
Northern Plains states is part of the longest
continuous unguarded boundary line in the
world. The forty-ninth parallel bisects a borderland
region characterized by physical uniformity
in its grassland ecosystem and continental
climate and by socioeconomic affinity
in its predominantly rural and agrarian economy,
low population density, and geographical
isolation from markets. The kinds of interactions
taking place over time, as well as
similar geographical conditions, have added
to the synthesis within this borderland region.
North-south intermingling occurred well before
European settlement, as the American
and Canadian fur trading systems converged
within a frontier context in which the border,
first established in an 1818 treaty between the
United States and Great Britain, was relatively
meaningless. This unsurveyed line, stretching
from the Lake of the Woods in southwestern
Ontario to the Rocky Mountains and later extended
to the Pacific Coast, was ignored by the
buffalo and by the whites, Native peoples, and
M&#233;tis who hunted them. Further integration
in the nineteenth century was ensured by the
development of north-south trade links between
the Hudson's Bay Company and St.
Paul and Chicago capitalists who competed
for control of the Northern Plains and saw the
monopoly of the British firm in Canada as an
impediment to their imperialist schemes. Fort
Benton, Montana, located at the head of navigation
on the Missouri River and functioning
as the gateway to the Whoop-Up Trail to Fort
Macleod and Calgary, dominated the commerce
of the Canadian Plains for twenty-five
years (1858-83).</p>

<p>Even after the boundary line was delineated
in 1874 by a joint British and American commission,
north–south flows continued, primarily
in terms of goods and then people. Yet
immediately the boundary acquired significance,
as it became the focus for changing relations
taking place within the borderland region.
It cut across the hunting grounds of
Native peoples and Métis and erased their former
territories. Ironically, these groups viewed
it as a "Medicine Line" because it represented
refuge from persecution by whites on the other
side. During the 1870s the whiskey trade with
Natives caused tension along the border and
was used by Canadian nationalists to fuel anti-
American sentiment. In this context the fortyninth
parallel came to be viewed by Canadians
as a "shield" to America's "manifest destiny,"
while for most Americans, the border shared
with Canada was too far removed to acquire
much notice at all.</p>

<p>At the beginning of the twentieth century
the Prairies held the promise of the "Last Best
West" for Canadians, Europeans, and a considerable
number of Americans, while the
Northern Plains was increasingly viewed as a
remote place, a region to be bypassed by those
seeking opportunity in the Far West. While
integration within the Northern Plains and
Prairie borderland region continued to occur
because of a common hinterland, migration
flows, the diffusion of technology and ideas,
and the evolution of capital relations across
the border, the east-west flow of trade and
migration into the region paralleling the Canadian
Pacific Railway and the Great Northern
Railroad served to form national ties that
counterbalanced the continuing north-south
connections. And even though the border was
obscured by the migration of settlers from
eastern North America and Europe who carried
with them an array of social and economic
affiliations, their different settlement
histories, loyalties, political cultures, urban
systems, and core-periphery relations ensured
divergence between the Northern Plains and
Prairies.</p>

<p>The forty-ninth parallel has served as a major
symbol of the predominant east–west
development in both countries, and for Canadians
it takes on added importance as a territorial
axis, defined in terms of their relationship
with the United States. In this context, this
artificial line has become a matrix for Canadian
culture, at least an Anglo-Canadian culture,
which is by its nature regional in composition
as well as in origin. Today, however,
the forty-ninth parallel as a spatial metaphor
has become blurred in a world where the forces
of new technologies, globalization, and "timespace
compression" have challenged the traditional
Canadian view of the border as a territorial
symbol of sovereignty and separation.
In this new global environment, place as defined
by borders is no longer the essential element of
identity. Regional differences are diminishing in
the face of homogeneous economic forces and a
global culture, as is the importance of cartographic
lines and compass points that enable
inhabitants of this region, regardless of which
side of the forty-ninth they inhabit, to orient
themselves in time and space.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">EUROPEAN AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ea.032">Settlement Patterns, Canada</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">IMAGES AND ICONS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ii.038">Last Best West</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">INDUSTRY</hi>: <ref n="egp.ind.041"><hi rend="smallcaps">NAFTA</hi></ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">TRANSPORTATION</hi>: <ref n="egp.tra.042">Whoop-Up Trail</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Randy William Widdis<lb/>
University of Regina</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Lecker, Robert, ed. <title level="m">Borderlands: Essays in Canadian-
American Relations</title>. Toronto: <hi rend="smallcaps">ECW</hi> Press, 1991.</bibl> <bibl>Sharp, Paul
F. "The American Farmer and the 'Last Best West.'" <title level="j">Agricultural
History</title> 21 (1947): 65–74.</bibl> <bibl>Widdis, Randy W. <title level="m">With
Scarcely a Ripple: Anglo-Canadian Migration into the
United States and Western Canada, 1880–1920</title>. Montreal:
McGill-Queen's University Press, 1998.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>