<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.arc.035">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Native American Traditional Architecture</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Steven R. Holen</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.arc.035</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Holen, Steven R.">Steven R. Holen</author>. <title level="a">"Native American Traditional Architecture."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">88-89</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-13</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">NATIVE AMERICAN TRADITIONAL ARCHITECTURE</head>

<p>Native Americans were living two distinct lifestyles
in the Great Plains at the time of first
contact with European Americans. Tribes
along the eastern edges of the Plains were
practicing a semisedentary lifestyle, relying on
agriculture for part of their subsistence. Tribes
farther west were leading a more mobile lifestyle
based on hunting and gathering. These
two adaptations are reflected in distinctive
patterns of architecture.</p>

<p>The agriculturists developed more permanent
structures. These included earth lodges
in the Central Plains and farther north along
the Missouri River. The prototype earth lodge
was probably first developed as an adaptation
to a more northerly climate by northward-moving
ancestral Pawnee and Arikara groups
around <hi rend="smallcaps">A.D.</hi> 1200. This architectural style then
spread to neighboring groups, including the
Mandans, Hidatsas, Omahas, Poncas, Otoes,
and Kansas by the eighteenth century.</p>

<p>The Pawnee/Arikara earth lodge was constructed
by first digging a circular pit thirty to
fifty feet in diameter and eighteen inches deep.
The central framework consisted of four to
eight large center posts, which held up the
rafters of the domed roof. An outer circular
row of posts held the lower end of the rafters.
The rafters were covered with willow
branches, a layer of grass, and a thick layer
of earth. The earth covering and subsurface
floor made the structure easy to heat in the
winter and allowed it to stay cool in the summer.
The circular roof had a central opening
at the peak to allow smoke to exit. An entranceway
extended to the east for several feet.
The earth lodge was home to from thirty to
fifty people, depending on the size of the
structure. Larger structures were also used for
religious ceremonies.</p>

<p>Pawnee earth-lodge symbolism was highly
developed. The dome of the roof was the sky,
and the circular wall of the earth lodge was the
horizon. The house was divided symbolically
into four quadrants, each with a center post
represented by a symbolic color, wood, animal,
and weather pattern. The house was divided
into the male east half and the female
west half. The west half of the lodge was symbolized
by the Evening Star and contained the
sacred altar with a bison skull and the sacred
bundle with its ears of Mother Corn hanging
above. The east half was symbolized by the
Morning Star, the god of light, fire, and war.
Each morning when the Morning Star rose in
the eastern sky it shot beams of light through
the entranceway across the lodge to light the
fire, symbolizing the first union of the Morning
Star with the Evening Star in an act of cosmic
procreation. The earth lodge also acted as
an astronomical observatory for the village
priests. Observations of star positions were
made through the central smoke hole, and
each of the eighteen to twenty outer wall posts
and the four center posts was associated with a
star.</p>

<p>On the Southern Plains, the Wichitas, Hasinais,
and Caddos built conical-shaped grass
lodges with double-curve profiles and wooden
frames. Two kinds of grasses were used in constructing
these dwellings: the external roof
was thatched with coarse Prairie grasses, while
the interior walls were sealed over with softer
grasses from riverbanks. The walls rested on
dozens of poles that were bent and bound together
at the top. This structure in turn leaned
against an interior ring of posts and beams.
The frame, which could be sixty feet in diameter,
was tightened with horizontal sapling
stringers. The grass lodge could be transformed
into a cool summer dwelling by exposing
the lower ribs. Traditionally, the grass
lodges had no smoke holes; instead, the smoke
seeped through the grass roofs.</p>

<p>The tipi was used from the Prairie Provinces
to the Southern Plains. The tipi is an inverted
cone, steeper on the windward side, with an
off-center smoke hole at the top. Overall, the
floor plan is subcircular. Two types of tipi architecture
are recognized: a four-pole framework
was more common on the Northern
Plains among groups like the Sarcees, Blackfoot,
and Crows, and a three-pole variety was
more common on the Southern and Central
Plains among the Kiowas, Apaches, Arapahos,
Lakotas, and Cheyennes. The agricultural
groups on the eastern Plains also used the
three-pole variety when hunting bison.</p>

<p>Covering for the conical-pole framework
was originally made of tanned bison hides
sewn together. Before the advent of the horse,
when dogs pulled the travois made of tipi
poles and loaded with the tipi cover and other
belongings, six to ten bison hides were used in
the average tipi. Later, horses allowed larger
tipis to be moved. Canvas began to replace
bison hides for covering the tipi in the late
nineteenth century. Some tipi covers were
painted to represent events of importance in
the owner's life, including a defining vision. In
most societies the tipis were owned by the
men but were constructed, assembled, and
disassembled by the women. Tipi poles were
generally lodgepole pine on the Central and
Northern Plains, with red cedar more common
on the Southern Plains.</p>

<p>The Plains Indians utilized several types of
temporary or specialized structures, the most
famous of which was the Sun Dance lodge.
The centerpiece of the Sun Dance lodge was a
forked cottonwood trunk, which directed the
dancers' focus toward the sky and the deity.
From the center pole, sapling rafters radiated
to a circular fence forty to fifty feet in diameter.
The side fence and sometimes the rafters
were covered with leafy branches. The interior
design was dominated by a low, circular barrier
of brushes that separated the dancers
from the altar, fire pit, drummers, and singers
in the middle. Like the earth lodges, grass
lodges, and tipi, the Sun Dance lodge opened
to the east, toward the rising sun.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">RELIGION</hi>: <ref n="egp.rel.046">Sun Dance</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Steven R. Holen<lb/>
University of Nebraska State Museum<lb/>
</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Nabokov, Peter, and Robert Easton. <title level="m">Native American Architecture</title>.
New York: Oxford University Press, 1989.</bibl> <bibl>Weltfish,
Gene. <title level="m">The Lost Universe</title>. Lincoln: University of Nebraska
Press, 1997.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>