<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.pd.061">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Woodsworth, James Shaver (1874-1942)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Mark R. Ellis</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.pd.061</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Ellis, Mark R.">Mark R. Ellis</author>. <title level="a">"Woodsworth, James Shaver (1874-1942)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">728</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-07</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">WOODSWORTH, JAMES SHAVER (1874-1942)</head>

<p>Methodist minister, politician, and social reformer,
James Shaver Woodsworth was born
on July 29, 1874, near Toronto, Ontario. He
moved with his family to the Great Plains in
1882 when his Methodist minister father took
a new position in Winnipeg. Woodsworth followed
his father into the ministry; he was ordained
in 1896 and worked for several years as
a circuit rider in the Manitoba Plains. In 1899
he traveled to Oxford, England, where he
studied for two years and worked in settlement
houses in the slums of East London. The
extreme poverty and dire living conditions he
witnessed had a profound impact on the minister;
thereafter he became a proponent of the
"Social Gospel" and strived to improve the
living conditions of the poor. By 1904 he was
back in the Great Plains, working with immigrants
in the slums of Winnipeg's North End.
For almost ten years he operated a settlement
house called the All Peoples Mission. He also
wrote extensively on the plight of poor immigrants
and the working class, producing two
books, <title level="m">Strangers within Our Gates</title> (1909) and
<title level="m">My Neighbor</title> (1911).</p>

<p>World War I marked a turning point in
Woodsworth's career. As a staunch pacifist, he
opposed Canadian involvement in the war
and spoke openly about his views. He particularly
despised the draft and the participation
of Methodist ministers as recruiters. Because
of his vocal opposition, Woodsworth
lost his government job and, unable to find
work as a minister in Winnipeg, was forced to
move his family to Vancouver. There he became
became increasingly more politicized, as he
worked on the docks, joined the longshoremen's
union, and wrote for labor newspapers.
In June 1919, while visiting Winnipeg, he was
arrested for writing "seditious" editorials during
the Winnipeg General Strike. Woodsworth's
arrest and his widely read coverage
and criticism of the government's handling of
the strike boosted his popularity among Canada's
working class. In 1921 he was elected to
Canada's House of Commons as a member of
Manitoba's Independent Labour Party. As a
legislator, Woodsworth became one of Canada's
leading social reformers; among other
reforms, he helped create Canada's Old-Age
Pension Plan. In 1932 he helped form the Cooperative
Commonwealth Federation (forerunner
to the New Democratic Party), a political
party comprised largely of labor, farmer,
and socialist groups from western Canada. He
served as the party's chair and its parliamentary
leader until his death.</p>

<p>World War II was Woodsworth's final political
battle. Once again, he opposed Canadian
involvement, and in 1939 he was the only
member of the House of Commons to vote
against a declaration of war. Despite Woodsworth's
opposition to the war, he remained
party chairman and was elected in 1940 to another
term in the House of Commons. Weakened
by ill health, however, Woodsworth returned
with his wife to the family home in
Vancouver, where he died on March 21, 1942.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</hi>: <ref n="egp.pg.014">Cooperative Commonwealth Federation</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Mark R. Ellis<lb/>
University of Nebraska at Kearney</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Mills, Allen George. <title level="m">Fool for Christ: The Political Thought of
J. S. Woodsworth</title>. Toronto: University of Toronto Press,
1991.</bibl> <bibl>Woodsworth, James Shaver. <title level="m">My Neighbor: A Study of
City Conditions, a Plea for Social Service</title>. Toronto: Missionary
Society of the Methodist Church, 1911.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>