<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.war.044">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Sioux Wars</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Carole A. Barrett</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.war.044</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Barrett, Carole A.">Carole A. Barrett</author>. <title level="a">"Sioux Wars."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">836-837</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-28</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">SIOUX WARS</head>

<p>During the last half of the nineteenth century,
Lakota Sioux and their Cheyenne and Arapaho
allies defended their homelands and natural
resources against incursions by the federal
government and European American settlers.
Collectively known as the Sioux Wars, major
engagements included the Grattan Massacre
(1854), Fetterman Fight (1866), Battle of the
Rosebud (1876), Battle of the Little Bighorn
(1876), and the Wounded Knee Massacre
(1890).</p>

<p>The first violent conflict in the Plains involving
the Lakota Sioux and the federal government
grew out of increased travel along the
Oregon Trail. To protect overland travelers,
the federal government built Fort Kearny in
present-day Nebraska and purchased Fort
Laramie in present-day Wyoming. Government
agents also negotiated the Fort Laramie
Treaty of 1851, which guaranteed the safe passage
of emigrants in exchange for annuities
and the recognition of tribal territories. Peace
held until 1854 when a trivial event&#8211;the theft
of an emigrant's cow by young Lakotas&#8211;led to
the Grattan Massacre and subsequent army
retaliations. On August 19, 1854, Lt. John Grattan
led a detachment of twenty-nine men to
recover the stolen cow from the village of
Conquering Bear along the North Platte River.
Misunderstandings and a belligerent Grattan
sparked violence. When the shooting stopped,
Grattan and all of his men lay dead; Conquering
Bear was the lone Lakota casualty. Army
retaliation was certain. The following summer,
Col. William S. Harney destroyed a Sioux
village at Ash Hollow (present-day Nebraska),
killing more than 100 men, women, and children.
Harney then pushed into Lakota territory,
briefly occupying Fort Pierre (South Dakota)
and finally establishing Fort Randall on
the Missouri River. Harney's invasion of the
Sioux homeland caused the Sioux to move
away from the roads, soldiers, and forts and,
in combination with the federal government's
preoccupation with the Civil War (1861–65),
led to almost ten years of relative peace.</p>

<p>Trouble flared again in 1865–67 when emigrants,
in violation of the 1851 Treaty of Fort
Laramie, moved along the Bozeman Trail
to the Montana goldfields. This pathway cut
through the heart of Plains Indian hunting
grounds in the Powder River area. Persistent
Lakota raids against settlers and soldiers along
this route prompted the federal government
to build Forts Reno, C. F. Smith, and Phil
Kearny to protect emigrant travel. Despite the
heavy military presence, Indian attacks continued,
and in the second half of 1866 Lakotas
led by Red Cloud and Crazy Horse battled
federal troops. The most notorious engagement
was the Fetterman Fight (December 21,
1866) near Fort Phil Kearny, Wyoming Territory,
where eighty men under Capt. William
Fetterman were killed. Public cries for decisive
action against the Sioux reached a fever pitch,
but Congress voted to broker peace with the
warring tribes. Red Cloud signed the Fort
Laramie Treaty (1868), which guaranteed,
among other things, abandonment of the
Bozeman Trail forts and creation of a large
reservation that included the Black Hills. After
agreeing to this treaty, Red Cloud and many
Lakota bands moved onto this Great Sioux
Reservation, while Sitting Bull, Crazy Horse,
and Gall continued to resist encroachment on
their lands. They openly rejected the treaty
and continued to pursue their traditional life.</p>

<p>Hostilities erupted once again after an 1874
military expedition into the Black Hills confirmed
rumors of gold. Gold seekers flooded
into Paha Sapa (the Black Hills)&#8211;a clear violation
of the 1868 Fort Laramie Treaty&#8211;forcing
leaders such as Crazy Horse and Sitting
Bull to defend Sioux territory. To avoid conflict,
the federal government in 1875 offered
to purchase the land from the Sioux. Overwhelmingly,
the Sioux rejected this, and the
government provoked a military showdown
by issuing an ultimatum requiring all Sioux to
report to an agency by January 31, 1876, or be
considered hostile. The off-reservation people,
now loosely allied under Sitting Bull, were
scattered in the Powder River area (southeastern
Montana and northwestern Wyoming)
in small winter camps, and they largely
ignored this arbitrary, impossible demand.</p>

<p>In May 1876 the army launched a threepronged
campaign to force the Lakotas back
onto the Great Sioux Reservation: Col. John
Gibbon advanced eastward from Fort Ellis
(Montana), Gen. George Crook moved north
from Fort Laramie, and Gen. Alfred Terry
(with George Custer) moved westward from
Fort Abraham Lincoln (North Dakota). The
military's campaign began to crumble when
on June 17, 1876, the Sioux, led by Crazy
Horse, routed and turned back Crook's command
at the Battle of the Rosebud. On June
25.26, 1876, in the most famous fight of the
offensive, Lt. Col. George Custer's Seventh
Cavalry attacked an enormous Indian encampment
on the Little Bighorn (Greasy
Grass) River. Custer divided his command
and attempted to strike the village from both
ends but was quickly overwhelmed by superior
numbers. Custer and 210 men in his immediate
command (263 total) were killed.</p>

<p>After this victory, the Sioux and their allies
fragmented into small bands and dispersed.
The army initiated a winter campaign and relentlessly
hunted down those bands that had
not returned to their agencies. In May 1877,
Crazy Horse surrendered at Fort Robinson,
Nebraska; he was killed four months later, reportedly
while trying to escape. Sitting Bull
fled to Canada with as many as 2,000 followers.
In retaliation for defeat at the Little Bighorn,
Congress annexed the Black Hills from the
Great Sioux Reservation on February 28, 1877.</p>

<p>Essentially, these events marked the end of
the Sioux Wars and the start of the reservation
era. After Sitting Bull returned to the United
States in 1881, all Lakota Sioux bands lived on
reservations and any hope of effective resistance
was gone. The final conflict between
the Sioux and the federal government&#8211;the
Wounded Knee Massacre&#8211;was hardly a military
confrontation. Militarily defeated, the
Sioux readily adopted the Ghost Dance religion
but with a more militaristic twist&#8211;some
believed they would be impervious to bullets
and most believed that if they danced and
prayed with enough fervor the European
Americans would be driven from the country.
Their newfound focus caused great fear in the
Plains, leading to a confrontation with federal
troops. On December 29, 1890, while attempting
to disarm a fleeing band of Lakotas, the
Seventh Cavalry killed more than 250 Lakotas
(mostly women and children) on the Pine
Ridge Reservation in South Dakota. This massacre
marked the end of Sioux resistance and
the last chapter in the Plains Indian Wars.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi>: <hi rend="smallcaps">IMAGES AND ICONS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ii.017">Custer, George Armstrong</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">LAW</hi>: <ref n="egp.law.050"><hi rend="italic"><title>United States v. Sioux Nation of Indians</title></hi></ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">RELIGION</hi>: <ref n="egp.rel.023">Ghost Dance</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Carole A. Barrett<lb/>
University of Mary</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Olson, James C. <title level="m">Red Cloud and the Sioux Problem</title>. Lincoln:
University of Nebraska Press, 1965.</bibl> <bibl>Utley, Robert M.
<title level="m">The Indian Frontier of the American West, 1846–1890</title>. Albuquerque:
University of New Mexico Press, 1984.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>