<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.wat.010">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Gardiner Dam</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Max Macdonald</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.wat.010</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Macdonald, Max">Max Macdonald</author>. <title level="a">"Gardiner Dam."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">853-854</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-29</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">GARDINER DAM</head>

<p>Located sixty miles south of Saskatoon on the
South Saskatchewan River, the Gardiner Dam
was named in honor of federal Minister of
Agriculture James G. Gardiner, who fought
for its creation for many years. Construction
began in 1958 and the dam was completed in
1967. It is 210 feet in height and 16,700 feet in
length. Diefenbaker Lake, the reservoir the
dam created, is 140 miles long with a shoreline
of about 475 miles; it covers an area of 109,600
acres and has a total storage capacity of 8 million
acre feet. At the time of its construction
the Gardiner Dam, which cost $121 million,
was second only to the St. Lawrence Seaway in
terms of Canadian publicly funded projects. A
Saskatchewan study in 1996 placed the cost in
today's money at $1 billion. It is the largest
earth-filled dam in Canada and one of the
largest in the world.</p>

<p>The political will that fueled the undertaking
flowed directly from the experience of
the "dirty thirties." The dam is located in a
region described by the explorer James Palliser
in 1859 as being unfit for human habitation,
an area known for extreme droughts,
with crop failures expected three years out of
ten. During the 1930s it was the home of Canada's
Dust Bowl, when topsoil was torn from
its base and carried by prevailing westerlies in
huge black masses, leaving the farmlands barren
and houses and hedges all but buried.
Crops were ruined and farm life was left in
disarray. Some farmers were driven from the
land and some to madness and suicide. The
purpose of the Gardiner Dam was to mitigate
the effects of such drought by supplying irrigation
as well as providing electrical power,
urban water supply, flood control, and recreational
opportunities.</p>

<p>Power generation was the first benefit to
make an impact. From the moment it went
online, electricity generation began to produce
$10 million a year in savings. Urban water
supply was soon benefiting as well. A secondary
dam was built upstream from the
main structure to provide a controlled flow by
canal running south to serve the needs of
Moose Jaw and the capital city of Regina.
Other towns and hamlets and several industrial
sites are also being serviced, and access to
water is placed within reach of 40 percent of
Saskatchewan's population.</p>

<p>The main reservoir and a half dozen satellite
lakes fed by canals add substantially to recreational
opportunities: six vacation villages,
twelve fully developed parks, and three major
marinas have been established. Flood control
is generally a minor consideration, but in
years of high river runoff it is crucially important,
and in an average year it is responsible
for a savings of $44,000 in flood damage
by controlling the flow through the dam's
spillways.</p>

<p>Irrigation is the most significant aspect of
the project. There are now almost 100,000
acres under irrigation, which has resulted in a
shift to new crop mixtures, notably peas, fava
beans, pinto beans, lentils, grasses, potatoes,
rapeseed, mustard, and, in some isolated instances,
small orchards. Oddly enough, for
this part of the country, there has been a recent
move into mint production&#8211;a processing
plant has been established in the region,
with all of its production being exported to
the United States, United Kingdom, as well as
Japan and other Asian markets. Most of all,
the project has in large part eliminated the
fear of drought. As one farmer observed, "In
the past ten years I have never had a crop
failure on irrigated land."</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">AGRICULTURE</hi>: <ref n="egp.ag.042">Gardiner, Jimmy</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Max Macdonald<lb/>
University of Regina</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Fairley, Brad. <title level="m">South Saskatchewan River Basin Study</title>. Regina:
Canada Department of the Environment, 1997.</bibl>
<bibl>Kulshreshtha, Suran, et al. <title level="m">Social Evaluation of the South
Saskatchewan River Project</title>. Ottawa: Queen's Printer, 1988.</bibl>
<bibl>Macdonald, Max. <title level="m">Oasis for a Desert</title>. Regina: Canadian
Plains Research Center, 1999.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>