<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ind.004">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Agricultural Commodity Markets</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Dale G. Anderson</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ind.004</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Anderson, Dale G.">Dale G. Anderson</author>. <title level="a">"Agricultural Commodity Markets."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">409-410</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-02</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">AGRICULTURAL COMMODITY MARKETS</head>

<p>The Great Plains states and provinces are major
producers of basic agricultural commodities, including grain, oilseeds, cotton, hay,
sugar beets, and livestock. Because the end
products into which they are made are critical
in meeting basic human needs and because
they comprise a relatively small part of total
consumer expenditures, the prices of agricultural
commodities are highly responsive to
changes in supply and demand, with resulting
volatility of regional producer incomes. Owing
to vagaries of Plains weather, susceptibility
of living plants and animals to assorted pests,
and highly competitive conditions in the production
of most of these commodities, supplies
can vary widely from year to year and
over longer periods. As foreign markets have
become a major outlet for many of the products,
demand too has become much more
variable. A phase-out of U.S. government supply
controls and price supports has brought
further price and income variability.</p>

<p>The raw products of agriculture are heavy
and bulky relative to their value, and their
Plains production locales are far from major
centers of national and world demand. Because
production is seasonal in the face of
ongoing needs, large inventories must be carried
from one harvest to the next, and because
they are products of biological origin, agricultural
commodities are highly perishable.
Transportation, storage, and processing are
therefore challenging and costly.</p>

<p>In the 1950s and early 1960s, most grain
moving off American farms went first to country
elevators; from there, usually by rail and in
single-car lots, to much larger subterminal or
terminal elevators; and, finally, by rail or river
barge, to processors. Feed grains often bypassed
the system, moving directly from producers
to local feeders, and much of the grain
was used by producers themselves. Farms have
since become larger and more specialized and
country elevators fewer and much larger.
Long-haul grain shipments now move by rail
directly from train-loading country elevators
to ports of export or to domestic processing
and feed-deficit areas. Short-haul traffic formerly
moving by rail now goes mainly by
truck. These changes have been prompted by a
number of factors: economies of elevator scale;
rail innovations such as unit trains, "jumbo"
covered hopper cars, automated car-control
systems, and suspension of transit billing privileges;
abandonment of railroad branch-line
trackage; expanded port facilities; larger oceangoing
vessels; construction of the U.S. interstate
highway system beginning in 1956; opening of
the St. Lawrence Seaway in 1957; federal deregulation
of both rail and trucking industries
in 1980; and growth in foreign demand.</p>

<p>Wheat milling was once done in and near
sources of production, much of it in urban
centers such as Kansas City and Minneapolis.
Trainload shipments in specialized hopper
cars have since made it cheaper to ship wheat
than milled products, leading mills to relocate
to areas of flour demand. Milling has also become
more concentrated; the largest four
firms had 70 percent of U.S. capacity in 1992.
Grain marketing firms have integrated forward
into flour milling in both the United
States and Canada, the largest three Canadian
firms having 75 percent of that country's capacity
at latest count. Canadian millers, unlike
those in the United States, are often integrated
forward into baking as well. Feed grains were
formerly milled in small production-oriented
facilities. Today, mills are much larger and
fewer in number. Most are located in areas of
feed grain production and local livestock feed
demand, but some are situated in more distant
centers of poultry production in the
southeastern United States.</p>

<p>U.S. grain prices were formerly determined
largely in cash markets in places such as Minneapolis,
Chicago, Kansas City, and Omaha.
Now, cash markets are nearly extinct, and
price bids at country elevators are based on
futures markets in Chicago, Minneapolis, and
Winnipeg. Prices for grain moving into ultimate
domestic and foreign markets are determined
largely by telephoned bids and offers
for future deliveries. In Canada, the Canadian
Wheat Board has sole marketing authority
over barley and wheat, and producer prices
for exported grain vary each year only by
transportation differentials. The Winnipeg
Commodity Exchange has open-market trading
of canola, feed barley, feed wheat, and feed
oats. The Canada.United States Trade Agreement
(<hi rend="smallcaps">CUSTA</hi>) and the North American Free
Trade Agreement (<hi rend="smallcaps">NAFTA</hi>) have reduced government
interference in markets on both sides
of the border, making the two markets more
integrated. Rail shipping rates for agricultural
products were traditionally subsidized by the
Canadian government under the Crow's Nest
Pass Agreement, by which the government
funded rail-line construction in return for a
ceiling on shipping rates, giving Canadian
grain shippers favored access to Pacific Rim
markets. The ceilings are now being removed,
with resulting diversion of much Canadian
wheat across the border to American railroads.
Canadian rail system efficiency lags
behind that in the United States, and grain
moves through country elevators of smaller
size and load-out capacities than those south
of the forty-ninth parallel.</p>

<p>Innovations in transportation, especially
refrigerated railcars, and a gradual westward
shift of livestock and feed grains production
prompted a westward migration of U.S. livestock
markets and slaughter. Chicago, once
the nation's largest livestock marketing center,
was superseded in the 1950s by Omaha. Peripheral
Plains-oriented markets prospered in
Sioux City, Kansas City, Fort Worth, and elsewhere.
More recently, urban markets and
packing houses have given way to slaughter
and processing in smaller, rural Plains communities.
Direct packer purchases of cattle
from producers have supplanted the auction
and terminal markets of the past. Packers now
disassemble carcasses into "boxed beef" cuts
for shipment by refrigerated trucks to retail
markets, leaving bone and other waste behind
for manufacture into feed and fertilizer. Meatpacking
and meat-processing plants and firms
have grown sharply in size while shrinking in
number; by the 1990s, the four largest packing
firms had 82 percent of U.S. beef slaughter and
80 percent of boxed beef production.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">AGRICULTURE</hi>: <ref n="egp.ag.007">Agricultural Price Supports</ref>; <ref n="egp.ag.075">Wheat</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Dale G. Anderson<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Anderson, Dale G. <title level="m">Transporting Nebraska Grain and Oilseeds: Changing Markets in a Changing World Economy</title>.
Report no. 177. University of Nebraska Department of
Agricultural Economics, Lincoln, 1998.</bibl> <bibl>Cramer, Gail L.,
and Eric J. Wailes. <title level="m">Grain Marketing</title>. Boulder <hi rend="smallcaps">CO</hi>: Westview
Press, 1993.</bibl> <bibl>Larson, Donald W., Paul W. Gallagher, and
Reynold P. Dahl, eds. <title level="m">Structural Change and Performance of the U.S. Grain Marketing System</title>. Champaign <hi rend="smallcaps">IL</hi>: Prestige
Printing, 1998.</bibl>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>