<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.med.011">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Cavett, Dick (b. 1936)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>David J. Wishart</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.med.011</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</author>. <title level="a">"Cavett, Dick (b. 1936)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">509</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-26</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">CAVETT, DICK (b. 1936)</head>

<p>Richard A. "Dick" Cavett, comedian, writer,
actor, and, most famously, talk-show host, was
born in the small Nebraska town of Gibbon
on November 19, 1936. Both his parents were
teachers. When Cavett was five his family
moved to Grand Island; his high school years
were spent in Lincoln. Cavett remembers his
Nebraska upbringing fondly: a landscape of
idyllic images, darkened only by his mother's
death when he was ten, a tragedy from which,
he admits, he has never fully recovered.</p>

<p>Cavett started into acting early and performed
his magic act at various Lincoln venues.
(He first met another rising star, Johnny
Carson, at a magic show in a Lincoln church
basement.) Cavett was driven by a sense of
destiny, a knowledge that he would be famous,
and he acted in stage productions at Yale
(from which he graduated in 1958) and then,
without much success, in New York City. He
maneuvered his big break in 1960 when he
cornered Jack Paar in a corridor off the set of
<hi rend="smallcaps">NBC</hi>'s <title>The Jack Paar Tonight Show</title> and handed
him an envelope of jokes. Paar used the jokes
and hired Cavett a week later.</p>

<p>During the next few years, Cavett wrote
jokes for Paar, Carson, Merv Griffin, and Jerry
Lewis and performed in stand-up comedy and
on television. His first stint as a television host
was on <hi rend="smallcaps">ABC</hi>'s <title>The Morning</title> in 1968. The show
lasted only a season, but Cavett was soon in
the limelight as host of <title>The Dick Cavett Show</title>,
which ran on abc from 1969 to 1974. While
Cavett rejects being labeled as intellectual, the
urbane tenor of the show and the high caliber
of his guests (who included Laurence Olivier
and Ingmar Bergman) set it apart from other
talk shows.</p>

<p>But the show's ratings were never high
enough to suit executives, and, despite receiving
three Emmy Awards, it was canceled in
1974. <title>The Dick Cavett Show</title> was revived on <hi rend="smallcaps">PBS</hi>
from 1977 to 1982 and briefly again on <hi rend="smallcaps">ABC</hi> in
1986–87. After 1989 Cavett hosted a regular
show on the cable network <hi rend="smallcaps">CNBC</hi>. Cavett also
made numerous other television appearances
and acted in many movies (often as himself )
during these years. As he makes clear in his
autobiographical conversation with Christopher
Porterfield, however, despite his successes
elsewhere, he remains firmly rooted in
his Great Plains background.</p>

<closer>
<signed>David J. Wishart<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Cavett, Richard A., and Christopher Porterfield. <title level="m">Cavett</title>.
New York: Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, 1974.</bibl> <bibl>Rooney, Terrie
M., ed. <title level="m">Contemporary Theater, Film, and Television</title>.
Detroit: Gale, 1996: 15: 83–85.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>