<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.asam.011">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Denver's Anti-Chinese Riot</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Mark R. Ellis</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.asam.011</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Ellis, Mark R.">Mark R. Ellis</author>. <title level="a">"Denver's Anti-Chinese Riot."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">142-143</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-22</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">DENVER'S ANTI-CHINESE RIOT</head>

<p>On the afternoon of October 31, 1880, a mob
descended on Denver's Chinatown. Within
hours the mob destroyed businesses, residences,
and killed one Chinese resident. Denver's
riot was one of 153 anti-Chinese riots that
swept through the American West during the
1870s and 1880s. Because so few Chinese settled
in the Great Plains during the nineteenth
century, however, the Denver riot was one of
two major anti-Chinese incidents to strike the
region (the other was in Calgary in 1892).</p>

<p>The Chinese had experienced discrimination
and violence since 1849 when they first
arrived in California. They were driven out of
California mines by the "foreign miner's tax"
and also experienced outright violence (a Los
Angeles mob killed twenty-eight Chinese in
1871). By the late 1870s the anti-Chinese movement
had entered national politics. Fearful
that cheap Chinese labor would threaten the
white working class, Denis Kearney, an Irish
immigrant and founder of the Workingman's
Party, led a campaign to ban Chinese immigration.
During the presidential election of
1880 Chinese immigration became an important
issue when Winfield Hancock, the Democratic
candidate, supported a ban on Chinese
immigration.</p>

<p>Colorado was not immune to anti-Chinese
agitation. In 1874 white miners drove 160 Chinese
out of Nederland, and in 1879 the people
of Leadville were proud to announce that they
had no Chinese living in their community. By
1880 the anti-Chinese movement had reached
Denver, a city with 238 Chinese residents.
During the presidential election of 1880, Denver's
Rocky Mountain News, a staunchly Democratic
paper, launched an anti-Chinese campaign,
igniting Denver's working class. In its
October 23 issue, for example, the newspaper
called the Chinese the "Pest of the Pacific" and
pointed out that if they invaded Colorado in
greater numbers, white men would starve and
women would be forced into prostitution.
Other editorials attacked the opium dens located
along Hop Alley in Chinatown. On October
28 the Rocky Mountain News reported
that there was open talk in Denver of running
the Chinese out. The night before the riot,
supporters of the Democratic Party marched
through the streets, many carrying anti-
Chinese banners.</p>

<p>Denver was ready to explode. The spark
that ignited the riot came on the afternoon of
October 31 when several intoxicated white
men entered a saloon and began harassing
two Chinese. The Chinese patrons retreated
out the back door but were pursued and assaulted.
Soon after, a crowd composed mostly
of Irish laborers gathered near the scene of the
crime. By two o'clock the crowd had turned
into a mob of 3,000, and Denver's police force,
which was understaffed and without a police
chief, was unable to control the masses. The
mayor called on the fire department to help
with crowd management and then tried to
persuade the mob to disperse. When the
crowd shouted down the mayor, he ordered
the fire department to disperse them with water
hoses. Enraged by the soaking, the crowd
hurled bricks and rocks at the firemen and
then turned their rage on Chinatown. They
sacked businesses, burned homes, and attacked
innocent victims. By early evening rioters
had burned every laundry in Chinatown.
When the mob found Sing Lee, a laundryman,
they pounced on him, kicking him as he lay
on the ground. The helpless laundryman was
dragged down the street with a rope around
his neck and eventually was beaten to death.</p>

<p>A few Denverites stood up to the mob and
protected their Chinese friends. Several citizens
hid Chinese friends in their homes. Jim
Moon, a gambler of ill repute, held off a mob
bent on burning out a Chinese laundry. With
a revolver leveled at the crowd and using
forceful language, Moon single-handedly dispersed
the crowd. In another act of bravery,
Liz Preston, the madam of a brothel, and ten
of her employees protected several terrified
Chinese. Armed with shotguns, champagne
bottles, and high-heeled shoes, the women
forced the crowd to retreat. Preston's brothel
served as a safe haven for Denver's Chinese
during the riot; at least thirty-four Chinese
waited out the riot inside her parlor.</p>

<p>In the heat of the riot the mayor appointed
Dave Cook, a Denver fireman, as acting police
chief, and he quickly appointed 125 special policemen
to help reestablish order. Police officers
rounded up the Chinese and lodged
them in the county jail for their own protection.
With law enforcers finally on the streets,
the crowd slowly disappeared into the night.
By eleven o'clock Cook reported that Denver's
streets were quiet.</p>

<p>Authorities kept the Chinese locked in the
county jail for several days. On November 4
they were released, only to find their businesses,
homes, and temples destroyed. Estimates
of the total damage exceeded $53,000.
The Chinese consul in San Francisco requested
reparation payments from the federal
government and the city of Denver. His requests
were denied. To add further insult to
the Chinese victims, Denver's rioters escaped
punishment. Those who had been jailed during
the riot were released for lack of evidence,
and Sing Lee's murderers were acquitted in
February 1881. Despite the violence and destruction
of their property, many Chinese remained
in Denver. They rebuilt their businesses
and homes along Hop Alley, and by
1890 more than 980 Chinese lived in Denver.
Chinatown remained a part of the Denver
landscape until 1940 when it was razed in the
name of urban renewal.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">CITIES AND TOWNS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ct.018">Denver, Colorado</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Mark R. Ellis<lb/>
University of Nebraska at Kearney</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Wortman, Roy T. "Denver's Anti-Chinese Riot, 1880," <title level="j">Colorado Magazine</title> 42 (1965): 275–91.</bibl> <bibl>Wunder, John R. "Anti-
Chinese Violence in the American West, 1850–1910." In
<title level="m">Law for the Elephant, Law for the Beaver: Essays in the Legal History of the North American West</title>, edited by John Mc-
Claren. Pasadena <hi rend="smallcaps">CA</hi>: Ninth Judicial Circuit Historical Society,
1992: 212–36.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>