<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ct.057">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Winnipeg, Manitoba</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Ian Wight</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ct.057</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Wight, Ian">Ian Wight</author>. <title level="a">"Winnipeg, Manitoba."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">189</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-28</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">WINNIPEG, MANITOBA</head>

<p>Winnipeg is located at the extreme northeastern
edge of the Great Plains, on the bed of
ancient glacial Lake Agassiz, at the interface of
the Laurentian Shield and Prairies, and at the
confluence of two great rivers of the Plains,
the Red and Assiniboine. The city centers
Canada's eighth largest metropolitan area in a
province that centers the country. It is the capital
of Manitoba, the so-called Keystone Province,
and it is possibly the province more than
the city itself that has in the past been more
strongly connected with the Great Plains, reinforced
by the prominent featuring of the
bison as the provincial animal symbol.</p>

<p>Winnipeg itself has always had aspirations
well beyond Manitoba and well beyond provincial
status. Its early boosters envisaged
a commercial metropolis on the Chicago
model, serving the Canadian Prairies and the
Northern Great Plains. Winnipeg was named
during the 1860s for one of the two large lakes
to its north. Even though the naming of Winnipeg
is thought by some to have been a joke
(the name comes from the Cree word for
muddy or murky water&#8211;the low-lying settlement
was prone to flooding and was often
coated with gumbo), the name stuck and indeed
became a point of pride, especially when
the fledgling province, at the city's incorporation
in 1873, tried to rename it Assiniboia.
The latter actually became the appellation for
the young city's first region, extending across
most of the southern half of what is now the
Prairie Provinces. From its beginning Winnipeg
treated this macroregion as its incipient
hinterland, casting itself as the independent
commanding metropolis.</p>

<p>In 1870 a tiny unincorporated Winnipeg,
with a population of no more than a few hundred,
became the provincial seat of government
simply by virtue of hosting Fort Garry,
an early fur-trading hub. Its aggressive business
elite ensured that no rival of any consequence
would emerge, and to this day
Winnipeg enjoys exceptional primacy in the
provincial urban system. However, Winnipeg's
early ascendancy is mainly associated
with the emergence of the Canadian Prairies
as the "Breadbasket of the British Empire."
The colonial overseers described Winnipeg as
the "buckle of the wheat belt" and the "bull'seye
of the Dominion."</p>

<p>Winnipegers themselves cast their city in
even grander roles as the "Heart of the Continent"
and the "Gateway to the West." The
years from 1875 to 1915 were indeed heady
times: the city enjoyed rapid growth, especially
after the arrival of the railway in 1881. Winnipeg's
population increased rapidly, reaching
42,340 by 1901. It was then touted, quite plausibly,
as the "Chicago of the North"; but it was
not to be, and at times it has seemed more
likely that Winnipeg would become the "Detroit
of the North." Some blame the 1919 Winnipeg
General Strike; others point to a particularly
long and deep depression following
the opening of the Panama Canal. Competition
from more westerly cities was certainly a
factor.</p>

<p>Winnipeg's star can now be seen to have
been in relative decline for most of the twentieth
century. Other, more western centers
have steadily eroded Winnipeg's initial expansive
Prairies hinterland; Calgary, in particular,
has eclipsed Winnipeg as the dominant Prairie
commercial metropolis, but Regina, Saskatoon,
and Edmonton have also played their
competing parts. The city has steadily slipped
in rank, from third largest in Canada (after
Montreal and Toronto) in 1911, to fourth in
1941, to eighth in 1996 (with a population
of 618,477). Nevertheless, Winnipeg does possess
a remarkably diversified economy, with
considerable economic activity&#8211;a condition
of dynamic stability that puts its now slow
growth in a more tolerable perspective.</p>

<p>Many influential Winnipeggers have difficulty facing their distinctly reduced circumstances
and in taking a more inclusive provincial
perspective. Their provincial brethren
often diagnose them as having a pronounced
case of "perimeteritis," an inability to see beyond
the perimeter highway that surrounds
and roughly delimits the city. But this condition
is actually still as much one of overlooking
the rest of Manitoba as it is the inward
looking of self-preoccupation. And, intriguingly,
it seems to be leading to an outlook
that is much more inclusive of a Great Plains
perspective.</p>

<p>Winnipeg boosters now tend to embrace
not so much a national but a continental (the
Americas) frame of reference, with a more
north-south than east-west orientation. For
example, the city has hosted the Pan-Am
Games twice (1967 and 1999) and is now reconnecting
with the Great Plains by its enthusiastic
participation in the development of
the midcontinent corridor concept, which
links Manitoba with Mexico. This concept
and Winnipeg's aspiration to become a meeting
place on a continental scale have been
given expressive form since 1990 in the pridefilled
redevelopment of The Forks at the junction
of the Red and Assiniboine Rivers. Given
over to the railway for much of the city's history,
the site is again a humanized place of
quality, eliciting considerable affection from
current residents as it connects to the city's
presettlement Aboriginal roots, a heritage that
plays a large part in the future now unfolding.</p>
</div1>
<div1>
<p><hi rend="italic">See also<hi rend="smallcaps">MEDIA</hi>: <title level="j">Winnipeg Free Press</title> / <hi rend="smallcaps">PROTEST AND DISSENT</hi>: <hi rend="italic">Winnipeg Free Press</hi></hi>.</p>
</div1>

<div1> <p/>
<closer>
<signed>Ian Wight<lb/>
University of Manitoba</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Artibise, Alan F. J. <title level="m">Winnipeg: A Social History of Urban Growth, 1874–1914</title>. Montreal: McGill-Queen's University
Press, 1975.</bibl> <bibl>Dafoe, Christopher. <title level="m">Winnipeg: Heart of the Continent</title>. Winnipeg: Great Plains Publications, 1998.</bibl>
<bibl>Morton, W. L. <title level="m">Manitoba: A History</title>. Toronto: University
of Toronto Press, 1957.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>