<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fil.051">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main"><hi rend="italic">Northern Lights</hi></title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Eunice Pedersen Johnston</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fil.051</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Johnston, Eunice Pedersen">Eunice Pedersen Johnston</author>. <title level="a">"<hi rend="italic">Northern Lights</hi>."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">275</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-12</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main"><hi rend="italic">NORTHERN LIGHTS</hi></head>
<figure n="egp.fil.051" rend="granted" type="noclick">
<figDesc>Nortern Lights (1978) film poster</figDesc>
</figure>    

<p><title>Northern Lights</title> (1978), an independently produced
film, tells the story of North Dakota
farmers who rebel against the economic tyranny
of the railroads, grain dealers, and bankers
by working for the election of Nonpartisan
League candidates in 1916.</p>

<p>A mixture of historical fact and imaginative
fiction, the film shows why one individual becomes
involved in a radical, grassroots political
movement. It begins with shots of Henry
Martinson, a lifelong socialist who was in his
nineties at the time the film was made. Martinson
reminisces about the old days when ‘‘we
had the powers that be on the run'' and then
discovers a diary that belonged to the fictional
Ray Sorenson. The action flashes back to 1915,
when Ray, his brother John, and their father
are farming near Crosby, North Dakota. Visiting
Nonpartisan League members advocate
political changes that will give farmers more
control over the grain-marketing process and
thus ease their economic troubles. At first Ray
is skeptical, but after his father dies and his
fianc&#233;e's parents lose their farm, he is motivated
by these personal losses not only to join
the league but also to become an organizer,
recruiting new members and campaigning for
league candidates. League candidates win the
primary election of 1916, but John and Ray
receive a letter notifying them the bank is foreclosing
on their farm. Martinson concludes
the film by reporting the league's victory in the
general election of 1916 and hoping that such
victories might happen again in the future.</p>

<p>Another major theme of the film is the desire
to have a personal life and the sacrifice of
that life required by those who commit themselves
to a cause. At the beginning of the film,
Ray proposes to Inga Olsness. However, as Ray
becomes increasingly involved in league activities,
they seldom see each other, and their
relationship deteriorates. Inga tells a friend
that she no longer loves Ray as she once did,
and she fears that Ray will always be away
from home because the struggle will continue
indefinitely. Ray and Inga might eventually get
together or they might drift apart, but the disillusioned
Inga feels they will never be able to
live the better life for which Ray is struggling.</p>

<p>The film was written, directed, produced,
and edited by John Hanson and Rob Nilsson
through Cine Manifest, a San Francisco–
based film collective that was formed to produce
socially conscious narrative films. Both
Hanson and Nilsson have family connections
in North Dakota. A few actors, including
Robert Behling, Susan Lynch, and Joe Spano,
are professionals, but nonprofessional North
Dakotans play the other roles. Most of the film
was shot in Crosby and at Bonanzaville, a pioneer
village in West Fargo, North Dakota.
The North Dakota Humanities Council contributed
greatly to the production of the film,
which was made with an extremely low budget&#8211;
a little over $300,000. The film premiered
in Crosby in July 1978 and was shown
throughout North Dakota and the Midwest
before being entered in the Cannes Film Festival,
where it won the Camera d'Or (Golden
Camera) Award for best first feature film in
1979.</p>

<p>Although <title>Northern Lights</title> depicts an actual
political movement, viewers will learn little
about the Nonpartisan League from it. Martinson,
an ardent socialist, is not a good representative
of the league's politics, which were
much more moderate. None of the league's
three main leaders&#8211;A. C. Townley, Lynn
Frazier, and William Lemke&#8211;appears in the
film (Lemke is not even mentioned), and it
does little more than hint at why the league
was in power for only six years. The film has
been criticized for showing women only in
subservient, passive roles rather than as partners
and leaders in the movement. Hanson
and Nilsson, however, state that their intent
was to create a social documentary that depicts
the personal aspects of a political movement
rather than a historical documentary.</p>

<p>The style of the film is unusual. The dialogue
is extremely sparse, and sometimes the
characters speak Norwegian. The film's photography
captures both intimate family scenes
and the open spaces of the prairie, and the
scene that shows people threshing during a
blizzard is particularly effective. Photographed
by Judy Irola with 16-mm black-and-white
film, which created a high-contrast image
with rich tones and frequent silhouettes,
the film was later blown up to 35 mm for theatrical
release, which added to its grainy appearance.
Irola also used a relatively oldfashioned
camera style: the camera seldom
moves, and most action takes place inside the
frame. These techniques help create a sense
that the film takes place at a much earlier time,
and its visual world, which includes hard
work, struggles against the forces of nature,
and tough economic times, evokes the theme
so often repeated in the history of the Great
Plains&#8211;that of farm families being forced off
their farms.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">PROTEST AND DISSENT</hi>: <ref n="egp.pd.034">Martinson, Harry</ref>; <ref n="egp.pd.039">Nonpartisan League</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Eunice Pedersen Johnston<lb/>
North Dakota State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Anderegg, Michael. "History, Image, and Meaning in
'Northern Lights.'" <title level="j">North Dakota History</title> 57 (1990): 14–23.</bibl>
<bibl>Dempsy, Michael. "'Northern Lights': An Interview with
John Hanson and Rob Nilsson." <title level="j">Film Quarterly</title> 32 (1979):
2–10.</bibl> <bibl>Jenkinson, Clay. <title level="m">A Humanities Guide to "Northern Lights."</title> Bismarck: North Dakota Humanities Council,
1981.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>