<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.pd.035">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">McGrath, Tom (1916-1990)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Tom Matchie</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.pd.035</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Matchie, Tom">Tom Matchie</author>. <title level="a">"McGrath, Tom (1916-1990)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">717-718</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-06</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">MCGRATH, TOM (1916-1990)</head>

<p>Perhaps America's most talented political
poet, Thomas Matthew McGrath was a man
dedicated to protest. Born (on November 20,
1916) and raised on a farm near the tiny Plains
town of Sheldon, North Dakota, he returned
there through his poetry to relate the simple
struggles of his boyhood in the 1920s. The
family farm fell into the hands of bankers in
the Great Depression. It is such hardships, as
well as joys, that he captures in his poems,
especially his best and longest, the semi-autobiographical
<title level="m">Letter to an Imaginary Friend</title>
(published in four parts from 1962 to 1985 and
as a combined definitive edition in 1997).</p>

<p>McGrath's father was influenced by the
Wobblies and was a storyteller who read
poems and sang to his son on the farm. Tom
grew up respecting the workingman, and the
rhythms and images of the threshing machine
influenced his poetry. As a young adult he rode
the rails, and in the early 1940s he worked as a
welder and union organizer in the New York
shipyards. He still found time to earn his bachelor
of arts degree from the University of
North Dakota in 1939 and his master of arts
from Louisiana State University a year later. He
received a Rhodes scholarship to study at Oxford,
but delayed it until after World War II,
during which he served reluctantly in the Aleutian
Islands. In 1954 McGrath was ousted from
a teaching job at Los Angeles State College of
Applied Arts and Sciences for his radical views
and his refusal to testify before the House
Committee on Un-American Activities.</p>

<p>Following a year in New York, where he
wrote what he called "junk fiction," McGrath
returned to teach writing at North Dakota
State University in Fargo in 1962, and after
that, at Moorhead State University in Moorhead,
Minnesota, from 1968 to 1982. However,
he often took leaves to travel in Europe and
Mexico, and he published prolifically. His poetry
has been described as a Whitmanesque
song about America, though unlike Whitman,
he candidly attacks the country's racism, classism,
and sectionalism. McGrath was a Marxist,
but his communism functioned as a vehicle
for his art, a framework within which he
could build and render his vision of life. Like
Crazy Horse, whom he championed, he was
an outsider, rooted in the Plains and a defender
of the people.</p>

<p>McGrath received many honors for his poetry,
including an American Book Award for
<title level="m">Echoes inside the Labyrinth</title> in 1983, but his
frank, outspoken political views probably prevented
him from receiving the recognition he
deserved as a great American poet. Tom McGrath died in Minneapolis on September 19,
1990.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Tom Matchie<lb/>
North Dakota State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>McGrath, Tom. <title level="m">Letter to an Imaginary Friend</title>. Port Townsend
<hi rend="smallcaps">WA</hi>: Copper Canyon Press, 1997.</bibl> <bibl>Stern, Frederick C.
<title level="m">The Revolutionary Poet in the United States: The Poetry
of Thomas McGrath</title>. Columbia: University of Missouri
Press, 1988.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>