<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.na.014">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Blackfoot</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Hana Samek Norton</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.na.014</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Norton, Hana Samek">Hana Samek Norton</author>. <title level="a">"Blackfoot."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">567-568</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-03</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">BLACKFOOT</head>

<p>One of the largest Native American groups of
the Northern Plains, the Blackfoot Confederacy,
consists of the Siksikas (Blackfoot proper),
Kainahs (Bloods), Northern (Canadian) Piegans,
and Southern Piegans (or Blackfeet, as
they came to be known). The Algonquian-speaking
Blackfoot may have migrated from
the north and northwestern woodlands into
the Plains of southern Alberta and northern
Montana sometime in the fifteenth century. If
so, they adapted to become one of the defining
Plains Indian nations, so much so that their
own history places their homeland in the
Northern Plains.</p>

<p>Early estimates of Blackfoot population
varied from 15,000 to 40,000. Blackfoot territory
included the area from the North Saskatchewan
River south to the Yellowstone
River, and from central Saskatchewan west to
the continental divide. By the middle of the
eighteenth century, the Blackfoot had acquired
horses from other tribes and guns from
British traders. Raiding, gathering, hunting,
and trading became the mainstays of their
economy, and their power and influence grew.
Wider contacts, however, made the Blackfoot
vulnerable to smallpox, such as during the
1837 epidemic, and to other diseases which periodically
decimated them.</p>

<p>The Blackfoot saw themselves as a part of a
vibrant, sacred world, regarding the Sun as
one of the most powerful beings. Like other
Plains tribes, Blackfoot men and women secured
their place in this world through vision
quests, through ceremonies of sacred bundles
to secure the blessing and protection of powerful
bird and animal spirits (the "beaver
medicine" being considered among the oldest
and most powerful ceremonies), and through
reliance on the spiritual guidance of medicine
men and women. Although no central authority
governed the Blackfoot, the Sun Dance
eventually emerged as the principal summer
ceremony that brought together dozens of independent,
dispersed bands.</p>

<p>In 1806 the Lewis and Clark expedition incurred
the enmity of the Blackfoot, resulting
in periodic attacks on Americans. The Blackfoot
gained a reputation for fierceness due to
their opposition to the incursion of American
fur trappers into their territory. They remained
on friendlier terms with the Hudson's
Bay Company, which encouraged the Blackfoot
to trade at its posts. After the establishment
of Fort McKenzie on the Marias
River in 1833, contacts with Americans grew.
The Blackfoot exchanged buffalo robes, pemmican,
elk and deer hides, and furs for manufactured
goods. These contacts occasionally
led to trader- or trapper-Native marriages and
the appearance of a mixed-blood population.</p>

<p>The transition from independence to reservation
life was harrowing for the Blackfoot. In
1855 the Blackfoot, with several other tribes,
took part in their first American treaty. The
so-called Lame Bull's Treaty set aside for the
Blackfoot a portion of a reservation in what
became Montana in exchange for annuities
and other pledges by the U.S. government.
Few promises were fulfilled, and in subsequent
years, as whiskey peddlers, miners, cattlemen,
and settlers moved into the area, conflicts
increased and clamor for the reduction
of this reservation grew. Congress failed to
ratify two such treaties, and in the 1860s the
situation led to a series of raids and clashes
called the "Blackfoot War." On January 23,
1870, Blackfoot resistance to encroachment on
their lands ended with the massacre on the
Marias River of 173 men, women, and children
by the U.S. Army under Maj. Eugene V. Baker.</p>

<p>In July 1873 an executive order set aside a
new reservation for the Blackfeet, Gros Ventres,
and River Crows. The 2,750-square-mile
reservation was bounded on the west by the
continental divide, on the north by the U.S.-
Canadian border, on the south by the Missouri
River, and on the east by Dakota Territory. In
1874, upon the urging of settlers, Congress restored
the land between the Sun and the Missouri
Rivers to public domain.</p>

<p>The remaining bands of the Confederacy
signed Treaty Number 7 with the British government
in 1877. The Blackfoot and the Kainahs,
along with the Sarcee (Sarsi), received as
their reserve a four-mile by 200-mile strip of
land along the Bow River in southern Alberta.
The Kainahs subsequently moved to a new reserve
between the St. Mary and Belly Rivers,
and the Piegans went to a reserve west of Fort
Macleod. The land was more suited to hunting
than to farming, and the disappearance of
the bison from the Northern Plains between
1879 and 1883 brought famine and starvation
to the Confederacy. In Canada, an estimated
1,000 Blackfoot died, and almost 600 died of
starvation and associated diseases in Montana.
As a result, the American Blackfeet were
pressured in 1888 and 1896 to trade their only
remaining resource, their land, for the prospect
of government annuities.</p>

<p>In both countries, efforts to teach selfsupport
through farming and irrigated agriculture
initially failed, but by the turn of the
century cattle raising began to emerge as a
successful enterprise, especially among the
growing population of the mixed bloods. In
the United States, however, the acts of 1907
and 1919 allotted the reservation, resulting in
an erosion of the Blackfeet land base and the
crippling of their nascent economy. The Canadian
Blackfoot lands were also reduced by
the early twentieth century.</p>

<p>The American practice of allotment and
assimilation formally ended with the passage
of the Indian Reorganization Act in 1934.
The Blackfeet chose to organize under this act
with a tribal council elected by residents of the
various districts of the reservation. Health,
education, and economic conditions on the
reservation slowly began to improve. During
World War II many Blackfeet served in the
armed forces and found employment off the
reservation. Many consequently chose to relocate
to urban centers while maintaining their
tribal a.liation. Some entered skilled and
professional occupations and pursued higher
education.</p>

<p>Since the 1930s the Blackfeet economy has
followed the pattern of other tribes with various
tribal enterprises&#8211;ranching, timber and
gas, and light manufacturing industries&#8211;
which experienced mixed success. The 1.3-
million-acre Blackfeet Reservation, adjacent to
Glacier National Park (which was once part of
it), attracts tourists and visitors. The tribally
owned and operated Museum of the Plains
Indians houses exhibits and publishes monographs on tribal history and culture. The fully
accredited Blackfeet Community College in
Browning, Montana, offers standard curriculum
as well courses in the language and traditions
of the tribe. Tribal enrollment is about
15,000, with about 7,000 residing on the Montana
reservation. The registered population of
Canadian Blackfoot is about 16,000, with almost
12,000 living on the three reserves.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">LITERARY TRADITIONS</hi>: <ref n="egp.lt.079">Welch, James</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Hana Samek Norton<lb/>
Albuquerque, New Mexico</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Ewers, John C. <title level="m">The Blackfeet: Raiders on the Northwestern Plains</title>. Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1958.</bibl>
<bibl>Ground, Mary. <title level="m">Grass Woman Stories</title>. Browning <hi rend="smallcaps">MT</hi>: Blackfeet
Heritage Program, 1978.</bibl> <bibl>Samek, Hana. <title level="m">The Blackfoot Confederacy 1880–1920</title>. Albuquerque: University of New
Mexico Press, 1987.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>