<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fol.018">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Folk Toys</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>John R. Nelson Jr.</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2009</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fol.018</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2009</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2009 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Nelson, Jr., John R.">John R. Nelson, Jr.</author>. <title level="a">"Folk Toys."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">300</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-16</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">FOLK TOYS</head>

<p>Centuries before the influx of European American
settlers, Native Americans of the Great
Plains developed hundreds of ingenious and
highly differentiated toys to instruct and entertain
both the young and not-so-young. Among
the most widespread and creative examples
were six-foot-long knotted loops, usually of
deer hide or rawhide, which were used to produce
string figures, variations of the modern
"cat's cradle." Play could be solitary, or it might
join two persons of different generations passing
the intricate loops back and forth (thus, the
practice was called "web weaving"). Tribes
shared many designs and each produced a
variant of the nearly universal cat's cradle.
Many Great Plains Native American string figures
illustrated tribal histories and folklore, as
well as religious narratives.</p>

<p>Other Native American toys both entertained
and developed eye-hand coordination.
Many were comprised of an eight- to twelve-inch
pin of wood, bone, or antler connected
by a length of cord to a series of up to nineteen
small rings, or to a piece of leather punched
with various-sized holes. As the pin is swung
upward at arm's length, the rings or leather
form a large arc, and when reaching the apex,
begin to fall downward. At that instant, the
player attempts to thrust the pin through all
the rings or through a designated hole in the
leather. The considerable deftness and skill required
helped train children for spearfishing
and hunting.</p>

<p>A related toy combines a hoop with darts.
In each variant, whether from the Ojibwas of
North Dakota, Lakotas of South Dakota, or
Gros Ventres of Montana, a hoop, with a diameter
from two-and-three-quarters up to
twenty-five inches, fashioned from a thin
branch, bone, or supple corn husk, surrounds
a central weaving of yarn, string, beads, or
rawhide. The weaving divides the hoop's enclosed
area into sectors, with a small hole remaining
in the center. The target hoop may be
set on the ground, suspended from a tree
branch, or rolled along the ground. Two players
throw sharpened and sometimes elaborately
decorated darts, or shoot arrows at the
hoop, seeking to hit an exact spot or find the
hoop's center. A variation has players throwing
short spears instead of darts while running
after a rolling hoop.</p>

<p>One of the continent's most ancient toys is
the buzzer, a disk-shaped piece of wood, bone,
or pottery pierced with two holes, through
which a deerskin thong or piece of doubledover
sinew, about two feet long, is passed. The
object is placed at the center of the doubled
thong and spun rapidly by the winding and
unwinding of the thong, with the rhythmic
pressure of the hands and arms moving inward
and pulling outward on the thong in the
manner of playing an accordion. The thong,
stretched tight between the hands, supports
the buzzer, which functions as a flywheel. The
Gros Ventres and the Lakotas used a knee
bone or knucklebone as a buzzer; other tribes
used painted and patterned wooden disks that
would change color (for example, red and
yellow becoming orange) and apparent shape
as the buzzer spun. The term "buzzer" derives
from the sound made while the bone, wood,
or pottery piece is rotated clockwise and then
counterclockwise at high speed.</p>

<p>Plains Indians also fashioned many designs
of spinning tops of wood, bone, and horn; the
Crees of Alberta as well as the Crows of Montana
and the Lakotas crafted tops of solid
horn, which children kept spinning with rawhide
whips.</p>

<p>Balls for numerous kinds of play were crafted
from hardwood, buckskin filled with rag or
animal hair, and even pebbles covered with
yarn. In Montana, the Northern Cheyennes
and Crows, and in North Dakota the Mandans,
developed a soft ball of buckskin, antelope
hair, or dyed porcupine quills wrapped
with cord, which they kicked gently in the air
and caught on the top of the foot. A girl's
toy, it was nearly identical to the modern
"hacky sack."</p>

<p>Many Plains Indian children fashioned human
and animal forms (especially horses and
buffaloes) of red-brown sun-dried mud; Lakota
children made clay animal forms and
mixed vertebra from buffalo, deer, or antelope
and their imagination to create "bone ponies."
Children would gather the bleached bones
into herds or use them in single combat or
races. These folk toys were sometimes copied
by white settlers' families in the nineteenth
century.</p>

<p>Native American dolls were nearly universal,
with great variations in design, color, and
sophistication. Construction materials ranged
from the simplest combinations of fabric tied
to a forked stick to finely finished figures with
beaded deerskin dresses, sometimes attached
to miniature cradleboards. Today, replicas of
these latter dolls are sold widely at reservation
gift shops.</p>

<p>Great Plains settlers brought with them a
small number of notable folk designs from
Europe and the eastern United States, including
the "limberjack," an Irish and Scandinavian
dancing figure used to accentuate Celtic
musical rhythms; carved, brilliantly painted
Scandinavian toy animals; and carved dolls.
Rag dolls had become common in New England
following the Revolutionary War, took
up little space, and traveled well. But because
of the hardships involved in settling the Plains,
children's amenities, including folk toys, were
often lost.</p>

<p>Folk toys could be constructed by parents
or other adults at a final destination once
housing, a water supply, and other necessities
were established. Miniature cradles and rocking
horses were fashioned using a saw, jackknife,
hammer, and nails. Additional sturdy
folk toys, including stilts, swings, and seesaws
were made on the spot from scraps of available
wood, providing years of delight to Great
Plains children.</p>

<closer>
<signed>John R. Nelson Jr.<lb/>
University of Massachusetts-Amherst</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Culin, Robert Stewart. <title level="m">Games of the North American Indians</title>.
Washington <hi rend="smallcaps">DC</hi>: Government Printing Office, 1907.</bibl>
<bibl>Nelson, John R. Jr. <title level="m">American Folk Toys</title>. Newtown <hi rend="smallcaps">CT</hi>:
Taunton Press, 1998.</bibl> <bibl>Toelken, Barre. <title level="m">The Dynamics of Folklore</title>. Boston: Houghton Mifflin Company, 1979.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>