<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fil.011">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main"><hi rend="italic">Cimarron</hi></title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>William M. Wehrbein</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fil.011</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Wehrbein, William M.">William M. Wehrbein</author>. <title level="a">"<hi rend="italic">Cimarron</hi>."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">261-262</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-09</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main"><hi rend="italic">CIMARRON</hi></head>
<figure n="egp.fil.011" rend="granted" type="noclick">
<figDesc>Theatrical Release Poster</figDesc>
</figure>    

<p>Released in 1931, <title>Cimarron</title> was directed by
Wesley Ruggles, with a script by Howard Estabrook
and Edna Ferber, based on her novel.
The film won Academy Awards for best picture,
art direction, and adapted screenplay.</p>

<p>One of the earliest epic films of the sound
era, <title>Cimarron</title> (Spanish for "wild and unruly"
and the name of a river in Oklahoma and
Kansas) traces the history of the state of Oklahoma
through its first forty years, beginning
with the great land rush of April 22, 1889,
when two million acres were opened to settlement.
Although cheated out of his claim,
Yancy Cravat (Richard Dix), a lawyer and
newspaperman, moves his wife, Sabra (Irene
Dunne), and child from her family's home in
Wichita to the instant boomtown of Osage,
Oklahoma. Well liked by nearly everyone,
Cravat metes out two-gun justice to the town
bully during a church meeting in the town's
gambling tent and later kills an old friend who
has become an outlaw. Lured by the spirit of
adventure, Cravat abandons his family and
lights out for the Cherokee Strip when it
opens in 1893. Besides raising their two children,
Sabra publishes Yancy's newspaper, leaving
his name on the masthead. He returns after
serving in the Spanish-American War and
runs unsuccessfully for governor when the
territory becomes a state in 1907. Once again
he takes off for new adventures, leaving the
paper in his wife's hands. By 1929 Oklahoma is
in an oil boom, Osage is a modern city, the
newspaper is a success, and Sabra, never giving
up hope for her husband's return, has
been elected to Congress. While touring the
oil fields with other dignitaries she discovers
her mortally injured husband, now an anonymous
drifter hired as a roughneck. In the final
shot, a statue unveiled in the city park honoring
Oklahoma pioneers bears an unmistakable
resemblance to Yancy Cravat.</p>

<p><title>Cimarron</title> is the saga of the last frontier and
the building of an empire. As seen in consecutive
shots of its main street, Osage transforms
in stages from tents and hastily thrown up
shacks to a bustling modern city with automobiles,
streetcars, and skyscrapers. The film
also includes the theme, common in many
Westerns, of the passing of the West from
wide-open spaces to settled farms and towns.
Yancy civilizes Osage with his six-gun, and he
consistently stands for tolerance and progressive
policies toward Native Americans. Ironically,
it is practical Sabra, much less tolerant
and more conventional in her attitudes about
race and society, who is eventually elected to
Congress, while her husband dies in obscurity.</p>

<p>Today the film looks slow, stilted, and talky,
and Dix's performance, filled with histrionics,
seems almost a self-parody. In addition, humor
based on racial and physical stereotypes
may make modern audiences wince. The
opening scene of the 1889 land rush, however,
is one of the most exciting action sequences in
cinema. Unfortunately, nothing else in the
film has so much energy.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">IMAGES AND ICONS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ii.003">Boomers</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>William M. Wehrbein<lb/>
Nebraska Wesleyan University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Fenin, George N., and William K. Everson. <title level="m">The Western: From Silents to the Seventies</title>. New York: Grossman, 1973.</bibl>
<bibl>Wright, Will. <title level="m">Six Guns and Society: A Structural Study of the Western</title>. Berkeley: University of California Press, 1975.</bibl>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>