<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.pg.023 SYSTEM "egp.pg.023.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.pg.023">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Federal Government, Canada</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Doreen Barrie</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.pg.023</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Barrie, Doreen">Doreen Barrie</author>. <title level="a">"Federal Government, Canada."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">663-664</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-29</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">FEDERAL GOVERNMENT, CANADA</head>

<figure n="egp.pg.023" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Political cartoon, "Putting on the Screws"</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Most of the area covered by Canada's three
Prairie Provinces was purchased by the federal
government from the Hudson's Bay Company
in 1868. The Canadian Plains was a sparsely
populated frontier, and the government was
anxious to settle the region quickly and uniformly.
The North-West Mounted Police force
was established, and the government in Ottawa
embarked on an aggressive campaign to
populate the area. To achieve this goal, control
over the land and natural resources of the
western interior was retained by the federal
government. In a sense, the three Prairie Provinces
are "Children of Confederation" in that
they had not existed as self-governing colonies
prior to Canadian Confederation in 1867.
Manitoba attained provincial status in 1870,
but Saskatchewan and Alberta did not become
provinces until 1905.</p>

<p>The way in which the Prairie Provinces became
part of Canada has given rise to the phenomenon
of western alienation. This includes
specific complaints about discriminatory
treatment, as well as the pervasive feeling
among its citizens that Manitoba, Saskatchewan,
and Alberta are second-class provinces.
They had to wait until 1930 to gain ownership
of their land and natural resources. In the
American Plains states and in the West more
generally, federal ownership and control over
large tracts of land created similar resentment.</p>

<p>Settlers to the Prairies came in waves between
the turn of the twentieth century and
World War II. They came with high expectations
fed by extravagant advertising campaigns
launched by the federal government and the
Canadian Pacific Railway. The Prairies were
described as a veritable Garden of Eden. Many
newcomers were defeated by the weather, the
uncertainty of the grain trade, and difficulty in
coaxing a crop out of virgin soil.</p>

<p>Ottawa's policies on tariffs, its decisions on
the railway, and its primary role in immigration
and homesteading had a crucial impact
on the evolution of the Prairie Provinces. Until
the onset of World War II, these provinces
were isolated from the rest of the country and
united in their dependence on the wheat
economy. A shared sense of grievance added
to their cohesion: national policies favoring
Central Canada, particularly in the early years,
fueled the perception that the federal government
was a remote, insensitive instrument of
the manufacturing sector located at the center.
There was some justification for these sentiments,
since federal domination of the region
in its formative years was unparalleled in the
rest of the country.</p>

<p>Common experiences led to a cross-fertilization
of ideas on the agrarian frontier on
both sides of the international boundary.
They were part of the raw material from
which populism and nonpartisan ideals were
constructed. Ideas popularized by the Nonpartisan
League, which originated in North
Dakota, were picked up on the Canadian
Plains. League candidates were unsuccessful in
elections during World War I, but nonpartisan
sentiments turned out to be more durable.
Canada's political system proved more
permeable to new political parties spawned by
Prairie discontent; some survive to this day.</p>

<p>More than a century after Canadian Confederation,
an identity of interest no longer
binds the Prairie Provinces. Their economies
have diversified, and powerful provincial governments
now articulate the interests and air
the grievances of their citizens. However, it is
still possible for provincial premiers to mobilize
the population by fanning the flames of
western alienation. For example, natural resource
ownership remains a flashpoint in Alberta,
which is home to the bulk of Canada's
conventional petroleum resources. Any hint
of federal intrusion into this industry is vigorously
resisted. There has been minimal change
in the division of powers. However, the importance
of the powers conferred on the provinces
has increased dramatically, while federal responsibilities
have declined in importance.</p>

<p>Hinterland status and the problem of being
a relatively small population continue to frustrate
citizens of the Prairies, to whom the federal
government seems as remote as it was before
technology compressed time and space.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">INDUSTRY</hi>: <ref n="egp.ind.046">Petroleum, Canada</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Doreen Barrie<lb/>
University of Calgary</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Francis, R. Douglas, and Howard Palmer. <title level="m">The Prairie
West: Historical Readings</title>. Edmonton: Pica Pica Press,
1985.</bibl> <bibl>Lower, J. Arthur. <title level="m">Western Canada: An Outline History</title>.
Vancouver: Douglas and McIntyre, 1983.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>