<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.afam.018">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Exodusters</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Jack Ravage</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.afam.018</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Ravage, Jack">Jack Ravage</author>. <title level="a">"Exodusters."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">14</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-12-03</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">EXODUSTERS</head>

<p>Tens of thousands of African Americans
moved into the Great Plains to begin new lives
during the last three decades of the nineteenth
century. These Plains settlers have often been
referred to as Exodusters. Beginning in the
1870s and continuing into the 1890s, the Exodusters
settled in all Great Plains states and
territories, even as far north as Canada, but
Kansas and what would become Oklahoma
Territory were the main destinations.</p>

<p>Several factors&#8211;both push and pull&#8211;help
explain this sudden and massive migration.
Shortly after the end of the Civil War, western
territories and states searched for ways to entice
prospective settlers. Increased populations
would bring statehood for territories
and profits for land speculators and railroads,
who owned a great deal of land and property.
Territorial and state governments and the U.S.
Congress passed a variety of land acts and
other provisions to attract people to the region.
The 1862 Homestead Act, for example,
opened up opportunities for African Americans
just as for other Americans. Local governments,
private individuals, and companies
also disseminated elaborate brochures, and
newspaper and periodical advertisements solicited
black individuals and families to relocate
to the Plains. The often-unscrupulous
western developers targeted African Americans
because of a belief that they would be
easy to attract with offers of free or low-cost
land. Seldom did boosters and speculators admit
that farming conditions, climate, and access
to water were not what these immigrants
were used to.</p>

<p>Although territorial and federal governments
offered inducements to African
Americans, a more immediate cause of black
migration was the dire conditions of the post-
Reconstruction South. The end of Reconstruction
in 1877 led to increased racial violence,
disfranchisement, loss of civil rights,
and lack of economic opportunity for southern
blacks. These hardships, combined with
rumors of free transportation, free land, and
even monetary gifts, led to a massive migration
of African Americans to the Great Plains during
the late 1870s. Men such as Henry Adams of
Louisiana and Benjamin "Pap" Singleton of
Tennessee organized and led large numbers of
southern blacks to Kansas. Singleton made
several trips to Kansas during the early 1870s
and helped found several black colonies.</p>

<p>The migrations of 1879&#8211;in which 6,000 African
Americans settled in Kansas&#8211;took on
a religious tone. African American migrants
saw themselves as taking part in a biblical exodus,
with Kansas as the promised land. In
1879, often referred to as the Exodus Year,
more than 20,000 black men, women, and
children passed through St. Louis to Kansas
and points west. Many never reached Kansas,
settling instead in urban areas such as Kansas
City, Missouri. More than 6,000, however, settled
in rural Kansas towns, including all-black
towns such as Nicodemus. This Plains town,
platted in Graham County, Kansas, in 1877,
is the best-known black town in the Great
Plains. By 1879 it had a population of more
than 600, making it the largest community in
Kansas north of the Kansas Pacific Railroad.
While Nicodemus was a major destination, it
was only one of many all-black towns established
in the Central Plains in the last decades
of the nineteenth century. Other black towns
included Langston, Oklahoma, founded in
1890; Boley, Oklahoma, founded in 1904; and
Dewitty, Nebraska, also founded in 1904.</p>

<p>The Exodusters often had dreams of recreating
the lush farmlands of their native
states only to find that the unpredictable climate
of the Great Plains thwarted their ambitions.
By the late 1800s many had returned
to their home states, but some, as in Nicodemus,
learned to adapt to the new environment,
use fertilizers, build water-diversion
channels, and survive the harsh winters. The
pioneers of African American settlement in
the Great Plains&#8211;the Exodusters&#8211;anticipated
the much larger black migrations from the
South after 1910, migrations that were increasingly
directed at large Plains cities.</p>


<closer>
<signed>Jack Ravage<lb/>
University of Wyoming</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Athearn, G. Robert. <title level="m">In Search of Canaan: Black Migration
to Kansas, 1879–1880</title>. Lawrence: Regents Press of Kansas,
1978.</bibl> <bibl>Painter, Nell Irvin. <title level="m">Exodusters: Black Migration to
Kansas after Reconstruction</title>. New York: Alfred A. Knopf,
1976.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>