<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->


<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.arc.036">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Nebraska State Capitol</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Robert Haller</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.arc.036</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Haller, Robert">Robert Haller</author>. <title level="a">"Nebraska State Capitol."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">89</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-13</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">NEBRASKA STATE CAPITOL</head>

<p>The present Nebraska State Capitol was authorized
by the legislature in 1918 as a memorial
replacement of the crumbling second capitol.
The Nebraska State Capitol Commission
adopted Omaha architect Thomas Rogers
Kimball's novel procedure for the choosing of
an architect. They pitted three Nebraska architects
against seven invited outsiders in a
double-blind competition: anonymous submissions
to an unidentified panel of judges.
Each architect submitted with his drawing a
500-word essay describing the use of a sculptor,
a muralist, and a landscapist in the realization
of the building on its site. Bertram
Grosvenor Goodhue's tall shaft in the center of
a three-story square base won the judges'
immediate acceptance as symbolizing the upward
aspirations of a people dwelling on the
level Plains. Construction began in 1922, and
the building was dedicated in 1934, each year's
building progress precisely accommodated to
the annual legislative appropriation. Goodhue
died in 1924, leaving his office and the commission
to supervise the building's completion.</p>

<p>The building integrates a variety of monumental
architectural styles. The shaft recalls
the Pharos lighthouse at Alexandria, the north
front has the form of the Great Temple of
Amon at Karnak, the balustrades and capitals
are elements of classical temples, and the
vaulting and rotundas are modeled on Byzantine
and Gothic structures. The stone was
quarried in Italy and Indiana, and the woods
and metals were specifically chosen for their
uses. Fixtures and decorations incorporate
Plains-specific motifs such as maize and the
buffalo head as well as more traditional elements
such as the fasces.</p>

<p>Goodhue had for twenty-five years integrated
the sculpture of Lee Lawrie into his
buildings. In 1921 he added young mosaic
muralist Hildreth Meiere to his artistic collaboration.
In 1923 he added University of Nebraska
philosophy professor Hartley Burr Alexander
as "thematic consultant." Initially
hired to write inscriptions, his pointed criticisms
of the Lawrie flying buffalo led to an
invitation to rewrite the artistic program. He
then worked intensively by mail with Meiere
and Lawrie from their first drawings to the
final placement of their works in the building.</p>

<p>From a distance, the first feature of this integrated
and collaborative artistic program
seen above the gold-leafed dome is The Sower,
a huge figure by Lawrie (inspired by French
sculptor Aime Millet) whose seeds, visually
and symbolically, bring the Plains to life. The
cornice relief panels that circle the building
depict the history of western law. Near the
north steps are four balustrade reliefs in the
Mayan style that represent the buffalo and
maize as sacred gifts to Native cultures. The
entrance to the building is surmounted by a
relief that depicts against a gold background
the arrival of pioneer settlers to the Plains.
The floors of the Great Hall and Rotunda are
paved in black-and-white mosaics that render
cosmic and geologic evolution in a dramatic
form, including precise copies of drawings by
E. H. Barbour of the Nebraska State Museum
of fossils discovered in the Plains. In the East
Chamber the ceiling mosaics are in the style
of Sioux painting and beadwork and depict a
hunt, hoeing, a war party, and a council fire.</p>

<p>Alexander's inscriptions, while recalling
classical and traditional sources, express his
conception of the state as a collective body
rediscovering its common goals in the building
of its "House of State." The thematic program,
left unfinished in 1934, was completed
in 1996 with the dedication of eight murals by
Omaha artist Stephen Roberts in the Memorial
Chamber.</p>

<p><ref target="http://capitol.org/">Nebraska State Capitol</ref> website.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Robert Haller<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln<lb/>
</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Luebke, Frederick, ed. <title level="m">A Harmony of the Arts: The Nebraska State Capitol</title>. Lincoln: University of Nebraska
Press, 1990.</bibl> <bibl>Whitaker, Charles Harris, ed. <title level="m">Bertram Grosvenor Goodhue, Architect and Master of Many Arts</title>. New
York: Press of the American Institute of Architects, 1925.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>