<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.lt.003 SYSTEM "egp.lt.003.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.lt.003">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Baum, L. Frank (1856-1919)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Nancy Tystad Koupal</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.lt.003</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Koupal, Nancy Tystad">Nancy Tystad Koupal</author>. <title level="a">"Baum, L. Frank (1856-1919)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">474</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-09</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">BAUM, L. FRANK (1856-1919)</head>

<figure n="egp.lt.003" rend="granted">
<figDesc>L. Frank Baum, ca. 1900</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Nine years before he wrote his first children's
book, Lyman Frank Baum followed the frontier
promise of prosperity to Dakota Territory,
embarking on an experience that would contribute
greatly to the themes and scenes of his
great American fairy tales about the Land of
Oz. Critics have long noted that <title level="m">The Wizard of Oz</title> (1900) celebrates the values of the agrarian
heartland and provided the nation with its
first recognizably American (as opposed to
European) fairyland. The book and its author
have also had lasting impacts on the culture
and image of the Great Plains region, from
Kansas to North and South Dakota.</p>

<p>Born into a wealthy family in Chittenango,
New York, on May 15, 1856, Baum sampled a
variety of careers, most involving writing and
publishing. When he married Maud Gage, the
youngest daughter of national suffãrage activist
Matilda Joslyn Gage, the couple settled in Syracuse,
New York, before the birth of the first
of their four sons in December 1883. For the
next five years Baum worked in a family business
that made axle grease. When the business,
like many of his earlier enterprises,
failed, Baum looked around for new opportunities.
In the early 1880s many of Baum's
neighbors, among them members of his wife's
family, had headed west to participate in
Dakota Territory's boom (1879-87). After a
whirlwind trip to the area in September 1888
Baum packed up his family and moved to Aberdeen,
a county-seat town in the northeastern
corner of what is now South Dakota,
where he established Baum's Bazaar to sell a
wide variety of luxury goods just as the Dakota
boom ended.</p>

<p>By the winter of 1889 drought conditions
had brought actual starvation to parts of Dakota,
and during the next five years almost
3,000 people abandoned the Aberdeen service
area. Baum's Bazaar failed, and in January
1890 Baum took over the weekly newspaper
of a fellow Syracuse transplant and began a
fifteen-month career as western editor and job
printer. His <title level="j">Aberdeen Saturday Pioneer</title> reveals
in depth his attitudes about politics, suffrage,
tolerance, and religion, offering an important
key to the themes that later surface in Baum's
fiction, especially his fourteen Oz books.</p>

<p>The year 1890 provided an incredible range
of events for an observant editor to comment
upon. South Dakota had become a state on
November 2, 1889, and the political events of
its first year included the formation of an independent
party that would evolve into the
Populist Party. A campaign to give women the
vote brought national personalities such as
Carrie Chapman Catt and Susan B. Anthony
to stump the state for suffrage, while the
Ghost Dance movement among the Lakotas
attracted Gen. Nelson Miles and Buffalo Bill
Cody. Temperance advocates and liquor dealers
exchanged heated rhetoric on the issue of
prohibition. To contribute barbed comments
to the political brew, Baum created a weekly
satirical column entitled "Our Landlady." In
April 1891, however, economic conditions
forced the editor and his family to join the
exodus from Dakota.</p>

<p>From Aberdeen Baum went to Chicago,
where he worked as a newspaper editor, crockery
salesman, and editor of a trade journal
before beginning to write children's books at
the age of forty-one. From 1897 until his death
in Hollywood, California, on May 5, 1919,
Baum wrote more than seventy books, many
under pseudonyms, but it is <title level="m">The Wizard of Oz</title>
(1900) that is most important. In it Baum created
a fairy tale that has become a cultural
symbol, largely through adaptation to stage
and screen (beginning with a musical comedy
in 1902). Its characters, attitudes, and values
are all distinctly American. Unfortunately,
its depiction of Kansas as a drab, droughtstricken
hinterland has affected the region for
years. On the positive side, the book also created
Dorothy Gale, a strong heroine who embodies
the assertiveness and ability of those
who settled the Plains.</p>

<p><title level="m">The Wizard of Oz</title> also contains an allegorical
commentary on American politics and the
Populist movement of the Great Plains region.
The other Oz books, the next of which is <title level="m">The Marvelous Land of Oz</title> (1904), continue the tradition
of strong female characters and add allegorical
commentary on women's rights and
utopian concepts. The Dakota prairie and its
wildlife&#8211;prairie dogs, bison, gophers, crows,
and grasshoppers&#8211;also provided the setting
and characters for some of Baum's shorter fiction,
his "Animal Fairy Tales," which appeared
in the <title level="m">Delineator</title> in 1905, and the "Tinkle
Tales," a series of small books for younger children
that appeared in 1906 and 1907.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">FILM</hi>: <ref n="egp.fil.065"><hi rend="italic">The Wizard of Oz</hi></ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">IMAGES
AND ICONS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ii.027">Gale, Dorothy</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">POLITICS AND
GOVERNMENT</hi>: <ref n="egp.pg.063">Populists (People's Party)</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Nancy Tystad Koupal<lb/>
South Dakota State Historical Society</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Baum, Frank Joslyn, and Russell P. MacFall. <title level="m">To Please a Child: A Biography of L. Frank Baum, Royal Historian of Oz</title>. Chicago: Reilly and Lee, 1961.</bibl> <bibl>Baum, L. Frank. <title level="m">Our Landlady</title>, edited and annotated by Nancy Tystad Koupal.
Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1996.</bibl> <bibl>Koupal,
Nancy Tystad. "The Wonderful Wizard of the West: L.
Frank Baum in South Dakota, 1888–91." <title level="j">Great Plains Quarterly</title> 9 (1989): 203–15.</bibl>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>