<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.pe.064">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Weeds</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Sva&#357;a M. Louda</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.pe.064</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Louda, Sva&#357;a M.">Sva&#357;a M. Louda</author>. <title level="a">"Weeds."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">641-642</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-27</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">WEEDS</head>

<p>According to the U.S. Department of Agriculture,
countless hours and millions of dollars
are spent each year to control weeds,
and millions more&#8211;hours and dollars&#8211;are
lost in yield reductions. However, what exactly
is a weed? And what makes a plant a weed?
Many people are surprised to learn that a
weed is technically "a plant out of place." So
one person's weed can be someone else's salad
green, pharmaceutical, transgenic crop, or
wildflower!</p>

<p>What are the characteristics of plants that
often grow out of place? One characteristic
is a tendency to reach high numbers rapidly
and to replace or slow the growth of more
desirable plants. Traits allowing rapid population
growth include early development, fast
reproduction, and many long-lived seeds.
Structures that aid dispersal often help weedy
plants colonize far and wide. Finally, many
weeds lack effective enemies, such as insects
and diseases that reduce plant growth and
reproduction.</p>

<p>Most of the economically important weeds
in the Plains were introduced, with many
coming from Eurasia; most arrived as contaminants
of seed brought in to expand agriculture.
While each list will be a little different,
only a few plants really cause serious problems.
Less than 1 percent of the plants listed in
the <title level="m">Flora of the Great Plains</title> are considered
serious weeds, and only 1 percent or so of
those are serious enough to be designated
as legally noxious. Similar ratios have been
found in other regions too, leading to the
"tens rule." This rule states that, on average,
one out of ten species that are introduced actually
establish, and one out of those ten species
escape into the wild, and then one out of
the ten that escape become pests (0.1 percent).</p>

<p>Given the agricultural economy of the region,
weedy plants have a special importance
in the Great Plains. Plants that are good at
competing with crops or forage plants in pastures
and rangeland create problems. Some
weeds can reduce crop yields dramatically,
such as heavy stands of pennycress (<hi rend="italic">Thlaspi
arvense</hi> L.) in winter wheat or annual grasses
like giant foxtail (<hi rend="italic">Setaria faberi</hi> Herrm.) in row
crops. Control of weeds in crops adds to the
cost of food production. Plants that invade our
gardens, lawns, and golf courses cause consternation,
and their control can be expensive,
economically and environmentally. Finally
plants that invade native plant communities in
parks, preserves, and natural roadside stands
of prairie jeopardize natural heritage.</p>

<p>Options for reducing weed densities include
mechanical, cultural, chemical, and biological
methods. Each method has advantages and
disadvantages. Mechanical methods include
hand cutting and tilling. The advantages, including
relatively low input costs, are balanced
against disadvantages, such as the time and
labor needed to cut weeds. Cultural methods
involve reducing the weed's effects on desired
plants by altering fertility, managing grass
growth, or timing disturbances to suppress
weed performance. The advantages are longerterm
decreases in weed densities, while the disadvantages
include a need for tighter planning
and possibly added inputs. Chemical control
involves spraying with selective or broadspectrum
herbicides. This has the advantages
of speed and coverage but the disadvantages of
chemical costs, increasing resistance of weeds,
and environmental release of chemicals. Biological
control involves the use of natural enemies
to lower weed densities, either by introducing
foreign or engineered species or by
augmenting native enemies that feed on the
weed. Here the advantages are persistence and
low maintenance costs, while the disadvantages
are more limited control and the risk of
side effects to forage and native species. Integrated
weed management programs combine
methods that reduce weeds and enhance the
growth of desired plants. Clearly the strategy
that provides for effective limitation of weed
density with the smallest economic and environmental
cost is preferred.</p>

<p>Weed control does not necessarily mean extermination.
Once a species is established it is
usually impossible, or at least extremely expensive,
to eradicate. Weed control is really a
management issue. The issue is a challenging
one, involving trade-offs and compromises.
One compromise is increasing the tolerance
for the presence of some noneconomic, non-environmentally
threatening weeds. An indiscriminate
"cure" can sometimes be worse than
the problem, reducing multiple beneficial species
along with the targeted pest plant species.
This lesson was learned the hard way, when the
side efects of broad-spectrum pesticides and
generalist biocontrol agents became evident.</p>

<p>However, weedy species can be valuable as
well. For example, some weeds contain chemical
compounds of medicinal values (e.g., thistles),
and many plant compounds have yet to
be researched or used. Others contain genetic
material with clues to effective pest control,
drought tolerance, or growth acceleration. Still
others are important for wildlife, and many
contribute to our "feeling of nature" when
outdoors. Economically useful weedy plants in
the Plains include dandelion for greens, chamomile
for tea, thistles for honeybees, and
countless species for cover and soil retention.
It is likely that researchers will find that wild
weedy plants hold secrets to problems that
have yet to be identified. So a weed is a potentially
useful plant that is sometimes out of
place and in the way. Knowing this can increase
the ability to appreciate and use plants, while
limiting their numbers where it really matters.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Sva&#357;a M. Louda<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Great Plains Flora Association. <title level="m">Flora of the Great Plains</title>.
Lawrence: University Press of Kansas, 1987.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>