<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.lt.001 SYSTEM "egp.lt.001.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.lt.001">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Literary Traditions</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Frances W. Kaye</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.lt.001</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Kayes, Frances W.">Frances W. Kaye</author>. <title level="a">"Literary Traditions."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">469-473</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-09</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">LITERARY TRADITIONS</head>

<p>Whatever stories the wolves tell, they do not
tell to human ears, and the songs of the earliest
hunter-gatherers in the Great Plains are
now lost to memory. Nonetheless, the extant
literatures of the Great Plains are plentiful,
rich, and diverse.</p>

<p>The tradition began with the oral literatures
of the many Native nations who have
lived in the area and with the folktales and
dramas of the early European and mixed-blood
peoples. The first written literature to
come from the Plains was the utilitarian recording
of tribal histories as winter counts
and the diaries and letters from early European
American explorers. In most people's
minds, Plains literature is probably associated
with the Wild West and with tales that pit humans
against a vast and harsh environment or
"cowboys" against "Indians," and certainly literature
of this sort has been both extremely
popular and influential in forming the American
self-identity. Popular Prairie fiction in
Canada, by contrast, featured order and community.
Plains writers in both the United
States and Canada also produced a body of
realistic fiction dealing with European American
settlement and ways of living on the land.
Poetry flourishes, though drama has not really
become naturalized on the Plains except in the
Prairie Provinces of Canada. Meanwhile, the
last twenty years have seen a renaissance of
writing by Native peoples and other longtime
cultures of the Plains, as M&#233;tis, Blackfeet, and
Chicano peoples, among others, have found a
voice in fiction and poetry.</p>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Native Oral Literatures</head>

<p>Living oral tradition as well as transcriptions
by literate observers have preserved much oral
literature. Narratives of a sacred or semisacred
nature explain the origins of the universe, of
the particular nation, of the hero figures of the
nation, and of the holy ceremonies of the people.
Thus the Blackfeet tell how Napi (Old Man)
created the universe, and the Kiowa tell of how
that nation came into this world through a hollow
log. White Buffalo Woman brought the sacred
pipe to the Lakotas, and the animals in the
medicine lodges gave curing ceremonies to the
Pawnee doctors. Orphan Boy among the Omahas,
the Tai-Me twins among the Kiowas, and
Scarface among the Blackfeet are heroes with
long story cycles. Trickster, called Nanabush
or Nanapush among the Ojibwas and Crees,
Iktome among the Lakotas, and many other
names in other languages, is a ubiquitous figure
in these narratives. The Winnebagos have a particularly
well-developed Trickster cycle, documented
by Paul Radin in the early part of the
twentieth century and more recently by Winnebago
storyteller Felix White. Trickster is neither
good nor evil but rather a representation of the
human spirit at its most basic level, creation and
destruction inextricably mixed.</p>

<p>Songs, chants, and prayers are also characteristic
of traditional oral Plains literatures.
Much oral literature consists of events in the
lives of the people, gossip, campfire stories,
and examples of both proper and improper
behavior to be told to young people. Winter
counts are such ordinary happenings compiled
by year, and they serve as both a calendar
and a mnemonic device for remembering and
recounting the history of the people. Petroglyphs
(writing on stone), hide paintings, and,
from the nineteenth and twentieth centuries,
ledger book drawings are other pictorial narratives
of events.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Mexican Folk Literature</head>

<p>Much of what is now the Southern Plains of
the United States was first colonized by Spain
and later controlled by Mexico, so it is not
surprising that the population of the area, a
racial and cultural mixture of Spanish and Indian,
should support a folk literature similar
to that of Mexico. Semisacred legends regarding
the Virgin of Guadalupe have always been
important to the Spanish speakers of the
Southern Plains, as to other Mexicans. Folk
pageants such as dramas based on the Spanish
tradition or spectacles showing the Spanish
conquest of the Moors or other heroic and
romantic action were part of village life.</p>

<p>After the Mexican War and the partition of
the territory that had been part of Mexico, the
border began to play a part in folk narrative,
particularly in the <hi rend="italic">corridos</hi>, long ballads often
printed on cheap broadsheets and sung in the
streets. Typically, a <hi rend="italic">corrido</hi> describes a Mexican
outlaw and folk hero who outwits the
Texas Rangers and other gringos sent to capture
him.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Explorers and Other Travelers</head>

<p>The first non-Native literature of the Great
Plains consists of the journals of predominantly
European and European American explorers.
These men ventured out into the
Plains for various pragmatic reasons. They
were careful to describe the terrain, its flora
and fauna, its human inhabitants, and the patterns
of social and economic trade and travel.
Missionaries and Indian agents also traveled
about the Plains in the eighteenth and nineteenth
centuries, recording in journals and
letters home what they saw and what they
thought. By the mid–nineteenth century, professional
travelers like Washington Irving and
Francis Parkman were following in the literal
steps of the explorers and writing about <title level="m">A Tour on the Prairies</title> (1835) and <title level="m">The Oregon Trail</title> (1849). Increasing numbers of men and
women, professional and amateur writers,
traveled west and recorded their experiences.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Plains Fiction</head>

<p>Not until James Fenimore Cooper's <title level="m">The Prairie</title>
(1827), written in Paris by a man who had
never been west of the Alleghenies, did European-
style fiction and poetry deal with the
Great Plains. Cooper was extremely influential
for American literature in general but particularly
so for Plains literature. His legacy was
twofold, leading to the popular Western, beginning
with the dime novel, and also to the
nonformula Western, the realistic agrarian or
small-town novel. The development of a written
European American literature on the Canadian
Prairies followed a different pattern
and came later.</p>

<p>In both popular and nonformula Plains literature,
in both Canada and the United States,
the land has been a major force. The vast expanse
of earth and sky, at once uplifting and
humbling, shapes the lives of all who dwell
upon the grasslands of North America. Even
in urban literature, where a distinctive Plains
environment is marked more by cultural and
ethnic enclaves and mixes than by the land
itself, the very air proclaims a place that
is unlike either East or West. In the mid.
nineteenth century, when the United States
was first creating for itself a national identity
that went beyond the ideals of the American
Revolution, poets, philosophers, and painters
all postulated that while Europe might have
history, America had Nature and therefore a
close and transcendental relationship with a
deity or first force. This sense of renewal in
nature affected Plains writers most strongly. In
the vastness of the Plains there was renewal
and communion with nature.</p>

<p>Within that nature there was also the Indian,
split into the "noble savage'' and the
"bloodthirsty redskin." In such formulations,
the Indian was always an "other" against
whom the white characters defined themselves
rather than a character deserving development
in his or her own right. Again,
Cooper set the pattern, with the "good" Mohicans
and "bad" Mingos of New York State
transformed into the "good" Pawnees and
"bad" Sioux of the Plains who help or hinder
Leatherstocking and his various white friends
and antagonists.</p>

<p>In the United States the genre Western,
from the dime novel to John Wayne and from
Zane Grey to Louis L'Amour, has become a
formative, though excluding, national myth,
the embodiment of the "rugged individual"
who takes the law into his (rarely her) own
hands and plows ahead, overcoming obstacles.
The conventions of the Western, of the
man living without and above the law, also
shaped the cop movie, the hard-boiled detective,
and the space fantasy. Cooper's hero,
Natty Bumppo, the eponymous Leatherstocking,
a white man living outside both white and
Indian society and claiming a higher moral
law than the conventions of either, is the first
fully developed representative of a European
American type.</p>

<p>Leatherstocking's popularity fitted in with
other frontier culture of the time, particularly
that of the Great Plains frontier. Thus the fictional
"autobiographies" of Daniel Boone and
Davy Crockett as well as of a host of lesser-known
or truly fictional frontiersmen showed
a hero who was close to nature. Wild and
rowdy he might be, but he was also eventually
a force for what an emerging society saw as an
ideal of order. He venerated "good" women
but saw them as representatives of an unduly
moralistic and legalistic order that he repudiated.
Except in the "autobiographies," he
rarely married. The frontier narrative became
truly formulaic with the dime novels. As the
Deadeye Dick series shows, the hero could
be a lawman or an outlaw or swap back and
forth. Calamity Jane was a female version of
this hero, but sagas featuring such heroines
were more likely than those of the male heroes
to be marked by unhappy love affairs.</p>

<p>Although the North American settlement
frontier did not close in 1890, as the Bureau
of the Census claimed, the massive population
movement in twentieth- and twenty-first-century
North America has been from the farms
and small towns to the cities. The mythologized
West became the setting for what was frankly
escape literature only a generation after the
Plains had offered a real escape. Owen Wister's
<title level="m">The Virginian</title> (1902) is the book that marks this
apotheosis of the West as a paradise lost. Wister,
a Philadelphia lawyer, found his own restorative
in the clean air and vast spaces of Wyoming, and
his fable of the romance between a Virginia
cowboy and a Vermont schoolmarm in Wyoming
proved enormously successful and durable.
<title level="m">The Virginian</title>, like most Westerns, reflects
a great admiration for violence. In Wister's
terms, his heroine, Molly, represents the overly
moralistic code of "snivilization," as he called it,
but she is able to come through in a crisis and
rally to her man after he kills the villain, Trampas,
in a shoot-out. The book reflects Wister's
elitist biases as well as the Anglo-Saxon nationalism
that flourished in the decade of the
Spanish-American War and was built on the
casual denigration of Indians that was implicit
in Cooper's "noble savage" formulations. For
Wister, the true noble savage was the Anglo-
Saxon, whose "nobility" led to lynch laws and
commercial success, while the "Indians" were
only a plot convention, "bloodthirsty savages"
whose attack on the hero allowed the heroine to
nurse him back to health and to fall in love.</p>

<p>The Virginian's immediate successors were
genial heroes whose appeal has been mostly to
a juvenile audience. <title level="m">Chip of the Flying U</title> (1906)
by B. M. Bowers, one of the few women to
write Westerns, and Clarence Mulford's Hopalong
Cassidy, introduced in <title level="m">Bar 20</title> (1907), are
charming but lack the mythic strength of the
Virginian. The most successful writer to follow
Wister was the enormously prolific Zane Grey.
His gutsy heroines, torrid love plots, and
action-packed dramas have proved endlessly
popular. <title level="m">Riders of the Purple Sage</title> (1912) was
considered risqu&#233; in its portrayal of the
two pairs of lovers and was, in a sense, innovative
in its use of Mormons, rather than Indians, as
the "savage" antagonists. During World War I
Grey capitalized on anti-German sentiment to
use Germans and Industrial Workers of the
World organizers as the bad guys in <title level="m">Desert of Wheat</title> (1919). And in <title level="m">The Vanishing American</title>
he tried in the 1922 serial version to have an
Indian war hero vanish by marrying a white
girl and assimilating, but a negative response
to the marriage led him to return to Cooper's
solution in <title level="m">The Last of the Mohicans</title>, killing off
his hero in the 1925 book version of the story.</p>

<p>Max Brand (Frederick Faust), Luke Short
(Frederick D. Glidden), and Ernest Haycox
were among the many prolific writers of pulp
Westerns who followed Grey. Eugene Manlove
Rhodes, a more sophisticated writer who, like
Wister, combined his romances with keenly
observed realistic details, published a number
of innovative Westerns, including <title level="m">Paso por Aqui</title> (1926) and the novel <title level="m">Beyond the Desert</title>
(1934). By the late 1930s the genre was so well
developed that it could be used allegorically
by Walter Van Tilburg Clark in his novel <title level="m">The Ox-Bow Incident</title> (1940), in which the conventions
of the lynching in The Virginian are
turned upside down and the action becomes a
parable of fascism and mob rule, not an example,
as it had been to Wister, of the workings
of a higher moral order. Jack Schaeffer's
<title level="m">Shane</title> (1949) also works by changing the convention.
Schaeffer loosely bases his story on
the same Johnson County (Wyoming) range
war that Wister had used but makes Wister's
rustlers his good guys, a switch that Frederick
Manfred also makes in his <title level="m">Riders of Judgment</title>
(1949). Manfred draws heavily, though without
explicit acknowledgment, on historical
documents of the range war. While many of
Zane Grey's books, set in the Southwest or Far
West, like Clark's Ox-Bow Incident, set in
Nevada, cannot, strictly speaking, be called
Plains literature, the conventions of the genre
do not allow for meaningful distinctions
based on geography. The world of the Western
is a region of the mind. The sexual revolution
of the 1960s affected the Western as well, to the
success of Louis L'Amour's dynastic Westerns
and to such role reversals as John Seelye's <title level="m">The Kid</title> (1972), in which the "kid" turns out to be a
girl and the man who plays the Leatherstocking
role is a mute African American man.</p>

<p>Whether in fiction, film, radio, or television,
the popular Western hero is a loner who
explicitly rejects society as it is represented by
law, organized religion, and most women. For
Leatherstocking and the dime novel heroes,
this divorce from society is final and absolute.
For the characters descended from Daniel
Boone and the Virginian, it seems possible to
have it all, as the hero marries, sires children,
and settles down with both wealth and prominence
in the community. Schaeffer's Shane,
by splitting the hero into the hard-working
farmer and the drifter-gunslinger who comes
to his aid but then leaves, shows again that the
dream of unfettered freedom and thus of violence
is inimical to the dream of the garden
fruitful in both crops and children.</p>

<p>The second strain in Plains fiction is that
dream of the garden. Although it clearly has
roots in the classic tradition of the pastoral, it
is descended primarily from the literary realism
and naturalism that flourished in the
United States in the late nineteenth and early
twentieth centuries. It deals not with the
larger-than-life figure of the cowboy or gunslinger
but with the ordinary dirt farmer and
not with the individual but with the family.
Hamlin Garland's <title level="m">Main-Travelled Roads</title> stories,
published in the 1890s, are the first fullblown
members of this genre. They deal with
the details and hardships of farm life on the
"middle border," the area running from Wisconsin
and Iowa through the Dakotas, and
contrast the beauty of the natural landscape
with the squalor of the built landscape and the
demeaning and destructive demands of organized
society. Instead of praising one individual
working to bring about an abstract justice
outside of the settlement, Garland's work celebrates
the efforts of the community to bring
about social justice within its borders. His essentially
populist view of Plains life has remained
pervasive. It appears in Sinclair Lewis's
<title level="m">Main Street</title> (1920), in which the prairie
town is a parasite on the industrious farmers,
and in Mari Sandoz's books, particularly <title level="m">Old Jules</title> (1935), the fictionalized story of Sandoz's
father, and <title level="m">Capital City</title> (1939), an allegorical
novel deploring the betrayal of the community
by the few who have become rich.</p>

<p>The difficulties of Plains settlement were
magnified when the settlers were outside the
dominant culture. O. E. R&#246;lvaag's <title level="m">Giants in the Earth</title> (1927), originally published in two
volumes in Norway in 1924 and 1925, remains
the classic immigrant novel. It pits Per Hansa,
at once the larger-than-life heroic pioneer and
the character who does not realize the cultural
loss involved in pioneering, against his wife,
Beret, a Cassandra-like figure whose warnings
that by losing their Norwegian culture they
will lose their souls and themselves are not
heeded by her fellow settlers. In two sequels,
<title level="m">Peder Victorious</title> (1929) and <title level="m">Their Father's God</title>
(1931), Rolvaag explores the emotional consequences
of assimilation into an American culture
characterized by materialism. While R&#246;lvaag's
work is often joyous and shows the
miraculous nature of the first plantings of
wheat on the Dakota Plains, nature is more
agnostic and culture more vital than in either
the popular Western or works following Garland's
essentially meliorist vision of the Plains.</p>

<p>Rölvaag's work not only presents the Scandinavian
experience on the Plains but also
serves as a model for the fiction of other ethnic
groups. Texas writer Tom&#225;s Rivera explicitly
patterned his classic of Tejano migrant life, . . . <title level="m">Y
No Se Lo Trag&#243; la Tierra</title> (. . . <title level="m">And the Earth Did Not Part</title>, 1971) on R&#246;lvaag's trilogy. Chicano
culture is more problematic for Rivera's characters
than Norwegian is for R&#246;lvaag's, however,
and Rivera's revolt against the social system that
virtually enslaves the migrants is closer to Garland's
than to Rölvaag's. Other portraits of ethnic
settlers such as Sophus Keith Winthur's
Danes in <title level="m">Take All to Nebraska</title> (1936) and Hope
Williams Sykes's Germans from Russia in <title level="m">Second Hoeing</title> (1935) detail the same conflicts between
the ethnic culture, the pressures of assimilation,
and the oppressive social and economic
system in which Plains agriculturalists live and
work. Oscar Micheaux's two Plains novels, <title level="m">The Conquest</title> (1913) and <title level="m">The Homesteader</title> (1917),
show the particular pressures on African American
settlers.</p>

<p>The two most popular authors in the agrarian
tradition are undoubtedly Willa Cather
and Laura Ingalls Wilder. Both explicitly reject
Garland's populism in favor of stories of the
trials and ultimate triumphs of the great individual.
Their heroes parallel the traditions of
the popular Westerns except for two crucial
differences. Their conquests are nonviolent,
and their transcendent individuals are women.
Willa Cather's first two Nebraska novels, <title level="m">O Pioneers!</title> (1913) and the perennial favorite <title level="m">My &#193;ntonia</title> (1918), feature strong heroines possessed
of an almost mythical sense of oneness
with the land. They create true homes in a
demanding environment that stymies most of
the men who surround them. Cather is a superb
stylist, justly noted for her ability to describe
the prairie and to capture its beauty,
actually creating a new aesthetic for a landscape
that had none of the features of the sublime
and picturesque conventions of beauty.
Long read as a sunny and feminist hymn of
praise to the land and to the pioneer tradition,
Cather's work is now being reinterpreted, not
least importantly as lesbian literature.</p>

<p>Laura Ingalls Wilder's Little House books,
children's classics and the basis for an extremely
popular television series, are also
more than simple autobiographical narratives
of one family's experiences pioneering in the
upper Midwest and South Dakota. Reflecting
the influence of Wilder's daughter, Rose Wilder
Lane, they are libertarian parables about
individual liberty within the roles of masculine
and feminine provided by the culture.
In a somewhat similar vein, L. Frank Baum's
Wizard of Oz books are a popular children's
series with an explicitly feminist point of
view. Like Cather and Wilder, Baum relies on
the great individual, his plucky Kansas heroine,
Dorothy, to right the wrongs that selfproclaimed
reformers have been unable to
conquer. <title level="m">The Wizard of Oz</title> (1900) is thus both
a great American fairy tale and a political parable.
Not surprisingly, the works of all three
writers include a subtle strain of erasing or
undercutting Native claims on the land.</p>

<p>Radicalism made its way into Plains fiction,
as into so much else in American culture, in
the 1930s. John Steinbeck's <title level="m">The Grapes of Wrath</title> (1939), though it actually takes place in
Oklahoma east of the Plains and in California,
is deservedly the classic Plains novel of the
period, expressing both the determination
and despair of the farmers who were forced to
leave the Plains by the twin disasters of Dust
Bowl and Depression. For all their heroism,
Steinbeck's characters cannot win until they
manage to lick the system and change it to
work for them, not to oppress them. Meridel
LeSueur and Tillie Olsen expressed the radicalism
of the 1930s from the Plains fringe,
LeSueur primarily from Minnesota but with
some descriptions of Kansas among the stories
in <title level="m">Salute to Spring</title> (1940) and Olsen from
Omaha, although the city is not explicitly
named in Yonnondio (a novel actually written
in 1934 but not published until 1974). Frederick
Manfred's <title level="m">Chokecherry Tree</title> (1948) and
<title level="m">The Golden Bowl</title> (1944) also present the plight
of the inarticulate, ordinary man during the
Depression on the Plains. Manfred is realistic
and sympathetic to his male characters&#8211;his
female characters are another matter&#8211;and
presents a radical point of view, though he is
not as explicitly ideological as the other writers
mentioned in this paragraph.</p>

<p>Since World War II, Plains fiction has occupied
a rather peculiar position in American
letters. The enormously prolific and talented
Wright Morris published a host of favorably
reviewed novels, appeared frequently in the
New Yorker, and yet regularly shows up on
lists of the most underrated authors. Morris is
little known and little read even in his home
state of Nebraska, where almost every schoolchild
has read something by Willa Cather. His
photo text <title level="m">The Home Place</title> (1948) provides in
pictures and a spare narrative a powerful look
at what has become of the pioneer generation,
while <title level="m">Ceremony at Lone Tree</title> (1960) examines
the legacy of the Western in sanctioned and
unsanctioned violence in a West that has both
come of age and degenerated. North Dakota
novelist Larry Woiwode has suffered something
of the same fate of critical acceptance
unaccompanied by commensurate fame or
readership. Larry McMurtry, on the other
hand, has been successful not only with novels
much like the formula Western, including
Horseman, <title level="m">Pass By</title> (1961) and <title level="m">Lonesome Dove</title>
(1985), but also with the merciless yet tender
portrayal of the contemporary Great Plains
(his hometown, Archer City, Texas) in <title level="m">The Last Picture Show</title> (1966) and its sequel, <title level="m">Texasville</title>
(1987). Meanwhile, hundreds of extremely talented
writers produce and publish short stories
and novels that depict the Great Plains
with clarity and insight but receive little attention
or readership.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Canadian Prairie Fiction</head>

<p>Prairie fiction in Canada developed quite differently
from Plains fiction in the United States.
While some dime novels were set or written in
Canada, mostly by British or American authors
quite ignorant of the terrain, the beginning of
popular Prairie fiction came from the writers
who were explicitly excluded from the popular
Western, women and preachers. Ralph Connor's
(Rev. Charles Gordon) books of Christian
uplift, particularly <title level="m">The Sky Pilot</title> (1899) and <title level="m">Corporal Cameron of the Mounted</title> (1912), were bestsellers,
along with Nellie McClung's <title level="m">Sowing Seeds in Danny</title> (1908). Although some later
American versions of the Mountie story are
nothing but variations on the Virginian, clothed
in a scarlet tunic, the homegrown Mountie
story, as it starts with Connor's Corporal Cameron,
tells a very different story from that of the
Western. Here the hero is not the man who
stands outside the law but rather the man who
represents the law of his country and imperial
order. McClung's best-sellers were rooted very
firmly in the realities of the Prairie communities
in which she lived. Her <title level="m">Purple Springs</title> (1921) is
a triumphant account of the woman suffrage
movement in Prairie Canada, a cause that she
also championed in essays and political activism.
Other primarily realistic novels include
Arthur Stringer's Prairie Trilogy, <title level="m">The Prairie Wife</title> (1915), <title level="m">The Prairie Mother</title> (1920), and <title level="m">The Prairie Child</title> (1922), a curious amalgam of the
purest romantic invention and a shrewd and
barely sympathetic look at the self-delusions of
the Prairie settlers. Robert Stead's several novels
move toward a realistic portrayal of homesteading
and Prairie farming, culminating in <title level="m">Grain</title>
(1926). Martha Ostenso's <title level="m">Wild Geese</title> (1925) is,
like Stringer's works, a combination of brooding
realism and equally brooding romanticism
of a gothic sort. Frederick Philip Grove (nee
Felix Paul Greve, a truly self-made man) put the
seal on the Prairie novel as dour, brooding, and
doomed with <title level="m">Settlers of the Marsh</title> (1925) and
<title level="m">Fruits of the Earth</title> (1933). At the same time, his
autobiographical sketches, <title level="m">Over Prairie Trails</title>
(1922), like Cather's work, found a new voice
and vocabulary for describing and hence creating
for the reader the beauty of the Prairies.</p>

<p>Sinclair Ross's <title level="m">As for Me and My House</title>
(1941) is a turning point for both Canadian
literature and Prairie/Plains literature. Its
deceptively simple form&#8211;ostensibly, it is the
diary of a clergyman's wife during a year in a
small Saskatchewan town during the mid-
1930s&#8211;masks an extremely complex book that
asks whether art, as defined by European conventions,
is possible in the Prairie Provinces of
Canada. The book is open-ended, and the answer
is provided at least in part by the subsequent
success of Canadian Prairie literature.
Like Cather, Ross also provides a homosexual
voice in Plains literature.</p>

<p>While American Plains literature has remained
either popular culture or a high culture
removed from the literary centers of the
United States, Prairie literature is at the very
center of the Canadian literary canon that has
been emerging since <title level="m">As for Me and My House</title>.
Although Ross's novel vanished almost without
a trace until it was republished in 1957,
Prairie writers such as Grove, Margaret Laurence,
Adele Wiseman, Robert Kroetsch, Rudy
Wiebe, and others have consistently won Canada's
most prestigious literary awards and
are central figures in Canadian literature. Laurence's
<title level="m">The Stone Angel</title> (1964), like <title level="m">As for Me and My House</title>, is one of the acknowledged
classics of the canon. Paradoxically, while the
Western is perhaps the most enduring form of
the American national myth of identity, serious
writing by Plains authors is at the fringes
of the contemporary American tradition,
while Canadian Prairie literature, which from
its inception rejected the popular American
form, is central to Canadian literature. Not
surprisingly, <title level="m">The Stone Diaries</title> (1993), written
in and about Manitoba by a former American
(Carol Shields), is the only recent Plains novel
to win a Pulitzer Prize. (It had already won the
Governor General's Award for fiction.) Canadian
Prairie fiction continues to flourish.
Among the many contemporary writers are
Sharon Butala and Guy Vanderhaege.</p>

<p>Implicitly or explicitly, Canadian Prairie literature
rejects the themes of the Western&#8211;the
noble savage, the rugged individual, the two-gun
man&#8211;in favor of community and to some
extent of women and family. Women as both
writers and characters are central to this fiction,
and Ross's choice of a woman's diary for
his form draws attention to the diaries and
letters by women that have always been part of
the literature of European American settlement
in the Great Plains. The themes of Prairie
fiction are heritage and community. Rather
than an American Adam, concerned with
starting anew in a new world, the Canadian
Hagar (the name of the heroine of <title level="m">The Stone Angel</title>) is a wanderer in a desert that she makes
a home partly by connecting it with her ancestors.
This is also a theme in the American
agrarian novel, both the ethnic novel, in which
a European culture fails in transplantation to
the New World, and works by old stock Americans
such as Garland and Cather. But Canadian
literature emphasizes creating a past
through stories or art. This is most clear in
Margaret Laurence's <title level="m">The Diviners</title> (1974), a
novel that deals with both the Native and European
histories of the land and recognizes both
the complicity in oppression and the cultural
significance of European settlement in the
Great Plains.</p>

<p>Like Laurence, many European Canadian
writers have used Native or mixed-blood characters
in their fiction. In part this reflects a
larger percentage of Native peoples on the
Canadian Prairies than on the Plains of the
United States, and in part it represents the
Canadian search for themes that differentiate
Canadians from Americans. It also represents
the Canadian commitment, at least in theory,
to multiculturalism and the tendency of Prairie
writers, unlike American Plains writers, to
be toward the left of the political spectrum. In
<title level="m">The Scorched Wood People</title> (1977) and <title level="m">The Temptations of Big Bear</title> (1973), Rudy Wiebe
has attempted to show the Red River and
North-West Rebellions from the viewpoints of
the Metis and the Crees, endeavors that have
drawn mixed reactions from critics and Native
readers. W. O. Mitchell has used many
versions of the noble savage, particularly in
<title level="m">Vanishing Point</title> (1973), while in <title level="m">Dance Me Outside</title> (1977) and subsequent Silas Ermineskin
stories W. P. Kinsella has updated the noble
savage to a streetwise and astute kid of
nineteen. Laurence was most cognizant among
these writers of the Native point of view in her
decision never to speak for Native people in
her characters, while Kinsella is the most controversial
of the writers among both Native
and European American critics.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Fiction by Native Peoples</head>

<p>Native peoples have shown themselves more
than capable of speaking for themselves, not
only in oral traditions but in writing. While
short writings by Indians and as-told-to autobiographies
have existed ever since European
contact with the peoples of North America, the
first flowering of Native writing in English occurred
in the 1920s and 1930s, a period when
legal restrictions on cultural, religious, and political
freedoms of Native peoples began to be
lifted. Cogewea, the <title level="m">Half Blood</title> (1927) seems to
be the first Plains novel published by an Indian
or mixed-blood author, although the author,
Mourning Dove (or Hum Ishu Ma or Christine
Quintasket), had to work through a fairly
intrusive European American editor. In the
next decade D'Arcy McNickle published his
classic novel of western Montana, <title level="m">The Surrounded</title>
(1936), and Black Elk (via white poet
John Neihardt) and Luther Standing Bear published
autobiographical accounts that described
and praised traditional Lakota ways.</p>

<p>While Native authors continued to write
and sometimes found publishers for their accounts
throughout the 1940s and 1950s, it was
not until the 1960s that a true cultural renaissance
began among the Native peoples of
North America. While N. Scott Momaday's
Pulitzer Prize–winning novel <title level="m">House Made of Dawn</title> (1968) is set primarily in the Southwest,
his formally innovative <title level="m">The Way to Rainy Mountain</title> (1969) deals specifically with
the Kiowas' relationship to the Plains. James
Welch's <title level="m">Winter in the Blood</title> (1974), <title level="m">The Death of Jim Loney</title> (1979), and <title level="m">Fools Crow</title> (1986)
form a trilogy of great power that traces the
survival of the Blackfeet from the late 1870s to
the present. In the Southern Plains a similar
cultural renaissance has produced a flowering
of Chicano fiction, which draws upon oral
traditions of both Spanish and Native origins.
Rudolfo Anaya's limpid <title level="m">Bless Me, Ultima</title>
(1972), set in the llano of eastern New Mexico
and self-consciously combining Native
and Hispanic traditions, is perhaps the best
known of these works. More recently, Louise
Erdrich's novels of the North Dakota Chippewa,
including <title level="m">Love Medicine</title> (1984), <title level="m">The Beet Queen</title> (1986), <title level="m">Tracks</title> (1988), <title level="m">The Bingo Palace</title> (1995), <title level="m">and Antelope Wife</title> (1998), have
been popular best-sellers as well as highly acclaimed.
Her use of Nanabush, the trickster, is
an example of how the oral tradition is being
subsumed into the new written literature.</p>

<p>The Native Canadian renaissance in Plains
literature lagged nearly two decades behind
that of the United States. It began with nonfiction
by two M&#233;tis writers, Maria Campbell's
<title level="m">Halfbreed</title> (1973) and Howard Adams's <title level="m">Prison of Grass</title> (1975). Beatrice Culleton's <title level="m">In Search of April Raintree</title> (1983) became the first prairie
novel by an author of Native descent, followed
by Thomas King's <title level="m">Medicine River</title> (1989) and
<title level="m">Green Grass, Running Water</title> (1993). King's infectious
humor and ability to blend Native
oral tradition and everyday life with history as
well as the European–North American literary
tradition have enabled him to create a new
Great Plains aesthetic. Buoyed by the political
resurgence of First Nations peoples in Canada
and the creation of Native newspapers such as
<title level="j">Windspeaker</title> (Edmonton) and First Nations
publishing houses such as Theytus and Pemmican,
Native Canadian Prairie writing continues
to grow in both quality and quantity.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Plains Poetry</head>

<p>Poetry, chant, and song have always been part
of the oral literary tradition on the Plains.
The contemporary powwow circuit and access
to inexpensive, high-quality recording
equipment have produced an outpouring of
both traditional and newly created songs and
chants. A contemporary sacred tradition including
both Native American church and
Gospel songs has spurred the writing of lyrics
in both English and Indigenous languages. Individual
performers such as John Trudell and
Keith Secola have now written and recorded
significant bodies of work.</p>

<p>Written European-style poetry on the Northern
Plains undoubtedly begins with Henry
Kelsey's doggerel narrative of his fur-trading
expedition in 1690, though similar narratives
probably exist in Spanish for the Southern
Plains. The monument of the long poem tradition
on the Plains is John Neihardt's five-part
<title level="m">Cycle of the West: The Song of Hugh Glass</title>
(1915), <title level="m">The Song of the Three Friends</title> (1919), <title level="m">The Song of the Indian Wars</title> (1925), <title level="m">The Song of the Messiah</title> (1935), and <title level="m">The Song of Jedediah Smith</title>
(1941). These poems, all in heroic couplets and
ranging from 110 to 179 pages, are Neihardt's
attempt to provide America with its own <title level="m">Iliad and Odyssey</title>, looking at the struggle for the
West from the point of view of the mountain
men and the Indians, particularly the Lakotas.
Although the work is an impressive achievement,
the unidiomatic quality of the heroic
couplets has discouraged both readers and
successors, while the explicitly Christian imagery
works against the Indian content. Tom
McGrath, Ed Dorn, Robert Kroetsch, and others,
using contemporary speech patterns and
such nonliterary genres as seed catalogs (in
Kroetsch's 1977 poem of that title), have written
long poems both more experimental and
more accessible than Neihardt's.</p>

<p>Lyric poetry rather than narrative has been
characteristic of the Plains as it has of the rest
of the English-speaking world for the last two
centuries. For the most part it began with popular
newspaper verse. Like butter-and-egg
money, pay or prizes for newspaper poetry
often helped the farm or small-town wife
round out the household budget. This tradition
of vernacular poetry is now represented
by the "cowboy poets," who work in ballad
styles and present their frequently humorous
verses to aficionados at "cowboy poetry" gatherings
all over the West. By the 1920s the literary
magazine, or little magazine, was starting
to supplant the small-town newspaper as the
major venue for the publication of lyric poetry.
Frequently connected to a college or university
and more recently to a creative writing program,
little magazines such as Prairie Schooner,
Midlands, Frontier, and Dandelion and small
local presses have both provided an outlet for
local poets and connected Plains writing to the
rest of the continent. Like most writers in English
in the twentieth century, Plains poets
have frequently chosen variable feet and sound
patterns other than end rhymes, although poets
like William Stafford manipulate blank
verse, slant rhymes, and other traditional
forms with marked success.</p>

<p>The differences in theme, outlook, and national
audience that distinguish Canadian and
American Plains fiction are much less evident
in poetry. Neihardt's cycle is similar to Canadian
documentary poems such as E. J. Pratt's
<title level="m">Towards the Last Spike</title> (1952), which sounds
the same blend of pride and chagrin at "progress"
onto the center of the continent. McGrath's social justice themes are not dissimilar
from those of Manitoban Dorothy Livesay.
Like William Stafford, Robert Kroetsch is concerned
with the past and its traditions, with the
domestication and violation of the land and
its inhabitants. Contemporary Plains women
poets such as Hilda Raz and Lorna Crozier are
particularly strong voices whose concerns with
naming, with birthing, and with identifying
the land as female and as mother are similar on
both sides of the border.</p>

<p>The renaissance in Native writing beginning
in the 1960s is evident in poetry as well as
fiction and frequently involves the same writers.
N. Scott Momaday's <title level="m">Angle of Geese</title> (1974),
James Welch's <title level="m">Riding the Earthboy 40</title> (1971),
and Louise Erdrich's <title level="m">Jacklight</title> (1984) are all
highly sophisticated in image, allusion, and
technique and unquestionably represent some
of the best contemporary Plains poetry. Emma
LaRoche is probably the best known of the
contemporary Native Canadian poets, while
Paula Gunn Allen, Linda Hogan, and Elizabeth
Cook-Lynn are among the best known on the
U.S. side.</p>

<p>Writers of Asian and African descent in any
genre are still extremely rare in the Great
Plains. Novelist and filmmaker Oscar Micheaux
was a rare African American voice at
the beginning of the twentieth century, and
Ralph Ellison and Langston Hughes both grew
up on the Plains. Fred Wah has become an
important contemporary Chinese Canadian
writer. Increased immigration, especially to
the Prairie Provinces, continues to add new
voices to the Prairie mosaic.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Plains Drama</head>

<p>Drama has to a large extent been an import to
the Plains. In the nineteenth century touring
companies from New York and Chicago followed
the railroad lines to present versions of
the latest plays and operas from the East and
of the classics to city and small-town audiences.
No Plains drama comparable to Plains
fiction or poetry has developed in the United
States, though there are notable local exceptions.
Folk drama has remained important on
the Southern Plains. Often, as in the Christmas
posadas, these dramas are religious, but
secular patriotic fiestas also include drama.
Town pageants, somewhere between mass and
folk art, have also attained popularity in some
locales throughout the Plains. They may be
produced somewhat formulaically by outsiders
for a specific occasion such as a town's
centennial or written and regularly produced
by townspeople.</p>

<p>Community-based drama has been far
more successful in the Prairie Provinces, particularly
Alberta and Saskatchewan, than in
the Plains states. The Banff School of Fine Arts
in Alberta began in the 1930s to promote and
produce community theater, written and often
acted by members of the community. Gwen
Pharis Ringwood emerged as the premier playwright
of the movement. While the Banff
School has moved away from community-based
theater to a more traditional and less
regional focus since the 1950s, Saskatchewan
has more recently become the venue of a vibrant
and popular community-based theater
that often includes dramas about carefully researched
incidents in the province, often improvised
or workshopped instead of written by
a solitary playwright. These include Theatre
Passe Muraille's <title level="m">The West Show</title> (1975) and its
successor, the Saskatoon 25th Street Theatre's
collective creation of <title level="m">Paper Wheat</title> (1982),
about the formation of the Saskatchewan
Wheat Pool, and, perhaps most remarkable,
Linda Griffiths and Maria Campbell's <title level="m">Jessica</title>
(1982/1986), about a mixed-blood woman's
successful attempt to come to terms with her
heritage and ancestral spirits in a racist and
sexist society. The communal/cooperative nature
of this sort of theater, though directly descended
from Paul Thompson and the Theatre
Passe Muraille of Toronto, seems especially
well suited both to Saskatchewan's political
history of cooperatives and democratic socialism
and to the ethos of Native peoples. An
alternative form of documentary by a single
playwright is exemplified in the works of Rex
Deverell of Regina's Globe Theatre, including
<title level="m">No. 1 Hard</title> (1978) and <title level="m">Medicare</title> (1980). Despite
perennial financial problems, theater continues
to flourish in the Prairie Provinces.
Sharon Pollock and Brad Fraser are among the
most successful contemporary playwrights,
but many theater groups and the almost endless
creativity of the summer fringe festivals
guarantee that Prairie theater remains an extremely
accessible literary art.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Conclusion</head>

<p>As the world has moved, rockily enough, on
into the twenty-first century, it seems likely
that the Great Plains will cease to be regarded
as the cultural hinterland it has seemed to be
in the United States and will become, as it is in
Canada, a region generating a particularly innovative
and high-quality literature. The popular
Western, if it is to become anything other
than an endlessly repeating formula, will become
more ambiguous and less purely heroic.
As an environmentalist consciousness becomes
more necessary and accepted for survival,
the progress that Owen Wister and his
heirs had presented as positive&#8211;—even as it destroyed
the wilderness Eden&#8211;will seem more
purely destructive. The communitarian ethic
and the multicultural point of view characteristic,
at least in theory, of Canadian and
Native peoples will become the norm, and the
search for ancestors in the land will continue
and be amplified. The myth of the vanishing
American that has haunted portrayals of Native
peoples for the past 500 years will pale and
recede as it becomes more clear that demographically,
politically, economically, and culturally
Native peoples are very decidedly not
vanishing, despite the often genocidal invasion
that was Native peoples' experience of the
"pioneering" of the Great Plains. But the land
will remain, and the harshness of a continental
climate will remain. And the starkness of
land and sky will encourage dreamers to write
more of what we call Plains literature.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">AFRICAN AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.afam.031">Micheaux, Oscar</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">EUROPEAN AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ea.014"><title level="m">Giants in the Earth</title></ref>; <ref n="egp.ea.023">Kelsey, Henry</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">FILM</hi>: <ref n="egp.fil.038"><hi rend="italic">The Last Picture Show</hi></ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">GENDER</hi>: <ref n="egp.gen.023">McClung, Nellie</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">MUSIC</hi>:
<ref n="egp.mus.046">Trudell, John</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">PROTEST AND DISSENT</hi>: <ref n="egp.pd.035">McGrath, Tom</ref>.</p>
</div2>

<closer>
<signed>Frances W. Kaye<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Bredahl, Carl A., Jr. <title level="m">New Ground: Western American Narrative and the Literary Canon</title>. Chapel Hill: University of
North Carolina Press, 1989.</bibl> <bibl>Etulain, Richard. <title level="m">Re-Imagining the Modern American West: A Century of Fiction, History, and Art</title>. Tucson: University of Arizona Press, 1996.</bibl>
<bibl>Fiddler, Don., ed. <title level="m">Looking at the Words of Our People: An Anthology of First Nations Literary Criticism</title>. Penticton,
British Columbia: Theytus, 1993.</bibl> <bibl>Filwod, Alan. <title level="m">Collective Encounters: Documentary Theatre in English Canada</title>.
Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 1987.</bibl> <bibl>Harrison,
Dick. <title level="m">Unnamed Country: The Struggle for a Canadian Prairie Fiction</title>. Edmonton: University of Alberta Press,
1977.</bibl> <bibl>Larson, Charles R. <title level="m">American Indian Fiction</title>. Albuquerque:
University of New Mexico Press, 1978.</bibl> <bibl>Meyer,
Roy W. <title level="m">The Middle Western Farm Novel in the Twentieth Century</title>. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1965.</bibl>
<bibl>Milton, John R. <title level="m">The Novel of the American West</title>. Lincoln:
University of Nebraska Press, 1980.</bibl> <bibl>New, W. H., ed. <title level="m">Native Writers and Canadian Writing</title>. Vancouver: University of
British Columbia Press, 1990.</bibl> <bibl>Olson, Paul, ed. <title level="m">Broken Hoops and Plains People: A Sourcebook</title>. Lincoln: Nebraska
Curriculum Development Project, 1976.</bibl> <bibl>Probert, Kenneth
G., ed. <title level="m">Writing Saskatchewan: 20 Critical Essays</title>. Regina,
Saskatchewan: Canadian Plains Research Center, 1989.</bibl>
<bibl>Quantic, Diane. <title level="m">The Nature of Place: A Study of Great Plains Fiction</title>. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1995.</bibl>
<bibl>Smith, Henry Nash. <title level="m">Virgin Land: The American West as Symbol and Myth</title>. Cambridge: Harvard University Press,
1950.</bibl> <bibl>Thacker, Robert. <title level="m">The Great Prairie Fact and Literary Imagination</title>. Albuquerque: University of New Mexico
Press, 1989.</bibl> <bibl>Tuska, Jon, ed. <title level="m">The American West in Fiction</title>.
Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1982.</bibl> <bibl>Western Literature
Association. <title level="m">A Literary History of the American West</title>.
Fort Worth: Texas Christian University Press, 1987.</bibl>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>