<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ind.041">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">NAFTA</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Ronald C. Griffin</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ind.041</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Griffin, Ronald C.">Ronald C. Griffin</author>. <title level="a">"NAFTA."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">427</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-04</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">NAFTA</head>

<p>The North American Free Trade Agreement
(<hi rend="smallcaps">NAFTA</hi>), implemented on January 1, 1994,
is an agreement to remove most barriers to
trade and investment in both goods and services
among Canada, the United States, and
Mexico. Its purpose is to stimulate economic
growth in the three countries and to increase
jobs. Full employment in Mexico, for example,
will help its economic growth, discourage
emigration, and create wealth for Mexican
consumers to buy American and Canadian
products. Items that now move more freely
among the signatory nations include capital,
textile products, petrochemicals, automobile
components, fertilizers, farm products, and
telecommunications. In the case of farm
products, for example, some tariffs were removed
immediately, and most others are
being phased out over a transition period.</p>

<p>In the Great Plains, two trading groups have
emerged to take advantage of <hi rend="smallcaps">NAFTA</hi>. The Camino
Real Economic Alliance (<hi rend="smallcaps">CREA</hi>) operates
at the western fringe of the Plains, linking fortyfive
business organizations from Chihuahua,
Ciudad Juárez, El Paso, Las Cruces, Albuquerque,
and Santa Fe. <hi rend="smallcaps">CREA</hi> seeks to strengthen
ties between and development of the states
of Chihuahua and New Mexico and the region
of West Texas. A second group is the Rocky
Mountain Trade Corridor (<hi rend="smallcaps">RMTC</hi>), which is a
membership organization for small businesses
throughout the Great Plains. The <hi rend="smallcaps">RMTC</hi> convenes
seminars on <hi rend="smallcaps">NAFTA</hi> and matches its
members with business partners in Canada
and Mexico.</p>

<p>Outside of these groups, businesses in the
Great Plains are trading under <hi rend="smallcaps">NAFTA</hi> on their
own. On a state-by-state basis, there is a positive
trade balance with Canada. The trade balance
with Mexico is more mixed. Exports to
Mexico in 1994–95 dipped in Kansas, Oklahoma,
Nebraska, South Dakota, and Texas but
went up in Colorado, North Dakota, Montana,
and Wyoming. The freight data for
goods shipped to Mexico in 1996 yield a similar
picture. At present Texas is positioned to
capitalize on the impending boom in Mexico.</p>

<p>What does <hi rend="smallcaps">NAFTA</hi> mean to the Great Plains?
It means highway construction, bridge maintenance,
railway mergers, train coordination,
warehousing, and trucking. Congress has set
aside $700,000 for highway construction. Interstate
35 will get the lion's share of that
money. The Santa Fe Railroad has concluded
a merger with Burlington Northern and relocated
its corporate headquarters in Texas, a
move from which Dallas–Fort Worth will
benefit. The Santa Fe must now coordinate its
train business with its rival (Union Pacific) to
ensure smooth flows of commerce across the
Plains. Warehousing facilities are going up in
the Great Plains. Big firms have constructed
one or two strategically located facilities from
which they ship consumer goods. Canadian
firms servicing the U.S. market and American
firms servicing the Canadian market have
erected warehouses in Omaha, Nebraska.
Denver, Colorado, Kansas City, Missouri,
and Dallas, Texas, have experienced similar
growth, a growth that has benefited local economies.
Though warehouses attract few workers,
the land on which these facilities rest produces
property taxes to fund local schools.
Trucking is booming on i-29, i-70, and i-35,
largely due to <hi rend="smallcaps">NAFTA</hi> commerce. But the flow
of commerce south to Mexico has been impeded
by bottlenecks. In Laredo, Texas, by far
the busiest U.S.-Mexican crossing point, cargo
lines have tested driver patience. Haulers often
have to wait up to ten hours before moving
their cargo into Mexico. Trucks have to cross
two aging bridges to get to their destinations.
The amount of commerce moving into Mexico
is also determined by the pace of border
inspections.</p>

<p>Beyond the bridge building, the inspectors,
and the highway improvements, nagging issues
threaten the flow of commerce. American
access to Canadian dairy and poultry markets,
grain trade between the United States and
Canada, and granting access to American beef
in Canada head the list.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Ronald C. Griffin<lb/>
Washburn University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Glick, Leslie A. <title level="m">Understanding the North American Free Trade Agreement</title>. Boston: Deventer, 1993.</bibl> <bibl>Moss, Ambler
H., Jr., ed. <title level="m">Assessments of the North American Free Trade Agreement</title>. Coral Gables <hi rend="smallcaps">FL</hi>: Transaction, 1993.</bibl> <bibl>Riggs, Alvin
R., and Tom Velk, eds. <title level="m">Beyond <hi rend="smallcaps">NAFTA</hi>: An Economic,
Political, and Sociological Perspective</title>. Vancouver: Fraser
Institute, 1993.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>