<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.rel.020">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Episcopalianism</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Kern R. Trembath</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.rel.020</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Trembath, Kern R.">Kern R. Trembath</author>. <title level="a">"Episcopalianism."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">744</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-18</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">EPISCOPALIANISM</head>

<p>Episcopalians constitute the American branch
or province of the worldwide Anglican Communion.
They adopted this name both because
of the political sensitivities generated
by the American Revolution and because they
wished to signal their continuity with that
Communion and especially its episcopal tradition.
The Episcopal Church of the USA has
approximately 2.5 million members, eleven
seminaries, and 103 dioceses, of which nineteen
are in the Great Plains. The Anglican
Church of Canada started in the mid–eighteenth
century and has nearly 750,000
members and thirty dioceses, of which nine
are in the Great Plains. In the United States,
the largest concentrations of communicants
are found on the coasts, especially the eastern.</p>

<p>In addition to the episcopal structure that
apostolically links the modern church to the
first century, the denomination's other distinctive
features are its liturgical style and its
commitment to social justice. Liturgically, the
Episcopal Church maintains both unity and
diversity through its Book of Common Prayer.
Each Anglican province in the world is responsible
for its own prayer book, which thus
symbolizes its continuity with the tradition as
well as local originality. The earliest prayer
books (1549 and 1552) were produced in England
largely by Thomas Cranmer, and they
reflected both Catholic and Reformation theologies,
as does the Episcopal Church's current
Book of Common Prayer, last revised in
1979. Unity and diversity are also embodied by
the honorific (but not juridical) primacy accorded
the archbishop of Canterbury.</p>

<p>The church's commitment to social justice
may be seen in traditional arenas such as civil
and women's rights. It was the second branch
within the Anglican Communion to ordain
women as priests and the first to consecrate
women as bishops. It can also be discerned in
what is often called "Anglican methodology"
or the <hi rend="italic">via media</hi>, which is shorthand for the
church's commitment to inclusivism wherever
possible and appropriate. This feature is evident
in the church's bicameral governing
structure, a somewhat cumbersome but deliberately
republican form of governance in
which laity, priests, and bishops have a significant
voice. It is also evident in the fact that the
church did not split over the Civil War. Its
refusal to take an official stance toward slavery
has been interpreted by some as weakness, but
by others as a deliberate avoidance of taking
any steps that would lead to schism. Regardless,
the church resumed its prewar pace both
quickly and peacefully after hostilities ceased.</p>

<p>While Episcopalians moved west along with
other Christians in the first half of the nineteenth
century, their dedication to evangelization
lagged behind that of other denominations.
This resulted from the denomination's
authority structure on the one hand and the
general suspicion of any kind of central authority
among westerners on the other. In part,
it also reflected the fact that many of the early
bishops in the Great Plains were "high church"
Anglo-Catholics, whereas most priests and
laypersons were "low church" evangelicals.
The resulting spirituality, occasionally referred
to as "evangelical Catholicism," has characterized
much Episcopal life and character in the
Great Plains ever since.</p>

<p>The General Convention of 1835 designated
the church itself as a missionary institution,
and all of its members as official missionaries
with regard to westward expansion. Ten years
later Bishop Jackson Kemper began what one
biographer called "the most fruitful single
ministry in the annals of the [Episcopal]
church." He organized the first dioceses in Indiana,
Illinois, Missouri, Iowa, Wisconsin,
Kansas, Nebraska, and Dakota. In the Canadian
Prairies, the Colonial and Continental
Church Society ministered to settlers and
maintained Emmanuel College in Saskatoon
from 1914 to 1954 for the training of clergy.</p>

<p>Sharing the constants of sparse population,
inclement weather, and widespread poverty,
parishes and dioceses grew slowly in the Great
Plains in the nineteenth century, although
rather more quickly in the more urban areas.
However, because of increased immigration
during the early decades of the twentieth century
and the economic surge caused by World
War I, the Plains grew in both industrial and
agricultural wealth and significance. The Episcopal
Church's fortunes rose accordingly, even
though the war itself resulted in the closing of
various schools and temporarily depressed
parochial budgets because of the absence of
soldiers and their contributions.</p>

<p>The Great Depression was disproportionately
harsh on both church and civil society in
the Plains, and many dioceses found themselves
at the bottom of national lists with regard
to parish offerings, baptisms, ordinations,
and the like. As with the previous war,
though, World War II generated an increase in
the fortunes of the Episcopal Church, though
there was a general falloff in membership after
1960 in the Plains and elsewhere. Episcopalians
remain a relatively small denomination
in the Great Plains&#8211;ranked sixth or seventh
by number of churches per state&#8211;and are
most strongly represented in cities of the eastern
part of the region. Many counties in the
western reaches of the Great Plains, especially
in the panhandles of Texas and Oklahoma and
in eastern Colorado and western Kansas, have
no Episcopal churches at all.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Kern R. Trembath<lb/>
University of Notre Dame</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Albright, Raymond W. <title level="m">A History of the Protestant Episcopal
Church</title>. New York: Macmillan Publishing Company,
1964.</bibl> <bibl>Pritchard, Robert W. <title level="m">A History of the Episcopal
Church</title>. Harrisburg <hi rend="smallcaps">PA</hi>: Morehouse Publishing, 1991.</bibl> <bibl>Taylor,
Blanche Mercer. <title level="m">Plenteous Harvest: The Episcopal
Church in Kansas, 1837–1972</title>. Topeka <hi rend="smallcaps">KS</hi>: Prepared by the
author for the Diocese of Kansas, 1973.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>