<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.pe.053">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Sandhills</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>James B. Swinehart</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.pe.053</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Swinehart, James B.">James B. Swinehart</author>. <title level="a">"Sandhills."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">638-639</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-22</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">SANDHILLS</head>
<figure n="egp.pe.053" rend="granted" type="noclick">
<figDesc>View of the Nebraska Sandhills</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>The Central and Southern Great Plains contains
the greatest concentration of windblown
sand in North America, and the Sandhills,
covering 20,000 square miles of central Nebraska,
is the largest of these Great Plains sand
dune fields. Currently stabilized by prairie
vegetation, the Sandhills is one of the world's
premier grasslands for cattle grazing. The
dune landscape is interspersed with about
2,000 shallow lakes and more than a million
acres of wetlands. These diverse wildlife and
plant communities present a sharp contrast to
the adjacent dryland communities of the
dunes.</p>

<p>Three major dune types occur in the Sandhills:
barchanoid-ridge and megabarchan
dunes, typically 120 to 300 feet high and one to
five miles long, formed by unidirectional winds
from the northwest; simple linear dunes, forty
to sixty feet high and one mile long, formed by
winds from two directions; and compound parabolic
dunes, fifty to seventy feet high and 1,400
feet long, also formed by unidirectional winds
from the northwest. Both linear and parabolic
dunes also occur superimposed on the larger
megabarchan and barchanoid-ridge dunes.
Sand sheets, areas of flat-lying sand with scattered
small dunes, are the only portion of the
Sandhills that lend themselves to typical Great
Plains farming practices.</p>

<p>The most crucial factor in the formation of
dune fields, given a supply of sand and sufficient
winds, is a sparse vegetative cover.
Radiocarbon dating of soils buried by dune
sand indicate several periods of widespread
blowing sand between 250 and 1,000 years ago
that were caused by droughts more severe
than any of the past 100 years. These episodes
of aridity have made it difficult to document
older periods of dune sand activity because
they "cannibalized" and buried the earlier history
of the dune field.</p>

<p>However, geologists have discovered ancient river valleys within the Sandhills that
were blocked and partially filled by dune sand
during major droughts. Lakes and marshes
that formed behind the sand dams were sites
of peat and/or mud deposition, as well as local
wind-blown sand layers. Radiocarbon dates
from these deposits indicate major periods of
dune sand activity during the following times:
13,000 to 12,000 years ago; 8,000 to 5,000 years
ago; and 3,500 to 2,800 years ago.</p>

<p>Analysis of the mineral grains that make up
the sand in the Sandhills indicates that there is
more quartz and less feldspar present than occurs
in possible source sediments. These include
sandstones of the Ogallala and Arikaree
Groups and the North and South Platte Rivers.
The most probable explanation for this discrepancy
is a reduction of sand-sized feldspar
(which is more easily broken than quartz) to
dust-sized particles via grain impacts during
windstorms. This would require many cycles
of aridity and suggests the Sandhills has a history
that may extend more than 100,000 years.
Only bits and pieces of that record may have
been preserved and will require much work to
discover and interpret.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">WATER</hi>: <ref n="egp.wat.029">Sandhills Lakes</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>James B. Swinehart<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Loope, David B., James B. Swinehart, and Jon P. Mason.
"Dune-dammed Paleovalleys of the Nebraska Sand Hills:
Intrinsic Versus Climatic-controls on the Accumulation of
Lake and Marsh Sediments." <title level="j">Geological Society of America
Bulletin</title> 107 (1995): 396–406.</bibl> <bibl>McIntosh, Charles B. <title level="m">The
Nebraska Sand Hills: The Human Landscape</title>. Lincoln:
University of Nebraska Press, 1996.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>