<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.tra.034">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Santa Fe Trail</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Pekka H&#228;m&#228;l&#228;inen</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.tra.034</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="H&#228;m&#228;l&#228;inen, Pekka">Pekka H&#228;m&#228;l&#228;inen</author>. <title level="a">"Santa Fe Trail."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">810-811</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-22</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">SANTA FE TRAIL</head>

<p>For most nineteenth-century European Americans
the Great Plains represented primarily a
transportation challenge, a vast expanse that
had to be crossed to gain access to greater
riches beyond its boundaries. The Santa Fe
Trail, the principal trade route connecting the
eastern United States and the Southwest, was
one of the most successful solutions to that
challenge. The trail opened in 1821, when
newly independent Mexico abolished restrictive
Spanish laws and allowed foreign traders
to enter its New Mexican outposts. The first to
capitalize on the new markets was William
Becknell, a struggling Missouri merchant who
arrived in Santa Fe in the fall of 1821 and sold
his goods at a huge profit. The following year,
Becknell ventured again from Franklin, Missouri,
to Santa Fe, pioneering the Cimarron
Cutoff across the Oklahoma Panhandle.</p>

<p>Becknell had tapped a vast commercial potential.
The isolated New Mexicans had surpluses of mules, silver, and furs, but they
lacked manufactured goods and therefore
were eager to have access to U.S. markets.
Stimulated by mutual benefits, the trade flourished.
During the following six decades, first
dozens, then hundreds, and finally thousands
of wagons moved each year along the Santa Fe
Trail, carrying calico, leather goods, hardware,
clothing, beaver pelts, and silver coins across
the Plains. By the 1850s the annual value of
merchandise shipped over the trail exceeded
$5 million. The trail served as a commercial
artery until 1880, when the completion of the
Atchison, Topeka and Santa Fe Railroad made
it obsolete.</p>

<p>By the 1830s a generally accepted routine
had developed along the trail. The traders usually
left Independence, Missouri (Franklin, the
first terminus, was destroyed by a flood in
1828), in mid-May, when Plains grasses were
tall enough to provide su.cient forage for
draft animals. Most traders used Murphy wagons,
three-foot-wide and sixteen-foot-long
canvas-topped vehicles with four-inch-thick
iron tires to protect the wooden wheels during
the arduous, 775-mile trek. After ten days of
travel, the traders paused at Council Grove,
Kansas, where they gathered into larger caravans
led by an elected captain and division
lieutenants and typically consisting of 25
freight wagons and 300 oxen and mules. After
the break, the caravans headed toward the Big
Bend of the Arkansas, traveling ten to fifteen
miles a day. The wagon trains followed the
northern flank of the Arkansas River valley to
the Middle Crossing, where the trail divided
into two branches. The longer Mountain
Branch followed the Arkansas River to Bentfs
Fort and then proceeded southwest through
Raton Pass to Santa Fe. The more heavily trafficked
Cimarron Cutoff first crossed the Cimarron
Desert and then followed a direct route
to Santa Fe.</p>

<p>Whichever route they chose, the caravans
could not escape the harsh Plains elements&#8211;dry
spells, torrential rains, wolves, fires, and
stampeding bison herds. River crossings were
particularly troublesome. Although shallow,
Plains rivers were filled with sinkholes, quicksand,
and other hazards that required careful
maneuvering. Traders also needed flexible Indian
policies. Caravans moved in parallel columns
that could be quickly formed into a protective
corral to repel raiders, but they had to
be equally ready to welcome trading parties
with gifts of coffee, bacon, and tobacco. As the
Native economies began to crumble the raids
intensified, making the Santa Fe trade a dangerous
business. Besides physical landmarks
such as the double-peaked Rabbit Ears on the
Cimarron Cutoff, the trail was in later years
marked by an unbroken string of destroyed
wagons and animal remains.</p>

<p>The Santa Fe Trail played a crucial role in
shaping North American history. It was critical
in absorbing New Mexico into the American
commercial orbit and, after the Mexican War,
in incorporating the province into the national
economy. During the California gold rush, the
trail also took thousands of emigrants across
the Plains. The trail increased geographic
knowledge of Plains rivers, springs, and topography
and made Bent's Fort one of the
most lucrative commercial centers in the West.
But the Santa Fe Trail also launched the European
American assault on Plains ecosystems.
The iron-rimmed wheels and the hundreds of
thousands of animals and people destroyed
native vegetation, accelerated erosion, polluted
springs, brought new diseases, and disturbed
bison herds. By the 1850s the Arkansas
River valley, once a haven for Indians and
bison, had become a mile-wide dust highway.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Pekka H&#228;m&#228;l&#228;inen<lb/>
Texas A&amp;M University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Brown, William E. <title level="m">The Santa Fe Trail: The National Park
Service 1963 Historic Sites Survey</title>. St. Louis <hi rend="smallcaps">MO</hi>: Patrice
Press, 1988.</bibl> <bibl>Walker, Henry Pickering. <title level="m">The Wagonmasters:
High Plains Freighting from the Earliest Days of the Santa
Fe Trail to 1880</title>. Norman: University of Oklahoma Press,
1966.</bibl> <bibl>West, Elliott. <title level="m">The Way to the West: Essays on the
Central Plains</title>. Albuquerque: University of New Mexico
Press, 1995.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>