<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.fil.005 SYSTEM "egp.fil.005.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fil.005">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Autry, Gene (1907-1998)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Kevin Mulroy</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fil.005</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Mulroy, Kevin">Kevin Mulroy</author>. <title level="a">"Autry, Gene (1907-1998)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">259-260</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-09</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">AUTRY, GENE (1907-1998)</head>

<figure n="egp.fil.005" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Gene Autry and Champion, ca. 1947</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Gene Autry's career spanned some sixty years
in the entertainment industry, encompassing
radio, recordings, motion pictures, television,
rodeo, and live performances. He also became
a broadcast executive and major league baseball
team owner. He is the only entertainer to
have five stars on Hollywood's Walk of Fame.
In his ability to transcend media and in the
sheer scope of his output, Autry is unsurpassed
as a popular image maker of the American
West.</p>

<p>Born in Tioga, Texas, on September 29,
1907, Orvon Gene Autry spent most of his
boyhood north of the Red River in Ravia, Oklahoma.
He bought his first guitar for $8 at the
age of twelve and began to sing in local drugstores
and nightspots. By the late 1920s he was
working as a telegrapher for the Frisco railroad
and moving from town to town in Oklahoma.
While he was singing and playing in the
Chelsea office one night, he was discovered by
the great cowboy humorist, Will Rogers. Rogers
advised the young Autry to try radio, and
the rest is history.</p>

<p>Autry began his radio career in 1928 with
station <hi rend="smallcaps">KVOO</hi> in Tulsa as "Oklahoma's Yodeling
Cowboy" and made his first recordings a year
later. His first hit came in 1931 with <title>That Silver-Haired Daddy of Mine</title>, the first record ever certified
gold for having sold more than a million
copies. Autry made his film debut as a dude
ranch cowboy singer in the 1934 Ken Maynard
film <title>In Old Santa Fe</title>. In 1935 he made his
first starring appearance in the science fiction
Western serial <title>The Phantom Empire</title>. Autry's
hugely successful movie formula combined
Hollywood elements with his Plains upbringing:
a mixture of flashy image and downhome
sense. Other important ingredients were
his singing; his trusty horse, Champion; and
his faithful comic sidekick, Smiley Burnette
(played by Pat Buttram). The combination
proved irresistible to Depression-ridden audiences.
By 1937 Autry was "America's Favorite
Cowboy," voted the number one Western star
by the theater exhibitors of America. He remained
in first or second place among cowboy
stars in terms of box office draw until he retired
from motion pictures in 1953.</p>

<p>The successful Hollywood singing cowboy
did not forget his roots. Many of his films,
with titles such as <title>Red River Valley</title> (1936),
<title>Yodelin' Kid from Pine Ridge</title> (1937), <title>Blue Montana Skies</title> (1939), and <hi rend="italic">Sunset in Wyoming</hi>
(1941), were set on the Plains. The effect
of his upbringing on his creative output can
also be seen in the frequent references to the
Southern Plains in Autry's songs. He surrounded
himself with Oklahomans: Bev Barnett,
his publicity director; the Marvin brothers
(Frankie and Johnny) and Jimmy Long,
collaborators on many of his songs; and
Jimmy Wakely and Johnny Bond, who played
with Autry for years, all hailed from the
Sooner State. His first wife, Ina Mae Spivey,
Long's niece, whom Autry married in 1932 and
who played a large part in his success until her
death in 1980, came from Duncan.</p>

<p>In 1941 Autry purchased a 1,360-acre spread
in the foothills of the Arbuckle Mountains,
just west of Berwyn, Oklahoma, as the headquarters
and winter home for his traveling
rodeo. He named it the Flying A Ranch and
Rodeo. Soon after, Berwyn changed its name
to Gene Autry. The small Oklahoma town
maintains a museum devoted to the man it
honors. Autry also toured the Plains states
extensively with his rodeo in the 1940s and
1950s, usually appearing in small towns before
packed audiences.</p>

<p>In total, Autry appeared in 93 feature films
and made 635 recordings, more than 300 of
which he wrote or cowrote. His best-known
movies were based on his hit records, including
<title>South of the Border</title> (1939), <title>Back in the Saddle</title>
(1941), and <title>Strawberry Roan</title> (1948). His
recordings have sold more than 60 million
copies and brought him more than a dozen
gold records. Autry's beloved Christmas and
children's records, <title>Here Comes Santa Claus</title>
(1947) and <title>Peter Cottontail</title> (1950), went platinum
(for more than two million copies sold),
while <title>Rudolph the Red-Nosed Reindeer</title> (1949)
remains the second best selling single of all
time (behind only Bing Crosby's <title>White Christmas</title>),
with sales totaling more than 30 million.</p>

<p>In addition to his movie and recording success,
Autry's <title>Melody Ranch</title> was heard weekly
over the CBS Radio Network between 1940
and 1956. During World War II Autry enlisted
for service on the air during a broadcast of
the show. Sgt. Gene Autry served his country
as a flight officer with the Air Transport Command.
From 1943 until 1945 he flew large cargo
planes in the China-Burma-India theater.
When the war ended, Autry was assigned to
Special Services and toured with a uso troupe
in the South Pacific before resuming his
movie career in 1946.</p>

<p>Realizing that the days of the B-Western
were numbered, in 1950 Autry became one of
the first major film stars to move into television.
For the next five years he produced and
starred in ninety-one episodes of <title>The Gene Autry Show</title> as well as producing such popular
television series as <title>Annie Oakley</title>, <title>The Range Rider</title>, <title>Buffalo Bill Jr.</title>, and <title>The Adventures of Champion</title>. In the late 1980s Autry and his former
movie sidekick, Pat Buttram, hosted
ninety-three episodes of the <title>Melody Ranch Theatre</title> show, spotlighting the telecasting of
his old Republic and Columbia movies.</p>

<p>In 1961 Autry's great love of baseball
prompted him to purchase the American
League's California Angels (renamed the Anaheim
Angels in 1996). He held the title of vice
president of the American League until his
death. Among the many hundreds of honors
this son of the Plains received were induction
into the Country Music Hall of Fame, the Nashville
Songwriters' Hall of Fame, the National
Cowboy Hall of Fame, and the National Association
of Broadcasters Hall of Fame. He also
was honored by his songwriting peers with a
lifetime achievement award from the American
Society of Composers, Authors and Publishers.</p>

<p>A long-cherished dream came true with the
opening in Los Angeles in November 1988 of
the Gene Autry Western Heritage Museum
(renamed the Autry Museum of Western
Heritage in 1995). Autry stated: "It has always
been my intention to build a museum which
would exhibit and interpret the heritage of the
West, and show how it has influenced America
and the world." The Autry Museum is now
acclaimed as one of the foremost museums of
the American West, with important collections
of art, artifacts, and documents, drawing
millions of visitors from around the world.
Jackie Autry, whom he married in 1981, serves
as chairman of its board of directors.</p>

<p>Autry's extraordinary life ended at his
home in Los Angeles on October 2, 1998 after
a long illness. He was ninety-one years old.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Kevin Mulroy<lb/>
University of Southern California</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Gene Autry Collection, Autry Museum of Western Heritage,
Los Angeles.</bibl> <bibl>Autry, Gene, with Mickey Herskowitz.
<title level="m">Back in the Saddle Again</title>. Garden City <hi rend="smallcaps">NY</hi>: Doubleday,
1978.</bibl> <bibl>Rothel, David. <title level="m">The Gene Autry Book</title>. Madison <hi rend="smallcaps">NC</hi>:
Empire Publishing Company, 1988.</bibl>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>