<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.ea.023 SYSTEM "egp.ea.023.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ea.023">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Kelsey, Henry (ca. 1667-1724)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Oliver B. Pollak</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ea.023</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Morton, Anne">Anne Morton</author>. <title level="a">"Kelsey, Henry (ca. 1667-1724)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">239</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-09</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">KELSEY, HENRY (CA. 1667-1724)</head>

<figure n="egp.ea.023" rend="granted">
<figDesc>C. W. Jefferys. Kelsey Sees the Buffalo, August 1691.
1928 calender illustration</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Famous as the first Englishman to have seen
the buffalo, in 1684 the London-born Kelsey
was apprenticed to the Hudson's Bay Company
and sailed to York Factory, its fur trade
post on the west coast of Hudson Bay. The
Hudson's Bay Company's strategy was to build
posts at the mouths of rivers flowing into the
bay and there await the Indians who came
down the rivers from the interior. To encourage
such a trade, the company required employees
who were skilled in Indian languages
and willing to travel inland. As these proved
hard to find, company directors were happy to
learn that "the boy Henry Kelsey [was] a very
active lad delighting much in Indians' company,
being never better pleased than when he
is traveling amongst them."</p>

<p>On June 12, 1690, Kelsey set forth from York
Factory with a group of Indians who had come
to the post to trade. Without their help, and
that of the other Indian men and women
with whom Kelsey traveled, his great journey
would not have been possible. George Geyer of
the Hudson's Bay Company reported that Kelsey
"cheerfully undertook" the expedition.
Kelsey himself recorded that it was "with a
heavy heart" that he headed off to the "Inland
Country of Good Report [which] hath been
by Indians but by English yet not seen." On
July 10 he reached a place he named Deering's
Point, now generally believed to have been
near The Pas, Manitoba, on a bend of the Saskatchewan River. He spent the winter of 1690–
91 in the neighborhood and returned there in
the spring, where he received orders and a
fresh supply of trade goods from Geyer.
Equipped with such items as guns, Brazilian
tobacco, and a brass kettle, he began the second
stage of his journey to "discover and bring
to a Commerce the Naywatame poets." (Linguistic
evidence has identified these people as
Siouan-speaking, perhaps the Hidatsas.)</p>

<p>It is not likely that Kelsey's route will ever be
definitely established. There is a well-argued
case that he traveled south of what is now the
town of Hudson Bay, Saskatchewan, as far as
the Yorkton area and ventured into both the
Beaver and Touchwood Hills. What is beyond
doubt is that he was the first European to see
the Northern Plains and to witness a buffalo
hunt, conducted on foot by people among
whom the horse had yet to be introduced. Kelsey
did reach the Naywatame, although he was
unable to persuade them to suit the interests
of the Hudson's Bay Company by concentrating
less on making war and more on hunting
beaver. Nonetheless, he returned to York Factory
in the summer of 1692 "with a good Fleet
of Indians," much to Geyer's pleasure.</p>

<p>Kelsey remained in the employ of the Hudson's
Bay Company until 1722 as a trader, mariner,
and administrator. He served not only
at York Factory but also on James Bay and the
east coast of Hudson Bay. In 1718 he was
named governor of all Hudson's Bay Company
posts on the bay. He was recalled to England
in 1722 and died in London in 1724.</p>

<p>During his years with the Hudson's Bay
Company Kelsey made several trips back to
England, two of them when he had the misfortune
to be taken by the French when they
captured and then recaptured York Factory. In
1698 he married Elizabeth Dix of East Greenwich.
The couple had two daughters and
a son.</p>

<p>In 1926 a Major A. F. Dobbs of Carrickfergus
presented to the Public Record Office
of Northern Ireland a collection of papers,
among them a manuscript volume titled
"Henry Kelsey his Book," now usually known
as "The Kelsey Papers." This is thought to have
come into the possession of the family in the
time of Arthur Dobbs, a vigorous critic of the
Hudson's Bay Company in the mid-1700s. The
volume includes Kelsey's journals of his 1690–
92 expedition and his 1689 journey to the Barren
Lands, as well as his account of some of
the customs and religious practices of the
Plains Indians. Kelsey also wrote a Cree vocabulary,
published by the Hudson's Bay Company
and long thought to have been lost, until
it was identified in the 1970s among the holdings
of the British Library.</p>

<p>It is for what he saw that Kelsey is remembered.
We think of him as a man privileged to
have seen the Northern Plains and their peoples
as they once were. Yet we should also acknowledge
that he traveled not primarily as a
recorder and observer but as a trader, devoted
to the interests of England and the Hudson's
Bay Company. He came to the Plains to
change what he saw even as he was seeing it.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">INDUSTRY</hi>: <ref n="egp.ind.029">Hudson's Bay Company</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Anne Morton<lb/>
Hudon's Bay Company Archives</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Davies, K. G. "Henry Kelsey." <title level="m">Dictionary of Canadian Biography</title>
2 (1969): 307–15.</bibl> <bibl>Epp, Henry, ed. <title level="m">Three Hundred Prairie Years: Henry Kelsey's "Inland Country of Good Report."</title>
Regina: Canadian Plains Research Center, 1993.</bibl>
<bibl>Warkentin, John. <title level="m">The Kelsey Papers</title>. Regina: Canadian
Plains Research Center, 1994.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>