<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.lt.077">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Vanderhaeghe, Guy (b. 1951)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>John Hugh Lent</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.lt.077</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Lent, John Hugh">John Hugh Lent</author>. <title level="a">"Vanderhaeghe, Guy (b. 1951)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">495</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-25</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">VANDERHAEGHE, GUY (b. 1951)</head>

<p>The publication and reception of Guy Vanderhaeghe's
<title level="m">Man Descending</title> in 1982 indicated the
arrival of a powerful new voice in both western
Canadian literature and Canadian fiction
in general. Over time, the strength of his narratives
and his vision of lives enduring and
surviving have been recognized with two Governor
General's Literary Awards, the City of
Toronto Award, and, in England, the Geoffrey
Faber Memorial Prize for fiction as well as
other honors. Vanderhaeghe was born in Esterhazy,
Saskatchewan, on April 5, 1951. He
was educated at the Universities of Saskatchewan
and Regina and lives in Saskatoon.</p>

<p>Vanderhaeghe's voice comes out of the traditions
and influences of previous writers from
the West&#8211;Wallace Stegner, Sinclair Ross, Martha
Ostenso, W. O. Mitchell, and Margaret
Laurence. Like those writers, Vanderhaeghe's
"naming" of the Prairies is a significant contribution
and, at the least, one of his starting
points. In an early interview with David Carpenter
in 1982, Vanderhaeghe said that his response
to reading Robert Kroetsch's <title level="m">The Studhorse Man</title> was precisely in this act of naming:
"Even though it was such a mythic book it had
a tremendous amount of authenticity for me.
. . . I said to myself, even before I had decided to
write, this part of the world can be written
about." His vision of the Prairie landscape is
painted deeply as a strong wash beneath the
struggles and images of his characters, especially
in <title level="m">Homesick</title> (1990) and <title level="m">The Englishman's Boy</title> (1996). Though he has hauled the urban landscapes of the <title level="m">Canadian Prairie</title> into the foreground of his work more than some previous writers, particularly in <title level="m">My Present Age</title> (1984), it is still true that, as an artist, he has helped celebrate the lyrical beauty and mythical
harshness of the Prairie landscape and universalized
it in his imagery.</p>

<p>Vanderhaeghe's voice also surfaces within a
renaissance of new voices in western fiction:
Robert Kroetsch, Rudy Wiebe, David Aranason,
Carol Shields, Kristjana Gunnars, Aritha
Van Herk, Edna Alford, Sandra Birdsell, and
Jack Hodgins. From the early short stories
through to the large designs of the novels, the
tension between modernist and postmodernist&#8211;
the positioning between past and present
influences&#8211;is always present. Like Alice Munro,
Vanderhaeghe has pushed realist narrative
in a postmodern direction, out into looser,
more chaotic forms, while, unlike Munro, he
has insisted upon an almost modernist leanness
in the images he sets up to control his
vision of contemporary life. The latest evidence
of this tension is the pull, in <title level="m">The Englishman's Boy</title>, between the postmodern, spatial
effects of its narrative as it weaves itself back
and forth between historical foregrounds and
backgrounds and the tight, modernist design
of its vision as it echoes Pound, Fitzgerald, and
Faulkner in its attempt to superimpose images
upon history, force the contradictions and
paradoxes of history into stylized resolutions
or representations of those things.</p>

<p>This struggle in Vanderhaeghe's narratives
is between where he wants to take the traditions
of social and psychological realism in his
forms and how he tries to organize the play
between existence and history in his content.
It accounts for a dichotomy in his texts between
an ever-loosening abandonment of linearity
and closure in form, reminiscent of
Kroetsch and Shields, and an almost mannered,
throwback design in content, reminiscent
of Fitzgerald, Stegner, and Hemingway
and fueled, one suspects, by his own background
in history and philosophy. That is why
the admittedly dark and even limited comedy
of <title level="m">My Present Age</title> can appeal to some readers
who might be suspicious of the lean designs of
<title level="m">The Englishman's Boy</title>, even though the latter
is the stronger work in many ways. It is the
looseness, more Kroetsch-influenced hilarity
of the former that appeals, with its mirrors of
form and content, and it is likely that in further
work this tension between the modern
and postmodern in Vanderhaeghe's writing
will break down, and he will fulfill the brilliance
of his voice and vision even more than
he already has.</p>

<closer>
<signed>John Hugh Lent<lb/>
Okanagan University College</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Carpenter, David. "Inside Guy Vanderhaeghe." <title level="j">NeWest Review</title> 8 (1982): 8–15.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>