<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.war.013">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Counting Coup</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Anthony R. McGinnis</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.war.013</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="McGinnis, Anthony R.">Anthony R. McGinnis</author>. <title level="a">"Counting Coup."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">825</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-26</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">COUNTING COUP</head>
<figure n="egp.war.013" rend="granted">
<figDesc>A depiction of counting coup</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Counting coup, or striking an enemy, was the
highest honor earned by warriors participating
in the intertribal wars of the Great Plains.
Native peoples recognized precise systems of
graduated war honors, and usually the greatest
exploit was counting coup. Key to a man's
success in Plains combat was demonstrating
his own courage by proving superiority over
his opponent and, in a competitive sense, over
his own comrades. Killing was part of war, but
showing courage in the process was more important
for individual status. This was best
accomplished by risking one's life in charging
the enemy on foot or horseback to get close
enough to touch or strike him with the hand,
a weapon, or a "coupstick."</p>

<p>Humiliating the enemy also played a part in
this fighting, as illustrated by an account from
the Jesuit missionary Father Pierre-Jean De
Smet. In De Smet's 1848 visit to the Oglala
Lakotas, the Oglala leader Red Fish related to
the priest how his men had just suffered a
disgraceful defeat at the hands of the Crows.
The Crows killed ten Oglalas, then chased the
others for a distance. The Crows then were
content merely to repeatedly count coup on
their enemies with clubs and sticks, thus demonstrating
to the Oglalas that they were not
worth the ammunition needed to kill them.</p>

<p>Counting coup carried over into the battles
against American troops. For example, the
Northern Cheyenne warrior Wooden Leg related
how, as a young man at the Battle of the
Little Bighorn, he and his friend Little Bird
chased a soldier across the river, counting coup
on him with their whips and grabbing his carbine.
They did not kill him, said Wooden Leg,
because after counting coup it did not seem
particularly brave, and besides, it would waste
bullets. Counting coup, then, was the epitome
of a type of warfare that pitted the skill and
daring of one man against another.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">RELIGION</hi>: <ref n="egp.rel.014">De Smet, Pierre-Jean</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Anthony R. McGinnis<lb/>
Lyons, Colorado</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>McGinnis, Anthony R. <title level="m">Counting Coup and Cutting Horses:
Intertribal Warfare on the Northern Plains, 1738–1889</title>.
Evergreen <hi rend="smallcaps">CO</hi>: Cordillera Press, Inc., 1990.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>