<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.na.077">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Omahas</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Mark J. Awakuni-Swetland</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.na.077</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Awakuni-Swetland, Mark J.">Mark J. Awakuni-Swetland</author>. <title level="a">"Omahas."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">586-587</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-15</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">OMAHAS</head>

<p>The Omahas have lived near the middle Missouri
River since the early 1700s. Their Sacred
Legend describes an origin in a wooded, gamefilled
region near a large body of water, perhaps
the Great Lakes. The Sacred Legend tells how the
people developed many subsistence skills, implements,
and social organizations with focused
thought and keen observation. During the
course of a slow migration westward, the people
adapted to their changing environment. The
language they developed is one of five related
dialects in the Dhegiha branch of the Siouan
language family that also includes the Poncas,
Quapaws, Osages, and Kanzas (Kaws). The
descriptive name "Omaha" (from <hi rend="italic">umo</hi><hi rend="superscript">n</hi><hi rend="italic">ho</hi><hi rend="superscript">n</hi>,
"against the current" or "upstream") indicates
a parting of company from these related peoples
during that migration.</p>

<p>After contact with Arikara and Pawnee
peoples, the Omahas adopted earth lodge
dwellings, bison skin tipis, and local varieties
of maize. They settled into the region west of
the Missouri between the Platte and Niobrara
Rivers. Village sites were situated along running
streams where the bottomlands provided
tillable soil, fuel, and building materials.
<hi rend="italic">To</hi><hi rend="superscript">n</hi>'<hi rend="italic">wo</hi><hi rend="superscript">n</hi><hi rend="italic">to</hi><hi rend="superscript">n</hi><hi rend="italic">gatho</hi><hi rend="superscript">n</hi>, or "Big Village on Omaha
Creek," was the principal Omaha village from
1775 until 1845, with a population estimated to
have been more than 2,000 people in 1795. The
Omahas created a complex schedule of seasonal
movements that enabled them to produce
substantial gardens of maize, beans, and
other cultigens, while conducting large-scale
communal bison hunts on the western plains
of present-day Nebraska and Kansas.</p>

<p>It was during the summer bison hunts that
Omaha social organization became graphically
visible. When the people paused in their
daily travels, all of the tipis were erected in a
circle on the prairie. The Omahas are divided
into ten patrilineal clans, each of which has
one or more subclans. The ten clans camped
in designated places around the circle.</p>

<p>The Omahas are further organized in a
moiety system, or complementary halves, in
which one half of the clans are associated with
the earth-female cosmic forces, and the other
half with sky-male cosmic forces. Each clan
and subclan has a catalog of unique personal
names for its members, as well as particular
duties, rights, and prohibitions. Marriage is to
a person outside the clan and, ideally, outside
the moiety. Any tendencies toward factionalism
are reduced because all ceremonial and
political functions require the presence and
assistance of multiple clans.</p>

<p>Seven of the ten clans traditionally provided
an individual to sit on the tribal council,
which deliberated on community affairs and
arbitrated disputes. Their authority was sanctioned
by the use of two Sacred Tribal Pipes.
The eighth clan, as keepers of the Sacred Tent
of War, provided military leadership during
times of external assault. The two remaining
clans did not have a seat on the council but
performed important duties for the maintenance
of the community.</p>

<p>The Omahas had several social societies
that served to foster martial and civic responsibilities.
One of the most important of these
was the <hi rend="italic">Heth&#250;shka</hi>. Membership was restricted
to men who had received public war
honors. The distinctive dances, songs, and regalia
of this society have become the foundation
of the "War Dance" of the contemporary
Great Plains powwow. Men performing acts
of generosity could become members of a
chief 's society. There were also several doctoring
and secret societies.</p>

<p>The Sacred Legend describes the first meeting
with Europeans while the Omaha were in
the east. This first amicable encounter was followed
by the establishment of relations with
the French by 1724, the British by 1790, and
American traders soon after. The Omahas
have maintained a tradition of peaceful relations
with European and American visitors
ever since. An example of this peace can be
seen in the material assistance Omahas rendered
to Mormon emigrants residing at their
Winter Quarters on the Missouri River in
1846–48.</p>

<p>Until the late nineteenth century amicable
relations with nearby Native groups were not
always the rule. The need to travel to the western
bison-hunting grounds for provisions
placed the Omahas in a vulnerable position
on two fronts. A successful summer hunt required
the presence of religious objects such
as the Sacred Pole and the Sacred Buffalo
Hide, their aged caretakers, and the entire
tribal group. Such a slow-moving company of
men, women, children, dogs, and horses burdened
with gear made an easy target for enemies.
Meanwhile, those people who were too
old or infirm to make the journey remained in
the earth lodge villages to tend the gardens.
The few able-bodied men who stayed to protect
them were at a disadvantage if a superior
force attacked.</p>

<p>Contact and interaction with European
Americans wrought many changes on Omaha
society. Subsistence hunting and agriculture
shifted to an international fur trade economy.
Traditional skills, arts, and crafts declined in
favor of the use of trade goods, including firearms.
Political and social status shifted as men
better able to negotiate trade or hunt successfully
for marketable quantities of pelts and
bison robes overshadowed customary leaders
whose prestige had been gained through oratorical
skills, consensus building, and acts of
generosity. Women expended more energy in
the preparation of furs and hides for market.
Recurring epidemic diseases reduced the population
several times, causing the Omahas to
lose control of the fur trade in their region
while becoming increasingly vulnerable to attack
by their enemies. They were forced to
finally abandonTo<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>'wo<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>to<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>gatho<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> in 1845 and
retreat to a village site closer to the mouth of
the Platte.</p>

<p>Under such pressures the Omahas signed
treaties relinquishing control of land. The 1830
Treaty of Prairie du Chien ceded their claims
to land in the present state of Iowa. To protect
their own future they signed an 1854 treaty
establishing a reservation in exchange for the
remainder of their Nebraska land. The Omahas
moved to their present reservation in
1855–56.</p>

<p>Many Omahas embraced some of the more
visible "Americanizing" efforts of the federal
government by adopting frame houses, new
farming techniques, Christianity, and English-language
education for their children. Important
institutions such as the Sacred Pole, Sacred
Buffalo Hide, the Sacred Tribal Pipes, and
the Sacred Tent of War were put to sleep. Some
of the secret and social societies went underground.
Other Native organizations, such as
the Native American Church, emerged.</p>

<p>In 1882 some Omahas joined with various
non-Indian interest groups to push for the allotment
of land. Much of the allotted lands
was later sold, or it was forfeited because the
taxes could not be paid. Allotments that once
blanketed the entire reservation at the turn of
the century were eroded to a strip of Omaha
holdings along the Missouri River bluffs by
the 1950s.</p>

<p>The Omahas voted to accept the provisions
of the Indian Reorganization Act of 1934, creating
a constitutional government with a tribal
council elected by popular vote. The Omaha
Tribal Council has emerged as the provider of
services or space for many of the secular and
sacred activities of the community. These
efforts were given a boost in 1962 with a $2.9
million award from the Indian Claims Commission
for Omaha lands taken in 1854. Reservation
lands stranded east of the shifting Missouri
River in Iowa were reclaimed and are
being developed. Proceeds from these enterprises,
including the Casino Omaha, have been
applied to social and cultural revival efforts.</p>

<p>In 1994 about 2,000 of the 5,227 tribal members
lived on the reservation, most in the Macy,
Nebraska, area. A large number of Omahas
make their homes in the surrounding urban
centers of Omaha and Lincoln, Nebraska, and
Sioux City, Iowa. An annual August encampment
and powwow is held at Macy that serves
as a homecoming opportunity for the off-
reservation tribal members.</p>

<p>Many Omahas continue to negotiate their
lives between the pressures of mainstream western society and the traditional values of Omaha
culture. Leaders continue to emerge out of this
struggle, men and women who emulate the
values in the Sacred Legend of focused thought
and keen observation. It is their strength and
dignity that encourage the Omaha people to
continue traveling upstream as a proud nation.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Mark J. Awakuni-Swetland</signed>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Dorsey, James Owen. "Omaha Sociology." In <title level="m">Third Annual
Report of the Bureau of American Ethnology</title> (1881-
1882). Washington <hi rend="smallcaps">DC</hi>: Government Printing Office, 1884.</bibl>
<bibl>Fletcher, Alice C., and Francis La Flesche. "The Omaha
Tribe." <title level="m">Twenty-seventh Annual Report of the Bureau of
American Ethnology</title> (1905-1906). Washington <hi rend="smallcaps">DC</hi>: Government
Printing Office, 1911.</bibl> <bibl>Tate, Michael L. <title level="m">The Upstream
People: An Annotated Research Bibliography of the
Omaha Tribe</title>. Metuchen <hi rend="smallcaps">NJ</hi>: Scarecrow Press, 1991.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>