<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.gen.014">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Gay and Lesbian Life</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Will Fellows</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.gen.014</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Fellows, Will">Will Fellows</author>. <title level="a">"Gay and Lesbian Life."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">329</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-18</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">GAY AND LESBIAN LIFE</head>

<p>Social isolation is a major force in the lives of
gay men and lesbians in the Great Plains, especially
in small towns and rural areas. This
isolation results from the region's great distances
and low population density, the conformist
and privacy-guarding aspects of rural
and small-town life, and the tendency of many
gays and lesbians to leave their hometowns for
larger cities within and outside the region. In
urban places it is generally easier for them to
be themselves and to connect with other gays
and lesbians.</p>

<p>Though the intensity of this migration has
possibly lessened in recent years, it continues,
and it helps to foster the idea among many
heterosexuals that homosexuality is an exclusively
urban phenomenon, irrelevant to rural
or small-town life. Many gays and lesbians who
stay in their small communities strengthen this
belief by concealing their homosexuality, or by
denying and suppressing it in order to follow a
traditional life pattern that typically includes
marriage and child rearing. Growing up in
a homogeneous and conformist community,
lacking information and openly gay role models,
gay and lesbian youth are likely to perpetuate
this pattern.</p>

<p>In recent years, with television and other
vehicles of popular culture depicting gays and
lesbians living openly, gay and lesbian youth
are less likely to remain ignorant of, or confused
by, their natures and are less susceptible
to making life choices that are rooted in concealment
and pretense. Internet access to supportive
information and social connections is
especially valuable to the most isolated gays
and lesbians, perhaps reducing their likelihood
of attempting suicide or engaging in
substance abuse, unsafe sexual practices, or
other self-destructive behaviors.</p>

<p>Great Plains culture celebrates individualism,
but only within the tightly delimited
boundaries of conventional gender identity.
Females are allowed somewhat more latitude
to stray from the feminine ideal than are males
to deviate from the masculine. Especially
when it is combined with fundamentalist interpretations
of biblical texts and with the
puritanism of Judeo-Christian culture, this
gender-role rigidity is a powerful enforcer of
the heterosexual norm.</p>

<p>No state or provincial government of the
Plains region has been progressive in extending
full civil rights to gay men and lesbians. In
many places, their consensual sexual activity is
criminalized, their access to housing and employment
is threatened, and the recognition of
marriage or domestic partnership for their
committed relationships is denied. It is not
uncommon for acts of antigay violence to be
viewed with indifference or a sense of being
deserved. In a widely publicized case, Matthew
Shepard was murdered in Laramie, Wyoming,
in 1998. Though he was a native of that state,
the twenty-one-year-old had attended high
school in Europe and had lived on the East
Coast. Returning to Wyoming, he brought
with him a manner of self-presentation that
proved to be fatally at odds with Plains culture:
he would not, or could not, conceal his
gayness.</p>

<p>Before contact with Europeans, many Native
cultures of the Plains accommodated and
even valued gender-atypical males and females.
Regarded as a blend of woman and
man, these individuals were clearly counterparts
of contemporary gays and lesbians, but
their differences from typical men and women
were understood by their tribes to be more
complex than simply "sexual orientation."
Seen as having special talents, they performed
well-defined and respected functions within
their communities: artists, healers, mediators,
keepers of cultural traditions. As Native cultures
have been eroded or destroyed, so have
these intermediate gender identities, though
some contemporary Native Americans are
embracing and reviving them&#8211;preferring to
call themselves two-spirit rather than gay or
lesbian.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Will Fellows<lb/>
Milwaukee, Wisconsin</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Fellows, Will, ed. <title level="m">Farm Boys: Lives of Gay Men from the Rural Midwest</title>. Madison: University of Wisconsin Press,
1996.</bibl> <bibl>Jacobs, Sue-Ellen, Wesley Thomas, and Sabine Lang,
eds. <title level="m">Two-Spirit People: Native American Gender Identity, Sexuality, and Spirituality</title>. Urbana: University of Illinois
Press, 1997.</bibl> <bibl>Loffreda, Beth. <title level="m">Losing Matt Shepard: Life and Politics in the Aftermath of Anti-Gay Murder</title>. New York:
Columbia University Press, 2000.</bibl>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>