<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.na.107">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Sioux</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Guy Gibbon</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.na.107</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Gibbon, Guy">Guy Gibbon</author>. <title level="a">"Sioux."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">601-602</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-20</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">SIOUX</head>

<p>The Sioux, and most particularly the Lakota
Sioux, are the iconic warrior horsemen of the
Northern Plains. They have become perhaps
the best known of all Indian nations through
paintings and photographs, confrontations
with the U.S. military, Wild West shows, and
hundreds of Hollywood movies. Sitting Bull,
Crazy Horse, Red Cloud, and other Lakota
Sioux leaders are among the most famous of
all Native Americans, and the Battle of the
Little Bighorn in 1876 and the Wounded Knee
Massacre in 1890 are among the most widely
known events in U.S. history. But the Lakotas
are only one division of the Great Sioux
Nation.</p>

<p>The Great Sioux Nation, known as <hi rend="italic">Oceti
Sakowin</hi>, or "Seven Council Fires," is a confederation
of closely allied cognate bands.
They speak three mutually intelligible dialects
of the Siouan language family: Dakota, Nakota,
and Lakota. They became known as the
Sioux, or a word like it, in the seventeenth
century, when their enemies, the Ojibwas, told
the French that that was what they were called.
The word derives from the Ojibwa term <hi rend="italic">Na
dou esse</hi>, which means "Snakeline Ones" or
"Enemies." The French spelled the word <hi rend="italic">Nadousioux</hi>,
and the English and Americans shortened
it to Sioux. In recent years, the Sioux, like
many other Native peoples, have made a concerted
effort to replace their imposed, derogatory
name by the names they called themselves.
Self-identification is commonly based
on either band or sub-band names (e.g., Santee,
Oglala, or Sicangu), linguistic groups
(Lakota, Dakota, or Nakota), or, increasingly
in the twentieth century, by the name of the
reservation of origin (e.g., "Rosebud Sioux" or
"Cheyenne River Sioux").</p>

<p>The Great Sioux Nation has seven primary
divisions, based on their respective places in
the Seven Council Fires. The Isantis (Santees),
Dakota speakers, occupy the east and are comprised
of four council fires: the Mdewakantunwan,
the Sisitunwan, the Wahpetunwan,
and the Wahpekute. The Wiciyelas, Nakota
speakers, occupy the middle division and are
composed of two council fires: the Ihanktunwun
(Yanktons) and Ihanktunwanna (Yanktonais).
The western council fire is occupied
by the Titunwans (Tetons), Lakota speakers,
composed of seven sub-bands: Oglala (Scatter
One's Own), Sicangu or Brul&#233; (Burnt Thigh),
Hunkpapa (Those Who Camp At the Entrance),
Mnikowoju o Minneconjou (Those
Who Plant By the Stream), Itzipco or Sans
Arcs (Without Bows), Oohenunpa (Two Kettles),
and Sihasapa (Black Feet).</p>

<p>Europeans first encountered the Sioux in
the seventeenth century in the mixed hardwood
forests of central Minnesota and northwestern
Wisconsin. In the mid-seventeenth
century, the Sioux began moving westward
and southward, pushed by the Ojibwas, who
gradually infiltrated into Minnesota from the
Lake Superior area, and pulled by the abundant
Plains bison herds and the diffusion of
horses from the Southern Plains. While some
bands had a few horses by 1707, if not earlier,
the Lakotas did not fundamentally become
Plains horsemen until 1750-75, by which time
they had crossed the Missouri River, displacing
the previous residents of the region. By
the mid-eighteenth century, the Lakotas and
Nakotas were closely associated with the Central
and Northern Plains. The Dakotas (Santees)
remained primarily in Minnesota, where
they received reservations in the nineteenth
century. The Sioux Uprising of 1862 resulted
in the relocation of many Santees to small reservations
in South Dakota and Nebraska, although
others remained in Minnesota.</p>

<p>As each of the Council Fires adapted to different
Plains environments, their lifeways
changed and diverged from one another. Yet
they maintained their political, economic, and
social ties through intermarriage, trade, religious
ceremonies, communal hunting, and
military alliances.</p>

<p>The Yanktons and Yanktonais, who eventually
settled in the eastern Dakotas, became
middlemen in a far-flung trade system between
the Lakotas, who had pushed westward
as far as Wyoming and eastern Montana, and
the eastern Santees, who were closely involved
in the French fur trade in Minnesota. While
the Lakotas became buffalo-hunting, nomadic
horsemen, and the principal grain grown by
the Santees shifted from wild rice to corn,
some Yanktons and Yanktonais adopted many
of the traits of the semisedentary Plains villagers,
such as the Mandans and Arikaras, including
the building of earth lodges. With the
horse for transportation and vast herds of
bison, the Lakotas prospered and their numbers
grew until, by the nineteenth century,
they outnumbered all other bands of the
Great Sioux Nation combined. By the mid.
nineteenth century, the Lakotas and their allies
presented a formidable military and political
barrier to European American expansion
into the Central and Northern Plains.</p>

<p>The Lakotas eventually controlled a vast
hunting territory stretching from the Platte
River north to the Heart River and from the
Missouri River west to the Bighorn Mountains.
Their highly flexible social and political
organization was well suited to the demands
of maintaining such an empire. The basic unit
of Lakota society was the <hi rend="italic">tiyospaye</hi>, a small
group of bilaterally related kin, informally led
by a headman. Each of the seven Lakota subbands
had societies, including <hi rend="italic">akicitas</hi> (police)
and <hi rend="italic">nacas</hi> (civil leaders). Nacas from each of
the sub-bands formed a tribal council (<hi rend="italic">Naca
Ominicia</hi>) with executive committees commonly
known as <hi rend="italic">wicasa</hi> (shirt wearers). When
the seven sub-bands congregated each summer
for the Sun Dance, the nacas of each of
the seven sub-bands constituted a national
council. Holy men and medicine people were
also consulted on important matters, revealing
the centrality of Lakota spiritual and ceremonial
life.</p>

<p>The belief systems and rituals of the Lakotas
and Nakotas reflect many of the values essential
for successful nomadic bison hunting in
the Northern Great Plains (e.g., individuality,
bravery, sacrifice, vision seeking). The Lakotas
are further anchored to the Great Plains by
their conviction that they were created by
<hi rend="italic">Wakan Tanka</hi> (Grandfather, the Great Spirit)
and emerged from a cave (Wind Cave) in <hi rend="italic">Paha
Sapa</hi>, the Black Hills of South Dakota. This
place, more than any other, is sacred to the
Lakotas. It was in the Great Plains that the
Lakotas received their Sacred Pipe and the
Seven Sacred Rites, including the Sun Dance,
from White Buffalo Calf Woman.</p>

<p>Life within the tiyospaye centered around
daily subsistence tasks divided by age and gender.
Hunting, raiding, and making tools and
weapons were the responsibilities of men,
with time leftover for trading, counsels, ceremonies,
and leisure activities, such as wagering
on foot and horse races. Women's responsibilities
included gathering wild resources,
such as prairie turnips, processing and tanning
hides, cooking, sewing, quillwork, and
managing the daily needs of the household.
Women were responsible for breaking camp,
packing belongings on travois, and setting up
camp again at the end of the day. Older children
and youth frequently had responsibility
for gathering firewood and water and tending
to horses and dogs. Grandparents and elders
were often entrusted with the primary responsibility
for caring for small children
and infants and assisting with household
tasks. In Lakota society, men were allowed to
have more than one wife, and men of high
status frequently had several wives, ideally sisters
or women from the same tiyospaye.</p>

<p>During the first half of the nineteenth century,
at the very time the horse-riding nomadic
way of life of the Lakotas was flourishing, the
grasslands were being invaded by European
Americans. The U.S. government initiated an
aggressive military policy in the Plains during
the 1860s. This policy included building additional
military posts and pursuing Indian
groups characterized as "hostile," activities
that inflamed already tense relations between
the federal government and the Lakotas and
their allies. The Great Sioux Nation and its
allies proved formidable opponents, militarily
and politically, and brought the U.S. government
to the negotiating table twice at Fort
Laramie (1854 and 1868) to sign treaties. The
1868 Treaty of Fort Laramie established the
Great Sioux Reservation, spanning more than
half of the modern state of South Dakota (west
of the Missouri River), and provided annuities
and rations for the Sioux. Economic relief was
welcomed by the tribe. Bison were an increasingly
scarce resource in the Plains by the mid-
1870s, and by the mid-1880s they were virtually
extinct. The eradication of the bison, mainstay
of their economy, had a devastating impact on
the Sioux.</p>

<p>By the 1870s intolerable pressures led to a
series of "Indian Wars," the most famous of
which was the annihilation of Gen. George
Armstrong Custer's Seventh Calvary at the
Battle of the Little Bighorn in 1876 by Sitting
Bull's Lakotas and their Cheyenne allies. Retribution
was swift, and even those Lakotas
who held out, including the bands of Crazy
Horse and Sitting Bull, were eventually settled
on the Great Sioux Reservation. In 1889 Congress
broke up the Great Sioux Reservation
into several smaller reservations in North and
South Dakota. These reservations were loosely
based on membership of the sub-bands. Their
holdings were further diminished and scattered
by allotment in severalty in the 1890s,
which forced nuclear families onto small
acreages and opened the remaining ‘‘surplus''
land to non-Indian settlement. Many Lakotas
selected their allotments near other members
of their tiyospayes, maintaining a semblance
of their old organization. The massacre of Big
Foot's band at Wounded Knee Creek in 1890
and the killing of Sitting Bull by Indian policemen
the same year marked the end of freedom
and the preferred nomadic way of life for
many Lakotas.</p>

<p>The 1890s were difficult years for the Sioux.
Confined to reservations, where indifferent and
self-serving Indian agents controlled them, they
were expected to farm arid land. Their children
were shipped to boarding schools, such as Carlisle
Indian School in Pennsylvania, where they
were urged to abandon their Indian ways. The
Sun Dance, which had always served as an integrating
mechanism for the Lakotas, had been
banned along with other Lakota rituals in 1882.
Although it was banned, the Lakota Sun Dance
was never eradicated; it simply went "underground"
to await a more tolerant era. In the
1890s other religions, such as the Ghost Dance
and peyotism, helped fill the gap.</p>

<p>The first two decades of the twentieth century
were periods of adjustment to reservation
life on scattered allotments. Some reservations
even began to prosper, to a degree, in the 1920s,
only to be devastated during the Dust Bowl
and Depression of the 1930s. Still, the catastrophe
provided an opportunity to introduce radical
reforms. These well-intentioned reforms
were introduced by John Collier of the new
Roosevelt administration and enacted as the
Indian Reorganization Act (<hi rend="smallcaps">IRA</hi>) of 1934. The
<hi rend="smallcaps">IRA</hi> was designed to improve subsistence and
employment opportunities on the reservations
and to ensure that tribal councils were
democratically elected (counter to the traditions
of the Lakotas and others). Collier and
his staff targeted the Sioux reservations in the
Dakotas and pressured them to adopt <hi rend="smallcaps">IRA</hi>-style
governments and constitutions, which they
did. The <hi rend="smallcaps">IRA</hi> reforms resulted in short-term
moderate relief, as the Lakotas took advantage
of some of the economic development programs,
but they had negligible long-term benefits,
with the exception that allotment policy
was ended, which allowed the Lakotas to halt
the erosion of their land base.</p>

<p>The second half of the twentieth century was
a time of far-reaching change and renewal for
many Sioux. Reduction in mortality and high
birthrates almost doubled their population,
which strained employment on reservations.
As part of the termination policy, the Eisenhower
administration encouraged Indians to
leave their reservations with the 1952 Voluntary
Relocation Program. In the 1950s and 1960s
regional centers such as Denver, Cheyenne,
Bismarck, Minneapolis, Sioux Falls, and Sioux
City became home to many Sioux. Poorly educated
and discriminated against, many young
Sioux soon returned to their reservations. The
turbulence of this period in federal Indian policy,
coupled with the civil rights movement,
encouraged the birth of the American Indian
Movement (<hi rend="smallcaps">AIM</hi>). <hi rend="smallcaps">AIM</hi> has maintained a close
connection to the Great Sioux Nation, with
many leaders&#8212;Russell Means, Leonard Peltier,
and John Trudell&#8212;claiming Sioux ancestry.</p>

<p>By the 1970s the once radical position that
Indians should be able to follow their own
cultural traditions&#8212;rather than be forced to
assimilate to European American traditions&#8212;
became more widely accepted. The publication
of Dee Brown's immensely popular <title level="m">Bury
My Heart at Wounded Knee</title> in 1971 and a new
confrontation at Wounded Knee in 1973 led by
<hi rend="smallcaps">AIM</hi>, heightened public consciousness of the
plight of the Sioux. Moreover, this era confirmed
that the sacred Black Hills were not,
nor had they ever been, for sale. In 1980 the
U.S. Supreme Court reviewed the fifty-seven-year-
old Black Hills land claims case of the
Great Sioux Nation and concluded that the
taking of the Black Hills by the U.S. government
was illegal and that the Great Sioux Nation
was entitled to compensation for the taking.
That award has now grown to more than
$600 million and continues to draw interest
in the U.S. Treasury because the Great Sioux
Nation has refused the settlement, demanding
the return of Paha Sapa, the Black Hills,
instead.</p>

<p>Despite the gains reaped from the political
and economic programs of the self-determination
era, the Sioux reservations in
North and South Dakota remain some of the
poorest places in the United States. Many reservations
have chosen to open casinos, and
some have enjoyed the benefits of large-scale
capital infusions into their local economies;
others, because of their remoteness from urban
population centers, have seen little improvement
in their economies, besides improving
joblessness rates, as a result of casinos.
Today, although transformed through decades
of hardship and deprivation, the Great Sioux
Nation is in a vigorous, if difficult, renaissance.
Many Lakotas continue to speak their language
and practice traditions such as the Sun Dance.
Tribal community colleges, frequently named
after important Lakota leaders, have sprung up
on the reservations and are educating tribal
members in the skills required to engage the
global economy and simultaneously recapture
their tribal heritage and traditions.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">IMAGES AND ICONS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ii.061">Wild West Shows</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">LAW</hi>: <ref n="egp.law.050"><hi rend="italic">United States v. Sioux Nation of
Indians</hi></ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">PROTEST AND DISSENT</hi>: <ref n="egp.pd.005">American Indian Movement</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">SPORTS AND RECREATION</hi>:
<ref n="egp.sr.037">Mills, Billy</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">WAR</hi>: <ref n="egp.war.014">Crazy Horse</ref>; <ref n="egp.war.025">Little Bighorn, Battle of the</ref>; <ref n="egp.war.036">Red Cloud</ref>; <ref n="egp.war.044">Sioux Wars</ref>;
<ref n="egp.war.056">Wounded Knee Massacre</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Guy Gibbon</signed>
University of Minnesota</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>DeMallie, Raymond J., and Douglas R. Parks, eds. <title level="m">Sioux
Indian Religion</title>. Norman: University of Oklahoma Press,
1987.</bibl> <bibl>Howard, James H. <title level="m">The Canadian Sioux</title>. Lincoln:
University of Nebraska Press, 1984.</bibl> <bibl>Price, Catherine. <title level="m">The
Oglala People, 1841–1879: A Political History</title>. Lincoln: University
of Nebraska Press, 1996.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>