<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.pg.046">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">McGovern, George (b. 1922)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Stephen Zunes</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.pg.046</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Zunes, Stephen">Stephen Zunes</author>. <title level="a">"McGovern, George (b. 1922)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">674</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-30</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">MCGOVERN, GEORGE (b. 1922)</head>

<p>South Dakota senator and 1972 Democratic
presidential nominee George McGovern was
born on July 19, 1922, in the small town of
Avon in southeastern South Dakota. He later
moved with his family to Mitchell, where his
father served as minister for the town's Methodist
Church. McGovern's interest in politics
first became apparent in high school, where
he was an active member of the debate team,
through which he met his future wife, Eleanor
Sternberg. He entered Dakota Wesleyan University
in Mitchell on an academic scholarship
in 1940. Three years later he enlisted in the
U.S. Army Air Corps, becoming a highly decorated
<hi rend="smallcaps">B</hi>-24 bomber pilot in Europe. He completed
his bachelor of arts degree at Dakota
Wesleyan in 1946.</p>

<p>Following his graduation, McGovern, who
had a deep interest in the Social Gospel, enrolled
at Garrett Theological Seminary on the
campus of Northwestern University in Evanston,
Illinois. But after hearing a lecture by the
western historian Ray Allen Billington, he
opted for graduate work in history. He received
his doctorate from Northwestern in
1953. McGovern then began a short career as a
professor at Dakota Wesleyan University before
being elected to the U.S. House of Representatives
in 1956. In 1961 President John F.
Kennedy named him director of the Food for
Peace program. He left the Kennedy administration
the following year to run for Senate
and was elected for the first of three terms.
Though best known in his Senate career for
his outspoken opposition to the Vietnam War,
South Dakotans appreciated him most for his
efforts on behalf of Plains farmers and his expertise
on food and agricultural policy.</p>

<p>McGovern briefly entered the race for the
1968 presidential nomination following the
assassination of Robert Kennedy. The widespread
outcry over the perceived unfairness of
the presidential nomination process led to the
creation of a reform commission in 1969,
which McGovern chaired. In 1972 he ran again
for the presidency, this time winning the Democratic
nomination with the help of an army of
young volunteers. Pundits were stunned that
the junior senator from a small Plains state,
widely known as "the prairie populist," could
defeat the better-financed favorites of the party
leadership.</p>

<p>Although McGovern was a deeply religious
family man rooted in the populist traditions
of the Great Plains, Republicans and some elements
of the Washington media tried to link
him with the excesses of the radical counter-culture
of the day. Abandoned by much of the
Democratic Party establishment, badly outspent,
and subjected to a series of "dirty
tricks" that were later revealed in the Watergate
investigation, McGovern lost the election
to incumbent President Richard Nixon in one
of the biggest landslides in U.S. history. Less
than a year later, however, as Nixon's scandals
unfolded, public opinion polls showed that
were the election held over, McGovern would
have won.</p>

<p>McGovern was reelected to the Senate in
1974 but was defeated in 1980 in a stunning
upset, along with several other prominent
Democrats, in the Republican landslide. He
became a part-time lecturer at Northwestern
and other universities and continued to speak
out on political affairs. He launched an unsuccessful
bid for the Democratic presidential
nomination in 1984. He became president of
the Middle East Policy Council in 1991, calling
for a more balanced U.S. policy toward
the region. The alcohol-related death of his
daughter Terry in 1994 led McGovern to write
a widely acclaimed personalized biography of
her struggle with alcoholism, and he soon became
a prominent spokesperson for the recognition
and treatment of the disease. In 1997
President Bill Clinton named him the U.S.
permanent representative to the United Nations
Food and Agricultural Organization
based in Rome.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Stephen Zunes<lb/>
University of San Francisco</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>McGovern, George. <title level="m">Grassroots</title>. New York: Random House,
1977.</bibl> <bibl>Weil, Gordon L. <title level="m">The Long Shot: George McGovern Runs
for President</title>. New York: W. W. Norton Co., 1973.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>