<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fil.026">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main"><hi rend="italic">The Grapes of Wrath</hi></title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Jim Sanderson</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fil.026</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Sanderson, Jim">Jim Sanderson</author>. <title level="a">"<hi rend="italic">The Grapes of Wrath</hi>."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">268</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-12</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main"><hi rend="italic">The Grapes of Wrath</hi></head>
<figure n="egp.fil.026" rend="granted"  type="noclick">
<figDesc>The Grapes of Wrath theatrical release poster</figDesc>
</figure>     

<p>While John Ford was filming <title>The Grapes of Wrath</title> in 1940, St. Louis citizens were dumping
the controversial "communist" novel into
the Mississippi. Darryl F. Zanuck, head of
Twentieth Century Fox, acquired the rights to
John Steinbeck's novel, appointed the most respected
screenwriter of the time, Nunnally
Johnson, to write the script, and then negotiated
for what seemed to be the obvious director,
John Ford. Henry Fonda coveted the role
of Tom Joad so much that he bargained away
his career to get the role. But with the Hays
Commission criticizing any overt political
statement and the novel's controversy, Zanuck
was worried about his prize property. Ford
took his production inside a sound stage so
that no one could interfere. Gregg Toland,
whose stylized black-and-white photography
would contribute greatly not only to Ford's
<title>The Long Voyage Home</title> (1940) but also to Orson
Welles's <title>Citizen Kane</title> (1941), was Ford's
cinematographer. Toland's work became part
of Ford's translation of Steinbeck's naturalism
and pessimism to the screen.</p>

<p>In John Ford's films, one or two protagonists
try to maintain their sometimes perverse
individuality while helping some nuclear, professional,
social, or makeshift family. Often
the family or society may incorporate the individual
into its mythology and thus guarantee
cultural continuity. In John Steinbeck's
novel, set in eastern Oklahoma during the
Great Depression, family and individuality are
crushed by the times. Ford's film doesn't cheat
Steinbeck. It recognizes the times and Steinbeck's
points (and even his tone), but it maintains
Ford's romanticism (a romanticism that
would dim with later films).</p>

<p>In the film, Ford and Toland's compositions
confine or squeeze the protagonist, Tom Joad,
played by Henry Fonda at his iconic best. Ford
and Fonda, both cognizant of the dark side of
the American male hero, present Tom Joad, a
returning convict, in danger of turning sociopathic
if not even psychopathic. When Ma
Joad (Jane Darwell) first sees him upon his
return from prison, she asks, "Did they [the
prison, the system] hurt you and make you
mean, mad?" From the way that Fonda conducts
himself, from Ford's composition, we
see that Tom could turn mean or mad. But his
madness is the key to his salvation and his
transcendence.</p>

<p>Casey, the preacher (John Carradine), becomes
a stand-in for John the Baptist and
anoints Tom Joad as the visionary. When
Casey is killed, Tom, not yet fully aware of his
new status, not fully past his psychopathic
urges, kills a deputy. Later, fully aware of
Casey's vision in his "I'll be there speech" to
Ma, Tom becomes Emersonian: "Fella ain't got
a soul, just a piece of the big soul. The big soul
that belongs to everybody. I'll be all around in
the dark." He walks into the dark and disappears,
into the compositions that squeezed
him. He may die, but he has learned something
of a new consciousness, or maybe he has
learned to forget his own consciousness in
order to become a part of the flow of all life. His
sacrifice makes society better. The only false
note is the ending, Ma's "We're the People"
speech that tries to turn the film into patriotic
propaganda. Ford claims Zanuck attached the
last scene; Johnson claimed that it was in his
original script; Zanuck denied attaching it. In
other words, no one claims it, for it smears this
epic poem.</p>

<p>Ford's Grapes of Wrath is not so much a
portrayal of a particular American time and
place as a dark, brooding, but ultimately optimistic
and poetic vision of America. It shows
the way one medium can adopt or adapt from
another to produce not a hybrid, not a completely
different animal, but a meditation and
variation on the tone and theme of the original.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">IMAGES AND ICONS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ii.044">Okies</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT</hi>: <ref n="egp.pe.022">Dust Bowl</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">TRANSPORTATION</hi>: <ref n="egp.tra.032">Route 66</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Jim Sanderson<lb/>
Lamar University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Gallagher, Tag. <title level="m">John Ford: The Man and His Films</title>. Berkeley:
University of California Press, 1986.</bibl> <bibl>Place, J. A. <title level="m">The Non-Western Films of John Ford</title>. Secaucus <hi rend="smallcaps">NJ</hi>: Citadel
Press, 1979.</bibl> <bibl>Sanderson, Jim. "American Romanticism in
John Ford's The Grapes of Wrath: Horizontalness, Darkness,
Christ, and F.D.R." <title level="j">Literature/Film Quarterly</title> 17
(1989): 231–44.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>