<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.afam.019">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Fields, Mary (ca. 1832–1914)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Darlene Clark Hine</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.afam.019</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Hine, Darlene Clark">Darlene Clark Hine</author>. <title level="a">"Fields, Mary (ca. 1832-1914)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">14-15</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-12-03</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">FIELDS, MARY (ca. 1832–1914)</head>
<figure n="egp.afam.019" rend="granted" type="noclick">
<figDesc>Photograph of Mary Fields (Source: Sister Mary Rose Krupp, Ursuline Convent Offices, 4045 Indian Road, Toledo, OH 43606. Used with permission. (www.lkwdpl.org/wihohio/fiel-mar.htm)</figDesc>
</figure>    
    
<p>Mary Fields was one of the most colorful characters
in the history of the Great Plains. Various
descriptions of her claim that she was six
feet tall, weighed over 200 pounds, smoked
homemade cigars, and carried a pair of six-shooters
and a ten-gauge shotgun. She never
married or had children. She gained widespread
fame, and the nickname "Stage Coach
Mary," for deftly maneuvering U.S. mail stagecoaches
and freight wagons over daunting
mountain trails.</p>

<p>Born into slavery around 1832 in Tennessee,
Mary Fields gave meaning to her freedom at
the earliest opportunity by migrating to Toledo,
Ohio, where she worked for the Ursuline
Convent. In 1884 Mother Amadeus of the
Ursuline Convent founded the St. Peter's
Catholic Mission School in Montana. Three
years later Mary Fields joined her there. For
the next ten years she provided protection for
the nuns and the school and drove a supply
wagon hauling essential freight and other
goods. Mary chopped wood, did rudimentary
carpentry, and whatever else was necessary to
ensure the smooth functioning of the nuns'
enterprise.</p>

<p>Mary Fields's temper was as legendary as her
ability to get hard jobs done. Indeed, one altercation
almost proved her undoing. Bishop
Filbus N. E. Berwanger fired Mary from her
position with the nuns following a shootout
with a cowpuncher that left her unharmed and
the cowpuncher slightly wounded and greatly
embarrassed. Mary never allowed social conventions
or expectations of feminine behavior
to circumscribe her. Rather, she carved a space
for herself that allowed her the freedom to
exploit both her penchant for hard work and
her desire to help others.</p>

<p>She settled in a town in Cascade County,
Montana, where she was the only black resident.
With some money from the nuns, she
opened a caf&#233; and became an avid supporter of
the local baseball team. The restaurant failed
because Mary fed too many who could not
pay, and besides, her cooking was unremarkable.
Mary took the closing of her restaurant in
stride, and for a brief time she subsisted by
doing laundry. She never made enough to be
considered rich, but she was reasonably content.
Her zest for life enthralled the local community.
When her laundry burned down the
townsfolk pitched in and helped her rebuild it.
The owner of the Cascade Hotel and the local
saloons all allowed Mary Fields ready access to
their facilities, privileges denied to women in
general.</p>

<p>In 1895 Mary secured a job delivering mail
for the U.S. postal services, and she continued
to do so into her seventies. Citizens marveled
at her fierce determination to deliver, on
schedule, letters and parcels without concern
for weather, the ruggedness of the mountain
trails, or the remoteness of the homes and
outposts that relied on dependable means
of communication in order to process land
claims. Without doubt, her work facilitated
central Montana's development. Mary Fields
died in 1914 of liver failure. Neighbors buried
her in the Hillside Cemetery in Cascade. A
simple wooden cross marks her grave.</p>


<closer>
<signed>Darlene Clark Hine<lb/>
Michigan State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Hine, Darlene Clark, and Kathleen Thompson. <title level="m">A Shining
Thread of Hope: A History of Black Women in America</title>.
New York: Broadway Books, 1998. Miller, Robert. T<title level="m">he
Story of Stagecoach Mary Fields</title>. Englewood Cliffs <hi rend="smallcaps">NJ</hi>: Silver
Burdett Press, 1995.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>