<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fol.036">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Proverbs and Proverbial Sayings</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Wolfgang Mieder</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2009</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fol.036</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2009</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2009 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Mieder, Wolfgang">Wolfgang Mieder</author>. <title level="a">"Proverbs and Proverbial Sayings."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">310-311</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-17</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">PROVERBS AND PROVERBIAL SAYINGS</head>

<p>The proverbial language of the Great Plains is
as varied as the landscape and culture of this
vast area of North America that stretches from
Canada to Mexico. With English being the
dominant language, traditional proverbs and
their wisdom, as well as proverbial sayings
with their colorful metaphors, were brought to
this continent by British settlers and abound
throughout the United States and Canada. In
fact, such standard texts as "The early bird
catches the worm," "First come, first served,"
and "Honesty is the best policy," as well as such
common proverbial sayings as "A feather in
your cap," "Hit the nail on the head," and "On
the tip of my tongue" are known and used in
oral and written communication in all parts of
the world where English is spoken. They belong
to the basic stock of proverbial utterances
in the English language, and they certainly appear
frequently in the verbal communication
of people living in the Great Plains.</p>

<p>Naturally, not all proverbial texts can be
traced back to British sources. Every region,
state, province, or country also develops its
own homegrown metaphors, which through
repeated use develop into new proverbs and
sayings. This is also true for the Great Plains,
of course, but it must be noted that it is usually
extremely difficult to ascertain the specific
regional origin and distribution of proverbial
texts. Fortunately, the American Dialect Society
undertook a major proverb collection
exercise between 1945 and 1985 that resulted in
250,000 references, which have now been registered
and annotated in <title level="m">A Dictionary of American Proverbs</title> (1992). This massive collection
identifies whether a particular text is known
generally throughout the United States and/
or Canada, and if it is not, locates the state or
province where it was collected and registered.
Impressive as this information might be, it is
nevertheless of limited value since only English-
language texts were collected. Foreign-language
proverbs and sayings from the various
immigrant groups and Native Americans
are lacking, and the same is true for many
texts from ethnic groups such as African
Americans, Mexican Americans, Volga Germans,
and Ukrainians in Canada.</p>

<p>For some states, small special proverb collections
have been assembled, notably for Colorado,
Kansas, Nebraska, and Texas. As expected,
they contain primarily standard English
proverbs, but there are at least some truly
regional texts among them that reflect the life
and mores of the inhabitants of the Plains,
with its ranches, prairies, wheat fields, horses,
and cattle. A few examples from Colorado are:
"Money greases the axle," "Keep your feet in
the stirrups," "To not have sense enough to
pound sand into a rat hole," "As cold as yesterday's
pancakes," "Only fools and tenderfeet
predict the weather in Colorado," "As big as a
horse and almost as smart," and "Lower than a
snake's belly in a wagon track." Among the
texts collected in Kansas are: "You can build a
house but you have to make a home," "Mud
thrown is ground lost," and "A dry well pumps
no water." From Nebraska stem such proverbs
and sayings as "Where there's room in the
heart, there's room in the house," "Don't holler
before you're hurt," and "As safe as a cow in
the stockyards." And the large state of Texas
might have originated such proverbial utterances
as "Don't waste your ammunition on a
dead duck," "To have about as much use for
(something) as a hog has for a sidesaddle," "So
lazy that grass grows under your feet," and
"Don't kick until you're spurred." Of course,
there are also such stereotypical sayings as
"Rich as a Texan and as full of hot air," "Cold
as a well-digger's lunch in Nebraska," and
"Hot as corn in Kansas in August." As can be
seen, such regional sayings often contain their
dose of humor and ridicule, and they can
quickly be changed by substituting one state's
name for another. Furthermore, it must be
kept in mind that the geographical borders of
states or provinces do not hinder proverbs
and sayings from spreading beyond them. It is
extremely difficult to pinpoint the precise
origin of any given saying, and it is better to
speak of proverbs that are current in a particular
region rather than claiming too quickly
that they are indigenous to it.</p>

<p>The situation is just as vexing when one
considers the proverbs and sayings that the
various immigrant groups brought to the
Great Plains. Books have been assembled of
Mexican and Spanish proverbs in current use
in Spanish in New Mexico, Texas, and southern
Colorado. Among this rich verbal lore are
proverbs (in English translation) like "Don't
look for three feet on a cat," "Whoever is
burnt by milk is even afraid of cottage cheese,"
and "Faces we see, hearts we don't know." The
Germans brought along proverbs like "The
morning hour has gold in its mouth," "Old
love does not rust," and "You can't make good
hay from poor grass," and the Swedish settlers
still say "Dust is always dust, however near
to heaven it may be blown," "A tall house is
empty under the rafters," and "No one thinks
of the snow that fell last year." Czech immigrants
employ proverbs like "Custom is rust
that mocks at every file," "The farmer's footprints
make the field fertile," and "Young people
and dogs take many useless steps in an
hour." Among Chinese railroad laborers were
such proverbs as "Even dust, if accumulated
enough, will form a mountain," "Through old
things we learn new things," and "Ten fingers
cannot be all the same size." Jewish traders
and merchants brought along such Yiddish
proverbs as "Dumplings in a dream are not
dumplings but a dream," "Words should be
weighed and not counted," and "One cannot
live by another's wits." And the Ukrainians in
Canada still use proverbs like "The plowman
has no time for mischief," "The farmer's
hands are muddy and black, but his loaves are
sweet and white," and "Another's fur coat does
not warm you as your own." While most of
these proverbs are cited in their original language,
some of them have been translated into
English over time and have gained a more
general currency. This is especially true for the
German proverb <hi rend="italic">Der Apfel f&#228;llt nicht weit vom
Stamm</hi> and the proverbial saying <hi rend="italic">Das Kind mit
dem Bade aussch&#252;tten</hi>, which have become
quite well known throughout North America
as "The apple does not fall far from the tree"
and "To throw the baby out with the bath
water."</p>

<p>There are also, of course, the proverbs of
African Americans who moved north from
Texas all the way to Canada trying to escape
prejudice and looking for jobs. Some of their
proverbs go back to slavery, such as "Every bell
you hear is not the dinner bell" (there was also
the "rising bell" in the morning that called the
slaves to work) and "The quicker death, the
quicker heaven." Other proverbial wisdom
from the black experience is shown in such
texts as "Scraping on the bottom of the meal
bin is mighty poor music," "A robin's song is
not pretty to the worm," and "When bugs give
a party they never ask the chickens."</p>

<p>But while there are at least some collections
of African American proverbs and proverbial
sayings from the Plains (primarily Texas), very
little is known about the proverbial language
of Native Americans. Anthropologists, folklorists,
and linguists have hitherto registered
only very few proverbs of Native Americans. It
is even argued that their tribal languages are
basically void of any proverbial language. This
is proven false by at least the few texts that
have been collected and annotated. From the
Crow Indians of Montana are such texts as
"When pine needles turn yellow" (a proverbial
phrase characterizing an impossibility),
"To be like the one who wanted to catch
the porcupine" (referring to a person who
persists in a hopeless enterprise), and "To be
like the turtle that was thrown into the water"
(applied to people feigning dislike for what
they really crave). The entire stock of Native
American proverbs collected thus far does not
even number 300, and much work remains to
be done to register this treasure trove of folk
wisdom among Native Americans of the Great
Plains and elsewhere.</p>

<p>The proverbial language of the Great Plains
is thus a "mixed bag," to use a folk metaphor.
While many texts can be traced back to Anglo-
American traditions, the various immigrant
groups, as well as Native Americans and African
Americans, have also added much linguistic,
cultural, and ethnic diversity to this basic
stock of proverbs and proverbial sayings. Field
research among the inhabitants of the Great
Plains would uncover many more hitherto
unrecorded proverbs and proverbial sayings
that bear witness to the rich and diverse cultural
traditions of the heartland of North
America.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Wolfgang Mieder<lb/>
University of Vermont</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Glazer, Mark, ed. <title level="m">A Dictionary of Mexican American Proverbs</title>.
Westport <hi rend="smallcaps">CT</hi>: Greenwood Press, 1987.</bibl> <bibl>Mieder, Wolfgang.
<title level="m">American Proverbs: A Study of Texts and Contexts</title>.
Bern Switzerland: Peter Lang, 1989.</bibl> <bibl>Mieder, Wolfgang,
Stewart A. Kingsbury, and Kelsie B. Harder, eds. <title level="m">A Dictionary of American Proverbs</title>. New York: Oxford University
Press, 1992.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>