<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.na.016">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Caddos</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>F. Todd Smith</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.na.016</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Smith, F. Todd">F. Todd Smith</author>. <title level="a">"Caddos."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">568-569</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-15</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">CADDOS</head>

<p>The Caddo Indians are a tribe whose traditional
historic homeland was located along
the borders of present Louisiana, Texas, Arkansas,
and Oklahoma. In the seventeenth
and eighteenth centuries the Caddos occupied
a strategic position between Spanish Texas
and French Louisiana. In the early nineteenth
century, however, Texans forced the tribe out
into the Great Plains. After wandering for
three decades, they finally settled in western
Oklahoma, where most of the Caddos still live
today.</p>

<p>The Caddos were the southernmost tribe of
the Caddoan language group, whose membership
stretched northward to include the Wichitas,
Pawnees, and Arikaras. About 2,000 years
ago the Caddo peoples settled down in small
horticultural villages between the Neches and
Arkansas Rivers. By about 1000 <hi rend="smallcaps">A.D.</hi>, the Caddos
had developed complex and socially ranked societies
with well-planned civic and ceremonial
centers. They conducted elaborate ceremonial
practices and mortuary rituals led by a religious
and political elite, and engaged in extensive
interregional trade.</p>

<p>In 1542 the Caddos were visited by the remnants
of Hernando de Soto's Spanish <hi rend="italic">entrada</hi>,
at this point led by Luis de Moscoso. Although
the Spaniards spent only a few weeks among
the Caddos, they, and later members of other
Spanish expeditions, left behind epidemic diseases,
which caused the Caddo population to
decline catastrophically. By the time Europeans
returned to Caddo country in the late
seventeenth century, the tribe had abandoned
their village sites in the Arkansas Valley. The
10,000 remaining Caddos established permanent
farming villages along the Red and the
Neches Rivers. The Red River Caddos consisted
of the four tribes of the Kadohadacho
Confederacy, as well as the Yatasis and the
Natchitoches. To the west, along the upper
reaches of the Neches River in East Texas, were
the nine tribes that made up the Hasinai Confederacy.
Each individual Caddo tribe was
led by a hereditary chief, or caddi, who presided
over a well-defined chain of command
that provided the tribe with strong, e.cient
government.</p>

<p>By 1730 both the French and the Spanish had
established themselves in the Caddos' territory.
The French maintained trading posts at
the Natchitoches, Yatasi, and Kadohadacho
villages, while the Spanish set up three Franciscan
missions in Hasinai country, as well as
establishing the capital of Texas at Los Adaes,
only a few miles west of the French post at
Natchitoches. Despite the Spanish presence, all
of the Caddo tribes obtained French weapons
and metal goods, which, together with the
adoption of the horse in the seventeenth century,
allowed them to better defend themselves
against enemies such as the Lipan Apaches to
the west and the Osages to the east. By the
mid–eighteenth century, however, the Caddos
had abandoned most of their traditional crafts
and were increasingly dependent upon European
metal goods. When Spain obtained Louisiana
from France in 1763, it continued to allow
French trade goods to flow to the Caddos and
their Wichita and Comanche allies in Texas.
When the United States acquired the territory
in 1803, the Caddos found themselves occupying
an undefined border between American
Louisiana and Spanish Texas. Seizing the moment,
the Kadohadacho caddi, Dehahuit, expertly
played the two rivals against one another
to gain even further munificence for all of the
Caddo tribes for whom he had become spokesman.
After 1821, however, the border between
Louisiana and Texas was settled, and both the
United States and the newly independent Mexico
neglected the Caddos. By the 1830s alcohol,
disease, and Osage pressure had caused the
Caddo numbers to dwindle to about 1,000, and
the original fifteen tribes had coalesced into
only three: the Hainais, Nadacos, and Kadohadachos.
In 1835 U.S. Indian agent Jehiel
Brooks forced the Kadohadachos to sign a
treaty by which the tribe agreed to move to East
Texas to live with the Hainais and Nadacos.</p>

<p>Unfortunately for the Caddos, Texas gained
its independence from Mexico the following
year and the Anglo-Americans who ruled the
republic after 1836 and the state after 1845 were
extremely hostile to the Indians of the region.
In 1838 Texan settlers drove all three Caddo
tribes from their homes in the forests of East
Texas out onto the plains of central Texas,
where they lived in various settlements for the
next sixteen years. In 1854 the Caddos&#8211;along
with Wichitas, Tonkawas, and Penateka Comanches&#8211;
settled on two Indian reservations
established by the U.S. government on the
Brazos River. On the Brazos Reservation, the
three Caddo tribes were led by Nadaco caddi
Iesh (or José María), an impressive leader who
convinced his fellow tribesmen to accept the
federal government's "civilization" program
and to assist the United States and the Texas
Rangers in their struggle with hostile Comanches.
Despite this accommodationist stance,
in 1859 Texas vigilantes forced the Brazos Reservation
tribes to move north of the Red River
into Indian Territory. The Caddos splintered
during the chaos of the Civil War, moving into
Kansas and Colorado. The federal government
finally brought them together on a reservation
in 1872. On the Wichita Reservation,
between the Washita and Canadian Rivers, the
three remaining Caddo groups united into
one tribe. Although the Caddos did everything
the federal government asked of them in
their new homes&#8211;farming, stock raising, and
submitting to education and Christianity&#8211;the
Wichita Reservation was dissolved in 1901 and
the 534 remaining Caddos went through the
allotment process as outlined by the Dawes Act
of 1887.</p>

<p>Despite the attempts of the federal government
to destroy it, the Caddo tribe remained
intact, and a measure of home rule was provided
through the terms of the Oklahoma Indian
Welfare Act of 1936, which was accepted
by the enrolled Caddo voters. The tribe ratified
a constitution that remained in effect until
1976, when it was replaced by a completely
new document. A measure of compensation
for their historical losses came in the 1970s
when the U.S. Court of Claims awarded the
Caddo tribe $383,475 for abuses in the 1835
treaty and $1,222,800 for inadequate payments
for allotments and surplus lands on the Wichita
Reservation. Today, the approximately
3,200 Caddos maintain a tribal complex on
thirty-seven acres of tribal-controlled land located
at Binger, in Caddo County, Oklahoma.</p>

<closer>
<signed>F. Todd Smith</signed>
University of North Texas</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Carter, Cecile. <title level="m">Caddo Indians: Where We Come From</title>. Norman:
University of Oklahoma Press, 1995.</bibl> <bibl>Smith, F. Todd.
<title level="m">The Caddo Indians: Tribes at the Convergence of Empires,
1542–1854</title>. College Station: Texas <hi rend="smallcaps">A&amp;M</hi> University Press,
1995.</bibl> <bibl>Smith, F. Todd. <title level="m">The Caddos, the Wichitas, and the
United States, 1846–1901</title>. College Station: Texas A&amp;M University
Press, 1996.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>