<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.gen.001">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Gender</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Deborah Fink</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.gen.001</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Fink, Deborah">Deborah Fink</author>. <title level="a">"Gender."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">319-323</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-18</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">GENDER</head>

<epigraph><p><hi rend="italic">Practically this whole study has been devoted
to the men. . . . The Great Plains in the early
period was strictly a man's country&#8211;more of
a man's country than any other portion of the
frontier. Men loved the Plains. . . . But what
of the women?</hi>&#8212;Walter Prescott Webb, <title level="m">The Great Plains</title> (1931: 505)</p></epigraph>

<p>"I was tricked!" cries the Nebraska woman. "I
read 504 pages of The Great Plains, the classic
work on my environment, trusting that I was
gaining insight into my own experience, only
to find on page 505 that practically the whole
thing applied specifically to men and not to
women. I want my time back!"</p>

<p>While there remain scholars inclined to dismiss
the gravity of the woman's protest, increasing
numbers have granted its validity.
They have made a variety of responses to the
neglect of women and the representation of
the male experience as normative in canonical
writings about the Great Plains. The diverse
answers to the complaint have formed a body
of scholarship dealing with the problem of the
inclusion or exclusion of women in texts
about the Plains and with the relationship between
women and men.</p>

<p>One response has been that women were
indeed included in the processes described
in <title level="m">The Great Plains</title>. Webb just didn't understand
that women were present throughout as
homesteaders, as fighters, as men's equals.
Some who would make this response ask that
the woman substitute inclusive language in
Webb's writing and try to understand that
"man" in English is used in a generic way to
include both men and women. Webb overlooked
women and we need only write them
in. The broad contours of the text stand; the
inclusion of women merely strengthens it and
makes it more comprehensive.</p>

<p>Others would find nearly as much fault
with this response as with the exclusion of
women in Webb's account. Their answer to
the woman's complaint would affirm it and
underscore the difference between men's and
women's lives in the Plains and hence the critical
necessity of a thoroughgoing consideration
of women. From this corner would
come the observation that Plains men and
women have been different in terms of legal
rights, family roles, economic resources, political
power, and cultural expectations. Surely
this would produce different experiences for
men and women in the Great Plains. What
needs to be done, they contend, is to study
cultural constructions of maleness and femaleness
and the effects they have had on the
institutions of the Plains. Did the Great Plains
shape a sense of maleness and femaleness distinct
from that of other regions? How did diverse
racial and ethnic groups in the Plains
define maleness and femaleness? From this
perspective, the canon must be radically revised
so that women are included.</p>

<p>In the past twenty-five years, probing into
various dimensions of gender has provided
intriguing openings for scholars. The study of
gender, of cultural constructions of maleness
and femaleness, has mainly grown out of the
study of women. This scholarship has also
contributed to an understanding of racial and
ethnic diversity in the Great Plains, although
much remains to be done in theorizing the
intersection of gender and race.</p>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Life of a Woman Homesteader</head>

<p>In the spring of 1876, eighteen-year-old Luna
Kellie packed up her five-month-old baby,
Willie, bade her husband, J. T., a sad farewell,
and left St. Louis on a train for central Nebraska,
where she would prepare for the family's
homesteading and wait for J. T. Luna's
father had already been lured to a Nebraska
homestead through railroad advertising, and
he would help to settle the couple. Since both
he and J. T. had been railroad workers, they
had the advantage of cheap passage to Grand
Island, which was the stopping-off point for
their homesteading. Luna spent the summer
with her father and siblings. In November, after
completing a final season of railroad work,
J. T. joined them.</p>

<p>February of 1877 found Luna, J. T., and Willie&#8211;
young, inexperienced, but at least together&#811;
striking out on their own Nebraska
homestead a few miles from that of Luna's
father. They had less than $400 with which to
outfit their 160-acre government grant. After
digging a shelter out of the side of a hill, they
dipped into their cash reserve to buy boards to
complete the house, since they could get no
sod at that time of year. They also bought a
new stove and a few food staples. To begin
farming they purchased fifteen steers, a milk
cow, and a plow. J. T. traded his watch for an
old wagon. With these basics, they began farm
life.</p>

<p>Their first reversal of fortune came when a
sudden blizzard struck in the night just as they
had begun to savor the Nebraska spring and to
think about putting their cattle out on the
buffalo grass. Hearing the wind, J. T. bolted up
in fear of losing the cattle. He and Luna ran
out into the night and rounded up all but one
of the cattle and drove them into their tiny
house. Again and again they chased the last
one, but each time they got him closer to the
house he ran in the opposite direction. Finally,
cold and exhausted, they let him go and returned
to bed, where J. T., Luna, and Willie
warmed themselves as the cattle pressed in on
them. Although J. T. made repeated trips into
the blizzard to get the wild steer, he finally
gave it up. The three Kellies spent the next day
huddled in bed and ate boiled oatmeal with
no milk while the cattle occupied most of the
room in the house.</p>

<p>Through the summer of 1877 the Kellies
worked themselves nearly to death. They had
no money at all. A neighbor saved them from
starvation by giving J. T. a sack of flour as early
pay for harvest work. Luna had a second baby
that year. This baby and the one born the following
year died early, undoubtedly because
overwork and lack of food had dried Luna's
milk. Luna survived these deaths, she survived
her terror of the rattlesnakes that lurked in the
fields around the house, and she survived her
despondency at being unable to send her
grandmother a birthday greeting because she
did not have three cents to buy a stamp. Luna
and J. T. pressed on, they had more babies in
the following years, and their crops came in as
they established themselves and learned farming
skills. By the 1880s their farm was producing
abundantly and their family was steadily
increasing in number.</p>

<p>However, defeat came when their farming
operation failed and they lost their homestead,
not through acts of God or their own failings,
but because they could not turn a profit on
their successful production. And here the railroad
was to blame. Why? It seemed to be the
price gouging inflicted by the railroad. The
railroad made money by bringing settlers to
Nebraska, by shipping farming tools and supplies
west, and by carrying grain to market.
Railroad rates were not standardized, and the
companies tended to charge higher rates per
mile for short, local runs that served small
communities than for long runs. Where competition
existed, typically in cities, rates were
lower than in rural areas. While the railroads
extracted high fares from farmers, they offered
free passes to politicians and controlled local
and state politics through their patronage. The
railroad, it seemed, fattened itself on the Kellies'
labor, returning only misery to them. Of
the railroad Luna wrote, "[T]he minute you
crossed the Missouri River your fate both soul
and body was in their hands. . . . [T]hey robbed
us of all we produced."</p>

<p>Losing the homestead and moving to another
farm to begin again, Luna's rage exploded
into political action as she joined the
Farmers Alliance. She became secretary of the
Nebraska Farmers Alliance, and from her
farm home she published an Alliance paper
that attacked the railroads and the middlemen
that profited from the exploitation of farmers.
In a rousing speech delivered to the Nebraska
Farmers Alliance in 1894, she declared, "[T]he
people now know that they have the constitutional
right to take the railroads under right of
eminent domain and run them at cost in the
interest of <hi rend="italic">all the people</hi>." Later, her hopes for
the Alliance and for the populist movement,
like her earlier hope of farming prosperity,
died a painful death, a disillusion readers can
follow through her experience of trying to
hold the principles of the farm movement
above the egos of its Nebraska leadership,
which was male.</p>

<p>Luna's loss of her two babies, the poverty
that constricted her spirit, her sadness at her
beloved J. T.'s repeated failures, the vulnerability
to exploitation by external forces, and her
resilience must be recognized as a piece of the
Plains experience. Contrary to Webb, the
Plains was a woman's country as well as a
man's country. Without women such as Luna
Kellie, European Americans could not have
claimed the Plains.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Putting Women into the Plains Picture</head>

<p>Publication of the stories of Luna Kellie and
other Plains women grew out of the 1970s explosion
of studies on women that accompanied the revitalization of the feminist movement.
Scholars in many disciplines began
to notice that women were absent, or only
peripherally present, in standard works by
such accepted authorities as Webb. The first
work on Plains women was compensatory,
much of it having to do with European
American women in farming. Two articles by
Mary W. M. Hargreaves in <title level="j">Agricultural History</title>,
"Homesteading and Homemaking on
the Plains: A Review" (1973) and "Women in
the Agricultural Settlement of the Northern
Plains" (1976), set the path for further research.
These articles placed women in the
history of Plains farming, underscored the
significance of women's contribution to European
American settlement, and pointed to the
particular hardships that Plains life imposed
on women.</p>

<p>A further step in this compensatory scholarship
was more systematic and focused on
the exhuming of texts and records of Plains
women. Most of the political, military, and
commercial records available from the early
European American settlement of the Plains
are male-centered. Focusing on women meant
bringing forward a different set of sources:
diaries, letters, church and club records, wills,
deeds, court records, local newspapers, advertisements
and personal columns in magazines
and journals, and oral histories.</p>

<p>Scholars seeking to put women into accounts
of the Plains have found them almost
everywhere they have looked. For example,
women figured in the fur trade, which writers
have typically represented in terms of rugged
men and growth of capital. Women of the Native
Plains nations did some trapping, and
they processed skins for trade. In <title level="m">Many Tender Ties: Women in Fur-Trade Society, 1670–1870</title>,
Sylvia Van Kirk (1980) describes early European
traders' practice of taking Native wives,
who stabilized ties with Native nations, served
as guides and interpreters, provided moccasins
and snowshoes, which eased travel on
the Northern Plains, supplied pemmican and
other local foods, and helped make canoes.
Women, as well as men, shaped the dynamics
of the fur trade.</p>

<p>In the United States the Homestead Act of
1862 allowed single women as well as men to
homestead. Studies of women homesteaders
include <title level="m">Bachelor Bess: The Homesteading Letters of Elizabeth Corey, 1909–1919</title> (1990), edited
by Philip L. Gerber, <title level="m">The Land of the Burnt Thigh</title> by Edith Eudora Kohl (1938), and Elaine
Lindgren's article "Ethnic Women Homesteading
on the Plains of North Dakota" (1989).
In Canada, single or married women were not
allowed to homestead (although widows and
divorced or unwed mothers could). Still,
women's participation was central to most
family farming operations. Single Canadian
women might purchase and operate farms. In
<title level="m">Wheat and Women</title> (1914), Georgina Binnie-
Clark, an Englishwoman with enough resources
to buy a Canadian farm and hire most
of the labor, wrote about her adventures and
gave advice on the economics of running
a farm in the years immediately preceding
World War I. In addition to their economic
contributions, Plains women were active in
political struggles&#8211;including populist, suffrage,
and temperance movements&#8211;in both
Canada and the United States.</p>

<p>Binnie-Clark wrote that "they realized that
what men had done for themselves in agricultural
pursuits on the prairie, women could
also do for themselves." Like men, women
were daring and adventurous; they worked
hard to claim the land; they could own property
and engage in commerce; and they were
as capable of effective political participation as
men. Adding women has filled out the picture
of the Plains.</p>

<p>But did men and women inhabit different
parts of that picture? Following the lead of
historian Joan Kelly, who concluded that the
existing periodization of European history was
not valid from the perspective of women,
Plains researchers asked if the accepted historical
movements and markers were what in reality
moved and marked women's lives. Do we
really know that homesteading or populism
had the same appeal for the majority of women
as for men? What was it that drove women?
Elinore Pruitt Stewart's <title level="m">Letters of a Woman Homesteader</title> (1914) reveals the importance she
placed on human interaction; she shows little
concern for politics or empire building. Yet the
early-twentieth-century writings of Albertan
Nellie McClung, collected in <title level="m">Our Nell</title> (1979),
indicate that her personal leanings placed her
in the woman-centered political struggles of
suffrage, temperance, and women's economic
rights. Perhaps the gap between the personal
and the political was not as wide for women as
for men.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">From Women to Gender</head>

<p>Are women persons? In 1927, eleven years after
western Canadian women had won full suffrage
rights, the Supreme Court of Canada
was called upon to decide the issue of women's
personhood. The question itself is remarkable;
the answer, "no," is astonishing. The issue
had arisen through the activism of Nellie
McClung and other women in the Prairie
Provinces who had refused to stay on their
side of the line drawn between the world of
men and that of women.</p>

<p>The case began in 1916 when Alice Jamieson
of Calgary and Emily Murphy of Edmonton
were appointed police magistrates, the first
women in the British Empire to receive such
appointments. On Murphy's first day in court
a defense lawyer challenged her authority on
the grounds that by law she was not a person.
Although the challenge was dismissed, the
point was well taken. Under British common
law, women were persons in "matters of pains
and penalties" but not in "matters of rights
and privileges."</p>

<p>The issue lay dormant for several years,
then resurfaced in the 1920s when a group of
Alberta women wanted the law set right. Their
strategy was to advocate a Senate appointment
for Murphy. Since the law stipulated that only
a "fit and qualified person" was eligible for
such an appointment, the question of whether
a woman was a person would have to be settled.
Any five citizens could request an interpretation.
Murphy, McClung, suffrage leader
Louise McKinney, legal scholar Henrietta
Muir Edwards, and provincial cabinet minister
Irene Parlby joined to request a ruling
on whether or not women were persons. Although
four out of five Supreme Court justices
joined in the opinion that they were not
persons, the women were accustomed to opposition
and they forged ahead by appealing
to the Privy Council in London, which at that
time had the authority to override Canadian
decisions.</p>

<p>In 1929 the women prevailed in the Privy
Council and became persons under British
common law and hence under Canadian law.
It had been a long road to arrive at what
would seem to be square one. From the vantage
of the twenty-first century, the question
seems patently ridiculous, as it did to the five
Alberta women at the time. Many men saw it
with different eyes. The women were moving
toward gender equality before the law. The
question of men's and women's legal equality
went beyond the rearrangement of women's
affairs and into a redefinition of what it meant
to be a man as well. If being a person was not
coterminous with being a man, then the legal
definition of "man" was also being revised. It
was a question of gender delineation, and this
mattered to both men and women at a deeply
personal level.</p>

<p>Two principles are tied up in the recent
scholarship using the term "gender." First is
the assumption that definitions of maleness
and femaleness are culturally defined rather
than biologically given. Without denying that
men and women are in some ways different,
these studies point to the similarities between
men and women, which are considerable, and
view the construction of gender as a suppression
of natural similarities rather than an
elaboration of natural differences. Both men
and women cry, but European American constructions
of gender suppressed the crying of
men and accentuated that of women, thereby
creating a cultural difference where no biological
difference existed. Canadian women who
sought to join men in their identities as persons
were asking that the accepted understanding
of "person" be recognized as a cultural
artifact and therefore subject to reasoned
modification. Second, as can be inferred in
the Canadian judges' opposition to women
being persons, gender has to do with both
maleness and femaleness and with the constructions
arising out of the relations between
maleness and femaleness.</p>

<p>While often such questions emerge in esoteric
points that seem far removed from the
reality of most people's lives, they are embedded
in basic social and economic structures.
Farming in European American culture is
generally associated with males: Asked to
draw a picture of a farmer, most European
Americans will automatically draw a man.
The potential for being a farmer helps to
shape male identity for European Americans,
and the correlate dissociation of women with
farming shapes female identity. This dual classification
gives rise to the particular configuration
of the family farm. We appreciate the
cultural contingency of this arrangement by
observing that, in Native American nations
that cultivated corn, women had the major
farming roles. Asked to draw a picture of a
farmer, a Native American would have drawn
a woman. What it meant to be a man or
woman in these societies was not the same as
what it meant to European Americans, and
this difference was further reflected in religion,
art, and ethical norms.</p>

<p>Drawing on Henry Nash Smith's <title level="m">Virgin Land: The American West as Symbol and Myth</title>
(1950), Annette Kolodny has underlined the
extent to which the westward movement
across North America was gendered. In <title level="m">The Lay of the Land: Metaphor as Experience and History in American Life and Letters</title> (1975) and
<title level="m">The Land Before Her: Fantasy and Experience of the American Frontiers, 1630–1860</title> (1984),
Kolodny explores gender in myths and symbols
of land. At first, men saw the land as maternal
and nurturing; later the dominant metaphor
changed from the land as Mother to
the land as Mistress, a place to be explored
and conquered for its material treasures. For
women, the dominant metaphor of the new
land was the garden, a social setting to be cultivated
and adapted for human needs. Kolodny's
analysis resonates through writing about the
Plains. Various Plains writers, among them
Meridel LeSueur, have used the metaphor of
the plowed land as the flesh of a woman and
the conquering of this virgin land as a triumph
of masculinity.</p>

<p>A study of a Kansas farming county extended
the significance of gender beyond
symbol and metaphor and into the economic
and political shaping of Plains life. In "Structure
of Agriculture and Women's Culture in
the Great Plains" (1988), Cornelia Butler Flora
and Jan L. Flora contrasted farming patterns
in three ethnic groups: German, Volga German,
and American-born (or Yankees). These
ethnic groups formed different complexes of
gender relations, which affected fertility, labor,
and resource allocation. The willingness
of the two foreign-born groups to allow their
daughters to take domestic service work, thus
augmenting farm income, and the unwillingness
of the American-born families to do
so greatly affected success rates. The Volga
Germans had the most staying power on the
land, followed by the Germans, with the
American-born a distant third. Thus, the
evolving ethnic character of the farming community
came to derive more from German
and Volga German traits than from those of
the Yankee farmers. Such studies of gender
reveal complexities in the agricultural economy
that were not apparent when only men's
production was considered.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Gender and Interregional Differences</head>

<p>Gender and Interregional Differences
Not only did cultural configurations of gender
modify the cultural landscape of the Plains,
but geographic and economic conditions associated
with the Great Plains in turn reconfigured
gender. For the last 200 years the Great
Plains has seen constant migration and readjustment,
and studies of gender reflect this
continuing change as well as significant continuities
with external traditions. People entered
the Great Plains from different directions
and with different cultural baggage,
including gender. In what ways did the Plains
rearrange this baggage and in what ways did
the constructions that people brought rearrange
the cultures of the Great Plains? Some
scholars, including Mary Neth in <title level="m">Preserving the Family Farm: Women, Community and the Foundations of Agribusiness in the Midwest, 1900-1940</title> (1995) and Katherine Jellison in <title level="m">Entitled to Power: Farm Women and Technology, 1913-1963</title> (1993), minimize the specificity of
the Plains experience of gender and emphasize
instead the continuities between European
American patterns in the Midwest and
Great Plains. By contrast, Dorothy Schwieder
and Deborah Fink in their article "Plains
Women: Rural Life in the 1930s" (1988) and
<title level="m">Fink in Agrarian Women: Wives and Mothers in Rural Nebraska, 1880-1940</title> (1992) argue that
gender patterns were reworked in the Great
Plains. Rather than emphasizing the continuity
arising from shared cultural roots and
common federal policy, Schwieder and Fink
point to the sparse population and the greater
sacrifices required of Plains women and relate
this to a reconfiguration of gender. Glenda
Riley's <title level="m">The Female Frontier: A Comparative View of Women on the Prairie and the Plains</title>
(1988) draws out contrasts but considers that
in fundamental ways the tasks facing the
women in the Midwest and Great Plains were
similar. Further comparative work will deepen
the understanding of whether and to what
extent the Plains experience altered the gender
identities of its people.</p>

<p>If the Plains environment did have an effect
on gender relations, what was that effect?
Scholars disagree. On one hand is the view
that for European American settlers the move
into the open spaces removed restricting conventions
and social controls and opened the
way for more egalitarian relationships between
men and women. Writing of British
women in <title level="m">A Flannel Shirt and Liberty: British Emigrant Gentlewomen in the Canadian West, 1880-1914</title> (1982), Susan Jackel found the birth
of a feminist consciousness and a collective
identity among British women migrants to
the Prairies of Canada. Katherine Harris, in
"Sex Roles and Work Patterns among Homesteading
Families in Northeastern Colorado,
1873-1920" (1984), also presents a case for
greater egalitarianism: with homesteading
came a muting of gender-role distinctions,
shared decision making between husbands
and wives, and the accrual of greater power to
women because of their acknowledged economic
centrality.</p>

<p>In various articles, including "Every Husband's
Right: Sex Roles in Mari Sandoz's <title level="m">Old Jules</title>" (1983), Melody Graulich makes a contrary
argument: with the loosening of social
restraints in the West, women were more vulnerable
to men's brutality. <title level="m">Old Jules</title> (1935), the
story of Sandoz's parents' homesteading and
marriage in western Nebraska, may be read as
a study in gender relations, and not a happy
one. Fink's <title level="m">Agrarian Women</title> represents another
entry in the case against the salutary
effects of the Plains for male-female relations.
The controversy is complicated by the methodological
difficulties in assessing the intimacy
of marriages. No one denies that there
were good marriages as well as oppressive
ones in the Plains, just as there have been in
every social setting. The question remains of
the effects of the Plains environment on them,
and it is a messy and possibly imprudent question.
Notwithstanding the enormous problems,
including ethical ones, the subject has
been broached and has not been laid to rest.</p>

<p><title level="m">A Harvest Yet to Reap</title> (1976), a collection of
early-twentieth-century writings by Canadian
Prairie women, describes shifts in the cultural
definitions of women as migrants crossed into
the Great Plains. Life in the Great Plains at the
time of settlement placed its inhabitants under
specific constraints. Drawing on studies of
Canadian farming and on Marxist theory,
Max Hedley's 1981 article "Relations of Production
of the 'Family Farm'" theorizes that,
through relations of production, the domination
of capital in Canadian farming penetrated
and marked internal family relations,
including those between husbands and wives.
As Hedley points out, the idea of the family
farm implied collective ownership; the vocabulary
of kinship evoked obligations to the
farm operation that in an ideal kinship setting
would have been reciprocal. However, the demands
of a capitalist economic system dictated
the subordination of kinship obligations
to the imperatives of the cash economy. What
a woman wanted and deserved from a marriage
partnership became subordinate to the
banker's demands on a farmer. <title level="m">"Other" Voices: Historical Essays on Saskatchewan Women</title>, edited
by David De Brou and Aileen Moffatt
(1995), complicates this analysis by pointing
out the ethnic diversity present in Saskatchewan
alone, and hence the diversity of gender
constructions arising from migration to the
Plains.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Plains Towns</head>

<p>The Great Plains south of the forty-ninth parallel
is as rural as any region of the United
States, and except for the major cities of Calgary,
Edmonton, and Winnipeg the Prairie
Provinces of Canada are also largely rural. The
rural ethos has colored all of the institutions
in the region. But cities, with their colleges,
universities, museums, libraries, orchestras,
and opera houses, have also been integral to
Plains culture. Women have done much of the
building of these institutions and have found
employment and influence through them.
These institutions have also been points of articulation
with the world beyond the Plains.
For some women, such as Willa Cather, they
have provided routes of departure. Women in
the small towns dotted across the map were
instrumental in bringing and maintaining
churches, which also served as connections to
European and European American cultures to
the east and were transmitters of gender
norms as well. June O. Underwood's article
"Civilizing Kansas: Women's Organizations,
1880–1920" (1984/85) surveys the ways in
which Kansas women worked for the reforms
associated with the Progressive Era. These included
establishing homes for indigent and
helpless persons; lobbying for better conditions
in county homes and other institutions;
working for a broad range of health
concerns, including clean water, better nutrition,
and more accessible medical care;
promoting municipal improvements such as
parks, restrooms, and sidewalks; fighting for
prohibition; and working for child labor and
truancy laws.</p>

<p>Women's suffrage was a burning issue
throughout the United States and Canada in
the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries.
The Plains protest movements of the
time advocated women's suffrage, although
the depth of commitment has been questioned.
From one point of view the Great
Plains, removed from the entrenched prejudices
of the East, represented a fertile field for
the establishment of equal voting rights. As a
territory in 1869 Wyoming became the first
government to grant women equal voting
rights, and it became a state in 1890 with this
voting legislation intact. In Canada, women
voted first in the Prairie Provinces and British
Columbia. Whether this can be attributed to
frontier democracy, however, has been questioned.
Julie Roy Jeffrey, in <title level="m">Frontier Women: The Trans-Mississippi West, 1840-1880</title> (1979),
wrote that when men of the western territories
granted women the vote their motivations
involved more conservative expediency than
altruistic commitment to democracy. In Wyoming,
legislators concerned about the sparse
and transient population believed that granting
the vote to women would attract attention
to the territory and draw women to establish
domesticity and stability on the frontier. The
fragility of women's rights in Wyoming was
evident in 1870 when women lost their right to
serve on juries. Women serving on a grand
jury had upset male politicians by indicting
Laramie saloons for doing business on Sunday;
the men shut the women down instead of
the saloons. It was 1950 before women regained
the right to serve on Wyoming juries.
Whatever men's motivations for cultivating
the appearance of women's equal rights, the
gain with suffrage was real, and it happened
first in the Great Plains.</p>

<p>In contrast to the image of the Plains town
as a setting for the noble causes for which
women worked, there has been no shortage of
criticism of the Plains town for its crushing of
female spirits. Willa Cather's fiction, including
<title level="m">My Ántonia</title> (1918) and <title level="m">A Lost Lady</title> (1923),
may be read as a gender critique of Plains
towns, as may the life of Cather herself in her
Nebraska years, which is analyzed in <title level="m">Willa Cather: The Emerging Voice</title> by Sharon O'Brien
(1987). Sinclair Lewis's novel <title level="m">Main Street</title>
(1920) stands as a classic depiction of suffocating
conformity imposed on women by smalltown
society. Although Gopher Prairie, the
setting of Main Street, is in Minnesota, Lewis
wrote that Gopher Prairie was every small
town west of the Mississippi. While the subject
matter of these disquieting works is unmistakably
gendered, they do not picture men
as evil agents and women as victims; often it is
women rather than men who appear as the
enforcers of the deadly social norms.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Race and Ethnicity</head>

<p>Just as gender study has tended to focus on
women, considerations of race in the Plains
have tended to be about Native Americans,
African Americans, and Hispanic Americans
rather than European Americans. Moreover,
like the studies of European Americans, the
studies of these groups have tended to be
about men. Anthropologist Robert Lowie's Indians
of the <title level="m">Great Plains</title> (1954), for example,
has indexed entries for women in a work otherwise
given over to men. Similarly, the Pulitzer
Prize–winning novel of Kiowa writer N.
Scott Momaday, <title level="m">House Made of Dawn</title> (1966),
is unself-consciously male centered.</p>

<p>Researchers have disrupted the conventions
of discourse about race, declaring that race
exists as a cultural construct rather than as
biological fact. While race remains a political
and analytical category, its essential significance
is as a particular form of ethnicity.
Moreover, scholars have found gender and racial
constructions to be intimately related.
The proclaimed goal of making the Plains safe
for European American women justified the
isolation of Plains Indians as well as the restrictions
on activities of European American
women. Yet, as pointed out by Joan Jensen in
her publication of Mary Jemison's captivity
account (1981) and Glenda Riley in her book
<title level="m">Women and Indians on the Frontier, 1825–1915</title>
(1984), European American women's actual
experiences of contact with Indians seldom
matched what they had been led to expect.
Riley believed that women were more likely
than men to revise their views of Indians
based on what happened to them personally
after they reached the Plains. On the other
hand, Van Kirk's study of the Canadian fur
trade indicates that in this setting British
women were more prejudiced against persons
of the original nations than were British men.</p>

<p>While not specifically addressing the Plains,
Joan Jensen has pointed to the significance of
women's farming as a base of economic power
in nations of the southwestern and northeastern
United States. Balancing the image of
the male warrior and buffalo hunter that has
dominated popular representations of Native
Americans, Jensen has brought out the economic
importance of women as food producers
and processors. Contrary to early European
American scholarship, which viewed
the considerable labor inputs of Native American
women as evidence of their debased social
position, anthropologists such as Alice
Fletcher, Francis La Flesche, and Gene Weltfish,
who studied Plains nations, interpreted
women's labor as a sign of their economic and
social centrality. <title level="m">The Hidden Half</title>, edited by
Patricia Albers and Beatrice Medicine (1983),
shows Plains Indian women from diverse societies
to have been major food providers,
controllers of assets, decision makers, and
central to the political and spiritual functioning
of their societies. Although Plains nations
were culturally diverse, women usually did
most of the perennial labor&#8211;including building
lodges and tipis, farming, processing
hides, and rearing young children.</p>

<p>Native American women writers have provided
intimate studies of the world of Plains
men and women from the original nations.
Ella Cara Deloria's novel <title level="m">Waterlily</title>, written
in the 1940s and published in 1988, offers a
Lakota woman's understanding of women's life
among her people in the 1840s and 1850s. <title level="m">Waterlily</title>
depicts a past in which women occupied
a valued and powerful place, notwithstanding
the male dominance of the warrior society.
Mary Crow Dog's <title level="m">Lakota Woman</title> (1991), which
is about recent political struggles, represents
another powerful study of gender from the
perspective of a Plains woman. The fiction of
Louise Erdrich explores twentieth-century adjustments
made by Chippewa peoples who had
been displaced to the Plains from their homes
in the Eastern Woodlands.</p>

<p>In addition to the revisions and scholarship
critiquing the conventional wisdom about the
lives of Native American women of the Great
Plains, recent scholarship has dislodged the
authority of early observers who pictured the
Plains Indian man as a lazy dandy. As David J.
Wishart (1995) finds, these early observers
failed to understand that men's work took
place away from the village. Men's activities
were raiding, hunting, defending, trading,
and diplomacy. The skewed demographics
observed in the nineteenth century, when in
many Plains tribes more than two-thirds of
the adults were women, are testimony to the
physical risk inherent in men's roles. Further,
Wishart believes that European American observers
also misinterpreted polygyny. Rather
than a debasement of women, it was a practical
response to the relative shortage of men.</p>

<p>Modern Plains Indians recount a history in
which women commanded a great deal of respect;
they attribute degradation of Native
American women to the postcontact introduction
of alcohol and loss of the traditional
economic and spiritual nexus. One of the
most unpardonable sins of a modern Lakota is
to fail to show respect to a senior Lakota
woman, thereby acceding to European American
norms rather than Lakota order.</p>

<p>Yet the widespread belief in a kinder, more
respectful precontact past may reflect modern
cultural politics as well as Indian history. Notwithstanding
the tendency to attribute gender
violence to European influence, reliable historical
accounts reveal that Plains Indian
women faced violence and death when they
violated sexual or familial norms. For both
men and women, secure status in the traditional
societies appears to have rested on the
degree to which they fulfilled moral expectations
associated with their respective genders.</p>

<p>Although African American men and women
settled in the Great Plains, many of the
details of their lives are unexplored. Glenda
Riley, who made a brave attempt to include
accounts of African Americans in <title level="m">The Female Frontier</title>, came up with little information. The
largest concentration of black settlers was in
Kansas, but small numbers of African Americans
settled in other areas of the Plains as well.
Race mattered in the Plains and shaped a distinct
Plains experience for these settlers as
compared to European Americans; nevertheless,
African Americans were faced with problems
of survival similar to those confronting
European Americans. Perhaps the experience
of gender for black persons in the Plains was
similar to that of European Americans, although
available anecdotes provide insufficient basis for firm conclusions.</p>

<p>Similarly on the list of gender studies that
have not yet emerged are the early experiences
of Hispanic Americans and Asian Americans
in the Plains. With so much intriguing work
done on gender in these populations in other
locations, it is hard to believe that there is
nothing to be uncovered that would reveal
what the Plains has meant for them both historically
and in the present.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Gender and Masculinity</head>

<p>Gender doesn't mean women. A burgeoning
body of scholarship has appeared to address
the significance of gender in the understanding
of male activities as well. Unfortunately,
little of this has been about the Plains, although
there have been some beginnings.
Kolodny's <title level="m">Lay of the Land</title> ferrets out male imagery
in the conquest of western lands. Elizabeth
Atwood Lawrence's <title level="m">Rodeo: An Anthropologist Looks at the Wild and the Tame</title> (1982)
opens the subject of the significance of maleness
for cowboys, and Garrison Keillor's radio
program, "Prairie Home Companion," includes
an intriguing sequence of gender satire
on the lives of the cowboys, which are forever
being complicated by the addition of women
and social responsibility. Much remains to be
explored. The significance of the maleness of
the soldier/warrior in European American
and Native American cultures must have
reached into other social domains and colored
gender relations more generally for both.
These studies are sorely needed before we can
reach a balanced understanding of the significance
of gender in the Plains.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Conclusion</head>

<p>Few questions of gender in the Great Plains
have been put to rest. They are being revisited
in ongoing investigations, and debates are
wide-ranging. As with much other scholarship
on gender, the Plains research is multidisciplinary.
In 1984 a conference in Las Cruces,
New Mexico, entitled "Rural Women in Historical
Perspective," provided a forum for academics
and activists engaged in work on rural
women. It drew heavily from the discipline of
history, but the scope was broad enough to
include anthropologists, sociologists, literary
analysts, economists, extension personnel,
rural activists, and farm women. The continuing
development and evolution of the conference
has provided a network for theorists,
many of them isolated, addressing questions
of gender in the Great Plains. Now, unlike in
Webb's day, anyone who writes accounts of
the Great Plains and ignores women can expect
to get called on it. Beyond that, there is
little consensus.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">ASIAN AMERICANS</hi>: 
<ref n="egp.asam.012">Female Employment Act</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">EDUCATION</hi>: 
<ref n="egp.edu.040">Women in Higher Education</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">FOLKWAYS</hi>: 
<ref n="egp.fol.037">Quilting</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">LITERARY
TRADITIONS</hi>: <ref n="egp.lt.009">Cather, Willa</ref>; <ref n="egp.lt.018">Erdrich, Louise</ref>;
<ref n="egp.lt.078">Webb, Walter Prescott</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">PROTEST AND DISSENT</hi>:
<ref n="egp.pd.051">Temperance Movement</ref>.</p>
</div2>

<closer>
<signed>Deborah Fink<lb/>
Ames, Iowa</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Albers, Patricia, and Beatrice Medicine, eds. <title level="m">The Hidden Half: Studies of Plains Indian Women</title>. Washington <hi rend="smallcaps">DC</hi>:
University Press of America, 1983.</bibl> <bibl>Binnie-Clark, Georgina.
<title level="m">Wheat and Women</title>. Toronto: University of Toronto Press,
1979.</bibl> <bibl>Corey, Elizabeth. <title level="m">Bachelor Bess: The Homesteading Letters of Elizabeth Corey, 1909-1919</title>, edited by Philip L. Gerber.
Iowa City: University of Iowa Press, 1990.</bibl> <bibl>De Brou, David,
and Aileen Moffatt, eds. <title level="m">"Other" Voices: Historical Essays on Saskatchewan Women</title>. Regina: University of Regina, Canadian
Plains Research Center, 1995.</bibl> <bibl>Fink, Deborah. <title level="m">Agrarian Women: Wives and Mothers in Rural Nebraska, 1880-1940</title>.
Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1992.</bibl>
<bibl>Flora, Cornelia Butler, and Jan L. Flora. "Structure of Agriculture
and Women's Culture in the Great Plains." <title level="j">Great Plains Quarterly</title> 8 (1988): 195-205.</bibl> <bibl>Graulich, Melody.
"Every Husband's Right: Sex Roles in Mari Sandoz's Old
Jules." <title level="j">Western American Literature</title> 18 (1983): 3-20.</bibl> <bibl>Hallett,
Mary, and Marilyn Davis. <title level="m">Firing the Heather: The Life and Times of Nellie McClung</title>. Saskatoon: Fifth House, 1993.</bibl>
<bibl>Hargreaves, Mary W. M. "Homesteading and Homemaking
on the Plains: A Review." <title level="j">Agricultural History</title> 47 (1973):
156-63.</bibl> <bibl>Hargreaves, Mary W. M. "Women in the Agricultural
Settlement of the Northern Plains." <title level="j">Agricultural History</title>
50 (1976): 179-89.</bibl> <bibl>Harris, Katherine. "Sex Roles and
Work Patterns among Homesteading Families in Northeastern
Colorado, 1873-1920." <title level="j">Frontiers</title> 7 (1984): 43-49.</bibl>
<bibl>Jackel, Susan. <title level="m">A Flannel Shirt and Liberty: British Emigrant Gentlewomen in the Canadian West, 1880-1914</title>. Vancouver:
University of British Columbia Press, 1982.</bibl> <bibl>Jeffrey, Julie
Roy. <title level="m">Frontier Women: The Trans-Mississippi West, 1840</title>.
1880. New York: Hill and Wang, 1979.</bibl> <bibl>Jellison, Katherine.
<title level="m">Entitled to Power: Farm Women and Technology, 1913-1963</title>.
Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1993.</bibl>
<bibl>Jensen, Joan M. <title level="m">With These Hands: Women Working on the Land</title>. Old Westbury <hi rend="smallcaps">NY</hi>: Feminist Press, 1981.</bibl> <bibl>Kellie, Luna.
<title level="m">A Prairie Populist: The Memoirs of Luna Kellie</title>, edited by
Jane Taylor Nelsen. Iowa City: University of Iowa Press,
1992.</bibl> <bibl>Kohl, Edith Eudora. <title level="m">The Land of the Burnt Thigh</title>. St.
Paul: Minnesota Historical Society Press, 1986.</bibl> <bibl>Kohl, Seena
B. <title level="m">Working Together: Women and Family in Southwestern Saskatchewan</title>. Toronto: Holt, Rinehart and Winston of
Canada, 1976.</bibl> <bibl>Kolodny, Annette. <title level="m">The Land before Her: Fantasy and Experience of the American Frontiers, 1630-1860</title>.
Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1984.</bibl>
<bibl>Kolodny, Annette. <title level="m">The Lay of the Land: Metaphor as Experience and History in American Life and Letters</title>. Chapel Hill:
University of North Carolina Press, 1975.</bibl> <bibl>Lawrence, Elizabeth
Atwood. <title level="m">Rodeo: An Anthropologist Looks at the Wild and the Tame</title>. Knoxville: University of Tennessee Press,
1982.</bibl> <bibl>Lindgren, H. Elaine. "Ethnic Women Homesteading
on the Plains of North Dakota." <title level="j">Great Plains Quarterly</title> 9
(1989): 157-73.</bibl> <bibl>Neth, Mary. <title level="m">Preserving the Family Farm: Women, Community and the Foundations of Agribusiness in the Midwest, 1900-1940</title>. Baltimore <hi rend="smallcaps">MD</hi>: Johns Hopkins
University Press, 1995.</bibl> <bibl>O'Brien, Sharon. <title level="m">Willa Cather: The Emerging Voice</title>. New York: Oxford University Press, 1987.</bibl>
<bibl>Rasmussen, Linda, Lorna Rasmussen, Candace Savage,
and Anne Wheeler. <title level="m">A Harvest Yet to Reap: A History of Prairie Women</title>. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press,
1976.</bibl> <bibl>Riley, Glenda. <title level="m">The Female Frontier: A Comparative View of Women on the Prairie and the Plains</title>. Lawrence:
University Press of Kansas, 1988.</bibl> <bibl>Riley, Glenda. <title level="m">Women and Indians on the Frontier, 1825-1915</title>. Albuquerque: University
of New Mexico Press, 1984.</bibl> <bibl>Riley, Glenda. "Women on the
Great Plains: Recent Developments in Research." <title level="j">Great Plains Quarterly</title> 5 (1985): 81-92.</bibl> <bibl>Savage, Candace. <title level="m">Our Nell: A Scrapbook Biography of Nellie L. McClung</title>. Saskatoon:
Western Producer Prairie Books, 1979.</bibl> <bibl>Schwieder, Dorothy,
and Deborah Fink. "Plains Women: Rural Life in the
1930s." <title level="j">Great Plains Quarterly</title> 8 (1988): 79-88.</bibl> <bibl>Stewart,
Elinore Pruitt. <title level="m">Letters of a Woman Homesteader</title>. Boston:
Houghton Mifflin Company, 1914.</bibl> <bibl>Underwood, June O.
"Civilizing Kansas: Women's Organizations, 1880-1920."
<title level="j">Kansas History</title> 7 (1984/85): 291-306.</bibl> <bibl>Van Kirk, Sylvia.
<title level="m">Many Tender Ties: Women in Fur-Trade Society, 1670-1870</title>.
Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1980.</bibl> <bibl>Webb, Walter
P. <title level="m">The Great Plains</title>. Boston: Ginn and Company, 1931.</bibl>
<bibl>Wishart, David. "The Roles and Status of Men and Women
in Nineteenth-Century Omaha and Pawnee Societies:
Postmodernist Uncertainties and Empirical Evidence."
<title level="j">American Indian Quarterly</title> 24 (1995): 509-18.</bibl>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>