<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fol.044">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Trickster</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Anthony Farrington</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2009</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fol.044</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2009</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2009 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Farrington, Anthony">Anthony Farrington</author>. <title level="a">"Trickster."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">315-316</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-18</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">TRICKSTER</head>

<p>The trickster is the embodiment of lawlessness
and paradox. He is a divine buffoon, a hero
who breaks taboos, a rebel, a coward, and a
creator. Trickster helps establish social rules,
and he deliberately flouts them. He is commonly
depicted as deceitful and humorous.
He is amoral, rather than immoral, and he has
a voracious appetite for food and sex. In his
traditional and mythic incarnations, he is almost
always male. As the supreme boundarycrosser,
trickster is always <hi rend="italic">between</hi> classifications&#8211;
between what is human and what is
animal, between what is cultural and what is
natural.</p>

<p>Native American tricksters tend to be associated
with animal spirits (such as Coyote,
Rabbit, or Raven). Their tales are both sacred
myths and simple folk tales. Among the Indigenous
peoples of the Great Plains, the trickster's
name is Old Man (Crow and Blackfoot),
Iktomi (Lakota), and Veeho (Cheyenne). The
most common incarnation of the Plains trickster,
however, is Coyote.</p>

<p>In his various (and strikingly similar) cultural
guises, trickster is the self-indulgent
clown who dupes women into having sex with
him; he steals food from his industrious neighbors;
he cross-dresses and becomes temporarily
a woman; he dies and is reborn. As expected,
his tomfoolery frequently backfires.
He juggles his eyes and loses them in a tree;
he accidentally sleeps with his wife; he drowns
in his own feces; he uses his enormous penis
to attack a chipmunk (who in turns bites his
penis off to "human" size). Further, trickster is
a cultural hero. In some narratives, he creates
the Earth; he creates animals or substantially
alters their bodies; he steals tobacco from
the gods; and, more recently, he tricks the
white man.</p>

<p>Symbolically, the trickster is always located
at the periphery of the community (though,
importantly, never totally separated from
it). From this "outer" vantage point, trickster
reveals "inner" communal structures. His
very presence determines the limits of social
boundaries. Trickster thus serves as a political
tool with which to subvert (or endorse) social
practices. Indeed, trickster continually offers
us the possibility of transcending (or renewing)
social codes. As such, trickster is arguably
an incarnation of creativity itself. At the very
least, trickster allows us to poke fun at the
powers that restrain us. He reveals the <hi rend="italic">structure</hi>
of social structures and offers us glimpses
of new (and terrifying) world orders. Not surprisingly,
many contemporary authors use
tricksterlike characters as creative forces that
both define and critique dominant cultural
practices.</p>

<p>Ultimately, the trickster is disturbing, not
because of his difference but because of his lack
of difference. As purely a cultural construct,
the trickster's body is a cultural body&#8211;our
body. He is always a part of us, and he exists
only to be interpreted. And when we interpret
trickster, we interpret ourselves. Even though
we often attempt to alienate ourselves from the
trickster&#8211;by making his body grotesque,
indistinguishable&#8211;wherever we are, there is
trickster, laughing at what we've become.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Anthony Farrington<lb/>
University of Arkansas at Monticello</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Babcock, Barbara. "'A Tolerated Margin of Mess': The
Trickster and His Tales Reconsidered." In <title level="m">Critical Essays on Native American Literature</title>, edited by Andrew Wiget.
Boston: G. K. Hall, 1985: 153–84.</bibl> <bibl>Ballinger, Franchot. "Living
Sideways: Social Themes and Social Relationships in
Native American Trickster Tales." <title level="j">American Indian Quarterly</title>
13 (1989): 15–30.</bibl> <bibl>Radin, Paul. <title level="m">The Trickster: a Study in American Indian Mythology</title>. New York: Philosophical Library,
1956.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>