<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.sr.018">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Football, American</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>G. Allen Finchum</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.sr.018</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Finchum, G. Allen">G. Allen Finchum</author>. <title level="a">"Football, American."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">772-773</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-20</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">FOOTBALL, AMERICAN</head>

<p>Football has been a mainstay of sports and
team-oriented recreation in the Great Plains
region for more than a century. Since early
settlers opened schools and towns began to
organize community sporting activities, football
has played a prominent role in the culture
and identity of the region. High school,
college, and professional football teams in
the Great Plains have enjoyed great success
throughout the twentieth century and now
into the twenty-first century.</p>

<p>High school football in the Great Plains is
played by eight-player teams in the smallest
communities and on the simplest of playing
fields as well as by students in some of the
largest and best-equipped school districts in
the United States. The latter is especially true
in the region's largest state, Texas, where some
high schools have facilities and budgets that
would be the envy of many smaller college
programs. The role of high school football in
serving as a community identifier is visible
every day on the local landscapes, where many
small towns and larger cities have signs and
water towers proclaiming the successes of
the local team. The level of community identification
with the high school football team has
also been well established in the popular media,
as is evident in several major motion pictures
such as <title>Varsity Blues</title> (1999). The impact
of high school football on the West Texas communities
of Midland and Odessa was also critically
chronicled by Pulitzer Prize–winning
journalist H. G. Bissinger in his book <title level="m">Friday
Night Lights</title>.</p>

<p>While high school and Little League football
continue to play a major role in the everyday
life of people throughout the Great Plains
region, no form of sport has brought more
recognition to the region than college football.
Legendary college basketball coaches
have parlayed their talents in the region, and
college baseball and other sports have also
achieved much, but it is the college football
teams from the Great Plains that have had unparalleled
success over the past fifty years.
During that time, Plains schools have won
outright or shared sixteen national titles, as
determined by the year-end polls of sportswriters
and coaches, with the University of
Oklahoma winning seven, Nebraska five,
Texas three, and Colorado one.</p>

<p>These four teams represent the most successful
of the region's college football programs,
but they are not the only ones that have
triumphed on the gridiron. In 1958 the Big 8
Conference, one of college football's most important
leagues, was created. This conference
was comprised of Iowa State University, Kansas
State University, Oklahoma State University,
and the Universities of Colorado, Kansas,
Missouri, Nebraska, and Oklahoma. Two of
these universities are outside the formally defined
Great Plains region (Iowa State University
and the University of Missouri); the remaining
six are located along the peripheries
of the region. While not all of these programs
have not had the accomplishments of the dominant
programs in the league, all have had their
moments in the college football spotlight. Oklahoma
State thrived in the 1980s, not least
because of Heisman Trophy winner Barry Sanders,
who set numerous conference and national
rushing records during his time with the
Cowboys. The University of Kansas launched
the Hall of Fame running back Gale Sayers, and
in the 1990s the Kansas State Wildcats became
one of college football's most successful teams
after decades of suffering as one of the nation's
poorest programs.</p>

<p>The Big 8 Conference became synonymous
with the Great Plains region, but prior to the
1990s, college sports in Texas were dominated
by the Southwest Conference (<hi rend="smallcaps">SWC</hi>). This conference
was comprised of eight universities
from Texas (the University of Texas, University
of Houston, Texas Tech, Baylor University,
Southern Methodist University, Texas Christian
University, and Texas A&amp;M University),
together with the University of Arkansas. Unfortunately,
this group of programs came to
symbolize the problems afflicting college football
in the late 1980s and 1990s. At one point
seven of the eight Texas programs were on
probation with the National Collegiate Athletic
Association (<hi rend="smallcaps">NCAA</hi>) for various rules violations,
and Southern Methodist University is
the only program in college football history to
suffer the "death penalty": the suspension of
the program for one or more years. While
rules violations were rampant in the <hi rend="smallcaps">SWC</hi>, the
Big 8 was not without its own problems. Oklahoma
and Oklahoma State were found to have
committed major rules violations as well. By
1995 major college football in the region was
in disarray, so a plan was put in place to restore
respect in the sport. The Big 12 Conference
was formed in 1996, comprising the
Big 8 programs plus four of the schools from
the <hi rend="smallcaps">SWC</hi>: the University of Texas, Texas A&amp;M
University, Texas Tech, and Baylor University.
In the first five years of the conference's existence,
two schools from the league won or
shared the national title&#8211;Nebraska in 1997
and Oklahoma in 2000.</p>

<p>Colorful coaches and players are often part
of college football, and the Great Plains region
is no exception. Oklahoma has benefited
from the coaching careers of Bud Wilkinson,
Barry Switzer, Chuck Fairbanks, and now Bob
Stoops; Nebraska has contributed coach Bob
Devaney and the twenty-five-year head coaching
career of Tom Osborne; and Texas was
led by legendary coaches Dana X. Bible and
Darrell Royal. U.S. Supreme Court Justice Byron
"Whizzer" White was an all-American at
Colorado.</p>

<p>Professional football in the region has had a
shorter but also a successful past. Both the
Denver Broncos and Kansas City Chiefs were
charter members of the original American
Football League in 1960. Each of these teams
has won the ultimate pro football prize, the
Super Bowl, with Kansas City winning in 1970
and Denver winning twice, in 1997 and 1998,
the latter game closing out the storied career
of quarterback John Elway. Like the major
college programs of the region, these teams
are located along the periphery of the Great
Plains. The most successful of the professional
football teams located on the edge of the region
is the Dallas Cowboys. Founded in 1960
as an expansion team in the National Football
League, the Cowboys were led for twenty-nine
years by coach Tom Landry. After an uneventful
first five seasons, the Cowboys played in
more Super Bowls than any professional football
team, winning the title five times.</p>

<p>The rough-and-tumble sport of football in
the Great Plains can be seen as a parallel to life
in this often difficult region&#8211;hard but leading
to triumph and attainment. The Great Plains
has seen success in football at all levels, from
the small high schools around which family life
and Friday nights are often centered in small
prairie towns to the national championships of
wealthy college and professional teams.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">AFRICAN AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.afam.036">Sanders, Barry</ref>; <ref n="egp.afam.037">Sayers, Gale</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">IMAGES AND ICONS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ii.025">Friday Night Football</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">LAW</hi>: <ref n="egp.law.053">White, Bryon</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>G. Allen Finchum<lb/>
Oklahoma State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Bissinger, H. G. <title level="m">Friday Night Lights: A Town, a Team, and a
Dream</title>. New York: HarperCollins, 1990.</bibl> <bibl>Dortch, Chris, ed.
<title level="m">Blue Ribbon College Football Yearbook: 2001 Edition</title>. Dulles
<hi rend="smallcaps">VA</hi>: Brasseys, Inc., 2001.</bibl> <bibl>Watterson, John Sayle. <title level="m">College
Football: History, Spectacle, and Controversy</title>. Baltimore
<hi rend="smallcaps">MD</hi>: Johns Hopkins University Press, 2000.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>