<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.sr.044">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Riding Around</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Pamela H. Brink</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.sr.044</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Brink, Pamela H.">Brink, Pamela H.</author>. <title level="a">"Riding Around."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">784</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-21</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">RIDING AROUND</head>

<p>Riding around is a time-honored rural recreation
in the Great Plains. When evening
comes, families like to pile in the car and take a
leisurely drive down familiar country roads to
shake off the cares of the day. A multigenerational
activity lasting about an hour at a time,
riding around, in its purest form, has no particular
destination or set purpose. It is primarily
a way for families and sometimes close
friends to enjoy each other's company and the
countryside they know and love. It is also a
tried-and-true technique for putting babies to
sleep and a traditional time for humming or
singing favorite old songs.</p>

<p>Riding around is a simple celebration of
loved ones, the landscape, and the seasons. In
the summer, when a high evening wind comes
up to blow away the heat of the day, riding
around might easily include appreciative observations
of a corn, grain sorghum, or sunflower
crop nearing harvest, the aroma of alfalfa
in bloom, or the slow meander of a hawk
also making evening rounds. Autumn weather
is a natural enticement for outings that can't
help but include cottonwood groves and a maple
tree or two decked out for the season.
Winter and spring are traditional wheat times,
when every inch of growth in the crop draws
attention, admiration, and sometimes great
worry.</p>

<p>Riding around is not always an evening activity.
Some families and friends like to take a
drive in the very early morning or after church
on Sunday. However, evening is the preferred
time. It seems that nothing else inspires Plains
people quite so consistently as a sunset sweeping
the sky, and taking to the country roads is
one of the most satisfying ways to experience
the drama of a Great Plains sunset. Taking to
the country roads is also one of the most satisfying
ways to participate in the unencumbered
landscape of the region and enjoy the spirit of
freedom it engenders. Since the introduction
of the automobile, riding around has been a
distinctive Plains tradition. It remains today
the same undemanding, meditative recreation
rooted in a rural lifestyle that keeps people
close to each other and close to the land.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Pamela H. Brink<lb/>
Associated Authors and Editors, Inc.</signed>
</closer>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>