<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ct.043">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">River Towns</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Timothy R. Mahoney</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ct.043</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Mahoney, Timothy R.">Timothy R. Mahoney</author>. <title level="a">"River Towns."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">180-181</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-28</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">RIVER TOWNS</head>

<p>As European American settlement moved
onto the edges of the Great Plains in the 1840s
and 1850s, American entrepreneurs from St.
Louis transformed the fur-trading network of
forts and outposts along the upper Missouri
River into a system of river towns that served
both as outfitting centers at the termini of the
major overland trails that crossed the Plains
and trading centers that connected settlers to
the national market. In the 1830s, while regular
St. Louis boats ran only out to the terminus
of the Santa Fe Trail at Westport, Missouri,
other St. Louis boats traded as far north as
Forts Lisa, Pierre, Mandan, and Union. Increased
tra.c along the overland routes to the
west in the 1840s and the opening of Kansas
and Nebraska Territories in 1854 triggered the
development of the river towns of Kansas City,
Missouri; Kansas City, Atchison, and Leavenworth,
Kansas Territory; and Brownville, Nebraska
City, and Omaha, Nebraska Territory.
After Dakota Territory was opened in 1861,
Yankton, Chamberlain, and Pierre and later
Mandan (Bismarck) and Williston (near Fort
Union) all emerged as river towns in the
1860s. The navigability of the Yellowstone
River in Montana reinvigorated Fort Benton
and led to the establishment of Miles City,
Coulson City (and later nearby Billings), and
Bozeman as river towns in the late 1860s and
1870s.</p>

<p>The history of each river town varied with
the timing of the arrival of the steamboat and
the arrival of the railroad there or at towns
farther north. With the arrival of steamboats,
Kansas City, Atchison, Leavenworth,
Nebraska City, and Omaha and later Yankton
and Bismarck each became a terminus and
outfitting center for a major overland route to
the West. In each case, the discovery of gold,
whether in Colorado in 1858, Montana in the
1860s, or the Black Hills in the 1870s, deepened
the town's outfitting function. In the 1850s St.
Joseph, Missouri, and Atchison and Leavenworth,
Kansas, became the headquarters for
major freight and mail companies providing
shipping services to the West. Both Omaha,
the territorial capital located at the terminus of
the Platte River route, and its rival, Nebraska
City, after 1858 the outpost of a freighting company
from Leavenworth at the terminus of the
northern route to the Rockies, enjoyed a decade
of prosperity as river towns. Farther
north, freight companies at Sioux City, Iowa,
and Yankton and Bismarck, Dakota Territory,
vied with each other for the Montana and
Black Hills gold trade in the 1860s and 1870s.
As settlement increased around each place, the
town became a depot for shipments between
St. Louis merchants and farmers and landlocked
towns in the hinterlands.</p>

<p>At each river town, however, the heyday of
the steamboat trade was short-lived. The arrival
of the railroad at Kansas City in 1854,
St. Joseph in 1858, Council Bluff's in 1867, and
Omaha and Sioux City in 1868 intersected and
truncated the St. Louis.controlled urban system
extending up the river. As St. Louisans
were cut out of their river trade, the new railroad
terminus replaced St. Louis as the steamboating
entrepot to the north until it too had
its trade cut off by a railroad arriving at some
town upriver. For example, when the railroad
reached Sioux City, Iowa, in 1868 it became
the upriver steamboat entrepot until the railroads
reached Yankton and Bismarck in 1873.
They in turn enjoyed their heydays as entrepots
only until the railroad reached Pierre
and Chamberlain and later Fort Benton in the
1880s. On the river below, steamboating declined
into local or secondary freight service,
thus ending its significance in each river
town's economy.</p>

<p>The history of most of these river town outposts
followed a similar scenario, varying only
in the timing of their development as river
towns and the arrival of the railroads. A river
town was a particular kind of urban trading
center along one of the great interior rivers
of North America or their tributaries to and
from which steamboats transported goods,
services, and passengers. The river and the
steamboat were the lifeblood of the classic
river town. Its economy was defined by the
seasonal rise and fall of the river. During the
brief spring navigation season on the Missouri,
steamboats delivered and picked up
tons of produce at the wharf or adjacent warehouses
or factories. The river was the Main
Street and the levee was the front door of the
typical river town. Near the wharf stood mills
and factories to process the products of the
hinterland. In larger towns, hotels, saloons,
and taverns adjacent to the levee became the
focal point of a vibrant river-town culture.
Nearby, lower-income workers and transients
and, especially in towns from Kansas City to
Omaha, African American residents usually
crowded into cramped living quarters. Farther
back from the river, merchants and professionals,
the social elite, lived in elaborate
row buildings and houses, often built in a
steamboat architectural style, interspersed
with churches.</p>

<p>This spatial differentiation was often reflected
by a hierarchical society. In most river
towns a small booster elite ruled as a political
and social oligarchy over a diverse local population.
Though some river towns developed a
reputation for tolerating deviant social behavior,
the social elite usually ruled indirectly
through a working-class boss who controlled
the local political machine and the police to
protect and support the city's wide-open vice
business. By the later nineteenth century,
some river towns such as Kansas City and
Omaha developed into railroad and manufacturing
gateway cities and entrepots of the
Great Plains. Most stagnated and settled for
slower growth as secondary or local railroad
and manufacturing centers. Riverfronts once
crowded by steamboats and then railroads
evolved in the early twentieth century into
warehouse and industrial districts that cut the
river off from the city. Periodic floods and
shifting economic conditions caused many
manufacturers to relocate and railroads to
shut their lines, gradually leaving most river
fronts underused or vacant. Only since the
1980s have some former river towns and cities
tried to reclaim riverside lands as industrial
or corporate parks, public parks, or sites for
gambling casinos (and their adjacent parking
lots), but in both Omaha and Kansas City the
riverfront remains an underused industrial
district and railroad right-of-way, inaccessible
to most residents, who have long since turned
their backs on the river to live and work farther
and farther out in the suburban and
fringe city hinterland.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">ARCHITECTURE</hi>: <ref n="egp.arc.052">Warehouse Districts</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Timothy R. Mahoney<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Larsen, Lawrence H. <title level="m">The Urban West at the End of the Frontier</title>. Lawrence: Regents Press of Kansas, 1978.</bibl> <bibl>Lass,
William E. <title level="m">A History of Steamboating on the Upper Missouri River</title>. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1962.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>