<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.edu.006">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Blanton, Annie Webb (1870-1945)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Margaret C. Berry</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.edu.006</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Berry, Margaret C.">Margaret C. Berry</author>. <title level="a">"Blanton, Annie Webb (1870-1945)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">199</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-28</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">BLANTON, ANNIE WEBB (1870-1945)</head>

<p>Annie Webb Blanton was a recognized international
leader in education, a teacher, a suffragist,
and the first woman in Texas elected to
a statewide office. The twin daughter of early
Texas pioneers Thomas Lindsay and Eugenia
Webb Blanton, she was born in Houston on
August 20, 1870. She had six siblings: her twin,
Fannie, who died at age twelve, two other sisters,
and three brothers. After early education
in Houston and at La Grange (Texas) High
School, she began teaching in a small school in
Pine Springs, Fayette County, where her special
interest in rural education began. In 1888,
with both parents deceased, she moved to
Austin and taught in elementary schools and
later in Austin High School to support herself
while studying at the University of Texas. She
graduated in 1899 with a bachelor of literature
degree.</p>

<p>Blanton taught English in Denton at North
Texas State Normal (now the University of
North Texas) from 1901 to 1918. While there
she was active in the Texas State Teachers Association
and was elected its first woman president
in 1916. She also served as vice president
of the National Education Association for
three terms, 1917, 1919, and 1921. A strong advocate
of equal rights for women, she entered
Texas politics in 1918 and was elected state superintendent
for public instruction in the first
election in which Texas women had the right
to vote. Her accomplishments included adoption
of a system of free textbooks, revision of
teacher certification laws, efforts to improve
rural education, increased salaries for teachers,
increase in length of the school term, and
passage of the Better Schools Amendment to
remove state constitutional limitations on tax
rates for local school districts.</p>

<p>After serving two terms, Blanton ran unsuccessfully
for the U.S. Congress in 1922 and
then returned to the University of Texas at
Austin for a master's degree in 1923. Here she
began teaching as adjunct professor of school
administration. In 1926 she took a leave of
absence to attend Cornell University for a
doctorate in rural education and rural sociology,
which she received in 1927. She returned
to Austin and in 1933 became professor of
rural education, the third woman to receive
the rank of full professor at the University of
Texas.</p>

<p>In 1929, at her residence in the Faculty
Women's Club near the campus, she founded
the Delta Kappa Gamma Society, an honor
society for women teachers that in 2001 had an
international membership of 143,951. She was
author of several books, including textbooks.
Texas public schools in Austin, Dallas, and
Odessa and a residence hall at the University
of Texas bear her name. She died in Austin on
October 2, 1945, and was buried in Oakwood
Cemetery.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Margaret C. Berry<lb/>
Austin, Texas</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Cottrell, Debbie Mauldin. <hi rend="italic">Pioneer Woman Educator: The
Progressive Spirit of Annie Webb Blanton</hi>. College Station:
Texas A&amp;M University Press, 1994.</bibl> <bibl>Holden, Eunah Temple.
<hi rend="italic">Our Heritage in the Delta Kappa Gamma Society</hi>. Austin
<hi rend="smallcaps">TX</hi>: Delta Kappa Gamma Society, 1970.</bibl>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>