<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.arc.037">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Public Buildings</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Keith Sawyers</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.arc.037</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Sawyers, Keith">Keith Sawyers</author>. <title level="a">"Public Buildings."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">89-90</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-13</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">PUBLIC BUILDINGS</head>

<p>Public buildings such as schools, libraries, city
halls, and courthouses are the physical embodiment
of pride, stability, and cultural enlightenment.
They functionally acknowledge
and aesthetically symbolize the foundations of
civil life in a community.</p>

<p>The need for universal public education
was well established by the time immigrants
began to settle the Great Plains. At that time a
basic knowledge of reading, writing, and elementary
arithmetic was considered a sufficient minimum. Facilities to accommodate
these requirements were generally very modest,
often temporary structures built by the
fledgling communities utilizing indigenous
materials such as logs, sod, and even baled
hay. Few of these early buildings survive.</p>

<p>During the frontier period many school
buildings were barely suitable for educational
functions, due primarily to a lack of design
and building expertise. Consequently, educational
reformers focused attention upon rectifying
common deficiencies in illumination,
heating, sanitation, and furnishings by developing
design guidelines and creating standardized
plans. At the same time, state and
provincial governments began to assert their
influence upon the design of school buildings.</p>

<p>One of the earliest and most basic purposebuilt
designs for education was the one-room
schoolhouse. A small rectangular structure
with a gable roof, it became a ubiquitous feature
of the rural Plains landscape. Based upon
a common plan, the vast majority were of
wood-frame construction, although some
were constructed of brick or stone where available.
Likewise, many medium-size schools
were based upon standardized plans. Characteristically
rectangular in configuration, many
of these buildings were organized around a
central hall flanked by several rooms and accommodating
stairs to a basement and upper
floor. Exterior composition was typically symmetrical,
with emphasis upon vertical proportions,
the latter frequently accentuated by a
central tower. Popular Victorian styles considered appropriate for schools at this time included
Italianate, Second Empire, and Romanesque.
By the turn of the century the formal
classical styles were widely favored for
their more pretentious symbolism and distinctive
monumental character.</p>

<p>During the early decades of the twentieth
century, preparation of the citizenry for an
increasingly complex society transformed the
mission and magnitude of education. More
sophisticated school subtypes evolved to satisfy
new educational requirements, ranging
from the nursery school to the junior high
school and vocational high school. Specialuse
rooms were required for instruction in
science, fine and performing arts, physical education,
home economics, and vocational
training. The compact but rather confining
rectangular plan of earlier years gave way to
increasingly flexible T-shaped and courtyard
plans. The elevations of these more complex
configurations accommodated a variety of
stylistic variations, including the Late Gothic
Revival, which was popularly associated with
educational buildings ranging from grade
schools to collegiate institutions.</p>

<p>The architectural character of schools in the
Great Plains continued to evolve after World
War II, paralleling changes in educational philosophy,
technology, and design. Elementary
and high schools were typically sited on tracts
of land large enough to accommodate generous
playgrounds and outdoor athletic facilities.
Their designs were characterized by openspace
planning, spreading classroom wings,
and clearly articulated special-use facilities.
Designs in the 1950s and 1960s were distinctly
modern, emphasizing efficiency and displaying
a functional, almost industrial image.
Glass curtain walls, simple brick facades, and
flat roofs were characterizing features that
were used extensively.</p>

<p>School design in recent decades features a
return to subtle historical references in material
usage and decorative details, a utilization
of the latest advances in building technology,
plans based on the concept of learning communities,
and an increasingly sensitive response
to environmental issues. On the other
hand, shifting rural and suburban populations
and obsolescent educational facilities
have resulted in the closing of many older
school buildings and their conversion to offices
and housing.</p>

<p>An interest in establishing libraries also accompanied
immigrants to the Great Plains.
Small collections of books were housed wherever
unused space was available such as the
rear of a store or the corner of a church basement.
These modest collections were frequently
the property of local citizens such as
women's groups whose goal was to improve
the cultural climate of the community. The
greatest momentum for founding public libraries
in the region occurred between the
1890s and World War I.</p>

<p>After the turn of the century the Carnegie
Foundation provided funding and stimulated
the construction of many libraries in the
Great Plains region of Canada and the United
States. In 1911 the foundation published a
set of design standards for these libraries. The
favored scheme was a rectangular, one-story
building set on a raised basement and entered
from a small vestibule. The Carnegie Endowment
program placed almost no restrictions
on exterior design, but the overwhelming majority
exhibited the influence of classicism,
which gained widespread popularity following
the World's Columbian Exposition of 1893.</p>

<p>Prior to World War II, library design was
characterized by a bias for monumentality,
modest attention paid to function, and meager
consideration given to future expansion.
After 1950 the use of fixed book stacks and
walls gave way to a more spatially open, functionally
flexible, and user-friendly design.
In recent decades the information explosion,
new technology, provision for the handicapped,
and population growth have forced
additional changes upon libraries. In larger
cities the main downtown library may be retained,
but new satellite branches are being
constructed in the suburbs. The exterior appearance
of these new buildings varies considerably,
partially due to changing attitudes
regarding the symbolism considered appropriate
for a contemporary public building.
Monumentality, once very much in favor for
civic architecture, has given way to an imagery
that is less formal and imposing. Common
interior features include innovations in illumination,
environmental control, and flexibility
in the functional use of space.</p>

<p>Governmental buildings made their appearance
early in the settlement of the Great
Plains. In Canada the municipal building, or
town hall, was the primary symbol of government
after the provincial capitol. Sparsely
populated rural communities and townships
constructed small, unimposing structures that
accommodated only the most basic functions
of local government, but by the end of the
nineteenth century the largest Plains towns
were erecting monumental city halls following
European precedents. In addition to providing
for governmental activities such as
a council chamber, offices, and courtroom,
many city halls also housed a public auditorium
for cultural events and a variety of additional
civic amenities.</p>

<p>In the United States the county courthouse
emerged as the most important symbol of
government, second only to the state capitol.
It was commonly believed that a building displaying
a dignified and monumental character
was appropriate for the transaction of county
business, security of public records, and administration
of justice. The courthouse commanded
a place of honor in the town plan and
typically occupied a full city block. One of the
most distinctive spatial arrangements features
the courthouse in the midst of the business
district surrounded on four sides by commercial
buildings. Status within the anonymous
grid was also achieved by siting the building
on a hill or at the end of a prominent street
or vista.</p>

<p>The function of the courthouse changed little
during the nineteenth and first half of
the twentieth centuries, during which time the
spatial arrangement tended to follow a distinctive
pattern. offices for the daily business
of elected officials were usually located within
a rectangular plan, the more significant activities
being located on a raised first floor and
the remainder placed in the basement. The
second floor accommodated the most important
public space, the courtroom, and related
functions.</p>

<p>Nineteenth-century governmental buildings
revealed evidence of the prevailing Victorian
styles, including the Italianate and Second
Empire. The Gothic style was quite popular in
Canada but seldom utilized in the United
States due to its religious connotations and the
desire to separate church and state. During the
1880s the round arch, or Romanesque, style
was widely favored for its solid, dignified appearance.
The overwhelming majority of governmental
buildings built between the turn of
the century and the 1930s exhibit the influence
of classicism.</p>

<p>Since World War II many city halls and
county courthouses have been remodeled or
replaced. The design of new governmental
buildings tends to be significantly affected by
functional and economic factors. In contrast
to the pride and optimism expressed in much
traditional civic architecture, the scale and
imagery of many contemporary governmental
buildings resemble the sobriety and efficiency characteristic of today's utilitarian office
blocks.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">EDUCATION</hi>: <ref n="egp.edu.032">One-Room Schoolhouses</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Keith Sawyers<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln<lb/>
</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Kalman, Harold D. <title level="m">A History of Canadian Architecture</title>.
Toronto: Oxford University Press, 1996.</bibl> <bibl>Maddex, Diane,
ed. <title level="m">Built in the U.S.A.: American Buildings from Airports to Zoos</title>. Washington <hi rend="smallcaps">DC</hi>: Preservation Press, 1985.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>