<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.lt.014">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Debo, Angie (1890-1988)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Heather M. Lloyd</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.lt.014</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Lloyd, Heather M.">Heather M. Lloyd</author>. <title level="a">"Debo, Angie (1890-1988)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">477</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-23</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">DEBO, ANGIE (1890-1988)</head>

<p>Angie Debo was an historian and advocate for
human rights who spent all of her life in the
Great Plains. She wrote nine books about Native
Americans and the development of Oklahoma,
edited four other volumes, and was the
author of numerous scholarly articles. Several
of her books have been used as textbooks in
college courses. In addition to writing, she
lobbied for civil liberties and for the rights of
Native Americans.</p>

<p>Angie Debo was born January 30, 1890, on a
farm near Beattie, Kansas. Nine years later her
father used a covered wagon to move his family
to a new farm near Marshall, Oklahoma.
Debo attended rural one-room schools and at
age twelve completed the instruction they offered.
When she was sixteen and could obtain
a teacher's certificate, Debo began teaching in
rural schools near Marshall. Finally, the town
acquired a four-year high school. Debo graduated
from it in 1913 and from the University of
Oklahoma in 1918. She then taught in Enid,
Oklahoma, until 1923, when she attended the
University of Chicago and received a master's
degree in 1924. For nine years, from 1924 to
1933, she taught preparatory classes in the history
department of West Texas State Teachers
College while completing her doctorate at the
University of Oklahoma. Debo's doctoral dissertation
received wide acclaim upon its publication
in 1934 under the title <title level="m">The Rise and Fall of the Choctaw Republic</title>. When she was
unable to find a college teaching position, she
decided to move back to her parents' home in
Marshall and devote all her time to researching
and writing.</p>

<p>Debo's next book, <title level="m">And Still the Waters Run: The Betrayal of the Five Civilized Tribes</title>, became
available in 1940. This pioneering work
describes the tribes and their relations with
the federal government and the courts of
Oklahoma. It took almost four years for her to
find a willing publisher, largely because she
was exposing graft and corruption, topics that
heretofore had not been addressed in scholarly
works. This and another of her books,
<title level="m">The Road to Disappearance: A History of the Creek Indians</title> (1941), were used by the U.S.
Supreme Court in deciding a 1976 case, <hi rend="italic">Harjo
v. Kleppe</hi>. Other books by Debo include <title level="m">The Five Civilized Tribes of Oklahoma: Report on Social and Economic Conditions</title> (1951); <title level="m">Geronimo: The Man, His Time, His Place</title> (1976);
<title level="m">Oklahoma: Foot-loose and Fancy-free</title> (1949);
<title level="m">Tulsa: From Creek Town to Oil Capital</title> (1943);
<title level="m">Prairie City: The Making of an American Community</title>
(1944); and the seminal <title level="m">A History of the Indians of the United States</title> (1970).</p>

<p>Debo's study of Native Americans and their
relationships with the federal government
took her into new areas of research in the 1930s.
She said that her only goal was to conduct the
research to reveal the truth and to publish it. To
achieve this goal she pioneered in writing from
the Indian point of view. Her books have been
widely recognized as resources for determining
Native American property rights. Through
her lobbying efforts she contributed to the passage
of the Alaska Native Claims Settlement
Act and helped Arizona Indians establish land
and water rights. Over the years Debo received
numerous awards for her research, her writing,
and her involvement in efforts on behalf
of civil liberties. Shortly before her death
in Marshall, Oklahoma, on February 21, 1988,
she became the fourth person, and the first
woman, to receive the prestigious Award for
Scholarly Distinction from the American Historical
Association.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Heather M. Lloyd<lb/>
Oklahoma State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Angie Debo Papers, Collection 88-013, Oklahoma State
University Library, Stillwater.</bibl> <bibl>Leckie, Shirley A. <title level="m">Angie Debo: Pioneering Historian</title>. Norman: University of Oklahoma
Press, 2000.</bibl> <bibl>Sandlin, Martha, producer. <title level="m">Indians, Outlaws and Angie Debo</title>. Alexandria <hi rend="smallcaps">VA</hi>: <hi rend="smallcaps">PBS</hi> Video, 1988.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>