<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.art.032 SYSTEM "egp.art.032.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.art.032">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Hogue, Alexandre (1898-1994)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Lea Rosson DeLong</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.art.032</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="DeLong, Rosson Lea">Lea Rosson DeLong</author>. <title level="a">"Hogue, Alexandre (1898-1994)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">119-120</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-22</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">HOGUE, ALEXANDRE (1898-1994)</head>

<figure n="egp.art.032" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Alexandre Hogue. American 1898–1994. Erosion No. 2. Mother Earth Laid Bare, 1936. Oil on canvas.</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>American artist Alexandre Hogue is known
primarily for his paintings of the Dust Bowl of
the 1930s. Hogue was one of the few painters
of the period to acknowledge the conditions
of the Southern Plains during the Great Depression,
and his works are considered both
accurate and provocative. His concern with
the environment and with humans' relations
with it endures as a major theme in his work.</p>

<p>Born in Memphis, Missouri, on February
22, 1898, Hogue grew up in Denton and Dallas.
He worked briefly (1921-25) in New York
as a graphic designer and then returned to
Texas, where he established himself as an artist,
teacher, and writer. His explorations of the
landscape along with his interest in Native cultures
and their attitudes toward nature formed
an artistic credo that emphasized not only the
beauty of the land but also the effects upon it
of human activities.</p>

<p>In his travels through the region he witnessed
the development of the Dust Bowl, and
in 1932 he began his series on the ecological disaster
unfolding before him. <title>Dust Bowl</title> (1933,
Smithsonian Museum of American Art),
<title>Drouth Stricken Area</title> (1934, Dallas Museum
of Fine Art), and <title>Drouth Survivors</title> (1936,
destroyed in 1948, formerly in the Mus&#233;e National
d'Art Modern, Paris) all show a landscape
described by Hogue as a "lush grassland"
transformed into a desertlike place
scarcely able to sustain life of any kind. Tractors
and dead cattle half-buried in sand dunes,
an abandoned farm with its broken windmill
and dust-filled water trough, and the eerie
light of a dust-choked, sandy, and barren
ranch&#8211;all these images created an apocalyptic
iconography that Hogue used to convey the
reality of the situation on the Plains as well as
his condemnation of the farming and ranching
practices that had created it. Unlike the
photographers of the Farm Security Administration,
who also documented Depression
Era conditions, Hogue expressed little sympathy
for the families forced off the land by the
Dust Bowl (in fact, they do not appear in his
work) but instead made it clear that he held
humans accountable for their deliberate misuse
of the land.</p>

<p>Perhaps the grimmest and most accusatory
painting is <title>Mother Earth Laid Bare</title> (1938, Philbrook
Museum of Art Museum, Tulsa), in
which overproduction of the land and disregard
for the forces of nature are clearly presented
as acts of desecration. In contrast to
other painters of the period such as Grant
Wood and Thomas Hart Benton, who generally
treated their region as a place of hope,
good values, and productivity, Hogue presents
a sobering view of a land exhausted and
ruined by the failure to acknowledge and respect
nature. Later works from the 1950s on
were less condemnatory but continued to express
the artist's reverence for nature, even at
times in an abstract style. His series of drawings,
pastels, and paintings on the Big Bend
landscape (c. 1960–c. 1990) especially demonstrate
the persistence of this theme.</p>

<p>In addition to his career as an artist, Hogue
was an important teacher in the region, notably
as head of the art department at the University
of Tulsa (1945–68). During the 1930s he
was a leader in one of the most active regional
groups, known as the Dallas Nine, and was
also a founder (1938) of the Lone Star Printmakers.
Hogue died in Tulsa on July 22, 1994.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT</hi>: <ref n="egp.pe.022">Dust Bowl</ref>.</p>


<closer>
<signed>Lea Rosson DeLong<lb/>
Des Moines, Iowa</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>DeLong, Lea Rosson. <title level="m">Nature's Forms/Nature's Forces: The Art of Alexandre Hogue</title>. Norman: University of Oklahoma
Press; Tulsa: Philbrook Museum of Art, 1984.</bibl> <bibl>Hogue, Alexandre.
"Progressive Texas." <title level="j">Art Digest</title> 10 (1936): 17–18.</bibl>
<bibl>Stewart, Rick. <title level="j">Lone Star Regionalism: The Dallas Nine and Their Circle</title>. Dallas: Dallas Museum of Art, 1985.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>