<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.sr.012">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Crow Fair</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>C. Adrian Heidenreich</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.sr.012</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Heidenreich, C. Adrian">C. Adrian Heidenreich</author>. <title level="a">"Crow Fair."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">769-770</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-20</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">CROW FAIR</head>
<figure n="egp.sr.012" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Dancers at Crow Fair</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Crow Fair, called the "Tipi Capital of the
World," is an annual event held the third
weekend in August on the Crow Reservation
in Montana. It is one of the largest Native
American events in North America and is run
by a committee of the Crow tribe. Crow Fair
combines a celebration of Crow culture, reunion
of family groups, powwow, rodeo,
horse racing, and commercial vendors. Native
Americans of various tribes and many non-Indian
people, including visitors from around
the world, gather to celebrate and enjoy themselves.
There may be 1,000 tipis, along with
wall tents, pickup campers, trailers, and mobile
homes. Each family has its own camp
area, and people visit and eat under arbor
shades and awnings.</p>

<p>These camps surround an open circular
dance arbor with bleachers. Immediately
around the dance arbor are commercial booths
that serve food as well as sell Native crafts, arts,
supplies, and children's carnival toys. Social and
popular dances are held for young people in the
Round Hall. An all-Indian rodeo and horse
races are held at the racetrack arena adjacent to
the fairgrounds. Crow Fair runs four days for
the tribe and general public. A fifth day is devoted
to Crow tribal members and their immediate
friends and includes dances, giveaways,
feasting, and the Parade Dance around camp
with a salute to the mountains.</p>

<p>Each morning there is a parade, and spectators
line the edges of the road, sitting on folding
chairs, in cars, or in the beds of pickup
trucks, many holding umbrellas for shade. The
procession is led by a color guard of Native
American veterans. The main parade includes
people on horseback, on foot, and riding on
cars and floats. Most are dressed in powwow
finery, wearing traditional Plains regalia, including
fancy beaded vests, eagle-feather bonnets,
shawls, and elk tooth dresses, mixed with
cowboy dress. Many horses are outfitted with
traditional Crow saddles, beaded or painted
saddlebags, Pendleton blankets, beaded rifle
bags, and cradleboards. Vehicles and floats also
are covered with traditional finery; along the
sides, draped banners declare titles of tribal or
family affiliation. The floats have displays such
as a small tipi and arbor with elders and children
or a drum group with dancers. The paraders
smile, wave to the people lining the
roadside, and throw candy to the children. The
current Crow Fair princess leads "visiting royalty"
who have won princess titles at other
reservations and powwows. Awards are given
for the best dress outfits, decorated horses,
and floats.</p>

<p>Drum groups, dancers, and spectators assemble
at the central dance arbor for the afternoon
and evening powwow. The grand entry
is led by an Indian veteran color guard, followed
by distinguished individuals, honored
guests and elders, and then male traditional
dancers, male fancy dancers, women traditional
dancers, girl's shawl or fancy dancers,
jingle dress, grass dancers, and tiny tots.
The powwow includes announcements, jokes,
dance competitions in various categories and
age groups, and intertribal and social dances.
Honor songs and dances, giveaways, and
adoption and naming ceremonies occur. After
the powwow, there are sometimes forty-nine
dances and tipi doorway singing. The all-Indian
rodeo and horse races are held at the
nearby racetrack arena. The rodeo includes
saddle bronc and bareback riding, bull riding,
bulldogging, calf roping, team roping, and
barrel racing. Quarter horse and Thoroughbred
racing are featured. There is much betting
on the outcomes of the races.</p>

<p>Crow Fair started in 1904, when the Bureau
of Indian Affairs agent and Crow leaders
agreed that a country fair format would help
induce the Crows to become self-supporting
farmers while at the same time allow the people
to showcase aspects of Crow culture. Crow
women exhibited traditional Native foods,
clothing, and handicrafts. People brought
ponies, calves, pigs, turkeys, and chickens for
exhibit as well as potatoes, pumpkins, squash,
grain, jellies, pies, bread, butter, and cakes.
Schoolchildren exhibited basketry, embroidery,
and various crafts and played band music.
A committee of chiefs and elders scheduled
entertainment events and arranged a parade,
foot and horse racing, relay races, rodeo (including
bucking broncos), and dancing to the
beat of singers around drums. Storytelling of
war deeds by veterans, victory dances, sham
battles and reenactments, and the distribution
of gifts to tribal members and visitors became
popular. Prizes were given for the best-pitched
and decorated tipis, tipi-pitching races, farm
exhibits, horse work teams and wagons, buggies,
and races.</p>

<p>Federal Indian policy at that time generally
forbade traditional singing, dancing, and ceremonies,
but the combination of agricultural
assimilation and traditional culture coincided
with public interest in tourism. Visitors included
non-Indians as well as members of
many other tribes. The fair became a successful
national model for Indian events. After
World War II the agricultural aspects of Crow
Fair were dropped, and the combined Crow
and modern pan-Indian event has grown to
become one of the most popular cultural celebrations
in the world.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">NATIVE AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.na.024">Crows</ref>; <ref n="egp.na.091">Powwows</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>C. Adrian Heidenreich<lb/>
Montana State University, Billings</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl><title>Baasaxpilua: Northern Plains Celebration</title>. Video. Denver
Museum of Natural History, 1982.</bibl> <bibl>Loeb, Barbara. "Crow
Fair." <title level="j">Native Peoples</title> 3 (1990): 16–24.</bibl> <bibl>Wisherd, Edwin L.
"The Friendly Crows in Festive Panoply." <title level="j">National Geographic</title>
52 (1927): 315–22.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>