<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.afam.041 SYSTEM "egp.afam.041.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.afam.041">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Tulsa Race Riot</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Larry O'Dell</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.afam.041</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>
 
<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="O'Dell, Larry">Larry O'Dell</author>. <title level="a">"Tulsa Race Riot."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">22-23</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-12-08</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">TULSA RACE RIOT</head>

<figure n="egp.afam.041" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Burned ruins after race riot in Tulsa, Oklahoma, June 1, 1921</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>On the night of May 31, 1921, in one of
the worst episodes in Oklahoma and American history, Tulsa exploded in violence that
scarred the city forever. Although many details
of the riot are shrouded in controversy,
what is known is that about thirty-five blocks
in the African American district were destroyed
and at least thirty-nine people&#8211;and
probably considerably more&#8211;lost their lives.
The white mob torched the influential black
business district known as "Deep Greenwood,"
and all African Americans who did not
flee or get killed were arrested. It took the arrival
of the National Guard and martial law to
bring order to the violence-torn city.</p>

<p>The Jim Crow climate in Oklahoma and in
much of the nation at the time set the tone for
Tulsa's riot. Oklahoma had its share of lynchings
and racial violence prior to 1921 and after,
and the Ku Klux Klan was just gaining a
foothold in the young state. Tulsa's African
Americans, many of them returning World
War I veterans, had a new sense of pride (as
well as training), and numerous organizations,
including Cyril Brigg's national group,
the African Blood Brotherhood, preached
self-reliance and the need for community defense.
The black press in Oklahoma, and especially
A. J. Smitherman's <title level="j">Tulsa Star</title>, also advocated
protecting family and community.
Smitherman had witnessed other racial conflicts
prior to Tulsa's catastrophe. In one case
in Okmulgee, Oklahoma, he saw a white mob
back down from a group of armed blacks who
were protecting their houses. This lesson, and
also the failure of Oklahoma City authorities
to stop a lynching of an African American less
than a year before, and the lynching of a white
person who was pulled out of the Tulsa jail in
1920, increased the determination of Tulsa's
black leaders not to let an African American
lynching occur in their city.</p>

<p>On May 30, 1921, Dick Rowland, an African
American shoe-shiner, went to the Drexel
Building to use the restroom. The closest "colored"
restroom was located on the top floor of
the building. Speculation after the riot suggested
that Rowland tripped as he entered the
elevator and grabbed the arm of the elevator
operator, Sarah Page, who then screamed.
Whether this is actually what happened is
not fully known. It has also been suggested
they had an ongoing relationship. The next
morning Tulsa police arrested Rowland for attempted
rape. The Tulsa Tribune printed an
article titled, "Nab Negro for Attacking Girl
in Elevator," and may have included an even
more incendiary article in the editorial section,
but all known Tribune copies are missing
this entry. These news stories aroused both
sections of the town.</p>

<p>A large group of whites surrounded the
courthouse and jail on the night of May 31.
Armed African Americans twice went to the
courthouse offering to help protect Rowland.
Their second appearance sparked mayhem as
a shot scattered the crowd. Skirmishes between
blacks and whites occurred from the
courthouse back to the African American
neighborhoods. Whites broke into stores to
get arms and ammunition, and many were
sworn in as special deputies. Sporadic fighting
lasted through the night. In the middle of the
night Tulsa officials sent a telegram to Oklahoma
City requesting help from the National
Guard.</p>

<p>At dawn the next morning, June 1, a whistle
reportedly blew signaling the white invasion
of North Tulsa. One controversy surrounding
the riot has been the extent to which machine
guns and airplanes were used during the battle
for Greenwood. Both were present, and there
is evidence that explosives were dropped from
planes, though the planes seemed to have been
used mainly for reconnaissance. The outnumbered
African Americans tried to defend their
homes, but the invaders descended, burning
and looting. Among the African Americans
killed was A. C. Jackson, a nationally renowned
black surgeon. Others fled north out
of the city, but many were arrested and detained
at the convention center and later at a
ballpark and the fairgrounds. The National
Guard arrived at 9:15 that morning, and Gen.
Charles Barrett declared martial law at 11:29.
By this time the riot had nearly run its course.</p>

<p>African Americans in Tulsa faced an uphill
struggle after the riot. The city government
enacted a fire-ordinance restriction to stop the
rebuilding process. African American lawyers
fought and won the fire-ordinance battle, but
many North Tulsans were homeless through
the winter and lived in tents and makeshift
homes. Greenwood did rebuild and, some
contend, became more prosperous than before
1921, but no insurance claims were ever
paid to the holders nor did the city pay restitution.
Urban renewal later leveled North Tulsa
a second time.</p>

<p>In 1997 the Oklahoma legislature established
a Race Riot Commission to study the
violence of the 1921 race war. In 2001 the commission
submitted an official report of its
findings to the legislature and recommended
reparations be paid to the survivors of Oklahoma's&#8211;
and one of the nation's&#8211;worst civil
disturbances.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">CITIES AND TOWNS</hi>: 
<ref n="egp.ct.052">Tulsa, Oklahoma</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Larry O'Dell<lb/>
Oklahoma Historical Society</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Ellsworth, Scott. <title level="m">Death in a Promised Land: The Tulsa Race
Riot of 1921</title>. Baton Rouge: Louisiana State University Press,
1982.</bibl> <bibl>Franklin, John Hope, and Scott Ellsworth, eds. <title level="m">The
Tulsa Race Riot: A Scientific, Historical, and Legal Analysis.
Tulsa</title>: A Report Submitted to the Tulsa Race Riot Commission,
2000.</bibl> <bibl>Parrish, Mary E. Jones. <title level="m">Race Riot 1921,
Events of the Tulsa Disaster</title>. Tulsa: Out on a Limb Publishing,
1998.</bibl>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>