<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fil.052">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Oil Field Films</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Donald E. Staples</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fil.052</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Staples, Donald E.">Donald E. Staples</author>. <title level="a">"Oil Field Films."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">275-276</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-12</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">OIL FIELD FILMS</head>
<figure n="egp.fil.052" rend="granted" type="noclick">
<figDesc>Boom Town (1940) film poster</figDesc>
</figure>      

<p>Movies about the discovery and production of
oil are usually a subgenre of the Western and
often take place in Oklahoma or Texas. From
<title>Boom Town</title> (1940), with Spencer Tracy and
Clark Gable, to <title>Stars Fell on Henrietta</title> (1995),
with Robert Duvall and Aidan Quinn, the tale
of the adventuring wildcatter is always a popular
theme. <title>Giant</title> (1956) is the best known. Oil
production films can start in the Great Plains
and go anywhere in the world: <title>Hellfighters</title>
(1968), <title>Local Hero</title> (1983), and the Imax production
of <title>Fires of Kuwait</title> are examples. Oil
field scenes and plot devices also appear in
other films such as <title>Cimarron</title> (1931), Hud
(1963), and <title>The Last Picture Show</title> (1971).</p>

<p>Since U.S. oil fields and movies are both
about a hundred years old, they have coexisted
and interacted. Speculators in oil and film
know that the odds of bringing in a gusher or
a blockbuster are about the same. A great
monetary risk is involved; however, in the oil
fields as well as the movie studios, the love of
the game is supreme. The continuing players
love the process and the romance of the search
for big-time success.</p>

<p>From silent films to talkies and from black
and white to color, oil has been a popular
mid-American subject. It is part of the lore of
the Plains pioneers. The movies often depict
the cattle ranchers versus the sheepmen, farmers,
trainmen, and finally oilmen. In many
stories of later times (<title>Hud</title>, <title>Stars Fell on Henrietta</title>, and <title>Oklahoma Crude</title>, released in 1973),
the rancher must find oil on his property in
order to survive because the land has been
fenced and the railroads have taken over from
the cattle drives. Some of the land has dried up
and been farmed out, and the Plains ecosystems
have deteriorated. Oil will be the salvation
of the entrepreneur and his family.</p>

<p>Women wildcatters sometimes take over as
oil prospectors. In <title>Tulsa</title> (1949) Susan Hayward
goes for oil to avenge the death of her
cattle rancher father, and in <title>Waltz across Texas</title>
(1982) Anne Archer is a modern-day geologist
looking for oil and finding romance. In <title>Lucy Gallant</title> (1955) Jane Wyman plays the title role
of a woman who finds success in selling expensive
dresses to the women of an oil town.
One line of gowns is even in the colors of oil.
Charlton Heston is the love-interest rancher
who becomes an oilman.</p>

<p>Since these films are Westerns, the men and
women in the oil business are tough and aggressive,
coming from strong pioneer stock.
Because wealth is at stake, they are clever and
conniving. They work hard and play hard at
very high emotional levels of romance and adventure.
Their fortunes may wax and wane
with many highs and lows; however, they survive
with great determination and effort. Oil is
the black gold, which has a great attraction,
and whether they are searching, drilling, hauling,
selling, or putting out fires, it is always
exciting on the motion picture screen.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Donald E. Staples<lb/>
University of North Texas</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Graham, Don. <title>Cowboys and Cadillacs</title>. Austin: Texas
Monthly Press, 1983.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>