<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.arc.008">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Clay Construction</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>David Murphy</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.arc.008</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Murphy, David">David Murphy</author>. <title level="a">"Clay Construction."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">71-72</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-12</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">CLAY CONSTRUCTION</head>

<p>Soils with clay content suitable for building
purposes are found throughout the Great
Plains. The most prolific use of these was in the
industrial manufacture of fired brick, which
flourished in countless brickyards around the
region from the early years of European American
settlement through the first decades of the
twentieth century. The earthen construction
described here, however, refers to materials
used in traditional, preindustrial technologies.</p>

<p>Four techniques predominated. Most common
was sun-dried brick, in which clay was
first worked into molds, later removed and
allowed to dry in the sun, then laid up to form
walls. A second was the puddled-clay wall,
which was built up from large lifts of clay that
were shaped after the clay had set. Rammedearth
construction used puddled clay that was
packed or stamped between a formwork. Numerous
variations on these techniques are
known, including the use of clay lumps and
the incorporation of field stones into rammed
walls. A fourth technology, wattle and daub,
utilized a wooden framework&#8211;often of woven
materials&#8211;in and over which puddled
clays were packed to form a reinforced massive
wall. Clays were also commonly used as
plasters for walls, roofing membranes, finishes,
and masonry mortars.</p>

<p>The manner of processing the clay was similar
in all cases. Varying quantities of clayey
soil and water were mixed together by hand,
animal power, or some mechanical device,
fusing the soil particles and producing a dense
composition ideal for building purposes.
Other materials such as straw, grass, manure,
and sand were often added to the mix to improve
performance. The most common processing
method was to mix the materials in a
pit near the building site.</p>

<p>Earthen building in the Great Plains occurred
in multiple waves. The oldest involved
wattle-and-daub walls constructed by Indigenous
peoples in the Central and Southern
Plains. The most pronounced of these were
evident in square and early circular lodges
built between 500 and 1,000 years ago.</p>

<p>Initial European American expansion into
the western and southwestern Plains was built
upon the adoption of Hispanic adobe brick
technology by fur traders. Their construction
facilitated by imported Latino labor, these architectural
forms often imitated the fortified
Spanish presidio. The earliest examples were
built by trader John Gantt and his competitor,
the Bent, St. Vrain &amp; Company. Gantt's Fort
Cass was built in 1834, while Bent's Fort followed
closely; both were located along the upper
Arkansas River. Bent's Fort was state of the
art for the fortified trading post. It was a large
presidio built by laborers from Taos; its form
and construction influenced a number of later
trading posts. By 1838 four more adobe forts
had been built along the upper South Platte.
Along the upper North Platte River, Forts
Platte and John, both adobe-walled trading
posts, were completed by 1841.</p>

<p>Adobe construction spread farther with the
adoption of the technique by the United States
Army. Recommendations concerning the utility
of adobe bricks in the West did not appear
until 1848, coincidental with but unrelated to
the adobes' first military use on the Plains in
what became Nebraska. There their use was
recommended by an old trader with experience
in adobe construction, Andrew W. Sublette,
then a captain under the command of Lt.
Daniel P. Woodbury at the new Fort Kearny.
Their first adobe construction was a large
storehouse, completed in November 1848. In
1849 Woodbury purchased the American Fur
Company's adobe Fort John and renamed it
Fort Laramie. By 1852 a number of new adobe
buildings had been constructed at the post.
Other forts were eventually constructed, in
whole or in part, of adobe all over the region.</p>

<p>The final waves of earthen construction
appeared quite independent of the earlier
ones. Foremost among the European builders
were Black Sea Germans. During their threegeneration
stay on the steppes of Russia they
learned the local building methods, including
the manufacture of <hi rend="italic">kohlsteine</hi>, or sun-dried
bricks (called <hi rend="italic">batsa</hi> in South Dakota), puddled
clay, and rammed-earth techniques. Earthen
construction was introduced wherever Black
Sea Germans settled, from Kansas to North
Dakota. Mennonites in Marion County, Kansas,
used both clay brick and rammed earth,
while puddled clay, clay lumps, and rock-filled
rammed earth were also used in the North and
South Dakota settlements.</p>

<p>Other major introductions were made by
Czechs and Poles. The five-room Polish house
constructed in 1882 by Mary Zwfka Roschynialski
in Sherman County, Nebraska, was
built of puddled clay. The Czech structures
were located in South Dakota and Nebraska
and were of sun-dried brick, rammed earth,
and puddled clay (hlin&#234;n&#253;). Other immigrants
also used clay technologies, including Germans
and Danes. In North Dakota Ukrainians
introduced post-and-earth construction, a
form similar to wattle and daub. This technology
included wattle&#8211;or lathe&#8211;between
earth-fast posts, with packed clay between the
lathes in a kind of rammed-earth fashion, before
finishing with clay plaster both inside
and out.</p>

<p>The last introduction of earthen building
emanated again from the Hispanic Southwest,
with the early-twentieth-century immigration
of Latinos from Mexico, New Mexico, and
Texas to the west-central High Plains of Nebraska
and Colorado. Their first adobe dwellings
were of the familiar flat-roofed variety,
with projecting vigas, while later houses were
built with the gabled roofs common to the
host culture. Large hoppers rather than pits
were used to mix the clay.</p>

<p>emanated again from the Hispanic Southwest,
with the early-twentieth-century immigration
of Latinos from Mexico, New Mexico, and
Texas to the west-central High Plains of Nebraska
and Colorado. Their first adobe dwellings
were of the familiar flat-roofed variety,
with projecting vigas, while later houses were
built with the gabled roofs common to the
host culture. Large hoppers rather than pits
were used to mix the clay.</p>

<closer>
<signed>David Murphy<lb/>
Nebraska State Historical Society</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Koop, Michael H., and Stephen Ludwig. <title level="m">German-Russian Folk Architecture in Southeastern South Dakota</title>. Vermillion:
South Dakota State Historical Preservation Center,
1984.</bibl> <bibl>Murphy, David. "Building in Clay on the Central
Plains." In <title level="m">Perspectives in Vernacular Architecture</title>, edited
by Thomas Carter and Bernard L. Herman. Columbia:
University of Missouri Press for the Vernacular Architecture
Forum, 1989: 3: 74–85.</bibl> <bibl>Valdez, Anthony Arnold. "Hispanic
Vernacular Architecture and Settlement Pattern of
the Culebra River Villages of Southern Colorado (1850–
1950)." Master's thesis, University of New Mexico, Albuquerque,
1992.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>