<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ea.015">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Henday, Anthony (1725-?)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Barbara Belyea</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ea.015</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Belyea, Barbara">Barbara Belyea</author>. <title level="a">"Henday, Anthony (1725-?)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">234-235</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-04</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">HENDAY, ANTHONY (1725-?)</head>

<p>Anthony Henday, the younger son of a farm
family on the Isle of Wight, is said to have
been outlawed for smuggling (a common occupation
on the island) before he signed with
the Hudson's Bay Company in 1750. For several
years he worked as a common laborer at
York Factory, then volunteered to travel inland
from the bay with a Native band from the
Saskatchewan River. James Isham, the chief
factor, based his plan of sending company employees
to winter inland on the journeys of
Henry Kelsey and William Stewart; he saw this
practice of wintering as a response to the British
government's demand for exploration as
well as to French commercial rivalry west of
Lake Winnipeg. After his first trip inland,
Henday worked as a netmaker and then returned
to the Saskatchewan River in 1759–60.
For the next two years, serving at York Factory
and its satellite Severn House, Henday was occasionally
given greater responsibility. When
the company refused the salary he demanded,
Henday claimed his back pay and left the service.
Nothing more is known of him.</p>

<p>Henday is remembered for his first trip inland.
He left York Factory on June 26, 1754,
equipped with a small consignment of trade
goods, a supply of paper, and a "boat compass"
by which he was to determine his route.
When he set out Henday knew nothing of canoe
travel, nor could he speak the language
of his companions. Even so, he managed the
arduous tracking and portaging necessary to
reach the Saskatchewan River, where the canoes
were abandoned and they met the rest of
the band. Henday joined a "family," or tenting
group, including a woman referred to as his
"bedfellow." Henday's journal describes his
acculturation to this Plains band, his growing
skill at hunting, his pleasure at feasts. At the
same time, he fretted that his companions refused
to hunt more animals than were needed
for their own use.</p>

<p>Isham considered the purpose of Henday's
trip inland to have been fulfilled when the
young man met with leaders of the "Archithinues,"
Natives who did not trade at the
Hudson Bay forts and whose language was
unfamiliar. In one version of his journal, Henday
persuaded them to make the long journey
east; in another version the Archithinue chiefs
answered him that they could not paddle, or
eat fish, or leave the buffalo. After a winter
spent "pitch[ing] too &amp; fro to Get furrs and
provisions," Henday's band assembled on a
riverbank, built canoes, and paddled down to
Hudson Bay. They arrived at York Factory on
June 23, 1755.</p>

<p>Presumably Henday brought with him a
journal of his year inland and a map of the
region he had visited. Neither document has
survived. Four copies of the journal are extant,
three of them copied by Andrew Graham,
the clerk at York Factory, and a fourth
made for Graham by an unknown copyist.
The earliest copy, sent to the London Committee
of Hudson's Bay Company a few weeks
after Henday's return, reports that he had success
in urging the Archithinues to trade and
in preventing his companions from exchanging
their best furs at French posts along the
Saskatchewan River. The other three copies
are found in Andrew Graham's compilation of
his memoirs and other documents, written
and rewritten over a period of thirty years
and called "Observations on Hudson's Bay." In
Graham's "Observations," Henday cannot
persuade the Archithinues to trade, nor can he
prevent the band he has wintered with from
trading at the French posts. Other problems
presented by the four extant texts are discrepancies
in the courses and distances that
chart Henday's route, and in the designation
of landmarks he noted along the way.</p>

<p>Henday's journal was published in 1907 as
an article in <title level="j">Transactions of the Royal Society of Canada</title>. The text was the last of Graham's
copies in the "Observations"&#8211;a text that the
editor never saw, copying as he did a late-nineteenth-
century copy of Graham's copy of
Henday's holograph. Gradually the other surviving
texts came to light: by 1931 three were
known to exist, and in 1968 a fourth was
found in the company archives. Nevertheless,
historians and anthropologists continued to
rely on the <title level="j">Transactions</title> text and to draw inferences
from its all-too-vague statements. By
1969 the accepted story was as follows: Henday
traveled with some Crees from the Saskatchewan
watershed up to The Pas, Manitoba, then
across to the Battle River to his meeting with
Blackfoot leaders south of Red Deer, Alberta.
After viewing the Rocky Mountains from a
nearby hill, Henday's Crees drifted north to
the Beaver Hills east of Edmonton, Alberta,
and built canoes on a bank of the North Saskatchewan
River. When the ice broke up, they
returned to York Factory after passing two
French forts on the Saskatchewan River.</p>

<p>However, if all four texts are considered and
wishful inferences are rigorously excluded, no
consistent account of Henday's movements or
activities is possible. The four extant texts are
rife with differences and contradictions that
no honest, scholarly treatment can rationalize
or reconcile. Exactly where Henday went,
whom he met, and what trading success he
had must remain at best uncertain and on
most points unknown. His journal is an enduring
puzzle, a lesson in the textual limits of
historical research.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">INDUSTRY</hi>: <ref n="egp.ind.029">Hudson's Bay Company</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Barbara Belyea<lb/>
University of Calgary</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Barbara Belyea, ed. <title level="m">A Year Inland: The Journal of a Hudson's Bay Company Winterer</title>. Waterloo, Ontario: Wilfrid
Laurier University Press, 2000.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>