<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.tra.029">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Railways, Canada</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Ted D. Regehr</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.tra.029</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Regehr, Ted D.">Ted D. Regehr</author>. <title level="a">"Railroads, Canada."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">808-809</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-22</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">RAILWAYS, CANADA</head>

<p>Railways provided absolutely essential economic
and commercial transportation and
auxiliary services for all Prairie people during
the pioneer settlement period, and they remain
one of the most important components
of the region's economic infrastructure. They
not only provided basic transportation services
but also influenced and shaped many
other aspects of Prairie life.</p>

<p>The first railway in western Canada was
opened for tra.c in 1878. It was a short government-built
line from Winnipeg to the U.S.
border, where it connected with American
railroads to Duluth, Minnesota. From Duluth,
Canadian traffic was carried by lake steamers
to Ontario ports. That first railway was part of
a cautious scheme that used water transport
on rivers and lakes, wherever possible, with
rail links where needed. A much more ambitious
all-rail transcontinental scheme had
been proposed. It went down in scandal in
1873 but was revived in 1880. The Conservative
government elected in 1878 provided substantial
cash and land subsidies and turned over all
of its surveys and the rail links already built,
including the little Manitoba line, to a syndicate
of railway promoters who organized the
Canadian Pacific Railway Company. The Prairie
portion of the new railway was built between
1881 and 1883.</p>

<p>The railway determined the course and patterns
of settlement on the Canadian Prairies.
When the promoters, in an effort to fend off
competition from American railroads, chose a
route across the relatively arid southern Prairies
rather than a more northerly route through the
fertile and already partially settled parklands,
new settlers took up homesteads or bought
railway land close to the tracks. Those living
farther north were served by north.south
branch lines from Regina to Prince Albert and
from Calgary to Edmonton, which were built
in the late 1880s and early 1890s. Thousands of
new towns and villages were created. Older
ones served by the railway prospered; those
bypassed by the railway languished, or, in a few
cases, the buildings of bypassed towns were
moved to new locations adjacent to the railway.
Town sites were laid out approximately
eight or ten miles apart, that being the distance
it was thought farmers could haul a load of
grain and return home the same day if the
primitive dirt roads and trails were in good
condition. Farmers farther away from the railway
and those traveling in inclement weather
faced sharply increased costs and frustrations.</p>

<p>Two political and economic issues.freight
rates and branch lines.dominated early railway
history on the Canadian Prairies. Freight
rates in western Canada were higher than in
eastern Canada or in the United States. Canadian
Pacific officials insisted this was necessary
because they had built and were operating
an expensive 1,000-mile line north of Lake
Superior and another 600-mile line across the
Rockies. Neither generated appreciable local
traffic. In eastern Canada freight rates had to
be set to meet competition by water carriers
and rival American railroads. On the Prairies
effective measures were taken to keep out rival
American railroads, and rates were then set to
pay for the costs of carrying traffic to and
from western Canada, including the operating
costs of the unproductive Lake Superior and
mountain sections. Vehement protests resulted
in modest rate reductions in the late
1880s, followed by an agreement in 1897, under
the terms of which the Canadian Pacific
agreed to more substantial rate cuts in return
for federal financial assistance to build a major
branch line through the Crow's Nest Pass
in southern British Columbia.</p>

<p>There were also persistent complaints about
lack of adequate service for farmers far removed
from the railway's main line. They demanded
construction of branch lines. Railway
officials argued that remote and sparsely settled
areas did not generate su.cient traffic to
justify construction of a branch line railway.
Settlers responded with claims that growth was
impossible until a region had rail service.</p>

<p>The resulting frustrations led to demands
for railway competition. In 1895 two former
Canadian Pacific contractors built a small,
competitive branch line in Manitoba with government
financial assistance. They gradually
expanded their railway until, in 1901, the Manitoba
government agreed to provide financial
help if the contractors would build a railway
from Winnipeg to Lake Superior that would
compete directly with the Canadian Pacific.
The ambitious contractors, who had in the
meantime reorganized their railway as the Canadian
Northern Railway, built and operated
the new line as cheaply as possible but drastically
reduced freight rates and continued to
expand their lines with further government
assistance. The federal government tried, with
limited success, to regulate freight rates and
other railway operations when it established
the Board of Railway Commissioners in 1903.</p>

<p>The rapid settlement of the Canadian Prairies
after 1900 prompted Canadafs oldest and
largest railway, the Grand Trunk Railway, to
expand westward. The railway tried first to
acquire the economically weak but politically
popular Canadian Northern Railway. Failure
to provide assurances that it would carry
freight at Canadian Northern rates scuttled
Grand Trunk efforts to take over the Canadian
Northern. Instead, the Grand Trunk sought
and obtained federal and provincial assistance
to build its own railway across the Prairies. A
frenzy of railway construction by the Canadian
Pacific, Canadian Northern, and Grand
Trunk Railways followed. Thousands of miles
of new rail lines were built on the Prairies.
Many, however, were located in ways designed
to injure competitors rather than to provide
the broadest possible coverage. The result was
wasteful crowding of new lines in some areas
and neglect of other more remote regions.
Even more disastrous was the decision of the
managers of both the Canadian Northern and
Grand Trunk Railways to build or make arrangements
to expand their systems from
coast to coast, including new lines north of
Lake Superior and across the Rockies.</p>

<p>Rumors and threats of war after 1911 and
then the actual outbreak of war in 1914 resulted
in financial crises and inflated costs that
pushed the new and as yet incomplete transcontinental
railways to the edge of bankruptcy.
They were only rescued when the federal government
nationalized the Grand Trunk and
Canadian Northern systems and amalgamated
them with other government-owned railways
to form Canadian National Railways. There
was new construction in the 1920s, particularly
on the Prairies, to integrate previously competitive
Canadian Northern and Grand Trunk
lines into a single system capable of competing
with the privately owned Canadian Pacific.
Neither system prospered in the dismal conditions
of the 1930s. The Canadian Pacific, with
its very low debt charges, survived, and the
federal government paid most of Canadian
National’s much heavier debt charges inherited
from its predecessor companies.</p>

<p>The railways were always much more than
merely a transportation system. They were the
harbingers of a new way of life and as such
seriously disrupted the lives of the Native and
mixed-blood peoples living on the Canadian
Prairies. They made possible extensive settlement
and the development of commercial agriculture.
As holders of large tracts of land they
influenced and on occasion dictated the nature
and progress of settlement in particular districts.
Their preference for experienced farmers,
including many from central and eastern
Europe, changed the ethnic composition of
many Prairie communities. Canadian Pacific
interest in arid land in southern Alberta resulted
in the development of massive irrigation
projects organized or assisted by the railway.
Ownership of thousands of lots in hundreds of
prospective towns along the right-of-way of
the new railways made the railways key players
in the development of towns and villages
throughout western Canada, and their large
holdings in urban real estate properties made
them a dominant force in the shaping of all
urban centers in western Canada.</p>

<p>The railways also acquired or participated
in numerous ancillary enterprises, ranging
from telegraph services to mining and lumbering
and later oil and gas ventures. Huge
land grants made them partners with the federal
government in promoting aggressive federal
immigration, homestead, and settlement
policies.</p>

<p>During the Great Depression of the 1930s
the railways in western Canada became unique
symbols of the nation’s failing economic system
as hundreds of unemployed and angry
young men moved about the country, riding
illegally on railway freight cars. About 1,800
unemployed men, riding the rails with plans to
stage a massive protest demonstration in Ottawa,
were forcibly disbanded, with considerable
violence, by the police in Regina in 1935.
But the railways also performed valuable Depression
Era services in moving animals and
settlers from the drought-stricken southern to
more northerly communities and animal fodder
and other supplies from the northern communities
southward.</p>

<p>Essential wartime services partially reestablished
the reputation of the railways. They
were, and still are, the most e.cient carriers
of bulky western Canadian export products.
They carried all manner of military supplies
and made possible massive troop movements
and the shipment of food products
from western Canada to eastern ports and to
Great Britain.</p>

<p>After the war Canadian railways faced serious
competition in their freight business as
a result of the conversion of wartime industrial
production plants to the production of,
among other items, automobiles and trucks as
well as major government initiatives in the construction
of better highways. They never recovered
from a damaging strike in 1957 during
which they lost much of their time-sensitive,
high-cost, small-volume freight to the trucking
industry. Airline competition gradually inflicted
even greater damage on the passenger
service offered by the railways in spite of a very
costly effort, particularly by the Canadian Pacific
in the late 1950s and early 1960s, to offer
the best possible passenger service on the most
modern passenger, observation, and dining
cars. Canadian, like American, railways have
abandoned or surrendered the passenger service
to independent operators&#8211;Via Rail in
Canada, Amtrak in the United States, both of
which are heavily subsidized.</p>

<p>A contentious postwar issue, particularly in
western Canada, has been the abandonment
of tens of thousands of miles of branch lines
and the decline or death of thousands of small
Prairie towns served by those branch lines.
With better road transport facilities, railway
shipping points at six- to eight-mile intervals
are no longer needed, but longer hauling distances
increase costs to farmers and divert
business from the small towns to larger centers.
Nevertheless, the railways continue to
provide an essential service in the transportation
of bulky western Canadian agricultural
and natural resource commodities to market.
The increasing importance of that business is,
perhaps, most clearly demonstrated by the
move in the 1990s of Canadian Pacific headquarters
from Montreal to Calgary.</p>

<p>The Canadian railway system was an essential
building block in the development of Prairie
society and in the integration of the trade
of the Canadian Prairies with other parts of
Canada. Passage of the North American Free
Trade Agreement has resulted in the flow of
more western Canadian tra.c southward,
and the major Canadian railways have acquired
or strengthened their links with vital
American railroads, but on the Canadian
Prairies they continue to provide essential
economic services.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">EUROPEAN AMERICANS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ea.032">Settlement Patterns, Canada</ref> /
<hi rend="smallcaps">INDUSTRY</hi>: <ref n="egp.ind.010">Canadian Pacific Railway</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">PROTEST AND DISSENT</hi>: <ref n="egp.pd.043">On-to-Ottawa Trek</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Ted D. Regehr<lb/>
University of Saskatchewan and University of Calgary</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Eagle, John A. <title level="m">The Canadian Pacific Railway and the Development
of Western Canada</title>. Montreal: McGill-Queen's
University Press, 1989.</bibl> <bibl>Lamb, W. Kaye. <title level="m">History of the Canadian
Pacific Railway</title>. New York: Macmillan Publishing
Company, 1977.</bibl> <bibl>Regehr, T. D. <title level="m">The Canadian Northern
Railway: Pioneer Road of the Northern Prairies, 1895–1918</title>.
Toronto: Macmillan Publishing Company, 1976.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>