<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.lt.010">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Children's Literature</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Susanne George</author>
<author>Susan Naramore Maher</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.lt.010</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="George, Susanne">Susanne George</author> and <author n="Maher, Susan Naramore">Susan Naramore Maher</author>. <title level="a">"Children's Literature."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">476</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-23</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">CHILDREN'S LITERATURE</head>

<p>The most realistic children's literature about
the Plains during the settlement period and
into the 1920s can be found in family periodicals.
Popular magazines such as <title level="j">St. Nicholas</title>
and weekly newspapers like the <title level="j">Youth's Companion</title>
highlighted the sense of adventure to
be discovered on the Plains frontier as well as
the uniqueness of the various Native American
cultures.</p>

<p>Although these periodicals published works
by well-known writers of the era, a large percentage
of the stories were by lesser-known
writers such as Kate M. Cleary, Elia Peattie, and
William R. Lighton, who wrote fiction about
Nebraska; Charles Askins, John R. Spears, Elizabeth
Grinnell, and G. W. Ogden, who set their
stories in Kansas and Oklahoma; L. Frank
Baum and Franklin Welles Calkins, whose stories
depict Wyoming and the Dakotas; and Canadian
writers Nellie McClung and Edward
McTavish, whose tales center on Manitoba,
and Rev. Charles W. Gordon (aka Ralph Connor),
whose best-selling fiction represents life
in Saskatchewan. Many authors contributed
only one story, usually based on personal accounts
of Plains life. Serials were especially
popular, like <title level="m">The Little Squatters</title> by Hamlin
Garland, <title level="m">The Boy Settlers</title> by Noah Brooks, and
<title level="m">A Banker's Judgment</title> by Marianne Gauss.</p>

<p>The typical pattern in the stories of Plains
settlement is of an initiation, beginning with a
physical and emotional separation as the children
withdraw into an unknown and often
hostile environment. The innocent pioneer
versus the complex frontier forms the conflict.
Although the stories about boys reaching
manhood have various plots and settings, the
boys' tasks are mainly physical tests. Stereotypically,
the girls achieve a moral rather than
physical triumph.</p>

<p>Though strongly informed by this earlier
tradition, children's literature of the Plains
published since the 1930s has all but eclipsed
these periodical writers. In 1932 Laura Ingalls
Wilder, with the help of her daughter, Rose
Wilder Lane, published <title level="m">Little House in the Big Woods</title>, commencing a family saga now
known collectively as the Little House books.
The genius of Wilder's vision is its blending of
adventure and domestic realism, its positing
of a feisty, tomboy heroine, Laura, against the
ameliorating influence of her gentle sister,
Mary, and her firm-handed mother, Caroline.
Along the way, readers receive moral lessons,
learn songs, poems, and recipes, and gain an
understanding of schooling, farming, and
town building on the Plains during the late
nineteenth century. Wilder's series provided
a narrative pattern for many other children's
writers of the Plains, including Carol Ryrie
Brink (<title level="m">Caddie Woodlawn</title> and <title level="m">Magical Melons</title>),
Lois Lenski (<title level="m">Prairie School</title>), Barbara Smucker
(<title level="m">Days of Terror</title>), Patricia MacLachlan (<title level="m">Sarah Plain and Tall</title>), Pam Conrad (<title level="m">Prairie Songs</title>,
<title level="m">Prairie Visions</title>, and <title level="m">My Daniel</title>), Laurie Lawlor
(the Addie series), Celia Barker Lottridge
(<title level="m">Ticket to Curlew</title>), Kathryn Lasky (<title level="m">The Bone Wars</title>), Cecil Freeman Beeler (<title level="m">The Girl in the Well</title>), and Charlene Joy Talbot (<title level="m">An Orphan for Nebraska</title>). Adventure writers like Texan Fred
Gipson (<title level="m">Old Yeller</title>) continue the tradition of
the male initiation story, yet even Gipson's classic
novel centers its dramatic plot around the
stability of home and a strong mother figure.</p>

<p>Though the history of settlement preoccupies
children's writers of the Plains, a number
of other significant genres emerged in the
twentieth century. In particular, this literature
has attempted to provide a more accurate and
humane depiction of Plains tribes than found
in many settlement novels. Native and non-
Native writers alike have worked to replace
stereotypes and misrepresentations of Native
American life with truthful, unedited retellings
of oral tales and balanced portraits of life
in biographies and fiction. Mari Sandoz (<title level="m">The Horsecatcher</title>, <title level="m">The Story Catcher</title>), Virginia
Driving Hawk Sneve (<title level="m">Betrayed</title>, <title level="m">When Thunders Speak</title>), Maria Campbell (<title level="m">People of the Buffalo</title>), and Paul Goble (<title level="m">The Girl Who Loved Wild Horses</title>) have added immeasurably to
children's appreciation of Native American/
First Nations history, oral storytelling, and art.</p>

<p>Some Plains children's writers focus on
contemporary life with all its attendant problems
and challenges. In 1967 Oklahoma writer
S. E. Hinton changed the course of contemporary
young adult literature with her gritty first
novel, <title level="m">The Outsiders</title>. Ivy Ruckman's bestselling
<title level="m">Night of the Twisters</title> re-creates modern
Grand Island, Nebraska, during the hours of a
natural disaster. To this day, literary realism
defines children's literature of the Plains. Even
the Oz stories of the great fantasist L. Frank
Baum bear the imprint of realism. However,
Native American writers for children are now
adding the fabric of vision, myth, and legend
to this tradition of realism, countering European
American myths of settlement and creating
new narrative patterns inspired by oral
storytelling.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Susanne George<lb/>
University of Nebraska at Kearney<lb/>
Susan Naramore Maher<lb/>
University of Nebraska at Omaha</signed>
</closer>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>