<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ea.005">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Coronado (ca. 1510-1554)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Ralph H. Vigil</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ea.005</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Vigil, Ralph H.">Ralph H. Vigil</author>. <title level="a">"Coronado (ca. 1510-1554)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">227-228</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-02</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">CORONADO (ca. 1510-1554)</head>

<p>Francisco Vásquez de Coronado explored the
American Southwest and the Great Plains
from 1540 to 1542. As a younger son born into
a family of the lesser nobility in Salamanca,
Spain, Coronado was given a limited portion
of the family estate by the laws of primogeniture
and entail. Seeking to improve his fortune,
this poor gentleman joined the retinue
of Antonio de Mendoza, New Spain's first
viceroy. Shortly after his arrival in Mexico City
in 1535, Coronado married Doña Beatriz, one
of five daughters of Alonso de Estrada, treasurer
and governor of the colony in the 1520s
and reputed to be the illegitimate son of Ferdinand
II of Aragon (1479–1516). Coronado's
marriage elevated his social status and allowed
him to enjoy half the tribute of the Indians of
the town and province of Tlapa, granted to the
couple by his wealthy mother-in-law. Favored
by the viceroy, Coronado became a member
of the municipal council of Mexico City before
being appointed governor of the northwestern
province of Nueva Galicia in 1538.</p>

<p>From the time of Columbus's discovery, the
impulse for exploration was grounded in mistaken
medieval geographical theory and legendary
tales of rich kingdoms. The search
led by Coronado for the gold of the Seven
Cities of Cíbola and Quivira had its origins in
European legend, a tall tale told by an Indian
in Mexico, and the disastrous expedition led
by P&#225;nfilo de Narv&#225;ez to Florida in 1528. When
four survivors of the Narv&#225;ez expedition arrived
on the northern frontier of Nueva Galicia,
their tale of adventure and subsequent
report to Viceroy Mendoza set the stage for
the Coronado expedition.</p>

<p>The desire of the Franciscan order to peacefully
convert the Indians of the north and the
dream of finding "another Mexico" by the
conquistadors led to at least two reconnoitering
expeditions by Franciscan friars. The alleged
discovery of Cíbola by Fray Marcos de
Niza, who described the humble Zu&#241;i village
of Hawikuh as a city of fine appearance larger
than Mexico City, persuaded the viceroy to
send Coronado north with an army of 300
Spaniards and some 800 Indians on February
4, 1540. Fray Marcos acted as chief guide but
returned to Mexico after C&#237;bola was reached
and proved to be a crowded little village lacking
wealth.</p>

<p>After choosing winter quarters on the Rio
Grande, the Spaniards met an Indian slave at
Pecos who told them of large settlements to
the east rich in gold and silver. In the spring of
1541 this Indian, called the Turk, led the expedition
on a fruitless quest into the Great
Plains. Coronado reached Golden Quivira in
the vicinity of Great Bend, Kansas, only to
find a Wichita Indian village of grass lodges.
After wintering in New Mexico, Coronado,
disillusioned, in ill health, and 50,000 ducats
poorer, led the disappointed army back to
New Spain. After being replaced as governor
of Nueva Galicia in 1544, Coronado returned
to Mexico City, where he acted as councilman
until his death.</p>

<p>Coronado's quest for golden kingdoms was
a failure, but his journey through the present
states of Arizona and New Mexico, the Texas
Panhandle, and the Great Plains of Oklahoma
and Kansas gave the European world
geographical knowledge of these hitherto
unknown regions. Moreover, reports of the
expedition described the way of life of the sedentary
and hunting tribes the Spaniards encountered
and the flora and fauna seen in that
country. Further, the fantasy of Quivira persisted
and would be joined to utopian dreams
of spiritual conquest between 1542 and 1580.
The final result would be the colonization
of New Mexico and the mission system, the
chief institution responsible for the extension
of Hispanic culture onto Spain's northern
frontier.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">IMAGES AND ICONS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ii.048">Quivira</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Ralph H. Vigil<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Bolton, Herbert E. <title level="m">Coronado: Knight of Pueblos and Plains</title>.
Albuquerque: University of New Mexico Press, 1949.</bibl>
<bibl>Hammond, George P., ed. <title level="m">Narratives of the Coronado Expedition, 1540–1542</title>. Albuquerque: University of New
Mexico Press, 1940.</bibl> <bibl>Hodge, Fredrick W., ed. <title level="m">Spanish Explorers in the Southern United States, 1528–1543</title>. New York:
Barnes and Noble, Inc., 1953.</bibl>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>