<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.med.014">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main"><hi rend="italic">Dallas Morning News</hi></title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Gerald L. Grotta</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.med.014</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Grotta, Gerald L.">Gerald L. Grotta</author>. <title level="a">"<hi rend="italic">Dallas Morning News</hi>."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">510</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-03-26</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main"><hi rend="italic">DALLAS MORNING NEWS</hi></head>

<p>The <title level="j">Dallas Morning News</title> traces its roots to
the thriving port city of Galveston, where in
1842 Samuel Bangs, a publisher from Boston,
founded the <title level="j">Galveston News</title>. After the Civil
War, a Confederate colonel from North Carolina
named A. H. Belo joined <title level="j">the Galveston News</title> as bookkeeper. Belo quickly became a
full partner, and the newspaper became the
foundation of the A. H. Belo Corporation,
now one of the largest diversified media companies
in the United States.</p>

<p>In 1885 Belo told his mailroom manager,
George Bannerman Dealey, to find a place in
North Texas to start a sister publication. Dealey
chose the small town of Dallas and named the
newspaper the <title level="j">Dallas Morning News</title>. When the
<title level="j">Dallas Morning News</title> was launched in 1885, its
most serious challenge came from the far-off <title level="j">St. Louis Post-Dispatch</title>, which had a greater circulation
in Texas than any Texas newspaper. To meet
this threat, the <title level="j">Dallas Morning News</title> used a special
train to deliver copies to McKinney, Sherman,
Denison, and other towns in North and
East Texas. It also used trains to deliver copies to
Fort Worth to the west.</p>

<p>By 1906, the year the predecessor of the <title level="j">Fort Worth Star-Telegram</title> began publication, the
<title level="j">Dallas Morning News</title> had reached a circulation
of 38,000, and Dallas was soon to be
the major city in North Texas. An often-bitter
rivalry developed between Dallas and Fort
Worth. Dallas was becoming a sophisticated
metropolitan center, while Fort Worth remained
a cow town and proudly identified
itself as "Where the West Begins." While it had
some circulation in the Fort Worth area, the
<title level="j">Dallas Morning News</title> concentrated most of its
circulation efforts in the city of Dallas and
cities in the northern and eastern regions of
Texas. The <title level="j">Fort Worth Star-Telegram</title>, looking
westward, became the newspaper for all of
West Texas and into New Mexico.</p>

<p>An almost impenetrable wall grew up along
the boundary line that separates Dallas County
and Tarrant County, where Fort Worth is located.
For most of the twentieth century, the
<title level="j">Dallas Morning News</title> and the <title level="j">Fort Worth Star-Telegram</title> respected that boundary, and other
than single-copy newsstand sales, each stayed
on its own side of the county line. However, by
the 1960s the thirty-mile-wide rural area between
Dallas and Fort Worth began to explode
in industry and population. Arlington grew
almost overnight from 7,500 to more than
300,000. Several other cities in the former noman's-
land had exceeded 100,000 by the end of
the twentieth century. This led to a major circulation
war between the <title level="j">Dallas Morning News</title>
and the <title level="j">Fort Worth Star-Telegram</title>. Both coveted
the rapidly expanding population as possible
subscribers and readers. In the 1990s both
newspapers established Arlington editions
that grew into the <title level="j">Arlington Morning News</title> and
the <title level="j">Arlington Star-Telegram</title>. The circulation
battle also includes the area to the north of
Arlington known as the Mid-Cities. Most of
this disputed territory is in Tarrant County.</p>

<p>Although the <title level="j">Dallas Morning News</title> has become
one of the largest newspapers in the
country and now competes for the Plains border
country to the west, it has never approached
the influence of the <title level="j">Fort Worth Star-Telegram</title> in the West Texas and eastern New
Mexico portions of the Great Plains.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Gerald L. Grotta<lb/>
Texas Christian University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl><title level="m">A. H. Belo Corporation: Commemorating 150 Years, 1842– 1992</title>. Dallas: A. H. Belo, 1992.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>