<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ct.021">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Edmonton, Alberta</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Paul Voisey</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ct.021</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Voisey, Paul">Paul Voisey</author>. <title level="a">"Edmonton, Alberta."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">166</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-27</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">EDMONTON, ALBERTA</head>

<p>Edmonton is the capital of the province of
Alberta and the dominant urban center for
the central and northern regions of the province
and for much of Canada's Far North. In
1996 the population of the city proper stood at
616,306 and of the greater metropolitan area at
862,597.</p>

<p>The city is situated on the North Saskatchewan
River in the Parkland Belt region of the
Canadian Prairies. This strategic location
made it an attractive site for fur trading, and in
1795 the Hudson's Bay Company built the first
Fort Edmonton downstream from the present
city. The last post to bear that name was
built in 1830, by which time Edmonton had
emerged as one of the company's most important
inland depots. Following the transfer of
company territory to Canada in 1870, speculators
and merchants promoted Edmonton as a
future agricultural center, but the first trans-
Canada railway crossed the Prairies 200 miles
to the south, where the rival city of Calgary
emerged. A branch line from Calgary in 1891
failed to cross the river into Edmonton, giving
rise to the south-side upstart of Strathcona.
Few agricultural settlers reached the district,
with the result that Edmonton-Strathcona had
a population of only 4,000 by 1901.</p>

<p>The following decade brought explosive
growth. Two new transcontinental railways
reached Edmonton, and settlers swarmed into
the surrounding hinterland. Led by Frank
Oliver, an Edmonton newspaperman, politician,
and booster, the city outmaneuvered
Calgary to become the capital of the new
province of Alberta in 1905 and the site for the
University of Alberta in 1909. The construction
of a high-level railway bridge across the
river facilitated the amalgamation of Edmonton
and Strathcona in 1912. By 1916 the population
of the city had reached 54,000, but by
then rapid growth had already ended. Most of
the surrounding hinterland had been settled,
and a speculative real estate bubble burst in
1913. Recession gripped the agricultural economy
after the World War I. Although growth
and prosperity resumed in the mid-1920s, the
Great Depression soon brought the return of
hard times.</p>

<p>World War II stimulated new growth when
American money and manpower poured into
the city to launch three major wartime projects:
the Alaska Highway, which would provide
an alternate supply route to that state
safe from Japanese attack; the Canol Pipeline,
which carried petroleum from northern Canada
to Alaska; and the North-West Staging
Route, a series of northern airports constructed
to shuttle aircraft to the Soviet Union
under lend-lease. These projects gave the
city the expertise and economic base to become
a major oil service center following the
Leduc strike of 1947. While Calgary remained
the financial and corporate headquarters for
the petroleum industry, Edmonton became
more important for oil field supply, refining,
petrochemical manufacturing, and pipeline
construction.</p>

<p>Geographically, the city has sprawled in
typical North American fashion, with major
arterial roads leading to suburbs clustered
around shopping centers. The most impressive
of these, West Edmonton Mall, was completed
in stages and in 1985 became the largest
shopping center in the world. The regional
planning commission established by the province
in 1950 also encouraged the development
of satellite communities beyond the city.
These included the industrial complex at Fort
Saskatchewan, the airport center of Leduc,
and major residential communities like Sherwood
Park and St. Albert.</p>

<p>While the city attracted many newcomers
from outside the region, much of its postwar
growth also came from rural depopulation in
Alberta. Arrivals from the many ethnic settlements
in the rural hinterland ended the overwhelming
dominance of the city by people of
British origins. Symbolic of this change was
the populist mayor of Ukrainian descent, William
Hawrelak, who was elected for various
terms from the 1950s to the 1970s in spite of
corruption scandals. Since then, the city has
also attracted immigrants from the Far East
and India.</p>

<p>Although the collapse of oil prices in the
early 1980s jolted the city economically, it
recovered quickly and began to diversify. Today
there are many more industries and
information-based services unrelated to agriculture
or petroleum. In addition to its economic,
political, and educational importance,
the city is also a major cultural and recreational
center. Attractions include a symphony,
opera, theater, art galleries, space science
center, and provincial museum. Festivals
devoted to culture and recreation are held almost
continuously throughout the summer
months, including Klondike Days and the
Fringe Theater. The city also boasts superb facilities
for amateur and professional sports,
and citizens take great pride in the championship
dynasties established by the Edmonton
Grads in basketball, the Edmonton Eskimos in
football, and the Edmonton Oilers in hockey.
With its steep banks, the river valley remains
the dominant element in the city landscape,
and it features vast wilderness parks and golf
courses connected by a network of recreational
trails.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">INDUSTRY</hi>: <ref n="egp.ind.046">Petroleum, Canada</ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">MEDIA</hi>: <ref n="egp.med.016"><hi rend="italic">Edmonton Journal</hi></ref> / <hi rend="smallcaps">SPORTS AND RECREATION</hi>: <ref n="egp.sr.016">Edmonton Grads</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Paul Voisey<lb/>
University of Alberta</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Hesketh, Bob, and Frances Swyripa, eds. <title level="m">Edmonton: The Life of a City</title>. Edmonton: NeWest Press, 1995.</bibl> <bibl>MacGregor,
James G. <title level="m">Edmonton: A History</title>. Edmonton: Hurtig, 1975.</bibl>
<bibl>Smith, P. J., ed. <title level="m">Edmonton: The Emerging Metropolitan Pattern</title>. Victoria: University of Victoria, 1978.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>