<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.pg.006">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Bennett, Richard B. (1870-1947)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Louis A. Knafla</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.pg.006</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Knafla, Louis A.">Louis A. Knafla</author>. <title level="a">"Bennett, Richard B. (1870-1947)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">654-655</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-29</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">BENNETT, RICHARD B. (1870-1947)</head>

<p>Businessman, lawyer, politician, and prime
minister, Richard Bennett was born in Hopewell,
New Brunswick, on July 3, 1870, the eldest
son of five children. His father, Henry,
was a shipbuilding craftsman who drank
heavily and drove his business into bankruptcy.
His mother, a schoolmistress of strong
religious tenets, poured herself into raising
her children, of whom Richard was her favorite.
A shy and studious boy gifted with a clear
mind, superb memory, compelling voice, and
strong tenacity, he spent his childhood and
teens in school, church, and household duties.
He avoided most other children and their pastimes,
including alcohol, tobacco, games, and
sports. A devout Methodist, he focused on the
goal of living life opposite to that of his father
and bringing to his mother the success in life
he thought she deserved.</p>

<p>Bennett graduated from eighth grade at age
twelve, joined the militia, and was a teacher
from age sixteen. He entered Dalhousie Law
School at age twenty, working part-time as a
librarian to finance his studies. Called to the
bar in the year of his graduation in 1893, he
made a striking figure. Tall, lean, and fair-skinned,
and with a glib eloquence, he was
successful in court. Possessing an insatiable appetite
for current affairs and politics in Canada,
Britain, and the Empire, he ran for Chatham
city council in 1896 and won. His manager
was his youthful friend Max Aitken, the future
Lord Beaverbrook. He left office after several
months of feuding with his fellow councilors.
Later that year his law dean at Dalhousie recommended
him to Sir James Lougheed of Calgary,
who went to Chatham for a personal
interview. Bennett was offered a job as Lougheed's
law partner, and after several months of
hard negotiations, he accepted it. He saw his
future on the Prairies.</p>

<p>The young lawyer devoted his career to
fame and fortune: fame through the ballot box
and fortune through his legal practice. A strict
sabbatarian, he never joined in Prairie culture.
Uninterested in horses, farming, or ranching,
he lived a solitary, bachelor life first in boardinghouses
and later in the Palliser Hotel. He
worked twelve-hour days, six days a week.
Dressed in a stiff hat, topcoat, striped pants,
starched wing collar, and cravat, he took his
meals at the Alberta Hotel, where he entertained
clients at a separate table behind a
drawn curtain. By 1913 he was a rotund figure
who had his assistants carry his briefcase
and law books into court. Bennett became
Calgary's premier corporate lawyer. He was
legal counsel for the Canadian Pacific Railway
(<hi rend="smallcaps">CPR</hi>), the Hudson's Bay Company, the
Royal Bank, and numerous insurance companies.
He also made a fortune buying <hi rend="smallcaps">CPR</hi>
land and selling it to out-of-town investors. He
brought Max Aitken out west and with him
created monopolies in grain elevators, electric
utilities, and cement. Sitting on corporate directorates
and participating in joint ventures,
he became president of Calgary Power and a
major investor in the Alberta-Pacific Grain
Company and Canada Cement. By 1914 he was
one of the wealthiest men in the Canadian
Prairies.</p>

<p>Bennett had a clear view of his adopted land.
He saw its economic potential as unlimited:
grains, meats, hydroelectric power, oil and gas,
mining, transportation, and settlement. The
Canadian Prairies were seen as Britain's hinterland,
a place where British culture could flourish
in the new industrial world, serving as a
counterbalance to the economic power of the
American Plains. He saw himself as the conduit
between eastern Canadian and British
bankers and investors and the development of
an industrial, and imperial, Prairie economy.
Thus, he was a strong proponent of the British
Empire, preferential tariffs, and British foreign
policy. He went into politics to develop these
ideas. A Conservative, he was elected for Calgary
to the territorial assembly in 1898, to the
provincial legislature in 1909, and to the Dominion
Parliament in 1911. His great lament
was World War I, which split the Empire and
brought a depression from which the Prairies
would never recover in his lifetime.</p>

<p>The 1920s were a period of transition in
Bennett's life. He split in anger with his law
partner Lougheed in 1921, lost several elections,
and considered moving to Britain. But
after he won the seat of Calgary West in 1925,
his career turned from law and business to
politics and from the Prairies to Ottawa. He
became the leader of Canada's Conservative
Party in 1927 and prime minister in the election
of 1930. He promised aggressive and progressive
action, but he could not convert his
ideas into legislation. Indecisive, he was unable
to gain the confidence of the people or to
understand from his hotel suite how they saw
the world. Bennett became isolated in his own
party by 1934, and his party was defeated in
the election of October 1935.</p>

<p>His vision of the Prairies, however, still captured
the minds of most of his constituents,
who continued to vote for him. In these later
years he was one of the major philanthropists
of Prairie society. But embittered by the belief
that his country did not appreciate him, in
1939 he bought the Mickleham estate in Surrey,
England, and moved there. Supported by
his friend Max, now Lord Beaverbrook, his
wealth and political beliefs brought him the
title of viscount in 1941. He died at his estate
on June 26, 1947, of heart failure.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">LAW</hi>: <ref n="egp.law.028">Lougheed, James</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Louis A. Knafla<lb/>
University of Calgary</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Bennett Papers. National Archives of Canada, Ottawa, and
Glenbow-Alberta Institute, Calgary.</bibl> <bibl>Gray, James H. <title level="m">R. B.
Bennett: The Calgary Years</title>. Toronto: University of Toronto
Press, 1991.</bibl> <bibl>Knafla, Louis A. "Richard 'Bonfire' Bennett:
The Legal Practice of a Prairie Corporate Lawyer,
1898 to 1913." In <title level="m">Beyond the Law: Lawyers and Business in
Canada, 1830 to 1930</title>, edited by Carol Wilton. Toronto:
Osgoode Society, 1990: 320–76.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>