<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.pe.013">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Blizzards</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Kenneth F. Dewey</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.pe.013</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Dewey, Kenneth F.">Kenneth F. Dewey</author>. <title level="a">"Blizzards."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">623</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-04-22</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">BLIZZARDS</head>
<figure n="egp.pe.013" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Image: "Song of the Great Blizzard 1888 'Thirteen Were Saved' or 'Nebraska's Fearless Maid' Song and Chorus by Wm. Vincent, published by Lyon &amp; Healy, Chicago"</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>The climate of the Great Plains region is punctuated
with extreme variation in both temperature
and precipitation, and one of these
extreme weather events is the blizzard. A blizzard
is a storm with sustained winds in excess
of thirty-five miles per hour, temperatures below
20&#186;F, and blowing or falling snow that
reduces visibility to less than a quarter mile.</p>

<p>Although most common in winter, Plains
blizzards also occur in autumn and spring.
The meteorological "stage" is set when a mass
of cold polar air moves rapidly southward
from higher latitudes and encounters a strong
northward flow of moist tropical air from
lower latitudes. When a low-pressure cell encounters
the energy difference between these
two unlike air masses, it rapidly grows in
strength, becoming a "deepening low." As the
low-pressure cell strengthens, it feeds itself by
pulling southward even greater amounts of
cold air and northward even larger amounts
of warm air and moisture. By the time the
blizzard reaches full intensity, it is not unusual
to have severe thunderstorms and tornadoes
across the southern portion of this major
storm. Snowfalls often exceed 1&#189; feet just
north of the path of the low, and wind chill
temperatures drop to life-threatening levels
across the northern portion of the storm. The
winds pack the snow, making it extremely difficult
to walk through and to remove from
driveways and sidewalks. Although urban
highways are usually opened within a day or
so of a blizzard, rural roads often remain impassible
for many days.</p>

<p>Blizzards have, on rare occasion, occurred
as far south as northern Texas, but they increase
in frequency northward up the Great
Plains. Nebraska, for example, averages one to
two blizzards per year while the southern
parts of the Prairie Provinces average from
three to five blizzards per year. The climate
history of the Great Plains is replete with stories
of blizzards, but two storms stand out.
Most legendary is the "Blizzard of '88," which
occurred in January 1888. The region from
Texas to Alberta was affected by this paralyzing
storm. The suddenness of the blizzard
conditions resulted in many people losing
their lives as they traveled even short distances
to their homes. The blizzard of January 1975,
called the "blizzard of the century," struck the
Plains from Kansas to Manitoba. This blizzard
was so fierce that it set all-time record lowpressure
values for the region.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">FOLKWAYS</hi>: <ref n="egp.fol.004">Blizzard Stories</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Kenneth F. Dewey<lb/>
University of Nebraska-Lincoln</signed>
</closer>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>