<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY egp.fol.007 SYSTEM "egp.fol.007.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fol.007">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Cowboy Crafts</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Timothy H. Evans</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2009</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fol.007</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2009</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2009 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Evans, Timothy H.">Timothy H. Evans</author>. <title level="a">"Cowboy Crafts."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">293-294</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-16</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">COWBOY CRAFTS</head>

<figure n="egp.fol.007" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Saddlemaker John King of King's Saddlery, Sheridan, Wyoming</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>"Cowboy crafts" refers to a group of traditional
crafts associated with cowboys and
ranchers. Historically, the tools of the cowboy&#8211;
saddles, bridles, bits, quirts, chaps,
boots, hats, branding irons, and other objects&#8211;
were handmade by cowboys, saddlemakers,
or specialized craftsmen working out
of saddle shops. Many still are, although massproduced
goods now dominate the lower price
ranges.</p>

<p>Most cowboy crafts have roots in the <hi rend="italic">vaquero</hi>
traditions that emerged in Mexico in the
sixteenth century as adaptations of Spanish
and Moorish horse culture. As American imperialism
brought northern Mexico into the
United States in the 1840s, much of the occupational
lore of vaqueros was adopted by
American ranchers. This included techniques
for handling horses, cattle and sheep, the construction
and layout of ranches, and occupational
folk speech, as well as cowboy crafts.
As the ranching industry spread north from
Texas and the Southwest during the nineteenth
century, all of these traditions spread
with it. Most of them continue in altered and
localized forms to the present day.</p>

<p>Although many of the simpler crafts (and
repairs) are carried out by cowboys in their
spare time, the center of cowboy crafts has
always been the saddle shop. Large saddle
shops existed in Mexico by the sixteenth century,
employing many saddle- and harness
makers, leather carvers, apprentices, and specialists
in related crafts such as silver engraving.
All saddles and other products produced
in a shop bore its stamp, no matter who actually
did the work. This atelier system still exists
in large saddle shops throughout Mexico, the
United States, and Canada. In addition, cowboys
and others sell crafts to the shop or work
on consignment.</p>

<p>The western stock saddle is the predominant
saddle type in the Great Plains and
throughout the West. Much larger and heavier
than the English saddle, it is a specialized piece
of occupational equipment, meant for extended
periods of heavy riding and for cattle
herding and roping. Its origins can be traced
to the Mexican vaquero saddle of the 1700s.
It has large skirts, a deep seat, and a horn
for roping. It is a complicated and timeconsuming
object to put together, consisting
of sixty or more parts and requiring dozens of
specialized tools.</p>

<p>By the mid- to late nineteenth century, the
western stock saddle had developed regional
variations throughout the American West,
most notably in Texas, California, and the
Great Basin. Texas saddles were larger and
heavier than other western saddles: skirts were
large, heavy, square, and lined with sheepskin,
and riggings (the assemblage of hardware,
straps, and cinches that holds the saddle on
the back of the horse) were doubled, having
both front and rear cinches. With the settlement
of the Northern Plains, a distinct variant
developed that resembled Texas saddles but
with a lower and sturdier horn, a higher seat,
and a projecting rim on the cantle known as a
Cheyenne roll. In the twentieth century, regional
variations in saddle form became less
important, while many specialized forms of
rodeo and show saddles developed.</p>

<p>The decoration of leather has always been
integral to the saddlemaker's craft. This includes
the carving and stamping of leather, as
well as the use of engraved silver and other
minor aspects such as lacing and quilting.
Great Plains saddles have generally relied less
on silver and more on leather carving than
saddles from farther west. Leatherwork patterns
vary from basketwork and other geometric
designs to intricately carved flowers,
wildlife, or scenes of rodeos and ranch life.
Fancy carved saddles for use by wealthy
ranchers or in parades go back to the seventeenth
century, but in the twentieth century
became more abundant, commissioned for
Hollywood stars or as rodeo trophies. Since
the 1950s, Sheridan, Wyoming, and other centers
of the craft have specialized in highly decorated
"art" saddles and produce a variety
of intricately carved leather items, such as
briefcases and photo albums. At the same
time, many saddlemakers continue to produce
less-expensive custom saddles for working
cowboys.</p>

<p>After saddles, bits and spurs are the most
prestigious cowboy craft. Like saddles, they are
generally made by specialists. Also like saddles,
their roots lie in eighteenth-century Mexico,
and variations developed as they diffused in
the nineteenth century into the American
West. In general, bits and spurs in the Great
Plains were simpler and less decorated than
those farther west. Modern bit and spur makers,
like saddlemakers, compete with factory
goods but continue to thrive, producing highly
polished and elaborately engraved silverplated
art objects, as well as undecorated bits
and spurs for everyday use.</p>

<p>Although some other cowboy crafts are
made by specialists&#8211;for example, hats and
boots&#8211;many others are made by cowboys in
their spare time or are produced as a sideline
by full-time crafters. These include bridles,
belts, billfolds, and other smaller leather
items, often carved; soft leather items such as
chaps and leather vests; twisted ropes; ropes,
horse tack, and decorative items made from
twisted rawhide; and items made from dyed
horsehair that has been braided, twisted, or
hitched into ropes, bridles, hatbands, and
jewelry.</p>

<p>One of the most notable developments in
late-twentieth-century cowboy crafts was the
emergence of art and collectors' markets. Saddles,
spurs, and other items from prestigious
older saddle shops such as Myres of Texas,
Collins of Nebraska, and Meanea of Wyoming
command huge prices and are proudly displayed
in museums and private collections;
the same is true of well-known contemporary
shops such as King's Saddlery of Wyoming.
Along with "western" paintings, beaded moccasins
and silver mounted rifles, they are part
of a regional art market, a "taste culture" that
characterizes many museums, galleries, and
private art collections of the Great Plains and,
more generally, the West.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">IMAGES AND ICONS</hi>: <ref n="egp.ii.015">Cowboy Culture</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Timothy H. Evans<lb/>
Western Kentucky University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Dary, David. <title level="m">Cowboy Culture: A Saga of Five Centuries</title>.
New York: Alfred A. Knopf, Inc. 1981.</bibl> <bibl>Evans, Timothy H.
<title level="m">King of the Western Saddle: The Sheridan Saddle and the Art of Don King</title>. Jackson: University Press of Mississippi,
1998.</bibl> <bibl>Rice, Lee M., and Glenn R. Vernam. <title level="m">They Saddled the West</title>. Centreville <hi rend="smallcaps">MD</hi>: Cornell Maritime Press, 1975.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>