<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fil.045">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">McGuire, Dorothy (1918-2001)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Samuel J. Umland</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fil.045</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Umland, Samuel J.">Samuel J. Umland</author>. <title level="a">"McGuire, Dorothy (1918-2001)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">273</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-12</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">MCGUIRE, DOROTHY (1918-2001)</head>
<figure n="egp.fil.045" rend="granted">
<figDesc>Dorothy McGuire in a scene from "Gentleman's Agreement" (1947)</figDesc>
</figure>     

<p>Dorothy McGuire was born June 14, 1918, in
Omaha, Nebraska, where she grew up. Her
acting debut at age thirteen was on the stage of
the Omaha Community Playhouse, where she
appeared opposite Henry Fonda in <title>A Kiss for Cinderella</title>. Like Fonda, also a native Nebraskan,
Dorothy McGuire had a warm, engaging
personality, an honest, homespun sincerity
that was to characterize the roles she played
during her highly successful career.</p>

<p>She went to New York, first to work in radio
and then on Broadway, getting her start as the
understudy to Martha Scott in Thornton Wilder's
<title>Our Town</title> in 1938. She then toured with
John Barrymore in <title>My Dear Children</title> and in
1940 was the understudy to Julie Haydon in
<title>The Time of Your Life</title>. She was chosen by playwright
Rose Franken to star in the Broadway
comedy <title>Claudia</title> (1941) and in 1943 played the
role, opposite Robert Young, in David O. Selznick's
successful film version. She and Young
appeared in the sequel, Claudia and David, in
1946, by which time she had also appeared in
Elia Kazan's <title>A Tree Grows in Brooklyn</title> (1945)
and <title>The Spiral Staircase</title> (1946), a thriller
in which she played a mute servant. She was
nominated for but did not win an Academy
Award for best actress for her performance in
<title>Gentleman's Agreement</title> (1947), a film about
anti-Semitism. In 1947 she also founded the La
Jolla Playhouse with Gregory Peck and Mel
Ferrer.</p>

<p>She continued to appear in prestigious films
&#8211;the romantic comedy <title>Three Coins in the Fountain</title> (1954) and a drama about Quaker
pacifism, <title>Friendly Persuasion</title> (1956)&#8211;while
her versatility as an actress continued to garner
praise. Her appeal lay in the way she gave unglamorous,
common, hardworking women a
beauty and integrity that came from inside,
from the spirit. She starred in two classic films
by Walt Disney for precisely these reasons: <title>Old Yeller</title> (1957) and <title>Swiss Family Robinson</title> (1960)
were both about the value of family and the
difficulties of adolescence. Perhaps because her
personal life remained intensely private, her
screen persona dominated; she eventually
played the Virgin Mary in George Stevens's <title>The Greatest Story Ever Told</title> (1965), after which she
made fewer and fewer feature film appearances.</p>

<p>In 1976, after an absence of many years, she
starred in a revival of Tennessee Williams's
<title>The Night of the Iguana</title> on Broadway and also
began acting in made-for-television features.
All her appearances thereafter were in television,
the medium in which she continued to
work until the late 1980s, when she was in her
seventies. Her talent and professionalism
placed her in the upper echelon of the best
Hollywood film actresses of the century. She
died from heart failure in Santa Monica, California,
on September 13, 2001.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Samuel J. Umland<lb/>
University of Nebraska at Kearney</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Chaneles, Sol, and Albert Wolsky, eds. <title level="m">The Movie Makers</title>.
Secaucus <hi rend="smallcaps">NJ</hi>: Derbibooks, 1974.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>