<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.pd.045">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Posse Comitatus</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Leonard Weinberg</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.pd.045</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Weinberg, Leonard">Leonard Weinberg</author>. <title level="a">"Posse Comitatus."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">721-722</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-05-07</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">POSSE COMITATUS</head>

<p>This extreme right-wing group takes its name
from the Latin for "power of the county." Its
founders, Henry Beach and William Potter
Gale, were radical localists who claimed that
the county is the highest and only legitimate
level of government to which citizens owe allegiance.
it is only the county, they argue,
headed by a sheriff chosen by the community's
white male residents, that possesses the right to
enforce the law. According to Posse doctrine,
the law itself is derived from the Bible, English
common law, the Articles of Confederation,
and, more vaguely, the U.S. Constitution. In
their minds, no "Jew-dominated" legislature
or Congress has the ability to make laws that
"real, white Americans" are obliged to follow.</p>

<p>Beach, a member of the pro-Nazi Silver
Shirt movement during the 1930s, and Gale, a
former World War II army officer and a key
figure in the development of the racist and
anti-Semitic Christian Identity ideology, organized
the Posse Comitatus in Portland, Oregon,
in 1969 in the midst of the Vietnam War
and the country's racial tensions. But it was
during the mid-1970s and 1980s, and in the
Great Plains, that this loosely connected organization,
whose members sought to retain
their anonymity, achieved prominence. The
farm crisis of these years created the conditions
necessary for their doctrine to attract significant
support. Such Posse figures as Gordon
Kahl, a North Dakota farmer, James Wickstrom,
the Posse's self-proclaimed "counterinsurgency
director," and Rick Elliot, a Colorado
dairy farmer who became the publisher of the
anti-Semitic Primrose and Cattlemen's Gazette
(its message being that Jews were leading cattlemen
down the primrose path), crisscrossed
the region explaining to farmers and ranchers
why they were under no obligation to repay
overdue loans or peacefully accept the foreclosure
of their property. This appealed to some
indebted and hard-pressed farmers whose entire
way of life was in jeopardy. At "seminars"
and on country music radio stations such as
<hi rend="smallcaps">KTTL-FM</hi> in Dodge City, Kansas, Posse spokesmen
explained to their listeners that they were
under no obligation to pay income taxes to a
fraudulent Internal Revenue Service or abide by
the judgments of federal or state courts. According
to a 1976 <hi rend="smallcaps">FBI</hi> report, the Posse had seventyeight
chapters located in twenty-three states,
concentrated, for the most part, in the Great
Plains and the Midwest.</p>

<p>Some Posse figures attempted to transform
their rhetoric&#8211;about resisting the government
and cleansing the land&#8211;into reality. Violent encounters
between law enforcement officers and
Posse members attracted widespread attention.
The most notorious of these incidents&#821;it was
later made into a television film&#8211;involved Kahl,
who in 1983 shot and killed two deputies in a
dispute over his failure to pay taxes. He fled to
Arkansas, where he murdered a local sheriff
and was then himself killed in the ensuing conflict.
This was the most dramatic, but hardly
the only, episode in which Posse members
threatened or carried out violent attacks on
individuals they defined as their enemies. Although
the Posse Comitatus is not as visible
today as in the past, it continues to be an intermittently
active faction of antigovernment
protest.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Leonard Weinberg<lb/>
University of Nevada, Reno</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Corcoran, James. <title level="m">Bitter Harvest: Gordon Kahl and the
Posse Comitatus: Murder in the Heartland</title>. New York: Penguin
Books, 1990.</bibl> <bibl>George, John, and Laird Wilcox. <title level="m">American
Extremists</title>. Amherst <hi rend="smallcaps">NY</hi>: Prometheus Books, 1996.</bibl>
<bibl>Sargent, Lyman Towered, ed. <title level="m">Extremism in America</title>. New
York: New York University Press, 1995.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>