<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.fil.012">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Clift, Montgomery (1920-1966)</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Mary C. Kalfatovic</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.fil.012</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Kalfatovic, Mary C.">Mary C. Kalfatovic</author>. <title level="a">"Clift, Montgomery (1920-1966)."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">262</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-02-12</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">CLIFT, MONTGOMERY (1920-1966)</head>
<figure n="egp.fil.012" rend="granted" type="noclick">
<figDesc>Edward Montgomery Clift</figDesc>
</figure>     

<p>A major film star from the late 1940s through
the early 1960s in such widely admired movies
as <title>Red River</title> (1948), <title>A Place in the Sun</title> (1951), and <title>From Here to Eternity</title> (1953), Montgomery Clift set the standard for the new breed of
Hollywood stars who emerged in the post–
World War II era. Clift's casual attire, preference
for life in New York instead of California,
and belief that an actor owes nothing to the
public except a good performance quickly became
de rigueur attitudes for American actors
wishing to be taken seriously.</p>

<p>Clift was born Edward Montgomery Clift
in Omaha, Nebraska, on October 17, 1920.
His family had no roots in the Great Plains.
Clift's father, William, a Tennessean by birth,
served for several years as vice president of the
Omaha Trust Company. A 1921 Omaha city
directory lists the Clift family residence at 3527
Harney Street. Clift's mother, Ethel, a Philadelphian,
disliked Omaha, and when Clift was
a small child the family relocated to Chicago.
In the early 1930s they settled permanently in
New York City, where Clift's father set up a
lucrative investment counseling firm.</p>

<p>In 1934 Clift made his professional acting
debut in a summer stock production of <title>Fly Away Home</title>, a new comedy by Dorothy Bennett
and Irving White. When <title>Fly Away Home</title>
moved to Broadway in January 1935, Clift remained
in the cast and was launched on a
career as a Broadway juvenile. Broadway productions
he appeared in include <title>Jubilee</title> (1935),
a Cole Porter musical, and <title>There Shall Be No Night</title> (1940), a Pulitzer Prize–winning drama
by Robert E. Sherwood. A chronic case of
amoebic dysentery exempted Clift from military
service in World War II. Throughout the
war years Clift continued with his Broadway
career in Thornton Wilder's <title>The Skin of Our Teeth</title> (1942), Lillian Hellman's <hi rend="italic">The Searching
Wind</hi> (1944), and Elsa Shelly's <title>Foxhole in the Parlor</title> (1945). Clift's final Broadway appearance
came in the drama <title>You Touched Me!</title> by
Tennessee Williams and Donald Windham in
the fall of 1945.</p>

<p>In 1946, after having spurned earlier offers
from Hollywood due to his reluctance to sign
a long-term contract with a movie studio,
Clift accepted director Howard Hawks's offer
of a principal role in the independently produced
film <title>Red River</title>, a psychologically centered
Western about a young man (Clift) and
an older man (John Wayne) in conflict over
leadership of a cattle drive. While Red River
was entangled in legal and financial difficulties
that delayed its release, Clift went to Europe to
star in <title>The Search</title>, a low-budget semidocumentary
about an American soldier working
with displaced children in war-ravaged Germany.
Released in the spring of 1948 to laudatory
reviews, <title>The Search</title> introduced Clift to
the moviegoing public and earned him a best
actor Academy Award nomination. Finally released
in September 1948, <title>Red River</title> was a critical
and box office smash that firmly established
Clift as an important new star. Publicity
material presented Clift as the son of a Wall
Street stockbroker and rarely mentioned his
early years in Omaha. Clift considered himself
a New Yorker, and in interviews he never suggested
that his Nebraska birth had any effect
on his life or acting style.</p>

<p>In 1953 Clift earned another Academy
Award nomination for his portrayal of a sensitive
young soldier in <title>From Here to Eternity</title>.
After this Clift's career faltered because of his
extreme choosiness in regard to scripts and his
increasing problems with alcohol and prescription
drugs. Injuries suffered in a 1956 auto
accident blunted his finely turned facial features,
and he began appearing in character
parts that incorporated his now-battered appearance.
Clift's later films include <title>Suddenly Last Summer</title> (1959), <title>The Misfits</title> (1960), <title>Judgement at Nuremberg</title> (1961), and <title>Freud</title> (1962). Clift died of a coronary occlusion at his home in New York City. His final film, <title>The Defector</title>, a low-budget spy thriller, was released posthumously
in the fall of 1966.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Mary C. Kalfatovic<lb/>
Arlington, Virginia</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Bosworth, Patricia. <title level="m">Montgomery Clift: A Biography</title>. New
York: Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, 1978.</bibl> <bibl>Montgomery Clift
Papers, New York Public Library for the Performing Arts,
New York City.</bibl> <bibl>Kalfatovic, Mary C. <title level="m">Montgomery Clift: A Bio-Bibliography</title>. Westport <hi rend="smallcaps">CT</hi>: Greenwood Press, 1994.</bibl>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>