<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD TEI.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include\TEI.dtd" [
]> -->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="egp.ct.056">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Wichita Falls, Texas</title>
<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
<author>Kenneth E. Henrickson Jr.</author>
<editor>David J. Wishart</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Katherine Walter</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno>egp.ct.056</idno>
<authority>Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<date>2011</date>
<availability>
<p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note type="project">

</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl><author n="Henrickson, Jr., Kenneth E.">Kenneth E. Henrickson, Jr.</author>. <title level="a">"Wichita Falls, Texas."</title> In <editor n="Wishart, David J.">David J. Wishart</editor>, ed. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of the Great Plains</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date value="2004">2004</date>. <biblScope type="pages">188-189</biblScope>.</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-01-28</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Model Encoding</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div1>
<head type="main">WICHITA FALLS, TEXAS</head>

<p>According to tradition, the land where the city
of Wichita Falls is presently located, in southeastern
Wichita County, Texas, was acquired
in a poker game by one John A. Scott of Mississippi
in 1837. In fact, Scott acquired the tract
by purchasing Texas land certificates, which
he packed away and promptly forgot. Years
later the certificates were rediscovered by
Scott's heirs, who commissioned M. W. Seeley
to map out a town site in the tract on the
Wichita River. As platted by Seely in July 1876,
the town site included the location of a small
waterfall on the Wichita River that was later
washed away, several named streets, and a
town square. In a fanciful drawing that accompanied
the plat, Seeley also included an
imaginary lake, a steamboat on the river,
and warehouses laden with cotton and other
goods. The town never became a steamboat
shipping center, although railroads were later
very important to its development.</p>

<p>The first permanent settlers were the Barwise
family of Dallas. They first came to the
town site on an exploring trip in 1878 and
returned to stay the following year. The first
public school opened in the fall of 1880, and
the first church, First Methodist, was formally
organized in 1881. By that time, according to
various reports, there were between eight and
thirteen families living within the town site.</p>

<p>In 1881 and 1882 the residents of Wichita
Falls induced the Fort Worth and Denver Railroad,
then building tracks west out of Fort
Worth, to run its line through the town by offering
substantial property concessions along
the right-of-way. The arrival of the first train
on September 27, 1882, triggered a boom in
the sale of town lots. Also in 1882 the first
manufacturing concern, a shingle and sorghum
mill, was established along with the first
lumberyard. J. A. Kemp, later to become one
of the most prominent of the town's promoters,
arrived in 1883 and soon established a general
merchandise store. Wichita Falls became
the county seat of Wichita County in November
1883.</p>

<p>The city of Wichita Falls was officially incorporated
on July 29, 1889. Soon the economy
was stimulated by the arrival of more
railroads, making the town a transportation
and supply center for northwest Texas and
southern Oklahoma. By 1890 the population
was 1,987, and as the town continued to grow
its leaders recognized the need for a reliable
water supply. The Lake Wichita project was
completed in 1891. It remained the primary
source of water for drinking and irrigation as
well as a major recreation site until the 1920s.
Lake Kemp was added during the twenties,
followed by Lake Kickapoo in 1947 and Lake
Diversion in 1960. Currently, the primary water
supply comes from Lake Arrowhead, constructed
in 1966.</p>

<p>By 1907 the population of Wichita Falls was
5,055, and the economy was firmly based upon
railroads. The infrastructure was also growing:
in 1909 Wichita Falls boasted 30 miles of
sidewalk, 5 miles of sewers, and more than 100
businesses. A streetcar system also appeared
with an extension to Lake Wichita, which
made the lake a recreation center. Soon a
hotel, domed pavilion, racetrack, boardwalk,
and vacation cottages sprang up. The lake remained
the center of leisure activity for the
city until well after World War I, even though
the hotel was destroyed by fire in 1915.</p>

<p>Wichita Fall's first newspaper was the <title level="j">Wichita Falls Mirror</title>, printed by Steve Reynolds
in the early 1880s. Dr. H. A. Lewis started
the <title level="j">Wichita Falls Herald</title>, which was later
owned by F. F. Dougherty and Ed Howard.
<title level="j">The Times</title>, founded in 1887 by Sam Bell
Thomas, was purchased by Howard in 1897.
He organized the Times Publishing Company
in 1904 and began printing the <title level="j">Daily Times</title>
and the <title level="j">Record News</title>. Those two papers continued
to appear separately until 1987, when
they were combined into one morning paper.</p>

<p>The opening of the Electra oil field in 1911
triggered a shift in the economic base. By 1913
the North Texas fields were producing 46 percent
of all the oil in Texas, and refineries began
to appear in Wichita Falls in 1915. Then came
the discovery of the Burkburnett fields in 1918.
By 1920 there were nine refineries and fortyseven
factories within the city. The oil boom
also produced a building boom. More than a
dozen major building projects were inaugurated
in the downtown area during the early
twenties. In addition, the city added a municipal
auditorium in 1927 and an airport in
1928. It also adopted the city manager form of
government.</p>

<p>The population of Wichita Falls in 1930, on
the eve of the Great Depression, was 43,607.
The Depression slowed growth but did not
stop it, thanks in part to a major oil discovery
at nearby Kamay in 1938. In 1940 the population
was 55,200. Bank deposits exceeded
$36 million, and there were 92 miles of paved
streets, 77 manufacturing establishments, 127
wholesale outlets, and 741 retail stores. In 1941
the economy was bolstered by the opening of
Sheppard Field, an army air corps training facility.
By May 1945, when the base reached
its peak strength, 46,650 army personnel were
stationed there. The base was deactivated on
August 31, 1946, but reopened as Sheppard Air
Force Base in August 1948. It continues to
function as a major training center for air
force technicians and a flight training center
for <hi rend="smallcaps">NATO</hi>.</p>

<p>Wichita Falls reached its peak population of
110,100 in 1955, then went into gradual decline.
By 1960 the population had dropped to
101,724, and while oil production in the area
still ranked eighth in the state, it would soon
be eclipsed by other areas. Also, by 1962 oilrefining
activity had practically ceased. Recognizing
that change was in the air, the city's
leaders formed Industrial Development, Inc.,
which sought to diversify the economy by attracting
other types of industries. In 1970 Industrial
Development, Inc., merged with the
chamber of commerce under the name Board
of Commerce and Industry. This organization
was successful in attracting fifteen new industries
during the 1970s, including Pittsburgh
Plate Glass, Certain Teed, Washex, Howmet
Turbine, AC Spark Plug, and Ciba-Geigy.
These successes produced great optimism that
the new trend would continue, but instead it
had petered out by the early eighties. Meanwhile,
because of the construction of a large
shopping mall in the southwestern part of the
city, the downtown collapsed as a viable shopping
area.</p>

<p>Wichita Falls was devastated on April 10,
1979, by one of the largest tornados on record.
Sweeping through the southern part of the
city, the storm destroyed 20 percent of all
dwellings in town, destroyed numerous business
establishments, killed 46 people, and injured
3,200 more. Within three years, most of
the damage had been repaired. Also, the boom
in oil prices during the early eighties caused a
brief flurry of activity in business. But in the
mideighties, when oil prices slumped again,
the economy stagnated.</p>

<p>In the 1990s Wichita Falls showed signs of
recovery. New businesses entered the economy,
there was a building boom, and the population
soared over 100,000 for the first time
in twenty years, reaching 104,192 in 2000.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">See also</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">INDUSTRY</hi>: 
<ref n="egp.ind.047">Petroleum, United States</ref>.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Kenneth E. Henrickson Jr.<lb/>
Midwestern State University</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1>
<bibl>Auty, Michael. Wichita Falls: A Century of Photographs.
Wichita Falls <hi rend="smallcaps">TX</hi>: Midwestern State University Press, 1982.</bibl>
<bibl>Kelly, Louise. Wichita County Beginnings. Burnet <hi rend="smallcaps">TX</hi>:
Eakin Press, 1982.</bibl>
</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>